<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>26. Letter From Soviet General Secretary Brezhnev to President to President
                    Reagan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1981-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1981-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recBIWbnPJBWQERtR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military balance</term>
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Detente</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">military
                        presence</term>
                    <term ref="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001519"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recAynYh8uzxYGQRH" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009928"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Strategic weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recMqCyaCVCS2rBsP" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Equal security</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="recbm2CDfl6YlSCnq" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Modernization</term>
                    <term ref="recr08QgEMEm1Bk04" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011308"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ballistic missiles</term>
                    <term ref="recFUg0jqFk2tUZ15" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85087216"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Moratorium</term>
                    <term ref="recqaxqBsfTYVWHfR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034367"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cruise missiles</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1981-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1981-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="26"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d26">
                <head>26. Letter From Soviet General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BL_1"
                        >Brezhnev</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1"
                        >Reagan</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d26fn1">Source: Reagan Library, <persName
                            corresp="#p_BDC_1">Blair</persName> Files, <persName corresp="#p_BL_1"
                            >Brezhnev</persName> Correspondence 1981, 03/11/1981–03/24/1981. Secret.
                        Printed from an unofficial translation. In a covering memorandum to
                            <persName corresp="#p_ARV_1">Allen</persName>, March 7, <persName
                            corresp="#p_BLP_1">Bremer</persName> wrote that <persName
                            corresp="#p_BA_1">Bessmertnykh</persName> handed the letter to Acting
                        Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWJ_1">Stoessel</persName> on the afternoon
                        of March 6, and that the Department of State translated it “during the
                        night.” He went on to say: “The Secretary believes we should conduct a
                        thorough analysis and consult with key allies prior to transmission of a
                        response. We further recommend against publicly acknowledging receipt of the
                        letter, unless the Soviets make the fact public.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1981-03-06"
                            >March 6, 1981</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Mr. President:</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I consider it necessary to turn to you concerning the most vital problems that
                    are raised by the present international situation. I suppose you are aware that
                    the Congress of our Party, which recently took place in Moscow, devoted
                    paramount attention to analysis and evaluation of the international situation;
                    as well as to the practical conclusions stemming from this. The question was,
                    what should be done in order to preserve peace and to ensure for present and
                    future generations the most basic right of each person—the right to life. This
                    is the essence of the decisions that were taken, which will determine the <rs
                        corresp="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic">foreign policy</rs> course of the
                    Soviet Union in the years ahead.</p>
                <p>We are realists, and of course we take due account of the fact that improvement
                    of the international situation, the lessening and liquidation of the threat of
                    war depend not only upon us but also upon the will of other governments, upon
                    the success of establishing more <pb facs="0091" n="60" xml:id="pg_60"/>
                    appropriate mutual understanding and effective cooperation, both bilaterally and
                    multilaterally, in resolving the vital problems of present times.</p>
                <p>We are convinced that one’s attitude toward the strategic <rs
                        corresp="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic">military balance</rs> that has
                    taken shape between the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and the USA,
                    between the Warsaw Pact states and those of <gloss target="#t_NATO_1"
                        >NATO</gloss>, is of fundamental significance here. The Soviet Union has not
                    sought, and does not seek military superiority. But neither will we permit such
                    superiority to be established over us. Such attempts, as well as attempts to
                    talk to us from a position of strength, are absolutely futile.</p>
                <p>The existing strategic military equilibrium is objectively serving the cause of
                    preserving world peace. We are for consistently bringing matters to the lowering
                    of level of the equilibrium, without violating its balance. To attempt to win in
                    an <rs corresp="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic">arms race</rs>, to count on
                    victory in an atomic war—would be dangerous madness. It must be recognized that
                    endless competition and accumulation of ever newer weapons, while keeping the
                    world under tension, is the real source of the military threat that hangs over
                    all countries. We are prepared to act, hand in hand with all countries and above
                    all with the United States, in decisive struggle against this threat. It is
                    clear the great extent to which success here depends upon the joint actions
                    precisely of our two countries.</p>
                <p>We are in general for normal, good relations with the USA, for the development of
                    these relations in the interests of the peoples of our two countries, in the
                    interests of peace.</p>
                <p>The present state of Soviet-American relations, the sharpness of the problems
                    demanding solution, create the imperative need for the conduct and development
                    of dialogue that is active and at all levels. The Soviet Union favors such a
                    dialogue and is prepared to come to agreement regarding mutually acceptable
                    decisions, with account for the lawful interests of the sides.</p>
                <p>Soviet-American summit meetings have special significance in all this, and at the
                    Congress we considered it feasible and advisable to speak out directly in favor
                    of such a meeting.</p>
                <p>As is known, in recent years the Soviet Union has put forward numerous proposals
                    for reducing the threat of war and for strengthening international security.
                    Many of these have been approved by the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> and
                    other impressive fora. All of our proposals remain in force and we will work
                    toward their realization.</p>
                <p>However, the current situation is such that it is necessary to intensify efforts
                    still more in order to improve the international situation radically, to give
                    people confidence in a safe, peaceful future. Guided by this vital necessity,
                    the Soviet Union has come forward with new, large initiatives permeated with
                    deep concern to restrain the <rs corresp="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic">arms
                        race</rs>, deepen <rs corresp="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic">detente</rs>,
                    strengthen peace.</p>
                <pb facs="0092" n="61" xml:id="pg_61"/>
                <p>I found it necessary to call your personal attention, Mr. President, to these
                    proposals, put forward, as you know, at the Congress of our Party. Apart from
                    the scale and the far-reaching character of these initiatives, I wish in
                    particular to underscore their realism, the account they take of both our own
                    interests as well as the interests of our partners.</p>
                <p>Experience shows how complicated and difficult it is to liquidate, to extinguish
                    hotbeds of military conflict. It is therefore important to conduct preventative
                    work to prevent such hotbeds from occurring.</p>
                <p>In this context, measures to strengthen trust in the military sphere, carried out
                    at the decision of the all-European conference, play a positive role. The Soviet
                    Union has made proposals for widening significantly the volume of these
                    measures.</p>
                <p>We are now proposing to widening substantially the zone of applicability of such
                    measures. We are prepared to extend them to the entire European part of the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, on the condition, of course, of a
                    corresponding widening of the zone of measures of trust by the Western states. I
                    would like in this connection once again to emphasize that the Soviet Union
                    favors the successful conclusion of the Madrid meeting. Adoption at it of a
                    decision to call an all-European conference for discussion and solution of
                    problems of military <rs corresp="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic">detente</rs>
                    and disarmament in Europe would have a particularly important significance.</p>
                <p>We also consider that the working out and adoption of measures of trust could
                    also be useful in the area of the Far East. The Soviet Union would be prepared
                    to conduct concrete negotiations on this account with all interested countries.
                    Without predetermining now all problems relating to such negotiations, attention
                    nonetheless should be called to the fact that in this region not only the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, China and Japan are neighbors. As is known,
                    there is also a U.S. military presence. This and other specifics of the region
                    would have to be considered, so that measures of trust would in fact be
                    effective.</p>
                <p>In some countries the opinion is expressed that our recent proposals concerning
                    the Persian Gulf cannot be separated from the question of the presence of a
                    Soviet military contingent in <rs corresp="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic"
                        >Afghanistan</rs>. Our position consists of the following: while prepared to
                    reach agreement on the Persian Gulf as an independent problem, and to
                    participate in a separate settlement of the situation around <rs
                        corresp="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic">Afghanistan</rs>, we also do not
                    object to the questions connected with <rs corresp="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9"
                        type="topic">Afghanistan</rs> being discussed in conjunction with the
                    questions of the security of the Persian Gulf. Such discussions naturally can
                    concern only the international aspects of the Afghan problem, and not the
                    internal affairs of that country. The <rs corresp="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X"
                        type="topic">sovereignty</rs> of <rs corresp="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9"
                        type="topic">Afghanistan</rs> must be fully-protected, as must its status as
                    a nonaligned state.</p>
                <p>Proceeding from the exceptional importance—not only for the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and the U.S.A., but also for other
                    countries—of the problem of <pb facs="0093" n="62" xml:id="pg_62"/> limiting and
                    reducing strategic weapons, we for our part are prepared to continue without
                    delay appropriate talks with the United States while preserving everything
                    positive that has been achieved thus far in this field. It is understandable
                    that such negotiations can be conducted only on the basis of equality and equal
                    security of the sides.</p>
                <p>As one of the practical measures in this area, we are prepared to reach agreement
                    on limiting the deployment of new submarines—in the U.S.A., the Ohio class, and
                    submarines of a similar type in the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. We
                    could also enter into accord on banning modernization of existing <rs
                        corresp="recr08QgEMEm1Bk04" type="topic">ballistic missiles</rs> and the
                    creation of new ones for deployment on these submarines.</p>
                <p>Attempting to avert the dangerous accumulation of nuclear missiles in Europe and
                    to facilitate the speediest possible attainment of a decision regarding such
                    weapons, we propose that agreement be reached on establishing a moratorium now
                    on the deployment in Europe of new medium-range nuclear missile facilities in
                    the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and the countries of <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>—that is, to freeze both quantitatively and
                    qualitatively the existing level of such means, including, of course, the
                    forward-based nuclear facilities of the U.S.A. in this region. Such a moratorium
                    could come into force as soon as negotiations on this question commence, and
                    would be effective until a treaty is concluded on limiting, or even better, on
                    reducing such nuclear facilities in Europe. In this we proceed from the position
                    that both sides would cease all preparations for deployment of corresponding
                    additional means, including the American Pershing II missiles and ground-based
                    strategic cruise missiles.</p>
                <p>Judging from reports we have received, in certain places attempts are being made
                    to represent the situation as if there were nothing new in this Soviet proposal.
                    Nothing could be further from the truth. Assertions of this sort can only
                    indicate an effort to evade a decision of the matter, a lack of desire to take
                    account of the vital interests of the European peoples.</p>
                <p>We consider that informing the general public, indeed all people, of the
                    consequences with which atomic war is fought would have great significance, and
                    would in particular bring additional influence on governments for attainment of
                    agreements directed in a practical way toward averting such a war. With this aim
                    in mind, we propose the creation of an authoritative international committee
                    that would demonstrate the vital necessity of averting a nuclear catastrophe.
                    The committee might include the most prominent scientists from various
                    countries. Very likely the General Secretary of the U.N. could play a role in
                    the realization of this aim. The conclusions reached by the committee should be
                    made known to the entire world.</p>
                <p>Further, for solution of many current international problems a far-sighted
                    approach, political will and courage, authority and influence <pb facs="0094"
                        n="63" xml:id="pg_63"/> are required. This is why we believe it would be
                    useful to convene a special session of the Security Council, with the
                    participation of the top leaders of the permanent and non-permanent member
                    states of the Council, in order to seek the key to improving the international
                    atmosphere and preventing war. Leaders of other states obviously could take part
                    in the session, if they wished. Naturally, thorough preparation for such a
                    session would be required to ensure positive results.</p>
                <p>Returning to the theme of hotbeds of tension and the task of liquidating them, I
                    would like particularly to single out the question of the situation in the
                    Middle East. No matter how one regards that which has thus far been done in this
                    region, it is clear that political settlement there has been set back. The
                    present situation urgently demands a return to a collective search for an
                    all-embracing settlement on a just and realistic basis, which could be done, say
                    within the framework of a specially convened international conference.</p>
                <p>The Soviet Union is prepared to take part in a constructive spirit in such work
                    jointly with other interested Liberation Front, and with Israel. We are prepared
                    for such a joint search with the U.S.A., with which we have had in the past
                    certain experience. We are prepared to cooperate with European states, with all
                    who sincerely desire securing a just and stable peace in the Middle East. The
                    U.N. clearly can continue to play a useful role here.</p>
                <p>These are the questions that I wanted to touch upon in this message. We expect,
                    Mr. President, that you will regard our proposals with appropriate attention. As
                    you see, they embrace a wide circle of problems and foresee measures of a
                    political and military character; they concern various types of weapons and
                    military forces; they touch upon the situation in various regions of the
                    world.</p>
                <p>We of course understand that time is required for study and consideration.
                    Probably the necessity for some sort of consultations, exchange of views—in
                    short, for various forms of dialogue—will arise. We are prepared for this.</p>
                <p>Respectfully,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BL_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">L. Brezhnev</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="2" xml:id="d26fn2">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
