<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1981-01-23T21:51:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1981-01-23T21:51:00-05:00" n="4" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d4">
                    <head>4. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in the Soviet
                            Union<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d4fn1">Source: Department of
                            State, Central Foreign Policy File, [no film number]. Secret; Immediate;
                                <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_PM_1">Parris</persName>; cleared by Newsom, <persName corresp="#p_VGS_1">Vest</persName>, Ridgway, <persName corresp="#p_WPD_1">Wolfowitz</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_BRR_1">Burt</persName>; approved by <persName corresp="#p_BLP_1">Bremer</persName>. On the same day, <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> informed <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> that he had sent a letter to
                                <persName corresp="#p_GA_1">Gromyko</persName> “stating that I would
                            work for development of US-Soviet relations on the basis of restraint
                            and reciprocity,” and focusing “on the irresponsible Soviet treatment of
                            the hostage situation and our concern over the Polish situation.”
                                <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> also reported that
                                “<persName corresp="#p_GA_1">Gromyko</persName> is on vacation, but
                            in receiving the letter Acting Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_KG_3">Korniyenko</persName> expressed his ‛personal’
                            view to our Charge that it was unfortunate that the initial
                            communication from the new Administration dealt with such issues.”
                            (Department of State, Executive Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_SSI_1">S/S–I</gloss> Records, The Executive Secretariat’s Special Caption
                            Documents, Lot 92D630, Evening Reading: Jan–June 1981) </note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1981-01-24T02:51:00+00:00">January 24, 1981, 0251Z</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>19053. Subject: Secretary’s <rs corresp="recLZdhL4g1ojYmng" type="compound-subject">Letter</rs> to <persName corresp="#p_GA_1">Gromyko</persName>.</p>
                    <p>1. (Secret—Entire text).</p>
                    <p>2. Following message from the Secretary to <persName corresp="#p_GA_1">Gromyko</persName> should be delivered to <gloss target="#t_MFA_1">MFA</gloss>
                        <gloss target="#t_ASAP_1">ASAP</gloss>: Begin text: Dear Mr. Minister: I
                        would like to thank you for your message of congratulations on my
                        appointment as Secretary of State. I can assure you that I share your hopes
                        for strengthening the peace and that as Secretary I will work for the
                        development of relations between our two countries on the basis of restraint
                        and reciprocity.</p>
                    <p>If these goals are to be realized, I believe it is essential from the start
                        that our two governments fully comprehend each other’s concerns and
                        intentions. For this reason I would like in this initial correspondence to
                        address two issues which I consider of immediate importance.</p>
                    <p>The first deeply affects American opinion and thus the entire climate of our
                        relations. I refer to the treatment by the official Soviet <rs corresp="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic">media</rs> of events
                        surrounding the release by Iran of the 52 American diplomatic personnel
                        illegally held captive in Tehran for over a year. The attitude of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> throughout our efforts to deal with the
                        hostage crisis has already contributed to strains in our relations.
                        Continued distortion of the facts concerning the <rs corresp="recMNSn3ulaoClE2c" type="topic">hostages</rs> and of our policy
                        toward <pb facs="0042" n="11" xml:id="pg_11"/> Iran can only raise further
                        doubts in this country concerning Soviet intentions.</p>
                    <p>The second is a matter of utmost potential seriousness—the situation in
                        Poland. I wish to make clear at the outset that there will be no change in
                        the US position of noninterference in Poland’s internal affairs. We are
                        prepared to do what we can to help Poland resolve its serious economic
                        difficulties. And we are convinced that, if left to themselves, the Poles
                        are fully capable of solving their problems themselves. Nor do I wish to
                        leave any doubt as to the seriousness with which the US would view efforts
                        by the Soviet Union to influence developments in Poland through military
                        pressure or direct intervention. This administration fully supports the
                        conclusions of the December 12 North Atlantic Council communique.<note n="2" xml:id="d4fn2">The text of the December 12, 1980, Final Communiqué of
                            the North Atlantic Council is printed in Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, February 1981, pp. 50–52. </note> Any
                        intervention in Poland would fundamentally alter the entire international
                        situation, and the US with its allies would be compelled to act in a manner
                        which the gravity of the situation would require.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Minister, I cannot in this initial <rs corresp="recLZdhL4g1ojYmng" type="compound-subject">letter</rs> address all of the issues
                        between us. At an appropriate time I would hope it would be possible to
                        exchange views on a wider range of subjects, particularly the problem of
                        <rs corresp="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic">Afghanistan</rs>, and the need for an early and complete Soviet withdrawal from
                        that country. The points I have raised are those which I believe deserve
                        immediate attention.</p>
                    <p>I would hope you would be prepared to address them in that spirit.</p>
                    <p>Sincerely, <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Alexander Haig</persName>. End
                        text.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1"><hi rend="strong">Haig</hi></persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>