<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Mr. Noel H. Field of the Division of Western European
                    Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d116</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">116</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-09-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-09-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-09-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-09-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="116"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d116">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A5/493</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Noel H. Field of the Division of Western
                        European Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-09-17">September 17,
                            1935</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Davis called me on the telephone this morning and told me he had had a most
                    satisfactory talk with the President on the naval question. <pb facs="0215"
                        n="113" xml:id="pg_113"/> The President had said it would be perfectly all
                    right to go ahead and show our hand to the British, telling them frankly that if
                    they will accept 14 inch guns and 32 to 33,000 tons for capital ships, we will
                    be prepared to try them out for a period and subsequently work out a new
                    agreement on the basis of the experience gained. In the President’s view, the 14
                    inch gun is better than the 16 inch gun any way.</p>
                <p>The President agreed with Mr. Davis that there might be an advantage in holding a
                    conference this year and he was prepared to conclude an agreement with the
                    British even without the Japanese.</p>
                <p>Mr. Davis said the President had been thinking along the lines of using the
                    Italo-Ethiopian conflict as a pretext for suggesting an extension of the Naval
                    Treaties for a while. He thought we might propose that inasmuch as one of the
                    parties to the Washington Treaty is at war, it would be a good thing for us just
                    to let the Treaties continue for a year or two until that Power was in a better
                    position to negotiate. Mr. Davis, however, pointed out to the President that
                    this would not fit in with the British desire to retain overage cruisers. The
                    President replied that that was all right and that the United States would in
                    that case hold on to what it wanted also.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
