<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-11-18T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-11-18T18:00:00-05:00" n="145" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d145">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A5/550a: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">President <persName type="from">Roosevelt</persName>
                                to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Bingham</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-11-18T18:00:00-05:00">November
                                    18, 1935—6 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>343. Since talking with you I have reviewed and given every possible
                            consideration to all the aspects of the many questions involved. I have
                            of necessity come to the following conclusions, largely because of my
                            own personal familiarity with the great technical and political
                            difficulties involved.</p>
                        <p>The coming session includes even more greatly than previous sessions the
                            naval relations between many and perhaps all important naval powers, and
                            goes far beyond naval relations purely between the United States and
                            Great Britain. Evidence of this is furnished by the character of the
                            national delegations being sent to the Conference by Japan, by France,
                            and possibly other nations.</p>
                        <p>Since June, 1934, we have maintained continuously a special group or
                            delegation dealing particularly with naval questions. The forthcoming
                            Conference is a definite continuation of the general negotiations on
                            Naval Limitation which were carried on last Fall. The American group has
                            kept in close touch with the world aspect, in <pb facs="0246" n="144" xml:id="pg_144"/> addition to the diplomatic negotiations which you
                            have had with the British preparatory to this coming Conference.</p>
                        <p>For technical reasons, but especially because of the political world
                            questions which undoubtedly will play an important part in the
                            Conference, I have decided to make no change in the delegation or
                            mission which went to London last Fall, with Norman Davis as the head of
                            the delegation, and Admiral Standley as a delegate except that in
                            thinking over your suggestion about sending Phillips to the Conference I
                            have decided to send as an additional delegate the Under Secretary of
                            State, who has worked actively with the group here in order that he may
                            become personally acquainted with the problems as they are brought out
                            during the earlier days of the Conference. He will, as soon as this is
                            accomplished, return to Washington in order that I may have personally a
                            complete and up-to-date picture, and in order that subsequent liaison
                            may be facilitated.</p>
                        <p>I agree with you that under the circumstances it would not be entirely
                            appropriate for you, as my Ambassador to Great Britain, to be a member
                            of the delegation, since the delegation will have to carry on
                            multilateral negotiations involving not only technical questions, but
                            also political aspects of our relations with several other powers
                            besides Great Britain, these powers including Japan and the Pacific
                            field. Furthermore, in view of the British situation and its close
                            relation to the Italian-Ethiopian war, I want you to be footloose.</p>
                        <p>I need not tell you how greatly I appreciate the services you rendered in
                            the preliminary diplomatic discussions with the British preparatory to
                            this conference and even though you are to be independent of the
                            delegation I am sure that Mr. Davis and the other delegates can count
                            upon your counsel and helpful cooperation particularly in their
                            relations to the British Government.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Roosevelt</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>