<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Mr. Noel H. Field of the Division of Western European Affairs
                    of a Meeting Held November 19, 1935, at the Executive Office of the White
                    House</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d146</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">146</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-11-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-11-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recQ0ODajfiIQB8Cy" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-11-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-11-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="146"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d146">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A5/564</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Noel H. Field of the Division of Western
                        European Affairs of a Meeting Held November 19, 1935, at the Executive
                        Office of the White House</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-11-23">November 23,
                            1935</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Present:</cell>
                        <cell>The President.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>The Secretary of State.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Norman H. Davis.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. William Phillips.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Admiral William H. Standley.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. James Clement Dunn.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Captain Ingersoll.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Commander Schuirman.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Noel H. Field.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb facs="0247" n="145" xml:id="pg_145"/>
                <p>Mr. Davis began by explaining that he did not desire to take the President’s time
                    in a discussion of technical naval questions since we had discussed these from
                    time to time with him and since they had been dealt with rather thoroughly in
                    our bilateral conversations with the British, but that he did want to discuss
                    the more fundamental questions. Mr. Davis then read out a brief memorandum (a
                    copy of which is attached), summarizing the present situation and the main
                    points of the American position. The President indicated his approval of the
                    individual points in this memorandum, with certain comments and exceptions which
                    may be summarized as follows:</p>
                <p>On the basic issues of Japanese claims for a common upper limit, for an increased
                    ratio, and for the abolition of capital ships, aircraft carriers and cruisers A
                    (paragraph 2 (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) and (<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)), the
                    President confirmed the position heretofore taken by the United States that
                    these claims are unacceptable and that no concession or compromise can be made
                    concerning them.</p>
                <p>With respect to paragraph 2 (<hi rend="italic">g</hi>) and (<hi rend="italic"
                        >h</hi>), Mr. Davis pointed out that, on the one hand, our Navy was inclined
                    to consider Great Britain’s insistence on additional cruisers sympathetically,
                    bearing in mind British responsibility throughout the world; on the other hand,
                    our Naval Experts are convinced that it would be extremely difficult to
                    compensate for increases in cruiser tonnage by reductions in other categories.
                    Admiral Standley said the United States had been in the undesirable position in
                    the past of attempting to prove to the British that they did not need what they
                    claimed they needed. The President agreed we should not try to determine British
                    requirements; nevertheless, he did not feel that the American people would
                    approve of a treaty which simply increased existing theoretical limits. He
                    suggested as a compromise that the cruiser increase might be absorbed at least
                    in part by reductions in other categories, for instance, by reduction of the
                    number of capital ships from 15 to 13. This would reduce the total theoretical
                    capital ship tonnage for the British Empire and the United States by 70,000
                    each, or approximately half the proposed increase in cruiser tonnage. A further
                    gradual reduction might be brought about through reducing the unit displacement
                    of future capital ships by some 2,500 tons. The President said that he would
                    agree to a treaty giving Great Britain the increased cruiser tonnage she needs
                    providing about 50% of this increase can be absorbed in other categories and the
                    resulting increase in total tonnage can be held down to about 75,000 tons. All
                    present at the meeting agreed that the President’s suggestion provided the most
                    hopeful basis for a constructive solution of the problem.</p>
                <p>With respect to the question of qualitative without quantitative limitation
                    (point 3 of the memorandum), it was brought out that to <pb facs="0248" n="146"
                        xml:id="pg_146"/> admit the possibility of our agreeing to this method at
                    the outset might remove the incentive for any further quantitative limitation
                    now or in the future. Great Britain’s primary interest is in qualitative
                    limitation and if she can get it, she will be quite satisfied to go along
                    indefinitely without any restrictions on quantity. Nevertheless, some form of
                    qualitative limitation appears to be the best that can at this time be hoped for
                    in the way of a multilateral treaty. Mr. Davis therefore felt that the
                    Delegation should be authorized, after making every attempt to obtain as much
                    quantitative restriction as possible, to agree to qualitative limitation even
                    without quantitative limitation. The President agreed.</p>
                <p>As regards a possible bilateral treaty between the United States and Great
                    Britain (paragraph 5), the President considered a treaty between these two
                    Powers alone as politically undesirable, although he would not object to a
                    trilateral or quadrilateral treaty without Japan. It was the President’s view
                    that any agreement with Great Britain alone should be embodied in
                    non-contractual form. After discussion of the possibilities of such methods as
                    joint declarations or unilateral, simultaneous declarations, the President
                    thought it might be better just to have an exchange of notes which might be
                    published. This exchange might include something along the lines of the
                    statements made last August by Craigie to Atherton, namely, an agreement on the
                    established principle of Anglo-American parity and on the intention of both
                    Powers to maintain, in substance, the 5–5–3 ratio.</p>
                <p>Mr. Davis then went over some of the subsidiary questions which might come up at
                    London, as embodied in the draft questions and answers previously prepared in
                    the Department.</p>
                <p>On the question of political cooperation with Great Britain, the President
                    approved the Department’s draft formula which reads as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“It is possible that the British Government may again bring up the
                            thought that some form of agreement for Anglo-American political
                            cooperation, particularly in the Far East, might be a determining factor
                            in Great Britain’s attitude toward naval limitation. The Delegation
                            should repeat the position taken in the conversations a year ago,
                            namely, that any agreement of this sort is out of the question. On the
                            other hand, the Delegation may emphasize the inevitable and growing
                            community of interests of the British Empire and the United States
                            throughout the world and particularly the Far East (maintenance of
                            treaties and rights accruing thereunder, stabilization of political and
                            economic relations, maintenance of Open Door, opposition to expansion by
                            means of military aggression, et cetera). From this community of
                            interests, it would appear evident that despite the absence of any
                            mutual commitments, the United States and the British Empire are likely,
                            in their own interests and in the interests of the community of nations,
                            to follow, in general, a parallel, though independent policy, notably in
                            the Far East.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0249" n="147" xml:id="pg_147"/>
                <p>Mr. Davis emphasized the importance of the question of overage tonnage which has
                    to be scrapped in accordance with the Treaties before the end of next year. The
                    British, he pointed out, are determined to retain their large overage cruiser
                    tonnage and, in his opinion, they would, if we did not come to an agreement to
                    permit their retention, invoke the escalator clause for the purpose of saving
                    these cruisers. Admiral Standley was of the opinion that the United States
                    should not consent to the retention of overage tonnage in excess of Treaty
                    totals since, to do so, would, in practice, amount to a change in the Treaty
                    ratios. The President made the suggestion that the parties to the Washington
                    Treaty might agree, in view of the special situation in the Mediterranean, to
                    extend the time limit for scrapping overage tonnage by six months or one year.
                    This would give time for a reconsideration of the problem at a later date. This
                    suggestion was not further pursued, however, when it was pointed out that it
                    would amount to our proposing the abandonment now of a vital provision of the
                    London Treaty, and the President agreed that it would be virtually impossible
                    for the United States to consent to alter the scrapping provisions of the Treaty
                    by agreement without jeopardizing the position of the United States.</p>
                <p>The President inquired as to the status of the global tonnage idea and Admiral
                    Standley explained that, in addition to France, it was possible that Japan might
                    support a global tonnage limitation on the basis of a common upper limit. The
                    President wondered whether a global quantitative limitation, combined with
                    qualitative provisions, might not be acceptable to us. Admiral Standley
                    explained that any form of global limitation would work out to the disadvantage
                    of the large naval Powers, since it would enable the smaller Powers to
                    concentrate their building in the smaller and cheaper units and the larger
                    Powers would have to freeze a portion of their global allotment in types of
                    ships designed to counteract this building instead of in types essentially
                    required by fleet needs.</p>
                <p>The question of fortifications in the Pacific was discussed at some length but
                    without any definite conclusion, although the consensus appeared to be that it
                    might be advantageous to continue the non-fortifications provisions in any
                    multilateral treaty which might be negotiated.</p>
                <p>The President agreed that we could accept anything acceptable to the British with
                    regard to France, Italy, Germany and Russia.</p>
                <p>The President thought his letter of last fall to Mr. Davis could be used as a
                    general basis for our attitude with minor revisions.</p>
                <p>In the Delegation’s relations with the public, he thought it would be wise
                    strategy to stress the fact that the United States has two coast lines to defend
                    which are separated by a vulnerable canal. He also felt the Delegation should
                    make all its public statements so simple that <pb facs="0250" n="148"
                        xml:id="pg_148"/> the man in the street could easily understand them, and
                    should avoid the use of such words as qualitative and quantitative, the meaning
                    of which few people understood. The Delegation should also bear in mind that it
                    might again run into the problem of having to counteract Admiralty
                    propaganda.</p>
                <p>In conclusion, the President jokingly said he felt as though he were sending the
                    Delegation on a Cocos Island treasure hunt.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Annex—Memorandum]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-11-19">November 19,
                                1935</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Summary of American Position on Naval Questions</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Although the United States has consistently favored and still favors
                            the conclusion of a new comprehensive naval agreement, providing for the
                            greatest possible over-all reduction of naval tonnage, or, at least for
                            a continuance of the present treaty limits, it is necessary to recognize
                            that under present conditions the achievement of this objective appears
                            to be impracticable.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Briefly, the situation today is that <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Japan has denounced the Washington Treaty and both the London
                                    and Washington Treaties will expire at the end of 1936;</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Japan insists on recognition of her claim to a common upper
                                    limit, i. e., parity with Great Britain and the United States,
                                    and refuses to agree to any limitation which would perpetuate
                                    the ratio system;</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Japan will not agree to qualitative without quantitative
                                    limitation;</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Japan favors a reduction in naval armaments, but by the method
                                    of abolishing capital ships, aircraft carriers and 8 inch
                                    cruisers;</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The United States and Great Britain, on the contrary, insist
                                    on continuance of the present treaty ratios, in fact if not in
                                    form, and reject the Japanese claim for a common upper limit or
                                    for an increased ratio;</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The United States and Great Britain oppose the abolition of
                                    capital ships, aircraft carriers and 8 inch cruisers;</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">g</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Great Britain has determined to increase the number of her
                                    cruisers from about 50 to about 70, necessitating a great
                                    increase in total cruiser tonnage;</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">h</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The United States cannot join in a new treaty which, in
                                    effect, will serve to increase total naval armaments, and
                                    therefore maintains the position that increases in one category
                                    should be compensated for by decreases in other
                                    categories.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>In the light of the above, a new comprehensive multilateral treaty at
                            this time is ruled out by the fundamental divergence between the United
                            States and Great Britain on the one hand, and Japan on the other,
                            respecting relative fleet strengths. A treaty covering <pb facs="0251"
                                n="149" xml:id="pg_149"/> qualitative limitation is also ruled out
                            as long as Japan refuses qualitative without quantitative limitation.
                            The British, however, seem quite hopeful that Japan will ultimately
                            agree to qualitative limitation and that while no power would be bound
                            as to quantitative limitation, an agreement can be reached for giving
                            advance notice of building programs.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>The United States believes, and the other naval Powers seem to share
                            the view, that even if no inclusive treaty is now possible, the effort
                            to limit and ultimately reduce naval armaments by international
                            agreement cannot and must not be abandoned. With a view to bridging the
                            gap until a new comprehensive treaty can be negotiated, we must at least
                            endeavor to get a limited agreement, if possible in a new multilateral
                            treaty or, if that is impossible, at least in non-contractual form, such
                            as declarations, which will prevent a naval race and tend to prevent any
                            undue tension or effort to alter the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi>
                            until a more opportune time for a new conference to negotiate a
                            comprehensive agreement. If a new race is allowed to develop through the
                            failure to achieve a new multilateral limitation treaty at this time,
                            the obstacles to such an agreement in the future may become insuperable,
                            and, fortunately each naval power seems to want to avoid a race.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>In case it is not possible to negotiate a multilateral treaty now
                            providing for qualitative limitation and salvaging such other portions
                            of the existing naval treaties as may be possible, but exclusive of
                            quantitative limitation, it is at least possible for the United States
                            and Great Britain to enter into a naval treaty continuing the essential
                            principles of the Washington and London Treaties, thus making an
                            Anglo-American naval race impossible, which would include a broad escape
                            clause designed to meet excessive building by other naval Powers and
                            which would serve as a powerful stimulus throughout the world for
                            avoiding a naval race and to pave the way for a multilateral agreement
                            later on. It might also be possible to include in such a treaty France
                            and Italy, as the British have indicated, in case Japan refuses even
                            qualitative limitation. Since Great Britain seems determined to increase
                            her cruiser tonnage above the present Treaty limitations by 20 cruisers,
                            we should explore the possibility of finding ways and means of providing
                            compensatory reductions in other categories, such, for instance, as
                            through a reduction in the number of battleships and possibly, later on,
                            some slight reduction in the unit tonnage.</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
