<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-02-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="290" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d290">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.114 Great Britain/441½</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of the Treasury</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Morgenthau</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Counselor of the British Embassy</hi>
                                (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Osborne</hi></persName>)<note n="31" xml:id="d290fn31">Copy furnished to the Department of State
                                by the Treasury Department.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-02-05">February 5,
                                1935</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Osborne</hi>: Your letter of January
                            31st, 1935, has been received. Thank you for the information contained
                            therein.</p>
                        <p>With regard to the notification of our Consul General in London of
                            departure of vessels with cargoes of alcohol for any port adjacent to
                            the United States, we are much interested in such departures due to the
                            activity now prevailing in smuggling operations. We will appreciate it
                            if you will have the former practice of such notification resumed, not
                            only from your ports in Great Britain with regard to sailings to any
                            port in the Western Hemisphere, but also from your possessions in the
                            Western Hemisphere to any other port west of the Azores. In addition to
                            shipments of alcohol as such we would also appreciate having included
                            shipments of compounds of alcohol, such as wood stain, ink and similar
                            combinations which permit of extraction of alcohol, and which, our
                            experience shows us, come under the head of “interesting” cargoes. With
                            regard to shipments from the <pb facs="0513" n="411" xml:id="pg_411"/>
                            United Kingdom direct to the Western Hemisphere, we would also
                            appreciate information as to such shipments to intermediate ports of
                            call in Europe on freight routes to this side of the water.</p>
                        <p>It will be satisfactory if your Customs authorities communicate the above
                            information direct to our Consular representatives instead of by the
                            alternative method you mention.</p>
                        <p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Morgenthau, Jr.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>