<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the American Delegate ( (Wilson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-02-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-02-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft treaty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-02-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-02-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="32"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d32">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A4 General Committee (Arms)/126</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the American Delegate</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Wilson</hi>)<note n="50" xml:id="d32fn50">Transmitted to the Department in
                        the delegation’s despatch No. 110, February 28, 1935; received March
                        9.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-02-28">February 28,
                            1935</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Wilson, accompanied by Mr. Mayer, called this morning on the Japanese
                    Consul-General, Mr. Yokoyama, to discuss disarmament questions. Mr. Yokoyama had
                    with him Mr. Yoshimura, who attends the committee work for the Japanese.</p>
                <p>Mr. Wilson referred to his call on Ambassador Matsudaira last December when he
                    was in London with regard to the Naval conversations.<note n="51"
                        xml:id="d32fn51">See <ref target="frus1934v01#pg_299">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1934, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 299</ref> ff.</note> Mr. Wilson said
                    that now that the “general discussion” was concluded, practically all the
                    delegations had expressed their sentiments on the subject of the American Draft
                    except the Japanese; that while he felt he knew pretty well what the Japanese
                    point of view was, it was always useful to discuss questions with one’s
                    colleagues and therefore he would be glad to learn what the Japanese attitude
                    might be as of to-day, bearing in mind that should they prefer not to discuss
                    the matter at all, he would understand perfectly.</p>
                <p>Mr. Yokoyama said that he was glad Mr. Wilson had called; that the Japanese
                    position had not changed since they had made it clear in the General Commission
                    and Bureau last year, but that it was always useful to go over things in common.
                    Mr. Yokoyama continued that the Japanese had not taken any part in the debates
                    thus far because they felt they were in the position of observers on the one
                    hand, waiting until the treaty should develop finally before taking any public
                    stand, and furthermore, because they thought it more helpful at this stage—their
                    attitude being what it was—not to speak. He said that to repeat the Japanese
                    position, there were two principal points—one, <pb facs="0130" n="28"
                        xml:id="pg_28"/> the Japanese desire not to treat State and private
                    manufacture of armament on the same basis; and the other, their opposition to
                    inspection on the spot.</p>
                <p>Mr. Wilson and Mr. Yokoyama then reviewed the present situation of the committee
                    work, both agreeing that the primary divergencies of view had come down to two
                    in number: (1) inspection on the spot, and (2) global returns versus specific
                    returns. (Incidentally, Mr. Yokoyama seemed very well informed regarding the
                    course of the discussions and gave evidence of following the matter rather
                    closely.)</p>
                <p>Dealing with the inspection features primarily, Mr. Yokoyama wondered whether
                    their difficulties weren’t solvable by an application of the regional idea, with
                    Japan and the United States—if we desired—in a different category from the
                    European States who had their special problems and their particular reasons for
                    supervision and control of a very special character. Reference was made to the
                    fact that for more than twelve years the United States, Great Britain and Japan
                    had carried out an agreement involving their most vital defense arm without any
                    supervision or control or the slightest thought or desire for the same. Mr.
                    Yokoyama indicated here the Japanese feeling that there was something
                    dishonorable about subscribing to a supervision arrangement among countries of
                    good faith. Mr. Wilson said that regional treatment of these “universal
                    problems” was a sympathetic one to us and a method which we had often
                    considered. In this case, however, there was the difficulty that Russia was both
                    European and Asiatic. Mr. Yokoyama seemed to feel the force of this point and
                    nodded his head several times during the course of Mr. Wilson’s remarks in this
                    regard.</p>
                <p>Mr. Wilson then discussed at some length the question of supervision and control.
                    Assuming, for the sake of argument, the Japanese point of view, control was only
                    a nuisance, and the Continental Powers were not concerned with Japan nor indeed
                    with the United States and neither of these countries had anything to fear from
                    an inspection of their execution of the treaty; nevertheless, wasn’t this
                    nuisance well worth putting up with if it meant an agreement of this character
                    in which all the States concerned could participate? Mr. Wilson also brought out
                    the advantage which he felt the inspection feature held for a State whose treaty
                    execution was unjustly attacked. He referred specifically to Article 27 where a
                    State can ask for an inspection in such circumstances.</p>
                <p>Mr. Wilson stressed the great value to the world in general of an agreement such
                    as that now under negotiation. He also indicated the possibility that since this
                    present draft treaty did not raise the point of “Equality”, Germany might be
                    willing to join in, which would be an excellent start toward an improvement of
                    conditions in <pb facs="0131" n="29" xml:id="pg_29"/> Europe in particular and
                    the world in general. Mr. Yokoyama seemed to recognize this point very
                    clearly.</p>
                <p>Although Mr. Yokoyama maintained the same position as his Government has held
                    consistently with regard to the question of inspection and control, it did seem
                    during the conversation that Mr. Yokoyama wished to indicate that the Japanese
                    Government did not want to be any more difficult than could be helped in the
                    circumstances; that while being present, it desired to stand aside until the
                    whole picture was before it, when perhaps a final reconsideration might take
                    place in the light of what had been thrashed out and determined and after seeing
                    how general was the agreement.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
