<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-09-04T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-09-04T17:00:00-05:00" n="526" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d526">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">765.84/1039: Telegram</note>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Geneva</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gilbert</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                            State</gloss>
                                    </hi>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-09-04T23:00:00+01:00">September 4, 1935—11 p.m.</date>
                                        <lb/> [Received September 5—3:54 a.m.]</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>293. Consulate’s 289, September 4, 5 p.m.<note n="71" xml:id="d526fn71">Not printed.</note> After the private
                                    meeting the Council sat in public with Guiñazu, the Argentine
                                    representative, presiding.</p>
                                <p>The following is a summary of the proceedings:</p>
                                <p>(1) The President announced that the decision of the Arbitral
                                    Commission concerning Wal Wal incident had been delivered, that
                                    the five arbitrators had unanimously concurred therein, that the
                                    decision had been communicated to the Secretary General and
                                    would be distributed at once. He then recalled that the Council
                                    had decided on August 3 to meet today to consider the general
                                    question of the relations between Italy and Ethiopia<note n="72" xml:id="d526fn72">See League of Nations, <hi rend="italic">Official Journal</hi>, August 1935, p. 967.</note> and
                                    stated that the Council would like to be informed concerning the
                                    conversations which had taken place in the interval.</p>
                                <p>(2) Eden first made a statement concerning the Paris
                                    conversations in which he outlined the proposals which had been
                                    submitted to and rejected by the Italian Government. He feels
                                    that the suggestions made to Italy were of an exploratory nature
                                    which did not commit the Governments concerned. The proposals as
                                    outlined by Eden may be summarized as follows: <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>While not failing to recognize that the situation of
                                            Abyssinia might call for extensive reforms, it was felt
                                            that these reforms should be clearly assented to by
                                            Abyssinia in the fullness of her sovereignty and without
                                            anything being imposed on her contrary to her
                                            independence or her integrity.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>As a member of the League of Nations Abyssinia might
                                            appeal to the League for the collaboration and
                                            assistance necessary to assure the economic development
                                            and administrative reorganization of the country.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>France, Great Britain and Italy as limitrophe powers
                                            would be particularly well qualified to lend this
                                            collective assistance either by virtue of a mission
                                            entrusted to them by the Council or through a treaty
                                            between the three Powers and the Abyssinian Government
                                            approved by the Council.</item>
                                        <pb facs="0746" n="644" xml:id="pg_644"/>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>The work of reorganization was to have extended to
                                            economic, financial, commercial and constructional
                                            development; foreign settlement; modernization of
                                            administrative services; anti-slavery measures and
                                            frontier and other police services.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>The collective character of the assistance would not
                                            have prevented particular account being taken of the
                                            special interests of Italy.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>The Powers did not examine but the proposals did not
                                            exclude the possibility of territorial adjustments
                                            between Italy and Abyssinia.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>After the foregoing Eden made a general statement concerning the
                                    British position after describing postwar efforts to create a
                                    new international order through such instruments as the League
                                    Covenant and the Pact of Paris. He said, “It is because His
                                    Majesty’s Government are acutely conscious of their
                                    responsibilities as members of the League, because they are
                                    prepared [to] fulfill their share of such responsibilities, that
                                    I can assure my colleagues of our most wholehearted cooperation
                                    in the difficult task that confronts us. I am sure that all of
                                    us as members of the Council of the League must be fully alive
                                    to our responsibilities at this time. World opinion is watching
                                    us.”</p>
                                <p>He then referred to the successes of the League in the past and
                                    recalled the important part played therein by Italy. He
                                    emphasized the grave consequences to the League and
                                    international order should the League fail in this dispute. He
                                    repeated that in this dispute between Italy and Abyssinia there
                                    was no question of any political or economic conflict between
                                    the United Kingdom and Italy, Great Britain’s only concern being
                                    as a member of the League and signatory of the Pact of Paris. He
                                    concluded as follows: “In the position in which we find
                                    ourselves today the nature of the task which lies before the
                                    Council is plain. It is our duty to use the machinery of the
                                    League that lies to our hand. Let us set it to work forthwith
                                    and if we may obtain the loyal collaboration of the two parties
                                    to the dispute then we shall not fail to achieve that peaceful
                                    settlement which we so earnestly desire.”</p>
                                <p>(3) Laval in a general statement which threw no new light on the
                                    French position expressed France’s attachment to the principle
                                    of collective security and said that he refused to believe that
                                    an equitable settlement could not be reached which would give
                                    satisfaction to legitimate Italian claims without jeopardizing
                                    the essential rights of Ethiopian sovereignty.</p>
                                <p>(4) Aloisi said he was submitting to the Council a memorandum
                                    which contained in detail the numerous reasons why his
                                    Government considered that Ethiopia had systematically and
                                    openly violated all the conventional undertakings which it had
                                    assumed both towards Italy and the League. It was for the same
                                    reasons that Italy had been unable to consider the proposals
                                    made in Paris. For nearly 50 years Italy had patiently pursued a
                                    policy of peaceful collaboration with respect to Ethiopia. This
                                    was marked by (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>), Italian support of
                                    Ethiopia’s candidacy for admission to the League and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>), signature in <pb facs="0747" n="645" xml:id="pg_645"/> 1928 of a Treaty of Friendship of long
                                    duration and comprehensive nature. Under this treaty Italy had
                                    agreed to arbitrate the Wal Wal incident which, even though
                                    material proof of eventual responsibility had not been entirely
                                    established, had shown the attitude of the Ethiopian Government
                                    through the circumstance of a premeditated attack.</p>
                                <p>He said that Ethiopia had been increasing its armaments and
                                    multiplying its hostile manifestations against the Italian
                                    colonies any one of which would have justified a resort to war
                                    against her. Italy had been patient for a long time but had
                                    finally become convinced of Ethiopia’s enmity and could no
                                    longer remain passive toward a barbarous country incapable of
                                    controlling itself or its subjects who threatened the Italian
                                    frontiers.</p>
                                <p>He pointed out that the League Covenant not only provided member
                                    states with guarantees but imposed obligations which justified
                                    the guarantees. Any other interpretation would provide unworthy
                                    states with an asylum incompatible with the security of the rest
                                    of the world. The subcommittee which considered the admission of
                                    Ethiopia to the League had reported that it had been unable to
                                    determine with certainty the extent of the Government’s control
                                    over the remote provinces and that it could not affirm that
                                    Ethiopia’s international obligations had in the past been
                                    entirely fulfilled. Despite a general belief that Ethiopia was
                                    not eligible the Assembly had preferred to show confidence in
                                    Ethiopia and Italy had shown its good will by supporting this
                                    position. Yet in 12 years there had been no real change in
                                    Ethiopia. Its Government did nothing to make itself worthy of
                                    belonging to the Community of civilized nations and it even had
                                    failed to live up to the obligations which it had undertaken in
                                    order to enter the League.</p>
                                <p>He stated that under the circumstances Ethiopia could not have
                                    either equality of rights nor of duties with civilized states.
                                    If such an equality had been granted Ethiopia there was no
                                    reason why a mistake made in 1923 should be allowed to continue
                                    to the prejudice of other states. Italy admitted that it had
                                    participated in that mistake and Aloisi here recalled that the
                                    Australian delegate had declared that the admission of backward
                                    peoples into the League could hardly be justified. He referred
                                    at this point to the continuance of slavery in Ethiopia.</p>
                                <p>Aloisi said that “to pretend that the Members of the League of
                                    Nations are obliged to observe the rules of the Covenant in
                                    their relations with a member which has always and constantly
                                    violates outright those rules is contrary to every principle of
                                    right and of justice”. He said that his Government “is obliged
                                    to declare that Italy would feel deeply wounded in its dignity
                                    as a civilized nation if she continued discussions within the
                                    League of Nations on a footing of equality with Ethiopia. She
                                    refuses in fact to recognize such <pb facs="0748" n="646" xml:id="pg_646"/> equality …”. Furthermore, Italy could no
                                    longer count on the provisions of the Treaty of 1928 to
                                    guarantee the peaceful existence of the Italian territories, nor
                                    in the case of a country like Ethiopia could she depend upon
                                    purely juridical guarantees to safeguard her colonies. In
                                    conclusion he stated that his Government reserved full liberty
                                    of action to take whatever measures might become necessary for
                                    the security of its colonies and the defense of its
                                    interests.</p>
                                <p>(5) Jèze expressed amazement at Italy’s indictment of Ethiopia as
                                    to which he made an energetic protest. He insisted upon the
                                    extreme gravity of such a precedent as discussing in the Council
                                    the domestic situation of a nation and of seeking through such
                                    considerations a sentence of death. He recalled that as early as
                                    January the Ethiopian Government had agreed to arbitrate the Wal
                                    Wal incident and to pay any reparation fixed by impartial
                                    arbitrators. That incident which had been the sole reason
                                    invoked for military preparations had now been definitely
                                    settled and Ethiopia absolved of all responsibility. Under the
                                    circumstances why has, as pointed out at this point, Italy
                                    produced its new indictment, a new pretext invoked against
                                    Ethiopia. The Ethiopian Government was naturally not prepared to
                                    reply on the instant but time pressed and the Council had to
                                    deal immediately with the question of a possible war of
                                    extermination breaking out within a few days.</p>
                                <p>(6) The Spanish delegate while reserving the right to define
                                    later the attitude of his Government urged as a matter of
                                    principle that contrary to certain defeatist tendencies now
                                    evident the League use all the means at its disposal for the
                                    maintenance of peace. Pointing out that time was an essential
                                    factor he said the procedure of the Covenant must quickly be set
                                    in motion and that the Council should not approach its task with
                                    the idea that it was faced with an irremediable situation but
                                    with the firm determination to safeguard the peace.</p>
                                <p>(7) While the foregoing to a degree renders explicit the
                                    positions of the states most interested, the background afforded
                                    by private conversations and the general atmosphere of the
                                    situation here does not suggest any necessary finality in these
                                    positions or their translation into the action implied.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gilbert</hi>
                                    </signed>
                                </closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>