<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Italy ( (Kirk) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d619</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">619</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-08-17T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-08-17T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-08-17T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-08-17T14:00:00-05:00" n="619"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d619">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">765.84/859: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Italy</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-08-17T20:00:00+01:00"
                            >August 17, 1935—8 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received August 17—6:06 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>493. Marriner has repeated to me his telegram to the Department, number 697,
                    August 17, 9 a.m., and 699, August 17, noon.</p>
                <p>Although it is impossible to surmise the effect which a message along the lines
                    suggested in the second paragraph of the abovementioned telegram would have on
                    the psychology of Mussolini at this moment, judging from the past there will be
                    an inclination to regard any such gesture as unwelcome interference.
                    Furthermore, when the message would be published in Italy it would be presented
                    to the public only in such a way as would, according to the views of the
                    Government, best serve its interests in furthering its present policy.</p>
                <p>The situation, however, is critical and any means calculated to strengthen the
                    possibility of a peaceful solution is justified. If, therefore, it is decided
                    that a message along the lines indicated be delivered, I venture to suggest that
                    the susceptibilities of the Italians would less likely be adversely affected and
                    the possibility of the Italian Government turning the message to their own
                    purposes would be reduced if the message could be withheld from publication.
                    Whether this could be done or agreed to by Rosso, the Department only is in a
                    position to judge. I further venture to suggest that the reference to “moral
                    isolation”, as mentioned by Campbell, might well have an effect on the Italian
                    mind which would detract from the effectiveness of the message.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kirk</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
