<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Italy ( (Long) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d632</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">632</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-09-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-09-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Tariffs</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recXuFW8WO1tqBrVK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                    <term ref="recKrzVuLHn3WbqNd" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85105939"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Poverty</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec83f6d11c10a4344" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="league-of-nations" subject="league-of-nations">League of Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-09-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-09-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="632"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d632">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">765.84/1502</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Italy</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Long</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1318</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-09-17">September 17,
                            1935</date>.<lb/>[Received October 2.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that this evening I
                    saw Signor Mussolini at the Palazzo Venezia, by appointment. The request to see
                    him was made after my recent return to Rome, and on last Saturday he advised me
                    he would receive me today. I arrived at five o’clock, was kept waiting fifteen
                    or twenty minutes, and left at six fifteen.</p>
                <p>It just happened that the time of my engagement coincided with the development at
                    Geneva which contemplated the imminent report of the Sub-Committee of Five
                    assigned to the study of the Italo-Ethiopian dispute.</p>
                <p>I told him that I had come to pay my respects after an absence of a considerable
                    length of time. After an exchange of personal courtesies I said that I had no
                    instructions from my Government to talk with him and that my Government did not
                    know that I had an appointment with him and had no knowledge of my intentions of
                    speaking with him, I asked if I might speak as an individual and without in <pb
                        facs="0855" n="753" xml:id="pg_753"/> any way involving my Government. He
                    said that I might speak in that way.</p>
                <p>I said I wanted to be sure that he fully understood my conversation and asked if
                    he preferred me to speak English or French. He said French would be better; so
                    from that point the conversation proceeded in French.</p>
                <p>I proceeded to say that I thought that he had today one of the greatest
                    opportunities that any man could have. The position in which he found himself
                    and the circumstances which existed offered him a chance to exert a great
                    influence and do a very great service.</p>
                <p>I proceeded to take up the matter mentioned to you in my 572, September 12, 5
                    p.m. I also had in mind your 143, September 14, 2 p.m.,<note n="73"
                        xml:id="d632fn73">See footnote 72, <ref target="#pg_749">p.
                        749</ref>.</note> from the second paragraph of which I assumed that there
                    was no prohibition placed upon me in the matter. Acting entirely on my own
                    authority and specifically so stating and announcing that I was speaking as an
                    interested and active student of European politics and anxious to see an
                    adjustment not only of the present difficulties but of the complications which
                    continually threatened the peace of Europe, I proceeded to outline my
                    thoughts.</p>
                <p>The Conference at Geneva is proceeding. Most of the Governments in the world are
                    represented there. They are all frightened that war is imminent and afraid that
                    it may spread.</p>
                <p>They are in the mood to make some kind of mutual concessions for the common good
                    and to prevent an outbreak of war. A subcommittee of the League is just about to
                    bring in a report making a proposal to Italy and Abyssinia for a sort of
                    compromise in order to avert hostilities.</p>
                <p>In other words, the stage is set, and the psychology is correct for a movement to
                    be made calling for mutual concessions on the part of the interested Powers with
                    the possibility that the scope might be extended to include the important
                    elements of European discord as well as the difficulties in Africa.</p>
                <p>One of the troubles with the European situation is that these elements are not
                    treated as a whole. They are taken up piece-meal. They recur, one by one, from
                    time to time, and develop into clashes of interest which keep the whole of
                    Europe in a state of political unrest. No attempt has been made to weave them
                    all together and to eliminate at one time the major causes of trouble.</p>
                <p>Referring to this situation and mentioning the anxiety which prevailed in Geneva
                    and the desire which must be present there to make some mutual concessions in
                    order to avoid the conflict which apparently every nation desires to avoid, I
                    said that the nations in attendance at the League meeting were held together by
                    a common thought, <pb facs="0856" n="754" xml:id="pg_754"/> and I believed any
                    of them would be willing now to make some concession in the interest of general
                    security and peace.</p>
                <p>I approached Mussolini with an appeal to his alleged pacific intentions, with an
                    appeal to his vanity, and with an appeal to his sense of the dramatic. I
                    pictured the drama of his refusing a compromise offered by Geneva but
                    immediately taking charge himself of the whole proceedings and making his own
                    proposal as a supplement and demanding that the other Powers make some
                    concession comparable to his. I appealed to his vanity by calling it his own
                    idea—his Four Power Pact—his arrangement between Italy, France, England and
                    Germany, the abortive pact which has never become operative but which might be
                    used by him to further this program. I appealed to him in the ways which, as I
                    understand him, are most apt to interest his understanding, sympathy, and
                    support, with the hope that through those emotions might lie the way to induce
                    him to consider some sort of compromise and pacific settlement. As I went
                    through the recital he made only one or two interruptions. For the rest, he sat
                    with rapt attention and an intent look upon his face. He betrayed no emotion.
                    The expression on his face was fixed. His eyes were immovable and his attention
                    was complete. I doubt if he had ever even in his own mind woven together all the
                    elements of discord in Europe with the related problems of Africa. There was the
                    necessity for German expansion. There was the necessity for Italian expansion.
                    There was the independence of Austria. There was the right of Germany to arm.
                    There was the air Locarno and the hope of reduced armaments. There was the
                    security of France against attack by Germany. These were all woven together
                    about Europe and Africa. The contributions to be made were that Italy should
                    renounce some of her ambitions, even with the thought that the low-land tribes
                    in Abyssinia might not consent and that he might have his little war anyhow.
                    There was the contribution of Germany to guarantee the independence of Austria.
                    There was the contribution of France to agree to the armament of Germany. There
                    was the contribution of England to return part of Germany’s African colonies.
                    And there was the concession of England to join in an air pact to include Italy,
                    which she has heretofore refused, having limited her proposal to France and
                    Germany.</p>
                <p>If it could be done, it would eliminate the constant irritation about German
                    aspirations in Austria. It would eliminate the continuing French fear of German
                    aggression, which is the football of politics in France and used by the
                    intermittently reappearing members of the Cabinet as one of the means to
                    maintain themselves in political control. It would provide for the systematic
                    reduction of military establishments. It would provide an opportunity for the
                    reduction of tariffs and obstacles to commerce and some sort of related
                    stabilization <pb facs="0857" n="755" xml:id="pg_755"/> of monetary values. It
                    would provide for realizing the expansionist aspirations of Germany and of
                    Italy. It would take out of Europe the major points of clashing interest and
                    re-introduce an era of limited armament, peace, and commerce.</p>
                <p>I was saying that the Governments represented at Geneva are now held together by
                    a common thought, and I believed any of them would be willing to make some
                    concession in the interest of general security and peace, and that Geneva was
                    about to make him some proposition of conciliation and compromise.</p>
                <p>He interrupted to say “The compromise will not be acceptable.”</p>
                <p>I then continued, “I understand that to be the case, and let us assume that you
                    do refuse; that you say, ‘I will not accept the proposal’; but that you then
                    take charge of the negotiations and say ‘I have a proposal of my own to make to
                    you. I will make certain concessions provided each of the great Governments in
                    Europe will make concessions.’”</p>
                <p>I suggested that he limit his ambitions in Ethiopia to the extent of leaving
                    intact that part of the country which was the original Ethiopia, as indicated
                    upon the maps which he had filed along with his memorial with the League of
                    Nations, with certain additions to the South and Southwest, and that by
                    agreement with England and France he occupy or take over a large part of the
                    remaining territory but that the original Kingdom of Ethiopia be continued as an
                    independent state.</p>
                <p>That was to be his contribution to the general cause. Instead of proceeding to
                    take over the whole territory he would himself suggest a renunciation of some of
                    his objectives provided each of the western Powers would make some contribution
                    of their own to the general cause of peace and proceed to eliminate the
                    principal and recurring causes of war in Europe as well as in Africa. His
                    contribution was based on the thought that he had proceeded with his military
                    plans and that his soldiers were there and that his needs for territorial
                    expansion had been admitted in various quarters.</p>
                <p>It was then proposed that he demand of England and France certain concessions on
                    their part. England was to agree to return to Germany a part of the former
                    German colonies in southeast Africa.</p>
                <p>At this point he raised up his hand and said, “England! Return colonies! It is to
                    laugh! England would never return anything!”</p>
                <p>I replied that he might find an unexpected willingness to cooperate and that he
                    should demand of the other Governments that each of them make some contribution
                    and that that would be the contribution of England. Germany would then be
                    brought into the discussions. His own Four Power Pact would be operating. In
                    case Germany should receive her colonies she would agree, as the <hi
                        rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi>, to guarantee the independence of Austria;
                    that England, France, and <pb facs="0858" n="756" xml:id="pg_756"/> Italy should
                    then admit the right of Germany to have the land and air armament which she now
                    had and which existed as a matter of fact and that this would be the
                    contribution of France. That the four Governments, England, France, Italy, and
                    Germany, should agree immediately within fifteen or thirty days seriously to
                    attend a conference for the reduction of their respective armaments and that the
                    principles of Locarno be extended to the air and to include all four
                    Governments, and at the same time to have another conference to consider
                    stabilization amongst their currencies and the reduction of duties and tariff
                    barriers.</p>
                <p>In this way each of the four great Governments would be making contributions, and
                    each of them would benefit proportionately, all of them having the prospect of a
                    long period of peace in Europe and each of them gaining something direct and
                    specific: Germany, her colonies; France, her security against attack from
                    Germany reinforced by the air Locarno and with reduced German armies; Italy, the
                    independence of Austria; and Italy and Germany, their right of expansion and an
                    enlarged sphere of activity in Africa, and all without the war.</p>
                <p>To all this he had listened attentively and with an apparent deep interest. His
                    position did not change while I spoke, nor did he interrupt except for the two
                    instances mentioned. When I finished he continued to regard me for a moment,
                    then sat back in his chair, and in a very quiet voice said, “It is too late. My
                    plans have developed too far. My soldiers down there could not be controlled.
                    They would act on their own account, and what could I do with my army of a
                    million?”</p>
                <p>He then proceeded to elaborate upon the situation and to make a long historical
                    review. He said that the Ethopians had a feeling of superiority as regards the
                    Italians, which had started at the battle of Adowa and that the effects of it
                    had been a source of irritation to Italy and had caused great difficulty in the
                    Italian colonies, because the Ethopians thought they could act with something of
                    contempt toward the Italians; that the celebration of the victory at Adowa was
                    the national holiday of Ethopia and that each celebration was a matter of
                    offense to Italy.</p>
                <p>He then made a discourse of some length upon the nature of the people in that
                    country and analyzed the component elements of the population, saying that of
                    the ten million inhabitants seven million of them were subject races and slaves,
                    and the subject races were subordinated to the ruling class and were similar to
                    slaves in that they were not free; that the remaining three million of the
                    population were the ruling element and were a very strong war-like race of
                    mountaineers who were wonderful fighters and adversaries. They had subjugated
                    all the surrounding tribes but they exercised no continuing influence or control
                    over them from the point of view of political or <pb facs="0859" n="757"
                        xml:id="pg_757"/> governmental authority; that the people were illiterate,
                    wild, barbarous, and in no way entitled to consideration by or respect of
                    civilized nations, for Ethopia was not a nation but an aggregation of slaves
                    under a barbaric control.</p>
                <p>Mussolini then proceeded to the question of sanctions, and he showed every
                    indication of strong, deep feeling and some anger. He mentioned one by one the
                    activities of France in Morocco, where he said the natives had been murdered by
                    the wholesale, and that within the last few years, and without any public outcry
                    or expression of pity, and that there had been no mention of sanctions; the
                    Chaco War, for which various efforts in settlement had been made but that there
                    had been no conversation about the application of sanctions; that action of
                    Germany in violating the Treaty of Versailles during the present calendar year,
                    and about that there had been no talk of sanctions; the action of the English in
                    Irak four years ago in the course of which by their ruthless methods the
                    inhabitants had been literally massacred, and without a word of protest from the
                    public, and without even a mention of sanctions; the matter of Japan and her
                    operations in Manchuria and in other parts of China in which they had infringed
                    upon the sovereignty of China which was not a disgraceful or a barbaric state
                    and that there had been not one word of sanctions; and that today in northwest
                    India England is shooting down natives who rebel at her methods, and not a
                    single criticism is levelled at her and no mention of sanctions; but when Italy
                    (and here he sat up in his chair, raised his voice, wrinkled up his forehead,
                    tapped his breast with his fingers, and looked at me with a direct intensity),
                    “But when Italy proceeds to rectify wrongs which have been committed against her
                    and to secure the rights of her colonies and to proceed to a legitimate
                    expansion—which even England has recognized—when I proceed, they talk about
                    sanctions!”</p>
                <p>He then calmed down again and proceeded slowly in a quiet voice but determined
                    manner to say, “It is too late to talk of compromise. It is too late to withdraw
                    any of my plans for operation in East Africa. I will proceed. I will not
                    interfere with anyone. I do not expect anyone will interfere with me. But I will
                    not permit interference. I have one million men under arms in Italy. I have a
                    competent navy. I have an air force with a certain superiority. I will not
                    permit interference from any source.”</p>
                <p>He then followed this line of conversation: he said it is too late to talk of the
                    things I had suggested and it is not timely as they involve European questions.
                    This is purely a colonial matter for Italy. It must continue as a colonial and
                    local matter. If it is continued that way, just as was the action of France in
                    Morocco, there is no need for it to involve anybody. As soon as it ceases to be
                    a colonial matter it becomes a European matter, and as soon as there are
                    European <pb facs="0860" n="758" xml:id="pg_758"/> developments in a colonial
                    matter it assumes a very complicated character. So that the only thing to do is
                    to keep it a purely colonial matter, and if nobody interfered with him, he will
                    interfere with nobody, but will proceed along the ways that he had planned and
                    arranged.</p>
                <p>He then referred to American history. He said that we had no very bad neighbors
                    but that we had had from time to time, and that our history proved that we would
                    insist upon and secure proper treatment of our nationals near the border and
                    protect them from raids and molestations. He recalled the war with Spain over
                    Cuba and remarked how roundly we had beaten Spain, who was at that time a bad
                    neighbor. He mentioned the Civil War and said that the north had given a supreme
                    effort and had beaten the south. He referred to our difficulties with Mexico and
                    said that when that bad neighbor had harassed our borders, we had not hesitated
                    to show our superiority and protect our interests. And he said that he thought
                    that if America was troubled with neighbors like Abyssinia, who maltreated
                    American citizens and disturbed the Government, America would feel the same way.
                    The fact was that Italy had a very bad neighbor and had tried for a long time to
                    live in amicable relations with her but that it was no longer possible to do so.
                    He was proceeding to take care of Italian interests in the Italian colonies in
                    East Africa and would render them secure from any further attacks and from any
                    further indignities at the hands of the Ethiopians.</p>
                <p>He added that Abyssinia would be civilized and opened up to commerce of all the
                    nations after order had been restored. European and American capital and
                    cooperation would be welcomed and business relations rendered secure.</p>
                <p>I then referred to the reflection on the League and the diminished influence of
                    that organization in the future if Italy proceeded in spite of its objections.
                    He denied the League would suffer. He said he would not withdraw from it. That
                    the League would continue and Italy with it. He then referred sarcastically to
                    Egypt and asked, “Why is Egypt not a member of the League of Nations?” and
                    answered the question by saying “Because England will not permit her to be.” He
                    said that he had no criticism to make of the British Empire or the way it was
                    built up. He said that that was done in former times but that many of its
                    peoples were still held in subjugation. While he had no desire to criticise
                    England, he did not want England to pass judgment on him and would not admit her
                    right to criticise him or his methods in Abyssinia.</p>
                <p>Several times during the conversation I interrupted his remarks at pertinent
                    points and reverted to one phase or another of the suggestion I had made, making
                    arguments designed to appeal to the opportunity <pb facs="0861" n="759"
                        xml:id="pg_759"/> which presented itself to him to settle not only the
                    African question but all the important elements of the complicated European
                    situation.</p>
                <p>His responses were always reasonable and well considered but invariably negative
                    as regards conciliation and definitely opposed to any compromise of any kind.
                    His principal reactions to my suggestions were that it was a colonial matter and
                    must be kept as such and that it was now too late, because of the advanced stage
                    of his military preparations, to consider any compromise. As regards his remark
                    that it was “too late” I must comment that it has always been “too late.” He
                    determined on this venture several years ago. In the summer of 1934 factories
                    were working three shifts on war material, orders had been placed for cloth for
                    uniforms for a large army and half a million sun-helmets were in process of
                    manufacture, all of which I reported at the time. So that it was “too late” in
                    1934—and, of course, it is “too late” in 1935 to stop a war which had been
                    conceived two years or more in advance, prepared for in the intervening time,
                    and which is now ready to proceed.</p>
                <p>His antagonism to England was marked. His sarcastic ejaculation that England
                    would give up nothing in the way of colonies, when I projected the release of
                    the former German colonies; his ironic reference to Egypt and her non-membership
                    in the League of Nations, are indicative of his entire mental attitude toward
                    England. There was apparent an ill-subdued hostility toward Great Britain as
                    such, not only as regards her opposition to his plans in Ethiopia. He seemed to
                    personify that marked hatred of England in all its manifestations which is a
                    distinct feature of all Italy today. The reflections of that sentiment in the
                    press are mild in comparison to the outspoken hatred one meets everywhere in
                    Italy and in every walk of life—though it is to be remarked that that feeling is
                    not universal, for some of the upper class are fearful of the impending clash
                    and express great respect for England’s power. But the Duce this afternoon was
                    the epitome of a national antagonism.</p>
                <p>He finally rose, and we walked slowly to the door. As I left him I impressed upon
                    him again and asked him to remember that I was not this afternoon the spokesman
                    of my Government and that I had broached the subject to him purely out of my
                    understanding of European politics and out of my personal desire to be of
                    service if possible in avoiding what had many characteristics of being a very
                    great complication in Europe. He said that he understood and that he would
                    consider it as such. He shook hands warmly, smiled genially, thanked me for my
                    interest—and I left.</p>
                <p>During this interview there were lacking any indications of the histrionic which
                    have characterized some of my other interviews with him in the past. There was
                    no play-acting at all. He was suave, <pb facs="0862" n="760" xml:id="pg_760"/>
                    courteous, quiet, simple, direct, from time to time forceful, very expressive.
                    Occasionally he gave evidences of temper, but never lost perfect self-control.
                    Throughout it all he gave the definite impression of a calm, quiet, determined
                    man who had made an irrevocable decision. There is no turning back nor turning
                    aside. Mussolini intends to proceed in Abyssinia, insofar as the physical
                    possibilities of his army, navy, and air force will permit, over any obstacles
                    and in spite of any interference. If he is to be prevented, it will be by force
                    of arms, and not by persuasion. His manner in speaking of his army, his navy,
                    and his air force, left no doubt that the man is supremely confident of his
                    ability to handle the situation and to handle England too in case she should
                    attempt to prevent his actions.</p>
                <p>In holding this conversation I realize that I engaged upon an undertaking which
                    was dangerous in that it might have been used—might still be used—as a pretext
                    for involving the American Government. I realized that when I decided to talk to
                    him on the matter. However, I was prepared to act immediately in an effective
                    way to disconnect the American Government from any complicity whatsoever, and I
                    will be ready to conduct myself in a convincing manner in case the necessity
                    develops. However, I do not expect any such contingency to arise. In the first
                    place, I obtained Mussolini’s consent to proceed in my individual capacity. In
                    the second place, I doubt if he could use the incident to any advantage to
                    himself or to his Government for the simple reason it would be additional
                    evidence he had refused to consider another proposal for peaceful
                    settlement.</p>
                <p>However, I report the matter fully to you but do not ask you to approve my action
                    or anything I may have said. I report simply as a matter of which you should be
                    advised.</p>
                <p>If I need to invoke any justification for my unauthorized action I will simply
                    say that in the situation which exists I feel that any person with a full
                    comprehension of the dangerous possibilities to European peace with contacts
                    with persons in authority would be neglectful of his highest duties if he failed
                    to do what he could to contribute to an understanding. I only regret that I have
                    failed to achieve anything.</p>
                <p>In closing I desire to call your attention to two phases of this interview which
                    have singular political significance.</p>
                <p>First. This proposal I made to Mussolini offered him a perfect road of escape.
                    Instead of accepting an offer of compromise from the League I proposed to him
                    the thought of an alternative which would have improved his diplomatic position,
                    which could have been used to gain him credit in the world, which would have
                    given him the offensive in the “battle for peace”. It would have permitted him
                    to shift his entire position and have enabled him to sit back and watch <pb
                        facs="0863" n="761" xml:id="pg_761"/> others accept or refuse to compromise.
                    Their refusal would have helped to justify him in the light of world opinion. It
                    offered him a perfect “out”.</p>
                <p>He does not want an “out”. He does not want a way of escape. He proposes to go
                    straight ahead, in spite of everybody and against anybody.</p>
                <p>His refusal to accept a suggestion which could, in those circumstances, be put to
                    very great use in bolstering his esteem in world opinion, is very
                    significant.</p>
                <p>He is adamant. He is irrevocably determined and serenely calm and is riding into
                    the face of a storm which will either ruin him and bring disaster to his
                    country, or raise him actually to that pedestal where he is sentimentally placed
                    by his fanatic adherents.</p>
                <p>Second. One of his first remarks when I had finished speaking was, “What would I
                    do with my army of a million?” And what would he do? To disband them would
                    create merely a million unemployed. To stop war orders at the factory would
                    throw others out of work and increase the number of idle, add possibilities for
                    local discontent, and foment trouble. He now has no unemployed, everybody is
                    busy, and the entire country organized. Economic necessity is driving him
                    forward. Hope of fame and riches in Africa is lighting the way. The grandeur of
                    Empire and the dream of glory buoy him up. His determination to fight his way
                    through the encirclement of economic poverty and his fear of facing the social,
                    economic and political phases of a <hi rend="italic">volte-face</hi> have lined
                    the road of his advance.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Breckinridge Long</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
