<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-10-13T16:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-10-13T16:30:00-05:00" n="641" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d641">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">765.84/1784: Telegram</note>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                            State</gloss> to <gloss type="to">President
                                            Roosevelt</gloss>
                                    </hi>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-10-13T16:30:00-05:00">October 13, 1935—4:30 p.m.</date>
                                    </dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>Your telegram October 13<note n="88" xml:id="d641fn88">Not
                                        printed.</note> requesting exact language Paris Pact under
                                    which it can be “invoked”. There is no provision and no language
                                    prescribing any method of its invocation. The Pact simply
                                    outlaws war as a solution of international controversies and
                                    renounces it as an instrument of national policy, and the
                                    signatories agree that <pb facs="0876" n="774" xml:id="pg_774"/>
                                    all disputes of whatever nature shall be settled only by pacific
                                    means. Former Secretaries of State have unofficially expressed
                                    the opinion that the Pact impliedly authorizes and calls for
                                    consultation; and it is our view that consultation at the
                                    present stage at least does not contemplate anything more than a
                                    concerted or simultaneous appeal by all of the signatories to
                                    the belligerent countries to abide by their legal and moral
                                    obligations by desisting from further hostilities and returning
                                    to a state of peace.</p>
                                <p>The two substantive articles are as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <list>
                                            <item>“Article 1. The High Contracting Parties solemnly
                                                declare, in the names of their respective peoples,
                                                that they condemn recourse to war for the solution
                                                of international controversies and renounce it as an
                                                instrument of national policy in their relations
                                                with one another.</item>
                                            <item>Article 2. The High Contracting Parties agree that
                                                the settlement or solution of all disputes or
                                                conflicts, of whatever nature or of whatever origin
                                                they may be, which may arise among them, shall never
                                                be sought except by pacific means.”</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </quote>
                                </p>
                                <p>May I sum up our record thus far as follows: The League, with the
                                    special cooperation of England, France and others of its members
                                    assumed leadership and initiative at the outset in the endeavor
                                    to preserve peace. The United States, avoiding any interference
                                    with this plan and movement, sought to cooperate at every stage
                                    in every practical way consistent with our well defined foreign
                                    policy. These efforts of the United States revolved around the
                                    Paris Pact and our obligations under it. We repeatedly recited
                                    and emphasized the Pact and the solemn and inescapable
                                    obligations of each signatory. We went further and, to all
                                    practical intent and purpose, really invoked it both in public
                                    statements and special urgings upon the Italian Government. In
                                    reply to a British Government inquiry<note n="89" xml:id="d641fn89">See telegram No. 472, September 25, 6
                                        p.m., from the Ambassador in the United Kingdom, <ref target="#pg_766">p. 766</ref>.</note> we some days ago
                                    cabled Bingham<note n="90" xml:id="d641fn90">Telegram No. 270,
                                        September 27, 6 p.m., to the Ambassador in the United
                                        Kingdom, <ref target="#pg_767">p. 767</ref>.</note> that we
                                    would not be opposed to accepting an invitation to a
                                    consultation of the signatories for the presumed purpose of
                                    further mobilizing world opinion. But we especially referred to
                                    what we and others had already said and done in this respect,
                                    and to what the League and its members have been and are doing
                                    in a far more substantial respect, and raised the question of
                                    the hurtful interference that might result to the League and its
                                    concrete program by now projecting an invocation of the Paris
                                    Pact. We have, during the days since, been closely observing and
                                    studying every phase of situation as it might involve Paris Pact
                                    and still are doing so. Our present slant of mind is as it has
                                    been heretofore, but we feel that if there is to be an
                                    invocation in existing circumstances not the American <pb facs="0877" n="775" xml:id="pg_775"/> Government nor the
                                    League but four to six important governments in North and South
                                    America and Europe would through diplomatic channels more
                                    appropriately initiate this formal step.</p>
                                <p>I herewith submit proposed draft of cable to Bingham for your
                                        approval<note n="91" xml:id="d641fn91">In a telegram dated
                                        October 14, 1935, President Roosevelt replied: “Think draft
                                        of your proposed cable to Bingham is excellent.”
                                        (765.84/1783)</note> as follows:</p>
                                <p>[Here follows text of telegram No. 299, October 14, 1 p.m., to
                                    the Ambassador in the United Kingdom, printed <hi rend="italic">infra.</hi>]</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                    </signed>
                                </closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>