<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Near Eastern Affairs ( (Murray) )
                    to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d795</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">795</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-12-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-12-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-12-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-12-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="795"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d795">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">765.84/3022</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Near Eastern
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murray</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-12-12">December 12,
                            1935</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary</hi>: We have discussed with the Legal
                    Adviser’s Office the question presented by the recent bombardment of the Seventh
                    Day Adventist Hospital at Dessie by Italian airplanes. The facts in the case and
                    our conclusions as to possible action are as follows: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Statements from missionary doctors and newspaper correspondents make
                            it clear that the hospital was severely bombed on December 6th despite
                            the fact that it was plainly marked with numerous red crosses and was
                            flying a large American flag. According to reports from the Chargé
                            d’Affaires at Addis Ababa, the hospital building is located at some
                            distance outside of the town of Dessie. At the same time it seems clear
                            that substantial numbers of Ethiopian troops were concentrated in the
                            vicinity of Dessie and it is an established fact that the Emperor was in
                            the city, and apparently nearby the hospital.</item>
                        <label>3 [<hi rend="italic">2</hi>].</label>
                        <item>Reports from both the Chargé d’Affaires at Addis Ababa and from the
                            Consul at Geneva make clear that the hospital was affiliated with the
                            Ethiopian Red Cross and consequently entitled to the protection accorded
                            by the Red Cross Convention of 1929. In this connection it is pertinent
                            to mention that foreign Red Cross establishments operating as such in
                            belligerent territories are entitled to the protection of the Convention
                            only in those cases where the Government of the establishment in
                            question has given its approval to the organization. We have not given
                            our approval to the establishment at Dessie or to any other organization
                            of a similar character operating in Ethiopia. Nevertheless, since the
                            hospital at Dessie is duly recognized by the Ethiopian Red Cross, and
                            thus entitled to the protection of the Convention, it might be asserted
                            that this Government has a secondary interest in the institution not
                            only because the hospital is to considerable extent, if not entirely, an
                            American organization, but also because the United States is a party to
                            the Red Cross Convention.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The Consul at Geneva has learned that the International Red Cross has
                            forwarded to the Italian Red Cross a copy of the protest against this
                            bombardment executed by the Ethiopian Red Cross and transmitted to
                            Geneva by the Ethiopian Government. In conveying this protest to the
                            Italian Red Cross the International Red Cross authorities requested that
                            the Italian Government investigate the allegations of the Ethiopian Red
                            Cross and added the following statement: <pb facs="1006" n="904"
                                xml:id="pg_904"/>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The Tafari Makonnen Hospital figures on the list addressed to
                                    you on November 6 of hospitals authorized to display the Red
                                    Cross. We did not know that it was an American missionary
                                    hospital, but we take the liberty of reminding you that the
                                    missions at work on Ethiopian territory were mentioned in our
                                    telegram to you dated October 15. Furthermore, a list such as
                                    that communicated to you is intended only for reference use when
                                    need arises and cannot include all stationary hospitals let
                                    alone field hospitals legitimately covered by the Red Cross.
                                    This emblem alone ought to be sufficient guarantee of
                                    protection.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>It seems clear from the foregoing that the appropriate international
                            body, the International Red Cross at Geneva, has already brought the
                            protest of the Ethiopian Red Cross to the attention of the Italian
                            authorities. Nevertheless, it might well be said that we might likewise
                            be justified in bringing the matter to the attention of the Italian
                            authorities on two grounds: (1) the American character of the
                            institution which was injured and (2) as a signatory of the Red Cross
                            Convention we have a secondary interest in seeing that the provisions of
                            the agreement are carried out with respect to American institutions,
                            even those institutions which are operating in the war zone without the
                            approval of this Government.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>On the other hand, it must be borne in mind that we have urged
                            American missionaries in Ethiopia on numerous occasions to leave the
                            country. If, acting contrary to our advice, they continue to remain in
                            the danger zone it is at their own risk and we have a clear right to
                            refuse to afford them protection if such seems to be the proper course.
                            Furthermore, it is not apparent that a protest if made to the Italian
                            authorities would have any greater effect than that already made by the
                            International Red Cross authorities. In addition it is not altogether
                            clear that the hospital at Dessie is a 100 per cent American
                            institution.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>We are informed in the latter connection by the Seventh Day Adventist
                            headquarters here in Washington that the land on which the hospital is
                            built was furnished by the Ethiopian Emperor who likewise contributed
                            15,000 thalers (about $5,000 at the then existing rate of exchange)
                            toward the cost of the building. The Adventist headquarters is rather
                            certain that the deed to the property is held by their organization or
                            by one of its members, but before advising us officially to that effect
                            they consider it necessary to obtain information from their London
                            office which has direct supervision over Ethiopian activities of the
                            church. Apparently the bulk of the funds used in supporting the hospital
                            come from the United States but it is possible that funds are
                            contributed from various European countries where the church has
                            branches. Moreover, we know definitely that some of the personnel of the
                            hospital are not American citizens.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>The Seventh Day Adventist headquarters here have also raised <pb
                                facs="1007" n="905" xml:id="pg_905"/> informally the question of
                            submitting a claim to the Italian Government for the damage done to
                            their property at Dessie. The Legal Adviser’s Office is of the opinion
                            that such a claim could be supported only if it can be shown that the
                            hospital was immune from attack (that now seems to be the case) and that
                            the building was damaged not merely as a casualty of war but was
                            wilfully attacked. It would be most difficult to establish that the
                            Italian attack was wilful, for the Italian authorities would undoubtedly
                            contend that the bombardment was intended as an attack upon the
                            concentration of Ethiopian troops at Dessie and that the falling of
                            bombs on the hospital was an incident which could not be avoided unless
                            the Italian planes descended to an altitude which would have unduly
                            exposed them to Ethiopian fire. Under the circumstances it seems
                            unlikely that a claim could be established.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>In view of all the circumstances as set forth above, it would appear
                            to be wise to refrain from making any protest to the Italian Government
                            at this time.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>It would appear to be proper, however, to consider the advisability of
                            bringing to the attention of the Italian Government the fact that
                            several American institutions are located in provincial towns in
                            Ethiopia and request that this information be brought to the knowledge
                            of Italian military authorities in East Africa. Similar action, it will
                            be recalled, was taken with respect to American institutions at Addis
                            Ababa and there is no good reason why the same information should not be
                            conveyed with respect to property outside the capital. Before taking
                            even that action, however, it would seem to be prudent to obtain
                            definite information from the missionary organizations in the United
                            States as to the extent of American interests in their lands and
                            buildings in Ethiopia. If you agree with this conclusion we shall
                            communicate with the missionary organizations here and seek the
                            information desired.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wallace Murray</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
