<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-03-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-03-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="810" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d810">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">882.6176F51/411<hi rend="superscript">8/11</hi></note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Agreement Between the Government of Liberia and
                                    the Finance Corporation of America, Signed March 16, 1935</hi>
                            </head>
                            <dateline>
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1935-03-16">March 16, 1935</date>
                            </dateline>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Agreement</hi>, dated, for convenience, as of
                                the first day of January, 1935, by and between the Government of the
                                Republic of Liberia, of the first part, (hereinafter referred to as
                                the Government), Finance Corporation of America, a corporation
                                organized and existing under and by virtue of the laws of the State
                                of Delaware, United States of America, of the second part,
                                (hereinafter referred to as the Corporation), <pb facs="1028" n="926" xml:id="pg_926"/> and The National City Bank of New
                                York, a national banking association organized and existing under
                                the laws of the United States of America, of the third part
                                (hereinafter referred to as the Fiscal Agent);</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, the Government and the
                                Corporation entered into a Loan Agreement as of the first day of
                                September, 1926, in which the Fiscal Agent was party of the third
                                part, which Agreement thereafter became effective upon ratification
                                by the Government, and is in effect; and</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, the Government represents to the
                                Corporation that it finds itself unable to fulfill certain of the
                                obligations undertaken by it by virtue of the terms and conditions
                                of said Loan Agreement; and</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, the Government is desirous of
                                modifying certain of the obligations undertaken by it under and by
                                virtue of the terms of said Loan Agreement; and</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, the Government represents to the
                                Corporation that it has decided to undertake a Three-Year Plan for
                                the accomplishment of certain important improvements in sanitation,
                                public instruction, hinterland administration, judicial system,
                                interior road extension and other matters of social and economic
                                welfare; and to that end will retain, in addition to the officers
                                appointed under the Loan Agreement, the services of six competent
                                foreign specialists, of whom the majority, including the Chief
                                Administrative Specialist, are to be American citizens; and</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, the Corporation fully sympathizes
                                with these purposes and is desirous of cooperating with the
                                Government for their attainment:</p>
                            <p>Now, <hi rend="smallcaps">Therefore</hi>, this Agreement is executed
                                for the purpose of modifying and supplementing said Loan Agreement
                                in the following respects only <hi rend="smallcaps">To Wit</hi>:</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section I</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Article I of the said Loan Agreement is hereby amended so as to
                                provide for a reduction of the basic interest rate from seven per
                                cent (7%) per annum, to five per cent (5%) per annum. Effective
                                January 1, 1935, and continuing until December 31, 1942, the
                                “External Forty-Year Sinking Fund Seven Per Cent. Gold Bonds” shall
                                bear interest at the rate of five per cent (5%) per annum, payable
                                semi-annually on January 1st and July 1st in each year.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section II</hi>
                            </p>
                            <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>It is understood and agreed that while the Government is
                                    obligated for the payment of interest at said five per cent (5%)
                                    per annum on all outstanding Bonds issued under said Loan
                                    Agreement, <pb facs="1029" n="927" xml:id="pg_927"/> the
                                    Government shall be relieved from the payment of said interest
                                    for any calendar year when the total revenues and receipts of
                                    the Government shall be less than $450,000.00, (which amount is
                                    required for the operating expenses of the Government, certain
                                    public works and salaries and allowances of the three fiscal
                                    officials, the military adviser, and the six foreign
                                    specialists), and in this event, the said interest shall be
                                    waived and condoned.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>For any calendar year when the total revenues and receipts for
                                    the Government shall exceed $450,000.00, all of such excess to
                                    and including such an amount as will equal five per cent (5%)
                                    interest for one year on all outstanding Bonds issued under the
                                    said Loan Agreement of 1926, shall be set apart by the
                                    Government and paid over to the Corporation for application
                                    against and/or liquidation of the said five per cent (5%)
                                    interest for such calendar year. In the event such excess over
                                    and above $450,000.00 shall not be sufficient to liquidate fully
                                    such five per cent (5%) interest for such calendar year, then
                                    the amount constituting the difference between such excess and
                                    the five per cent (5%) interest for such calendar year shall be
                                    waived and condoned.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>In the event the total revenues and receipts of the Government
                                    for any calendar year shall exceed $450,000.00, plus the amount
                                    necessary to liquidate fully such five per cent (5%) interest
                                    for such calendar year, and until such time as the amortization
                                    requirements of the said Loan Agreement of 1926 are no longer in
                                    arrears and are being currently complied with, at least
                                    thirty-three and one-third per cent (33⅓%) of such excess shall
                                    be applied to amortization of the Bonds issued and outstanding
                                    under the terms of the Loan Agreement of 1926, and/or under the
                                    terms of this Supplementary Agreement, and at least thirty-three
                                    and one-third per cent (33⅓%) of such excess shall be applied
                                    towards the liquidation of the principal only of the
                                    Government’s floating debt existing on December 31, 1934, which
                                    floating debt on that date was in an amount of approximately
                                    $650,000.00, and in no event to be applied against any floating
                                    indebtedness created after December 31, 1934.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                <item>In the event such floating debt shall have been liquidated in
                                    full prior to the time that the amortization requirements of the
                                    Loan Agreement of 1926 are no longer in arrears and are being
                                    currently complied with, then at least fifty per cent (50%) of
                                    the excess of the total revenues and receipts of the Government
                                    for each calendar year over and above $450,000.00, plus the
                                    amount necessary to liquidate fully such five per cent (5%)
                                    interest for such calendar year shall be applied to amortization
                                    of the Bonds issued and outstanding under the terms of the Loan
                                    Agreement of 1926 and/or under the terms of this Supplementary
                                    Agreement.</item>
                                <pb facs="1030" n="928" xml:id="pg_928"/>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The Government shall forthwith, after the date at which this
                                    Agreement becomes effective, execute and deliver to the
                                    Corporation additional bonds provided for under the said Loan
                                    Agreement of 1926 in the principal amount of three hundred and
                                    thirty-five thousand U. S. dollars ($335,000.00) in liquidation
                                    of past due interest coupons as of January 1st, 1935, inclusive,
                                    which coupons shall upon delivery of said bonds be surrendered
                                    to the Fiscal Agent for cancellation. Bonds issued in payment of
                                    overdue interest as herein provided shall be redeemable at par
                                    at any interest date upon notice given in the manner provided in
                                    Article V of the Loan Agreement, and the said bonds shall be
                                    stamped with a notice to that effect, and shall bear interest
                                    coupons beginning with coupons to mature as of July 1st,
                                    1935.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section III</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Under the provisions of Article IX of the Loan Agreement for the
                                readjustment of the salaries of the fiscal officers, in the event of
                                a substantial change in money values, and, in recognition of the
                                existing financial emergency, to reduce the cost to the Government
                                of the operation of the fiscal service required by the Loan
                                Agreement, the fourth paragraph of Article IX of the Loan Agreement
                                is hereby amended to read as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“1. A Financial Adviser, who shall be designated and
                                        appointed as hereinbefore stated, at a salary of $9,000.00
                                        per annum U. S. Currency.</p>
                                    <p>“2. An official who shall be designated Supervisor of
                                        Revenues, and shall perform the duties devolving under the
                                        Loan Agreement upon the incumbents of the offices of
                                        Supervisor of Customs and Supervisor of Internal Revenue,
                                        (which are abolished), at a salary of $5,000.00 per annum,
                                        U. S. Currency.</p>
                                    <p>“3. A bonded Auditor appointed by Agreement between the
                                        President of the Republic of Liberia and the Fiscal Agent,
                                        at a salary of $5,000.00 per annum U. S. Currency.</p>
                                    <p>“4. A bonded Assistant Auditor, who shall be appointed by the
                                        President of the Republic of Liberia.</p>
                                    <p>“The salaries of the officers named in sub-paragraphs 1, 2,
                                        and 3 hereof shall be paid monthly in pounds sterling at the
                                        selling rate of exchange for United States dollars
                                        prevailing at the respective monthly due dates of
                                        payment.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section IV</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The first sentence of Article VIII is hereby amended to read as
                                follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“As an additional guarantee of the prompt payment of the Loan
                                        and to insure the efficient organization and functioning of
                                        the Liberian Fiscal Service and the administration thereof,
                                        the Government covenants and agrees to appoint to its
                                        service said Financial Adviser, who shall be designated by
                                        the President of the United States of America to the
                                        President of the Republic of Liberia and, subject to his
                                        approval, appointed to said office.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <pb facs="1031" n="929" xml:id="pg_929"/>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section V</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Article IX is hereby amended by the addition of the following
                                paragraph: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The number of the employees of the Financial Adviser, the
                                        Fiscal Officers and the Fiscal Service shall be sufficient
                                        for the efficient collection, audit, disbursement and
                                        administration of the revenues of the Government. The
                                        personnel shall be appointed by the President of Liberia
                                        upon the nomination by the Financial Adviser of persons
                                        qualified to fill vacancies. The Financial Adviser shall
                                        select his nominees from the Civil Service lists of
                                        qualified persons, if such be available; otherwise his
                                        nominations may be made at large, upon such tests of fitness
                                        as he may deem advisable. Such personnel shall serve under
                                        the jurisdiction of the Financial Adviser, who shall bear in
                                        mind the desire of the Government for the proper training of
                                        Liberian citizens for positions of trust and responsibility.
                                        The duties of such personnel, insofar as they may not have
                                        been prescribed by law, shall be prescribed by such
                                        regulations in pursuance thereof as may be issued from time
                                        to time by the Financial Adviser. The property and supplies
                                        for the use of such officers and employees shall be under
                                        the jurisdiction of the Financial Adviser. The number of
                                        employees of the Financial Adviser, the Fiscal Officers, and
                                        the Fiscal Service shall not exceed the average number of
                                        employees during the year 1930 or the average number of
                                        employees for the three-year period next preceding,
                                        whichever be greater, except by agreement between the
                                        President of Liberia and the Financial Adviser.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section VI</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>In Article IX, after the sentence: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p rend="flushleft">“The officers above mentioned shall perform
                                        such duties and employ such persons as may be defined by law
                                        or prescribed by the Government with or upon the advice of
                                        the Financial Adviser, as provided in Article XII”,</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">the subsequent sentence is hereby amended to read as
                                follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p rend="flushleft">“Such officers in the performance of their
                                        duties shall be responsible to the Financial Adviser;
                                        provided, nevertheless, that the Auditor and Assistant
                                        Auditor shall not be subject to control in making decisions
                                        upon matters within their jurisdiction.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section VII</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Article XII, paragraph numbered 3, is hereby amended to read as
                                follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“For the further security of the revenues and receipts, the
                                        Government shall maintain a Liberian Frontier Force, and
                                        shall further maintain patrol service by sea as may be
                                        necessary from time to time. The patrol service by sea shall
                                        be administered by the Customs Service. The Frontier Force
                                        shall be administered by the War Department. The strength of
                                        the Frontier Force shall be fixed by agreement <pb facs="1032" n="930" xml:id="pg_930"/> between the
                                        President of Liberia and the Financial Adviser, and it shall
                                        not be increased or decreased in number without the
                                        agreement of the Financial Adviser, except temporarily in
                                        case of emergency declared to be such by the Government. A
                                        duly qualified and experienced officer of American
                                        nationality shall be employed for the Government by the
                                        President of Liberia who shall report directly to the
                                        President of Liberia and who shall be senior in rank to the
                                        commanding officer of said Frontier Force. The salary of
                                        said officer shall not exceed the sum of (U. S.) $5,000.00
                                        per annum; provided, however, that said sum may be at any
                                        time increased or diminished by agreement between the
                                        Government and the Fiscal Agent. Such salary shall include
                                        all allowances except medical care and attendance, travel on
                                        duty and quarters suitable for his rank, or commutation
                                        therefor on the basis provided for officers in the United
                                        States Army drawing pay at the same rate, which shall be
                                        furnished by the Government. Among his duties shall be the
                                        preparation and execution of a plan of organization of the
                                        Force which shall be based on the idea of creating an
                                        efficient constabulary organization for the purposes
                                        aforesaid, and which plan shall include the qualifications
                                        and disciplining of all commissioned and non-commissioned
                                        officers and the training of the men in accordance with the
                                        best practice now obtaining in similar organizations.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section VIII</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Article XII, paragraph numbered 6, item designated (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) is hereby amended to read: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) Incorrectness or irregularity of
                                        the account to be paid.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section IX</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Article XII, paragraph numbered 6, is hereby amended by the addition
                                after the item designated (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) of the
                                following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) Fraud.</p>
                                    <p>“The decisions of the Auditor in relation to the approval or
                                        disapproval of accounts shall be final and conclusive,
                                        subject only to an appeal by the Government or the creditor
                                        to the Financial Adviser, which appeal shall be taken within
                                        ten days after notice of the ruling. The decisions of the
                                        Financial Adviser upon such appeals shall be final and
                                        conclusive upon the Executive but not upon the Judicial
                                        branch of the Government.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section X</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Article XII, paragraph numbered 8, third sentence, is hereby amended
                                to read: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p rend="flushleft">“The Financial Adviser may only refuse to
                                        approve the Budget when and if the disbursements which
                                        should be included therein, as provided in this Agreement,
                                        or by obligation of law, have not been properly included, or
                                        when and if the Budget submitted by the Secretary of the
                                        Treasury exceeds the estimates of the revenues as prepared
                                        by the Supervisor of Revenues, in conjunction with the
                                        Comptroller <pb facs="1033" n="931" xml:id="pg_931"/> of the
                                        Treasury, under the supervision of the Financial
                                        Adviser.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section XI</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Article XII, paragraph numbered 8, is hereby amended by the addition
                                thereto, immediately before the last sentence thereof, of the
                                following sentence: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p rend="flushleft">“No special appropriation shall be passed by
                                        the Legislature except in accordance with a supplement to
                                        the annual budget prepared and approved as herein provided
                                        with respect to such annual budget.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section XII</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>During the term of this Supplementary Agreement, as provided by
                                Section XVII hereof, the first sentence of Article XIII and
                                paragraphs one to six, inclusive, thereof are hereby amended to read
                                as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The first $450,000 of the annual revenues and receipts of
                                        the Government shall be applied by the Government in the
                                        following order: <list>
                                            <label>1.</label>
                                            <item>To the payment of the salaries, allowances and
                                                expenses of the Financial Adviser, the Auditor, the
                                                Supervisor of Revenues, the Military Adviser and the
                                                six foreign specialists; and the salaries of their
                                                staffs.</item>
                                            <label>2.</label>
                                            <item>To all other operating expenses of the
                                                Government.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </p>
                                    <p rend="flushleft">All revenues and receipts of the Government
                                        in excess of $450,000 annually shall be applied as provided
                                        in Section II hereof.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section XIII</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Article XVIII, paragraph designated (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>), is
                                hereby amended to read: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“No unexpended credit to any account provided for in the
                                        budget may be transferred to any other account of the budget
                                        or to any new account except in accordance with a supplement
                                        to the annual budget prepared and approved as herein
                                        provided with respect to such annual budget. Any credit to
                                        any account remaining unexpended at the end of any fiscal
                                        year shall be released and taken into account in the
                                        preparation of the budget for the next ensuing year.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section XIV</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>It is understood and agreed that in any fiscal year, after the
                                payment each month of the cost and expenses of the collection,
                                application, audit and administration of the revenues and receipts,
                                as provided in Section XII hereof, any balance of unassigned
                                revenues may be applied to the ordinary expenditures of the
                                Government.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section XV</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>In any calendar year when the total revenues and receipts of the
                                Government shall be less than $300,000.00 for the first six months
                                    <pb facs="1034" n="932" xml:id="pg_932"/> thereof, the interest
                                on all the outstanding Bonds issued under the Loan Agreement of
                                1926, which is payable on July first of such year, need not be paid
                                on that date, and in lieu thereof, the total interest on such Bonds
                                for such year shall be due and payable on January first of the next
                                succeeding year.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section XVI</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The word “dollar” or “dollars”, wherever used herein, unless
                                otherwise specifically indicated, shall mean Liberian dollars on the
                                basis that Four and Eighty One-Hundredths ($4.80) Liberian dollars
                                is equivalent to One Pound (£1:0:0) English Sterling.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section XVII</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>This Supplementary Agreement shall be and remain in force until the
                                thirty-first day of December, 1937, upon the expiration of which
                                period the provisions of the Loan Agreement of 1926 shall, <hi rend="italic">ipso facto</hi>, again become operative as
                                originally adopted, except as regards the amendments thereto made by
                                Sections IV to XI, inclusive, and Section XIII, hereof, which shall
                                continue in effect; provided, however, that Section I hereof shall
                                continue in effect until the 31st day of December, 1942.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section XVIII</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The National City Bank of New York has executed this Supplemental
                                Agreement as Fiscal Agent at the request of the other parties
                                hereto, upon the express understanding and agreement that no new
                                duties or responsibilities are incurred by it hereunder and that it
                                shall continue entitled to all the exemptions, assurances and
                                indemnities provided for in the Loan Agreement of 1926; and upon the
                                further understanding that said Supplementary Agreement shall be and
                                become effective only as and when all the Bonds outstanding under
                                the Loan Agreement shall have been stamped by the Fiscal Agent with
                                an appropriate legend reciting the execution and delivery of this
                                supplemental and amendatory agreement.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Section XIX</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>This Supplementary Agreement shall come into force and effect when
                                duly approved by the Legislature of the Republic of Liberia after
                                execution on behalf of the Government by the officer or officers
                                thereunto duly authorized; provided, that the Legislature of Liberia
                                shall have previously repealed all Legislative Acts and Executive
                                Orders in contravention of the Loan Agreement of 1926, including the
                                following measures heretofore enacted by it, namely: <pb facs="1035" n="933" xml:id="pg_933"/>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>The Act passed over the veto of the President constituting
                                        Chapter Seven of the Public Acts of the Thirty Sixth
                                        Legislature at the fourth session thereof entitled “An Act
                                        to Relieve the Strain Upon the Revenue of this
                                        Republic”;</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>The Joint Resolution approved December 23, 1932, entitled
                                        “Joint Resolution Authorizing the President of Liberia to
                                        Suspend Payment of Interest and Amortization on the 7% Gold
                                        Loan of 1926, and for other purposes”;</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>The Act approved January 6, 1933, entitled “An Act
                                        Providing for the Funding of the National Floating
                                        Debt”:</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>The Act approved January 31, 1933, entitled “An Act
                                        Relating to the Officials of the Loan Agreement; and</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>The Joint Resolution approved January 12, 1934, entitled
                                        “A Joint Resolution Amendatory to a Joint Resolution
                                        Authorizing the President of Liberia to Suspend Payment of
                                        Interest and Amortization on the 7% Gold Loan of 1926, and
                                        for other purposes, being Chapter II of the Acts of the
                                        Legislature of Liberia, approved December 23, A. D.
                                        1932.”</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <table cols="2" rows="3">
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Attest: <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">A. J. Sawyer</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The Government of the Republic of
                                            Liberia</hi>,<lb/>By <hi rend="smallcaps">Gabriel L.
                                            Dennis</hi>
                                        <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of the Treasury</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Attest: <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">F. C. Fisher</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Finance Corporation of
                                        America</hi>,<lb/>By <hi rend="smallcaps">Harvey S.
                                            Firestone, Jr.</hi>
                                        <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Attorney-in-Fact</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Attest: <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">K. J. Adorkor</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">National City Bank of New
                                        York</hi>,<lb/>By <hi rend="smallcaps">John Loomis</hi>
                                        <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Attorney-in-Fact</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <p>This Agreement made and entered into this 16th day of March, A.D.
                                1935, by and between Gabriel L. Dennis, Secretary of the Treasury,
                                acting for and on behalf of the Government of the Republic of
                                Liberia, of the first part, and Firestone Plantations Company, a
                                corporation organized and existing under and by virtue of the laws
                                of the State of Delaware, United States of America, engaged in
                                business in the Republic of Liberia, of the second part, hereinafter
                                known and referred to as the Company,</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">witnesseth</hi>: <list>
                                    <item>
                                        <hi rend="italic">First</hi>. The Company undertakes and
                                        agrees that it will forthwith proceed to cause the
                                        organization under the laws of a state of the United States
                                        of America of a corporation, to be called Bank of Monrovia,
                                        authorized by its charter or articles of incorporation to
                                        engage in the business of banking in the Republic of Liberia
                                        and other foreign countries.</item>
                                    <item>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Second</hi>. That the Company will cause
                                        the said Bank of Monrovia to apply for authorization to
                                        engage in the business of banking under the laws of the
                                        Republic of Liberia and to establish its principal place of
                                        business in the said Republic in the City of
                                        Monrovia.</item>
                                    <item>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Third</hi>. Upon the establishment in
                                        Monrovia of the said Bank of Monrovia the Government, at any
                                        time subsequent to the 30th day of <pb facs="1036" n="934" xml:id="pg_934"/> June, 1935, with the consent of the
                                        National City Bank, of New York, first had, will on the
                                        request of the Company designate said Bank of Monrovia its
                                        depositary for the purposes of the applicable provisions of
                                        the Loan Agreement of 1926 between the Government and
                                        Finance Corporation of America, and to that end will enter
                                        into an Agreement with the said Bank in accordance with the
                                        terms of the <hi rend="italic">pro forma</hi> Agreement
                                        hereunto attached, marked Annex A and made a part
                                        hereof.</item>
                                    <item>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Fourth</hi>. As security for the
                                        performance of its obligations to the Government, the
                                        Company will cause the Bank of Monrovia, simultaneously with
                                        the execution of the Depositary Agreement, to place in
                                        escrow in a bank in New York or London, bearer bonds of the
                                        Liberian Government, issued pursuant to the Loan Agreement
                                        of 1926, of the par value of Three Hundred Thousand dollars
                                        ($300,000.00) pursuant to an escrow agreement in terms as
                                        set forth in the form hereunto appended, marked Annex B, and
                                        made a part hereof.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">In Witness Whereof</hi>, the parties hereunto
                                have caused this agreement to be written and executed in Monrovia,
                                Liberia, the day and year first above set forth.</p>
                            <table cols="2" rows="3">
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Witnesses: <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">A. J. Sawyer</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The Government of the Republic of
                                            Liberia</hi>
                                        <lb/> By <hi rend="smallcaps">Gabriel L. Dennis</hi>
                                        <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of the Treasury</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">F. C. Fisher</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Firestone Plantations Company</hi>
                                        <lb/> By <hi rend="smallcaps">Harvey S. Firestone, Jr.</hi>
                                        <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">President</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Approved and Accepted: <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Edwin Barclay</hi>
                                        <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">President of Liberia</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head>Annex A</head>
                                <p rend="center">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Depositary Agreement Between the Government of
                                        the Republic of Liberia and the Bank of Monrovia</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, Article XVIII of the Loan
                                    Agreement dated September A. D. 1926, by and between the
                                    Government of Liberia and the Finance Corporation of America,
                                    provides that the Government shall designate a Depositary
                                    agreeable to the Fiscal Agent created in virtue of the terms of
                                    said Agreement, and</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, Bank of Monrovia, a banking
                                    institution organized under the laws of......., with registered
                                    office at......., is agreeable to the Fiscal Agent, The National
                                    City Bank of New York, as such Depositary,</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Therefore</hi>, it is agreed between
                                    Gabriel L. Dennis, Secretary of the Treasury, acting for and on
                                    behalf of the Government of Liberia, <pb facs="1037" n="935" xml:id="pg_935"/> hereinafter known and referred to as the
                                    Government, of the First Part, and Bank of Monrovia, hereinafter
                                    known and referred to as the Depositary, of the Second Part, <hi rend="smallcaps">That</hi>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section I</hi>. The Government hereby
                                            designates and appoints the said Bank of Monrovia as its
                                            legal Depositary, and the said Bank, in consideration of
                                            the compensation to be paid to it by the Government as
                                            hereinafter expressed, has accepted such appointment on
                                            the terms and conditions of this Agreement.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section II</hi>. The Government agrees
                                            with Bank of Monrovia to deposit with it as Depositary
                                            all receipts and revenues collected by and on behalf of
                                            the Republic of Liberia, indicating with each deposit
                                            the specific deposit account to which the Depositary
                                            should pass corresponding credit. The Government’s
                                            receipts for postal money orders and radio tolls, which
                                            will also be deposited, shall be kept in special
                                            accounts in trust as hereinafter provided.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section III</hi>. Liberian silver and
                                            copper coin shall be received by the Depositary from the
                                            Government for deposit at the fixed rate of Four dollars
                                            and eighty cents ($4.80) to the pound sterling; and the
                                            Government shall at the request of the Depositary accept
                                            and receive from the Depositary in payment of its
                                            cheques drawn on the Disbursement Accounts the whole or
                                            any part of such Liberian currency that it may have
                                            deposited in the Depositary, and at the same fixed
                                            rate.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section IV</hi>. The Depositary agrees
                                            to accept in Liberia all deposits made by the Government
                                            as outlined in paragraph 2 of this contract and to
                                            credit them to one or more deposit accounts as the
                                            Government may desire. For this purpose, the Government
                                            agrees to furnish the Depositary with an inclusive list
                                            of the deposit accounts which are desired to be
                                            maintained.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section V</hi>. The Government agrees
                                            with the Depositary that moneys received by the
                                            Depositary and credited to deposit accounts as indicated
                                            under Section II of this Contract, will be disposed of
                                            only by transfer to one or more disbursement accounts to
                                            be maintained by the Depositary. Such transfers will
                                            only be made by the Depositary upon receipt of numbered
                                            transfer orders requested by the Secretary of the
                                            Treasury, approved by the Auditor, and countersigned by
                                            the Financial Adviser. The Government further agrees
                                            with the Depositary that such transfers shall be at all
                                            times in full conformity with the terms of the Loan
                                            Agreement. It is further agreed that no responsibility
                                            shall attach to the Depositary for effecting any
                                            transfer in violation of the terms of the Loan Agreement
                                            provided the corresponding numbered transfer order has
                                            been duly approved as herein outlined.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section VI</hi>. To facilitate the
                                            operations outlined in the preceding Section, the
                                            Government will provide the Depositary with facsimile
                                                <pb facs="1038" n="936" xml:id="pg_936"/> signatures
                                            of the Secretary of the Treasury, the Auditor, and the
                                            Financial Adviser, and of those authorized to sign for
                                            them in their absence, as well as an inclusive list of
                                            disbursement accounts which are desired to be maintained
                                            by the Depositary.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section VII</hi>. Moneys transferred
                                            from deposit to disbursement accounts as outlined under
                                            Section V hereof, shall then be available for
                                            disbursement as provided in the Loan Agreement (Article
                                            XVIII, Section <hi rend="italic">d</hi> and Article XII,
                                            Section 6). It is agreed that such disbursements shall
                                            only be made by the Depositary against cheques drawn to
                                            the order of specific payees by the Secretary of the
                                            Treasury and countersigned by the Auditor, such cheques
                                            to bear in every case the name of the disbursement
                                            account against which they are to be charged and an
                                            exact reference to the Transfer Order under the
                                            authority of which they have been issued. In the event
                                            that the Depositary is in doubt as to the identity of
                                            the Payee or of the validity of any endorsement it may
                                            refer the cheque to the Secretary of the Treasury or to
                                            any official of the Government thereto designated in
                                            writing by the Secretary, for written authority to pay
                                            the cheque to the person asserting title thereto as
                                            payee or endorsee; and no responsibility shall attach to
                                            the Depositary for incorrect payments made upon such
                                            identification.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section VIII</hi>. The Government
                                            agrees with the Depositary that moneys arising from
                                            postal orders and radio tolls, which are deposited in a
                                            special trust account as outlined in Section II of this
                                            contract, shall be drawn upon warrant of the President
                                            by cheques of the Postmaster-General, and the Depositary
                                            agrees to pay such cheques as presented against these
                                            funds, provided sufficient funds are on hand in the
                                            trust account to cover them.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section IX</hi>. The Depositary agrees
                                            to name an Agent at each of the following Ports of
                                            Entry: Robertsport, Buchanan, River Cess, Greenville and
                                            Harper, for the protection of the Government revenues
                                            and receipts and for the requirements of its Fiscal
                                            Administration. Upon mutual agreement between the
                                            Government and the Depositary, further agents may be
                                            named or any of those agreed upon may be withdrawn, as
                                            conditions may justify. No responsibility will attach to
                                            the Government for the payment of any compensation to
                                            any Agent in virtue of the provisions of this
                                            Agreement.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section X</hi>. The Depositary will
                                            arrange with its designated Agents that the Government
                                            may draw cheques against the Depositary as provided
                                            under Section VII of this contract, indicating on the
                                            cheques that they are payable at a designated agency. It
                                            is agreed, however, that there will be no obligation on
                                            the part of the Agent to pay such cheques prior to
                                            receipt of advice from the Depositary, which advice the
                                            Depositary agrees to forward as soon as received from
                                                <pb facs="1039" n="937" xml:id="pg_937"/> the
                                            Government without, however, accepting any
                                            responsibility for delays in the mail or from other
                                            causes beyond its control.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section XI</hi>. The Government agrees
                                            to pay, and the Depositary agrees to accept, the
                                            following fees for services rendered the Government by
                                            it: <list>
                                                <label>
                                                  <hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                                <item>a commission of one per centum on Government
                                                  revenues and receipts deposited with the
                                                  Depositary;</item>
                                                <label>
                                                  <hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                                <item>for cable transfers to Europe and America,
                                                  three quarters of one per centum;</item>
                                                <label>
                                                  <hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                                <item>for drafts sold on Europe and America, one
                                                  half of one per centum.</item>
                                            </list>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>The cost of cable tolls for telegraphic transfers and
                                            of revenue stamps thereon and on drafts shall be paid by
                                            the Government. The Depositary agrees that it will not
                                            Chargé any commission for deposits of money brought from
                                            the United States of America on account of the Loan
                                            Agreement hereinbefore mentioned. And no Chargé
                                            whatsoever shall be made by the Depositary for keeping
                                            Government accounts required and necessary for the
                                            proper control of Government moneys under this
                                            Depositary Agreement.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section XII</hi>. The Secretary of the
                                            Treasury, the Financial Adviser, and the Auditor, or the
                                            designated representative of each of them, shall each
                                            have the right at all times during banking hours to
                                            examine such books and accounts of the Depositary as
                                            relate to Government accounts and verify balances held
                                            by the Depositary to the credit of the Government. The
                                            Depositary further agrees to render quarterly statements
                                            to the Secretary of the Treasury, the Financial Adviser
                                            and the Fiscal Agent.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section XIII</hi>. As security for the
                                            trust created by the terms of this Agreement the
                                            Depositary covenants to warrant to the Government the
                                            faithful and honest discharge of the duties herein
                                            imposed by placing in escrow in the hands of a banking
                                            institution in New York or London bonds of the Liberian
                                            Government issued pursuant to the Loan Agreement of 1926
                                            of the par value of Three Hundred Thousand Dollars
                                            ($300,000); provided, however, that in the event that
                                            the revenues of the Government shall exceed the sum of
                                            One Million Two Hundred Thousand Dollars ($1,200,000) in
                                            any one year during the life of this Agreement, the
                                            amount of the bonds in escrow shall be increased in an
                                            amount equal to twenty-five per centum of such
                                            excess.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section XIV</hi>. Should the
                                            Depositary refuse to cash any cheque duly signed by the
                                            officials of the Government designated by law and
                                            regulation and payable pursuant to the terms of this
                                            Agreement, or should it refuse to perform any of the
                                            duties herein imposed or neglect to keep and perform any
                                            of the covenants herein contained, then in <pb facs="1040" n="938" xml:id="pg_938"/> such case the
                                            Government shall be authorized to cancel this Agreement
                                            in accordance with Section XVI, anything to the contrary
                                            herein expressed notwithstanding.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section XV</hi>. During the life of
                                            this Agreement, all currencies imported or exported or
                                            shipped between ports in Liberia by the Depositary, or
                                            without the Republic shall be open to examination upon
                                            the premises of the Depositary by the Customs Officials
                                            in accordance with existing regulations.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Section XVI</hi>. It is agreed that
                                            this contract shall be effective for a period of five
                                            years from the date hereof, subject to cancellation upon
                                            three months’ notice by either party.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">In Witness Whereof</hi>, we have affixed
                                    our hands and seals at the City of Monrovia, in the County of
                                    Montserrado and Republic of Liberia, as of the.....day of.....A.
                                    D. 1935.</p>
                                <table cols="2" rows="2">
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>Witnesses:<lb/>________</cell>
                                        <cell>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">The Government of the Republic of
                                                Liberia</hi>
                                            <lb/> By________ <lb/>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Secretary of the Treasury</hi>
                                        </cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>________</cell>
                                        <cell>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bank of Monrovia</hi>
                                            <lb/> By________<lb/>Approved and
                                            Accepted:<lb/>______________ <lb/>
                                            <hi rend="italic">President of Liberia</hi>
                                        </cell>
                                    </row>
                                </table>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head>Annex B</head>
                                <p rend="center">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Escrow Agreement</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>This agreement, dated as for convenience June 30, 1935, by and
                                    between</p>
                                <p>The Government of the Republic of Liberia, of the first part
                                    (hereinafter called the Government);</p>
                                <p>Bank of Monrovia, a corporation organized under the laws of the
                                    State of..........., United States of America, of the second
                                    part (hereinafter called the Depositary); and</p>
                                <p>............., a banking corporation (or a trust company)
                                    organized under the laws of............., of the third part,
                                    (hereinafter called the Bank)</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">witnesseth</hi>: <list>
                                        <label>1.</label>
                                        <item>By an instrument dated as of........, 1935, (a copy of
                                            which, marked Annex A, is hereunto appended and made a
                                            part hereof) the Government, with the approval of
                                            National City Bank, an American Banking Corporation, has
                                            designated Bank of Monrovia as its depositary upon the
                                            terms and conditions therein set forth.</item>
                                        <pb facs="1041" n="939" xml:id="pg_939"/>
                                        <label>2.</label>
                                        <item>In compliance with and for the purposes of the
                                            requirements of Article . . of the said Agreement (Annex
                                            A) the Depositary has placed in the hands of
                                            the............., in escrow, bonds, with interest
                                            coupons attached, of the Government of Liberia issued
                                            pursuant to the Loan Agreement of 1926, or the par value
                                            of Three Hundred Thousand ($300,000.00) dollars, the
                                            numbers of which and other identifying particulars are
                                            specified in the schedule hereunto appended, marked
                                            Annex B, and made a part hereof.</item>
                                        <label>3.</label>
                                        <item>If the Depositary shall fully account to the
                                            Government for all funds placed in its keeping as
                                            depositary and shall make all payments due from it as
                                            such, then three months after the termination of the
                                            said Depositary Agreement by expiration of the agreed
                                            term or previous cancellation in accordance with its
                                            provisions the Bank shall release and surrender unto the
                                            Depositary the bonds described in said Annex B; but if
                                            prior to the expiration of such term of three months the
                                            Government shall notify the Bank that it has a claim
                                            upon the said bonds by reason of any breach of the said
                                            Depositary Agreement asserted by it to have been
                                            committed by the Depositary, then the Bank shall retain
                                            in its possession the said bonds until such claim has
                                            been adjusted or abandoned as hereinafter
                                            provided.</item>
                                        <label>4.</label>
                                        <item>Within . . days from the date of the notification of
                                            such claim, if the same is contested by the Depositary,
                                            the Government shall commence proceedings for the
                                            arbitration of its demand in the manner provided in the
                                            Loan Agreement of 1926 for the arbitration of disputes
                                            between the parties thereto, which said arbitration
                                            provisions are hereby adopted by the parties to this
                                            agreement as fully as though incorporated herein. Should
                                            the Government fail to institute arbitration proceedings
                                            within the time hereinabove specified its claim or
                                            claims against the Depositary shall be deemed to have
                                            been abandoned, extinguished and waived, and the Bank
                                            may surrender the said bonds to the Depositary as though
                                            no such claim or claims had ever been formulated. If
                                            such claim or claims are submitted to arbitration within
                                            the time limited hereby, the Bank shall retain the bonds
                                            in its possession until the final award has been made or
                                            the demand for arbitration withdrawn. If a final award
                                            is made in favor of the Government upon one or more of
                                            its demands against the Depositary the Bank shall
                                            deliver to the Government forthwith bonds of a par value
                                            equal to the amount of the award. The remaining bonds,
                                            if any, shall thereupon be surrendered by the Bank to
                                            the Depositary.</item>
                                        <label>5.</label>
                                        <item>All interest coupons of the said bonds which mature
                                            while the same are being held in escrow by the Bank and
                                            before notification by the Government of a claim or
                                            claims hereunder, shall be detached and delivered by the
                                            Bank to the Depositary.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <pb facs="1042" n="940" xml:id="pg_940"/>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">In Witness Whereof</hi> the parties hereto
                                    have caused this agreement to be executed as of the date first
                                    above written.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Government of the Republic of
                                        Liberia</hi>,<lb/>By ____________ <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Secretary of the Treasury</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Bank of Monrovia</hi>,<lb/>By
                                    ____________<lb/>By ____________<lb/>Approved and
                                    Accepted:<lb/>______________ <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">President of the Republic of Liberia</hi>
                                    <lb/> _____________</closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>