<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-03-16T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-03-16T15:00:00-05:00" n="838" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d838">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">681.003/159: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Ambassador in Frame</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Straus</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-03-16T15:00:00-05:00">March
                                        16, 1935—3 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>92. Your despatch 1645, February 19, and your telegram 171, March 1,
                                1 p.m. Department has given careful consideration to the
                                observations of the French representatives as outlined therein and
                                can see no valid reason for changing its decision as set forth in
                                Department’s 61, February 19, 7 p.m.</p>
                            <p>In connection with the indications you reported that whether or not
                                we assent to the proposals, the French Government is determined to
                                put the reforms into effect, we feel that we should reiterate our
                                position as stated in second paragraph of Department’s 47, February
                                9, 3 p.m., as follows: This Government strongly believes that it is
                                obligatory that the parties to the Act of Algéciras should not only
                                be consulted but that each Power should acquiesce before any changes
                                are made in the customs regime in Morocco.</p>
                            <p>In order that there may be no misunderstanding, since the discussions
                                in Paris have been informal, we feel that the time has come to lodge
                                with the Ministry for Foreign Affairs this Government’s formal
                                protest against the establishment of the proposed system on the
                                following grounds: (1) The system involving quotas would prove to be
                                discriminatory and, therefore, definitely out of harmony with the
                                principle of commercial equality as guaranteed in the Act of
                                Algéciras <pb facs="1076" n="974" xml:id="pg_974"/> and by the
                                French in various treaties and declarations which constitute the
                                foundation of the French Administration of Morocco. (2) The
                                establishment of such a system would be particularly unfortunate at
                                this time when efforts are being made to increase world trade by the
                                removal of trade barriers. (3) From the point of view of this
                                Government the essence of the Moroccan question is the maintenance
                                of the “Open Door” which would preclude our assenting to any
                                proposals inconsistent therewith.</p>
                            <p>For your information despite Coursier’s assertion that we are “the
                                only country adopting other than a utilitarian view of the matter”
                                we understand that the Netherlands<note n="56" xml:id="d838fn56">See
                                    memorandum of November 9. 1934, by the Chief of the Division of
                                    Western European Affairs, <ref target="frus1934v02#pg_855">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1934, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 855</ref>.</note> and
                                    Belgium<note n="57" xml:id="d838fn57">See memorandum of January
                                    24, 1935, by the Chief of the Division of Western European
                                    Affairs, <ref target="#pg_961">p. 961</ref>.</note> are opposed
                                and that Spain<note n="58" xml:id="d838fn58">See telegram No. 15,
                                    February 21, 6 p.m., to the Ambassador in Spain, <ref target="#pg_1012">p. 1012</ref>.</note> is reluctant to
                                accept.</p>
                            <p>If you should deem it inadvisable to lodge this formal protest at
                                this time, please telegraph statement of your reasons therefor.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>