<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Diplomatic Agent and Consul General at Tangier ( (Blake) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d868</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">868</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-01-23T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-01-23T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-01-23T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-01-23T09:00:00-05:00" n="868"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d868">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">681.003/135: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Diplomatic Agent and Consul General at Tangier</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Blake</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tangier</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-01-23T14:00:00+00:00"
                            >January 23, 1935—2 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received January 23—12:50 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1. Your cable number 1, January 19, 2 p.m. Recent conversations with Spanish
                    Foreign Office started from position reached in Spanish note of January 22,
                        1930<note n="13" xml:id="d868fn13">
                        <ref target="frus1930v03#pg_608">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1930, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 608</ref>.</note> referred to in
                    Department’s number 75, August 6, 1930 to Madrid Embassy.<note n="14"
                        xml:id="d868fn14">
                        <ref target="frus1930v03#pg_617">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p. 617</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1108" n="1006" xml:id="pg_1006"/>
                <p>This note agreed to execute Blake-Jordana agreement<note n="15" xml:id="d868fn15"
                        >May 13, 1929; see despatch No. 392, May 17, 1929, from the Diplomatic agent
                        and Consul General at Tangier, <ref target="frus1929v03#pg_493">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1929, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 493</ref>.</note> but subjected
                    payment of certain claims to relinquishment of capitulations and required
                    Kittany claim to be deferred to decision of local Spanish courts before becoming
                    subject to diplomatic discussion.</p>
                <p>Political recognition of Spanish Zone and establishment of normal official
                    contact with Spanish authorities would greatly facilitate straightening out
                    entire position and application of my tentative formula while assuring this
                    would not involve concessions on any essential principles or the surrender of
                    equitable rights embodied in any claims.</p>
                <p>My proposal is to accord recognition of Spanish Protectorate after payment of
                    claims agreed to in Spanish note above referred to and subject to an agreement
                    by Spanish Government to confide adjustment of Kittany claim to myself and
                    Spanish High Commissioner.</p>
                <p>Have my position Kittany claim unaltered. However, I saw in the Embassy files
                    Madrid an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                    <note n="16" xml:id="d868fn16">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aide-mémoire</hi> of January 20, 1931; for text, see <ref
                            target="frus1931v02#pg_751">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 1931, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>,
                            p. 751</ref>.</note> left by Laughlin<note n="17" xml:id="d868fn17"
                        >Irwin B. Laugblin, Ambassador to Spain, 1929–33.</note> with the Spanish
                    Foreign Office agreeing to submit Kittany claim to a court whose competency
                    American Government could legally admit. Since the Spanish insist upon their own
                    courts this proposition leads to an impasse or in reality imposes an
                    administrative or diplomatic adjustment of the claim. My object is to secure
                    settlement of the claim in agreement with Spanish High Commissioner failing
                    which agreement with him for its arbitration.</p>
                <p>After recognition on above conditions discussion concerning assent to legislation
                    and taxation in Spanish Zone would be pursued with Spanish High Commissioner
                    under same procedure and safeguards as followed by this Legation with the French
                    Protectorate and in all cases where American traders are found to have suffered
                    material prejudice to their business by the levy on them of unauthorized
                    taxation since the joint report, the refund thereof would be insisted upon,
                    insistence would obviously be made upon elimination of discriminatory features
                    of legislation and the position of the American Government fully reserved in
                    connection with subsequent recurrence of illegal levies.</p>
                <p>Fully appreciate importance Department’s observations number (5) but am frankly
                    unable to perceive in my proposal any compromise or commitments legal or moral
                    prejudicial to our present treaty position or departing from policy we followed
                    with the French Zone. Commercial guarantees we may legitimately exact in the
                    Spanish Zone to substantiate our present treaties would probably make
                    possibility <pb facs="1109" n="1007" xml:id="pg_1007"/> of any agreement
                    regarding the surrender of the capitulations a very remote contingency and in no
                    case would subject be given consideration before the same subject had been
                    resolved with respect to the French Zone.</p>
                <p>Numbers (4) and (5) are to be utilized only according to the exigencies of the
                    negotiations.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Blake</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
