<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-04-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="122" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d122">
                        <head>122. Letter from <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName> to
                                <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName>, April 6<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d122fn1">Military production facilities.
                                Secret. 2 pp. <gloss target="#t_CIA_2">CIA</gloss> Files, Job
                                80B01285A, ER Files, <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss> Chron,
                                1/1/62–12/31/62.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1962-04-06">April 6, 1962</date>
                            </dateline>
                            <pb facs="d122-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d122-1"/>
                            <salute>Dear Bill:</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>In connection with matters at this morning’s meeting, I hope that you are
                            giving very careful consideration to the question of our position
                            vis-à-vis the Soviets under a disarmament program with neither side
                            restricted in the maintenance of facilities for the fabrication and
                            assembly of military equipment. By maintaining factories intact, either
                            idle or at a very low level of production, arrangements could be planned
                            in a controlled society to bring the plants up to maximum production in
                            a minimum time. I can readily envisage such a plan involving substantial
                            inventories of fabricated and assembled components and a periodic
                            training of personnel. This to me represents serious dimensions of the
                            problem.</p>
                        <p>I observed this as a distinct possibility when I was in Russia two years
                            ago and, in fact, discussed it with Professor Emelyanov and others. From
                            them I gained the impression that under their system of central
                            government control of both factories and workers, it would be quite
                            possible for them to get the production lines going on an all-out basis
                            in a very minimum time. In fact, they were unable to answer my question
                            as to how we could protect ourselves against just such contingent
                            planning on their part.</p>
                        <p>By contrast, our society does not seem to have the capability of doing
                            these things. As you will recall when we were required to start up
                            reserve plants after the outbreak of the Korean War, it proved to be
                            both a laborious and time-consuming undertaking. I was disappointed in
                            those days to find idle aircraft, engine, tank, and armament <pb facs="0475" n="324" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_324"/> plants, which
                            had been maintained for years to provide instant mobilization potential,
                            not usable until large amounts of money had been spent and a great deal
                            of time consumed in re-equipping, modifying, etc.</p>
                        <pb facs="d122-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d122-2"/>
                        <p>One might argue that this need not happen in our society but it does and
                            you must find some way in your negotiations to safeguard us against such
                            a disadvantageous position. This is a problem not dissimilar from the
                            problem of safeguarding against secret preparation for further nuclear
                            testing.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_MJA_1"><persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">John A.
                                    McCone</persName>
                            </signed><affiliation>Director</affiliation>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>