<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>138. Letter from President Kennedy to to Macmillan, July 27, July 27</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v07-09mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d138</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">138</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-07-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-07-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reclbsHvbXLer8sMP" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">On-site inspections</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Yy9hoP1ve9DPX" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124537"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Atmospheric</term>
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="ozone-layer" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124537" lcsh-match="exact">Atmospheric</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-07-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-07-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="138"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d138">
                <head>138. Letter from President <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1">Kennedy</persName> to
                        <persName corresp="#p_MH_1">Macmillan</persName>, July 27<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d138fn1">Possible modification in proposals on test
                        ban. Top Secret. 4 pp. Department of State, Presidential Correspondence: Lot
                        66 D 204, <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1">Kennedy</persName>–<persName
                            corresp="#p_MH_1">Macmillan</persName>, 1962, Vol. III.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-07-27">July 27, 1962</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d138-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d138-1"/>
                <p>Dear Mr. Prime Minister:</p>
                <p>I am asking <persName corresp="p_OGWD_1">David Ormsby-Gore</persName> to send you
                    this message over the week end so that you can know just where we stand in our
                    discussion in the relation between our new technical data and the test ban
                    effort.</p>
                <p>I think your technical people and ours are agreed that the new data have two
                    principal technical meanings. First, they substantially reduce the number of
                    unidentified events with which the system will have to cope. Second, it appears
                    that our ability to detect shocks at a distance has been substantially improved.
                    These developments, in combination, may permit a number of modifications in our
                    proposals. The one thing which they clearly do not justify is a complete
                    abandonment of on-site inspections.</p>
                <p>The data now available, while encouraging, have not been examined in sufficient
                    detail, and their relation to various kind of risks have not been sufficiently
                    analyzed for us to be ready yet to say just how many on-site inspections would
                    now be necessary. The number is clearly going to be lower than it has been in
                    the past, but I could not today defend a particular figure against neutrals on
                    the one hand, and critics of all test ban proposals on the other. Thus we have
                    it in mind not to propose a new fixed number of on-site inspections at this
                    time. We think it better to emphasize that the adamant Soviet opposition to all
                    on-site inspection is the real stumbling block. We would indicate that if the
                    Soviet Government will change <pb facs="d138-2" n="2" type="facsimile"
                        xml:id="d138-2"/> its position on this point, we would be glad to enter the
                    most serious discussion of the appropriate number of inspections.</p>
                <p>With respect to control stations, my thinking is that it should be possible now
                    to adopt a system of some twenty-five stations, worldwide, of which five would
                    be in the Soviet Union. These systems would be internationally monitored and
                    coordinated, but nationally manned and controlled. Subject to some further
                    technical analysis in the next few days, we are hopeful that such a system would
                    give us adequate protections, in the light of the balance of risks involved in
                    this whole great subject. This matter of balance of risks, indeed, is what I
                    find more and more on my mind. As we have often said to each other, we have to
                    consider the consequences of not having a test ban as well as the risks of
                    having one.</p>
                <pb facs="0522" n="371" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_371"/>
                <p>At the same time that we indicate the possibility of modifications in the
                    comprehensive treaty, we are considering the possibility of a strong appeal for
                    an atmospheric test ban, to include underwater and space tests as well. We think
                    there may be real appeal in urging that possibility as well as the possibility
                    of a properly controlled and inspected comprehensive treaty. In terms of world
                    opinion, atmospheric fall-out may be more important than the arms race itself.
                    On the other hand, in terms of the great problem of nuclear proliferation, a
                    comprehensive treaty still seems better to me. Thus my tentative opinion is that
                    we may wish to press both proposals at once.</p>
                <pb facs="d138-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d138-3"/>
                <p>At the same time, in order to emphasize and win support for our purpose of
                    non-proliferation, we would consider pressing for a worldwide agreement which
                    would ban the transfer or acquisition of nuclear weapons or nuclear technology
                    to individual nations not now in the act.</p>
                <p>We are still considering the problem of timing which is presented by the Soviet
                    announcement of a new test series. (There is another related problem in the fact
                    that the completion of our own high-altitude tests has been delayed for an
                    indeterminate number of weeks by the failure of yesterday.) We do not think we
                    should foreclose the possibility of supplementary tests, in case the Soviet
                    series should produce extraordinary surprises. On the other hand, we wish to
                    make clear that this series does not in and of itself lessen our interest in
                    seeking agreement. Probably we shall need to have some reservation in our
                    position to cover this difficulty.</p>
                <p>One further point has become clear to us in these studies. If we get a test ban
                    agreement at all, either comprehensive or atmospheric, we shall still be faced
                    with the possibility of a sudden surprise by Soviet breach of the treaty.
                    Inspection of preparations no longer seems a very hopeful prospect, and the
                    logical alternative is to maintain our own test readiness. Indeed, Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> has suggested this
                    possibility to some of our people. In this context we would wish to consider
                    with you the possibility of maintaining Christmas Island, on a purely stand-by
                    basis, as a part of our proper posture under a safeguarded test ban. I should be
                    glad to have your personal view as to whether this possibility is worth
                    exploring.</p>
                <pb facs="d138-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d138-4"/>
                <p>I have asked <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Arthur Dean</persName> to come back here
                    at once, so that I can review these matters with him before reaching firm
                    conclusions of my own. Meanwhile I hope very much to have your own comments on
                    this general line of thinking. May I add in ending that I have written most
                    frankly and that in this period before a final decision, I am very eager not to
                    have these elements of our thought move outside the closest circle. May I
                    therefore ask that if you wish to consider any of <pb facs="0523" n="372"
                        type="typeset" xml:id="pg_372"/> these matters with your advisers, you avoid
                    indicating just what my own current thinking is.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_KJF_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1">John F. Kennedy</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
