<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-11-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="152" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d152">
                        <head>152. Memorandum of Conversation, November 30, between <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName> and Mikoyan<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d152fn1">Discussion of Latin America atom-free
                                zone. Secret. 3 pp. Department of State, Secretary’s Memoranda of
                                Conversation: Lot 65 D 330.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline>
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1962-11-30">November 30, 1962</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <pb facs="d152-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d152-1"/>
                        <list type="to">
                            <head><gloss target="#t_LA_1">LA</gloss> Atom Free Zone</head>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">The United States</hi></head>
                                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                                    <item>The Under Secretary</item>
                                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE_1">Thompson</persName></item>
                                    <item>Mr. Davis, <gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss></item>
                                    <item>Mr. Kamman, Interpreter</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Soviet Union</hi></head>
                                    <item>First Deputy Premier A. Mikoyan</item>
                                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName></item>
                                    <item>Mr. Kornienko, Counselor, Sov. Emb</item>
                                    <item>Mr. Chistov</item>
                                    <item>Mr. Vinogradov, Interpreter</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>At a working luncheon for Soviet First Deputy Premier, Anastas Mikoyan,
                            the Secretary turned the conversation, about dessert time, to a serious
                            discussion of problems by remarking that the President thought some
                            progress had been made in yesterday’s conversation at the White House.
                            Mr. Mikoyan responded he was very gratified if the President believed
                            some progress had been made. He was under the same impression. He had
                            been on the point of asking the President at the end of the discussion
                            whether they had made any progress but decided not to do so. He,
                            himself, however, felt we had achieved some progress and was glad that
                            the Secretary had mentioned it.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said we were seriously interested in the proposal for an
                            atom free Latin America. In the long run this might provide mutual
                            assurance which would give a feeling of security to these countries. In
                            addition, we were interested in the words of Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> who had spoken of measures
                            against surprise attack, such as observers in key seaports, airports and
                            rail centers. It was not clear to us whether Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> looked on these measures as
                            part of a complete package in the disarmament field or whether they were
                                <pb facs="d152-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d152-2"/> measures
                            valuable in themselves which should be taken up immediately without
                            waiting agreement on general and complete disarmament.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Mikoyan said he would not dwell on the history of disarmament
                            negotiations. He thought disarmament was an important issue on which we
                            should reach agreement. The arms race laid a very heavy burden on the
                            Soviet Union and on the United States. For many years we have been
                            conferring together. The Soviet Union had shown maximum flexibility, but
                            they did not know where the United States and Western countries were
                            moving. Though he did not wish to dwell on <pb facs="0550" n="399" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_399"/> history, he wanted to mention
                            missiles. First, the Soviet Union had agreed to destroy all missiles in
                            the first stage of disarmament, but since the United States had certain
                            apprehensions, it had made the Soviet position more flexible. Chairman
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> then said a
                            certain number of missiles could be retained during the first stage.
                            However, up to now no counter-proposals had been made by the United
                            States.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Mikoyan then referred to the Secretary’s statement about United
                            States interest in an atom free Latin America. He commented that the
                            Brazilian proposal had been a good one in its first draft. But now it
                            appeared that while the Latin American countries could not have atomic
                            weapons on their territories, the United States could have on its bases
                            in those countries. The Soviet Union could not support such a proposal,
                            which is based on “what is bad for you is good for me”. If, however, the
                            proposal concerned all Latin American countries—in other words, if the
                            United States would not have nuclear weapons in those countries—perhaps
                            the Soviet Union could support the Brazilian resolution. He had the
                            impression that Cuba would also favor it if the United States made
                            clear, for instance, that no atom bombs would be in the Panama Canal
                            Zone, and perhaps elsewhere. This would solve the problem of Cuba not
                            having <pb facs="d152-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d152-3"/> atomic
                            weapons if other Latin Americans also did not. Mr. Mikoyan concluded he
                            would like to touch on other things.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary responded he would like to come back to the Latin American
                            atom free zone proposal. The Secretary commented that perhaps there was
                            some misunderstanding and that our positions were not too far apart. If
                            such an arrangement could be made, we would not expect to have nuclear
                            weapons in Guantanamo, in the Panama Canal Zone or our base in Trinidad.
                            However, this could not apply to Puerto Rico because it was part of the
                            United States and we were not talking about an atom free United States.
                            We would suppose that such an arrangement would ban atomic weapons from
                            all existing and possible future bases, though he had nothing concrete
                            in mind in speaking of future bases. Furthermore, we would expect that
                            the Panama Canal Zone and Guantanamo would be subject to exactly the
                            same kind of inspection as the rest of Latin American countries. The
                            Secretary said, however, he would like to make one point quite clear.
                            The prohibition against nuclear weapons would not apply to transit
                            through the Panama Canal. For instance, we could not accept a
                            prohibition on shipment through the Panama Canal of atomic weapons from
                            the East Coast to our West Coast. The Secretary observed that when the
                            Cubans responded to the <gloss target="#t_LA_1">LA</gloss> atom free
                            zone proposal, they had introduced elements which had nothing to do with
                            an atom free zone. The Secretary concluded by saying he thought we
                            needed to discuss this matter further; our two positions were not so far
                            apart.</p>
                        <pb facs="0551" n="400" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_400"/>
                        <p>Mr. Mikoyan disclaimed knowledge of the details but expressed the opinion
                            that basically the Cubans were in favor of this proposal. He said that
                            he would report the Secretary’s observations to Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName>, after which the Soviet
                            Union would make a report.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>