<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-02-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-02-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="169" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d169">
                        <head>169. <gloss target="#t_Todis_1">Todis</gloss> 806 to Geneva, February
                                18<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d169fn1">Negotiating
                                instructions on substance of a test ban treaty. Confidential. 6 pp.
                                Department of State, Central Files, DEF 18–3 SWITZ
                            (GE).</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline>
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1963-02-18">February 18, 1963</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <pb facs="d169-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d169-1"/>
                        <p>Following instructions cleared as result of meeting of interested
                            principals with President February 18.</p>
                        <p>You should indicate to <persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName>
                            in private meeting that US has several specific points to make on
                            substance of a test ban treaty.</p>
                        <p>1. US proposes that on-site inspections be carried out within an agreed
                            upon time sequence and under an agreed procedure with inspections in
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> of seismic events designated
                            by US and <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>, with US-<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> selection of events, and conducted by 70
                            percent US/<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> nationals and 30 percent
                            nationals from non-<gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> and non-Warsaw
                            Pact nations with provision for an equal number of <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> observers. (<gloss target="#t_FYI_1">FYI</gloss>: Present thinking is that the Inspection Team should
                            include fourteen US-<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> technical experts
                            plus the number needed for support and drilling operations, if the
                            latter are <pb facs="d169-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d169-2"/>
                            required. The drilling operations will require an additional number of
                            people depending upon the area, <pb facs="0607" n="456" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_456"/> etc. END <gloss target="#t_FYI_1">FYI</gloss>.)
                            Chief of team would be US or <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                            national. In designating seismic events for inspection in <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, the US–<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> would submit seismic data from four seismic stations to
                            establish location of event, which it may want to inspect together with
                            a statement that it could not identify the event as natural in origin
                            under criteria contained in para 3 of Article VIII of August 27, 1962
                            comprehensive treaty draft. <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> would
                            be responsible for supplying all heavy transportation equipment, e.g.,
                            helicopters, trucks, for inspection in <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. Reverse procedures would apply for inspections in US
                            or <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>2. Review of scientific problems in determination of locating epicenter
                            indicates area can be reduced to an area of 500 square kilometers
                            specified as an elipse with a semi-major axis of a maximum of 15
                            kilometers.</p>
                        <p>3. In <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> the US would supply sealed
                            recorders and certain sealed instruments for the automatic recording
                            stations which would be built according to specifications agreed to by
                            US, <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and for which <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                            would have certain responsibilities for maintenance. Sealed recorder
                            would be picked up and checked by non-Soviet personnel maximum of eight
                            times a year. Data from these stations would also be recorded outside
                            the station by a recording device identical to the one within and this
                            data obtained outside would be picked up and transmitted regularly,
                            e.g., once a week by Soviet personnel to International Commission for
                            use there and for transmission to other side. Reverse situation pertains
                            for such stations in US. US proposes seven such stations be located in
                            US and <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>4. US, after further study of question of on-site inspection <pb facs="d169-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d169-3"/> quota,
                            believes that if the procedures for on-site inspection, along the lines
                            indicated, are acceptable to Soviet Union and can be agreed on in more
                            detail the US would accept a quota of seven on-site inspections annually
                            on the territories of the US and the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>5. US in making these proposals hopes they will be acceptable to Soviet
                            Union and negotiations for drafting treaty can proceed without
                            delay.</p>
                        <p>We have notified foregoing to British Embassy to inform <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> FONOFF. Subject to FONOFF approval,
                            these proposals can be notified to <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> at your meeting on Tuesday, 10 am as joint US/<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> views, such approval to be notified to
                            you by your <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> colleague in Geneva. In
                            absence of such notification these proposals should be put forward as US
                            proposals.</p>
                        <p>You should emphasize that the US does not intend to confirm its proposals
                            publicly until there are indications of moving toward an agreement.</p>
                        <p>Following are additional instructions on the conduct of on-site
                            inspections for use as appropriate.</p>
                        <pb facs="0608" n="457" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_457"/>
                        <p>Discussion is in terms of US–<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                            requesting an inspection in Soviet Union; obviously same procedure would
                            apply in reverse case.</p>
                        <p>1. US–<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> would submit seismic data to
                            International Commission <pb facs="d169-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d169-4"/> regarding unidentified seismic event no later than
                            60 days after event had occurred. Data must be sufficient to locate
                            event, i.e., must include clearly measurable arrival times from four
                            stations, and must include a statement from US–<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> that the data do not indicate the event has been
                            identified as natural in origin using criteria specified in treaty.</p>
                        <p>2. Soviet Union would have seven days in which to present any
                            supplementary information regarding event. Any other data not previously
                            available, such as data from automatic recording seismic stations, must
                            also be submitted within seven days; longer time may be permitted by
                            mutual agreement, due to emergency situations.</p>
                        <p>3. US–<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> would decide within seven days
                            from the receipt of the extra data whether to designate the event for an
                            on-site inspection. The designation would include the location and a
                            description of the area to be inspected as well as the manner in which
                            the inspection team planned to arrive at the port of entry.</p>
                        <pb facs="d169-5" n="5" type="facsimile" xml:id="d169-5"/>
                        <p>4. Soviet Union would have five days in which to notify the Commission of
                            its arrangements for receiving the inspection. Soviet transportation
                            would be used to take the team to the site of the inspection team’s
                            headquarters.</p>
                        <p>5. The Soviet Union could exclude from inspection a building located
                            within the area to be inspected, which the Soviet Union explained, in a
                            report, must be excluded on the grounds it was a sensitive defense
                            installation. An abuse of the exclusion provision would be considered a
                            violation of the terms of the treaty.</p>
                        <p>6. The maximum size of the area to be inspected would be 500 square
                            kilometers specified as an elipse with a semi-major axis of a maximum of
                            15 kilometers.</p>
                        <p>7. Composition of surface inspection teams for Soviet Union would be 20
                            persons, including 14 US–<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> nationals as
                            technicians and 6 nationals from non-<gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> and non-Warsaw Pact countries selected by Commission
                            on recommendation of administrative officer. Chief of team would be US
                            or <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> national. Soviet Union would have
                            number of observers equal to total number of inspection team.</p>
                        <p>8. Inspection team would have maximum of six weeks to complete its
                            surface inspection including low level helicopter flights; this could be
                            delayed by mutual agreement. If drilling was considered <pb facs="d169-6" n="6" type="facsimile" xml:id="d169-6"/> necessary,
                            notification of this need would be given within five weeks from start of
                            inspection, would include provision for additional persons, to be agreed
                            upon, and must be completed within a specified time period (<gloss target="#t_FYI_1">FYI</gloss>: Time period under consideration for
                            drilling is 3–6 months. END <pb facs="0609" n="458" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_458"/>
                            <gloss target="#t_FYI_1">FYI</gloss>) from the time of arrival of the
                            drilling equipment; such equipment must arrive by end of sixth week from
                            start of surface inspection.</p>
                        <p>9. Report of inspection team would be made no later than 30 days after
                            team had completed its inspection.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_RD_1"><persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>