<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>178. Memorandum of Conversation, April 12, between Rusk and and
                    Dobrynin</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v07-09mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d178</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">178</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-04-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-04-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBIWbnPJBWQERtR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation">Nuclear non-proliferation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recLA85IoR5zyxTTT" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91006127"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Nuclear power</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recieOBiY284bnHpv" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances">Western alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recuUFhBncrUg6V07" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015466"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bombers</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recXoDJKMCaKGDSrd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="reca29000439682274" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Warsaw Pact</term>
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                    <term ref="recAWJwqRIM3ZNS4f" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-04-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-04-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="178"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d178">
                <head>178. Memorandum of Conversation, April 12, between <persName corresp="#p_RD_1"
                        >Rusk</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d178fn1">Nuclear non-proliferation issues.
                        Secret. An attached copy of the draft non-transfer declaration with an
                        appended minute provides additional information on the declaration.
                        Confidential. 10 pp. Department of State, Secretary’s Memoranda of
                        Conversation: Lot 65 D 330.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1963-04-12">April 12,
                            1963</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d178-01" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d178-01"/>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Nuclear Non-proliferation</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <list>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">US</hi>
                            </head>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE_1">Thompson</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. Hillenbrand</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <list>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Anatoly F. Dobrynin</persName>,
                                Ambassador of <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                            </item>
                            <item>Georgi M. Kornienko, Counselor, Embassy</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>After discussing several aspects of the Berlin question with Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> (covered in separate memorandum of
                    conversation), the Secretary said he would like to turn specifically to the
                    question of nuclear non-proliferation. Here was a point in which a genuine
                    common interest existed between the Soviet Union and the United States and
                    indeed the United Kingdom and France. On purely theoretical grounds no nuclear
                    power could be interested in any other power’s <pb facs="0633" n="482"
                        type="typeset" xml:id="pg_482"/> becoming a nuclear power. On purely
                    practical grounds, looking ahead fifteen to twenty years and seeing the prospect
                    of as many as ten to fifteen countries coming into possession of nuclear
                    weapons, the prospect for peace was not good. An element of unpredictability
                    would be added. We therefore have a common interest in avoiding nuclear
                    proliferation.</p>
                <p>It was against this background, the Secretary continued, that he had talked with
                        <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName> at Geneva and urged that the
                    Soviet Union and the United States concentrate specifically on the question of
                    non-diffusion of nuclear weapons on a national basis, that is concentrate on
                    governments which could develop national capacities on their own. We believe
                    that we should concentrate on this central point and not try to solve all
                    related matters. If agreement were reached on this point, it would make further
                    steps possible in the disarmament field. With reference to the Western Alliance,
                    the Secretary said that he had pointed out to <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> that we did not have in mind the transfer of nuclear
                    weapons directly or indirectly through this Alliance. But he had also pointed
                    out to <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName> that the expression
                    “directly or indirectly through a military alliance” might lead to
                    misunderstanding and would require further discussion. With this in mind we had
                    drafted a <pb facs="d178-02" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d178-02"/>
                    declaration on nuclear non-transfer of two paragraphs and had also appended a
                    clarifying minute to explain what would or would not be covered. Our language is
                    illustrative but serious and does not necessarily cover all of the points we
                    would like to discuss at the time of the declaration. However, there are enough
                    points in the minute to show that our stress is on the extension of national
                    capabilities. We believe this to be not just another piece of paper but an
                    arrangement that would actually prevent the proliferation of weapons on a
                    national basis.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> asked whether the
                    Secretary had discussed the declaration with the French and the British and
                    whether they had agreed to it. The Secretary said we had given them copies but
                    that he was not acting as their agent today. He did want to say, with a full
                    sense of responsibility, that if the Soviets felt that our paper provided a
                    basis of negotiations, the Allies would take this as a very serious step and we
                    could take up the subject with them. We could not commit them today, the
                    Secretary added, but he was encouraged to find out if the Soviets did consider
                    the paper as a basis for negotiations.</p>
                <p>After <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> had carefully read the
                    paper which the Secretary had handed him (text attached), the Secretary observed
                    that some of the discussion in the West over the past few years on nuclear
                    matters, and the increase in consultation among the Western powers on this
                    subject, was due to the change brought about in the nuclear situation when in
                    1956–57 the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> had made clear that it was
                    targeting a considerable number of nuclear weapons on Western Europe to be <pb
                        facs="0634" n="483" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_483"/> delivered either by
                    bombers or by missiles. This brought the question to the forefront in the
                    thinking of Western European governments. The Soviets had stressed the point
                    either to visitors in Moscow or during visits of Soviets leaders to the West,
                    emphasizing that one or more countries would be destroyed. It was only natural
                    for the countries threatened by nuclear weapons to want to know something more
                    about them. Thus the increase in the discussion of nuclear problems in the West
                    was the direct result of the developments which he had mentioned in the nuclear
                    field.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, the Secretary went on, he sincerely asked the Soviet government to
                    believe that we ourselves are opposed to placing nuclear weapons in the hands of
                    national governments and national forces. This is a matter of our interest. We
                    have pursued this policy even though some of our Allies have disagreed with it.
                    There is nothing in the background which cuts across this most elementary policy
                    of the US government. Although the Soviets may have expressed concern from time
                    to time with regard to something <pb facs="d178-03" n="3" type="facsimile"
                        xml:id="d178-03"/> which has not yet come into being, this is US government
                    policy. What he was saying today, the Secretary pointed out, was not our answer
                    to the recent Soviet note on the multilateral force. We would deal with this in
                    due course, but Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName>
                    would not be surprised to hear that we disagree with many points in the Soviet
                    note. The Secretary said he did have one immediate comment. The note mentioned
                    the multinational as well as multilateral force. The former was mainly the
                    British V-bombers and US Polaris submarines. These were the principal elements
                    along with the coordination with other elements which might have related
                    missions. The multinational force does not change the existing situation as far
                    as the spread of weapons is concerned. Our view is that this is also true of the
                    multilateral force. The key point about the latter is that national governments
                    will not be able to employ it on a national basis by their own decision or that
                    of their armed forces. The main objective is to prevent the spread of national
                    nuclear capabilities. We are not interested solely in one, two or three
                    countries but on a world wide basis. After all, countries not allied either with
                    the US or the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> may be planning to acquire
                    nuclear capacities. Hence we think that a four-power agreement along the lines
                    of the declaration would be great progress.</p>
                <p>After some discussion of Berlin at this point (covered in separate memorandum of
                    conversation), <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> commented that
                    the main point about the non-transfer declaration proposed by the US is that to
                    which <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName> had objected previously.
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> said he had also made the
                    same point in an earlier conversation and his government had likewise had done
                    so in a note some months ago as well as in its recent note. This was not purely
                    a matter of propaganda but the way <pb facs="0635" n="484" type="typeset"
                        xml:id="pg_484"/> the Soviet government felt. The US was actually beginning
                    the proliferation of nuclear weapons. Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> had welcomed President <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1"
                        >Kennedy</persName>’s remarks regarding US policy on non-proliferation, but
                    what has been going on since last summer is the actual proliferation of nuclear
                    weapons. Without even speaking of Germany, a country like Italy which has not
                    had nuclear weapons will now have them in the so-called multilateral units. The
                    policy of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is to have no nuclear
                    weapons except in national units of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>.
                    The US has had the same within the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>
                    framework. This the Soviet Union could accept. But when the US speaks of
                    so-called multilateral teams made up of countries who do not now possess nuclear
                    weapons, this is a new and dangerous step. It marks a real difference in
                    quality. In a year or two the situation will further change and then there will
                    be proliferation. <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> repeated that
                    the multilateral force would put the control of nuclear weapons in the hands of
                    other countries which did not have them now. He recalled that before the Paris
                    Agreements <pb facs="d178-04" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d178-04"/> in 1954,
                    the Western countries had claimed that they were going to prohibit the Germans
                    from having all sorts of weapons, even heavy conventional armaments, but in a
                    few years this was pushed aside. The Germans had complained that they were not
                    being given equal treatment. Now they have the biggest army in <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>, and where were the Paris Agreements? Now
                    the first step in satisfying West German nuclear demands was to be the
                    multilateral force. This was only the beginning, the Soviets felt. The US was on
                    a dangerous path on which it could not stop. The Germans would always try to
                    bring about changes. The first step would be to change the rule of unanimity to
                    decision by majority and thus eliminate the US veto. The only solution would be
                    for the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and the US to keep their
                    monopoly. This was the basic position of the Soviet government. The US-proposed
                    declaration, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName>
                    continued, dealt with everything except the multilateral force or the
                    multinational force. He could only note the reservations in the minute, and felt
                    that the US was really proposing nuclear proliferation both quantitatively and
                    qualitatively.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said he would try to distinguish the two things. From the
                    quantitative aspect, the question of disarmament applied to both sides. The
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> had built up a substantial nuclear
                    force requiring a substantial nuclear force on our side. It appeared from a
                    recent <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> speech that important
                    decisions had been made to allocate a considerable amount of new resources to
                    military purposes. The question of quantity should be grappled with in the
                    disarmament context. In this sense, quantitative proliferation needs serious
                    attention.</p>
                <p>On the qualitative side, we were opposed to putting other governments in a
                    position, not merely on paper, to hold and employ nuclear weapons. We have no
                    arrangements in mind towards this end. This <pb facs="0636" n="485"
                        type="typeset" xml:id="pg_485"/> was an important point which the Soviets
                    should remember. <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> commented that
                    this was where the US and the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> differed.
                    The Soviets could not see how a development could be prevented over the years
                    which would lead to real control of nuclear weapons in the hands of the members
                    of the multilateral force. The Secretary said we were sure that this would not
                    happen with respect to the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> countries. But
                    there were also other countries which would move towards possession of nuclear
                    weapons in the next ten years or so unless there were some such agreement as we
                    had proposed. <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> said he was not
                    so sure about the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> countries. Unless, the
                    Secretary continued, we can combine a <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>
                    arrangement with a larger agreement, the question will get out of control.
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> observed that the
                    multilateral force was a process of <pb facs="d178-05" n="5" type="facsimile"
                        xml:id="d178-05"/> proliferation. The Secretary responded that we were quite
                    certain that this was not so as far as <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>
                    was concerned.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> said that when he looked at the
                    post-war history of West Germany, recalling for example statements made by Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAW_1">Dulles</persName> in 1954 and how the Germans
                    now had the strongest army in <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>, he could
                    only wonder where we would be in five years. The Secretary commented that he did
                    not want to go over the whole history of the post-war period, but it was a fact
                    that the West Germans had not begun to arm until after the East Germans had
                    started. The East Germans had been permitted to begin arming one year before the
                    West Germans over the protests of the Western powers. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> injected that he could produce a
                    list. The Secretary observed that if the Soviets maintained twenty divisions in
                    East Germany, we could not maintain that many in the Federal Republic. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> said the Soviets were prepared to
                    withdraw from East Germany anytime the US was prepared to withdraw from the
                    Federal Republic.</p>
                <p>The Secretary stated that we would have no objections if the Soviets were to make
                    arrangements within the Warsaw Pact similar to those we were proposing to make
                    within <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> responded that the Soviets did not want this. The
                    Secretary said he wanted to ask the Soviet government to study the draft
                    declaration against the background of his statement to Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName>. The latter said he would of course
                    refer the text to his government, but he was sure that it would be found
                    unsatisfactory. He inquired as to what we understood by the term “minute” to be
                    attached to the declaration. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE_1"
                        >Thompson</persName> said it was a document intended for purposes of
                    explanation. Referring to the text of the draft non-transfer declaration, the
                    Secretary noted that <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName> had raised
                    the point about using the device of an Alliance to achieve something indirectly.
                    The Secretary recalled that he had told him that it was not our intention to
                    transfer nuclear weapons through a military alliance to national control. But
                    since the expression “indirectly through a military alliance” does not <pb
                        facs="0637" n="486" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_486"/> carry a full
                    explanation on its face we must be clear what it means. It would therefore be
                    important to append a minute to avoid misunderstanding. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> said he could recall what <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName> had said about indirect transfer. He
                    had been against precisely what was going on in connection with the
                    multinational and multilateral force, although what the US proposed to do had
                    not been very clear at the time. The Secretary said the issue was the ability of
                    national governments to use their own national forces to launch nuclear weapons.
                    He recognized that there might be political reasons why the Soviet Union did not
                    want other <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> countries to consider
                    themselves part <pb facs="d178-06" n="6" type="facsimile" xml:id="d178-06"/> of
                    an Alliance which has nuclear weapons at its disposal. However this question of
                    national nuclear capacity was so important that it was worth taking hold of the
                    particular point and stopping that at least. We were prepared to enter into an
                    agreement on this. <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> said there
                    were no specific political reasons for the Soviet position. The <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> was against proliferation in any
                    Alliance.</p>
                <p>The Secretary observed that President <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1"
                        >Kennedy</persName> had already clarified the point that these arrangements
                    would be in no way separated from the responsibility of the United States.
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> injected that the fact was
                    that other countries would possess nuclear weapons. The Secretary responded that
                    no other country would come into their possession. <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> repeated that they would have possession. The US might
                    not be in a position to be fully responsible. The <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                        >USSR</gloss> already felt that the West Germans were exercising a strong
                    influence on US policy, for example in the negotiations on Berlin and German
                    problems. This influence would increase in years to come. One read that the
                    Germans would be paying one-third of the cost of the multilateral force. They
                    would try to acquire a decisive voice. The Secretary said that if he really
                    believed this he would sign the agreement today so that in five or ten years
                    from now the governments would be bound. What the Soviets fear would then not be
                    possible. <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> said that the fact
                    was that through a rather complicated scheme the US was going to give other
                    countries nuclear weapons. Who was proliferating? You or we?</p>
                <p>The Secretary observed that the Soviets should look at the alternative. It was
                    either this arrangement or no arrangement. The security of the Soviet Union and
                    of the US demanded the arrangement. <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> merely repeated that the Germans would be tempted to
                    acquire nuclear weapons. The Secretary pointed out that they would sign
                    paragraph two of the declaration. <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> said that he did not know whether they would sign. The
                    Secretary responded that he thought that they would sign. He thought that a lot
                    of countries should sign, for example the Chinese. <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> commented that the Soviet Union had no multilateral
                    force with the Chinese. The Secretary asked whether the Chinese <pb facs="0638"
                        n="487" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_487"/> would sign. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> said he did not know, but the Soviets
                    were not proposing a multilateral force to them. However the US was inviting the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> to do this. If the US continued, the
                    Soviet Union would have no alternative but to do the same for its friends.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said he wanted to suggest that this subject was one of importance
                    both to the US and the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. It should be
                    discussed seriously <pb facs="d178-07" n="7" type="facsimile" xml:id="d178-07"/>
                    on this kind of basis and not get caught up in public exchanges of notes.
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> observed that the Soviet
                    note dealt with the general subject and contained some of the same ideas that he
                    had expressed, but the Soviets had not published their previous discussions.
                    However, the whole subject was out in the open and was being discussed in the
                    Western press. The Secretary observed that a curious thing about the
                    multilateral force was that those who criticized it in the West were those who
                    wanted national nuclear forces. <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName>
                    said this merely illustrated that those who wanted this would press for more
                    tomorrow. The Secretary noted that the Soviet criticism of the multilateral
                    force was for opposite reasons. The fact was that those who want national
                    nuclear capacities tomorrow should be pinned down by a signed agreement today.
                    The multinational force was not really involved in the issue, the Secretary
                    added, despite the rude comments on it in the Soviet note.</p>
                <p>After a brief discussion of Berlin at this point, the Secretary said he did hope
                    that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> would urge that
                    his government give serious attention to the draft declaration against the
                    background of the Secretary’s statement. We are seriously interested in avoiding
                    proliferation of nuclear weapons into national hands. There is no question about
                    President <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1">Kennedy</persName>’s central purpose on
                    this question.</p>
                <pb facs="d178-08" n="8" type="facsimile" xml:id="d178-08"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                    </note>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">DRAFT NON-TRANSFER DECLARATION</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Desiring to promote international peace and security,</p>
                    <p>Desiring, in particular, to refrain from taking steps which will extend and
                        intensify the arms race,</p>
                    <p>Believing that the creation of nuclear weapons forces by additional states
                        will jeopardize these ends,</p>
                    <p>Recalling that General Assembly Resolution 1665 (XVI) urges all states to
                        cooperate for these purposes,</p>
                    <p>Reaffirming their determination to achieve agreement on general and complete
                        disarmament under effective international control,</p>
                    <pb facs="0639" n="488" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_488"/>
                    <quote>
                        <p>1. The Governments of France, the United Kingdom of Great Britain and
                            Northern Ireland, the United States of America, and the Union of Soviet
                            Socialist Republics solemnly declare that they will not transfer any
                            nuclear weapons directly, or indirectly through a military alliance,
                            into the national control of individual states not now possessing such
                            weapons, and that they will not assist such other states in the
                            manufacture of such weapons;</p>
                        <p>2. The other signatory Governments solemnly declare that they will not
                            manufacture nuclear weapons and that they will refrain from acquiring
                            directly, or indirectly through military alliances, national control of
                            any nuclear weapons, and that they will not seek or receive assistance
                            from other states in the manufacture of any such weapons;</p>
                        <p>3. This declaration, which shall be deposited with the Government of ,
                            shall be open to signature by all Governments. It shall remain in effect
                            indefinitely, subject to the right of any signatory to be relieved of
                            its terms if another signatory fails to observe them or if any other
                            Government takes action which signatories have declared they will not
                            take;</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned, duly authorized, have signed this
                        declaration.</p>
                    <p>DONE AT , this day of , one thousand nine hundred and sixty-.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="d178-09" n="9" type="facsimile" xml:id="d178-09"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                    </note>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">MINUTE FOR POSSIBLE USE IN DISCUSSION WITH DRAFT
                            NON-TRANSFER DECLARATION</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The United States is proposing for consideration a declaration dealing with
                        the non-diffusion of nuclear weapons. The principal operative sentence of
                        this declaration, insofar as the nuclear powers are concerned, reads as
                        follows:</p>
                    <quote>
                        <p>“The Governments of France, the United Kingdom of Great Britain and
                            Northern Ireland, the United States of America, and the Union of Soviet
                            Socialist Republics solemnly declare that they will not transfer any
                            nuclear weapons directly, or indirectly through a military alliance,
                            into the national control of individual states not now possessing such
                            weapons, and that they will not assist such other states in the
                            manufacture of such weapons.”</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p>This language is meant to make more precise the third point in the message
                        from the Foreign Minister of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                        which states that: “There should also be excluded the transfer of nuclear
                        weapons through military alliances to those states which do not possess
                        them, i.e., the transfer of such weapons in an indirect manner, irrespective
                        of whether or not the national armed forces of these states are component
                        parts of the armed forces of any military alliance.”</p>
                    <pb facs="0640" n="489" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_489"/>
                    <p>The US draft declaration applies the following test to actions respecting the
                        disposition of a nuclear weapon in connection with a regional arrangement:
                        Such actions are prohibited if they would give to any state which is a
                        member of the regional arrangement and which does not possess nuclear
                        weapons the ability to make a determination to use these weapons on the
                        basis of its national decision alone. A few illustrations may suffice:</p>
                    <p>1. The declaration proposed by the U.S. would prohibit the U.S. or the Soviet
                        Union from placing nuclear weapons under the control of units of national
                        forces of nations in the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> or Warsaw
                        Pact which do not now possess nuclear weapons even though those units are
                        assigned <pb facs="d178-10" n="10" type="facsimile" xml:id="d178-10"/> to
                        the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> or Warsaw Pact command
                        structure.</p>
                    <p>2. The declaration proposed by the United States would not prevent the United
                        States or the Soviet Union from deploying nuclear weapons in support of the
                        forces of member nations which are assigned to the forces of the <gloss
                            target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> and Warsaw Pact, respectively, even
                        though these members do not themselves have such weapons. The arrangements
                        would be such that the U.S. and <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>,
                        respectively, retain control over the weapons so that they could not be
                        deployed or used solely on the basis of the national decision of any
                        government not now possessing them.</p>
                    <p>3. The declaration proposed by the United States would not prevent the U.S.
                        or the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> from placing nuclear weapons
                        in the custody of units of a multinational defense force within the
                        framework of <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>, or Warsaw Pact defense
                        forces, respectively, if weapons could not be deployed or used on the basis
                        of the national decision of any government not now possessing them.</p>
                    <p>4. The declaration proposed by the U.S. would not prevent the U.S. or the
                        Soviet Union from entering into multinational consultative procedures with
                        respect to the deployment and use of nuclear weapons with countries not now
                        possessing such weapons.</p>
                    <p>5. The declaration proposed by the U.S. assumes adherence to the declaration
                        by all potential nuclear states or authorities. It would not become
                        operative until both the United States and the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                            >USSR</gloss> were satisfied that such adherences had been obtained, and
                        until both had ratified it pursuant to their constitutional processes.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
