<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>189. Message from Macmillan to President to President Kennedy, June 22, June
                    22</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v07-09mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d189</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">189</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-06-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-06-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec5Yy9hoP1ve9DPX" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124537"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Atmospheric</term>
                    <term ref="recNBOveCHYDHbAqL" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044163"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Environment</term>
                    <term ref="rec2qYX3T6ktEaSsg" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85087216"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Moratorium</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-06-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-06-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="189"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d189">
                <head>189. Message from <persName corresp="#p_MH_1">Macmillan</persName> to
                    President <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1">Kennedy</persName>, June 22<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d189fn1">Provides comments on possible Soviet testing,
                        damage control if suspicious events leaked, wisdom of a private message to
                            <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName>, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_HQMH_1">Hailsham</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_HWA_1"
                            >Harriman</persName> mission. Top Secret. 3 p. Kennedy Library, National
                        Security Files, Departments and Agencies Series, <gloss target="#t_ACDA_1"
                            >ACDA</gloss>, Test Ban Correspondence, 3/63–6/63.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-06-22">June 22, 1963</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d189-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d189-1"/>
                <p>Message begins</p>
                <p>Thank you for your message about the further suspicious in the Semipalatinsk
                    area. Our experts will not be able to complete their examination of the evidence
                    till Monday, but we must clearly reckon with the possibility that the Russians
                    may be conducting a series of low-yield atmospheric tests.</p>
                <pb facs="d189-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d189-2"/>
                <p>As you say, our hand may be forced by leaks. I doubt whether the Soviet
                    Government will make a statement. I think it is unlikely that anything will slip
                    out here and I trust you may be able to control what gets out with you, although
                    I know the difficulties. If we fail to control the leaks we may then have to
                    make a statement in advance of the <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1"
                        >Harriman</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_HQMH_1">Hailsham</persName>
                    mission. If so, I regard it as very important that it should be in the nature of
                    a reaction to whatever leak there is, and should keep the temperature down. We
                    might for example say that “signals had been registered consistent with the
                    possibility of low-yield atmospheric tests. This possibility only increased the
                    importance of a test ban agreement and of the <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1"
                        >Harriman</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_HQMH_1">Hailsham</persName>
                    talks.”</p>
                <p>I hope however that we can avoid even such a mild statement so near the Moscow
                    meeting.</p>
                <p>I am also not sure of the wisdom of a special private message to <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName>, in advance of the talks. If, as I
                    sense, he is wavering it might push him in the wrong direction. If, however, we
                    regard the evidence for low-yield atmospheric tests as absolutely certain, I
                    would not object to a message telling <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> that we know of these tests, that we are for the time
                    being keeping our information to ourselves, <pb facs="0669" n="518"
                        type="typeset" xml:id="pg_518"/> and that we regard it as important that,
                    until the talks in Moscow have taken place, neither side should conduct any
                    tests in any environment. If we are to do this, I think that we must be very
                    sure indeed of our grounds.</p>
                <pb facs="d189-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d189-3"/>
                <p>Another possibility, which I am inclined to favour, would be for <persName
                        corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HQMH_1"
                        >Hailsham</persName> to bring up the subject themselves not necessarily at
                    the beginning of their discussions but at a suitable later point. They would of
                    course make it clear that a comprehensive or partial ban would have to cover
                    low-yield atmospheric tests, and, if negotiations looked like resulting in an
                    agreement on the present line, it would be as well for the Russians to know that
                    we have picked up records of events that could be suspected of being small
                    atmospheric explosions. If on the other hand there does not seem any chance of a
                    full-scale agreement, which I would much deplore, and we have to concentrate on
                    a partial arrangement it is just possible that we could try to bargain a limited
                    moratorium on underground tests against a similar moratorium on minor
                    atmospheric tests below a certain threshold. But this needs more thought and
                    discussion before we get into such a complicated field.</p>
                <p>It seems to me that the important thing now is to hold the position until the
                    negotiation begins.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
