<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-07-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-07-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="191" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d191">
                        <head>191. Memorandum of Conversation, July 8, among Meeting of Committee of
                                Principals<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d191fn1">General
                                approach of U.S. policy in disarmament negotiations. Top Secret. 13
                                pp. Kennedy Library, National Security Files, Departments and
                                Agencies Series, <gloss target="#t_ACDA_1">ACDA</gloss>,
                                Disarmament, Committee of Principals, 3/61–11/63.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline>
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1963-07-08">July 8, 1963</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <pb facs="d191-01" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d191-1"/>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>General Approach of US Policy in Disarmament Negotiations, Meeting
                                of Committee of Principals</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Department of State</hi></head>
                                    <item>The Secretary of State, Chairman</item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">W. Averell
                                            Harriman</persName></item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW_1">George
                                        Ball</persName></item>
                                    <item>Mr. Raymond A. Garthoff</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_ACDA_1">ACDA</gloss></hi></head>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">William C.
                                            Foster</persName>, Director</item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Adrian S.
                                            Fisher</persName>, Deputy Director</item>
                                    <item>Dr. George Rathjens, Reporting Officer</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">White House</hi></head>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BM_1">McGeorge Bundy</persName>,
                                        Special Assistant to the President for National Security
                                        Affairs</item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KC_1">Carl Kaysen</persName>,
                                        Deputy Special Assistant to the President for National
                                        Security Affairs</item>
                                    <item>Dr. Jerome <persName corresp="#p_WJB_1">Wiesner</persName>, Special Assistant to the President for
                                        Science and Technology</item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KSM_1">Spurgeon
                                        Keeny</persName>, Office of the Special Assistant to the
                                        President for Science and Technology</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Department of Defense</hi></head>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">Robert S.
                                            McNamara</persName>, Secretary</item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Paul H. Nitze</persName>,
                                        Assistant Secretary of Defense for International Security
                                        Affairs</item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAW_1">Arthur Barber</persName>,
                                        Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for International
                                        Security Affairs (Arms Control)</item>
                                    <item>Captain Elmo R. Zumwalt, USN, Office of the Deputy
                                        Assistant Secretary of Defense for International Security
                                        Affairs (Arms Control)</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Joint Chiefs of Staff</hi></head>
                                    <item>General <persName corresp="#p_TMD_1">Maxwell
                                            Taylor</persName>, <gloss target="#t_USA_1">USA</gloss>,
                                        Chairman</item>
                                    <item>Colonel Philip A. Sykes, Office of the Special Assistant
                                        for Arms Control</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <pb facs="0673" n="522" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_522"/>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Atomic Energy Commission</hi></head>
                                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SGT_1">Glenn T.
                                            Seaborg</persName>, Chairman</item>
                                    <item>Mr. John G. Palfrey, Commissioner</item>
                                    <item>Dr. George M. Kavanagh, Assistant to the General Manager
                                        for Disarmament</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Central Intelligence Agency</hi></head>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">John A.
                                        McCone</persName>, Director</item>
                                    <item>Mr. Louis Marengo, Assistant to the Deputy Director</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss></hi></head>
                                    <item>Mr. Donald M. Wilson, Acting Director</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_NASA_1">NASA</gloss></hi></item>
                                    <item>Mr. John A. Johnson, General Counsel</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> opened the meeting by asking Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName> to summarize the developments
                            leading to the proposals under consideration and the content of the
                            proposals. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName></hi> began by pointing out first that the
                            proposals were in response to <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss>
                            239. He reviewed the history of the Russian position on reductions in
                            strategic delivery vehicles, pointing out that the <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName> proposals of last fall did
                            represent a substantial change and that we had been at every opportunity
                            since attempting to get them to elaborate on the <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName> proposal and that there had
                            been some elaboration in a recent Co-chairmen’s meeting in Geneva.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName></hi>
                            then pointed out that the purpose of today’s meeting was in his opinion
                            not to get an agreement on either of the two proposals under
                            consideration but rather to determine whether there was any virtue in
                            pursuing either one of these further. In addition, he felt it
                            appropriate that an attempt be made to decide what sort of guidance Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName> should have for the
                            Moscow meeting with respect to the <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName> proposals and the question of reductions in
                            strategic delivery vehicles. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName></hi> then outlined the main
                            features of the Separable First-Stage proposal, and followed this with a
                            brief outline of the Gradual Approach.</p>
                        <pb facs="d191-02" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d191-2"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> then asked Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName> if he had studied the
                            proposals and if he had any comments. <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> replied
                            that they had had some consideration in the <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> but he had not had an opportunity personally to study
                            them in great detail. He strongly favored the Gradual Approach. He felt
                            that the proposal for 50 to 75% reductions had several disadvantages.
                            First, it reduced the credibility of the West’s nuclear deterrent and
                            this would especially be the view of our <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> Allies. While he did not share their views regarding
                            the role of strategic forces as a deterrent in all respects, he did
                            agree that these proposals would be undesirable in that there would be a
                            reduction in credibility. Secondly, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName> felt that the proposals would
                            result in a wasting of the West’s superior nuclear power without our
                            getting any substantial compensating reductions in Soviet superior <pb facs="0674" n="523" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_523"/> conventional
                            strength. Thirdly, he felt that the inspection provisions, particularly
                            those for a 50% reduction, were inadequate to give us the protection we
                            require. Fourthly, he saw no advantage as compared with our presently
                            tabled proposal. In particular, he did not see that there would be any
                            reduction in risk of war as a result of the proposals, and suggested
                            that in fact the risk might increase and that the slight reduction in
                            damage that would result from implementing the proposals would not
                            compensate for the increased risk. He reiterated that he leans strongly
                            toward the Gradual Approach, and favored some confidence building
                            measures such as the recently negotiated “hot-line” agreement.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> then queried Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName> on the reliability of our intelligence. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName></hi> expressed concern about relying on
                            intelligence as a substitute for agreed inspection. He was particularly
                            concerned about the 50% reduction proposal. He then reviewed the
                            intelligence techniques that might be relevant in the event of
                            implementation of such proposals, and concluded by pointing out that
                            they were inadequate to provide sufficiently accurate knowledge of
                            retained levels of armaments. He added that we presently know nothing of
                            Soviet missile reload capability and little about missile manufacturing
                            facilities. He pointed out further that existing intelligence techniques
                            may be perishable and that in addition they can be deceived. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName></hi> then pointed out that there were certain to
                            be differences in the Soviet declarations of their forces and in our
                            estimates of them and that the resolution of these differences <pb facs="d191-03" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d191-3"/> would
                            require some compromise of our methods. He added that public and
                            congressional pressure can also lead to an undesirable compromise of
                            methods. Finally, he pointed out that we could certainly not do as well
                            intelligence-wise as we had in Cuba and that we were uneasy about our
                            knowledge of armaments there. In summary, he felt that we must have an
                            acceptable means of verifying retained levels.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> asked if Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName>’s remarks applied specifically to big missiles
                            and <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName></hi> replied in the affirmative. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> then asked if there was any evidence of
                            camouflage by the Soviets. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName></hi> replied there was not,
                            though he cited a conversation with <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> in 1959 wherein <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> claimed that we could not know the numbers of
                            their missiles because they could successfully hide them in canyons. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> then asked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName> if there had been any hints from defectors and
                                <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName></hi> replied in the negative.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> then asked for General <persName corresp="#p_TMD_1">Taylor</persName>’s comments regarding the
                            proposals. <hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_TMD_1">Taylor</persName></hi> stated that he concurred with Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName> and had nothing to
                            add. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName></hi> said he also concurred with Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName>.</p>
                        <pb facs="0675" n="524" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_524"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> then asked for Dr. <persName corresp="#p_WJB_1">Wiesner</persName>’s views. <hi rend="italic">Dr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_WJB_1">Wiesner</persName></hi> said that
                            he saw no reason for abandoning our present treaty and making drastic
                            proposals without evidence of Soviet interests. He suggested, however,
                            that our intelligence capabilities had changed and that he thought it
                            might be possible for us to modify the inspection provisions of our
                            present Treaty Outline. He also pointed out that we now felt that
                            differences of plus or minus 15% in the number of missiles either side
                            might have were not very significant. Regarding the question of
                            verification of remainders, he agreed with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName> in the case of very deep
                            reductions but felt that 30% and possibly 50% reductions might be safe
                            relying only on inspection of factories and of the weapons destroyed.
                            Because of uncertainties regarding the numbers of missiles, he indicated
                            a preference for discussing reductions in terms of absolute numbers
                            rather than percentages. He concluded by remarking that he thought it
                            would be desirable if Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName> could explore with the Russians general
                            disarmament measures in addition to a test ban.</p>
                        <pb facs="d191-04" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d191-4"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> then asked Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SGT_1">Seaborg</persName> for his views. <hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SGT_1">Seaborg</persName></hi> replied that he had
                            nothing to add. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> then asked about the report he had read to
                            the effect that we were considering cutting our fissionable material
                            production program by $1 billion. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> replied that the
                                <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> had been examining their needs
                            for fissionable materials, but that the examination was not completed
                            and the news reports were premature. He believed that we are reaching a
                            point where we can stabilize weapons’ requirements, and that one of the
                            plans they were considering would lead to a cut in the <gloss target="#t_AEC_1">AEC</gloss> production of materials for weapons by
                            a factor of two. He said that he would like to discuss this with Dr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_SGT_1">Seaborg</persName>, who agreed to do
                            so. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> then said that it was likely there
                            would be some kind of reduction, and that he had received a paper from
                            the Chiefs on that subject.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> then suggested the possibility of our
                            continuing discussions with the Russians not on the basis of specific
                            agreements, but rather on a basis of continuing consultation in which
                            each side would report on the steps it was taking relevant to
                            disarmament. He then raised as an example the question of what
                            difference it would make to us if the Soviets were to announce to us
                            that they were taking ten divisions out of East Germany. He also argued
                            that it would be unfortunate if we received no reciprocal response from
                            the Soviets to a reduction in fissionable material production.</p>
                        <p>There followed a discussion of our estimates regarding intelligence on
                            Soviet missiles, in which <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName></hi> concluded by remarking
                            that there was a possibility that a reduction by categories scheme could
                            leave us in a situation in which the Soviets might have enormous
                            destructive power concentrated in a relatively small number of
                            missiles.</p>
                        <pb facs="0676" n="525" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_525"/>
                        <p>Returning to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName>’s
                            remarks regarding a unilateral Soviet decision to reduce their strength
                            in East Germany, <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> suggested that we
                            might respond not by reducing our forces but rather by seeking to take
                            advantage of the Soviet reductions, in this instance by a buildup in
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> strength since with such
                            reductions on the part of the Soviets the possibility of a conventional
                            balance in Europe would seem more plausible to our Allies than under
                            existing conditions.</p>
                        <pb facs="d191-05" n="5" type="facsimile" xml:id="d191-5"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> pointed out that he felt that with such
                            reductions on the part of the Soviets there would be no realistic chance
                            of new buildup in <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName></hi> disagreed with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName> on the question of the
                            relationship of risks and reductions in forces, pointing out that he
                            felt that reductions of the kind proposed would lead to both a reduction
                            in the risk of war and in the destructive consequences if war should
                            occur. He then indicated that he was under the impression that we had
                            been making substantial progress in redressing the conventional
                            imbalance. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> agreed that we had made substantial
                            progress but that we were still clearly behind. He reiterated his
                            objections to the proposals and indicated he felt we would be giving up
                            a substantial part of our superiority in the strategic nuclear
                            capability.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName></hi>
                            then discussed the <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName>
                            proposal as being a possibly serious concession on their part,
                            indicating that a move in that direction might well be appealing to the
                            Soviet Union. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> wondered why the Soviets would not be
                            willing to cut conventional forces. <hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_WJB_1">Wiesner</persName></hi> then pointed out that
                            the proposals under discussion were in response, he thought, to <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> views in which it was indicated that
                            the <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> had a preference for not
                            reducing conventional forces.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName></hi>
                            pointed out that under the proposal calling for 75% reductions in
                            armaments, there would be a considerable ability to check on retained
                            levels by means other than intelligence, but that the 50% proposal was
                            based on the assumption that our intelligence, coupled with inspection
                            of production and quantities destroyed, would be adequate. He indicated
                            that he was puzzled by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName>’s lack of confidence in our intelligence
                            regarding big missile launchers. He pointed out that in building our
                            forces we relied on intelligence—he did not see why we could not rely on
                            intelligence in going the other way. <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> replied
                            that in building forces we did so with a 100% safety factor. He then
                            reviewed Soviet and US positions relating to reductions in strategic and
                            conventional forces pointing out that the present proposals seemed to be
                            a move toward Soviet desires to reduce strategic delivery capability
                            before dealing with conventional armaments, and he could not see why the
                            Soviets should not move from their position <pb facs="0677" n="526" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_526"/> towards our’s on this subject. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName></hi> cited the <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName> proposal of last fall as a move from their
                            previous position and a move towards our’s. He also indicated the
                            Soviets had expressed <pb facs="d191-06" n="6" type="facsimile" xml:id="d191-6"/> preference for reduction by categories. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> then asked the question, “Weren’t the
                            Soviets, in their position, simply asking to retain their advantages?”
                                <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName></hi> agreed that this might be true but also
                            suggested that they may have other motivations in making their
                            proposals.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_WJB_1">Wiesner</persName></hi> pointed out that our present position had
                            inspection provisions in it that appear to be unacceptable to the Soviet
                            Union. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> again raised the question as to why we
                            should be willing to accept the change in strategic balance which the
                            Separable First-Stage would lead to without the conventional balance
                            being affected.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Fisher</persName></hi>
                            then reviewed some of the discussion at the Deputies’ level pointing out
                            that it had appeared that the conventional imbalance was not as great as
                            had previously been thought to be the case and that, accordingly,
                            proposals of the kind under consideration had seemed acceptable. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> and <hi rend="italic">General
                                    <persName corresp="#p_TMD_1">Taylor</persName></hi> dissented,
                            pointing out that they felt there had been no significant change in the
                            estimate of Soviet conventional superiority. <hi rend="italic">Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Fisher</persName></hi> then pointed
                            out that there appeared to have been no satisfaction with the idea of
                            equal percentage cuts in conventional armaments in the light of the
                            superiority on the part of the Soviets in reserve armaments. He
                            indicated that it was not clear by what mechanism the <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> wanted to redress the conventional
                            imbalance. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> said this could be done by applying
                            the same percentage cuts to conventional armaments as would be applied
                            to strategic armaments. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Fisher</persName></hi> indicated that he
                            thought there has been no acceptance of that idea on the part of the
                                <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss>. <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> again
                            raised the question as to why we are considering disturbing the existing
                            balance and indicated that the <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss>
                            would prefer to accept 30% reductions across-the-board and then greater
                            reductions later.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_WJB_1">Wiesner</persName></hi> pointed out that he felt that the <gloss target="#t_ACDA_1">ACDA</gloss> proposals were a response to <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> pressure and that <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Fisher</persName> was explaining how <gloss target="#t_ACDA_1">ACDA</gloss> was trying to respond to what it
                            thought were <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> views. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName></hi>
                            reacted that his position has been that he felt that it was worthwhile
                            to explore various alternatives.</p>
                        <pb facs="d191-07" n="7" type="facsimile" xml:id="d191-7"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Fisher</persName></hi>
                            pointed out that there had been a weakening in the Soviet position, and
                            the question was whether we should disregard this and stick with our
                            present position, or alternatively explore whether our interests could
                            be served by a move in the direction of the <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName> proposal. He reiterated that 30% reductions
                            applied to conventional armaments might have a worse impact on us than
                            on the Soviets because of their superiority in reserve armaments and
                            that limitations on force levels might not be an effective way of
                            dealing with this Soviet superiority.</p>
                        <pb facs="0678" n="527" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_527"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> replied that in that case we must come
                            up with a more precise conventional plan. He reiterated his opposition
                            to the Separable First-Stage proposal, making two arguments. First, the
                            Soviets were ahead in conventional forces, and second, that the Soviets
                            had proposed emphasizing reductions in strategic delivery vehicles and
                            this automatically caused him to question whether it was in our
                            interest. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Fisher</persName></hi> replied that the Separable First-Stage
                            was in part based on the assumption by the staff that the conventional
                            confrontation is not really in such imbalance, particularly as one
                            looked at it, as one should, from a <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>-Warsaw Pact basis rather than on a purely bilateral
                            basis, and that under such circumstances the response to the <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName> proposals and the cuts
                            suggested might be better than none at all.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> pointed out that there seemed to be two major
                            obstacles to any agreement. One was Soviet unwillingness, or perhaps
                            inability, to do anything about areas of confrontation such as Laos, and
                            two, Soviet unwillingness to accept significant inspection procedures.
                            He felt that if the Soviets were really serious about disarmament they
                            should respond affirmatively on these points. He then raised the
                            question regarding the political considerations involved in a transition
                            from Stages I to II, and in particular asked what would be the political
                            prerequisites to collapsing both stages into one. He wondered if it was
                            feasible to do this if the necessary political prerequisites could be
                            made.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName></hi>
                            suggested that the major problem was time required for building up the
                            necessary international institutions. <hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_WJB_1">Wiesner</persName></hi> suggested that it
                            might be more reasonable to consider collapsing Stages II and III into
                            one. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName></hi> said that these had been looked into right
                            after the Cuban crisis.</p>
                        <pb facs="d191-08" n="8" type="facsimile" xml:id="d191-8"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> expressed concern that <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> holds in his hands the
                            possibility of forcing unilateral disarmament by the US, in that such
                            would probably be our response to any concerted relaxation of Communist
                            pressure that might occur in Southeast Asia, Berlin and elsewhere. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> said he was concerned that <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> had <hi rend="italic">not</hi> arranged for any such relaxation, and then pointed out
                            that the Separable First-Stage plan under consideration would allow the
                            Communists to keep up the pressure in Southeast Asia, Berlin and
                            elsewhere and at the same time to maintain superior conventional forces.
                                <hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_TMD_1">Taylor</persName></hi> questioned how the plan would affect the
                            confrontation between the two Alliances, particularly in Europe. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName></hi> pointed out that, with respect to the
                            question of participation, it was felt that a bilateral agreement might
                            be more negotiable, but that the possibility of participation of other
                            states was left open.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Fisher</persName></hi>
                            discussed the threat to Europe by Soviet <gloss target="#t_IRBM_1">IRBM</gloss>’s and the threat to the Soviet Union from <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> forces based in Europe and indicated
                            that the development of the proposal was based on the <pb facs="0679" n="528" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_528"/> assumption that it would be
                            necessary to consider its effect on the total confrontation. <hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_TMD_1">Taylor</persName></hi> raised the question as to whether there
                            would be consultation with our Allies before surfacing any such
                            proposals. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KC_1">Kaysen</persName></hi> pointed out that with respect to the
                            question of building up of our forces that the degree of consultation
                            with our Allies was somewhat obscure. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName></hi> suggested that in his
                            view the Germans and the French might be justified in looking to their
                            own forces for security in the event such a plan were surfaced.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> asked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName> to enumerate the issues on which there was
                            authorization for discussion with the Soviets. <hi rend="italic">Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName></hi> did so
                            calling off the following: B–47/Badger deal; the cut-off of fissionable
                            material production and transfer to peaceful purposes; exchange of
                            military missions; announcement of maneuvers prior to their taking
                            place; controls on expenditures; and a prohibition on the placing of
                            weapons of mass destruction in orbit. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Fisher</persName></hi> added nuclear free
                            zones, and <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName></hi> qualified this indicating in particular
                            the question of a nuclear free zone in Latin America. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName></hi> raised
                            the question of an African free zone.</p>
                        <pb facs="d191-09" n="9" type="facsimile" xml:id="d191-9"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> observed that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName> had a great deal to talk about with the
                            Soviets. He indicated that if pressed by the Soviets on the question of
                            the <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName> proposal Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName> might indicate that
                            the strategic delivery problem was under study but that we should seek
                            to find out how the Soviets proposed to deal with conventional forces.
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> then observed that conceivably we might go
                            to 50% reductions in Stage I. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> agreed with this,
                            but <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName></hi> raised the question of whether 50%
                            reductions across-the-board would be acceptable with China not a party
                            to the agreement. <hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_TMD_1">Taylor</persName></hi> raised the question as to why we could
                            not deal with absolute numbers of armaments to be destroyed rather than
                            with percentages. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC_1">Foster</persName></hi> observed that this had been tried before
                            but unsuccessfully.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_WJB_1">Wiesner</persName></hi> suggested that we should look to see how
                            much inspection would be necessary for reductions of 30 and 50%. He felt
                            the requirements might be quite different from those in our present
                            Treaty Outline. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName></hi> asked him to elaborate. <hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_WJB_1">Wiesner</persName></hi> said that at the 30% level and perhaps even
                            at the 50% level, it might be possible for us to depend on inspection of
                            plants and armaments destroyed only. He also questioned whether we could
                            not change our position with respect to continued production of
                            armaments during the First Stage. He felt that we should modify our
                            presently tabled Treaty Outline to bring it into agreement with our
                            present thinking on these subjects. He felt that in view of the
                            discussion, the old Treaty Outline would be a more desirable basis for
                            analysis and modification than a Separable First-Stage. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName></hi>
                            argued that we should abandon the <pb facs="0680" n="529" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_529"/> present Separable First-Stage, as it currently is
                            not acceptable, but that we should continue to look for a Separable
                            First-Stage that might be acceptable.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> again raised the question of a continuous
                            spectrum of small increments of disarmament as contrasted with a
                            proposal involving large discrete stages. <hi rend="italic">Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KC_1">Kaysen</persName></hi> asked
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName> whether his
                            views would be the same regarding a reduction scheme that might involve,
                            say, 50% cuts in strategic systems coupled with 30% cuts in conventional
                            armaments, as they would be with respect to schemes involving strategic
                            delivery vehicles only. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> replied
                            affirmatively. He <pb facs="d191-10" n="10" type="facsimile" xml:id="d191-10"/> added that he was concerned that we were spending
                            a disproportionate amount of time on proposals that might be of
                            propaganda value and not enough on smaller measures that might prove
                            practicable. He felt that there was too much distrust between the US and
                            the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> at the present time to
                            consider measures involving such drastic cuts as 75% and that we were
                            wasting our time in such considerations. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KC_1">Kaysen</persName></hi> suggested that we
                            should raise the question as to what are the minimum stakes required to
                            get into a serious disarmament game. He observed, if the minimum price
                            involved 75% reductions that perhaps we were not prepared to pay that
                            price at this time. He suggested perhaps it was part of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName>’s job to get a better feeling
                            for what that minimum price might be.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> observed that in the last two years we have
                            added 25% to the <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> budget and
                            wondered whether or not any of the factors that had influenced us in
                            arriving at those increases had changed. <hi rend="italic">General
                                    <persName corresp="#p_TMD_1">Taylor</persName></hi> observed
                            that there had been no change. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> wondered whether the
                            increases in the US defense budget might have led to a greater interest
                            on the part of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> in
                            disarmament. <hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_TMD_1">Taylor</persName></hi> observed that he thought they had; that
                            the increased economic burdens of high defense expenditures would be an
                            added incentive for the Soviets to move towards disarmament.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName></hi>
                            observed that there had been some changes in the last couple of years.
                            In particular, there had been at least a partially favorable resolution
                            of the Cuban problem, some degree of relaxation in the Berlin crisis,
                            and the growing split between the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                            and China, which might make it possible for us to do things now that
                            could not have been done two years ago.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName></hi>
                            expressed concern about the evidence of long term plans on the part of
                            the Soviet Union to go ahead with the build up in military strength. In
                            particular he expressed concern about indications that Soviets were
                            going ahead to increase their fissionable material production capability
                            while we were talking about cutting back on ours. <hi rend="italic">Dr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_WJB_1">Wiesner</persName></hi> expressed
                            the opinion that this was understandable considering our very great
                            superiority.</p>
                        <pb facs="d191-11" n="11" type="facsimile" xml:id="d191-11"/>
                        <pb facs="0681" n="530" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_530"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> asked if a look could be taken at the damage
                            that might be done to the US by 15 to 20 Soviet missiles each with a 50
                                <gloss target="#t_MT_1">MT</gloss> warhead. <hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_TMD_1">Taylor</persName></hi>
                            indicated that this could be done. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName></hi> observed that as a
                            first approximation one might expect two million deaths per weapon.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName></hi> suggested that a draft be made of instructions
                            for Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName> for response to
                            any Soviet query regarding our reaction to the <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName> proposals. He then adjourned
                            the meeting.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>