<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>265. Memorandum from the Secretaries to the Joint Chiefs of Staff, April
                    24</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v07-09mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d265</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">265</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recPnftMNhM1QKAYO" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Stockpile</term>
                    <term ref="recOJxlJVfRvlJiXp" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Nuclear material</term>
                    <term ref="recfkRWjb8Vcm4Gga" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005004553"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Warheads</term>
                    <term ref="recAHt1IiF33Lofk6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028349"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Development program</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="rechWxPReovs7qx7u" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009626"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Urban</term>
                    <term ref="recAwQiQEe2SLmG4S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="recuUFhBncrUg6V07" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015466"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bombers</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113036"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Research and development</term>
                    <term ref="recQTM14yBsvNgBmv" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="outer-space">Space program</term>
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recoJDbAasG9LhuGg" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Force structure</term>
                    <term ref="recMrVNgNJpQ8DjcR" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037301"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deterrence</term>
                    <term ref="recUrq2Zdb1Wo2PdW" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Strategic posture</term>
                    <term ref="rec4magYO3Xg02IU4" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Strategic balance</term>
                    <term ref="recyvYvKBWCiz1E8g" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026326"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil defense</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rec2p8MfOFI4NR3V8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                    <term ref="recqaxqBsfTYVWHfR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034367"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cruise missiles</term>
                    <term ref="reckP3QiieAZd7kwE" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003001255"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Launchers</term>
                    <term ref="recwtK4pWGzcpfduJ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">USCINCEUR</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recRBtAhU7ev0K7uh" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons">Titan
                        missiles</term>
                    <term ref="recBK2rfbOQodUVmw" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >SSBN</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="265"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d265">
                <head>265. Memorandum from the Secretaries to the Joint Chiefs of Staff, April
                        24<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d265fn1">Circulates copy of a memorandum
                        from Gen. <persName corresp="#p_LLL_1">Lemnitzer</persName> to <persName
                            corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName> on “Nuclear Superiority of the US
                        vis-a-vis the Soviet Union” for their information. Top Secret/Restricted
                        Data. 12 pp. National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 218, <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss>
                        Records, JMF 2210.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-04-24">April 24, 1962</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d265-01" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d265-01"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">NUCLEAR SUPERIORITY OF US VIS-À-VIS THE SOVIET UNION</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">Reference: <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss> 1924/127</p>
                <p>The attached memorandum by the Chairman, Joint Chiefs of Staff, <gloss
                        target="#t_CM_1">CM</gloss>–592–62, dated 18 April 1962, subject as above,
                    together with its Attachments (Tabs A and B), is circulated for information.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>F.J. Blouin</signed>
                    <signed>M.J. Ingelido</signed>
                    <affiliation>
                        <hi rend="italic">Joint Secretariat</hi>
                    </affiliation>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="d265-02" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d265-02"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                    </note>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Nuclear Superiority of US Vis-à-Vis the Soviet Union (U)</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>1. In response to your verbal request to me on 6 March to provide you with a
                        memorandum outlining the factors that contribute to nuclear superiority, the
                        following is provided.</p>
                    <p>2. On 5 October 1961, the Joint Chiefs of Staff submitted<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d265fn2">See Enclosure and Appendix to <gloss target="#t_JCS_1"
                                >JCS</gloss> 1924/127.</note> a study to the President, as a result
                        of his request, that compared the nuclear delivery capability of the US
                        vis-à-vis the Soviet Union. At that time, the study concluded that the US
                        enjoys a military superiority over the <pb facs="1097" n="946"
                            type="typeset" xml:id="pg_946"/>
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> in 1961 and this superiority will
                        continue through 1963, but that the Soviets in recognition of this imbalance
                        are striving for weapons systems that will, in the future, provide them with
                        a distinct military advantage.</p>
                    <p>3. This determination was based primarily on the nuclear delivery capability
                        of the US and the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. Since the original
                        study was completed, there have been no significant changes in the nuclear
                        delivery capability of either nation that would alter the conclusions of the
                        Joint Chiefs of Staff for the short term. However, in view of the recently
                        completed series of Soviet nuclear tests, it is highly probable that much
                        useful information was obtained that will advance their confidence and
                        competence in the area of nuclear systems development.</p>
                    <p>4. To compare the US nuclear delivery forces with those of the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is a reasonably easy task, but to make a
                        comprehensive evaluation of the relative posture of the two countries
                        requires consideration of many factors. Some of the factors which contribute
                        to the determination of nuclear capability are:</p>
                    <quote>
                        <p>a. Number of nuclear delivery vehicles.</p>
                        <p>b. Quantity and quality of nuclear weapons.</p>
                        <p>c. Capability, reliability and accuracy of delivery systems.</p>
                        <p>d. Application of technology to military uses.</p>
                        <p>e. Intentions.</p>
                    </quote>
                    <pb facs="d265-03" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d265-03"/>
                    <p>5. Tab A contains a comparison of the combat ready forces available to the US
                        and the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> for the periods 1 January
                        1962 and 1 July 1963. Forces for this comparison include those forces based
                        in the <gloss target="#t_CONUS_1">CONUS</gloss> and those employed overseas
                        which have the capability of striking the Sino-Soviet Bloc. No Allied forces
                        have been included. Soviet forces include those capable of striking the US
                        and US forces overseas. In Tab B are detailed explanations of the forces
                        immediately available to both sides. It will be noted that the US has a
                        considerable advantage in the heavy bomber category and is slightly behind
                        in the medium bomber force both in 1962 and 1963, but in total bomber force,
                        the US is superior in 1962 and will widen this gap further by 1963. In the
                            <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> category, the US superiority is
                        approximately three to one increasing in 1963 to about four to one. The one
                        category in which the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> enjoys a
                        decisive superiority is in the field of <gloss target="#t_MRBM_1"
                            >MRBM</gloss>’s. These do not pose a threat to the US but they are a
                        threat to the Allies in both Europe and Asia. This advantage is partially
                        offset by the US superiority in the fighter bomber category.</p>
                    <p>6. In the area of nuclear weapons, there is a lack of direct intelligence
                        information on Soviet nuclear weapons stockpile which precludes a definitive
                        appraisal of the Soviet capability as compared to that of the US. Although
                        we have estimates of the Soviet nuclear material stockpile, we have only
                        limited information regarding specific characteristics <pb facs="1098"
                            n="947" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_947"/> of Soviet stockpile weapons.
                        Nevertheless, a Soviet nuclear stockpile can be estimated for 1962 and 1963
                        using the assumptions that the weapons in the Soviet stockpile will have
                        roughly the same average material composition as those in the US stockpile.
                        In this respect, numbers of weapons are not the primary consideration, if we
                        assume, and the assumption appears to be valid, that each side has
                        sufficient numbers to provide the proper load or loads for each delivery
                        vehicle. Nevertheless, there is one important factor that must not be
                        overlooked. <pb facs="d265-04" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d265-04"/> The
                        recent Soviet nuclear tests have allowed them to achieve greater economy in
                        fissile materials while at the same time maintaining high thermonuclear
                        efficiencies. This achievement could ultimately permit the Soviets to build
                        warheads in the range of 50 to 100 <gloss target="#t_MT_1">MT</gloss> and
                        therefore, reduce the Soviet strategic requirements or permit the
                        accomplishment of a higher level of destruction of target systems with
                        estimated weapons inventories.</p>
                    <p>7. In comparing the capability, reliability and accuracy of the Soviet
                        missiles, we have relatively firm evidence on the test range and the test
                        firing program from which we have been able to derive basic characteristics.
                        From these data, we can also derive some of the basic factors affecting
                        performance under operational conditions, including ranges, accuracy and
                        reliability. These data can be combined with other evidence to provide a
                        sense of tempo of the <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> development
                        program and the degree of success the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                        has achieved. In general, the capability of the Soviet missiles compares
                        favorably to that of the US missiles in range, reliability and accuracy.
                        Consequently, an evaluation of the superiority of either side in the <gloss
                            target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> area would be dependent primarily on the
                        number of missiles available to each side and the concept of employment of
                        such missiles, i.e., would they be targeted against military targets, urban
                        targets or a mix of each. The same is true of the Soviet bomber force.</p>
                    <p>8. The Soviets are making vigorous efforts to counter Western weapons
                        systems. Within the next five years, they will probably introduce improved
                        radars and all weather interceptors, a surface-to-air missile system
                        designed to counter low altitude air attack and anti-missile defenses. The
                        recent Soviet nuclear tests, in part, were designed to obtain an <gloss
                            target="#t_AICBM_1">AICBM</gloss> capability. However, they probably
                        will still not achieve a high degree of assurance in coping with a
                        large-scale sophisticated attack by manned bombers. Although they would
                        probably expect to destroy a larger number of attacking forces, it is
                        doubtful they will be able to reduce the weight of such an attack.</p>
                    <pb facs="d265-05" n="5" type="facsimile" xml:id="d265-05"/>
                    <p>9. Soviet capabilities in guided missiles and space vehicles rest upon a
                        major national effort in research and development pursued over the past 15
                        years. The Soviets have concentrated on the development of only a few
                        systems at any one time. With the possible exception of <pb facs="1099"
                            n="948" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_948"/> the first surface-to-air
                        system, deployed around Moscow, there has been no indication that Soviet
                        guided missiles were developed on a “crash” basis. The Soviets now have
                        operationally available about 20 individual missile systems for surface,
                        air, and sea employment. Future Soviet efforts will probably place greater
                        emphasis on development of second generation missile systems. The importance
                        which the Soviets attach to the space program is demonstrated by the
                        assignment of leading scientists to its direction, by the wealth of
                        theoretical and applied research being conducted in the support and by the
                        allocation of resources and facilities to its implementation. A significant
                        achievement in this field has been the development of very powerful
                        propulsion systems and it is estimated that the Soviets will be able to
                        place in orbit about 25,000 pounds sometime in 1962. This progress by the
                        Soviets does not constitute a superiority in the area of weapons and space
                        at the present time, but is indicative of Soviet trends and we can be
                        assured that if the Soviets elect to exploit their technical capability
                        toward developing weapons systems that will narrow the gap between the US
                        and <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, they will, in fact, do so.</p>
                    <p>10. Of the factors listed above, probably the most difficult to assess is the
                        intentions of the Soviets. There is no indication that the Soviet national
                        policy precludes an initiative attack. Presumably, the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is aware of US policy which rejects
                        preventive war by the US. They could, therefore, make plans to attack the US
                        without strategic warning. An attack such as this, by a minimum force, would
                        have to be carefully planned and executed to prevent a possible pre-emptive
                        attack if the US were alerted through <pb facs="d265-06" n="6"
                            type="facsimile" xml:id="d265-06"/> intelligence. As the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> moves more and more toward a strategic
                        missile posture, the capability to achieve surprise increases. However, the
                        US forces during the period are simultaneously building toward a less
                        vulnerable posture. Since a basic requirement of an initiative attack is to
                        destroy the enemy’s capability to retaliate, the Soviet strategic force
                        structure will have to increase accordingly if they intend to exercise the
                        initiative. If the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> does not
                        contemplate an initiative strategic attack against the US, the requirement
                        would be reduced since all that would be needed would be the requirement to
                        deter an attack by the US. Since national policy of the US in effect
                        provides this deterrence, the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                        requirement for a deterrent posture could be comparably smaller.</p>
                    <p>11. As opposed to the Soviet requirement for a minimum deterrent force or for
                        an initiative force, the US is faced with the problem of attaining a
                        strategic posture adequate to attack effectively the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> under many circumstances, including a
                        second strike capability with those residual forces remaining after a Soviet
                        initiative attack. Estimates of forces and weapons required to attain this
                        posture vary widely depending on the assumptions as to how a nuclear war
                        will begin. <pb facs="1100" n="949" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_949"/> Answers
                        to these questions are being sought by the entire military establishment on
                        a continuing basis, in order to keep current the estimates of Soviet
                        strengths, weaknesses and future intentions so that a determination of
                        future forces, weapons and strategy to counter Soviet aggression can be
                        made.</p>
                    <p>12. From the preceding, we have been able to determine some of the factors
                        that contribute to the determination of nuclear superiority. In order to
                        define “nuclear superiority”, we must consider other factors, some of which
                        are less tangible than those mentioned previously. These include national
                        strategy and objectives, force application and national will. When these
                        factors are assessed against enemy ideology and philosophy, then we can make
                        a more meaningful determination of just what is meant by the term “nuclear
                        superiority”. <pb facs="d265-07" n="7" type="facsimile" xml:id="d265-07"/>
                        Although “nuclear superiority” is difficult to define in one sentence, one
                        such definition might be as follows: “Nuclear superiority is that degree of
                        nuclear capability possessed by one nation vis-à-vis another that,
                        regardless of the level and intensity of conflict threatened or actually
                        inflicted by the enemy, permits the nation possessing this capability to
                        disarm the enemy’s nuclear forces, conclude the conflict on favorable terms
                        and to prevail as a viable nation”.</p>
                    <p>13. Since World War II, the over-all national strength and purpose of the US,
                        supplemented by that of its Allies, has successfully deterred the Soviet
                        Union from initiating general war. US success in this regard during the past
                        seventeen years resulted primarily from the fact that US forces have had a
                        clear capability, whether [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>]
                        retaliation, to cause unacceptable damage to the Soviet Union and emerge
                        with a superiority in forces and resources which would place the US in a
                        position from which to prevail. While the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                            >USSR</gloss> possesses the capability to damage the Allies and the US
                        severely in general war, it does not possess the capability either in
                        initiative or retaliation, to damage the US sufficiently to permit it to
                        emerge in a position from which to prevail against the US. Analysis, based
                        on the current intelligence estimates of the relative postures of the US and
                        the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> for the current time period and
                        through 1963, indicates that the US will remain stronger than the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. Its total military capability and the
                        economic base supporting its forces give it an over-all military advantage
                        over the Soviets. Comparative analysis of the known and/or estimated nuclear
                        strike capabilities of the US and the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                        >USSR</gloss>, when considered in their entirety, and in relation to their
                        respective capabilities to defend against nuclear strikes makes it doubtful,
                        except through miscalculation or misadventure, that the Soviets will
                        initiate general war either now or through mid-1963.</p>
                    <p>14. In summary, despite a strong Soviet military posture, the relative
                        strategic balance of forces is in favor of the US at the present time. <pb
                            facs="1101" n="950" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_950"/> By 1963, our
                        strategic force levels and our rela<pb facs="d265-08" n="8" type="facsimile"
                            xml:id="d265-08"/>tively secure force levels assure for the US a
                        decisive retaliatory capability. However, the results of the analyses
                        obtained from the recent Soviet tests give grounds for serious concern.
                        There are indications that the Soviets have made substantive progress in
                        nuclear technology well beyond that commonly anticipated and there is reason
                        to believe they will exploit this advancement to the fullest extent.</p>
                    <p>15. Free world security depends on US strategic nuclear capability and it is
                        essential that the US maintain a nuclear superiority over the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> at least equal to that of the present
                        level. As the capability of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                        increases, so must that of the US. In this respect, consideration must be
                        given to all aspects of our national posture including an adequate civil
                        defense program. Any relaxation on the part of the US in the effort to
                        maintain a nuclear superiority could result in a deterioration of capability
                        with time to a point where irreparable damage could be done.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_LLL_1">L.L. Lemnitzer</persName>
                        </signed>
                        <affiliation>Chairman<lb/>Joint Chiefs of Staff</affiliation>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="d265-09" n="9" type="facsimile" xml:id="d265-09"/>
                <pb facs="1102" n="951" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_951"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Tab A</hi>
                    </note>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">FORCES</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="5">
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell cols="2">1962</cell>
                            <cell cols="2">1963</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>US</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>US</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>a. Long Range Aircraft Note 13</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>(1) Heavy Bombers</cell>
                            <cell role="num">529</cell>
                            <cell role="num">1503</cell>
                            <cell role="num">630</cell>
                            <cell role="num">1503</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>(2) Medium Bombers</cell>
                            <cell role="num">779</cell>
                            <cell role="num">9503</cell>
                            <cell role="num">575</cell>
                            <cell role="num">8003</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>TOTAL</cell>
                            <cell role="num">1308</cell>
                            <cell role="num">11003</cell>
                            <cell role="num">1205</cell>
                            <cell role="num">9503</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>b. <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>—Note 23</cell>
                            <cell role="num">62</cell>
                            <cell>10–254</cell>
                            <cell role="num">382</cell>
                            <cell>75–1255</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>c. Submarine Launched Missiles—Note 33</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>(1) Ballistic 1200 <gloss target="#t_NM_1">NM</gloss>
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="num">80</cell>
                            <cell role="num">03</cell>
                            <cell role="num">128</cell>
                            <cell role="num">03</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>(2) Ballistic 500–1000 <gloss target="#t_NM_1">NM</gloss>
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="num">0</cell>
                            <cell role="num">03</cell>
                            <cell role="num">0</cell>
                            <cell role="num">63</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>(3) Ballistic 350 <gloss target="#t_NM_1">NM</gloss>
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="num">0</cell>
                            <cell role="num">903</cell>
                            <cell role="num">0</cell>
                            <cell role="num">1153</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>(4) Cruise</cell>
                            <cell role="num">17</cell>
                            <cell role="num">03</cell>
                            <cell role="num">17</cell>
                            <cell role="num">03</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>TOTAL</cell>
                            <cell role="num">97</cell>
                            <cell role="num">903</cell>
                            <cell role="num">145</cell>
                            <cell role="num">1213</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>d. Other nuclear delivery forces—Note 43</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>(1) Light Bombers</cell>
                            <cell role="num">225</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2503</cell>
                            <cell role="num">160</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2503</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>(2) Fighter Bombers</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2389</cell>
                            <cell>0###3</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2381</cell>
                            <cell>0###3</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>(3) Cruise Missiles</cell>
                            <cell role="num">178</cell>
                            <cell>0####3</cell>
                            <cell role="num">144</cell>
                            <cell>0####3</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>TOTAL</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2792</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2503</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2685</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2503</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>(4) <gloss target="#t_MRBM_1">MRBM</gloss>/<gloss
                                    target="#t_IRBM_1">IRBM</gloss>
                            </cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell cols="2">On Launchers</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>(a) 700 nm</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1100 nm</cell>
                            <cell role="num">0</cell>
                            <cell>250–3003</cell>
                            <cell role="num">0</cell>
                            <cell rows="2">(7–11 &amp; 2500 nm TOTAL)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>(b) 2500 nm</cell>
                            <cell role="num">0</cell>
                            <cell role="num">03</cell>
                            <cell role="num">0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>TOTAL</cell>
                            <cell role="num">0</cell>
                            <cell>250–3003</cell>
                            <cell role="num">0</cell>
                            <cell>350–4503</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>* Notes 1, 2, 3 and 4—See Appendix</p>
                    <p># <gloss target="#t_CSAF_1">CSAF</gloss> believes about 75 is the correct
                        figure as of 1 March 1962.</p>
                    <p>## <gloss target="#t_CSAF_1">CSAF</gloss> believes about 250 is the correct
                        figure.</p>
                    <p>### There is some evidence, not yet conclusive, that the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is showing activity toward acquiring a
                        nuclear delivery capability for tactical fighters. USCINCEUR has expressed a
                        belief, although he has no positive proof, that about one-half of the Soviet
                        fighter-bombers possess a nuclear delivery capability.</p>
                    <p>#### It is estimated that some in class cruise type missile subs are probably
                        operational now (350 nm cruise missile)</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="d265-10" n="10" type="facsimile" xml:id="d265-10"/>
                <pb facs="1103" n="952" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_952"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Tab B</hi>
                    </note>
                    <p rend="center">NOTE 1—LONG RANGE AIRCRAFT</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> Forces</p>
                    <p>a. As of January 1961 the main weight of a large-scale nuclear attack against
                        distant targets would be by bombers of Long Range Aviation. The 160 heavy
                        bombers consist of 110 Bisons and 50 Bears and include aircraft fitted as
                        tankers. These are available to all Bison units and about half the Badger
                        units. These can be converted to bombers in a few hours. Within the next
                        year or so virtually all Bears will carry 350 nm ASMs.</p>
                    <p>b. Medium bombers (BADGERS) are assigned to components other than Long Range
                        Aviation, viz 375 to Naval Aviation. Yields of weapons assigned to these
                        aircraft could vary from 10 <gloss target="#t_KT_1">KT</gloss> to 7 <gloss
                            target="#t_MT_1">MT</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>c. It is estimate that, excluding combat attrition, at present the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> could put about 200 bombers over North
                        America on two-way missions in an initial attack, more than half of which
                        would be medium bombers. The Soviets have a considerably larger gross
                        capability for attacking the United States itself, but to exercise it they
                        would have to employ medium bombers on one-way missions and to use crews who
                        had not had Arctic training. With the advent of Soviet missile capabilities,
                        we regard this use of the medium bomber force in the initial attack as
                        increasingly unlikely.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">US FORCES</hi>—Of the 1308 long range bombers available 1
                        March 1962, the United States has [<hi rend="italic">text not
                            declassified</hi>] to strike targets in the Soviet Bloc, carrying [<hi
                            rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] weapons or an average of [<hi
                            rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] weapons per aircraft. Of the
                            [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] programmed aircraft, [<hi
                            rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] are programmed to be on alert
                        and could be launched within 15 minutes.</p>
                    <p rend="center">NOTE 2—ICBMS</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> FORCES</hi>—The figure 10–25
                        ICBMS indicates missiles on launchers and is concurred in by the United
                        States Intelligence <pb facs="d265-11" n="11" type="facsimile"
                            xml:id="d265-11"/> Board except the Assistant Chief of Staff,
                        Intelligence, <gloss target="#t_USAF_1">USAF</gloss>, believes Soviet <gloss
                            target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>’s to be about 75 as of 1 March 1962 and
                        250 in mid-1963. The Soviet ICBMs for the present and for the near future
                        will be deployed in soft sites. Evidence indicates that there will be no
                        hardened sites by 1963.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">US FORCES</hi>—The 62 US ICBMs in 1962 are ATLAS and TITAN
                        missiles; 30 are soft and 32 are in installations hardened to 25 <gloss
                            target="#t_PSI_1">PSI</gloss> and above. In 1963, US ICBMs are as
                        follows:</p>
                    <pb facs="1104" n="953" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_953"/>
                    <p>27 ATLAS D—Soft</p>
                    <p>29 ATLAS E—25 <gloss target="#t_PSI_1">PSI</gloss>
                    </p>
                    <p>75 ATLAS F—150–200 <gloss target="#t_PSI_1">PSI</gloss>
                    </p>
                    <p>57 TITAN I—150–200 <gloss target="#t_PSI_1">PSI</gloss>
                    </p>
                    <p>34 TITAN II—300 <gloss target="#t_PSI_1">PSI</gloss>
                    </p>
                    <p>156 MINUTEMAN—[<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                    <p>3788</p>
                    <p>*(20 missiles utilized for training purposes)</p>
                    <p rend="center">NOTE 3—SUBMARINE LAUNCHED MISSILES</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> FORCE</hi>—The Soviets would
                        probably assign US land targets to missile launching submarines. The number
                        to be deployed depends on the pattern of operations. The Soviets are
                        estimated to have the following number of submarines:</p>
                    <table cols="3">
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">1962</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">1963</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Z Class 350 nm (2 missiles)</cell>
                            <cell role="num">7</cell>
                            <cell role="num">7</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>G Class 350 nm (3 missiles)</cell>
                            <cell role="num">18</cell>
                            <cell role="num">18</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>H Class 350 nm (3 missiles)</cell>
                            <cell role="num">8</cell>
                            <cell role="num">16</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">US FORCES</hi>—Of the 80 POLARIS missiles now at sea in
                        operational <gloss target="#t_SSBN_1">SSBN</gloss>’s, 48 are on [<hi
                            rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>]; 16 others are in <gloss
                            target="#t_SSBN_1">SSBN</gloss>’s in [<hi rend="italic">text not
                            declassified</hi>] at Holy Loch; and, 16 others are on [<hi
                            rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] at Holy Loch.</p>
                    <p>In 1963, out of 128 missiles at sea in operational <gloss target="#t_SSBN_1"
                            >SSBN</gloss>’s, 80 will be on [<hi rend="italic">text not
                            declassified</hi>]; 16 to 32 will be in <gloss target="#t_SSBN_1"
                            >SSBN</gloss>’s in [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] at
                        Holy Loch; and 16 to 32 will be on [<hi rend="italic">text not
                            declassified</hi>] at Holy Loch.</p>
                    <pb facs="d265-12" n="12" type="facsimile" xml:id="d265-12"/>
                    <p>Of the 17 REGULUS missiles aboard, four SSG’s and one SSGN, four are
                        on-station at all times. The remainder are in submarines in transit between
                        the operating area and their base, in training, or at their base.</p>
                    <p rend="center">NOTE 4—OTHER FORCES</p>
                    <p>Of the total of 225 light bombers, 130 are overseas in theater areas, either
                        at shore bases or aboard aircraft carriers. The remainder are in the <gloss
                            target="#t_CONUS_1">CONUS</gloss> or aboard aircraft carriers in transit
                        or operating in the vicinity of the <gloss target="#t_CONUS_1"
                        >CONUS</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>Of the total of 2,389 fighter and attack bombers, 885 are overseas in theater
                        areas, either at shore bases or aboard aircraft carriers. The remainder are
                        in <gloss target="#t_CONUS_1">CONUS</gloss> or aboard aircraft carriers in
                        transit or operating in the vicinity of the <gloss target="#t_CONUS_1"
                            >CONUS</gloss>.</p>
                    <pb facs="1105" n="954" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_954"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> FORCES</hi>—The 250 Soviet light
                        bombers are all nuclear capable. The bulk of the Soviet <gloss
                            target="#t_MRBM_1">MRBM</gloss> launchers are in Western <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, within range of US forces in
                        Europe.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">US FORCES</hi>—US light bombers and fighter bombers
                        consist of the following:</p>
                    <table cols="3">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Light Bombers</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">1962</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">1963</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>B–57</cell>
                            <cell role="num">48</cell>
                            <cell role="num">0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>B–66</cell>
                            <cell role="num">48</cell>
                            <cell role="num">0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>A3D</cell>
                            <cell role="num">122</cell>
                            <cell role="num">118</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>A3J</cell>
                            <cell role="num">7</cell>
                            <cell role="num">44</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell role="num">225</cell>
                            <cell role="num">162</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Fighter Bombers</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>F–100F</cell>
                            <cell role="num">792</cell>
                            <cell role="num">724</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>F–101 A&amp;C</cell>
                            <cell role="num">74</cell>
                            <cell role="num">71</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>F–105 B/D</cell>
                            <cell role="num">265</cell>
                            <cell role="num">444</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>AD</cell>
                            <cell role="num">266</cell>
                            <cell role="num">244</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>A4D</cell>
                            <cell role="num">779</cell>
                            <cell role="num">907</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>A2F</cell>
                            <cell role="num">0</cell>
                            <cell role="num">20</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>FJ4B</cell>
                            <cell role="num">120</cell>
                            <cell role="num">112</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>F4H</cell>
                            <cell role="num">93</cell>
                            <cell role="num">185</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell role="num">2389</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2797</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
