<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-01-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-01-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="284" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d284">
                        <head>284. Notes on Remarks of President <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1">Kennedy</persName>, January 22<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d284fn1">A review of national security problems: Cuba;
                                Europe; the Neutrals; domestic affairs; foreign aid, and military
                                issues. Top Secret. 7 pp. Department of State, Central Files,
                                711.5/1–2363.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline>
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1963-01-22">January 22, 1963</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <pb facs="d284-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d284-1"/>
                        <p>Following is the substance of a forty-minute talk by the President at
                            11:00 a.m., January 22, 1963, to the National Security Council and a
                            large group of officers of the Government departments.</p>
                        <p>The subject was forthcoming National Security problems.</p>
                        <p>The President began by saying that he wanted particularly to review the
                            problems and areas that are going to be before us in the coming months.
                            U.S. responsibility is worldwide, he said, and the U.S. is the only
                            power that can fully exercise that responsibility. He cited the
                            commitments to <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SEATO_1">SEATO</gloss> and, in the case of <gloss target="#t_CENTO_1">CENTO</gloss>, the U.S.’s role as the key
                            country though it is not a member.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">CUBA</hi></p>
                        <p>The reason the Cuban crisis illustrates the importance of providing time
                            during moments of confrontation between the big powers so that both
                            sides can consider alternatives before moving to points of no return. He
                            pointed out that it was a “very close thing” between a U.S. decision to
                            mount an air strike against the Soviet installations and the final
                            decision, the quarantine. The results, he said, emphasized the
                            importance of the strategy we embarked on. It put the Russians in the
                            position of having to act within a twelve hour period. During the four
                            to five days leading up to the U.S. decision, he said, all the
                            principals involved somewhat changed their original views. There is
                            general agreement, he believes, that the final decision was the right
                            one.</p>
                        <p>We should hope, he said, to approach future crises with a similar
                            objective, namely to give the antagonist sufficient time to consider
                            alternatives.</p>
                        <p>It is entirely likely, he said, that we will have another serious
                            confrontation with the Russians somewhere in the next two years,
                            according to the history of the past two years.</p>
                        <pb facs="d284-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d284-2"/>
                        <p>This likelihood is one of the important reasons for extreme emphasis on
                            our present strategy of conventional force buildup in Europe. Also he
                            said, we should not dismiss from our minds the possibility that we might
                            have to consider again hitting Cuba in some way, either directly, or
                            from sort of reprisal action or with some other major move <pb facs="1275" n="1124" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1124"/> made
                            necessary by either further Soviet activities there or by the conduct of
                            the Cubans themselves.</p>
                        <p>Also he said, we should be prepared to have to move not only in Cuba but
                            perhaps in Berlin simultaneously. We now have a hostage in this
                            hemisphere just as the Russians have had one in Berlin for several
                            years.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">EUROPE</hi></p>
                        <p>Since 1958, the President said, we have been faced with General <persName corresp="#p_DGC_1">de Gaulle</persName>’s proposal for a French,
                            American, British directorate. The <persName corresp="#p_EDD_1">Eisenhower</persName> Administration rightly rejected this as a
                            step that would give the French a veto over U.S. policy and strategy all
                            over the world, and as one that would lead to the destruction of <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>The President is convinced that our refusal to accept the <persName corresp="#p_DGC_1">de Gaulle</persName> triumverate idea has not
                            produced our present troubles with <persName corresp="#p_DGC_1">de
                                Gaulle</persName>. In spite of what <persName corresp="#p_DGC_1">de
                                Gaulle</persName> says, his present course is not based on a real
                            distrust of us (in fact he is basing all his policy on reliance on U.S.
                            power) but it is based on a strong historical conviction of the
                            dominance of France in Europe having been rebuffed by the United States
                            and the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>. He has now turned to the
                            Germans in an effort to bring about this French hegemony. This is not
                            much of a threat to us. We have attempted since the war to prevent
                            Germany from turning East so this can be lasting value in developing
                            Franco-German amity.</p>
                        <p>The French blockage of the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> entry into
                                <gloss target="#t_EEC_1">EEC</gloss> is a definite setback for us
                            and even worse one for the British. It is not as bad as some of our
                            other problems in the world. We will have problems because the British
                            don’t get in but we are going to have some very serious economic ones if
                            they did get in. The President said we are “going to have trouble” with
                            Europe in the time ahead. <pb facs="d284-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d284-3"/> This is all the more reasons, he said, why we must
                            push hard and fast on the multilateral nuclear plan and on general
                            strengthening of <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>. Perhaps the
                            multilateral plan can’t be worked out, but it is the best course, and
                            one which would maintain our ability to influence Europe on behalf of
                            our own interests and would keep them somewhat dependent on U.S.
                            power.</p>
                        <p>The President recited the list of <persName corresp="#p_DGC_1">de
                                Gaulle</persName>’s non-cooperation in <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>, Congo, Laos and
                            Viet Nam, but concluded “he is there and we have to live with him”.</p>
                        <p>The President spoke at some length on our trade and balance of payments
                            problems and said that all those involved in trade negotiations are
                            going to have to be very careful about protecting the interest of this
                            country. He said, with great emphasis, that we have got to settle our
                            balance of payments hemorrhage by 1964. If not, great pressure <pb facs="1276" n="1125" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1125"/> will develop
                            in the Congress for us to withdraw from the world to narrower policy. We
                            have got to find ways to make Europe carry its full share. If the
                            balance of payments continues to worsen it could be the beginning of
                            fast deterioration of U.S. power. We have already lost most of our
                            economic power, with the rise to prosperity in Europe, so we must use
                            our military and nuclear power in negotiations for our interest. The
                            point, he drove home, was that we have to look out for ourselves in
                            months ahead and not expect that our allies are going to be particularly
                            generous about helping us settle our own problems.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">NEUTRALS</hi></p>
                        <p>The President recognized that there is considerable criticism here and
                            among some allies that we do not distinguish between neutrals and
                            allies. He said that Pakistan is a critic of this sort. We have got to
                            be pretty cold about this the President said. India may be neutral, but
                            it represents one-sixth of the world’s population and 40% of the
                            underdeveloped world. It is in our own interest to have a sub-continent
                            that can protect itself externally and internally. Since the split with
                            China, India represents a historical opportunity and we must coldly
                            assess our interests as we consider each neutral government. He pointed
                            out that we cannot tolerate the notion of any of our aid recipients that
                                <pb facs="d284-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d284-4"/> our aid
                            should be used to settle some of their historical differences with their
                            neighbors. Also he said, we can’t have neutrals falling into the
                            Communist camp. It may be personally obnoxious to have us to have to
                            deal with Sukarno and Nassar but it is necessary.</p>
                        <pb facs="d284-5" n="5" type="facsimile" xml:id="d284-5"/>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss></hi></p>
                        <p>Strong effort must be made in the next few months to tie our <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> very closely to the security of the
                            United States. The test of every Aid proposal is whether it serves the
                            U.S. It was a mistake, the President believes, to call the program
                                <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss>, a mistake made by this
                            Administration. Mutual Security may have become a tired term but it is
                            still a better one.</p>
                        <p>He said he particularly hopes that Defense officials will be more alert
                            to the necessity of economic as well as military aid. They have better
                            luck in getting military aid approved by the Congress but military aid
                            is simply not enough. South Korea can’t be kept alive by military aid
                            alone.</p>
                        <p>The President expressed great concern that the Congress will badly
                            mutilate the <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> weapon this year
                            unless the Administration really makes a case and drives it home to the
                            American people. The way to do this, he said, is to make very clear to
                            the American people how and why <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> is
                            in their interest.</p>
                        <pb facs="1277" n="1126" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1126"/>
                        <p>The President said he was sure that nobody in this Administration wanted
                            to be in power in a period where four or five or more countries fall to
                            Communism.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">DOMESTIC AFFAIRS</hi></p>
                        <p>The President spoke at some length on the budget situation pointing out
                            that we are going to have a deficit of 12 to 12½ billion dollars. He
                            pointed out that except for Defense, Space and interest on debt (about
                            which we can do nothing), the budget under the three years that has been
                            presented by this Administration has been increased less than under the
                            three years previously of the <persName corresp="#p_EDD_1">Eisenhower</persName> Administration.</p>
                        <p>He expressed deep concern about the slow growth rate of the U.S. in the
                            past ten years—only 1 percent a year per capita. This was one
                            illustration of why the Tax Reform Bill is very important. If we have
                            another recession in this country it will seriously hurt our gold <pb facs="d284-6" n="6" type="facsimile" xml:id="d284-6"/> reserves and
                            have an extremely bad psychological effect in the U.S. The very force of
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName>’s progress in
                            Russia while we drift could prove to be a tremendous victory for him if
                            we do not end the drift and move forward.</p>
                        <p>The President said with great emphasis, “We have to prevent another
                            recession.” If we had one, he said, the presently contemplated deficit
                            of 12 billion could go as high as 20 billion dollars and with disastrous
                            effects.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">MILITARY</hi></p>
                        <p>The President said he was confident that some of the military were
                            disturbed over the cut-backs in some programs such as B–70, Nike-Zeus
                            and Skybolt but he reminded that the highest proportion of the budget by
                            far is going to Defense.</p>
                        <p>In connection with Defense commitments he said that one of our biggest
                            jobs is to persuade some of our Allies in Europe, under very adverse
                            conditions, that they must do more themselves. The coming months are
                            going to be rather decisive, particularly as they effect the
                            multilateral question and our conventional strategy.</p>
                        <p>As he did in other places, the President stressed that we must consider
                            very hard the narrow interest of the U.S. as well as the general
                            interest of the world. Otherwise the voice of the U.S. will become less
                            and less and if this happens free world power will also become less and
                            less.</p>
                        <p>He remarked that DeGaulle’s strategy is in fact based entirely on the
                            power of the U.S.</p>
                        <pb facs="1278" n="1127" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1127"/>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">DISARMAMENT</hi></p>
                        <p>He placed heavy emphasis on the importance of a nuclear test ban. If the
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> really wants one and knows we
                            must ultimately include Red China, then the <pb facs="d284-7" n="7" type="facsimile" xml:id="d284-7"/> conclusion of test ban
                            negotiations can have helpful consequences that we are not yet able to
                            define.</p>
                        <p>He expressed great concern about the possibility of the Chinese Communist
                            nuclear capability. He thought a test ban agreement might produce
                            pressure against development of such a capability. Any negotiations that
                            can hold back the Chinese Communists are most important, he said,
                            because they loom as our major antagonists of the late 60’s and
                            beyond.</p>
                        <p>The President spoke for approximately more than 40 minutes with
                            considerable force and clarity. He used no notes but was obviously well
                            organized in his train of thought and concepts. He expressed thanks to
                            everyone at the meeting for the work they and their colleagues had done
                            in the last year. He was pleased by the way various branches of the
                            Government had been cooperating and hoped that this inter-relationship
                            would grow even stronger in the next year.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>