<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>306. Memorandum from Rostow to Members of Policy Planning Council, November
                    29 to Members of Policy Planning Council, November 29</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v07-09mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d306</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">306</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-11-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-11-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="rec9aDoDi7sluDnsm" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="civil-rights"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026371"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil rights</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="recozOKDL3hzRM0mM" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Détente</term>
                    <term ref="recoGY8BsVctNF3tT" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="arab-israeli-dispute">Arab-Israeli dispute</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec9i482eX195qnGX" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="detainees" subject="detained">detained</term>
                    <term ref="recfab616ca717a635" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="decolonization" subject="colonialism">Colonialism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-11-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-11-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="306"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d306">
                <head>306. Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_RWW_1">Rostow</persName> to Members
                    of Policy Planning Council, November 29<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d306fn1">Addresses input from regional bureaus on key issues.
                        Secret. 4 pp. Department of State, <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss>
                        Files: Lot 70 D 199, Secretary’s PPMs.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-11-29">November 29, 1963</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d306-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d306-1"/>
                <p rend="center">NOTIFICATION OF SECRETARY’S POLICY PLANNING MEETING, 10 A.M.,
                    TUESDAY, DECEMBER 3, 1963, IN THE SECRETARY’S CONFERENCE ROOM</p>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Comment on Key Issues Underlined by Assistant
                            Secretaries</hi>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The extremely able and terse summaries of current key issues developed by the
                    Bureaus speak for themselves. It may be useful to underline one general
                    reflection on them, which arose directly from their reading.</p>
                <p>1. In general they dramatize the fact that in all parts of the world we are
                    positioned in rather delicate balance between hopeful trends and political
                    degenerative forces. With one arm we are pressing forward, with the other we are
                    fending off danger. Relatively small shifts in policy, emphasis, or energy could
                    violate those balances and create major problems for us.</p>
                <p>2. In Africa there is the balance between friendship towards black Africa set off
                    against the dilemma posed for us by South Africa and Portuguese Africa. Here,
                    aside from the passage of civil rights legislation, the maintenance of some
                    marginal leverage on the radicals (Ben Bella, Kwame Nkrumah, and Sekou Toure),
                    plus continued support for the moderates, appears essential if the whole of our
                    African policy is not to be endangered.</p>
                <p>3. With respect to Western Europe, any faltering in our loyalty to Atlantic
                    partnership would, of course, strengthen de Gaulle’s hand and, at the same time,
                    endanger the movements forward which we must make in both the <persName
                        corresp="#p_HCA_1">Herter</persName>
                    <pb facs="d306-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d306-2"/> round of negotiations
                    and in European cooperation on the U.S. balance of payments problem, which, in
                    turn, could wreck the foundations of Western defense. Our stance at the <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> meeting and the manner in which we deal with
                    the impasse in the development of a <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>
                    strategy are critical. The most intimate bilateral consultation with the Germans
                    is the requirement for success at almost every point.</p>
                <pb facs="1526" n="1375" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1375"/>
                <p>4. In relations with Moscow, the critical issue appears to be whether we can keep
                    the <hi rend="italic">détente</hi> breathing—and, specifically, generate and
                    negotiate a sufficiently persuasive package to compensate for the possible
                    adverse reaction to the bilateral air agreement. The suggested elements are
                    Soviet acceptance of our requirement for notification of and access to U.S.
                    citizens detained in the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, plus the
                    provision of a leased line teletype link to Moscow.</p>
                <p>5. In the Middle East and Asia we confront the problem of maintaining delicate
                    balances in the Arab-Israeli dispute and in the India-Pakistan affair. The need
                    for balance in the case of the former is particularly important given the
                    possible Jordan waters crisis in the spring or summer of 1964.</p>
                <p>6. In the Far East we have a delicate balance in the Indonesian confrontation of
                    Malaysia, as well as the two precarious military situations in Laos and Viet
                    Nam.</p>
                <p>7. In Latin America, again we have a problem of balance between the thrust of the
                    Alliance for Progress and other elements of cohesion and the potential
                    corrosiveness of both Latin American nationalism, exacerbated by Communist
                    influence and pressures.</p>
                <p>8. In the United Nations, all of these balances are reflected, but notably those
                    in Africa and Asia; and the great issue is posed of the United Nations’ role in
                    helping keep the balances on the constructive side via peace-keeping
                    machinery.</p>
                <pb facs="d306-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d306-3"/>
                <p>9. What I draw from this array (quickly and incompletely ticked off) is the need
                    for us all, from the President on down, to perceive a general point that
                    transcends any of these items; namely, that the President has come to
                    responsibility at a time when we are working our way slowly through a whole set
                    of major historical transitions: the transition of Africa from colonialism to
                    responsibility; the transition of Western Europe from dependence to partnership;
                    the transition of Russia, hopefully, from a vicious offensive to something like
                    a stable, peaceful co-existence; the transition of the Middle East and South
                    Asia from an obsession with post-colonial boundary issues, which have been the
                    focus of the new nationalism, to a more stable maturity; in the Far East from
                    the aggressive nationalism of Sukarno to an Indonesian concern with its domestic
                    development; in old Indochina, hopefully, from limited probing aggression,
                    sparked by Hanoi, to peace.</p>
                <p>10. Every one of these balances is capable of being upset, if we falter or lose
                    resoluteness in either pressing in the hopeful direction or in fending off
                    potential degeneration. If the balances are upset, the U.S. could face major
                    crises.</p>
                <p>11. To see our way through these historical transitions will require that these
                    balances be understood and that we be prepared to sweat <pb facs="1527" n="1376"
                        type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1376"/> them out steadily; but it must always be
                    remembered that the balances are dynamic. They do not maintain themselves
                    without the steady application of energy to fend off evil and to promote the
                    good.</p>
                <p>12. It may be that if this general perspective on the bewildering array of
                    specific situations we face could be widely understood and shared (assuming for
                    the moment it is correct), we would be forwarder.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_RWW_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWW_1">W.W. Rostow</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
