<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>375. “Report of the Development Assistance Panel,” President’s Science
                    Advisory Committee, May 18</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v07-09mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d375</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">375</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-05-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113036"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Research and development</term>
                    <term ref="recKkhgppZ5fwGQoV" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">Development assistance</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="recR0zhXxdC8M9meR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic recovery</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec8PCbWGrkAaOOXZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001000124"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developed countries</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="rec2Vr3ggDH3KiJCO" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077482"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Literacy</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="rec9RYyHNCrX0AT9t" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85070654"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Joint ventures</term>
                    <term ref="rec_world_war_ii" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="world-war-ii" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148273" lcsh-match="exact">World War II</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recfrz0b94d87k9th" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-engineering" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092968" lcsh-match="exact">Engineering</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Conferences</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="rec90c76a0ac666292" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="public-health" subject="public-health">Public Health</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-05-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="375"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d375">
                <head>375. “Report of the Development Assistance Panel,” President’s Science
                    Advisory Committee, May 18<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d375fn1">Research
                        and development unit to help manage the U.S. development assistance program
                        recommended. Official Use Only. 5 pp. Washington National Records Center,
                            <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 286, <gloss target="#t_AID_1"
                            >AID</gloss> Administrator Files: <gloss target="#t_FRC_1">FRC</gloss>
                        65 A 481, White House, <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 1962.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-05-18">May 18, 1961</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d375-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d375-1"/>
                <p rend="center">RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT <lb/> IN THE NEW DEVELOPMENT ASSISTANCE
                    PROGRAM</p>
                <pb facs="d375-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d375-2"/>
                <p rend="center">I—INTRODUCTION</p>
                <p>Since the end of World War II it has been the policy of the United States to
                    stand ready with financial assistance for those foreign countries where
                    resources were insufficient to meet pressing needs. Initially, this assistance
                    was directed to the rehabilitation of the devastated areas of Western Europe
                    and, when this task was well in hand, to their <pb facs="1743" n="1592"
                        type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1592"/> economic recovery. Later, emphasis was
                    placed upon the ability of those nations, and others, to defend themselves
                    against aggression. But in recent years, as the industrialized nations have
                    achieved and surpassed their pre-war capabilities, the focus of attention has
                    become fixed upon the less developed nations of Latin America, the Middle East,
                    Africa and Asia. It is clear that in the future American foreign aid, augmented
                    now by those nations which were themselves its recipients only a few years back,
                    will be directed predominantly to the complex task of assisting in the economic
                    and social development of nations, new and old, in the less developed areas of
                    the world.</p>
                <p>The development assistance program that is now being shaped is intended to meet
                    these new responsibilities. They differ both in kind and in scope from those of
                    the past. The fundamental problems with which the new agency will deal are not
                    problems which will be resolved in one year, or five, or ten. The task is not to
                    rebuild, but to build; not to restore economies but to create them. The needs
                    are urgent. The United States must not only manage its own effort, but must
                    coordinate its activities with those of the other industrialized nations which
                    are joining in the task, and must help provide leadership for the less developed
                    countries themselves as they strive to further their own ambitions. These are
                    new dimensions in foreign aid programs, necessitating profound re-examination of
                    means and mechanisms.</p>
                <p>The people of the United States have come to realize that freedom at home is
                    affected by the fate of freedom in the rest of the world, and that human misery
                    and social chaos anywhere in the world imperil free men everywhere. Both our
                    present concern for the state of the world and our historic commitments to human
                    dignity and freedom justify our continuing attention to the grave problems
                    facing less developed countries.</p>
                <p>In doing this, we associate ourselves with men of understanding and good will
                    wherever they may be. We do not see this as a matter of an advanced nation
                    helping less advanced nations—we have by no means solved all our own problems.
                    Nor do we see it as a matter of a big nation helping smaller nations. It is a
                    matter of men of conscience, here and everywhere—men concerned with the state of
                    the world and the condition of man—joining hands in the ancient battle against
                    the afflictions of mankind.</p>
                <pb facs="d375-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d375-3"/>
                <p>Our goals are these:</p>
                <quote>
                    <p>1. To assist in the growth of social orders responsive to the needs of the
                        individual.</p>
                    <p>2. To bring about a steadily rising level of living in the less developed
                        nations.</p>
                    <p>3. To help the developing nations learn the difficult art of accomplishing
                        change within a framework of order.</p>
                    <pb facs="1744" n="1593" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1593"/>
                    <p>4. To help create an international order that will serve the maintenance and
                        the improvement of mutual security.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>There is a faith that goals such as these can be met by means of a development
                    assistance program, but there is also an awareness that we will encounter
                    difficulties along the way. Earlier tasks of rehabilitation, of economic
                    recovery and of military assistance could be approached confidently and
                    expertly. The problems encountered were those to which we are accustomed in our
                    own society, and the solutions were as familiar to those who needed our aid as
                    to those who brought it to bear. Indeed, it was often the foreign country itself
                    which identified its problem and suggested the form that aid should take. This
                    is no longer the case. The economies, the customs, the political structures and
                    the resources of the less developed countries have little or nothing in common
                    with our own. Each of these nations has special problems which the
                    industrialized nations, in their evolution into modern societies, were never
                    called upon to face; their economic, cultural and social differences rule out
                    any single, simple solution. Rarely can we rely upon basic resources which
                    normally we take for granted, such as minimal public health standards or
                    widespread literacy. Before we can hope to see answers, we must wage our own
                    intellectual struggle to recognize the questions in their proper
                    perspective.</p>
                <p>No development assistance program can hope to be effective unless it is built
                    firmly upon two broad foundations. The first of these is the organization of
                    skilled inquiry to define the needs of the nation we hope to assist; to develop
                    techniques by means of which the process of inquiry itself may be made more
                    efficient; to establish the knowledge that can be brought to bear on these needs
                    and the framework within which that knowledge can be applied; to discover means
                    of stimulating the flow of human resources, here and in the less developed
                    nations, into the stream of development assistance. The second broad foundation
                    is the detailed and imaginative engineering of each proposed solution in terms
                    of its actual application in the field, and the education and training of those
                    who will be called upon to apply it.</p>
                <pb facs="d375-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d375-4"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">SUMMARY OF REPORT</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">DEVELOPMENT ASSISTANCE PANEL</p>
                <p rend="center">PRESIDENT’S SCIENCE ADVISORY COMMITTEE</p>
                <p>Estimates of the scope, pace and long-term efforts required to meet the explosive
                    problems of the emerging nations and regions are rising rapidly. Imaginative
                    programs to meet this challenge call for the effective mobilization of diverse
                    talents and resources—public and private, national and international. The
                    private business and academic communities, in particular, must be more fully
                    tapped as a source of study, <pb facs="1745" n="1594" type="typeset"
                        xml:id="pg_1594"/> knowledge and experience as well as a source of qualified
                    personnel. A Research and Development Unit to serve the pending consolidated
                    U.S. Development Assistance Program is needed to help bring about such a
                    mobilization of effort and to ensure that the aims of the new Program will be
                    efficiently met and the huge investments involved protected.</p>
                <p>The R &amp; D Unit would have as its tasks to improve developmental planning, to
                    identify requirements and priorities, and to define the most effective forms and
                    channels of external assistance to the emerging countries; to help generate new
                    knowledge and techniques to meet the problems of the emerging nations; to
                    conduct appropriate experiments and pilot projects in the less developed areas;
                    to assist in the transition from pilot program to operation; in doing so, to
                    utilize existing institutions and to help them to provide the necessary trained
                    personnel; to create, where necessary, new institutional resources; to
                    coordinate relevant R &amp; D activities outside the Development Assistance
                    Program and to serve as a unifying factor among the elements of the assistance
                    program and to ensure that the entire effort is responsive to our foreign policy
                    objectives.</p>
                <p>The areas in which the Unit may expect to be active include the natural sciences,
                    and intimately involve the full range of social, political and cultural
                    sciences. It must deal particularly in the identification of those forces which
                    mold a society, with the adaptation of existing technology, with the pursuit of
                    problems that were by-passed in the evolution of our own society but which are
                    nevertheless central to less developed societies, and to a limited degree in
                    basic research. Its primary criterion must be the needs of the operational
                    programs in the field.</p>
                <pb facs="d375-5" n="5" type="facsimile" xml:id="d375-5"/>
                <p>The Unit itself is envisaged as small and compact, with a director of high
                    eminence, a small professional staff and a large body of able and energetic
                    consultants. Special steps should be taken to ensure the participation of
                    individuals from private industry.</p>
                <p>The Unit should lay great stress upon the promotion of international cooperative
                    activities and the creation of joint institutions with other industrialized
                    nations and the emerging countries. It should employ the services of academic
                    institutions by means of grants and contracts designed to maintain and
                    strengthen those institutions, should work with industrial firms, particularly
                    in the area of adaptive engineering, and should enter into joint ventures with
                    private foundations, international agencies and other governmental institutions.
                    It should promote action-oriented conferences and studies, and design ambitious
                    field activities around consultant teams.</p>
                <p>The budget may be expected to attain a level of approximately $95 million in four
                    or five years; the Panel recommends a first-year budget on the order of $50
                    million.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
