<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-06-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-06-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="131" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d131">
                            <head>131. Letter From Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_ESA1" type="from">Eden</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1" type="to">Eisenhower</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d131fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, Whitman
                                    File, International File. Secret. Attached to this letter was a
                                    note of transmission from <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>, dated June 3.</note></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-06-03"><hi rend="italic">June 3,
                                    1955</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: Thank you so much for
                                your message.<note n="2" xml:id="d131fn2"><ref target="#d128">Document 128</ref>.</note> Naturally I am disappointed that
                                you do not feel able to come to this country for preliminary talks,
                                but I quite understand how difficult it would be for you to get
                                away. I am sure excellent preparations will be made by the Foreign
                                Secretaries but I hope that you and I, perhaps with <persName corresp="#p_FE1">Faure</persName>, will have some chance of a
                                talk when we arrive in advance of our meeting with the Russians.</p>
                            <p>I am very glad that you think you could manage the four to five clear
                                days for the meeting at the summit. I understand your reasons <pb facs="0240" n="214" xml:id="pg_214"/> for wanting to identify
                                the problems and discuss methods of work rather than enter into a
                                discussion of solutions. This is our own approach also. It follows
                                that, if we are to carry public opinion with us the meeting should
                                be presented as a first of a series at various levels to handle the
                                problems confronting the world. For this reason I think it important
                                that we neither in our minds nor in anything we say publicly exclude
                                the possibility of further meetings at the top level if that seems
                                useful. Yours ever,</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_ESA1"><hi rend="strong">Anthony</hi></persName><note n="3" xml:id="d131fn3">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                                    signature.</note></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>