<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>142. Letter From Secretary of State Dulles to Foreign Minister to Foreign
                    Minister Molotov</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d142</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">142</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-06-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-06-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recEWsf4stFSIl3L6" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Press relations</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-06-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-06-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="142"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d142">
                <head>142. Letter From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_DAW1" type="from"
                        >Dulles</persName> to Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_MVM1" type="to"
                        >Molotov</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d142fn1">Source: Department of State,
                        Conference Files: Lot 63 D 123, CF 486. Confidential. Attached to this
                        letter was a cover sheet which noted that it had been drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_BCEC1">Bohlen</persName> and delivered to <persName
                            corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> just prior to his meeting with the
                        three Western Foreign Ministers (see <gloss target="#t_PMCGSFMC1">PMCG (SF)
                            MC</gloss>–2, <ref target="#d143">
                            <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>
                        </ref>). The Foreign Ministers were at San Francisco for ceremonies of the
                        tenth anniversary of the United Nations.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">San Francisco</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-06-20">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 20, 1955</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr.</hi>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi>
                    </persName>: We are all looking forward with pleasure to our dinner tonight
                    which as you have already been informed will be at eight o’clock at the Pacific
                    Union Club.</p>
                <p>With a view to facilitating our discussion this evening concerning certain
                    practical arrangements for the meeting of the four Heads of Government, I
                    enclose a list of a number of such questions. The list is, of course, tentative
                    and by no means inclusive, but I believe these questions represent at least some
                    of the points we should examine here.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">
                            <hi rend="strong">John Foster Dulles</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="2" xml:id="d142fn2">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">[Enclosure]</note>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="d142fn3">According to the cover sheet referred to in <ref
                            target="#d142fn1">footnote 1</ref> above, this list was based on Section
                        I of the report of the Washington Tripartite Working Group as amended by the
                        Foreign Ministers during their talks in New York.</note>
                    <head>SUGGESTED ARRANGEMENTS AND PROCEDURES FOR THE FOUR-POWER CONFERENCE OF
                        HEADS OF GOVERNMENT IN GENEVA</head>
                    <p>(Based largely on the pattern of the Berlin Meeting of 1954)</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">1.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Chairmanship and Seating</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Heads of Government will preside in daily rotation, proceeding
                                clockwise around the table, following the seating plan used at
                                Berlin and earlier meetings:</p>
                            <p>[Here follows a diagram of the seating arrangement.]</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">2.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Number at Table</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Each of the four powers will have five seats at table. A second row
                                of seats will be provided for five advisers. It is recognized that
                                there may be occasions when the four Heads of Government might wish
                                to meet on a more restricted basis.</p>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="0268" n="242" xml:id="pg_242"/>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">3.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Order of Speakers</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>With respect to formal statements, the Heads of Government will
                                normally be called upon in clockwise order. This should not exclude
                                interventions nor impose any restraint on free and full
                                discussion.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">4.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Agenda</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>There will be no fixed agenda, but as proposed in the invitation of
                                May 10<note n="4" xml:id="d142fn4">See <ref target="#d114">Document
                                        114</ref>.</note> and accepted in the Soviet reply of May
                                    26,<note n="5" xml:id="d142fn5">See <ref target="#d124">Document
                                        124</ref>.</note> the Heads of Government will, themselves,
                                decide upon the conduct of the proceedings.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">5.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Languages</hi> (English, French, Russian)</p>
                            <p>The words of each speaker will be interpreted into the other two
                                languages, using the consecutive system. In addition, there will be
                                simultaneous interpretation of the speaker into the other two
                                languages. Consecutive interpretation may be waived in any instance
                                by mutual agreement.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">6.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Agreed Conference Documents</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The official documents of the Conference will consist of such
                                decisions and communiqués as may be agreed by the four Heads of
                                Government. There will be no agreed verbatim minutes. Each
                                delegation will be free to take its own record.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">7.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Relations With the Press</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The sessions will be closed to the press and the public. In respect
                                to relations with the press, every effort should be made to handle
                                this in a way to prevent press relations impairing the ability of
                                the conference to achieve positive results. The four Foreign
                                Ministers might discuss in preliminary fashion the best way of
                                dealing with this question. Before the opening session is called to
                                order, and perhaps again at the close of the final session, ten
                                minutes will be allowed for photographs.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">8.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretariat</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>As at Berlin, the three Western powers will establish a common
                                secretariat which will make suitable arrangements with the Soviet
                                secretariat for records of decisions, interpretation, translation,
                                documentation, security of the Conference premises, housekeeping,
                                and cost-sharing.</p>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="0269" n="243" xml:id="pg_243"/>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">9.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Advance Arrangements</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The four powers will designate qualified experts who will proceed to
                                the Conference site at the earliest feasible date. These experts
                                will be authorized by their respective governments to conclude
                                agreements on the necessary arrangements.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">10.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Security</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Security arrangements at the Conference site will be organized by
                                agreement between the two secretariats. Access will be strictly
                                controlled. Passes will be issued and arrangements made to check
                                them at appropriate control points.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">11.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Finances</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Each of the four powers will pay one quarter of the common Conference
                                costs.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">12.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Meeting Schedule</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Conference will meet on four successive days. On the first day,
                                there will be a meeting both in the morning and in the afternoon. On
                                the succeeding days, the Heads of Government will, unless they agree
                                otherwise, hold one meeting each day, in the afternoon, The Foreign
                                Ministers may, as required, meet in the morning to discuss matters
                                remanded to them by the Heads of Government.</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
