<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>143. Memorandum of a Conversation, Pacific Union Club, San Francisco, June
                    20, 1955, 10:45 p.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d143</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">143</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-06-21T00:45:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-06-21T00:45:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-06-21T00:45:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-06-21T00:45:00-05:00" n="143"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d143">
                <head>143. Memorandum of a Conversation, Pacific Union Club, San Francisco, June 20,
                    1955, 10:45 p.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d143fn1">Source: Department of
                        State, Conference Files: Lot 63 D 123, CF 487. Secret. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_BCEC1">Bohlen</persName> on June 21. This conversation took
                        place following Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName>’
                        dinner for the Foreign Ministers. Also discussed following dinner were
                        Austria, the Berlin Autobahn situation, disarmament, and a declaration for
                        the U.N. tenth anniversary meeting. Memoranda of these conversations, <gloss
                            target="#t_PMCGSFMC1">PMCG (SF) MC</gloss>–3 through <gloss
                            target="#t_MC1">MC</gloss>–6, are <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>. For
                            <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>’s account of the dinner,
                        see <hi rend="italic">Tides of Fortune</hi>, pp. 609–610. For a French
                        account of this conversation, see <hi rend="italic">Documents Diplomatiques
                            Français</hi>, 1955, Annexes, Tome 1, pp. 223–228.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1955-06-20T22:45:00-07:00"
                            >June 20, 1955, 10:45 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_PMCGSFMC1">PMCG (SF) MC</gloss>–2</p>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">United States</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MAD1">MacArthur</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BCEC1">Bohlen</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">France</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName corresp="#p_CMM1">Couve de Murville</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. Andronikov</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <pb facs="0270" n="244" xml:id="pg_244"/>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">United Kingdom</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Sir <persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Harold Caccia</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Sir <persName>Pierson Dixon</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Wilkinson</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">U.S.S.R.</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Fedorenko</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ZGN1">Zarubin</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Sovolev</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Troyanovsky</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The Secretary suggested that they should exchange views on certain technical
                    matters involved in arrangements for the Four Power meeting. He had sent Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> a memorandum on behalf of the
                    Three Ministers listing certain of these questions.<note n="2" xml:id="d143fn2"
                        >See the enclosure, <ref target="#d142">
                            <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said he
                    would be glad to exchange views but he did not have a written translation of
                    this memorandum. He inquired if it was intended to discuss only these points.
                    The Secretary said “yes, for the present” but that any other matters could be
                    taken up subsequently if Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    desired. The Secretary began with the first point in the memorandum concerning
                    the seating arrangements at the Geneva Conference. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said he thought that the Heads of
                    Government could decide the points raised in the memorandum, but that he saw no
                    particular difficulty since it would be normal to follow the usual procedure.
                    There was one point, however, which was not clear and that was the duration of
                    the Conference, concerning which the views of the Soviet Government had already
                    been expressed in its notes. He assumed that that question would be decided also
                    by the Heads of Government. The Secretary said he would like to explain again
                    the special position of the President as compared with the other participants.
                    The President could not delegate his powers and that therefore the length of his
                    absence was strictly limited by this fact, especially while Congress is in
                    session. Some acts of Congress automatically become law with the President’s
                    signature, others are vetoed by failure to sign within the fixed period. This
                    meant that the President could not be absent from the United States for more
                    than one week at the most. The President indicated that he might stay on a day
                    or so beyond the four-day period if the work of the Conference justified it, but
                    that in any case it could not exceed a week. He remarked that, while these were
                    details, time was important since there was less than a month before Geneva. He
                    said he thought it <pb facs="0271" n="245" xml:id="pg_245"/> was necessary to
                    explain the particular circumstances of the President. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said no doubt the Heads of all Four
                    Governments were very busy and had many constitutional and practical matters to
                    deal with and hence their time was valuable. He felt, however, that the Heads of
                    Government could settle this themselves. He thought the other questions in the
                    memorandum might be worked out through diplomatic channels in any one of the
                    four capitals and he did not believe that there would be much difficulty. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> said he thought it would be
                    easier to settle these points in one of the capitals if they had had preliminary
                    discussions here. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> jokingly
                    said that perhaps the hardest question would be that of the seating as the
                    memorandum had even contained a picture. He believed that if they chose
                    Washington and that if that was acceptable to all this matter could be settled
                    without difficulty, that is unless it was too heavy a burden for Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName>. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1"
                        >Macmillan</persName> then said he thought they could all agree here that
                    the President of the United States as the only Chief of State should be the
                    first Chairman. The other question he had in mind for discussion was the press
                    problem. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> agreed to an
                    exchange of views and repeated he saw no difficulty in this question as well.
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> said the question was
                    whether they expected to issue a communiqué after each day’s meeting. He
                    personally felt this was not desirable since what was to go into the communiqué
                    might take a lot of time but it was a problem of dealing with the thousands of
                    press representatives who would be at Geneva and who without guidance might
                    indulge in all kinds of rumors and speculation and instead of helping the
                    success of the Conference might cause damage. He felt the question was not easy
                    but a preliminary exchange of views might be helpful. He said the only question
                    was what would be the best method to adopt. The Secretary said it was more a
                    point of what method would be the least bad. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                        >Molotov</persName> stated that he felt it was better to issue communiqués
                    but was prepared to discuss other alternatives. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1"
                        >Macmillan</persName> said he felt that if there was to be a daily
                    communiqué the Heads of Government could go away leaving to the Foreign
                    Ministers the task of working it out. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                        >Molotov</persName> replied that he agreed the Ministers would have a job of
                    work to do. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> said that even
                    if a daily communiqué was issued the press would still seek further accounts
                    from various sources and it was better to have them receive a generally
                    coordinated account than dealing in conflicting versions of what had taken
                    place.</p>
                <p>The Secretary mentioned that in past meetings of the Four Governments, beginning
                    with the first meeting in 1945, the Ministers had been making preparations not
                    so much as to persuade each other but for publication in the press. He felt that
                    if that developed at the Geneva meeting it would not be a success and would
                    suffer the fate <pb facs="0272" n="246" xml:id="pg_246"/> of previous meetings
                    of the Foreign Ministers. He felt that at this meeting the statements should be
                    short and to the point. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said
                    he could see no objection to that view.</p>
                <p>The Secretary then said there was one related matter not included in the
                    memorandum and that was the question of official entertainment. The President of
                    the Swiss Republic had suggested that a dinner be given for the President and
                    the Heads of the other Three Governments on Thursday night, July 21st. He felt
                    they should accept but that this should be the only formal official
                    entertainment. In order to permit informal contact and discussion a buffet might
                    be arranged which would permit the Heads of Government and the Foreign Ministers
                    to have informal and possibly more successful exchanges even than those at the
                    regular meetings, but that formal official entertainment should be limited to
                    the Swiss dinner. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said that
                    he felt those observations would not encounter any objection. The Secretary then
                    stated that if agreeable to the Soviet Government they might indicate to the
                    Swiss Government their acceptance of the invitation for Thursday, July 21st. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said that having had a
                    preliminary exchange of views that final decision might be made in the manner
                    suggested, namely in Washington.</p>
                <p>The Secretary inquired if there were any other matters of a formal nature to be
                    taken up. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said that he hoped
                    it was understood that the last point in the memorandum concerning the duration
                    of the Conference had not been accepted. The Secretary agreed but said, as he
                    pointed out, he wished to leave no doubts on the point that the President’s
                    constitutional responsibilities made it impossible for him to be absent for more
                    than a week. He said that this was a statement and he did not ask that Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> agree. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> asked if there were any other questions
                    on this general subject to be raised.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said there was one further point and that was that in the
                    invitation of the Three Powers reference had been made to the possible
                    desirability of a preliminary meeting of the Foreign Ministers at Geneva. He
                    wished to inquire if Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> thought
                    the meetings here and at Vienna were sufficient or if another meeting of the
                    Foreign Ministers at Geneva before the Heads of Government meeting was
                    necessary. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> replied that he
                    thought the Ministers had already done what they had to do and that it was now
                    up to the Heads of Government when they meet.<note n="3" xml:id="d143fn3">
                        <p>On June 21 and 23 <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> each discussed the
                            conference at Geneva further with <persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                                >Molotov</persName>. At both sessions <persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                                >Molotov</persName> stressed that the Soviet Union would want to
                            discuss disarmament, European security, and economic cooperation during
                            the conference. (Memoranda of conversations, <gloss
                                target="#t_PMCGSFMC1">PMCG (SF)</gloss> Memo–2, June 23, and <gloss
                                target="#t_PMCGSFMC1">PMCG (SF) MC</gloss>–10, June 23; Department
                            of State, Conference Files: Lot 63 D 123, CF 487)</p>
                        <p>On June 24, <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> told Dulles
                            that the Soviet Union accepted the procedural arrangements proposed in
                            the Western List (enclosure, <ref target="#d142">
                                <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                            </ref>) except that it wanted a quadripartite Secretariat rather than
                            two separate ones. (Memorandum of conversation, <gloss
                                target="#t_PMCGSFMC1">PMCG (SF) MC</gloss>–12, undated; Department
                            of State, Central Files, 396.1–GE/6–2455)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
