<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-07-20T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-07-20T17:00:00-05:00" n="193" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d193">
                            <head>193. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Delegation at the Geneva
                                    Conference</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                    State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d193fn1">Source:
                                    Department of State, Central Files, 396.1–GE/7–1955. Secret;
                                    Priority. Repeated to London, Paris for <persName corresp="#p_PGW1">Perkins</persName>, Moscow, and Bonn. The
                                    U.S. Delegation verbatim record, <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDEL</gloss>/Verb/M–1, July 19, and the record of
                                    decisions, <gloss target="#t_CFDoc1">CF/DOC</gloss>/RD/3, July
                                    20, are <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, Conference Files: Lot 63 D
                                    123, CF 509. The meeting began at 11 a.m. and adjourned at 12:20
                                    p.m. For <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName>’s
                                    account, which is in substantial agreement with this record, see
                                        <hi rend="italic">Recollections</hi>, pp.
                                33–34.</note></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-07-20T23:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">July 20,
                                            1955—11 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 43. Meeting of four Foreign
                                Ministers this morning devoted mainly to question of agenda for
                                today’s meeting of heads of government.<note n="2" xml:id="d193fn2">See <ref target="#d197">Document 197</ref>.</note>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> suggested that
                                subjects common to all four speeches yesterday should constitute
                                agenda; namely, German Reunification, European Security,
                                Disarmament, Development East-West Contacts. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> agreed that subjects of
                                common interest were disarmament, European security, German problem
                                and development of economic and cultural contacts. However <persName corresp="#p_BNA1">Bulganin</persName> had mentioned additional
                                questions yesterday on which Soviets would welcome comment: (1)
                                Termination cold war, (2) attitude toward neutrality, and (3) Far
                                East.</p>
                            <p>Secretary agreed with <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>’s proposal re list of subjects with following
                                comments: Re development East-West contacts, President had spoken
                                primarily about communication of knowledge and information rather
                                than contacts of economic and cultural character to which <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> had referred. Re three
                                additional subjects suggested by Soviet Secretary said he thought
                                omission of any reference to these subjects by President had
                                occurred not through oversight but from feeling such subjects did
                                not properly lend themselves to discussion here.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName> noted that <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> had listed four common
                                subjects in different order, and did not think the order would cause
                                difficulty. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said he
                                had no objection to the order proposed by <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName> commented regarding end of cold war and
                                re-establishment of atmosphere of trust, that once the four common
                                questions above were solved, there would not be any cold war and
                                trust would be restored. Therefore questioned usefulness including
                                these items on agenda.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said Soviet Delegation
                                had no objection to including communications in field of information
                                along with contacts in economic and cultural fields.</p>
                            <p>Secretary indicated agreement with <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName>’s view that end of cold war and restoration
                                atmosphere of trust and confidence would come about as we made
                                progress in other areas rather than as result <pb facs="0410" n="384" xml:id="pg_384"/> achieved arbitrarily or through
                                discussion. He pointed to <persName corresp="#p_BNA1">Bulganin</persName>’s refusal discuss problem of satellites and
                                international communism which appeared to be major causes of
                                distrust and tension so far as US concerned. Secretary stated that
                                US had made its views clear re proposed declaration of neutrality by
                                Austrian Government.<note n="3" xml:id="d193fn3">See <ref target="#d76">Document 76</ref>.</note> We doubted that
                                policy of so-called neutrality should be encouraged generally
                                because we believed in principle expressed in UN Charter that
                                broadly speaking there was duty of nations, subject to minor
                                exceptions, to be prepared take collective action for preservation
                                peace and prevention and removal of threats to peace. Neutrality was
                                an unrealistic policy for country with large population and
                                geological location of Germany. US had tried neutrality in 1914 and
                                1939 and found that it was dangerous for us and our friends. We
                                considered Far East questions not proper topic for discussion at
                                this conference where Asian nations concerned (principally National
                                Government of China and People’s Republic) were not present.</p>
                            <p>Agreed that press would be informed of decision on four items agreed
                                for afternoon’s meeting, and question of additional items would be
                                left to decision of heads of government.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> asked whether Foreign
                                Ministers might not also exchange views on substance of questions on
                                agenda as well as merely establishing list of items. Ministers
                                agreed that insufficient time remained at this session, but no
                                objection in principle to Foreign Ministers exchanging of views on
                                the four common subjects if so desired by the heads of
                                government.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>