<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-07-19T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-07-19T07:00:00-05:00" n="195" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d195">
                            <head>195. Memorandum of a Conversation, Geneva, July 19, 1955, 1
                                    p.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d195fn1">Source:
                                    Department of State, Conference Files: Lot 63 D 123, CF 516. Top
                                    Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BCEC1">Bohlen</persName>.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDEL</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_MC1">MC</gloss>/10</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1955-07-19T13:00:00+01:00">July 19, 1955, 1
                                        p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <list type="participants">
                                <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">United States</hi>
                                    <list>
                                        <item><gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_BCEC1">Bohlen</persName></item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">USSR</hi>
                                    <list>
                                        <item><gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_ZGN1">Zarubin</persName></item>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName>Soldatov</persName></item>
                                    </list></item>
                            </list>
                            <list type="subject">
                                <head>SUBJECTS</head>
                                <item>1. Exchange of Visits</item>
                                <item>2. U.S. Troops in Europe</item>
                                <item>3. Soviet Security Treaty Proposal</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>I had lunch today with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_ZGN1">Zarubin</persName> and Mr. <persName>Soldatov</persName>, Head
                                of the American Section of the Soviet Foreign Office. For the most
                                part, <persName corresp="#p_ZGN1">Zarubin</persName> and Soldatov
                                repeated the current line concerning the importance of
                                re-establishing relations of confidence and friendship between the
                                US and the Soviet Union. <persName corresp="#p_ZGN1">Zarubin</persName> particularly talked about the importance of
                                the exchange of visits, cultural and otherwise, as a means of
                                increasing mutual understanding, etc.</p>
                            <p>On the subject of the Conference itself, they both stressed the
                                importance of personal contacts and the necessity of reinforcing
                                security in Europe. In reply to my question on Germany, they made it
                                quite plain, as was certainly confirmed this afternoon,<note n="2" xml:id="d195fn2">See <ref target="#d197">Document
                                    197</ref>.</note> that the Soviet Government was not prepared to
                                accept the entry of a unified Germany into <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and that the proper procedure here was to
                                recognize certain “realities” and agree what could be done in the
                                light of these realities to prevent the development of tension and
                                friction between the military organizations in Europe. While they
                                did not depart in any important particular from <persName corresp="#p_BNA1">Bulganin</persName>’s speech of
                                    yesterday,<note n="3" xml:id="d195fn3">See <ref target="#d184">Document 184</ref>.</note> they certainly confirmed that
                                what the Soviets have in mind is <pb facs="0413" n="387" xml:id="pg_387"/> some sort of modus vivendi in Europe based on
                                the status quo with particular reference to some form of contact
                                between the two military set-ups along the lines indicated by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BNA1">Bulganin</persName>, namely, an
                                agreement not to use force against each other but to settle any
                                disputes by peaceful means and an undertaking not to increase
                                existing levels of troops stationed on foreign soil.</p>
                            <p>With reference to the three points raised by <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> this morning for inclusion
                                on the agenda,<note n="4" xml:id="d195fn4">See <ref target="#d193">Document 193</ref>.</note> they tended to dismiss those as
                                general questions of principles but did not seem to attach much
                                importance thereto. In reply to my observation that the restoration
                                of the pre-1939 situation in Europe in regard to troops would, in
                                effect, mean a complete departure of US forces from Europe, they
                                took the line that that was a very long term proposition and one
                                that they did not expect to be realized for many years. They
                                maintained, however, that, in principle, this must be a proper long
                                term goal whereby the troops of each country were confined to their
                                own territory.</p>
                            <p>In discussing the Soviet security treaty as envisaged by them, I
                                pointed out that, in effect, it would merely mean a re-creation of
                                Europe as it was in 1949 before the creation of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>; that Western Europe would have
                                no cohesive, collective security arrangement of its own and no
                                direct ties with the US, whereas Eastern Europe, whether or not the
                                Warsaw Pact was formally abolished, would still be a tightly-knit
                                monolithic bloc both politically and militarily. As was to be
                                expected, they took great issue of this and attempted the usual line
                                that the satellites were completely independent countries but would
                                not either make a very convincing case or pursue the point very far.
                                The only time any emotion was shown by <persName corresp="#p_ZGN1">Zarubin</persName> and Soldatov was when they were talking
                                about the destruction that Germany had caused to Russia in two World
                                Wars and that the Soviet Government did not take lightly the
                                re-creation of German militarism. They professed to be completely
                                unimpressed by my description of the safeguards built into <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_WEU1">WEU</gloss> in regard to Germany, and <persName corresp="#p_ZGN1">Zarubin</persName> made the point that if a
                                unified Germany was in that set-up, it would soon acquire a dominant
                                position—a state of affairs which the Soviet Government was not
                                prepared to accept.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_BCEC1">Charles E.
                                        Bohlen</persName><note n="5" xml:id="d195fn5">Printed from a
                                        copy that bears this typed
                                signature.</note></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>