<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>259. Memorandum of Discussion at the 256th Meeting of the National Security
                    Council, Washington, July 28, 1955</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d259</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">259</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-07-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-07-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recu3GH1ojKcJBA1c" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001281"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Aerial reconnaissance</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Information programs</term>
                    <term ref="recTNMFmPG15mKxJQ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">European security</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recfstIIL5scNKk3A" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recTUqfVf9DyIITuJ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001281"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconnaissance</term>
                    <term ref="recXOpgZpMOhBqvrd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88006884"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Consumer goods</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recbcbcHDEt9ge9nZ" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110610"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fissionable material</term>
                    <term ref="recdPycISbXW2cCGh" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85103582"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Plutonium</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-07-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-07-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="259"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d259">
                <head>259. Memorandum of Discussion at the 256th Meeting of the National Security
                    Council, Washington, July 28, 1955<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d259fn1"
                        >Source: Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> Records. Top Secret. Drafted by Bromley Smith on July
                        29.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1955-07-28">July 28,
                            1955</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follows a list of participants.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">1. Significant World Developments Affecting U.S. Security</hi>
                </p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of the situation in Indonesia and the Philippines.]</p>
                <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                <p>The President then told what took place following his statement calling for the
                    exchange of blueprints and mutual aerial reconnaissance. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BNA1">Bulganin</persName>, who was Chairman, indicated that the
                    USSR would study the U.S. proposal. The meeting then adjourned and the delegates
                    gathered in the buffet. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                    approached the President and said he did not agree with the Chairman (i.e.,
                        <persName corresp="#p_BNA1">Bulganin</persName>) because he believed the
                    President’s proposal was impractical and primarily a propaganda move. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> asked the President to accept the
                    Soviets’ inspection plan of May 10. The President replied that he was prepared
                    to take the Soviet plan if the Soviets would take the U.S. proposal. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> made no reply, and “ran out”. The
                    next day <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> stated to a group,
                    including the President, that there were always people at a conference who made
                    proposals, in the full knowledge that such proposals would be turned down, only
                    to gain a propaganda advantage. The President said he looked <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> directly in the eye and said, “Take
                    me up on my proposal.” <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s
                    response was to say that his generalization did not, of course, include the
                    President or refer to the President’s proposal. <pb facs="0556" n="530"
                        xml:id="pg_530"/> These two incidents, in the President’s opinion, revealed
                    a difference among the Soviet delegates, some of whom apparently accepted the
                    U.S. suggestion as a serious proposal.</p>
                <p>The Director of Central Intelligence called to the President’s attention the
                    concern that he and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_STC1">Streibert</persName> shared
                    regarding the effect of the Geneva Conference in the European satellites. He
                    said that “run-away” hope before the Conference had been followed by a let-down
                    in the Soviet-controlled satellites.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_STC1">Streibert</persName> called attention to the
                    informal Soviet statements alleging that there was no International Communist
                    Movement and that the Communist parties were indigenous. He said our propaganda
                    media would either have to reject these statements and continue attacks on the
                    International Communist Movement as a conspiracy directed from Moscow, or halt
                    this type of propaganda.</p>
                <p>The President said this situation should be given careful study. After
                    consideration of the study by the Secretary of State and by himself, any
                    necessary policy changes could be made.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The National Security Council:</hi>
                    <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>Noted and discussed an oral briefing on the subject by the Director of
                            Central Intelligence, with specific reference to political developments
                            in Indonesia and the Philippines; the status of Soviet military
                            assistance to the Chinese Communists; foreign reactions to the
                            President’s Geneva proposals for exchange of blueprints and mutual
                            aerial photography; and probably reactions in the satellites,
                            particularly East Germany, to the Geneva Conference.</item>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>Noted the President’s request that the Director of Central
                            Intelligence and the Director, U.S. Information Agency, prepare, on an
                            urgent basis for consideration by the Operations Coordinating Board, a
                            study on the psychological implications arising out of the Geneva
                            Conference as they affect U.S. information programs relating to the
                            European satellites and the International Communist Movement.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Note:</hi> The action in b above, as approved by the
                    President, subsequently transmitted to the Director of Central Intelligence, the
                    Director, U.S. Information Agency, and the Operations Coordinating Board.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">2. Report on the Four-Power Conference</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AD1">Dillon Anderson</persName> recalled to the
                    President and to the Secretary of State expressed willingness to report to the
                    Council on the Geneva Conference.</p>
                <p>The President said he believed he had already stated everything that would be
                    helpful or that had not already been heard by those present.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> began his report by
                    summarizing the Geneva developments relating to Germany and European security.
                    He said the Soviet leaders were not eager to talk about German unification. <pb
                        facs="0557" n="531" xml:id="pg_531"/> They revealed they are prepared to see
                    two sovereign German states continue indefinitely, both to be members along with
                    other states, of an European security arrangement. He said the Russians tried to
                    force the West to accept in the Directive<note n="2" xml:id="d259fn2">
                        <ref target="#d257">Document 257</ref>.</note> the following order: (1)
                    security, (2) disarmament, and (3) German unification. The Russians finally
                    agreed on the following wording in the Directive: “… taking account of the close
                    link between the reunification of Germany and the problem of European
                        security.”<note n="3" xml:id="d259fn3">Ellipsis in the source text.</note>
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> added that Soviet policy
                    positions will probably only become known at the October Foreign Ministers
                    meeting.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> said all members of the
                    U.S. Delegation had tried to get the Soviet leaders to state why they feared the
                    unification of Germany—did they fear the twelve German divisions now planned, or
                    did they fear <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> armies on a Soviet frontier?
                    The Russians were told that the West was prepared to reassure the Soviets if
                    they were fearful of German aggression or the revival of German militarism. Our
                    Delegation was unable to get any response from the Russians. Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> concluded that the Russians did not
                    really fear German rearmament or German military power, but were afraid that any
                    course of action leading to the eventual liquidation of the East German
                    Government would upset their satellite system. Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> cited present uneasiness in the
                    satellites as an indication that the liquidation of East Germany now would bring
                    about the situation which the Russians feared.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> said he would be greatly
                    surprised if the Soviets presented <persName corresp="#p_AK1"
                        >Adenauer</persName> with a serious offer of German unification during the
                    Chancellor’s trip to Moscow in September.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said the West must keep pressing the German unification issue. He
                    predicted, but did not wish to be held to his prediction, that we might get
                    unification in the next two years.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> said that prior to the
                    October meeting in Geneva, the West should agree on a concrete plan for German
                    unification, including precise provisions, dates, etc. This plan would be put on
                    the table in order to keep pressing the Russians to accept German unification.
                    At the same time, the West should present a European security plan containing
                    the general terms of a security treaty which would become effective only when a
                    united Germany had signed it. The Secretary recognized there would be major
                    difficulties within our own Government and with our allies in arriving at the
                    kind of specific proposals which he had in mind. He felt, however, that the West
                    should keep the initiative which it now has on the <pb facs="0558" n="532"
                        xml:id="pg_532"/> German unification issue, and make it as difficult as
                    possible for the Soviets to oppose unification.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> then reviewed the
                    developments in Geneva with regard to the control of armaments.</p>
                <p>The first problem, he said, arose over our desire to avoid reference in the
                    Directive to the Russian proposal to ban the bomb. Both the British and French
                    stated they were not in a position to oppose inclusion of the bomb prohibition.
                    Our Delegation, however, succeeded in keeping the bomb prohibition out without
                    public notice, which could have been awkward for the U.S., particularly if we
                    had been the only power among the four to have opposed its inclusion. Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> indicated that we now had time
                    to prepare public opinion so that our opposition to the prohibition of the use
                    of nuclear weapons cannot be used to attack us as being opposed to
                    disarmament.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> then referred to the
                    President’s proposal on exchange of blueprints and mutual aerial
                        reconnaissance.<note n="4" xml:id="d259fn4">See <ref target="#d221">Document
                            221</ref>.</note> He said the President convinced the Conference that
                    the proposal was not a mere propaganda move. The Secretary added that although
                    the proposal was dramatic, it was also a serious means of initiating a program
                    of disarmament.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> stated his belief that no
                    state would initiate nuclear war unless it was certain that it would not be
                    destroyed by a nuclear retaliatory blow. He said the President’s plan could
                    prevent nuclear war by making a surprise attack impossible. Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> stated that the number of reconnaissance
                    planes involved might be relatively few. He made this point in rebutting an
                    argument against the plan held by Senator <persName corresp="#p_KWF1"
                        >Knowland</persName>, who envisages hundreds of Soviet planes over the
                    United States dropping nuclear bombs simultaneously during their “peaceful”
                    reconnaissance.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> urged that we not follow
                    up on the President’s plan as if it were a propaganda stunt. He urged that it be
                    handled seriously, and suggested that a specific note, elaborating additional
                    details of the plan, be sent to the USSR. He indicated that we should not
                    belabor the Soviets for not accepting the plan at least for a month.</p>
                <p>Governor <persName corresp="#p_SHE1">Stassen</persName> interrupted to say that
                    his task force was already at work developing the plan and drafting an
                    appropriate note. He added that it should be made clear that the exchange of
                    nuclear weapons design was not involved in the President’s plan.</p>
                <p>The President commented that of course nuclear weapons designs were not involved.
                    He said the purpose of the plan was to end the possibility of massive surprise
                    attack. The President said <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                    <pb facs="0559" n="533" xml:id="pg_533"/> attacked the U.S. proposal on the
                    ground that it had nothing to do with the reduction of arms. The President said
                    he replied that the U.S. plan would ease international tensions and, in the
                    resulting improved political climate, reduction of arms.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> stated that the Soviets
                    may seriously want to reduce the economic burden of armaments in order to divert
                    Soviet resources to consumer goods.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName> stated that the essence
                    of any disarmament plan is inspection, adding that the President’s plan was a
                    practical beginning of inspection. In addition, the plan would reduce fear,
                    because states would know the location of potential enemy forces.</p>
                <p>The President noted that we had wanted to include in the Geneva Directive a
                    special directive to the UN to concentrate on the inspection problem but had
                    given in to Soviet objections in order to get the statement in the Directive
                    linking German unification to the problem of European security. The President
                    said he had told <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> that the
                    Soviet plan covering inspection at ports and airports was impractical because of
                    the large number of inspectors required. He said <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> replied that the Soviet plan aimed at revealing any
                    forward movement of national forces. The President pointed out that <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s reply indicated that the Russians
                    were preoccupied with land warfare and with the movement of large bodies of
                    armed men. He suggested that we should keep pushing the U.S. proposal, even to
                    the extent of accepting some of the Soviet inspection proposals if
                    necessary.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> stated that the magnitude
                    of the issues discussed at the Conference was best revealed by the fact that the
                    Soviet announcement of its intention to join the International Atomic Energy
                    Agency was all but forgotten. He pointed out that the Russians had decided to
                    join after nearly two years of efforts to persuade them to do so. The Soviet
                    decision is important, even though it was buried by other Geneva issues.
                    Although not publicly announced, the USSR has agreed to contribute to the
                    International Agency 50 kilograms of fissionable material as “an appropriate
                    amount”. The UK has agreed to contribute 20 kilograms, probably plutonium. The
                    U.S. first offered 200 kilograms, and later doubled this amount. Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> wondered whether any meaning
                    could be attached to the USSR contribution of 50 kilograms as an “appropriate”
                    amount, when they knew that the U.S. had contributed 200 kilograms.…</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> said the question of
                    developing contacts between East and West was dealt with so briefly that it was
                    not possible to discover how the Russians really felt about this issue. He said
                    the language in the Directive was drafted by the U.S. and accepted on the last
                    day of the meeting without debate, possibly as a Soviet gesture of good will to
                    overcome impressions of intransigeance created <pb facs="0560" n="534"
                        xml:id="pg_534"/> dining the debate earlier that afternoon. He said our
                    Delegation stressed the issue of free communications—information, books,
                    etc.—but that the Russians, in their personal conversations with members of our
                    Delegation, stressed the desirability of exchange of people.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> said the reference to
                    “peaceful trade” in the Directive was an attempt to deal with the trade problem
                    while avoiding the subject of restrictions on trade in strategic items.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> recalled that one of the
                    serious differences between the West and the USSR involved Soviet insistence
                    that further discussions on disarmament be handled by and controlled by the four
                    Foreign Ministers. He said the Russians finally gave in to Western insistence
                    that further discussions on disarmament be held within the UN framework.</p>
                <p>With reference to Soviet control of the European satellites, Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> said our Delegation made very clear to
                    the Russians that Soviet treatment of the satellites would be to us a barometer
                    indicating their real intentions. Our Delegation had numerous opportunities to
                    tell the Russians that good relations between the USSR and the U.S. could never
                    be achieved unless the Russians relaxed their control over the satellites.</p>
                <p>With regard to the issue of international Communism, Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> said the Russians maintained in their
                    private conversations that Communism was an internal matter in each state and
                    not internationally controlled, that there had been no meeting of the Cominform
                    for years, and that the West was beating a dead horse when it continued to
                    attack “international Communism”.</p>
                <p>In summary, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> said the
                    Geneva meeting was very much on the plus side for the West; that the USSR had
                    been put on the defensive. This result, he added, was not achieved without cost.
                    The cost was the breaking down or the blurring of the moral barrier between the
                    Soviet bloc and the free world. As a result, he said, we must re-think our basic
                    strategy in order to meet this new situation.</p>
                <p>As evidence of the different situation which we will face in the post-Geneva
                    period, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> referred to a
                    statement by Tito to the effect that because the danger of war had practically
                    disappeared, further U.S. military equipment was not essential to Yugoslavia, in
                    effect inviting the U.S. to halt shipment of equipment to Yugoslavia. Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> referred to the lessened sense
                    of danger of global war and the new impetus given to neutralism. The effect on
                    United States strategy would be that we would no longer be able to use the same
                    policies and expect to get the same results—that there would be less dependence
                    in other countries on U.S. military aid, that we could place less dependence on
                    alliances.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> urged that fundamental
                    review of our policies be made so that we can deal with foreign countries in
                    ways which <pb facs="0561" n="535" xml:id="pg_535"/> are responsive to the new
                    situation. He cited specifically our policy toward the satellites, Asia, and the
                    Middle East.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> concluded that the new
                    situation was not brought about solely by the Geneva meeting, and would have
                    taken place even if there had been no meeting. He added that we never wanted to
                    go to Geneva, but that the pressure of people of the world forced us to do.</p>
                <p>The President said he agreed with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1"
                        >Dulles</persName>’ conclusions but not with his premise. The President said
                    that Geneva was our recognition of the fact that a blurring of the distinction
                    between the USSR and the free world was taking place. The purpose of the Geneva
                    meeting was to correct the false picture of the U.S. which many people had come
                    to accept in the months preceding the meeting.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> said that this was
                    exactly what he had meant to convey.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The National Security Council:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Noted oral reports by the President and the Secretary of State on developments at
                    the recent Four-Power meeting, with particular reference to their relation to
                    national security policies.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of item 3, “Report on the <gloss target="#t_ICBM1"
                        >ICBM</gloss> Program”.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Bromley Smith</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Senior Member <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Special
                            Staff</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
