<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>310. Telegram From the Delegation at the Foreign Ministers Meetings to the to
                    the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d310</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">310</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-10-31T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-10-31T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="rechJJ62r5nmf4KiI" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Cultural exchanges</term>
                    <term ref="rec2SKz4RNoMDKY9k" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040584"
                        lcsh-match="exact">East-West trade</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="rec_world_war_ii" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="world-war-ii" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148273" lcsh-match="exact">World War II</term>
                    <term ref="recJFd5tAUUdqBj9H" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="east-west-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">East-West contacts</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="economic-sanctions" subject="embargo" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665" lcsh-match="exact">Embargoes on exports</term>
                    <term ref="recMpPwlFJwREQmrz" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="cultural-and-educational-exchanges" lcsh-match="no_match">Cultural relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-10-31T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-10-31T20:00:00-05:00" n="310"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d310">
                <head>310. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Delegation at the Foreign Ministers
                        Meetings</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d310fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 396.1–GE/11–155. Secret. Repeated to Moscow, London, Paris, Bonn, and
                        New York for the Mission at the United Nations. Passed to Defense. Copies of
                        the U.S. Delegation verbatim record of the fourth Foreign Ministers meeting,
                        which took place at 3 p.m., <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss>/Verb/4
                        Corrected, October 31, and the record of decisions, <gloss
                            target="#t_MFMDoc1">MFM/DOC</gloss>/RD/4, October 31, are <hi
                            rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, Conference Files: Lot 60 D 627, CF 571.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-11-01T02:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 1, 1955—2 a.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 107. Summary of discussion of item III
                    at Foreign Ministers Conference, October 31.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>After introductory remarks by Secretary, <persName corresp="#p_PA1"
                            >Pinay</persName> delivered opening speech in which he made following
                            points.<note n="2" xml:id="d310fn2">For text of <persName
                                corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName>’s statement, circulated as <gloss
                                target="#t_MFMDoc1">MFM/DOC</gloss>/17, see <hi rend="italic"
                                >Foreign Ministers Meeting</hi>, pp. 228–230, or <hi rend="italic"
                                >Cmd</hi>. 9633, pp. 135–136.</note>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Organization of peace not exclusively political or military
                                problem. Necessary to re-establish confidence to ensure peace.
                                France attaches great importance to re-establishment freer contacts
                                and easier exchanges. France has tried always to respect free
                                expression of thought and through constant comparison of ideas to
                                promote the objective formation of opinion. Such freedoms pushed to
                                such extent in France that occasionally they are condemned as
                                excessive; but Frenchmen prefer to run such risks to loss such
                                privileges.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>France has noted with satisfaction signs of Soviet interest in a
                                more liberal attitude toward cultural exchanges and a more objective
                                presentation of news. France favors development East-West trade.
                                However decrease in such trade is not a consequence of natural
                                developments but rather a consequence of Eastern Europe’s trade
                                policy. Trade sector covered by security controls too small to
                                encourage hope that their removal would result in substantial
                                increase in trade.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>While France favors broader contacts France does not hesitate to
                                refer to obstacles arising from different structure of the two
                                civilizations. Recognizing such obstacles may help in exploring the
                                means of overcoming them.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>France wants to know USSR as she is and insists that people of
                                USSR should know France as it really is. Cooperation can produce
                                fortunate results only if devoid of ulterior motives and if based on
                                mutual truthfulness.</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName> proposed that (1)
                                information centers in respective capitals be established, (2)
                                newspapers, books, and periodicals cross borders <pb facs="0680"
                                    n="654" xml:id="pg_654"/> more freely and (3) that French
                                correspondents in USSR have free access to normal sources of
                                information.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> emphasized that it is
                        through free passage of ideas and free intercourse of individuals that
                        countries gain proper appreciation both of common interest and differences
                        and learn to compose or at least adjust differences.<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d310fn3">For text of <persName corresp="#p_MH1"
                                >Macmillan</persName>’s statement, circulated as <gloss
                                target="#t_MFMDoc1">MFM/DOC</gloss>/21, see <hi rend="italic"
                                >Foreign Ministers Meeting</hi>, pp. 231–233, or <hi rend="italic"
                                >Cmd</hi>. 9633, pp. 137–139.</note>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Urged realism and emphasized that real and lasting value or
                                progress on item III will depend on progress made on first two
                                items. We must not be content with papering over cracks. We must try
                                to fill them.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>After referring to recent UK-USSR exchanges of delegations and the
                                establishment of Soviet Relations Committee of British Council, he
                                stressed that to multiply group visits without reducing obstacles to
                                free communications is to aim at the superficial and to ignore the
                                essential.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>Root cause of the artificiality of present contacts is systematic
                                regulation of opinion which is part of Soviet system. While we
                                understand historical reason for this, it is the free passage of
                                ideas which we regard as the clue to progress on this part of our
                                work. Problem remains so long as Soviet people presented with single
                                official view of our policies and actions, so long as our broadcasts
                                are jammed, so long as other means of conveying news and views so
                                limited as to be almost non-existent.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>Root cause of current low level of trade not our system of
                                strategic controls. These controls are result of a lack of
                                confidence and not one of its causes. Low level of trade caused by
                                Soviet Government’s own trade policies. Since World War II USSR’s
                                policy of self-sufficiency extended to include associates in eastern
                                Europe. UK nevertheless ready to consider sympathetically any
                                proposal likely to lead to mutual increase in peaceful trade.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> referred to summit
                            directive<note n="4" xml:id="d310fn4">
                            <ref target="#d257">Document 257</ref>.</note> and to August 5
                        resolution of Supreme Soviet on <persName corresp="#p_BNA1"
                            >Bulganin</persName> report of Geneva Conference,<note n="5"
                            xml:id="d310fn5">For texts of <persName corresp="#p_BNA1"
                                >Bulganin</persName>’s report to the Soviet Council of Ministers and
                            the Supreme Soviet resolution, August 5, see <hi rend="italic">Current
                                Digest</hi> of the Soviet press, vol. VII, No. 29, pp. 13–21. The
                            texts were also published in <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi>, August
                            5.</note> emphasizing “sovereign rights and non-interference in internal
                            affairs”.<note n="6" xml:id="d310fn6">For text of <persName
                                corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>’s statement, circulated as
                                <gloss target="#t_MFMDoc1">MFM/DOC</gloss>/24, see <hi rend="italic"
                                >Foreign Ministers Meeting</hi>, pp. 234–239, or <hi rend="italic"
                                >Cmd</hi>. 9633, pp. 139–143.</note> He then stressed need for
                        exchange of opinions as to scope and direction of work of experts committee.
                        Referring to reservations accompanying <persName corresp="#p_PA1"
                            >Pinay</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>
                        statements, he asserted that Soviet position based on interests Soviet
                        people (not on privileged social groups), on interests of defense of peace
                        and friendly relations among nations. <pb facs="0681" n="655"
                            xml:id="pg_655"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>In Soviet view development of East-West contacts would be
                                successful only if based on development of economic relations
                                between states. This inconceivable without normal development of
                                trade. Each country should be in position to buy and sell without
                                hindrance. Nevertheless a number of obstacles and artificially
                                created barriers impede normal development of trade. Discriminatory
                                measures generally known. These include embargoes on exports,
                                violation accepted practices in credit field and hindrance to free
                                navigation of merchant ships. They create distrust in relations
                                between countries and should be abandoned. Argument sometimes
                                advanced that Soviets have no goods for development of trade, does
                                not take into account fact that volume USSR external trade has
                                increased fourfold since prewar period.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Soviets believe that experts should first examine problem of
                                abolishing existing discriminatory measures hampering development
                                economic relations. In current atmosphere of relaxation these
                                barriers should be removed and most favored-nation principles should
                                be applied in trade and navigation.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>Returning to <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> point
                                on regulation of public opinion in USSR, <persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                                    >Molotov</persName> stated that all familiar with history USSR
                                can easily judge how freedom-loving Soviet peoples are and how
                                decisively they freed themselves from Czarist yoke. Work of Soviet
                                Government imbued with desire to raise welfare of people and provide
                                for people full freedom of development.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> then listed recent
                                Soviet actions promoting East-West contact. He mentioned
                                parliamentarians, exchanges of 20 delegations with UK, expansion
                                France-Soviet cultural ties, improvement in US-USSR cultural
                                relations and suggested that much has still to be done.</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>Speaking about the objectives which should guide work of the
                                experts, <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> summarized
                                main points of Soviet resolution on development of East-West
                                contacts which he later tabled. (Text cabled separately.)<note n="7"
                                    xml:id="d310fn7">For texts of <persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                                        >Molotov</persName>’s statement and the Soviet proposal,
                                    circulated as <gloss target="#t_MFMDoc1">MFM/DOC</gloss>/24 and
                                    18, respectively, see <hi rend="italic">Foreign Ministers
                                        Meeting</hi>, pp. 234–240, or <hi rend="italic">Cmd</hi>.
                                    9633, pp. 139–143 and 163. The text of the proposal was
                                    transmitted in <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 103 from
                                    Geneva, October 31. (Department of State, Conference Files: Lot
                                    60 D 627, CF 571)</note> In this summary he made point that
                                account taken of wishes re East-West contacts expressed by large
                                number Western businessmen, scientists, etc.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Full text <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> statement being
                        transmitted through <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss> channels.<note
                            n="8" xml:id="d310fn8">For text of <persName corresp="#p_DAW1"
                                >Dulles</persName>’ statement, circulated as <gloss
                                target="#t_MFMDoc1">MFM/DOC</gloss>/20, see <hi rend="italic"
                                >Foreign Ministers Meeting</hi>, pp. 240–245, or <hi rend="italic"
                                >Cmd</hi>. 9633, pp. 143–146.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Following completion speeches <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName> tabled
                    joint British-French-US memorandum (sent separately).<note n="9"
                        xml:id="d310fn9">For text of the tripartite proposal, circulated as <gloss
                            target="#t_MFMDoc1">MFM/DOC</gloss>/19 Rev. 1, see <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Ministers Meeting</hi>, pp. 245–248, or <hi rend="italic"
                            >Cmd</hi>. 9633, pp. 164–166. The text of the proposal was transmitted
                        in <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 102 from Geneva, October 31.
                        (Department of State, Conference Files: Lot 60 D 627, CF 571)</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> announced that <persName
                        corresp="#p_VSA1">Vinogradov</persName>, Soviet Ambassador to France, would
                    be Soviet expert on item III. <persName corresp="#p_BJ1">Baillou</persName>,
                    Deputy Director for Cultural Relations in Quai <pb facs="0682" n="656"
                        xml:id="pg_656"/> d’Orsay will represent France and Hohler to represent UK.
                    It was agreed that Committee of Experts would organize its own work, taking into
                    account the tabled memoranda; its deliberations would be secret and work would
                    begin eleven am Wednesday November 2. Experts would report back to the Foreign
                    Ministers by November 10.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
