<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-11-15T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-11-15T13:30:00-05:00" n="376" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d376">
                            <head>376. Memorandum of a Conversation, Palais des Nations, Geneva,
                                November 15, 1955, 7:30–8 p.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d376fn1">Source: Department of State, Conference Files:
                                    Lot 60 D 627, CF 586. Confidential.</note></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" from="1955-11-15T19:30:00+01:00" to="1955-11-15T20:00:00+01:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">November 15, 1955, 7:30
                                        p.m. to 8 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline></opener>
                            <p><gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_MC1">MC</gloss>/43</p>
                            <list type="subject">
                                <head>SUBJECT</head>
                                <item>Final Communiqué of Foreign Ministers Meeting</item>
                            </list>
                            <list type="participants">
                                <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">United States</hi>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>The Secretary</item>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName></item>
                                        <pb facs="0818" n="792" xml:id="pg_792"/>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MAD1">MacArthur</persName></item>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BRR1">Bowie</persName></item>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PH1">Phleger</persName></item>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCCW1">McCardle</persName></item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">France</hi>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>President <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName></item>
                                        <item>M. <persName corresp="#p_JMR1">Roland de
                                                Margerie</persName></item>
                                        <item>M. <persName corresp="#p_SJV1">Sauvagnargues</persName></item>
                                        <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JL1">Joxe</persName></item>
                                        <item>M. <persName>Andronikov</persName></item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">United Kingdom</hi>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName></item>
                                        <item>Sir <persName corresp="#p_KSIA1">Ivone
                                                Kirkpatrick</persName></item>
                                        <item>Sir <persName corresp="#p_HSGW1">Geoffrey
                                                Harrison</persName></item>
                                        <item>Lord <persName corresp="#p_HVS1">Hood</persName></item>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PITM1">Pink</persName></item>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPF1">Hancock</persName></item>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName>Boloshev</persName></item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">U.S.S.R.</hi>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName></item>
                                        <item>Marshal <persName>Sokolovsky</persName></item>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SAA1">Sobolev</persName></item>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_VSA1">Vinogradov</persName></item>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName>Pushkin</persName></item>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName>Troyanovsky</persName></item>
                                    </list></item>
                            </list>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>, as Chairman of
                                the Conference today, opened the restricted meeting called to
                                discuss the final Communiqué by suggesting that the form of the
                                Communiqué be first discussed. He suggested that it be short and
                                objective, and that if there were agreement on any of the three
                                Items of the Agenda, such a decision should be recorded in a
                                separate announcement on that Item. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> then suggested that the Communiqué should
                                point out that in compliance with the Directive of the Heads of
                                Government, the four Foreign Ministers had met and had had frank
                                discussions on all Items covered by the Directive. The Communiqué
                                would then go on to say that the four Ministers had agreed to report
                                the results of their work to their Heads of Government who had
                                appointed them to carry out this work. This would leave open the
                                question of how to deal with any future meeting of the four Foreign
                                Ministers. He concluded by saying that if his suggestion commended
                                itself to the other three Ministers, each could designate an adviser
                                to a working group which could get together to draft something along
                                these lines.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said perhaps Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> had a draft
                                which he could read to the Ministers.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> replied that he
                                thought it was better for the advisers to get together to produce a
                                draft.</p>
                            <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> said he
                                agreed with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>’s
                                suggestion as to the form and substance of the Communiqué, and his
                                own thought was that the question of a future meeting of the Foreign
                                Ministers be left for decision by the Heads of Government, since
                                obviously the Foreign Ministers could not decide that until the
                                Heads of Government had had a chance to study what had been done at
                                Geneva.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName> said that if the
                                Ministers were in general agreement on the form of a Communiqué,
                                they should get a text to serve as a basis for discussion.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said he had no
                                objection to this procedure, and agreed that the Communiqué should
                                be short and objective, to which <pb facs="0819" n="793" xml:id="pg_793"/> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName> commented that the shorter it was the more
                                objective it would be.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> replied that this
                                was “quite possible”.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> then said that the
                                idea that the Ministers should report to their Heads of Government
                                should evoke no objections. He said that with reference to future
                                meetings of the Foreign Ministers he would like to ask what
                                precisely was in mind as to the subject of such a meeting, as well
                                as the time and place.</p>
                            <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> commented
                                that a possible future meeting was a matter for the Heads of
                                Government to consider after they had had time to evaluate the
                                reports of their respective Foreign Ministers.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName> said he agreed with
                                what the Secretary said.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said he had simply
                                asked about a future meeting to obtain clarification, and suggested
                                that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> as the
                                author of the suggestion could perhaps indicate more clearly what he
                                had in mind.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> said he had in
                                mind that the Heads of Government would consider the reports of
                                their respective Foreign Ministers and that the question of a future
                                meeting of the Foreign Ministers, as well as the scope and character
                                of any discussions they might have, would be handled through
                                diplomatic channels.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said that Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> was correct in
                                that the Heads of Government had the right to be informed by their
                                respective Foreign Ministers. With respect to a future meeting of
                                the Foreign Ministers, public opinion would be much interested in
                                the kind of a meeting it was to be, as well as in its purposes and
                                objectives.</p>
                            <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> suggested
                                that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> draw up a
                                draft text of a Communiqué and circulate it tonight. Each Minister
                                could this evening designate an expert and then the experts could
                                form a drafting group to meet tomorrow morning.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said he would like
                                to look at a text, but he was interested in the substance of the
                                matter of the convening of another meeting of Foreign Ministers.</p>
                            <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> replied that
                                his idea was that the question of a further meeting, as well as its
                                scope and character, would be left for the Heads of Government to
                                decide in the light of their evaluation of their Ministers’ reports.
                                It could then be discussed through diplomatic channels. It was
                                possible the Heads of Government would decide not to have another
                                Conference because not much agreement had been reached at this one.
                                On the one hand, it would certainly be unwise to give the impression
                                that this Conference had resulted in what was tantamount to a break
                                in relations between the Soviet Union and the other Western powers.
                                On the other hand, it would not be wise to give the impression that
                                the four Foreign Ministers <pb facs="0820" n="794" xml:id="pg_794"/>
                                had reached agreement on matters of substance, since this was not
                                the case.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName> said that when the
                                Foreign Ministers reported back to their Heads of Government it was
                                up to the latter to decide what to do next, because if there was
                                another Conference it would be a prolongation of the Conference
                                which the Heads of Government had called.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> summarized again
                                the scope of the Communiqué he had suggested, stressing that it
                                would be short and objective and that it would conclude by saying
                                that the Ministers would report the results of their work to the
                                Heads of Government. He agreed to the suggestion that he draw up a
                                text which would be circulated tonight, and that the drafting group
                                could meet in the morning at ten o’clock.<note n="2" xml:id="d376fn2"><p>The draft circulated later that evening by
                                            <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>
                                        reads:</p>
                                    <p>“In compliance with the Directive issued by the four Heads of
                                        Government after their meeting in Geneva in July, the
                                        Foreign Ministers of France, the United Kingdom, the United
                                        States of America and the U.S.S.R. met in Geneva from
                                        October 27 to November 16.</p>
                                    <p>“The Foreign Ministers agreed to report the result of their
                                        discussions to their respective Heads of Government and to
                                        recommend that the future course of the discussions of the
                                        Foreign Ministers should be settled through diplomatic
                                        channels.” (Attachment to a note from the Secretary of the
                                        British Delegation to <persName corresp="#p_MAD1">MacArthur</persName>, November 15; <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, Central Files,
                                396.1–GE/11–1555)</p></note></p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said he did not
                                see why the idea of a future meeting should meet with objection, but
                                reserved his position because he was not clear about the character
                                of any future meeting.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> concluded by
                                saying that all the Ministers should reserve their positions with
                                respect to his draft until they had had a chance to receive and
                                study it.</p>
                            <p>The discussion then turned to tomorrow’s meeting, and it was agreed
                                that the communiqué drafting group would meet at 10:00; that the
                                Ministers would meet at 11:30 to complete discussion of Item I; that
                                they would adjourn by 1 p.m.; and that they would meet again for
                                final plenary session at 3 p.m. to conclude the Communiqué and to
                                make their final statements.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>