<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>58. Telegram From the Delegation at the Vienna Ambassadorial Conference to
                    the to the Delegation at the North Atlantic Council Ministerial Meeting, at
                    Paris</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d58</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">58</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-05-09T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-05-09T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-05-09T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-05-09T14:00:00-05:00" n="58"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d58">
                <head>58. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Delegation at the Vienna
                        Ambassadorial Conference</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Delegation at the
                        North Atlantic Council Ministerial Meeting, at Paris</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d58fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 396.1–VI/5–955. Secret; <gloss target="#t_niact1">Niact</gloss>.
                        Repeated to London, Bonn, and Washington. The source text is the copy sent
                        to Washington.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-05-09T20:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 9, 1955—8 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>404. Soviet <gloss target="#t_rep1">Rep</gloss> stood firmly on his position on
                    Art 35.<note n="2" xml:id="d58fn2">The sixth meeting was held from 2:30 to 6:40
                        p.m., May 9, with the same heads of delegation present as at previous
                        meetings. The official verbatim conference minutes and the U.S. Delegation
                        unofficial minutes of this session were transmitted as enclosures to
                        despatch 1302 from Vienna, May 11. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                        396.1–VI/5–1155) For a report on the restricted part of the sixth meeting,
                        see <ref target="#d59">
                            <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> French tabled new formulation of what was in essence my
                    proposal, text of which will be telegraphed separately.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d58fn3">Telegram 2665 from Vienna, May 9. (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Ibid.,</hi> 396.1–VI/5–955) The French proposal contained minor wording
                        changes and suggested that the economic clauses would be annexed to the
                        treaty with a preamble indicating that they were an implementing provision
                        of Article 35.</note>
                    <gloss target="#t_Sov1">Sov</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_rep1">Rep</gloss> refused despite our repeated urging to
                    produce any new reasons why he could not agree to some solution which would meet
                    our concern. I stated that if Aus and <gloss target="#t_Sov1">Sov</gloss>
                    Governments could conclude bilateral agreement covering points we had raised in
                    time for Foreign Ministers meeting we could agree that such agreement not be
                    annexed to the treaty provided the treaty itself contained appropriate reference
                    to it.</p>
                <pb facs="0120" n="94" xml:id="pg_94"/>
                <p>As there were indications he was merely probing strength of our position I took
                    firm line and was supported by Brit and French. I stated that while I would need
                    instructions to say so officially, I was convinced that Secy <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> would not come to the meeting we were
                    endeavoring to arrange for the end of this week unless we were sure that the
                    problem we had raised would be resolved.</p>
                <p>During the tea interval we endeavored to ascertain whether possibility of return
                    of oil fields to foreign control was the stumbling block. In order to prevent
                    Sovs from breaking story that we were blocking treaty over this issue, I told
                    Ilyichev that the Austs had made clear that they did not intend to transfer them
                    to US or anyone else and indicated that we might be able make this clear in some
                    form or another. He showed considerable interest in this idea and I believe that
                    if we are willing to attach to the treaty an annex along the following lines we
                    can obtain agreement our proposal: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Austria, for its part, undertakes not to pass to foreign ownership those
                            rights and properties indicated in lists 1 and 2 of Article 35 of the
                            State Treaty which are acquired thereby by the Soviet Union and which
                            will be transferred to Austria by the Soviet Union in accordance with
                            annex———.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Since we have already reached agreement in principle with the Austrians on this
                    point and the oil companies have accepted it, there would be some advantage in
                    making it public and avoiding the charge that our interest in getting back the
                    oil fields was the reason why agreement was delayed and was why we agreed to the
                    prohibitions against transfer to Germany of German assets in the Western
                    zones.</p>
                <p>It is of course possible that this may not be the principal problem for the
                    Russians and in the discussions Ilyichev has constantly indicated that important
                    point for them was that they had received these assets and could dispose of them
                    bilaterally without any interference from US.</p>
                <p>I made clear in the discussion today that our proceeding with arrangements for a
                    meeting the end of this week before agreement had been reached was due solely to
                    the shortness of time and should not be taken as an indication that we could
                    agree to abandon our position.</p>
                <p>In the event that we put forward this further concession and Ilyichev still
                    stands firm, request instructions as to position I should take. Would the
                    Secretary be prepared come to Vienna even though no agreement has been reached
                    on this point?</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
