<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1921-12-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1921-12-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="11" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d11">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A4a/162</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic"><persName type="from">Jonkheer van
                                        Karnebeek</persName>, of the Netherlands Delegation, to the
                                        <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1921-12-09"><hi rend="italic">December 9,
                                        1921</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: It was most
                                gratifying for me to be assured this afternoon of your readiness to
                                lend your valuable cooperation towards inserting into the general
                                arrangement for the Pacific a formal recognition of the territorial
                                    <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> which is also to benefit
                                countries who—like Holland—are no party to the Quadruple Agreement.
                                This is—as I had the honor to say to you—of great importance to my
                                country and I am anxious that the matter should there be rightly
                                understood from the outset. I believe to that end it would be
                                extremely useful if the prospect of the recognition referred to were
                                announced in the very statement you propose to make at the next
                                Plenary Session. Otherwise the impression might possibly at first
                                prevail that Holland is to be the only power with insular
                                possessions in the Far East whose territorial rights will find no
                                explicit recognition at the Washington Conference, an impression
                                which should be avoided.</p>
                            <pb facs="0150" n="30" xml:id="pg_30"/>
                            <p>While taking this opportunity, my dear Mr. Secretary, to convey to
                                you my congratulations on the success of your endeavors, I
                                remain</p>
                            <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Karnebeek</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>