<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-10-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-10-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="171" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d171">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">738.3915/229</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The High Commissioner in Haiti</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">J. H. Russell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Port au Prince</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-10-04"><hi rend="italic">October 4, 1922</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received October
                                    19.]</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 70</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my despatch No. 67 of
                                September 20th, 1922, relating to the Haitian-Dominican boundary
                                question, I have the honor to forward herewith copy and translation
                                of a note recently received from the Minister of Foreign
                                    Relations.<note n="72" xml:id="d171fn72">Not printed.</note></p>
                            <p>It appears to be a fact that the territory directly east of the
                                Pedernales River is and has for some time been occupied by Haitians.
                                The President informs me that the Moya map of the Dominican
                                Republic, which was adopted by the Dominican Congress and published
                                in 1905, shows this territory as Haitian, the boundary line running
                                well to the east of the Pedernales River, and not following the
                                river as it does on the United States Army Military Information map,
                                1907.</p>
                            <p>With the Military Occupation of the Dominican Republic, this question
                                became more or less disputed for the reason that taxes were levied
                                by the Military Government on the natives living in the section just
                                east of the Pedernales River, a coffee growing section.</p>
                            <p>President Borno informs me that there has never been any question
                                between the Dominican and Haitian Republics regarding this territory
                                until the <hi rend="italic">Status Quo</hi> line was defined by the
                                United States Government in 1912. Certainly the Moya map of 1905
                                bears out this contention.</p>
                            <p>I have informed the Haitian Government that this matter has been
                                referred to the Department of State.</p>
                            <p>In this connection, I desire again to point out to the Department the
                                advisability of establishing a border patrol under the Dominican
                                Receiver of Customs before the withdrawal of United States military
                                forces from the Dominican Republic.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">John H.
                                Russell</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>