<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>President Saavedra of Bolivia to President Harding</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1922v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d194</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">194</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1922-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1922-01-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-01-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="194"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d194">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">723.2515/843: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">President <persName type="from">Saavedra</persName> of Bolivia
                        to President <persName type="to">Harding</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation<note n="99" xml:id="d194fn99">File
                            translation revised.</note>]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">La Paz</hi>
                        </placeName>[, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-01-21">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 21</hi> (<hi rend="italic">?</hi>),
                            1922</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Animated by that spirit of high justice which belongs to the most conspicuous
                    representative of the free peoples of America, Your Excellency made known to the
                    Governments of Chile and Peru your wish to invite them to appoint their
                    delegates in Washington in order to bring to an end, under the moral influence
                    of the Government of the Union, the long-standing dispute between those
                    Republics in consequence of the War of the Pacific of 1879.</p>
                <p>Although the dispute in which the Republics of Peru and Chile are involved and to
                    the termination of which Your Excellency wishes efficaciously to contribute
                    seems to be confined to the disagreement over the nonfulfillment of the
                    so-called Treaty of Ancon, it cannot be overlooked that it concerns Bolivia, for
                    my country was indeed a victim of the conflict of the Pacific and there can be
                    no fair, no final solution until reparation is made for the loss of her maritime
                    territory. The pact of Ancón, having delivered to Chile the whole of the
                    southern coast of Peru, placed the conqueror <pb facs="0574" n="454"
                        xml:id="pg_454"/> in a position where he would not yield any part of the
                    Bolivian coast, so as not to break the continuity in his conquests toward the
                    north.</p>
                <p>My country’s insistent protests have been answered by the Republic of Chile
                    invoking the text of the treaty of October 20, 1904, by which Bolivia
                    transferred to it the sovereignty over her whole coast. But the treaty of 1904
                    was not a free spontaneous act. There is no people, no matter how unfortunate,
                    who will cripple its own sovereignty, who will of its own free will give up
                    intercourse with the other peoples of the civilized globe through the vehicle of
                    all human commerce, the ocean. In order to bring this about, the exertion of a
                    very powerful pressure, such as that exercised by the victor over the vanquished
                    who has been compelled to disrupt the essential attributes of his century-old
                    sovereignty, must necessarily be presumed. That is precisely what the pact of
                    1904 was, the outcome of a war unjust in origin and unequal in progress.</p>
                <p>A treaty of that nature merely attests an actual state or condition, not an
                    undisputed right or a freely accepted balance. And because Bolivian sovereignty
                    was injured and mutilated by the pact of 1904, immediately after its signature
                    my country raised the banner of vindication for its maritime dependencies
                    without which it cannot either live as an independent nation or work out its
                    destinies with dignity.</p>
                <p>Bolivia from her traditional respect for her international engagements would
                    claim nothing under these or like circumstances if that treaty under which Chile
                    shields her acquired rights represented, if not a relation of perfect justice,
                    at least a situation that my country could bear. But that treaty not only is
                    unjust because it cuts off a whole people from free connection with the ocean,
                    which that people had from the day it came into autonomous existence, but as an
                    enforced decision will forever be a source of uneasiness and unrest to the peace
                    of South America; for as long as Bolivia is not reinstated in the territory of
                    which she was despoiled, she will keep stirring the conscience of the world with
                    her demands that justice be done in her case. My country, Most Excellent Sir,
                    cannot possibly reconcile itself to living locked up within the walls of a
                    geographic jail forced upon it by the fortunes of war, when the principles of a
                    new law of nations has opened to all the peoples of the European continent born
                    under its protection, the doors to the ocean as an indispensable condition for
                    their existence, and when all the nations and the United States in particular
                    are earnestly advocating the reign of a policy of respect for the weak
                    peoples.</p>
                <p>And this is why I appeal at this moment to Your Excellency and ask you in the
                    name of the Bolivian people that in the hearing given to the dispute that Peru
                    and Chile wish to submit to you, you will <pb facs="0575" n="455"
                        xml:id="pg_455"/> listen to the claims of Bolivia and call my country so
                    that it may be considered as a constituent part in solving the case of the
                    Pacific. The Foreign Office of my country, in notes addressed to those at
                    Santiago and Lima with reference to the invitation extended by the Government of
                    Chile to that of Peru for a direct settlement, declared that no possible final
                    settlement of the lasting effects of the war of 1879 could be effected without
                    Bolivia’s being given an opportunity to be heard with regard to her invaded
                    rights. And so the attitude which it is my privilege to submit to Your
                    Excellency’s consideration is entirely consistent with the action taken again
                    and again by Bolivia for the purpose of having her very just claims attended
                    to.</p>
                <p>Therefore Your Excellency, representing a great people who are seeking solutions
                    of peace and justice for the world, will not forget that there is a nation in
                    need at this time when it may be possible to bring to a final solution the
                    dispute of the Pacific, and will entertain this petition which I present that
                    Bolivia may appoint a representative in Washington who will present the right
                    that stands on my country’s side in the exigencies of this international
                    dispute.</p>
                <p>I wish, on this occasion, to offer to Your Excellency the sentiments of my
                    highest and special consideration.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">B. Saavedra</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
