<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Secretary of State of a Conversation with the Permian
                    Ambassador ( (Pezet), ), June 7, 1922</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1922v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d220</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">220</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1922-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1922-06-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-06-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="220"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d220">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">723.2515/1333</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Secretary of State of a Conversation with
                        the Permian Ambassador</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Pezet</hi>), <hi
                        rend="italic">June 7, 1922</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1922-06-07">June 7, 1922</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>The Ambassador called on the Secretary at 1529 Eighteenth Street at 6.30 p.m.,
                    and said that the Peruvian Government thought that it had made a very fair
                    proposal for the arbitration of the Taena-Arica controversy; that Chile had made
                    a very unsatisfactory reply and that a deadlock had been reached; that it was
                    the understanding that the Ambassadors should respectively state their cases to
                    the Secretary. The Peruvian Ambassador had asked for an appointment because he
                    was leaving for New York, and he supposed the Chilean Ambassador would call on
                    the next day. The Ambassador left with the Secretary memoranda of what had taken
                        place,<note n="10" xml:id="d220fn10">Only one memorandum has been found in
                        Department files.</note> which are annexed. The Secretary made no comment,
                    saying that he did not desire to make any suggestion until he had heard from
                    both Governments and understood fully the entire situation.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Annex]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Statement by the Peruvian Delegation</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>In to-day’s session the Chilean Delegation declared that it did not accept
                        the Peruvian proposals—wherein arbitration is proposed to determine whether,
                        under present circumstances, a plebiscite should or should not be held, to
                        decide to whom possession of the provinces of Tacna and Arica should be
                        given, and under what conditions,—and proposed that the Government of the
                        United States, as arbitrator, should decide upon the third point alone of
                        the Peruvian proposition; that is to say, to decide upon the conditions for
                        the holding of the plebiscite.</p>
                    <p>The Peruvian Delegation, while accepting of course the choice of the
                        arbitrator, regrets that the Chilean Delegation should have given an
                        unfavourable reply to its conciliatory proposition, in which due regard was
                        given to the aspirations of both countries. The Peruvian Delegation
                        considered that the Chilean Delegation maintained a point of view which left
                        out of account all feelings of concord and justice, since its decision
                        implies the intention of overlooking present circumstances and also the
                        consequences of the actions of the Chilean authorities during the 28 years
                        which have elapsed since the date <pb facs="0590" n="470" xml:id="pg_470"/>
                        upon which the plebiscite should have taken place, as well as a disregard
                        for Peru’s right to demand that an impartial judge should examine the case
                        fully.</p>
                    <p>The Peruvian Delegation therefore, maintained in its entirety its proposals
                        as formulated on the 27th. of May.<note n="11" xml:id="d220fn11">See
                            paragraph 3 of the memorandum of June 15, 1922, from the Chilean
                            Embassy, <ref target="#pg_472">p. 472</ref>, and article 1 of the
                            supplementary act of July 20, 1922, <ref target="#pg_506">p.
                            506</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
