<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chargé in Peru ( (Sterling))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1922v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d259</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">259</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1922-02-06T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1922-02-06T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec6XfF2Oe1IjakB2" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="western-hemisphere" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Western Hemisphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-02-06T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-02-06T17:00:00-05:00" n="259"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d259">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">823.73 All America Cable Co/31: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chargé in Peru</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sterling</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="42" xml:id="d259fn42">The same, <hi rend="italic">mutatis
                            mutandis</hi>, to Colombia as no. 7 and to Ecuador as no. 1 (file nos.
                        821.73/26a, 822.73/1a).</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-02-06T17:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 6, 1922—5 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>12. [The first two paragraphs have been omitted since they are identical with
                    those of telegram number 3, February 4, to the Chargé in Argentina, <hi
                        rend="italic">supra.</hi>]</p>
                <p>On January 30th the following resolution was passed by the Board of Directors of
                    the All America Cables, Incorporated: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Whereas, the All America Cables, Incorporated, enjoys or claims certain
                            preferential or exclusive rights of entry, connection, or operation of
                            submarine cables in Colombia, Ecuador, and Peru; Whereas, the Western
                            Telegraph Company, Limited, enjoys or claims certain preferential or
                            exclusive rights of entry, connection, or operation of submarine cables
                            in the Argentine Republic, Brazil and Uruguay; Whereas, it has been
                            arranged that the All America Cables, Incorporated, and the Western
                            Telegraph Company, Limited, shall renounce all such preferential or
                            exclusive rights; now, therefore, <pb facs="0642" n="522"
                                xml:id="pg_522"/> be it resolved that the All America Cables,
                            Incorporated, agrees to renounce, waive, relinquish and surrender, in
                            favor of American and British cable companies only, any preferential or
                            exclusive rights of entry, connection, or operation of submarine cables
                            now enjoyed or claimed by it in Colombia, Ecuador and Peru, or elsewhere
                            in South America. However, the All America Cables, Incorporated, does
                            not give up its rights of entry, connection or operation of submarine
                            cables, but gives up only the preferential or exclusive features of such
                            rights in favor of American and British cable companies. Provided, that
                            this renunciation, waiver, relinquishment, and surrender shall become
                            effective upon the presentation to the Department of State of the United
                            States, in behalf of Western Telegraph Company, Limited, of the
                            corresponding resolution, renouncing, waiving and surrendering any
                            exclusive rights of a similar character which it enjoys or claims in the
                            Argentine Republic, Brazil and Uruguay, or elsewhere in South America,
                            and upon the acquiescence in the renunciation, waiver, relinquishment
                            and surrender of the All America Cables, Incorporated, by the
                            Governments of Colombia, Ecuador and Peru, and the acquiescence in the
                            renunciation, waiver, relinquishment and surrender of the Western
                            Telegraph Company, Limited, of the Governments of the Argentine
                            Republic, Brazil and Uruguay.</p>
                        <p>And be it further resolved, that a copy of this resolution shall be
                            transmitted to the Department of State at Washington and to the
                            Governments of Colombia, Ecuador and Peru.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>A corresponding resolution <hi rend="italic">mutatis mutandis</hi> was passed by
                    the Western Telegraph Company, Limited, on January 25th. The resolutions were
                    examined by the representatives of the Western Union, acting for the Western
                    Company, and of the All Americas, in the Department on January 31st, and
                    February 7th was fixed for the presentation of the resolutions to the South
                    American Governments concerned.</p>
                <p>The resolution of January 30th will be presented to the Peruvian Government by
                    the representative of the All America Company on the 7th, or as soon as possible
                    thereafter. You are requested to keep the Department promptly informed and
                    telegraph the text of the formal concurrence of Peru as soon as it is received
                    by you.</p>
                <p>The Department hopes that this solution of the controversy will commend itself to
                    the Peruvian Government. It is believed that in removing restrictive monopolies
                    the door will be opened to free and healthy competition and to the establishment
                    of additional cable facilities between North and South America and between the
                    countries of South America, reduction of rates, closer business relations,
                    increased press traffic, and freer exchange of ideas and bring closer together
                    the peoples of the Western Hemisphere.</p>
                <p>In waiving the exclusive or preferential features of its rights of entry,
                    connection, or operation of submarine cables in Peru, the All Americas does not
                    surrender the non-exclusive features of such <pb facs="0643" n="523"
                        xml:id="pg_523"/> rights. You should, therefore, satisfy yourself that the
                    acquiescence of the Peruvian Government will not adversely effect [<hi
                        rend="italic">affect</hi>] the interest of the All America Company in this
                    respect. You will readily understand that the Department’s effort throughout has
                    been to eliminate the monopolies enjoyed by the British Company so as to permit
                    American cable companies to extend their existing systems in South America.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hughes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
