<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-06-25T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-06-25T05:00:00-05:00" n="490" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d490">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/4493: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Schurman</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-06-25T18:00:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">June 25,
                                        1922—6 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received June 25—2:30
                                p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>285. Following telegram has been received June 24, 7 p.m. from Huston:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Urgent. June 23, 10 p.m. Sun appears to be willing to retire if
                                    allowed dignified exit. Hinted that if consular body would offer
                                    good offices might be acceptable. British consul general is
                                    willing in order to avoid further fighting. Sun awaiting arrival
                                    Northern Expeditionary Forces<note n="58" xml:id="d490fn58">The
                                        so-called “Punitive Expedition against the North”.</note>
                                    claims rank and file of the navy still loyal despite any
                                    agreement of naval officers with Chen, is still at Whampoa.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Situation as indicated in above telegram and in Huston’s previous
                            telegrams to the Department direct and to Legation does not seem to me
                            to justify, certainly it does not necessitate mediation or offer of good
                            offices by consular body. Mediation by foreigners might eliminate Sun
                            Yat-sen more speedily but it would not permanently settle the issue
                            which would inevitably return to plague the Chinese.</p>
                        <p>If Chen Chiung-ming himself cannot bring about Sun’s retirement the
                            Peking Government should grapple with the difficulty. Sun is the one
                            outstanding obstacle to re-unification which with disbandment of
                            superfluous troops is the cardinal policy of President Li Yuan-hung and
                            his Cabinet and supporters. That policy has gained great impetus and
                            outside events have favored its consummation during the last few weeks
                            without the Government’s doing anything. Now that nothing remains but
                            the elimination Sun Yat-sen, not victorious but defeated, it would seem
                            that the undertaking should be left to the Chinese Government if Chen
                            Chiung-ming cannot or will not accomplish it.</p>
                        <p>I venture to suggest also that foreign mediation will dignify and magnify
                            Sun Yat-sen and assure him of prestige in the future. Please
                            instruct.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Schurman</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>