<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-04-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="559" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d559">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/3803</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Group</gloss> to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                        York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-04-24"><hi rend="italic">April 24,
                                1922</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received April 25.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to your personal letter of April
                            13th to Mr. Lamont, which was received after he left for abroad, we are
                            very appreciative of the suggestions you make in connection with the
                            letter we prepared to be sent to the members of the American Group. We
                            have <pb facs="0886" n="766" xml:id="pg_766"/> incorporated your
                            suggestions in a new paragraph at the end of the letter, and enclose a
                            copy of the completed letter for your information and for the files of
                            the Department.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully,</p>
                        <closer><hi rend="smallcaps">J. P. Morgan</hi> &amp; Co.<lb/><hi rend="italic">For the American Group</hi></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Managing
                                        Committee</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Members of the
                                        American Group</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                            York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-04-24"><hi rend="italic">April 24,
                                        1922</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sirs</hi>: We have recently received
                                various inquiries from members of the American Group, and from other
                                sources, as to when it might be expected that the Consortium for the
                                assistance of China might begin functioning. Inquiry has also been
                                made as to whether, if the Chinese Government did not soon recognize
                                the Consortium, it would be wise to consider the dissolution of the
                                American Group. It is altogether likely that no such question has
                                arisen in the minds of your good selves, but in any event, for your
                                information, the Managing Committee has asked us to state to you
                                that it is of the clear opinion that the American Group should
                                continue intact, and with patience await the outcome of the
                                situation in China.</p>
                            <p>For your further confidential information, Secretary Hughes recently
                                expressed his personal opinion to one of the members of the Managing
                                Committee that any possible withdrawal from the Consortium by the
                                American Group at the present time would be a very serious matter,
                                as concerning the status of affairs in the Far East. The Secretary
                                expressed the earnest hope that the members of the American Group
                                would continue to have great patience and be prepared, when the time
                                came, to render their assistance along sound and legitimate lines to
                                furthering the objects of the Consortium, which were designed not
                                only for the maintenance of the principle of the Open Door in the
                                Far East, but also for the upholding of American prestige.</p>
                            <p>In forwarding to you this informal expression, the Managing Committee
                                suggests that we remind the members of the American Group that the
                                Consortium was formed originally at the instance of the Department
                                of State; that subsequent to the formation of the American Group
                                along lines laid down by the Department, the Department secured the
                                acquiescence of the Governments of Great Britain, France and Japan
                                to the establishment of a new consortium for the assistance of China
                                along broader lines than ever before. Thereafter, after considerable
                                difficulties, the Consortium was duly organized by banking groups
                                representative of the investment interests of the four countries
                                involved, and since that time the Consortium has been prepared <pb facs="0887" n="767" xml:id="pg_767"/> to render such service as
                                it could. Thus the organization of the new Consortium has been
                                peculiarly of American inception, and to its continuance through
                                reasonable conditions American good faith would seem to be
                                pledged.</p>
                            <p>The members of the American Group, we believe, clearly understood at
                                the time they were invited to participate in it, that while it was
                                expected the operations of the Group and of the Consortium would be
                                conducted not without profit, nevertheless the organization was
                                largely in the nature of a public service designed to substitute the
                                principle of international cooperation instead of competition on the
                                mainland of Asia. At that time the Managing Committee felt and still
                                feel that any break-up of the Consortium would at once lead to a
                                reversion of conditions in the Far East gravely detrimental to the
                                welfare of China, the re-establishment of the baneful spheres of
                                influence, and the undoing to a considerable extent of the
                                comprehensive work accomplished at the recent Washington
                                Conference.</p>
                            <p>The reason for the policies of our Government in China is to be found
                                in the conviction that, in the interests of the future economic
                                development of our own country, it is essential that there be
                                preserved equal opportunity for practical participation by Americans
                                in the financial and industrial development of China. The activity
                                of American bankers in this field is, therefore, not a matter of
                                mere academic concern, or the support of an abstract governmental
                                purpose, but is provision for a future stage in which they, jointly
                                with American manufacturers and merchants, will feel the need for
                                expansion in the potentially rich markets of China. It is hoped that
                                even a protracted unremunerative period of delay, before the
                                Consortium can begin active operation, will in the long run prove
                                amply justified by the ultimate benefits to the commercial and
                                financial interests of our own country.</p>
                            <p>We have no doubt that you will agree with us in all of the foregoing,
                                but this letter is simply addressed to you privately for the purpose
                                of covering the points brought out.</p>
                            <p>Yours very truly,</p>
                            <closer><hi rend="smallcaps">J. P. Morgan</hi> &amp; Co.<lb/><hi rend="italic">For the Managing Committee</hi></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>