<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in China ( (Schurman) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1922v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d564</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">564</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1922-05-31T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1922-05-31T08:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQJgxXbB2a4RsHo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00009290"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consortium</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-05-31T08:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-05-31T08:00:00-05:00" n="564"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d564">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/3846: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Schurman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-05-31T21:00:00+08:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 31, 1922—9 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[Received May 31—8:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>241. My telegram number 231, May 24, 1 p.m.<note n="20" xml:id="d564fn20">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_707">p. 707</ref>.</note>
                    Department’s telegram 130, May 25.<note n="21" xml:id="d564fn21">Not printed;
                        see Department’s telegram no. 150, June 17, <ref target="#pg_719">p.
                            719</ref>.</note> London gives British colleague discretion to act with
                    his three colleagues as suggested in identic telegram and also concurs in our
                    interpretation of consortium attitude. Alston<note n="22" xml:id="d564fn22">Sir
                        Beilby F. Alston, British Minister in China.</note> writes: “I gather that
                    Sir Charles Addis<note n="23" xml:id="d564fn23">Representative of British
                        banking group.</note> is not convinced that offer of financial [apparent
                    omission] is yet justified by the present prospect of stable government. Until
                    the situation becomes clearer my Government do not therefore consider that they
                    would feel justified in pressing the consortium to consider the question more or
                    less favorably.”</p>
                <p>Political situation has developed and become clearer since Addis’s visit to China
                    in consequence of military events North and South. All parties and leaders are
                    today advocating unification and ready to make concessions for the sake of it.
                    Reunion is the first plank in Wu Pei-fu’s<note n="24" xml:id="d564fn24"
                        >Inspector-General of Hupeh and Hunan.</note> platform and on May 15th Sun
                        Yat-sen’s<note n="25" xml:id="d564fn25">President of Canton
                        Government.</note> commissioner of Foreign Affairs said to Huston,<note
                        n="26" xml:id="d564fn26">Jay Calvin Huston, vice consul at Canton.</note>
                    “There was no reason why Dr. Sun and Wu Pei-fu should not come together in order
                    to reach an agreement concerning the unification of China.”</p>
                <p>Policy outlined Addis’s speech in New York March 28 is now obsolete. First, he
                    said that apart from arranging comprehensive funding loan consortium could do
                    nothing for Chinese Government until North and South China “are in the way of
                    composing their differences and have the will to unite.” That unexpected
                    condition of things has now arrived and the time is therefore propitious for
                    consortium action. Secondly, he said that the time has come for consortium to
                    negotiate independently with autonomous provinces or groups of them for
                    construction railways within their respective borders. But this proposal would
                    magnify provinces, obstruct and <pb facs="0891" n="771" xml:id="pg_771"/> retard
                    national sentiment now running so strongly in favor of unification. Furthermore
                    no central government would approve the bonds. Probably Addis had particularly
                    in mind desirability of completing and uniting Canton–Hankow line through
                    negotiations with Canton Government.</p>
                <p>The means approved by Wu Pei-fu and the political leaders generally with the
                    exception of the President, as well as by public opinion for carrying out
                    unification are the reconvocation of the old Parliament which Li Yuan-hung<note
                        n="27" xml:id="d564fn27">Resigned as President of Peking Government July 1,
                        1917.</note> dismissed in 1917 and the recognition of the continuance in
                    authority of the provisional constitution. This would necessarily eliminate
                    President Hsü<note n="28" xml:id="d564fn28">Hsu Shih-ch’ang, President, Peking
                        Government.</note> of which [<hi rend="italic">whom</hi>] all China is weary
                    and Wu Pei-fu is determined to get rid. Thirdly, it would rob the Canton
                    Government of its vital issues. In the speeches to which I listened in Canton by
                    Chen Chiung-ming,<note n="29" xml:id="d564fn29">Governor of Kwangtung; Commander
                        in Chief of Kwangtung troops; concurrent Minister of War in the Canton
                        Government.</note> Wu Ting-fang,<note n="30" xml:id="d564fn30">Minister of
                        Foreign Affairs, Canton Government.</note> Frank Lee<note n="31"
                        xml:id="d564fn31">Commissioner of Foreign Affairs, Canton Government.</note>
                    and others and the conversations I had with them, the burden of their criticism
                    and denunciation was always that the Peking Government was unconstitutional
                    …</p>
                <p>While the situation is hopeful reunion is not yet an actuality. The conditions
                    for it however have not been so favorable for years. The actual accomplishment
                    depends on political leadership. If the right men take hold of the problem
                    courageously they might possibly solve it unaided but the solution would be
                    facilitated and hastened by financial assistance from consortium.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Schurman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
