<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-04-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-04-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="626" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d626">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.003 C 73/7</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Chinese Minister</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Sze</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-04-25"><hi rend="italic">April 25,
                                1922</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Minister</hi>: In your communication of
                            April 13, 1922, receipt of which I have the honor to acknowledge, you
                            inquire on behalf of your Government whether it is agreeable to the
                            Government of the United States to have the meeting of the commission on
                            extraterritoriality provided for in a resolution adopted by the
                            Washington Conference on December 10 last, postponed until the fall of
                            1923.</p>
                        <p>In reply I beg to say that it would seem to be in the interest of all
                            concerned to have before the commission when it shall assemble, full
                            information regarding the codes of Chinese law, procedure and judicial
                            administration; and as your note states that the Chinese Government
                            cannot complete before that time the technical work of this character
                            which it desires to prepare for the use of the commission, the proposed
                            postponement of the meeting of the commission until <pb facs="0943" n="823" xml:id="pg_823"/> the fall of 1923 would be entirely
                            agreeable to this Government, if it be also acquiesced in by the other
                            powers.</p>
                        <p>I have, in conformity with what I understand to be your wish, informed
                            the American diplomatic officers to those powers, by cable,<note n="94" xml:id="d626fn94">Telegrams were sent, Apr. 25, to Belgium, France,
                                Great Britain, Italy, the Netherlands, Portugal, and Japan.</note>
                            of this reply and have instructed them to ascertain the views of the
                            governments to which they are respectively accredited.</p>
                        <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles E.
                            Hughes</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>