<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in China ( (Schurman) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1922v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d670</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">670</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1922-11-04T01:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1922-11-04T01:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-11-04T01:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-11-04T01:00:00-05:00" n="670"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d670">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">393.1111—Lundeen, Anton: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Schurman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-11-04T14:00:00+08:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 4, 1922—2 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[Received November 4—9:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>436. My 420, September [<hi rend="italic">October</hi>] 17, 4 p.m. and 434,
                    November 1, 10 [<hi rend="italic">11</hi>] a.m.<note n="33" xml:id="d670fn33"
                        >Latter not printed</note> October 26th and 27th talked several hours with
                    American wife of missionary Forsberg,<note n="34" xml:id="d670fn34">The Rev. C.
                        O. Forsberg, a Swedish missionary.</note> former resident of the United
                    States, captured with Lundeen, his fellow worker. I also read letters of two
                    missionaries to their wives up to September 18th. Following facts
                    established:</p>
                <p>Captors not ordinary robbers as they took no money and little of other property
                    though money was in sight. Believed to be former soldiers probably of late Honan
                    Tuchun Chosti [<hi rend="italic">Chao Ti?</hi>,] their object being to make
                    trouble for Wu Pei-fu. They demand as condition of releasing missionaries,
                    recognition of their band as unit of National Army.</p>
                <p>Missionaries report area traveled overrun by robbers and villages deserted.
                    Captors treat them as well as conditions permit, deliver to them food regularly
                    sent by wives who will also send warm clothes. Missionaries also preach gospel
                    to captors and appreciate opportunity.</p>
                <p>Wives apprehensive of prolonged captivity and in case of fighting exposure at the
                    front.</p>
                <p>Had full and frank conference on the subject with General Wu October 28th and
                    Christian General Feng 29th. They confirm Mrs. Forsberg’s diagnosis situation.
                    Both were hopeful early release. Unfortunately Presidential mandate 31st
                    appointed Feng Inspector General Army with command of metropolitan forces. His
                    successor, General Chang Fu-lai, not Christian. However, General Wu retains
                    supreme command in Honan, capture took place only 60 miles from his headquarters
                    and he is sincerely interested in release.</p>
                <p>Wu told me he expected release through negotiations and in a short time. Peking
                    Government had, contrary to his views, consented to incorporating captors as a
                    unit in National Army. He had finally acquiesced provided that they were sent
                    out of Honan. Feng also predicted release shortly through influence of leaders
                    he had captured.</p>
                <p>I have no doubt both generals are perfectly sincere, but I am not sure of their
                    power to accomplish speedy release. Wu September 18th promised French officer,
                    so French Minister told me yesterday, that in one month the two French engineers
                    on Lung-Hai Railway captured August 15th would be released but they are still
                    held. <pb facs="0986" n="866" xml:id="pg_866"/> Furthermore, British missionary
                    in Honan carried off October 30th. Seizure of foreigners by brigands or
                    insurgents as pawns in the contests of rival political and military groups is a
                    new development in China and it is impossible to foresee to what lengths the
                    insurgents may go. However, it is to the interest of the captors to keep the
                    missionaries alive. I will watch closely. Possibly Feng’s coming to Peking may
                    be helpful.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Schurman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
