<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-01-25T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-01-25T23:00:00-05:00" n="787" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d787">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/1266: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Schurman</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-01-26T12:00:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">January 26,
                                        1922—noon</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received January 27—6:47
                                a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>28. Your telegram 10, January 22, 3 p.m. My January 24, 4 p.m. Balfour’s
                            telegram to Alston arrived yesterday and delivered immediately. Alston
                            saw Minister of Foreign Affairs this morning. He presented case by
                            reading Balfour’s telegram with comments and he emphasized unexpectedly
                            good terms and contrasted consequences to China of acceptance or
                            rejection. Minister of Foreign Affairs said while he and also President
                            of the Republic were in favor of acceptance Chinese people would not be
                            satisfied with period so long as five years. Alston replied the
                            difference was nothing in an issue so vast and vital.</p>
                        <p>As soon as Alston left me I called up Foreign Office for earliest
                            possible appointment with Yen. He had Cabinet meeting this afternoon and
                            appointment was fixed at 5:30. I have just returned from this interview
                            after stopping to report to Alston.</p>
                        <p>Yen confirmed announcement President had yesterday granted Premier sick
                            leave for seven days and that Premier has gone to Tientsin. Yen added in
                            reply to my inquiry that he did not think <pb facs="1066" n="946" xml:id="pg_946"/> Premier would resume office. Yen is appointed
                            Acting Premier beginning tomorrow. He presided at Cabinet meeting today
                            as senior member. Recalling his conversation President’s tea I said his
                            appointment made [<hi rend="italic">as</hi>] Acting Premier would enable
                            him to settle the Shantung question in the best interests of China, that
                            he had an opportunity to render his country memorable service and that
                            it must be done now or never. He renewed inquiry if further concessions
                            could not be secured and I replied that it was absolutely impossible,
                            that present proposal was the very last. I added that proposal was
                            vastly better than any of us had ever imagined possible. Dr. Yen said
                            the terms were better than had been expected either by the President or
                                himself.<note n="24" xml:id="d787fn24">Sentence
                            paraphrased.</note></p>
                        <p>I inquired what the Cabinet had done about it. He took from his pocket a
                            paper which he said was the draft of instructions to be cabled to
                            Chinese delegates. First he read to me portions of it and then at my
                            request the whole. He explained that President and Cabinet as well as
                            himself had approved it but that he would not cable it till tomorrow as
                            he intended tonight to show it to some leaders members of an advisory
                            body. Nevertheless, he had, he said, yesterday telegraphed provinces
                            that he would be responsible for foreign policy.</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>Minister of Foreign Affairs’ draft of instructions was in Chinese
                            carefully written and so far as I could see without erasures. My guess
                            is that it was prepared yesterday and approved by the President and that
                            the Cabinet today adopted it without change.</p>
                        <p>I did not have to quote the authority of the President, authorized by
                            your telegram January 22, 3 p.m., though I meant doing so today if
                            prospects were unfavorable.</p>
                        <p>Minister of Foreign Affairs remarking that he would later ask me as a
                            favor to telegraph to the Secretary of State Shantung credentials
                            Chinese delegates to whom also he would telegraph them direct. Copy of
                            these credentials received by Legation subsequent to my visit of this
                            afternoon. I am cabling text separately.</p>
                        <p>Minister of Foreign Affairs said President Hsu and Cabinet as well as he
                            himself desire to [omission] the President and Secretary of State
                            sincere gratitude for their generous helpfulness.</p>
                        <p>But for the fact one does not know what a day may bring forth in China I
                            would add my own respectful congratulations.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Schurman</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>