<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-10-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-10-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="865" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d865">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">837.51/875</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Cuban Chargé</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Padró</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation<note n="53" xml:id="d865fn53">File translation revised.</note>]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-10-18"><hi rend="italic">October 18,
                                1922</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary</hi>: I have the honor to inform Your
                            Excellency, in compliance with instructions from my Government, that the
                            Cuban Congress has voted and the Honorable President has sanctioned a
                            law which was signed on October 9, 1922, countersigned by the Secretary
                            of Finance and published in the extra issue No. 16 of the <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette</hi> of the Republic of Cuba,—a copy
                            of same stamped with the seal of this Legation being sent herewith<note n="54" xml:id="d865fn54">Not found in Department files.</note>—, by
                            article 1 of which law the President of the Republic is authorized to
                            issue bonds for an exterior loan for an amount not to exceed fifty
                            million dollars ($50,000,000), payable in gold coins of the United
                            States of America of the present standard and fineness.</p>
                        <p>This loan is to be contracted pursuant to my Government’s program for the
                            solution of its economic difficulties, of which Your Excellency’s
                            Government is aware. In the law whereby it is authorized, all the
                            stipulations of article 59, paragraph 3, of the Constitution of Cuba
                            regarding loans, have been complied with, and the purposes to which the
                            proceeds of the bonds shall be exclusively applied are therein pointed
                            out.</p>
                        <p>While the Honorable President of the Republic is empowered by article 8
                            of this legislative measure to pledge as special guarantee for the
                            payment of the interest, expenses and amortization of the principal of
                            this debt, and to bind and engage to said end the proceeds of whatever
                            revenue and taxes at present in force he may deem necessary or
                            convenient and should these proceeds—although destined to the service of
                            other debts—reach such proportions as to allow their being applied to
                            the purposes above expressed, he has in mind to pledge as special
                            guarantee of this debt the surpluses of the special taxes connected with
                            the loan that is known as Speyer’s <pb facs="1165" n="1045" xml:id="pg_1045"/> thirty-five million dollar loan ($35,000,000)
                            estimated in the present Budget, (of which I send you herewith a copy
                            stamped with the seal of this Legation) at $1,655,000, excess taxes that
                            are now being collected and also the proceeds of the 6 percent tax on
                            banks and corporations, estimated in the present Budget at $3,500,000,
                            the collection of which is expected to increase. Both revenues are
                            estimated at $5,155,000, and the Speyer’s contract authorizes the
                            disposition of said surplus; therefore, supposing an amortization of
                            thirty years in equal yearly payments, and reckoning on an interest as
                            high as 6 percent, the annual sum that will be needed will not reach
                            $4,700,000, there being left an ample margin of a security that
                            guarantees still more the transaction that my Government desires to
                            carry out.</p>
                        <p>To the end of providing adequately for the current expenses of the Budget
                            and for making up the deficiency which in the ordinary revenues will
                            result when from them are deducted the taxes subject to the payment of
                            the public debt—the creation of which is authorized by the law to which
                            I here refer—a 1 percent tax on sales and on the exchange or transfer of
                            merchandise is created by article 10 of said law, its proceeds being
                            estimated at $15,000,000, which will not only cover said deficiency but
                            will go even much further, and, in anticipation of this, the President
                            is authorized by a transitory ruling of the law in question to reduce it
                            even to one-half percent, if, after the lapse of the time necessary to
                            ascertain the amount of its production, this amount should considerably
                            exceed the sums required for the object to which it is to be
                            applied.</p>
                        <p>As, on the other hand, the national expenses have been reduced by recent
                            successive readjustments to the annual sum of $54,852,102.11 authorized
                            by the present Budget, it is evident that the ordinary revenues of the
                            Government are more than sufficient for the payment of interest and the
                            final amortization of this public debt, after meeting the current
                            expenses of the Government.</p>
                        <p>That said revenues may be greater, if possible, than heretofore, the same
                            law establishes that the Cuban Government, starting from the present
                            fiscal year, may apply all the surplus of its revenues—after paying all
                            annual expenses and leaving in the Treasury a suitable balance for the
                            same purpose—to the amortization of its present debts in the order and
                            under the terms stated in paragraph 2, article 3, of the said law.</p>
                        <p>In view of these circumstances and prior to carrying out this operation
                            of credit that is projected with quite extraordinary guarantees in order
                            to insure its immediate success under the best possible conditions in
                            the money market, my Government desires to know if, in accordance with
                            the stipulations of article 2 of the Permanent Treaty of Relations
                            between Cuba and the United States <pb facs="1166" n="1046" xml:id="pg_1046"/> of America dated May 22, 1903, Your Excellency’s
                            Government has any objection to make with regard to this public
                            debt.</p>
                        <p>I take [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Arturo Padró</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>