<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-07-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-07-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="159" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d159">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">837.61351/4100</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Briggs</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 3848</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-07-17">July 17, 1943</date>.<lb/>[Received July
                                21.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my telephone
                            conversations with Mr. Scherer<note n="1" xml:id="d159fn1">George F.
                                Scherer of the Division of the American Republics.</note> on July 15
                            and 16, 1943 relative to the forthcoming sugar negotiations, I have the
                            honor to enclose for the confidential information of the Department a
                            copy of a memorandum<note n="99" xml:id="d159fn2">Not printed.</note> of
                            my conversation with Prime Minister Zaydín and Sr. López Castro on July
                            15, 1943. In this connection I also enclose a copy of my note<note n="99" xml:id="d159fn3">Not printed.</note> to the Minister of
                                State<note n="2" xml:id="d159fn4">Emeterio Santovenia, who succeeded
                                José Martínez-Viademonte on March 6, 1943.</note> informing him that
                            our Government is agreeable to beginning negotiations in Washington on
                            July 26 next.</p>
                        <p>The Department will note that during my conversation with the Ministers
                            they expressed themselves as optimistic that an agreement can be reached
                            at an early date (which the Cuban Government obviously much desires),
                            and that I raised as a possible obstacle to the speedy conclusion of an
                            agreement the difficulties encountered this year with the loading of
                            vessels at Cuban ports.</p>
                        <p>The Cuban argument against the sale of sugar on a delivered-aboard-vessel
                            basis I do not find in the least convincing, and I wish to recommend
                            that serious consideration be given to the desirability of making our
                            purchase on that basis.</p>
                        <p>There is no single item in the 1943 operations which has caused anything
                            approaching the difficulty experienced in endeavoring to expedite the
                            efficient handling of ships at Cuban ports. This subject <pb facs="0183" n="169" xml:id="pg_169"/> has been an almost daily matter of
                            discussion and argument between Ambassador Braden and me on the one
                            hand, and the Prime Minister, the Minister of Labor<note n="3" xml:id="d159fn5">José Suárez Rivas.</note> and Sr. López Castro on
                            the other. It has no less occupied the attention of our War Shipping
                            Administration representatives in Habana, with Cuban Labor Department
                            officials, the Cuban Maritime Commission, labor leaders, terminal
                            operators, et cetera. The favorable results obtained with respect to
                            movement of sugar have in my opinion been due largely to these constant
                            efforts on the part of the Embassy, of ten against very tenacious
                            opposition from the Cubans. Furthermore, Cuban shipping charges are
                            exceedingly high, and in my opinion Cuban port workers are by no means
                            ill paid. While admittedly they went through a difficult period in the
                            latter part of 1942 and early 1943, and while at certain ports (notably
                            Cienfuegos) the laborers have shown a thoroughly patriotic attitude, it
                            should not be forgotten that Cuban port workers received a subsidy
                            during their idle period, and that the picture of abnegation and
                            patriotic self-sacrifice painted by the two Cabinet Ministers appears to
                            me to be somewhat overdrawn.</p>
                        <p>I am not unmindful of the fact that the Embassy’s present suggestion was
                            considered during the last negotiations, and opposed by War Shipping
                            Administration on the grounds that it might interfere with agency
                            arrangements for the handling of vessels, an argument the validity of
                            which I consider at least debatable.</p>
                        <p>As to the Ministers’ assertions concerning the difficulties between
                            maritime labor and the sugar interests, terminal operators, the
                            Government, et cetera, which they argue would follow adoption of my
                            suggestion, I do not believe these statements are indicative of anything
                            more than reluctance to modify the business-as-usual arrangements under
                            which the Cuban sugar industry is trying to operate. Furthermore, if the
                            maritime labor situation is as explosive as Zaydín maintains, that
                            should in my opinion be all the more reason for our Government to avoid
                            becoming involved (as we have had to become involved incessantly during
                            the past six months) in that situation.</p>
                        <p>To my mind there is no valid reason why the Cuban Government should not
                            itself (if it does not desire to have the matter handled by the
                            Institute) establish a fund into which would be paid the amount paid by
                            us, representing the cost of handling and placing aboard ship, and I
                            perceive no valid reason why, at a time when we are apparently pre-pared
                            to commit ourselves to purchase many millions of dollars worth of Cuban
                            sugar, thereby supporting the economy of the entire country, we should
                            not do so on terms which should greatly minimize our operational
                            problem.</p>
                        <pb facs="0184" n="170" xml:id="pg_170"/>
                        <p>I hope therefore that the Department will give renewed consideration to
                            this suggestion, which I may add is endorsed by the Habana
                            representatives of War Shipping Administration.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Ellis O. Briggs</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>