<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-01-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-01-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="242" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d242">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">837.512/662</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The American Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Braden</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Cuban Minister of State</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Martínez</hi></persName>)<note n="30" xml:id="d242fn30">Copy transmitted to the Department by the
                                Ambassador in his despatch No. 2125 of February 4; received February
                                11.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 148</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-01-29">January 29, 1943</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to refer to Your
                            Excellency’s note No. 1125 of November 17, 1942<note n="31" xml:id="d242fn31">Not printed; this note was dated November 14 and
                                registered for dispatch on November 17.</note> in connection with
                            the general question of tax exemption to be accorded United States
                            undertakings <pb facs="0278" n="264" xml:id="pg_264"/> in Cuba. As
                            pointed out in my note No. 811 of November 2, 1942,<note n="32" xml:id="d242fn32">Not printed.</note> the Government of the United
                            States has consistently maintained that, in accordance with the
                            recognized principles of international law, foreign governments should
                            not be taxed on their personal property in the United States devoted to
                            governmental purposes and exemption from taxation has therefore been
                            granted to plant equipment and supplies used for the production of war
                            materials by private American companies whose operations are financed
                            and controlled by foreign governments. Your Excellency’s Government
                            would appear to have established a similar principle as evidenced by
                            communication No. 2967 of November 11, 1942<note n="32" xml:id="d242fn33">Not printed.</note> from His Excellency the
                            Minister of Hacienda, a copy of which was enclosed with Your
                            Excellency’s note No. 1125.</p>
                        <p>By agreement and decree of Your Excellency’s Government, the gross sales
                            tax of 2.65% has not been charged the United States Government projects
                            at San Antonio de los Baños, Metals Reserve Corporation stockpile
                            operations at Santiago de Cuba, and certain other similar projects. This
                            tax has, however, been collected on the project which is being carried
                            out by the Nicaro Nickel Company at Preston for the United States
                            Government. Funds for the acquisition and equipment of the plant at
                            Preston are being supplied by the United States Government and,
                            therefore, any Cuban taxes assessed and collected on this project must
                            be paid by the United States Government.</p>
                        <p>In view of the principles set forth in Your Excellency’s above-mentioned
                            correspondence and of the practice established in connection with other
                            United States Government projects in Cuba, I am sanguine that Your
                            Excellency’s Government will find it possible to exempt the Nicaro
                            Nickel Company development from the 2.65% gross sales tax, whether the
                            work is done by the Nicaro Nickel Company itself, by the Frederick Snare
                                Corporation,<note n="33" xml:id="d242fn34">An engineering and
                                construction firm with headquarters in New York City and wide
                                business interests in Latin America.</note> or by another contractor
                            or agency, since the tax falls ultimately on the United States
                            Government.</p>
                        <p>Please accept [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Spruille Braden</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>