<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Guatemala ( (Drew) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d310</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">310</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-03-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-03-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="recQFlapfZuYOQASo" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042795"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nationalization</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recF2jh59vGhjZ2KX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-03-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-03-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="310"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d310">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112A European War 1939/26961</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Guatemala</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Drew</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 3679</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Guatemala</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-03-09">March 9,
                            1943</date>.<lb/>[Received March 13.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the Department’s
                    instruction No. 1550 of February 17 and telegram No. 83 of February 20.<note
                        n="11" xml:id="d310fn11">Latter not printed</note> A preliminary reply was
                    contained in the Legation’s telegram No. 100 of March 4, 1943, 3 p.m.<note
                        n="12" xml:id="d310fn12">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department’s instruction referred to as well as other communications
                    addressed to the Legation indicated that no satisfactory permanent solution of
                    the problem presented by the disposition of coffee grown on Proclaimed List <hi
                        rend="italic">fincas</hi> can be reached until such time as the Guatemalan
                    Government formulates a plan for eliminating <pb facs="0363" n="349"
                        xml:id="pg_349"/> Axis interest in these properties. The Minister for
                    Foreign Affairs<note n="13" xml:id="d310fn13">Carlos Salazar.</note> has on
                    several occasions said quite definitely that the Government of Guatemala fully
                    realizes the danger of permitting such a large portion of the national economy
                    to fall into hands of any single nationality and that it is its firm intention
                    to effect the nationalization of enemy alien properties. Dr. Salazar stated that
                    he had given this matter serious study over a long period of time and as long
                    ago as October 1942 had submitted to President Ubico a plan which he had
                    prepared. He explained that only recently it had come to his attention that this
                    document had been lost in the President’s office but indicated that arrangements
                    will be made promptly to bring it to the President’s attention.</p>
                <p>Licenciado Salazar explained that his proposal was for the Government to take
                    over all enemy-owned property without, however, making direct compensation to
                    the owners. In order to conform to the Constitutional prohibition on
                    expropriation without compensation he proposed to set up against the German
                    Government a claim for direct and indirect damages arising out of the war which
                    would at least offset the actual value of the properties to be expropriated. He
                    said that it was his hope that Guatemala would have this problem settled before
                    the peace conference at the end of the war.</p>
                <p>From conversations with the Foreign Minister and other Guatemalan officials it is
                    my impression that the Government has not settled on any definite plan for the
                    actual operation and administration of such properties. Several officials have
                    expressed the opinion that the Government would not be competent to operate them
                    although no satisfactory alternate plan has been mentioned.</p>
                <p>It has been apparent from various conversations with the Foreign Minister that
                    the problem of the disposition of the CAPCO<note n="14" xml:id="d310fn14"
                        >Central American Plantations Corporation, organized under the laws of
                        Delaware. The Alien Property Custodian, acting in behalf of CAPCO, at this
                        time was negotiating a contract, signed April 19, 1943, with the Guatemalan
                        Government whereby all of the physical assets of the Corporation in
                        Guatemala consisting primarily of coffee plantations and their equipment
                        would be transferred to Guatemala. In return, Guatemala would assume certain
                        indebtedness of the Corporation and grant to CAPCO a 30–year right to
                        utilize one of the plantations for cinchona production. A majority of shares
                        of CAPCO common stock were owned at this time, directly or indirectly, by
                        nationals and residents of Germany.</note> properties, which, as the
                    Department is aware, is now in the process of negotiation, is closely involved
                    with the Government’s plan for nationalization of other enemy property. It is
                    apparently the Government’s view that it will be necessary to set up some
                    quasi-governmental agency to operate CAPCO properties with which the remaining
                    properties can be integrated.</p>
                <p>While there are reasonable expectations that the CAPCO problem will be settled in
                    the near future the Foreign Minister has indicated <pb facs="0364" n="350"
                        xml:id="pg_350"/> clearly that the major nationalization plan will require
                    considerable time to be placed in effect in view of the legal technicalities
                    involved in transferring land titles. In a recent conversation he informed me
                    that President Ubico had instructed him to take up with me the situation of the
                    Proclaimed List coffee, pointing out that the Government was concerned with the
                    revenue from the taxation involved as well as the continued operation by the
                    intervention system. I assured the Minister that the problem would receive our
                    sympathetic consideration and in response to his invitation I have informally
                    requested him to obtain detailed information with regard to the status of the
                    accounts of intervened <hi rend="italic">fincas.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is obvious that the proposed nationalization plan will be delayed for some
                    time and in the meanwhile it is anticipated that we will be subjected to
                    increasing pressure from the Government with regard to the disposition of
                    Proclaimed List coffee. According to figures collected by the Commercial Attaché
                    the production of coffee on non-Proclaimed List <hi rend="italic">fincas</hi>
                    during this crop year appears to be adequate to fill the present United States
                    import coffee quota assigned to Guatemala. The present quota against which
                    shipment can be made amounts to 784,000 quintales, after deducting the total
                    carry-over shipped to the United States and held in Guatemala from the previous
                    crop year amounting to 87,000 quintales. The current crop year is reliably
                    estimated to exceed previous crop years by approximately 10%. If the crop
                    estimates are borne out it therefore appears that no Proclaimed List coffee can
                    move within this year’s quota.</p>
                <p>As a stop-gap measure it has occurred to me that we might wish to suggest to the
                    Guatemalan Government the possibility of providing by decree for the
                    expropriation of all coffee and other products from Proclaimed List <hi
                        rend="italic">fincas</hi> until such time as adequate measures for their
                    nationalization can be carried out. In this way the Guatemalan Government would
                    obtain all income from the properties and the interest of the German owners in
                    current production would be eliminated. Such a proposal on our part might well
                    be accompanied by an offer to assist in arranging for the sale of 20% of the
                    global amount of Proclaimed List coffee outside of the quota to an appropriate
                    United States Government agency. By withholding action on our part on the
                    remaining 80% of Proclaimed List coffee the Guatemalan Government would
                    doubtless realize the necessity for expediting their consideration of the
                    nationalization program. From a conversation which I have had with the Minister
                    for Foreign Affairs I am inclined to believe that such a suggestion would be
                    favorably received.</p>
                <p>The situation as I visualize it may therefore be stated as follows: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The Guatemalan Government is determined to nationalize enemy alien
                            properties, although this program may be subject to protracted
                            delay.</item>
                        <pb facs="0365" n="351" xml:id="pg_351"/>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>No definite program will be adopted in any event untilthe current
                            CAPCO negotiations have been disposed of.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Present estimates are that non-Proclaimed List coffee will be ample to
                            fill Guatemala’s present United States coffee quota.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The Legation and the Department will be subject to constant pressure
                            for the disposal outside of the quota of Proclaimed List coffee.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                        <item>A temporary solution would be offered through immediate expropriation
                            by the Guatemalan Government of all products of proclaimed
                            coffee.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                        <item>An offer from the United States to facilitate the disposal of say 20%
                            of Proclaimed List coffee until adoption of a vesting procedure or
                            nationalization decree might offer a possible solution.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The Legation will forward to the Department figures on the accounts of the owners
                    of Proclaimed List <hi rend="italic">fincas</hi> which have been requested
                    through the Minister for Foreign Affairs as soon as received. In addition I hope
                    to have an opportunity during the current CAPCO negotiations to obtain further
                    clarification from the Foreign Minister of his views toward the Government
                    program for the nationalization of enemy-owned property.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gerald A. Drew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
