<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-11-09T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-11-09T19:00:00-05:00" n="387" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d387">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">812.5018/69: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Messersmith</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-11-09T20:00:00-04:00">November 9, 1943—8
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1932. The best information available to the Department regarding the corn
                            for Mexico is as follows:</p>
                        <p>From United States Government sources about 6,500 tons; from other
                            sources in the United States, about 18,000 tons (of which 12,000 tons is
                            said to have been acquired by Ambassador Del Rio although full details
                            are not available.) In addition, 1900 tons is available from Cuba of
                            which 500 have already been shipped with an additional 1500 tons
                            expected to be available shortly. The Department and other agencies at
                            Washington will continue to cooperate to expedite shipments.</p>
                        <p>With regard to Mexican oilseed meal exports, the interested agencies of
                            this Government would like to see these products move rapidly through
                            normal commercial channels at the price levels which were indicated to
                            you. You are authorized to furnish this information in writing to the
                            Minister of Agriculture as suggested in your telegram 1086, November 8,
                            4 p.m., and to add that quantities of oilseed meals shipped to the
                            United States under these conditions would be welcomed as evidence of
                            the Mexican Government’s cooperation provided that Mexico will similarly
                            accept all corn shipped from this country either through Government or
                            commercial channels.</p>
                        <p>Although the Department believes that the setting off of amounts of corn
                            furnished from the United States as against the amounts of oilseed meal
                            furnished by Mexico serves a useful purpose, it is the Department’s
                            position that an exact equivalence can not at all times be obtained, and
                            the Department believes it to the advantage of both Governments to
                            extend to each other a maximum of cooperation.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Stettinius</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>