<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Mexico ( (Messersmith) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d392</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">392</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-01-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-01-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recSj13D27GJZ1DiT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Allocations</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="recqDYPNCT9Q6HQio" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85039557"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Drilling</term>
                    <term ref="rec2WdyKi8trpNQBA" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Refinery</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="air-safety" subject="civil-aviation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aviation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-01-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-01-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="392"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d392">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">812.6363/7818</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Messersmith</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 6493</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-01-08">January 8,
                            1943</date>.<lb/>[Received January 13.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the Department’s
                    strictly confidential telegram No. 1650, of December 14, 11 a.m., 1942,<note
                        n="74" xml:id="d392fn74">
                        <ref target="frus1942v06#pg_536">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1942, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 536</ref>.</note> stating that it has
                    endorsed and approved the recommendations of the mission of oil experts on
                    repair and expansion equipment and materials needed by the oil refineries in
                    Mexico, and instructing me to convey certain information to the Mexican
                    Government.</p>
                <p>The Department’s telegram under reference states that there is being sent to me a
                    summarized portion of the oil mission’s report. The only such summary which I
                    have received is a copy of a memorandum dated December 3<note n="75"
                        xml:id="d392fn75">
                        <ref target="frus1942v06#pg_535">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p. 535</ref>.</note> prepared by Mr.
                    Thornburg for Secretary Hull, which reached me without any covering instruction,
                    but I assume from a telephone conversation with Mr. Duggan, of the Department,
                    that it is intended that the information contained in this memorandum may be
                    transmitted to the Mexican Government.</p>
                <p>In accord with the telegram under reference, I therefore left with the Minister
                    of Foreign Relations, Dr. Padilla, today, a memorandum dated January 8, of which
                    a copy is transmitted herewith. The Minister indicated that the Mexican
                    Government would immediately give <pb facs="0467" n="453" xml:id="pg_453"/>
                    consideration to the designation of appropriate representatives to proceed to
                    Washington to discuss with the Department of State the questions raised in the
                    memorandum.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>G. S. <hi rend="smallcaps">Messersmith</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Embassy</gloss> to the
                                <gloss type="to">Mexican Ministry for Foreign Affairs</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 928</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Some months ago, in accord with an arrangement between the Government of the
                        United Mexican States and that of the United States of America, a joint
                        mission of experts of the two Governments made a survey of the petroleum
                        situation in Mexico with particular reference to the needs of the petroleum
                        industry for materials for repairs and improvements. This mission has now
                        made its report to the Department of State and the Department has endorsed
                        and approved the recommendations of the mission on repair and expansion
                        equipment and materials which, in the opinion of the mission, are needed by
                        the oil refineries in Mexico. It has approved as well, in principle,
                        recommendations with respect to some new plant construction and facilities
                        to increase the facilities of existing plants. The necessary priority
                        allocations will be facilitated by the Government of the United States
                        towards this end.</p>
                    <p>The Department of State assumes that the Government of Mexico will discuss
                        with the Government of the United States the question of obtaining competent
                        American manufacturers, well-grounded in this particular category of work,
                        to design and erect the equipment, and if necessary to train the operators
                        thereof, in this manner assuring efficiency in the use of the machinery and
                        equipment for which priorities will be sought.</p>
                    <p>While the American Embassy in Mexico City has not received full information
                        concerning the contents of the report and recommendations of the petroleum
                        mission, it is in a position to convey the following information with
                        respect to the report, to the Government of the United Mexican States: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Producing operations currently require only maintenance and
                                operating materials, but an expanded program of exploration drilling
                                must be undertaken very soon to strengthen the fast-deteriorating
                                reserve position. This is a very considerable undertaking and one
                                which will require careful study.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The refineries further urgently require both maintenance and
                                expansion materials in order to continue current operations and to
                                fulfill the requirements which may arise out of the war emergency.
                                The most important steps in the refinery expansion program which
                                have been recommended by the mission are as follows: <pb facs="0468"
                                    n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/>
                                <list>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Additions to the Mexico City refinery to raise the crude
                                        distillation capacity from 18,000 barrels a day to 28,000
                                        barrels a day.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Installation of heavy oil cracking units of a certain
                                        capacity per day at the Mexico City refinery.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The mission notes that the Mexico City refinery operates on crude
                                transmitted by pipeline and states that the enlarged plant in Mexico
                                City will satisfy the full requirements of the central plateau,
                                which is at present partially served by products laboriously and
                                inefficiently carried by rail tank cars.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The expanded operations of the Mexico City refinery will yield
                                certain products and gases which furnish the raw feed for the
                                manufacture of high octane aviation gasoline. It is therefore
                                considered desirable to install additional equipment for processing
                                these raw materials into aviation gasoline in the amount of
                                approximately one thousand barrels a day.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The mission notes that the primary distillation and cracking
                                equipment could and should be obtained from shut-down refineries in
                                the United States but it emphasizes that the high octane
                                manufacturing facilities would have to be ordered from manufacturers
                                with a delivery schedule integrated into the over-all program of the
                                world-wide high octane gasoline plant construction.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>The mission notes that the Mexican Government should arrange for
                                the construction of these new units by established firms of United
                                States engineers and contractors, which should also be charged with
                                the operation of the expanded units until Mexican personnel can be
                                trained to take them over.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Department of State has instructed the Embassy of the United States in
                        Mexico City, in transmitting the above-summarized portions of the oil
                        mission’s report, to suggest that the appropriate Mexican authorities will
                        wish to review these and in due course send appropriate representatives to
                        the United States for discussions with the Department of State of their
                        proposed arrangements for the prosecution of the work and as regards
                        manufacturers and contractors.</p>
                    <p>While the discussions of the Mexican representatives will be with the
                        Department of State, it is noted that when it will be helpful to have the
                        aid of other United States Government agencies, the Department of State will
                        arrange therefor.</p>
                    <p>The Government of the United States expresses the desire that the
                        negotiations and conversations regarding the erection and management of the
                        proposed 100-octane gasoline plant under consideration be carried on between
                        Mexican and United States Government representatives. The interested
                        departments of the United States Government in Washington, with this in
                        mind, are already in consultation and will in the very near future be
                        prepared to consult with the appropriate Mexican officials.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-01-08">January 8,
                                1943</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
