<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-05-01T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-05-01T07:00:00-05:00" n="574" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d574">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">800.6363/1164: Airgram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Paraguay</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Montgomery</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Asunción</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-05-01T08:00:00-04:00">May 1, 1943—8:00
                                a.m.</date><lb/>[Received May 6—4 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>A–138. Reference Department’s airgram No. A–203, April 16, 1943, 6:30
                            p.m., in reply to Embassy’s despatch 702, January 12,<note n="55" xml:id="d574fn55">Latter not printed.</note> regarding sale of
                            petroleum products to Proclaimed List nationals.</p>
                        <p>Upon receipt of the Department’s airgram under reference an appointment
                            was made with the Minister of Agriculture, Commerce, and
                                Industries,<note n="56" xml:id="d574fn56">Francisco Esculies.</note>
                            under whose jurisdiction falls the rationing authority of petroleum
                            products which is practiced by the Direction General of Industries and
                            Commerce. The Minister as well as a representative of the Direction
                            General of Industry and Commerce were present at the conference.</p>
                        <p>The position of the Department was fully explained to the Paraguayan
                            authorities with emphasis upon the point that the provision of petroleum
                            products under the Pool system makes no allowance for the distribution
                            or sale of such products to persons or firms on the Proclaimed List of
                            Blocked Nationals. It was further suggested that if such sale or
                            distribution is continued it would be most difficult to justify the
                            allotments which have now been made on the basis of the essential needs
                            of the country’s economy. In view of the tenure <pb facs="0713" n="699" xml:id="pg_699"/> [<hi rend="italic">tenor</hi>] of the
                            conversations the authorities were also reminded that the identical
                            situation exists as regards the sale of any tires and tubes which, while
                            in theory are received from Brazil, are actually part of the stocks
                            owned by the United States Government.</p>
                        <p>The Paraguayan authorities did not dispute the position taken by the
                            United States Government, rather did they agree that it is just and
                            reasonable. It has been agreed that the automotive registrations of the
                            country, particularly for Asunción, will be checked against the
                            Proclaimed List and that any vehicles belonging to either a firm or a
                            person on the Proclaimed List of Blocked Nationals will be eliminated
                            and will be granted no ration of petroleum products and will not be
                            permitted to purchase tires or tubes. The Minister pointed out that
                            there is in the Paraguayan market a certain amount of bootleg gasoline,
                            and even tires, smuggled out of Argentina, and that at least for the
                            moment the local Government could do nothing to prevent this gasoline or
                            the tires being bought by listed firms provided they are willing to pay
                            the price. The Minister did by indirection, in reply to a question,
                            state that he is exploring the legal implications of cancelling the
                            operating permits of all automotive vehicles, both cars and trucks,
                            belonging to listed firms or individuals.</p>
                        <p>There is no doubt of the willingness of the Paraguayan authorities
                            consulted to fully meet the suggestions of the Department within the
                            limits of available powers. The check list of the automobiles and trucks
                            to be denied gasoline rations and the right to purchase tires has been
                            offered to the Embassy for examination. However it is believed that this
                            administrative process should be left entirely in the hand of the
                            Paraguayan authorities although the Embassy will not hesitate to follow
                            this matter through should any vehicles belonging to listed parties be
                            seen in circulation after a reasonable period of time has elapsed.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Montgomery</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>