<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-08-05T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-08-05T21:00:00-05:00" n="620" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d620">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">823.51/145: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Peru</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Norweb</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Lima</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-08-05T21:00:00-05:00">August 5, 1943—9
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received August 7—3:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1066. Reference Department’s telegram No. 881, August 5, 10 p.m. For the
                            Under Secretary. The subject has been discussed recently with the
                            President and the Finance Minister. Possibly the President’s radio
                            statement, reported in my despatch No. 7409 of July 20<note n="75" xml:id="d620fn75">Not printed.</note> and repeated in his annual
                            message to Congress, was a result. In paraphrase he said: “We have
                            totally cancelled many foreign obligations, no foreign loans have been
                            floated and the settlement of the foreign debt is under study depending
                            on the goodwill of our creditors to reach an honest and equitable
                            agreement. No part of the credit opened 3 years ago by the Export-Import
                            Bank for $25,000,000 has been used”.<note n="76" xml:id="d620fn76">See
                                    <ref target="frus1940v05#pg_1135"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1940, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp.
                                    1135</ref> ff.</note></p>
                        <p>On the basis of this statement, I recently requested that I be provided
                            with some offer for settlement to take with me on my contemplated trip
                            to Washington in September (see my letter to Mr. Bonsal dated August
                                2).<note n="75" xml:id="d620fn77">Not printed.</note> The President
                            informed me he would discuss the subject with the Finance Minister who
                            stated early this week that he is giving attention to the matter and
                            hopes to have something for me to present to Washington for discussion.
                            He also mentioned that the Council of Ministers had given him authority
                            immediately to effect complete payment of the entire postal debt without
                            further temporizing with partial payments in monthly or quarterly
                            installments. Although there is no budgetal provision for payment of the
                            postal debt he proposes to sell public works bonds in an amount
                            sufficient to effect the full payment.<note n="77" xml:id="d620fn78">In
                                despatch No. 7665, August 20, 1943, the Ambassador reported that the
                                Minister contemplated selling the bonds on the open market in
                                sufficient amount to cover the agreed postal debt to the United
                                States of $308,000 (811.71223/57).</note></p>
                        <p>Accordingly there seems to be some sound basis for belief that the
                            President and associated Peruvian authorities are giving serious thought
                            to the problem of regularizing the financial position of the Government.
                            Consequently strengthened by your telegram under <pb facs="0765" n="751" xml:id="pg_751"/> acknowledgment I shall be in a position with some
                            prospects of progress again to confer with the President on the question
                            of Peru’s financial obligations to the United States.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Norweb</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>