<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Under Secretary of State ( (Welles) ) to the Ambassador in Venezuela (
                    (Corrigan))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d698</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">698</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-04-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-04-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRAvRT7ZvyjvRU2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="recQFlapfZuYOQASo" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042795"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nationalization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-04-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-04-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="698"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d698">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112A European War 1939/29679</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Ambassador in Venezuela</hi> (<persName
                        type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Corrigan</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-04-17">April 17,
                            1943</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Ambassador</hi>: I have given the most careful
                    study to your letter of March 17 in which you refer to Dr. Parra Pérez’ request
                    regarding the railroad which runs between Caracas and Valencia. It is my
                    understanding that Dr. Parra Pérez has asked us to approve the purchase by the
                    Venezuela Government of this railroad even though free funds are paid to the
                    Germans who own a majority interest. As you know, I am anxious to resolve every
                    doubt in favor of granting any request made by Dr. Parra Pérez. In this case,
                    however, although all of us here in the Department feel that the nationalization
                    of this railroad and the elimination of its undesirable personnel would be
                    highly desirable, we cannot approve its acquisition on the terms proposed by Dr.
                    Parra Pérez.</p>
                <p>The difficulty is that the problem is not the narrow one of striking a balance
                    between the evil of leaving the railroad in Axis hands and the evil of supplying
                    foreign exchange to our enemies. Our approval of this transaction would, I
                    believe, constitute a violation of our commitments to hemispheric security. As a
                    signatory to the Rio and Washington Resolutions, this Government is pledged to
                    avoid transactions which will make free foreign exchange available to the
                    aggressor nations. Our approval in this case (with its implicit promise that
                    equipment necessary for the maintenance of the road would be furnished) and the
                    consequent increase of Axis resources, would not differ in essence from a direct
                    remittance of foreign exchange from the United States to Germany in clear
                    contravention of our Inter-American commitments.</p>
                <p>A second broad aspect of the problem is that our approval of the proposed
                    transaction would, I believe, undermine all attempts to secure effective
                    economic controls in Venezuela. As you know, the railroad is popularly known as
                    the “German railroad”; its present ownership and personnel are a threat to
                    Venezuelan and hemispheric <pb facs="0847" n="833" xml:id="pg_833"/> security;
                    it is a symbol, in a sense, of the kind of enterprise which the American
                    republics have declared to be inimical to their security, and have agreed to
                    purge of Axis influence. For these reasons, you and your staff have
                    energetically sought to bring about the sale of this railroad against blocked
                    funds, and in this effort, you have received the firm support of the Department.
                    For us to reverse our position at this point, and, in effect, to sanction action
                    by the Venezuelan Government which would permit the local agents of the railroad
                    to make foreign exchange available to the Axis, would, I am convinced,
                    irreparably prejudice the integrity of economic controls in Venezuela by
                    furnishing an undesirable precedent that could be exploited by Axis firms as a
                    reason for their being freed from any controls that now exist or may be
                    established.</p>
                <p>Finally, I cannot believe that the choice lies inescapably between leaving the
                    railroad in Axis hands and making free funds available to the German owners, for
                    I am confident that both evils can be avoided if the Venezuelan Government is
                    prepared to exercise its sovereign power in order to discharge its
                    Inter-American commitments.</p>
                <p>We have not been unmindful of the difficulties to which Dr. Parra Pérez makes
                    reference. Both in the Department’s instruction no. 1732 of February 23, and in
                    Mr. Acheson’s conversation with Dr. Escalante, the possibility of driving down
                    the valuation of the railroad in forced transfer proceedings by the use of the
                    Proclaimed List was suggested for the consideration of the Venezuelan
                    Government. I am enclosing for your information copies of the memorandum which
                    was handed by Mr. Acheson to Dr. Escalante,<note n="85" xml:id="d698fn85">Dated
                        March 2, <ref target="#pg_823">p. 823</ref>.</note> and the memorandum of
                    their conversation.<note n="86" xml:id="d698fn86">Not printed.</note> We
                    appreciate as well the problem raised by the nominal Spanish ownership. We have
                    faced that problem repeatedly in this country, and have never permitted formal
                    devices involving nationals of friendly countries, or even co-belligerent
                    countries, to prevent our taking whatever steps were required by our security
                    and the security of the hemisphere. Venezuela has pledged herself, through the
                    Rio and Washington Resolutions, to do no less.</p>
                <p>I realize that it is a matter of great delicacy and difficulty to reject this
                    request. However, I am confident that if you will present these considerations
                    again to Dr. Parra Pérez, he will understand the impossibility of our taking any
                    other course, and will appreciate as well the imperative necessity for
                    Venezuela’s taking appropriate measures against the railroad.</p>
                <p>Believe me, with kindest regards.</p>
                <p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sumner Welles</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
