<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-04-03T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-04-03T13:00:00-05:00" n="72" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d72">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">821.61/74: Airgram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Colombia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Lane</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Bogotá</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-04-03T13:00:00-05:00">April 3, 1943—1
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received April 9—noon.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>A–274. My telegram No. 572, March 31, 7 p.m.<note n="44" xml:id="d72fn44">Not printed.</note></p>
                        <p>President López<note n="45" xml:id="d72fn45">Alfonso López.</note> had
                            referred to the agricultural plan casually at a reception on March 27.
                            He had stated in a somewhat joking vein, although obviously serious
                            beneath, that now that the elections are over, the electorate is going
                            to demand of the Government some constructive progress within the
                            country, especially in the field of agriculture. He said he hoped
                            therefore that we would endeavor to assist him and his country. I
                            replied, in the same vein, to the effect that I did not wish to take
                            part in internal politics but that I would be glad to see what could be
                            done to help Colombia.</p>
                        <p>In view of the forewarning, I had with me the previous correspondence
                            when the President summoned me on March 31. I asked him whether he had
                            any concrete comments in addition to those made by his brother Miguel,
                            as reported in Embassy’s despatch No. 1390, January 13, 1943. The
                            President replied that he had some very concrete comments and proceeded
                            to give them to me: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>The people of Colombia consider, because Congress has authorized
                                    the issuance of sixty million pesos in economic defense bonds,
                                    that the Government is “overflowing” with money. Such is not the
                                    case. The following are the figures regarding the Government’s
                                    present financial obligations: <table cols="2" rows="9">
                                        <row>
                                            <cell role="num"><hi rend="italic">Pesos</hi></cell>
                                            <cell/>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell rend="padding-left: 4em" role="num">12,000,000</cell>
                                            <cell rendition="#hanging">1942 deficit</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell rend="padding-left: 4em" role="num">24,000,000</cell>
                                            <cell rendition="#hanging">1943 estimated deficit</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell rend="padding-left: 4em" role="num">5,000,000</cell>
                                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Debts to various Departments
                                                (State Governments)</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell rend="padding-left: 4em" role="num">2,000,000</cell>
                                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Grant to Instituto de
                                                Fomento</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell rend="padding-left: 4em" role="num">1,000,000</cell>
                                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Grant to Caja de
                                                Ahorros</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell rend="padding-left: 4em" role="num">10,000,000</cell>
                                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Public Works, including
                                                buildings and roads</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell rend="padding-left: 4em" rendition="#underline" role="num">6,000,000</cell>
                                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Miscellaneous
                                                appropriations</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell rend="padding-left: 4em" role="num">60,000,000</cell>
                                            <cell>Total</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table></p>
                                <pb facs="0086" n="72" xml:id="pg_72"/>
                                <p>There is always the danger that the estimated deficit for 1943 of
                                    24 million pesos may attain a higher figure, such as 36 million
                                    pesos, if conditions caused by the war continue at the present
                                    rate. The Government, therefore, finds itself in a financial
                                    situation which is critical and which it hopes the United States
                                    will find itself in a position to alleviate.</p>
                                <p>The Government has endeavored to avoid inflation through an
                                    increase of 35 percent of income taxes and a compulsory
                                    provision that 50 percent of the amount of income tax payments
                                    shall be invested in economic defense bonds.</p>
                                <p>Just as the President took the position in 1939, when a director
                                    of the Electric Light Company, that war was inevitable (against
                                    the advice of the other directors who tried to persuade him to
                                    buy machinery from Switzerland), now he takes the position
                                    publicly that the war will end within the next six or twelve
                                    months. If he did not take that position publicly, an economic
                                    and financial disaster might be expected in Colombia, due to the
                                    increasing critical situation of the Government because of lack
                                    of importations and consequent decreased revenue. The people of
                                    Colombia are in no mood to appreciate the seriousness of the
                                    situation. Instead of pulling together, they are indulging in
                                    luxurious, individualistic thought without regard for the
                                    morrow. In this Administration the President wishes to
                                    accomplish two things: (1) improvement in agriculture, and (2)
                                    road building. In the latter respect he contemplates the
                                    following highways: Medellín–Turbo; Medellín–Cartagena;
                                    Bogotá–Rio Hacha; Cali–Buenaventura; as well as lesser highways
                                    in the Putomayo.</p>
                                <p>The ten million dollar credit advanced by the Export-Import Bank
                                    to the Banco de la República in 1940 still has five years to
                                        run.<note n="46" xml:id="d72fn46">For correspondence
                                        concerning this loan, see <ref target="frus1940v05#pg_695"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1940,
                                            vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 695</ref>
                                        ff.</note> Of this sum, the Banco de la República still has
                                    a balance of eight million dollars on hand. It would be of the
                                    greatest help to the Colombian Government if the Export-Import
                                    Bank, at the request of the Department of State, would extend
                                    for a period of eight years as from now a credit of eight
                                    million dollars to the Government of Colombia, permitting the
                                    Banco de la República to transfer its balance to the credit of
                                    the Government. The Banco de la República can well afford to do
                                    this, having sufficient reserves, and the extension of this
                                    credit to the Government would enable the Government not only to
                                    proceed with the liquidation of some of its obligations but also
                                    to start constructive work on road-building.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>The President said that he would be extremely grateful to the Department
                            for any support which it could give to this situation which, he assured
                            me, he is not exaggerating in any respect.</p>
                        <p>In setting forth the President’s views as outlined above, the Department
                            may wish to review Annual Economic Review No. 10, dated January 7, 1943,
                            Report No. 160, dated March 16, 1943, and Report No. 185, dated March
                            29, 1943.<note n="47" xml:id="d72fn47">None printed.</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Lane</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>