<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-07T08:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-07T08:30:00-05:00" n="1087" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1087">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">891.2546/6–754: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in India</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_AGV1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Allen</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                            Delhi</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-07T19:00:00+05:30">June 7, 1954—7
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1784. For <persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Gerard Smith</persName>.
                                Gonsalves of <persName corresp="#p_BDSS1">Bhatnagar</persName>’s
                                office has sent Embassy for its advance information copy of note
                                which covering letter states is being sent Embassy by <gloss target="#t_MEA1">MEA</gloss> (Embassy telegram 1780 June 6).
                                Substantive part of <gloss target="#t_MEA1">MEA</gloss> note as
                                follows:</p>
                            <p>The Ministry of External Affairs has the honor to inform the Embassy
                                of the United States that the Government of India confirms the
                                memorandum of commitment with the following modifications: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>The Government of India accepts the proposal of the United
                                        States Government to substitute the phrase “at $2.20 per
                                        pound delivered at dock New York” for “$2.20 per pound
                                            <gloss target="#t_CIF1">c.i.f.</gloss> New York” in the
                                        third sentence of paragraph 5 of the memorandum.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>As the agreement mentioned in the memorandum will be
                                        entered into by the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>, the
                                        words “the Government of India” will replace the words “the
                                        Atomic Energy Commission” wherever they occur in clauses 2
                                        to 6 of the memorandum and other consequential modifications
                                        will be made.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>The consequential agreements shall contain a (“and” shall
                                        be used for “and” respectively) <hi rend="italic">“force
                                            majeure”</hi> clause.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>The following minor changes may be made in clause 4 of the
                                        memorandum: <list>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The words “make delivery of” may be replaced by
                                                the word “produce” in line 8.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The words “and the United States will purchase”
                                                may be added after the words “United States” in line
                                                11.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The words “is required” may be replaced by the
                                                words “is the steady commitment” in line 14.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The word “commitments” in line 15 may be
                                                omitted.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>The Government of India propose, if the Government of the United
                                States agree, to add the following sentence at the end of clause 4:
                                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“And except for such additional quantities not exceeding in
                                        the aggregate 100 tons which the Government of India may
                                        sell under arrangement to the governments of the countries
                                        referred to in clause 3.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>If this amendment is accepted, then the phrase “through no fault of
                                its own” in clause 6 must be deleted.</p>
                            <p>Subject to the above mentioned changes and observations, the
                                memorandum of commitment under reference is hereby confirmed as
                                accepted by the Government of India. If acceptable to the Embassy,
                                the Ministry proposes that the present note and the Embassy’s reply
                                    <pb facs="0709" n="1759" xml:id="pg_1759"/> constitute a
                                mutually agreed amendment to the memorandum of commitment of April
                                10, 1954.</p>
                            <p>Regarding the phrase <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> wishes add
                                at end of clause 4, covering letter of Gonsalves states: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“You will also note that a sentence has been added at the end
                                        of clause 4, of which Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> considers to be in keeping with the
                                        spirit of the agreement as envisaged by both parties. The
                                        memorandum is intended to provide for the purchase to and by
                                        the United States on all surplus thorium nitrate produced in
                                        India beyond the amounts required for commercial use in the
                                        countries mentioned in the memorandum up to the total amount
                                        therein mentioned. The purpose of the added sentence is to
                                        provide for the sale of a part of the surplus, not exceeding
                                        in the aggregate 100 tons, by the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> to the (<hi rend="italic">governments</hi>)
                                        of the countries mentioned in the memorandum. Such sales, if
                                        it takes place, will be undertaken with due safeguards.
                                        Since the intention of the United States was to absorb all
                                        the surplus, it will, if this contingency materializes, have
                                        to absorb less in the period up to the 30 September 1955,
                                        the total amount of 230 tons to the United States being made
                                        up by sales in the following period. Consequently, the
                                        phrase “through no fault of its own” in clause 6 has been
                                        omitted.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>As reported in <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 1780,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> stated <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> would not insist on this addition
                                to clause 4 if US has serious objection. He would be happier if no
                                complete rejection and would be content as reported to have
                                government-to-government exports in question limited to UK, France,
                                Italy, Norway, Sweden and Denmark. If US cannot accept either
                                proposal, please send Embassy plausible reason therefor.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_AGV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Allen</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>