<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-02-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-02-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="652" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d652">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">357.AB/2–1252</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Secretary of Defense</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_LRA1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Lovett</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-02-12">February 12,
                                        1952</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: The Department of
                                State has received a request from the Secretary General of the
                                United Nations for the assignment of twelve additional United States
                                officers for service with <pb facs="0138" n="1188" xml:id="pg_1188"/> the United Nations Military Observer Group in India–Pakistan.
                                Similar requests have been addressed by the Secretary General to the
                                other Governments which have provided observers for this
                                mission.</p>
                            <p>It is the purpose of this request to restore the strength of the
                                Observer Group to the level previously authorized. In the second
                                quarter of 1950, the Department of State approved a United Nations
                                proposal to increase the number of observers in India–Pakistan to
                                sixty, thirty of whom were to be detailed by the United States. The
                                Department of Defense concurred in this proposal and took steps to
                                raise the United States contingent to the total requested. However,
                                the Observer Group never reached the authorized level. In September
                                1950, there were forty-five observers in the field, twenty-three
                                from the United States. There are now approximately thirty-one
                                observers serving with this mission, seventeen from the United
                                States. (This latter figure does not include the two United States
                                Air Force officers on the crew of the aircraft assigned to this
                                mission.)</p>
                            <p>In view of the importance of maintaining and insuring the full
                                effectiveness of this Observer Group, the Department of State
                                strongly endorses the Secretary General’s recommendation that the
                                strength of the Group be increased. General Jacob L. Devers (United
                                States Army, Retired), who has served as military adviser to Dr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GDF1">Frank P. Graham</persName>, the
                                United Nations Representative for India–Pakistan, has expressed his
                                views in the enclosed communications<note n="1" xml:id="d652fn1">Letter from Devers to <persName>Andrew W. Cordier</persName>,
                                    Dec. 3, 1951; report prepared by Devers for <persName corresp="#p_GDF1">Graham</persName>, September 1951; neither
                                    printed.</note> as to the advisability of this increase. I would
                                appreciate it if you could give this matter your early and favorable
                                consideration.</p>
                            <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                            <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><persName corresp="#p_HJD1"><hi rend="smallcaps">John D.
                                            Hickerson</hi></persName><lb/><hi rend="italic">Assistant Secretary</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>