<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-08-14T05:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-08-14T05:30:00-05:00" n="782" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d782">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">690D.91/8–1453: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in India</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_AGV1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Allen</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d782fn1">This telegram was repeated for information to
                                    London and Karachi.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                            Delhi</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-08-14T16:00:00+05:30">August 14, 1953—4
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>315. Re <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 311, August
                                    13.<note n="2" xml:id="d782fn2"><p>In telegram 311 from New
                                        Delhi, Aug. 13, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AGV1">Allen</persName> reported in part as follows:</p>
                                    <p>“<persName corresp="#p_PSNR1">Pillai</persName> asked me to
                                        call today to discuss Kashmir. He repeated that he had no
                                        idea whatever that US Government had been interfering in
                                        Kashmir, and he had already spoken to information officer of
                                            <gloss target="#t_MEA1">MEA</gloss> requesting latter to
                                        do what he could to stop press allegations. He also said he
                                        would speak to Vishnu Sahay regarding latter’s ‘loose talk’
                                        as soon as <persName corresp="#p_SCASB1">Shah</persName>
                                        returns from Kashmir.” (690D.91/8–1353)</p></note>
                                <persName corresp="#p_PSNR1">Pillai</persName> also cited as basis
                                for allegations of American interference in Kashmir <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> article of July 5 stating that
                                consideration was being given to partition of Kashmir, with
                                independent status for Vale. Article added “it is rumored, without
                                official verification” that Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> supported solution of this nature. <persName corresp="#p_PSNR1">Pillai</persName> commented “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>, of course, never discussed
                                any such solution with Prime Minister. Trumbull’s article created
                                much resentment here.”</p>
                            <p>Information officer of <gloss target="#t_MEA1">MEA</gloss> recently
                                said “you Americans are responsible for reports of interference”
                                citing Trumbull’s article and <persName>Adlai Stevenson</persName>’s
                                article on India in <hi rend="italic">Look</hi> magazine Trumbull’s
                                basis.</p>
                            <p>It seems clear that both <persName corresp="#p_PSNR1">Pillai</persName> and <gloss target="#t_MEA1">MEA</gloss>
                                information officer were reflecting views of Prime Minister
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nehru</persName>. Meantime, <persName corresp="#p_RDS1">V. P. Radhakrishnan</persName> said yesterday
                                that neither he nor Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nehru</persName> has slightest evidence of American
                                interference in Kashmir. Answer to this seeming paradox is that
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nehru</persName> does not think US
                                Government has intervened officially but he believes private
                                American individuals, notably Stevenson, influenced <persName corresp="#p_ASM1">Abdullah</persName> and that US Government is
                                generally inclined to be pro-Pakistani on Kashmir issue.</p>
                            <p>False reports alleging that I have visited Kashmir are beginning to
                                backfire. Since fact that I have never been to Kashmir and have
                                never met any Kashmiri officials except brief handshake with
                                    <persName>Karan Singh</persName> at reception is well known in
                                official diplomatic and press circles in Delhi, and allegations of
                                my visits are beginning to be cited as proof that whole story of
                                American interference is based on either manufactured or flimsiest
                                evidence.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_AGV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Allen</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>