<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Pakistan ( (Hildreth) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v11p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d872</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">872</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-11-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-11-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001519"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="recQt10IdeXz66A6d" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="personnel-foreign-service"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005831"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign Service</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recAHt1IiF33Lofk6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028349"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Development program</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-11-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-11-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="872"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d872">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">689.90D/11–1954</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Pakistan</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HHA1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hildreth</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>No. 297</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Karachi</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-11-19">November 19,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>-Afghan Relations</item>
                </list>
                <p>The purpose of this despatch is to summarize the salient points developed in
                    several recent discussions which the Ambassador and members of the Embassy staff
                    have had in Karachi and in Kabul on the subject of Pakistan—Afghanistan
                    relations, and to offer certain comments for the Department’s consideration.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador and several members of the Embassy staff flew to Kabul with the
                    Air Attaché the weekend of November 5–7. While there, they talked at some length
                    with the American Ambassador and members of his staff, and with the staff of the
                    Pakistan Embassy in Kabul. (Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SCASB1"
                        >Shah</persName> was absent from his post.) The principal points which
                    emerged from these discussions may be summarized as follows: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Soviet efforts at penetration of Afghanistan are increasing in
                            pressure, and have already reached a point to cause us serious disquiet.
                            The Pakistanis are acutely conscious of this development and are seeking
                            all possible ways to check it. (The Embassy staff were impressed <pb
                                facs="0381" n="1431" xml:id="pg_1431"/> with the caliber of
                            Pakistani representation in Kabul; considering the relative scarcity of
                            trained skills in the Pakistan Foreign Service, they have obviously made
                            a considerable effort here. To a considerable extent, however, this has
                            been accomplished by means of recruitment from other than the normal
                            sources. Pakistan Embassy officials in Afghanistan expresed annoyance
                            that the people with “big names” in Pakistan wanted assignments in the
                            Western countries and were relucant to go to Afghanistan in spite of its
                            greater importance to Pakistan.)</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>A solution of the Pushtu question is the obvious prerequisite of
                            effective Pakistani moves to the above end. At present, such a solution
                            is nowhere in sight. Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_DSMK1"
                                >Daud</persName> is so emotionally involved in the issue, and his
                            personal prestige so bound up with it, that it would be unrealistic to
                            expect any change in the inflexible Afghan position so long as he
                            retains his dominant voice in Afghan policies.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Nevertheless, there is no fundamental anti-Pakistani feeling in the
                            country, and basic conditions are such as to make possible an
                            accommodation on the issue if <persName corresp="#p_DSMK1"
                                >Daud</persName> specifically, and the royal family generally should
                            change their attitude. In spite of the synthetically fabricated
                                anti-<gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> campaign in the press
                            (thought to be heavily subsidized by India) the people generally show
                            themselves friendly to Pakistan. In fact, there appears to be
                            considerable uneasiness with the Government policy of aligning itself
                            with India, whose internal and external policies can be considered as
                            anti-Moslem, and against Moslem Pakistan. It is difficult to assess the
                            strength or potential importance of this attitude, but it is a factor
                            which might become significant.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The motives of the Afghans in putting forward the Federation concept
                            last spring are not completely clear. At the moment, the idea is
                            quiescent, and it is best that it should remain so for the time being.
                            Signs that such a move was being seriously considered might be a signal
                            for the Soviets to move with vigor. Before this risk is run, Pakistan’s
                            military strength should be very substantially increased, and, if
                            possible, other deterrents developed in the area.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>As a practical matter, for the Pakistanis there seems to be no
                            feasible alternative at present to the policy they are following. This
                            policy is understood to include the following elements: <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Despite the constant Afghan provocation, to maintain a
                                    friendly attitude and a certain tolerance of the abuse which is
                                    their lot. (There are influential Pakistanis who reject this
                                    idea and have urged a campaign of retaliation, including the
                                    incitement of a jirgah or so. This policy threatened to win
                                    acceptance for a while last spring, according to Colonel
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SCASB1">Shah</persName>, but has lost
                                    ground in recent months.)</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>To try to persuade the Afghans to work with them in the
                                    removal of specific irritants in the relations of the two
                                    countries.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                <item>At the same time, to strengthen and consolidate their position
                                    in the tribal areas to the east of the Durand line, and to make
                                    a concentrated effort to improve the living conditions of the
                                    Pathans in this area. (This will be the most effective possible
                                    means of exerting pressure on the Afghans. At the same time,
                                    such an effort is needed to counter the demonstration which the
                                    Soviets are making among the peoples immediately to the north of
                                    Afghanistan of the material benefits which Communism
                                    brings.)</item>
                                <pb facs="0382" n="1432" xml:id="pg_1432"/>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                <item>It would be a most useful concrete measure if the <gloss
                                        target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>s could persuade the Afghanis to
                                    cooperate on at least one joint project of mutual benefit. Once
                                    the possibilities of fruitful cooperation had been demonstrated,
                                    it might be possible to extend the principle. (This
                                    recommendation had been made by Ambassador <persName
                                        corresp="#p_WA1">Ward</persName> both at the Ambassadorial
                                    Conference in Istanbul last May and during his subsequent visits
                                    to Washington.)<note n="1" xml:id="d872fn1">A conference of U.S.
                                        Chiefs of Mission in the Near East area was held at
                                        Istanbul, May 11–14, 1954. Ambassador <persName
                                            corresp="#p_WA1">Ward</persName> visited Washington for
                                        consultation and home leave from June 16 to July 2 and from
                                        Aug. 16 to 20. For documentation on the Chiefs of Mission
                                        conference, see <ref target="frus1952-54v09p1">volume
                                            IX</ref>.</note>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Given the realities of the situation in Afghanistan and the
                            limitations inescapably imposed on direct U.S. intervention there, the
                            conclusion seems clear that U.S. policy objectives in this general area
                            can be best served by a rapid strengthening of Pakistan. (Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_WA1">Ward</persName> concurred unreservedly on
                            this proposition.) We should encourage the <gloss target="#t_Pak1"
                                >Pak</gloss>s to follow the policy outlined in paragraph 5 above.
                            However, in encouraging “<hi rend="italic">c</hi>” we shall need to be
                            particularly discreet and avoid any overt involvement, since in the
                            present highly nervous state of the Afghan leaders this would be
                            interpreted as a hostile act and might impel them definitely into the
                            Soviet camp.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Following his return to Karachi, the Ambassador had talks on this general subject
                    with the Prime Minister and Colonel <persName corresp="#p_SCASB1"
                        >Shah</persName>, the Pakistani Ambassador to Afghanistan, who was in the
                    city on consultation, and Embassy officers discussed the matter with Secretary
                        <persName>Rahim</persName> of the Foreign Office. The following points were
                    developed in the course of these discussions: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The discussions just concluded betwen <gloss target="#t_Pak1"
                                >Pak</gloss> officials and the Afghan Foreign Minister, Prince
                                <persName corresp="#p_NSM1">Naim</persName>, showed the Foreign
                            Minister in a more conciliatory mood than previously, and the Pakistanis
                            were feeling somewhat encouraged.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>There had been no mention of Federation in these discussions, and the
                            idea was not active at this time.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>s think that the way to proceed
                            is to take up with the Afghans a series of specific problems: trade,
                            customs, etc. and settle these one by one.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>s are definitely interested in
                            the possibility of securing Afghan agreement to cooperate on some joint
                            project.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Embassy comment:</hi> So far as the Pakistan Government is
                    concerned, there is no doubt of the welcome which it would give to any proposals
                    of the United States Government designed to assist and facilitate <gloss
                        target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>-Afghan collaboration in the economic
                    development of the Pushtu area. (<gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 582,
                    November 4, 1954.)</p>
                <p>With the expanded development program in prospect for next year, and the
                    increased availability of counterpart funds, there should be opportunity for
                    accelerated development in the tribal areas within <gloss target="#t_Pak1"
                        >Pak</gloss> jurisdiction. The Embassy believes that in addition to the
                    objectives listed in 5<hi rend="italic">c</hi>, such developments might serve
                    specific U.S. security <pb facs="0383" n="1433" xml:id="pg_1433"/> interests in
                    the area, and that they should be discreetly examined. The Embassy concurs in
                    the judgment that the United States should not be openly involved in any such
                    developments, but considers that ways might be found to accomplish these
                    objectives through indirection.<note n="2" xml:id="d872fn2">Marginal comment by
                        an unknown author: “maybe but pretty risky”.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>For the Ambassador:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAB1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Alexander B. Daspit</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">First Secretary</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
