<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the. Deputy Director of the Office of International Materials
                    Policy ( (Armstrong) ) to J. Robert Fluker, Officer in Charge of Economic
                    Affairs, Office of South Asian Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v11p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d932</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">932</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-07-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-07-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec65d5a63ab10e2d2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Rubber</term>
                    <term ref="recPnftMNhM1QKAYO" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Stockpile</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-07-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-07-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="932"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d932">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">846E.2395/7–1552</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the. Deputy Director of the Office of
                        International Materials Policy</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_AWC1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Armstrong</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to <persName corresp="#p_FJR1" type="to">J.
                            Robert Fluker</persName>, Officer in Charge of Economic Affairs, Office
                        of South Asian Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-07-15">July 15,
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Rubber agreement with Ceylon.</item>
                </list>
                <p>This memorandum summarizes the points concerning the practicability of a rubber
                    agreement with Ceylon which were made at a meeting in your office on July
                    14.</p>
                <p>On June 30 the Government stopped buying rubber for current consumption by
                    industry. At present the Government is buying natural rubber only for the
                    stockpile.</p>
                <p>The General Services Administration now has under contract nearly enough rubber
                    to meet the minimum stockpile objective. Since some rubber remains to be
                    purchased, it theoretically would be possible for the Government to negotiate a
                    contract with Ceylon for a modest tonnage of stockpile rubber. However, those
                    officials in <gloss target="#t_GSA1">GSA</gloss> who are responsible for buying
                    rubber intend to maintain a maximum freedom of movement in purchasing the
                    remaining tonnage and have stated categorically that they no longer are
                    interested in signing a contract with any government for any tonnage of any kind
                    of rubber.</p>
                <p>If there were general agreement on the wisdom of such a course, the Department
                    could attempt by means of a high level approach to have the operating officials
                    overruled. <gloss target="#t_OMP1">OMP</gloss> believes that an attempt along
                    these lines would be unwise. It would be sure to irritate the operating
                    officials in <gloss target="#t_GSA1">GSA</gloss> who have been among the
                    Department’s strongest allies in interdepartmental rubber discussions. It might
                    fail, since no operating agency likes outside meddling in its affairs. In any
                    event, <gloss target="#t_GSA1">GSA</gloss> or Defense could not be approached on
                    the subject until full intradepartmental discussion had indicated that now was
                    the time and Ceylon was the issue over which to intervene. The whole operation
                    could hardly be concluded in time for the present series of meetings with the
                    Ceylonese.</p>
                <p>Conceivably an attempt may be made to justify a contract as a means of keeping
                    Ceylonese rubber away from communist China. The primary <pb facs="0475" n="1525"
                        xml:id="pg_1525"/> responsibility for initiating any such suggestion would
                    lie in <gloss target="#t_EDS1">EDS</gloss> rather than in <gloss
                        target="#t_OMP1">OMP</gloss>. It is only fair to state, however, that <gloss
                        target="#t_OMP1">OMP</gloss> perceives numerous pitfalls, not only for
                    rubber but for other commodities as well in any such scheme and would do its
                    best to secure recognition of these difficulties while an <gloss target="#t_E1"
                        >E</gloss> position was being formulated.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
