<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-09-19T00:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-09-19T00:30:00-05:00" n="945" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d945">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">493.46E9/9–1952: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Ceylon</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SJC1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Satterthwaite</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Colombo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-09-19T11:00:00+05:30">September 19, 1952—11
                                        a.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>124. Had first serious talk since my return with <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SDS2">Dudley Senanayake</persName> yesterday.
                                Said I had followed elections with interest and was of course
                                pleased with outcome. I had however been out touch with Ceylon
                                affairs during last six weeks my absence<note n="1" xml:id="d945fn1">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SJC1">Satterthwaite</persName>
                                    had taken home leave to the United States from late June to late
                                    August 1952.</note> and was therefore very disappointed learn on
                                arrival that our govts had reached no <pb facs="0492" n="1542" xml:id="pg_1542"/> agreement on rubber which was going to <gloss target="#t_Chi1">Chi</gloss> in ever increasing quantities and
                                that official Ceylon mission was now in <gloss target="#t_Chi1">Chi</gloss> one member of which had reportedly told press in
                                Singapore that Ceylon was ready sell its entire rubber crop to
                                    <gloss target="#t_Chi1">Chi</gloss>.</p>
                            <p><gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> at once protested mission
                                was authorized only investigate and report and had been sent in
                                reply to Chinese invitation only under dire political necessity of
                                exploring every offer rice. If possibility obtaining Chinese rice
                                were not explored and if present profitable sales rubber to <gloss target="#t_Chi1">Chi</gloss> were now shut off rice consumers
                                and rubber producers wld rise up and overthrow this govt.</p>
                            <p>I said I understood and sympathized with his difficulties in view
                                present econ crisis confronting Ceylon. I hoped however he realized
                                that any free country entering into the close relations with a
                                Commie country of kind so enthusiastically described in press
                                interviews by mission leader is in serious danger falling into
                                Commie clutches both politically and economically. I hoped he wld
                                also keep in mind reaction any such agreement wld have on US public
                                opinion. Our soldiers have been dying for over two years in defense
                                very objectives which he had advocated so successfully in his own
                                political campaign. He shld keep in mind also that rubber is
                                commodity most urgently needed by Commie China and was going
                                directly into its war machine. Moreover Ceylon’s ever increasing
                                commercial relations with <gloss target="#t_Chi1">Chi</gloss> were
                                being anxiously watched by Indonesia and Malaya who were observing
                                UN resolution.</p>
                            <p>It was unfortunate I continued he had not been present at talks
                                concerning rubber shipments I had had with his father and which
                                latter had had with his advisers. While his father felt very
                                strongly that Ceylon’s rubber shld be sold on free market he had
                                nevertheless mentioned several times to me his concern over moral
                                issue involved. He had also assured me his govt wld have nothing do
                                with rubber-rice barter deal reportedly offered <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> by Commie <gloss target="#t_Chi1">Chi</gloss> about year ago. To this <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> made curious reply that Food Min had told him
                                only reason this proposal was not accepted was because investigation
                                indicated <gloss target="#t_Chi1">Chi</gloss> actually had no rice
                                available.</p>
                            <p><gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> did however seem genuinely
                                concerned over failure our recent negots and said he had sent
                                    <persName>Goonetilleke</persName> to Wash because of importance
                                he attached to reaching agreement with US. Unfortunately assistance
                                we had offered Ceylon as compared with that being made other
                                countries in Asia made it politically impossible for him accept our
                                last proposal. He hoped we wld realize seriousness econ crisis
                                facing his govt re which he must face Parl next week. He concluded
                                by saying he wld like discuss situation at greater length with me
                                after this debate had been completed.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_SJC1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Satterthwaite</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>