<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-06-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-06-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="964" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d964">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.56346E/6–2753</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Ceylon</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SJC1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Satterthwaite</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi><lb/>No.
                                    774</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Colombo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-06-27">June 27, 1953</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <list type="references">
                                <head>Reference:</head>
                                <item>Department’s Instruction No. 15, May 28, 1953<note n="1" xml:id="d964fn1"><ref target="#d963"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi></ref>.</note></item>
                            </list>
                            <list type="subject">
                                <head>Subject:</head>
                                <item>Possibilities of Obtaining U.S. Military Rights in
                                    Ceylon</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>In the despatch under reference the Department requests my views on
                                behalf of the Department of Defense as to whether the political <pb facs="0524" n="1574" xml:id="pg_1574"/> situation in Ceylon
                                would permit the opening of negotiations for U.S. Military Rights
                                with the Government of Ceylon at this time, and if not, an estimate
                                as to when such negotiations could be initiated.</p>
                            <p>I have given the Department’s inquiry careful thought and have
                                reached the conclusion that, for reasons given below in greater
                                detail, the political situation is not at the present time favorable
                                for undertaking such negotiations. The reasons in brief for my views
                                are (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the present financial crisis which
                                the country is undergoing, which in turn has led (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) to growing fear on the part of the Government of being
                                overthrown by the parliamentary opposition which shows some signs of
                                cooperating and becoming more effective, (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)
                                fear on the part of the Government of the reaction of the Indian
                                Government to giving the United States such rights, and (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) the state of our own relations with Ceylon
                                as a result of Ceylon’s important trade in rubber with Communist
                                China.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Financial Crisis</hi></p>
                            <p>As has been reported the financial crisis in Ceylon has reached
                                rather serious proportions, primarily as a result of the excessive
                                food subsidies the Government has been paying. For more than a year
                                the Government has been selling rationed rice, which now costs it
                                between 85 and 90 Ceylon cents per measure, at a cost to the public
                                of 25 cents per measure. Originally this large subsidy was paid
                                mainly for political reasons and in order to assure the reelections
                                of the United National Party (<gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss>).
                                The Government felt at the time that it could afford to pay such a
                                large price. Although rubber prices had declined severely a very
                                unrealistic budget was, for purely political reasons, brought in
                                last year, since when with the decline of tea as well as rubber
                                prices the Government has been reducing its external assets at an
                                alarming rate.</p>
                            <p>The Government is now faced with the problem of reducing or
                                eliminating the food subsidy in order to survive economically and is
                                apparently about to face up to the issue in the budget which will be
                                presented about the middle of July. The <gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss> back-benchers, as well as some of the leaders of
                                the party themselves, are fearful of the effect this may have on
                                their political fortunes and there is as a result a distinct
                                possibility that a number of back-benchers may desert the party.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Growing Strength of the Opposition
                                    Parties</hi></p>
                            <p>The parliamentary opposition, made up mainly of the Marxist Communist
                                and Trotskyist (LSSP) Parties and the allegedly nonMarxist Freedom
                                Party, has taken full advantage of the Government’s financial and
                                political ineptitude and has had considerable success in turning
                                public opinion against the Government. Moreover the Communist Party
                                is apparently having some success in convincing the Trotskyists that
                                they should cooperate in forming a common <pb facs="0525" n="1575" xml:id="pg_1575"/> front. If this should happen and if the
                                Freedom Party, which often seems disposed to cooperate with the
                                Marxist Parties, should form a common front of the opposition, the
                                    <gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss> Government, in spite of now
                                having a substantial paper majority and four more years of political
                                life before the next elections have to be held, might possibly be
                                overthrown through the desertion of some of its present
                                supporters.</p>
                            <p>As the opposition is unanimous in proposing that Ceylon should leave
                                the Commonwealth, in favoring cooperation with Communist China and
                                the Soviet Union, and in condemning the present policy of the US
                                Government at every opportunity, the <persName corresp="#p_SDS2">Dudley Shenanayake</persName> Government would, in my opinion,
                                be very reluctant to undertake any negotiations which might tend to
                                strengthen the opposition. The Government would undoubtedly at this
                                time consider negotiations for United States military rights here to
                                be in this category.</p>
                            <p>As an indication of the real fear of some of the <gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss> leaders that the Government may be
                                overthrown, the Minister of Health, Major E. A. Nugawela, told me
                                only a few days ago that he was seriously thinking of getting out of
                                politics and asking to be appointed Ambassador in Washington. He
                                seems to feel that the intrigues of <persName corresp="#p_KSJL1">Sir
                                    John Kotelawala</persName>, Minister of Transport, to oust Lord
                                Soulbury as Governor General in order to fill that position himself,
                                coupled with the Government’s general ineptitude, may well be
                                ruinous to the Party. There seems moreover to be a growing feeling
                                that <persName corresp="#p_KSJL1">Sir John</persName> is secretly
                                doing everything possible to undermine the Prime Minister, his first
                                cousin. In brief, the political situation is very unsatisfactory
                                indeed.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Ceylon–Indian Relations</hi></p>
                            <p>The Department in the final paragraph of its Instruction of May 28
                                asks my views as to the probable effect on Ceylon–Indian relations
                                of the establishment of a United States military base in Ceylon. In
                                my telegram No. 84 of February 2, 1950,<note n="2" xml:id="d964fn2">The Ceylonese position reported in telegram 84 from Colombo is
                                    adequately summarized in this paragraph. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SJC1">Satterthwaite</persName> went on to state
                                    his belief that any attempt to pressure the Government of Ceylon
                                    into granting the United States any military concessions would
                                    be deeply resented by the Ceylonese people. He, therefore,
                                    supported the view, held by <persName corresp="#p_VSK1">Vaithianathan</persName>, that the United States attempt to
                                    satisfy its defense needs through cooperation with the British
                                    forces in Ceylon. (946E.20/2–250)</note> I reported the feeling
                                of <persName corresp="#p_VSK1">Sir Kanthiah
                                Vaithianathan</persName>, the influential Permanent Secretary of the
                                Ministry of Defence and External Affairs, on this subject. Referring
                                to the request we then had pending for permission to station a small
                                United States Naval unit within the existing British Naval
                                communications unit here, <persName corresp="#p_VSK1">Sir
                                    Kanthiah</persName> asked why the United States Navy could not
                                arrange to obtain the facilities it so badly needed through the
                                British forces already here. He said that there was a historical
                                pattern and necessity for the stationing of British forces in Ceylon
                                and that their presence here could therefore be explained by his
                                Government. <pb facs="0526" n="1576" xml:id="pg_1576"/> If, however,
                                Ceylon were to grant similar military privileges to the United
                                States, Ceylon was afraid that a great and powerful neighbor whom
                                she feared and distrusted, referring of course to India, would
                                insist on receiving similar privileges.</p>
                            <p>In spite of superficial indications to the contrary this inherent
                                fear of India still prevails here and will no doubt continue to do
                                so even if the present unsatisfactory relations between the two
                                countries over the question of the citizenship rights of persons of
                                Indian origin residing here should be settled. As an indication that
                                this fear of India is not unreasonable, high Indian military
                                personages are known to have told their friends in the Ceylon
                                Government that India is determined some day to get possession of
                                the great naval base at Trincomalee. Therefore the reaction of India
                                to the granting by Ceylon of military rights to the United States is
                                almost certain to be negative and should be a matter of some concern
                                to the United States Government in view of the predominant position
                                India holds in this area.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Sale of Ceylon Rubber to Communist
                                    China</hi></p>
                            <p>With reference to the unsatisfactory situation arising out of the
                                sale since October 1951 of substantial quantities of Ceylon rubber
                                to Communist China, I shall only comment briefly in view of the
                                Department’s current awareness of the implications of this
                                complicated and troublesome problem. I should, however, like to
                                refer to my telegram No. 497 of May 2, 1953,<note n="3" xml:id="d964fn3"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1571">p. 1571</ref>.</note> in which I point out
                                that it would in my view be unrealistic to expect Ceylon to break
                                its present rice-rubber contract with Communist China as long as it
                                continues to work so smoothly and so profitably. I also expressed
                                the opinion that any action which might lead to the termination of
                                the rice-rubber agreement in the near future would have to originate
                                outside of Ceylon, and mentioned in this connection the possibility
                                of a truce in Korea, which would presumably lead to the lifting of
                                the UN embargo with its resultant effect on rubber prices, and the
                                raising of the legal restrictions on trade with Communist China
                                imposed by the Battle Act.</p>
                            <p>The Embassy has of course made the opposition of the US Government to
                                this trade abundantly clear to the Ceylon Government. I am glad to
                                report that in addition to the rather powerful forces in Ceylon
                                always opposed to closer trade ties with China and favoring the
                                maintenance of Ceylon’s historical trade relations with the West,
                                there has recently been developing on the part of the powerful
                                Buddhist Priesthood, as reported in our OM of June 13, 1953,<note n="4" xml:id="d964fn4">Not found in Department of State
                                    files.</note> from the Public Affairs Officer, a realization
                                that Buddhism is not enjoying in Communist China the freedom which
                                many had believed. This favorable development has resulted in
                                vigorous public attacks on Communist <pb facs="0527" n="1577" xml:id="pg_1577"/> China at a large Buddhist meeting held at
                                Anuradhapura recently on the occasion of an important Buddhist
                                holiday.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Possibilities of Current
                                    Negotiations</hi></p>
                            <p>The Department’s despatch of May 28 states that the Department would
                                appreciate my views as to whether the Government of Ceylon might at
                                this time be willing to negotiate on the basis of the economic and
                                security benefits which would accrue to Ceylon as a result of the
                                establishment of United States facilities here. While such benefits
                                could indeed in more favorable circumstances play an important role
                                (many still remember the prosperous days of World War II when
                                British and American forces were stationed here), these
                                considerations would not alone in my opinion be sufficient to induce
                                the Government to enter into negotiations. Such benefits may well
                                have been in the mind of Sir <persName>Oliver
                                    Goonetilleke</persName>, Minister of Agriculture and Food, when
                                making his various suggestions for a formal defense agreement with
                                the United States and the stationing of small naval and air force
                                units here. As indicated in my Despatch 312, November 28, 1952,<note n="5" xml:id="d964fn5">See <ref target="#d963fn1">footnote 1,
                                            <hi rend="italic">supra</hi></ref>.</note> to which
                                reference is made in the Department’s Instruction under reference, I
                                am of the belief that Sir Oliver has been less than sincere in
                                making these proposals and has had in mind primarily the bargaining
                                strength which such suggestions might give to the Ceylon Government
                                in any controversy with the United States, and the favorable light
                                which he hoped Ceylon would be placed in as a result of such
                                suggestions in spite of its shipments of rubber to China.</p>
                            <p>It is my belief, in the light of the factors discussed above and in
                                spite of Sir Oliver’s suggestions, that we would have to offer both
                                economic and military benefits of a substantial character in order
                                to interest the Ceylon Government in our proposals, with the
                                emphasis on the former at the present time. As to the nature and the
                                amount of additional benefits which would have to be offered, I can
                                only say that the economic benefits would probably have to be
                                substantial in nature, as illustrated by the unreasonable feeling so
                                often expressed here that Ceylon should receive from us economic
                                assistance proportionate to that we give to India. This belief is
                                born out in part by Sir Oliver’s insistence during his mission to
                                Washington in July 1952 that the United States should agree to
                                advance a total of 50 million dollars during the next five
                                years.</p>
                            <p>If we are willing to offer both substantial economic and military aid
                                I think it is indeed possible that the Ceylon Government may, after
                                it has survived the present financial crisis (which I think it is
                                likely to do) be willing to consider granting us the right to
                                construct facilities for global communications which are so badly
                                needed by our Air Force <pb facs="0528" n="1578" xml:id="pg_1578"/>
                                and Army. There is some doubt, however, in spite of Sir
                                    <persName>Oliver Goonetilleke</persName>’s repeated suggestions
                                to the contrary, whether the Ceylon Government would be willing to
                                consider the establishment of a heavy bomber-staging base, unless we
                                are willing to offer a very substantial <hi rend="italic">quid pro
                                    quo</hi> indeed, primarily because of its fear of the reaction
                                the granting of such rights would cause in India.</p>
                            <p>It seems to me that the United States should not seriously enter into
                                a military program in Ceylon of large proportions unless and until
                                it is willing to take over from the British if need be the
                                responsibilities of the defense of the Indian Ocean and to face the
                                probable hostility of the Indian Government in doing so. I would
                                recommend that we limit our target for the present to global
                                communications facilities, and, if we succeed in obtaining these, we
                                could then decide whether to make a proposal for a heavy
                                bomber-staging base.</p>
                            <p>In the meantime we should, I feel, strongly support the military
                                position here of the British, whose base rights are rather
                                precarious. In fact their legal rights to their bases at Trincomalee
                                and Negombo are so uncertain that the continued use by the British
                                of these bases could possibly be lost if the present Government here
                                were overthrown at a time when a weak Government was in power in
                                England. Therefore it is in our best interest, it seems to me, to
                                continue to cooperate fully with the British in this area and to
                                encourage them to take the lead as far as possible, while at the
                                same time insisting that at all costs they maintain their military
                                rights here.</p>
                            <p>It may be of interest to report that I have discussed a number of
                                these questions during the past few months with <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Admiral Radford</persName>, General
                                Vandenberg and Vice Admiral Wright during visits they have made
                                here. I have shown them (except General Vandenberg who was here too
                                short a time) a number of the pertinent documents, including the
                                letter dated December 12, 1951, from the Acting Secretary of Defense
                                to the Secretary of State setting forth the position of the former
                                at that time with reference to military rights in Ceylon.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi></p>
                            <p>In conclusion I repeat that I do not feel that the political
                                situation in Ceylon at the present is such as to justify the opening
                                of negotiations for military rights here. I venture to make the
                                suggestion therefore that the question be reconsidered within a few
                                months, at which time my successor here may be able to give a more
                                optimistic view of the prospects of success.<note n="6" xml:id="d964fn6">In a letter to Assistant Secretary of Defense
                                        <persName corresp="#p_NFC1">Frank C. Nash</persName>, July
                                    28, 1953, in which a copy of this despatch was enclosed, Deputy
                                    Under Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_MHF1">H. Freeman
                                        Matthews</persName> wrote that the Department of State
                                    concurred in <persName corresp="#p_SJC1">Satterthwaite</persName>’s recommendation that negotiations
                                    for U.S. military rights in Ceylon be postponed
                                    (711.5346E/6–2753).</note></p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_SJC1"><hi rend="smallcaps">J. C.
                                            Satterthwaite</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>