<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-05-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="15" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d15">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.711/31a</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                President <persName type="to">Wilson</persName>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-05-05">
                                    <hi rend="italic">May 5, 1917</hi>
                                </date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: In reply to your note
                            of May 3d,<note n="17" xml:id="d15fn3">Not found in Department files.
                                Printed in part in R. S. Baker, <hi rend="italic">Woodrow Wilson,
                                    Life and Letters</hi> (New York, 1939), vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>, p. 47.</note> allow me to bring to
                            your attention some further facts for your consideration <pb facs="0060" n="14" xml:id="pg_14"/> in connection with the censorship of mails
                            brought to your attention in my note of April 30th. I am not doing this
                            in a controversial spirit or for any other purpose than to have the
                            whole situation laid before you, as I consider it to be of supreme
                            importance. Whatever may be the British facilities for censorship of
                            mails and telegraphs, and whatever may be the stringency of the American
                            censorship of telegraphs, it remains that there is by mail or courier to
                            Mexico and to South American countries an open channel for communication
                            of military information, of credit, and of intrigue, to the countries to
                            the south of us. This, in itself, is important, because we are aware of
                            German intrigue in Mexico, the flocking of thousands of Germans to that
                            country, probable German intrigues in Central America, and also in
                            certain countries of South America. There is, moreover, in these
                            countries, an effort on the part of Germans to build up German trade
                            after the war, which scheme is played up by German newspapers in order
                            to hearten the German spirit at the present time. Again, German raiders
                            have been operating off the South American coasts, and probably
                            obtaining some supplies from German firms in South America. It is very
                            probable that in the near future German submarines may endeavor to
                            undertake similar operations. The censorship of the mails to
                            Latin-American countries at least would assist very materially in
                            preventing or hindering the carrying out of any of the projects
                            mentioned. The matter came up for discussion yesterday at the conference
                            with Mr. Balfour, and he said that the importance of the information
                            obtained from censorship could not be overestimated and could not be
                            fully appreciated in advance.</p>
                        <p>In the second place, via South America there is direct means of
                            communication with Germany, which seems to me should be cut off. Mail
                            may be sent to South American countries from the United States and
                            transmitted from there by the diplomatic and consular officers of
                            Germany through devious channels of communication; or, I am told by Mr.
                            Balfour, direct to Spain by mail and possibly by cable (he was not sure
                            as to the cable), and thence by wireless from Spain to Germany. Mr.
                            Balfour said that this was a clear channel of communication still
                            open.</p>
                        <p>I trust you will understand that I am only desiring to inform you fully
                            on what to my mind is a very important matter. If it should turn out
                            that any censorship of mails is imposed by the United States, there
                            would, of course, be no duplication of the censorship by the Entente
                            Powers, as it would be arranged for them to pass mails censored by the
                            United States.</p>
                        <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>