<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Colonel E. M. House to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914-20v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d228</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">228</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-05-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-05-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec9aDoDi7sluDnsm" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="civil-rights"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026371"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil rights</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-05-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-05-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="228"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d228">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.94/259½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName type="from">Colonel E. M. House</persName> to the <gloss type="to"
                            >Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: This is the correspondence about
                    which Frank Polk spoke to you and which I am enclosing for your information and
                    files.</p>
                <p>I think of you every day, but do not try to reach you directly as I know the
                    burden you are carrying.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">E. M. House</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-05-16">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 16, 1917</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received May 17.] </dateline>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0449" n="403" xml:id="pg_403"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Japanese Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Sato</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to <persName type="to">Colonel E. M.
                                House</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-05-08">
                                <hi rend="italic">May 8, 1917</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Colonel House</hi>: For your kind reception and
                        open-hearted talk which I had the pleasure of enjoying in New York, I wish
                        you to accept my warm and sincere thanks.</p>
                    <p>According to your suggestion, I have since prepared a memorandum succintly
                        setting forth the point which found [<hi rend="italic">formed?</hi>] a part
                        of our conversation and I am taking the liberty to send it to you for
                        whatever you may see fit.</p>
                    <p>Mr Oscar S. Straus called on me two days after I had the pleasant interview
                        with you, and he was telling me about his idea of making the most of the
                        present trend of things for fostering better relations between our
                        countries. It is indeed gratifying to find evidences indicating that a more
                        serious interest in our relations is actually being taken in this country
                        and especially among men of great influence.</p>
                    <p>With high regard [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Aimaro Sato</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subenclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Japanese Ambassador</hi> (<hi
                            rend="italic">Sato</hi>)</head>
                    <p>The Japanese-American question which calls for an immediate adjustment, is
                        that of the treatment of the resident Japanese in this country. What Japan
                        desires is nothing more than the enjoyment of the most favored nation
                        treatment. That desideratum may be attained, in my personal opinion, by the
                        adoption of some of the following means.</p>
                    <p>1. By Treaty.</p>
                    <p>a. By concluding an independent treaty, mutually guaranteeing to the citizens
                        and subjects, the most favored nation treatment, in matters of property and
                        other rights relative to the exercise of industries, occupations, and other
                        pursuits. Negotiations in this line, were for some time conducted between
                        Secretary Bryan and Ambassador Chinda, which, however, for reasons I need
                        not here state, have since been in abeyance.</p>
                    <p>b. By revising the existing commercial treaty between our two countries, so
                        as to conform, in its stipulations, to similar engagements between Japan and
                        various European powers, which guarantee in principle, the most favored
                        nation treatment, in the enjoyment of property rights and in all that
                        relates to the pursuit of industries, callings and educational studies.</p>
                    <pb facs="0450" n="404" xml:id="pg_404"/>
                    <p>2. By American legislation.</p>
                    <p>Although the subject is not fit for international discussion, it may be
                        mentioned that a constitutional amendment restraining any state from making
                        and enforcing any law discriminatory against aliens in respect to the
                        property and other civil rights, will prove a far-reaching remedy. In fact a
                        resolution with the same object in view has, I understand, been introduced
                        in Congress lately.</p>
                    <p>In this connection, I may state the fact that the provisions of racial
                        distinction in the present naturalization law, were, in a number of
                        instances, made use of for the purpose of depriving Japanese subjects of the
                        rights and privileges of a civil nature. Although the wisdom of the law is
                        in itself a matter of national and not international concern, the
                        unfortunate circumstance that certain provisions of that law furnish a
                        pretext for the impairment of alien rights, should, I may be allowed to
                        remark, constitute a fit subject for legislative attention.</p>
                    <p>The comparative merits of each means should be studied by both Governments in
                        the light of expediency and feasibility. Whether the adoption of any one
                        means will be sufficient to cover the whole ground is a matter upon which
                        precaution forbids me to pass a final judgment at present, but I am strongly
                        convinced that each means will go a long distance towards a complete
                        solution of the question.</p>
                    <p>Before concluding, I desire to touch upon the subject of immigration. The
                        question whether Japanese laborers shall be admitted or not, has been
                        consummately solved by the continued faithful observance by Japan of the
                        so-called Gentleman’s Agreement. So far as the Japanese Government is
                        concerned, it is no longer in the realm of living questions, and in my view,
                        it would serve the best interests of both nations to leave the question as
                        it is.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName type="from">Colonel E. M. House</persName> to the Japanese
                            Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Sato</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Ambassador</hi>: Thank you for your letter
                        of May 8th enclosing the memorandum.</p>
                    <p>I shall take up the matter informally with Washington when the time seems
                        opportune. At the moment, I am afraid, it could not be given that calm
                        consideration which its importance justifies.</p>
                    <p>Please be assured that I shall always do what I can to help maintain the good
                        relations which exist between our two countries.</p>
                    <p>I shall remember with much satisfaction our conversation of the other day,
                        and I shall look forward to seeing you soon again.</p>
                    <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>[File copy not signed] <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-05-10">
                                <hi rend="italic">May 10, 1917</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
