<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to President Wilson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914-20v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d337</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">337</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-03-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-03-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="337"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d337">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.5914/218½a</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to President
                            <persName type="to">Wilson</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-03-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 19, 1917</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: By the treaty of cession of
                    August 4, 1916<note n="12" xml:id="d337fn1">
                        <ref target="frus1917#pg_694">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1917, p. 694</ref>.</note> we
                    are bound to pay over to Denmark the twenty-five million dollars and take
                    possession of the Danish West Indies before April 17th. That leaves us less than
                    a month to make the arrangements for the formal delivery of the islands and
                    payment of the money, which in view of the necessary communications with
                    Copenhagen is a very short time. We ought to start without delay.</p>
                <p>You have not indicated to me whether you have decided to have the War or Navy
                    Department take control of the provisional government. That is of course the
                    first question to be determined, because we must consult with the officials of
                    the Department selected as to the formalities and the officers to administer the
                    affairs of the islands. After this is decided I will name an official of the
                    State Department to consult with an official of the other Department and also
                    with the Danish Minister as to the procedure to be followed.</p>
                <p>On account of the naval importance of the new acquisition as well as the marked
                    efficiency shown by the naval officers in the conduct of affairs in Haiti and
                    the Dominican Republic I personally favor the assignment of the duty of
                    Government for the present to the Navy Department, although I realize that the
                    War Department is especially equipped for administration of insular possessions.
                    In voicing this opinion I do not intend to criticize in any way the War <pb
                        facs="0557" n="511" xml:id="pg_511"/> Department, which would undoubtedly do
                    well in the administration of the civil government of the islands. My opinion is
                    based on the fact that from the viewpoint of national defense the problems are
                    essentially naval and that the administration of affairs and control of the
                    public properties and improvements should be subordinated to the plans and
                    purposes of the General Board of the Navy. I fear that with the War Department
                    in control there might be failure to carry out these plans and purposes properly
                    and there is always the possibility of friction as to the policies to be
                    adopted.</p>
                <p>I hope that you will be able to give me very promptly a decision in this matter
                    as I feel that there is no time to lose in arranging for the formal delivery of
                    the islands.</p>
                <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
