<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Special Representative ( (House) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914-20v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-12-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-12-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="56"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d56">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">763.72 Su/1: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Special Representative</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">House</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-12-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 1, 1917—noon</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received December 3—6:35 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>901. The Supreme War Council sat at Versailles this morning at 10:30. General
                    Bliss and I represented the United States. Clemenceau and Foch, France, Milner
                    and Lloyd George, Robertson and Wilson, Great Britain, Orlando and Cadorna,
                    Italy, were present. The French Prime Minister presided. The following questions
                    submitted for examination: One, Italy, two, Saloniki, three, Roumania.</p>
                <p>One, Italy. The French Prime Minister said it was necessary to know whether
                    offensive or defensive measures were to be considered and that choice of
                    operation should not be left to enemy. Orlando thought that aid should be sent
                    to Italy immediately without waiting for a report, alleging that if divisions
                    sent were in excess of requirements they could always be sent back. Lloyd George
                    said that railway facilities to Italy were so limited that with six French
                    divisions using the Mont Cenis and six British divisions using the Ventimiglia
                    route no transportation facilities would be left for supplying Saloniki. He
                    suggested that a railway expert be appointed to report on the transportation
                    situation as a whole including not only Italian transportation question, but
                    also transportation across the Atlantic and railway transportation on the
                    various theatres of the war. He said that Geddes would be a good man to draw up
                    this report if he could be spared and report could be made in about 2 months.
                    Orlando said that in addition to the railways between France and Italy it was
                    possible always to send men by [ship?] from Marseilles to Genoa, a trip which
                    would involve only one night. At Genoa he said that the Italians had six large
                    steamers which could be utilized for this work.</p>
                <p>Two. The French Prime Minister proposed that the disposition of the Belgian [<hi
                        rend="italic">Greek</hi>?] army consisting of six divisions which had done
                    nothing up to the present time but issue communiqués be considered. It was
                    agreed that a dossier on this subject be distributed.</p>
                <p>Three. The question Saloniki was taken up and the chairman said that
                    unfortunately very little was known about the situation and what was known was
                    unfavorable. He stated that the British had 170,000 troops at Saloniki and only
                    40,000 bayonets. Wilson objected to this latter figure but could not give
                    reliable estimate thereof. The French Prime Minister said he could give
                    absolutely no details as to French army. Sarrail had been directed to report but
                    the report was not satisfactory. He stated that the French Government intended
                    to reorganize the French army at Saloniki and that, in view of the fact <pb
                        facs="0115" n="69" xml:id="pg_69"/> that in addition to the French and
                    British troops there were also Italian, Greek and Russian forces there, he did
                    not think that the expedition should be abandoned. The French [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Greek</hi>?] Prime Minister in the meantime having [assured?] the
                    conference there were three Greek divisions actually on the front at Saloniki
                    and that Greece was prepared to put nine divisions more into the field if the
                    munitions promised by the Allies at the conference in Paris of the present year
                    as well as the provisions were forthcoming. He said that the essential thing was
                    that Greece should receive provisions as his country was on starvation rations.
                    Foch objected that the Greeks had not lived up to their agreement to disband
                    their old army and to send the men back to the Peloponnesus. Venezelos admitted
                    that this had not been done because all of the rolling stock of the Greek
                    railways had been taken by the Allies for work at Saloniki and that the Greeks
                    had had most of their merchant marine taken by the Allies and if these ships
                    were restored to them they would transport their own provisions.</p>
                <p>Lloyd George said he thought it vital to the Allies that authority of Venezelos
                    be supported and that provisions be sent to Greece. He said that he had not
                    realized how badly and how unintelligently the Allies had treated Greece. Klotz,
                    the French Minister of Finance, appeared before council and stated that after
                    conferring with Venezelos [?] and Crosby he had ascertained that sum of 50
                    million francs was immediately necessary for the expenses of November and
                    December of the Greek army. This sum has been placed at the disposal of the
                    Greek Government yesterday although Crosby had made certain reservations as far
                    as the United States was concerned. The French Prime Minister asked House
                    whether the United States were prepared to participate with France and England
                    in lending money to Greece. House replied that he thought they would be. Klotz
                    said that Greek army budget for the year 1918 amounted to 900 million francs
                    divided as follows: 350 million francs pay for 1918. Venezelos stated that
                    Greece herself could provide internally 150 million francs of the amount,
                    leaving balance of 750 million francs to be provided by the Allies. Bliss and
                    House approving. Crosby states that he will recommend to McAdoo that the United
                    States provide one-third of this amount, England and France making up balance
                    provided tentative estimate of 600 million francs additional for the Greek army
                    munition program for 1918 is taken care of in similar or other manner. Crosby
                    will explain in a separate cable to the Treasury details of proposed
                    arrangement.</p>
                <p>Four. Details of the Roumanian situation left to military authorities which have
                    already discussed situation. Thereupon conference adjourned at 1:30 p. m.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward House</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
