<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to President Wilson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914-20v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d63</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">63</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-01-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-01-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-01-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-01-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="63"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d63">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">763.72119/1265½a</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to President
                            <persName type="to">Wilson</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-01-25">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 25, 1918</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: I presume you have read the
                    telegrams from Rome indicating a measure of dissatisfaction or at least of
                    disappointment on the part of the Italian Government and people with the
                    statement in your address of January 8th<note n="61" xml:id="d63fn1">
                        <ref target="frus1918Supp01v01#pg_12">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1918, supp. 1, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 12</ref>.</note> relative to Italy and
                    presumably the statement in regard to Austria-Hungary. The point which the
                    Italians seem to make is that if their frontiers are to be rectified only on the
                    basis of nationality, they will be as vulnerable to attack from Austria-Hungary
                    as they have been in the past. That is, the Adriatic Question will remain
                    unsettled and will compel the nation to continue its present policy of
                    defense.</p>
                <pb facs="0136" n="90" xml:id="pg_90"/>
                <p>There is no doubt but that Italy’s position in the Adriatic is more or less
                    precarious and that it is one which the Italian Government seeks to make more
                    stable in the final peace. The Italian coast is low-lying and without harbors.
                    It offers no opportunities for naval bases from which to operate. On the other
                    hand, the opposite coast is indented with numerous inlets and ports. As a
                    consequence the Italian shores are difficult of defense and control of the
                    Adriatic lies to a very considerable degree with the power possessing the
                    eastern shores of the sea.</p>
                <p>Manifestly an adjustment of the Italian frontiers along lines of nationality will
                    in no way cure this situation or make Italy’s position more secure than it is at
                    present. I think that this is the ground for Italian dissatisfaction, and it is
                    not entirely without justification.</p>
                <p>While, as you know, I am strongly inclined to nationality as the basis for
                    territorial limits I believe that it cannot be invariably adopted, but that in
                    certain cases physical boundaries and strategic boundaries must be considered
                    and modify boundaries based on nationality. These will constitute exceptions to
                    the general rule but will be very few in number.</p>
                <p>I mention this at the present time because I fear that if Italy gains the
                    impression that she is not to strengthen her position in the Adriatic, the
                    Italian people will become discouraged and feel that the war has no actual
                    interest for them, that they will be disposed to make peace provided the Germans
                    and Austrians retire from Italian territory, and that they will consider
                    themselves to have been abandoned by this country and the Allies. With the
                    present political situation in Italy and the depression following their military
                    reverses such an impression would be most unfortunate and might be
                    disastrous.</p>
                <p>Do you not think that something could be done to restore Italian confidence that
                    a satisfactory settlement of the Adriatic Question will be made at the peace
                    conference? If anything can be done it seems to me it ought to be done without
                    delay.</p>
                <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
