<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in France (
                        Caffery
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d164</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">164</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-03-25T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-03-25T13:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-03-25T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-03-25T13:00:00-05:00" n="164" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d164">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">862.6362/3–2547: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CJ1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-03-25T19:00:00+01:00">March 25, 1947—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1279. The Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs <persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Teitgen</persName> told me today that his government is still exceedingly
                    worried about the Ruhr coal situation and most unhappy in regard to <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bevin</persName>’s stand in that connection at Moscow. He
                    said that if France can obtain a reasonable solution for the Ruhr coal business
                    it would be much easier for his government to support our thesis on a number of
                    other points at Moscow. All the more because the entire Cabinet he said except
                    the Communist basically desires to cooperate with the United States.</p>
                <p>First of all he said his government considers the Four Power pact to be
                    essential. Next his government would go along with us in regard to economic
                    unity of Germany and also in raising certain production levels. His government
                    believes that a provisional government based on the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> but with certain delegated powers to a central authority
                    should be set up without delay, especially in view of the fact that it is
                    obvious no definite peace treaty for Germany can be terminated at an early date.
                    “Furthermore” he said “the powers of the central authority <pb facs="0435" n="401" xml:id="pg_401"/> could be gradually extended. I personally envisage
                    the possibility that one day it might evolve into a real central
                    government”.</p>
                <p>“Then there is” he said, “the question of unification of our zones. In principle
                    we are not opposed to that but it would be difficult for us to sign a solemn
                    agreement for unification. On the other hand unification of our zones could be
                    effected little by little on an informal basis. The same result could be
                    achieved and we would avoid the complications with the Communists which a public
                    notice of unification would bring on for us”. He then repeated “in view of our
                    public opinion on coal, however, we do not feel that we can contribute to any of
                    these matters until we have the coal matter settled.”</p>
                <p>He remarked “<persName corresp="#p_SJV1">Stalin</persName> told <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> in effect ‘you vote with us and we will
                    vote with you’”. “Obviously” said <persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Teitgen</persName>
                    “that is the last thing we want to do and <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> made it clear that we could not enter into such an
                        agreement”.<note n="50" xml:id="d164fn1">For additional information on the
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJV1">Stalin</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> conversation in Moscow on March 17 under reference
                        here, see telegram 974, <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1339,
                        March 24, from Moscow, <ref target="#pg_396">p. 396</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>He added “you are now about to spend a lot of money to keep the Communists out of
                    Greece and Turkey which is very fine; but don’t you think it is worth while
                    keeping the Russians out of here too? What I mean is this, if we have an
                    economic collapse because we don’t get coal the Communists will probably be the
                    gainers.”</p>
                <p>Repeated London 253; Moscow for US Delegation 181.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
