<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-04-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-04-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="184" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d184">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Council/4–1447</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the British Military Governor for
                                    Germany</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_RSBH1"><hi rend="italic">Robertson</hi></persName>)<note n="42" xml:id="d184fn1">
                                    <p>The source text is marked “SECOND DRAFT. (Not yet approved by
                                        British Secretary of State.)”. Attached to the source text
                                        is a copy of a letter, dated April 17, 1947, from General
                                            <persName corresp="#p_DWH1">Draper</persName> to General
                                            <persName corresp="#p_RSBH1">Robertson</persName> which
                                        reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                            <p>“I have received your memorandum on the operation of
                                                the fusion agreement which will be brought to
                                                General <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName>’s attention immediately. I
                                                see from your note that it is a first draft and not
                                                yet approved. But since it is drawn up as if
                                                presented jointly by you and me on behalf of our
                                                respective Commander-in-Chiefs, I must point out
                                                that I am not authorized to speak for General
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_CLD1">Clay</persName> on
                                                this matter. As you know, he believes that no
                                                specific decisions should be reached concerning the
                                                management of the bizonal area until you and he have
                                                had the opportunity of discussing the questions
                                                involved and of making joint recommendations. You
                                                indicated that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bevin</persName> would probably see General
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName> on
                                                Thursday [April 17] so I wanted you to have this
                                                word immediately.”</p>
                                        </quote>
                                    </p>
                                </note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-04-17">April 17, 1947</date>.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum on the Operation of the Fusion
                                    Agreement after the Moscow Conference</hi>
                            </p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Presented jointly to the U.S. and U.K. Secretaries of State by
                                    Major General <persName corresp="#p_DWH1">W. Draper</persName>
                                    on behalf of the Commander-in-Chief and Military Governor of the
                                    U.S. Zone and Lieut. General <persName corresp="#p_RSBH1">Sir
                                        Brian Robertson</persName> on behalf of the
                                    Commander-in-Chief and Military Governor of the British
                                    Zone.</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">section “a”—operation of economic fusion</hi>
                            </p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The Fusion Agreement signed in New York on the 2nd December,
                                        1946,<note n="43" xml:id="d184fn2">For the text of the
                                        Memorandum of Agreement under reference here, see Department
                                        of State Treaties and Other International Acts Series No.
                                        1575 or 61 Stat. (pt. 3), 2475.</note> shall continue to be
                                    operated fully in the spirit in which it was conceived with the
                                    object of securing the maximum success in the joint
                                    administration of the economy of the Combined Zones.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>While it is not necessary that there should be identity of
                                    views on the future political structure of Germany, the broad
                                    principles of the division of powers between the centre and the
                                        <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>, supported by the U.S. and
                                    U.K. Delegations in document <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>/47/M/121,<note n="44" xml:id="d184fn3">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_436">p.
                                            436</ref>.</note> Section “E”, as amended during its
                                    discussion in the Council of Foreign Ministers, shall be
                                    regarded for the purposes of the operation of fusion as the
                                    accepted policy of both Governments. These principles are
                                    summarized in Annexure “A”.<note n="45" xml:id="d184fn4">Annex
                                        A, not here printed, was an extract from Section E of
                                        document <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>(47) (M)
                                        121.</note> They will be regarded for the present as
                                    applicable to the division of powers between <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> governments <pb facs="0514" n="480" xml:id="pg_480"/> on the one hand and Military Government
                                    and the Bi-Zonal Administrations on the other hand.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item> (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) The Bi-Zonal Administrations shall
                                    be concentrated in one area. The choice of location for this
                                    purpose shall be determined primarily by the speed at which an
                                    efficient concentration can be effected.</item>
                                <label> </label>
                                <item>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) The Bi-Zonal Administrations shall
                                    be accorded sufficient executive authority and shall be staffed
                                    in a manner adequate to enable them to perform their functions.
                                    While excessive staffs are undesirable, both Governments agree
                                    to provide such Allied personnel as are essential and to ensure
                                    that adequate German personnel is assembled to execute the work
                                    efficiently.</item>
                                <label> </label>
                                <item>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) The chairman of each executive
                                    committee shall devote his whole time to his work as such. He
                                    shall be vested with executive authority subject to the
                                    decisions of his executive committee. </item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item> (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) In accordance with the principle
                                    contained in paragraph 2.(c) of Annexure “A”, the distribution
                                    of food and raw materials in short supply and the planning of
                                    industry shall be carried out centrally by the Bi-Zonal
                                    Administrations under the supervision of the appropriate Allied
                                    Control staffs.</item>
                                <label> </label>
                                <item>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) The planning of industry shall be
                                    done in a manner to ensure the best possible use of available
                                    resources, including particularly coal. This is necessary
                                    firstly to reduce as quickly as possible the expenditure being
                                    incurred by both Governments on the economy of the joint Zones
                                    and secondly in order to ensure that the export of coal is at
                                    the highest level consistent with the maintenance of a proper
                                    economy in the Combined Zones. </item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>The execution of the plans for the distribution of food and
                                    raw materials in short supply and for industry shall be carried
                                    out by the administrative machinery of the <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> Governments. Adequate measures of control shall
                                    be taken to ensure that this execution is prompt and effective
                                    to avoid the dissipation of resources and the waste of Allied
                                    money.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Measures shall be taken to develop greater freedom of trade
                                    between Germans in the Combined Zones and other countries,
                                    particularly by making it possible for the German exporter to
                                    negotiate contracts with potential buyers abroad subject only to
                                    essential control of foreign exchange. Financial resources
                                    available for the purchase of raw materials, etc., shall not, in
                                    the first instance, be used with the object of achieving a
                                    general improvement in the economy of the Combined Zones, but
                                    shall be used boldly to secure those things which are shown to
                                    be necessary for the rapid development of exports.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>Prompt measures shall be taken to bring about financial
                                    reform, <pb facs="0515" n="481" xml:id="pg_481"/> if possible on
                                    an all-German basis, including the issue of a new
                                    currency.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">section “b”—level of industry and
                                    reparations</hi>
                            </p>
                            <list>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>Immediately after the conclusion of the Moscow Conference, a
                                    joint Declaration shall be made by U.S. and U.K. Military
                                    Government to the effect that they intend forthwith to establish
                                    a fresh level of industry for the Combined Zones and that they
                                    do not intend to agree to any lower level in the future. The
                                    basis of the new Plan shall be an annual production of
                                    10,000,000 tons of steel and consequential increases in the
                                    level of other industries. The details of this Plan will be
                                    worked out in Berlin. The percentage increase in the permitted
                                    level of all industries need not be uniform. In some cases all
                                    restriction of level may be removed on industries at present
                                    restricted. In other cases a special quantitative restriction
                                    may be imposed. The new Plan shall be announced by the 1st July,
                                    1947, and the final list of plant and equipment to be removed
                                    from the Combined Zones shall be issued not later than the 15th
                                    August, 1947.</item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item>Plants rendered surplus by this revised level of industry Plan
                                    shall be offered to the Control Council for allocation between
                                    the Western and the Eastern Powers. Consideration shall be given
                                    to the advisability of reserving from immediate allocation a
                                    margin of plants, both to allow for the possible attachment of
                                    the Saar to the French economy and also for the possibility of
                                    excessive removals from the Eastern Zone.</item>
                                <label>10.</label>
                                <item>The U.S. and U.K. representatives on the Control Council and
                                    its Committees shall insist on more expeditious means of
                                    valuation and allocation than are in force at present.</item>
                                <label>11.</label>
                                <item>When plants have been allocated they shall be delivered both
                                    to the Western and to the Eastern Powers.</item>
                                <label>12.</label>
                                <item>All plants rendered surplus by the new level of industry Plan
                                    shall be closed immediately irrespective of whether or when they
                                    are to be delivered for reparations. Exceptions shall be made in
                                    the case of certain plants on the prohibited list which are by
                                    agreement to be retained in operation until imported supplies
                                    can be procured.</item>
                                <label>13.</label>
                                <item>Consideration shall be given to means for ensuring that the
                                    U.K. receives certain plants which are most urgently
                                    required.</item>
                                <label>14.</label>
                                <item>Within the level of industry fixed under this new Plan, every
                                    endeavour shall be made to build up the economy of the Combined
                                    Zones to the highest possible level. In particular steps shall
                                    be taken to ensure adequate supplies of food and also to raise
                                    the level of coal production in the Ruhr to 300,000 t.p.d. as
                                    quickly as possible.</item>
                            </list>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>