<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in France (
                        Caffery
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d259</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">259</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-11-06T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-11-06T07:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-11-06T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-11-06T07:00:00-05:00" n="259" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d259">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851.00/11–647: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CJ1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-11-06T13:00:00+01:00">November 6, 1947—1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>4757. Discussing in strictest confidence the forthcoming Foreign Ministers’
                    meeting in London, <persName corresp="#p_CJ2">Chauvel</persName> said to me last
                    evening that while the French want very much to reach agreement with US on
                    Germany, their position “for internal political reasons” is nonetheless very
                    difficult. He described the “psychosis” of the French public as the result of
                    having been invaded by Germany three times in seventy years and said that the
                    Communists on one hand and <persName corresp="#p_DGBC1">De Gaulle</persName> on
                    the other (my 4737 November 5<note n="45" xml:id="d259fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_699">p. 699</ref>.</note>)
                    will almost certainly attack bitterly any French decision which even appears to
                    give the slightest impression that the French Government has “sold out” to
                    US.</p>
                <p>With the foregoing in mind, <persName corresp="#p_CJ2">Chauvel</persName> said he
                    hoped (1) that at the very outset of the meeting either ourselves or the British
                    would make abundantly clear to the Russians the problems on which we expect a
                    decision to be reached at the meeting. Should the Soviets then engage in their
                    usual evasive delaying tactics (as <persName corresp="#p_CJ2">Chauvel</persName>
                    believes they will) and the conference break down, it will then be clear to
                    everyone including the French people exactly where the responsibility for the
                    failure of the conference rests. (2) He also said that if the French
                    subsequently go along with US and the British, such action would have to be
                    presented to the French public in such a way that there can be no doubt
                    whatsoever that France’s security requirements are in any way jeopardized.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CJ2">Chauvel</persName> said in all statements, etc., the
                    French would have to continue to harp on the theme of French security and the
                    fact that the <pb facs="0737" n="703" xml:id="pg_703"/> French Government is
                    determined to insure it and will not sacrifice it just to reach an
                    agreement.</p>
                <p>Repeated to London for Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>
                    as 829.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
