<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-12-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-12-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="310" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d310">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">
                                <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Files: Lot M–88: Box 86: <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>(47) (L) Documents</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Report of the <gloss type="from">Deputies for
                                        Austria</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Council of Foreign
                                        Ministers</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d310fn1">
                                    <p>This document was discussed by the Council of Foreign
                                        Ministers at its 9th Meeting, December 4; see telegram 6326,
                                            <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1521, December
                                        4, from London, <ref target="#pg_747">p. 747</ref>.</p>
                                    <p>The Deputies for Austria were: United States–Ambassador
                                            <persName corresp="#p_DJM1">Dodge</persName>; United
                                            Kingdom–<persName corresp="#p_MJAM1">James
                                            Marjoribanks</persName>, France–General <persName corresp="#p_CDBP1">Cherrière</persName>, Soviet
                                            Union–<persName corresp="#p_KNP1">N. P.
                                            Koktomov</persName>.</p>
                                </note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>(47) (L)15</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-12-02">2nd December,
                                        1947</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1. At the 2nd meeting of the Council of Foreign Ministers on 26th
                                    November,<note n="2" xml:id="d310fn2">See telegram 6210, <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1504, November 26, from
                                    London, <ref target="#pg_733">p. 733</ref>.</note> the Ministers
                                accepted a proposal by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bevin</persName> that the Report of the Austrian Treaty
                                    Commission,<note n="3" xml:id="d310fn3">Document <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ATC1">ATC</gloss> (47) 77, October 11, 1947, <ref target="#pg_631">p. 631</ref>.</note> together with the
                                proposal submitted by the French Delegation in Vienna (<gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ATC1">ATC</gloss>
                                (47)76 of 8th October, 1947—See Annex A<note n="4" xml:id="d310fn4">The document under reference here is not printed as an annex to
                                    this Report; for the text, see <ref target="#pg_620">p.
                                        620</ref>.</note>), should be referred for detailed
                                examination to Deputies for Austria who should report back to the
                                Council by December 2nd.</p>
                            <p>2. The Deputies at their meeting on 27th November decided to give
                                immediate consideration to the French proposal since it had not yet
                                been the subject of quadripartite discussion. The French Deputy
                                accordingly elaborated the proposal, introducing certain figures in
                                respect of the three following elements contained in the suggested
                                settlement:— <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>an apportionment of oil rights both for prospecting and
                                        extracting in the form of new concessions and of certain
                                        assets in the field of refining and distribution.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>a division of the assets of the <gloss target="#t_DDSG1">D.D.S.G.</gloss>;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>an amount fixed in dollars to be paid by Austria through
                                        deliveries in kind.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>This statement was circulated as <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>
                                47/L/8 of 27th November, 1947, and is shown at [<hi rend="italic">as</hi>] Annex B.</p>
                            <p>3. Discussion of the French proposal and of the statement of the
                                French Deputy took place at the Deputies’ Meetings on 28th and 29th
                                November and 1st December.</p>
                            <p>4. The positions of the United Kingdom, Soviet and United States
                                delegations are set out below:—</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Position of the United Kingdom Delegation</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The U.K. Delegation welcome the French proposals and consider that
                                they provide a general framework for a practical and constructive
                                    <pb facs="0833" n="799" xml:id="pg_799"/> solution of the
                                problem of German assets in Austria. Moreover, a solution on these
                                lines would appear to obviate the difficulties which have arisen
                                during the prolonged attempt to establish an agreed definition of
                                German assets.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Position of the Soviet Delegation</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Under the decisions of the Potsdam Conference former German assets in
                                Eastern Austria became the property of the Soviet Union and former
                                German assets in Western Austria the property of the United Kingdom,
                                the United States, France and other Allied powers.</p>
                            <p>On the question of German assets in Austria the Soviet Delegation has
                                based, and is basing, itself on the Potsdam decisions. Since,
                                however, the French Delegation has made an attempt to introduce
                                practical proposals on that subject the Soviet Delegation has not
                                refused to study these proposals. But the study of the French
                                proposal undertaken at the previous meetings has yielded quite
                                unsatisfactory results.</p>
                            <p>Thus the proposal of the French Delegation in the form as it is
                                outlined in the documents presented to the Austrian Treaty
                                Commission and to the Deputies is not, in the opinion of the Soviet
                                Delegation, a just basis for resolving the differences on the
                                question of former German assets in Austria.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Position of the United States Delegation</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The U.S. Deputy considered the approach of the French proposal as a
                                practical basis upon which to attempt a reconciliation of existing
                                disagreement regarding German assets in Austria.</p>
                            <p>5. The Deputies had a brief exchange of views regarding the
                                discussion of the unagreed articles of the Treaty, but did not
                                discuss these articles in detail for lack of time. In addition the
                                U.S. Delegation stated that further discussion would be useless
                                pending a larger measure of agreement on the subject of German
                                assets (Article 35).</p>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head>Annex B</head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-11-27">27th November
                                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p rend="center">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Statement by the French Deputy for
                                        Austria</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CDBP1"><hi rend="italic">Cherrière</hi></persName>)<note n="5" xml:id="d310fn5">Statement made at the meeting of the Deputies for Austria,
                                        London, November 27, 1947.</note>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">
                                    <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>(47) (L)8</p>
                                <p>The French delegation is now able to supply certain particulars
                                    in regard to the proposals which it put forward in Vienna on 8th
                                    October and which formed the subject of Document <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ATC1">ATC</gloss>(47)76 of 8th October 1947.</p>
                                <pb facs="0834" n="800" xml:id="pg_800"/>
                                <p>Definite settlement of the problem of German assets in Austria
                                    should comprise three elements i.e.: <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>an apportionment of oil rights both for prospecting
                                            and extracting in the form of new concessions;</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>a division of the holdings of <gloss target="#t_DDSG1">D.D.S.G.</gloss>;</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>an amount fixed in dollars to be paid by Austria in
                                            the form of products from her current production.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>After further study, since the adjournment of the work of the
                                    Austrian Control Commission, the French delegation is able to
                                    put forward certain figures in respect of each of these
                                    elements.</p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Oil.</hi>
                                </p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Extraction</hi>. The Soviet Union should
                                        receive concessions corresponding to about 50% of the
                                        present production of Austria. The duration and general
                                        terms should be fixed in accordance with precedents in
                                        similar cases.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Prospecting</hi>. The Soviet Union should
                                        receive about 1/3 of the area of the Zistersdorf
                                        oilfields.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Refining</hi>. Refineries representing a
                                        capacity of 250,000 to 300,000 tons should be transferred to
                                        the Soviet Union.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Distribution</hi>. The Soviet Union should
                                        keep those facilities which she now has in two distributing
                                        concerns.</item>
                                </list>
                                <p rend="flushleft">2. <gloss target="#t_DDSG1">
                                        <hi rend="italic">D.D.S.G.</hi>
                                    </gloss>
                                </p>
                                <p>Austria should forfeit in favour of the U.S.S.R. all holdings of
                                    the <gloss target="#t_DDSG1">D.D.S.G.</gloss> in Hungary,
                                    Roumania and Bulgaria. Further, Austria should transfer to the
                                    Allies a certain number of ships in order to compensate the
                                    losses suffered by their river fleets during the war through
                                    requisitions made for the benefit of the <gloss target="#t_DDSG1">D.D.S.G.</gloss>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">3. <hi rend="italic">Amount in dollars.</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>The figure envisaged by the French delegation for Eastern Austria
                                    is 100,000,000 dollars. Delivery should be spread over ten
                                    years, starting from such time as Austria’s minimum needs have
                                    been met.</p>
                                <p>The particulars set out above by the French delegation do not, of
                                    course, constitute a fresh proposal, and all the suggestions
                                    contained in the document of 8th October, which formed a whole,
                                    as indicated in paragraph 17 of this document, still stand
                                    particularly those concerning points not dealt with above; this
                                    is specially the case as regards the application of Austrian
                                    law, arbitration, and the property of United Nations and
                                    minority groups.</p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>