<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of Western European
                    Affairs ( (Reber))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d433</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">433</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-08-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-08-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-08-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-08-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="433"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d433">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/8–547</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of
                        Western European Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_RS1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Reber</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="68" xml:id="d433fn1">The source text is signed by Secretary
                            <persName corresp="#p_CMS1">Marshall</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-08-05">August 5,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>The Secretary</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>The French Ambassador</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Reber</persName>, <gloss
                                target="#t_WE1">WE</gloss>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The French Ambassador called this afternoon to give the Secretary a message from
                    M. <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> with reference to the United
                    States offer to give consideration to French representations on the subject of
                    level of industry in Germany and the management of the Ruhr mines.</p>
                <p>M. <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName> explained the French position
                    along the lines of the attached memorandum,<note n="69" xml:id="d433fn2">The
                        paper under reference, a French Embassy <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                        dated August 5, 1947, not printed, is filed separately under 840.50
                        Recovery/8–547.</note> as follows:<list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Since the two problems of German industry and the management of the
                            Ruhr mines were so vital to French security and to its relations with
                            the United States and Great Britain, the French Government cannot agree
                            to limit its expression of views on the subject to a written
                            presentation, but must insist upon a frank discussion.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>The letter which Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName> had
                            given to M. <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> two weeks
                                ago<note n="70" xml:id="d433fn3">The reference here is to the
                                message of July 21 from the Secretary of State to Foreign Minister
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName>, <ref
                                    target="#pg_1003">p. 1003</ref>.</note> had indicated that the
                            United States Government was prepared to suspend any announcement with
                            respect to these problems until the French Government had had the
                            opportunity of discussing these questions with the United States and
                            United Kingdom Governments. From this the French had believed all that
                            was necessary was to establish the manner in which these discussions
                            should be held.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>The instructions of the French delegation which was to have taken part
                            in these discussions had been prepared, since the French Government
                            thought it would be possible to find a basis of understanding which
                            would permit France, without concern for its security, to continue to
                            associate itself in the work of the Paris Conference. In the opinion of
                            the French Government the differences of opinion between the three
                            powers related to the method of presentation rather than to the
                            substance of the problem.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>The French Government, therefore, must insist that the proposals which
                            had been made by the American Ambassador in Paris be given effect. Given
                            the seriousness of the situation if the American Government considers it
                            necessary today to abandon the idea of tripartite conversations, M.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> is ready to proceed
                            immediately to Washington to explain France’s position directly to the
                            Secretary of State and to set forth the consequences of any refusal to
                            discuss these problems with the French Government.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>M. <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName> then went on to say that the
                    French Government was aware of the necessity of including German industry and
                    German <pb facs="1056" n="1022" xml:id="pg_1022"/> production in any plan for
                    European recovery. Without this it realized that not only could any plan never
                    be accepted by the American people and the American Congress, but it would not
                    be a complete program for Europe, since any such must include German production.
                    The Ambassador had been instructed, however, again to point out how impossible
                    it would be for prance to accept any program for European recovery built around
                    an agreement with respect to German industry in which it had not participated.
                    An agreement which had been drawn up solely by the bi-zonal commanders in
                    relation to Germany alone could not be considered acceptable by the French
                    people. Furthermore, his government could not place itself in the position of
                    accepting such a program merely for the purpose of obtaining credits, however
                    badly needed they might be.</p>
                <p>M. <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName> then said that the tenor of his
                    instructions clearly showed the conviction of the French Government that an
                    agreement in substance on these matters would be possible as a result of
                    discussion. Everything which he had received from Paris indicated not only the
                    desire of France to reach agreement with the United States and Great Britain in
                    this matter, but that such agreement was definitely possible.</p>
                <p>Without it, however, a serious situation would be faced at the meeting of the
                    Deputies in October and at the Council of Foreign Ministers in November, as the
                    United States and United Kingdom would have one position, France would have
                    another, and Soviet Russia another. Although full agreement among the four was
                    unlikely, at least agreement among the three could be achieved if properly
                    prepared. M. <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName> then said he wished to
                    conclude his explanation by once again repeating that M. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName>’s offer to come immediately to
                    Washington demonstrated the seriousness with which this question was viewed in
                    France.</p>
                <p>The Secretary replied that he had been informed of M. <persName corresp="#p_BH1"
                        >Bonnet</persName>’s recent conversations with Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_LRA1">Lovett</persName>, and he wished to confirm what Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_LRA1">Lovett</persName> had told the Ambassador. In
                    order to avoid any misunderstandings at this stage he could not at this time
                    comment upon the Ambassador’s communication. He promised to give it very careful
                    study and to let the Ambassador know, but at this time he could say nothing
                    more.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
