<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-08-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-08-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="452" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d452">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">862.60/8–647</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Office of
                                    European Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HJD1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hickerson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_LRA1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Lovett</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-08-23">August 23,
                                        1947</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Subject: International Control of Ruhr Resources</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The problem of dealing with the revival of German industry and its
                                relation to the reconstruction of western Europe has reached a
                                critical stage, both as regards the tripartite talks in London and
                                the general economic recovery plan now under study in Paris. There
                                can be no question that the disposition of the products of the Ruhr
                                is one of the central factors in the preparation of the European
                                program in Paris, not only because of the position taken by the
                                French but because of the legitimate interest of other European
                                nations in the rate of German recovery.</p>
                            <p>In order to meet the serious situation in Germany and to implement a
                                decision of the US-UK Governments taken during the Moscow
                                Conference, it has been agreed by this Government that the bizonal
                                level of industry plan prepared by the US and UK Zone Commanders
                                should be announced September 1st as soon as the French views have
                                been considered.</p>
                            <p>Not only is the French Government deeply concerned that the new level
                                of industry means that the industrial revival of Germany is being
                                given priority in European recovery; but similar concern has been
                                expressed in this country and the principal line of attack by the
                                Communists on present US policy is that its principal aim is to
                                rebuild Germany. As a counter-balance to agreeing to a higher level
                                of industry France is seeking assurances that (a) Ruhr industrial
                                capacity will never again be used for military purposes against
                                France, and (b) access by western Europe to the production of the
                                Ruhr will not be subject exclusively to the will of Germany.</p>
                            <p>Assurances that the US Government is still desirous of dealing with
                                the problem of military security through the controls established
                                under the terms of the Disarmament and Demilitarization Treaty have
                                already been given to the French Government in respect to the first
                                of these points. With respect to the second it has been agreed with
                                the War Department that any specific proposal in this connection
                                should be related to the peace treaty negotiations and not decided
                                in connection with the level of industry talks.</p>
                            <p>On the other hand, it must be recognized that French cooperation is
                                necessary both with regard to the solution of the German problem as
                                    <pb facs="1085" n="1051" xml:id="pg_1051"/> well as with regard
                                to the realization of the <persName corresp="#p_CMS1">Marshall</persName> Plan for the economic recovery of Europe.
                                There is a danger that the failure of the US Government to come to
                                an understanding with the French at this time on a general approach
                                to the Ruhr question might result in vocal opposition on the French
                                part to the new level of industry plan and might so weaken the
                                present French Government that a French political crisis could ensue
                                either through the resignation of <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> or the fall of the Government on this issue.
                                The United States has always expressed a lively understanding of the
                                French concern for security and it must be admitted that there is
                                justice in the French conception of an inter-relation between the
                                level of industry plan and the future of the Ruhr as affecting their
                                security.</p>
                            <p>Furthermore, it is the considered opinion of Messrs. <persName corresp="#p_CWL1">Clayton</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DLW1">Douglas</persName> that the United States should at this time
                                recognize the legitimate interest of France and other European
                                countries in the allocation of Ruhr production and give assurances
                                that it will support the inclusion in an international agreement in
                                connection with the peace settlement of articles providing for some
                                measure of international allocation. A more detailed analysis of the
                                French position and proposals in this respect is contained in the
                                attached annex.</p>
                            <p>In formulating the following recommendations it is appreciated that
                                they are not in line with the views presently held by the War
                                Department which is concerned lest French preoccupation with respect
                                to their own security imperil the economic development in Germany
                                necessary to enable the US to fulfill its responsibilities in this
                                respect and avoid continuing heavy charges. Minimum assurances of
                                the kind set forth are however considered in the interest of United
                                States policy, provide a basis for a real settlement involving the
                                western zones of Germany, and insure that the European recovery
                                program will not be adversely affected by the legitimate concerns of
                                European Powers. It should, of course, be understood that in giving
                                any assurances to the French Government in this connection the
                                United States is not committed to accept a particular method of
                                implementation until the peace treaty goes into effect. This is
                                important since the agreement will not be effective until a much
                                later date at which time the political conditions in France may be
                                very different from today. In guarding against future commitments
                                which might benefit a France which had gone Communist we should
                                however avoid action which increases this possibility. Any hesitancy
                                displayed in discussing our purposes and aims in respect of Germany
                                with other Governments tends to intensify suspicions as to these
                                aims and strengthen the Communist line of attack.</p>
                            <pb facs="1086" n="1052" xml:id="pg_1052"/>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>A decision on this matter is urgent in view of the present stages of
                                the London talks (see London’s telegram no. 4579<note n="10" xml:id="d452fn1">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note>) and is required before
                                further instructions can be sent <persName corresp="#p_DLW1">Douglas</persName>. It is recommended that United States policy
                                be clarified in this respect so that the French may be informed
                                during the London talks, that: <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item>The United States Government is prepared to agree in
                                        principle with the French and British Governments to support
                                        inclusion in an international agreement in connection with
                                        the peace settlement of Germany of provisions which would
                                        give assurances not only to France but to other European
                                        Governments that access by western Europe to the production
                                        of the Ruhr would not be subject exclusively to the will of
                                        Germany as in the past and,</item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item>The United States Government is prepared as soon as the
                                        tripartite discussions in London are concluded and the level
                                        of industry announced to agree to a further tripartite
                                        exploration of the methods by which this assurance may be
                                        implemented in the peace treaty. During these discussions
                                        sympathetic consideration should be given to the inclusion
                                        in the peace treaty of articles providing for the
                                        establishment of an international board, of which Germany
                                        will be a member, to insure that the distribution of Ruhr
                                        output of coal, coke, and steel between German internal
                                        consumption and exports will be determined on an equitable
                                        basis and that German domestic consumption will be devoted
                                        to peaceful purposes only, in accordance with
                                        demilitarization and disarmament measures which are agreed
                                        in the peace settlement.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Annex]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum Prepared in the Department of
                                        State</hi><note n="11" xml:id="d452fn2">The source text
                                        indicates that this paper was prepared by <persName corresp="#p_TH1">Howard Trivers</persName>, Division of
                                        Central European Affairs; <persName>Fritz E.
                                            Oppenheimer</persName>, Special Assistant to the Legal
                                        Adviser for German-Austrian Affairs; and <persName corresp="#p_DWJC1">John C. de Wilde</persName>, Acting
                                        Associate Chief, Division of Occupied-Area Economic
                                        Affairs.</note>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" when="1947-08-23">undated</date>.]</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>In a series of informal talks held at Paris during recent weeks,
                                    between Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWL1">Clayton</persName>,
                                    Ambassadors <persName corresp="#p_DLW1">Douglas</persName> and
                                        <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName> on one side
                                    and Messrs. <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName>,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MJ1">Monnet</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CDMM1">Couve de Murville</persName> and
                                        <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> on the other,
                                    the French have set forth as their position that they do not
                                    want to hold down production in Germany and would not object to
                                    the new level of industry plan, providing assurance is obtained
                                    that (1) Ruhr resources would not again be used for military
                                    purposes against France and (2) access to the products of the
                                    Ruhr shall not be at the exclusive will of Germany, as in the
                                    past.</p>
                                <pb facs="1087" n="1053" xml:id="pg_1053"/>
                                <p>To bring about such assurance, M. <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> proposed the creation of an
                                    international board which would allocate the Ruhr production of
                                    coal, iron and steel between Germany and other countries. After
                                    the peace treaty the board would be composed of representatives
                                    of the United States, the United Kingdom, France, Benelux and
                                    Germany; prior thereto it was to be composed of the same
                                    countries minus Germany. During the talks the French conceded
                                    that no special controls were required for the occupation and
                                    that their proposal referred to the post-occupation period and
                                    should be connected with the peace settlement.</p>
                                <p>In comparison with the French position at the Moscow Conference,
                                    this latest French proposal represents a very considerable
                                    concession and endeavor to meet United States views. The French
                                    have abandoned their previous demands for the political
                                    detachment of the Ruhr from Germany and for the
                                    internationalization of the Ruhr area. Furthermore, the French
                                    are willing to leave the ownership and administration of the
                                    Ruhr industry in German hands and declare no interest in the
                                    question whether the Ruhr should be nationalized or not.</p>
                                <p>The latest British proposal suggests that the coal, iron and
                                    steel industries of the Ruhr should be placed under
                                    international control with some form of public ownership in
                                    order that their resources may be used for the benefit of Europe
                                    as a whole, including Germany. The British agree on the
                                    necessity for international control, but this in their mind is
                                    connected with some form of German public ownership.
                                    Specifically, they seem to favor ownership by a German public
                                    corporation, with actual management vested in an international
                                    board of directors.</p>
                                <p>It will be recalled that Secretary <persName corresp="#p_CMS1">Marshall</persName> stated at Moscow on April 10 as
                                    follows: “When Allied Military Government in Germany is
                                    terminated and a German government is functioning under a
                                    constitution, however, some special provision for the overseeing
                                    of Ruhr resources may be advisable”. This statement was made in
                                    connection with the general conception that the Ruhr area is
                                    only one of the key industrial concentrations of Europe, whose
                                    resources should be equitably shared by European countries. It
                                    was also stated that Germany should have responsibility for
                                    management and operation of Ruhr industries and marketing of
                                    their products, and that only if the Germans act contrary to the
                                    just interests of the other countries should the matter be
                                    referred to an international agency.</p>
                                <p>It is our understanding that the War Department and <gloss target="#t_OMGUS1">OMGUS</gloss> are opposed to any
                                    international controls applicable only to the Ruhr, even in
                                    connection with a peace settlement.</p>
                                <pb facs="1088" n="1054" xml:id="pg_1054"/>
                                <p>In agreement with the War Department, the Department has
                                    instructed Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DLW1">Douglas</persName> that the French proposal on the Ruhr
                                    cannot be considered during the level of industry talks at
                                    London, although we are prepared to discuss it at an appropriate
                                    time and give sympathetic consideration to a solution of this
                                    problem. We told <persName corresp="#p_CWL1">Clayton</persName>
                                    and <persName corresp="#p_DLW1">Douglas</persName> that United
                                    States policy in respect to control of the Ruhr has not yet been
                                    resolved.</p>
                                <p>When <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> was informed
                                    of this essentially negative United States policy, he stated
                                    that no French Government, neither the present one nor any
                                    succeeding one, could agree to a revised level of industry for
                                    Germany, without some assurances as to French security and
                                    access by Europe to the products of the Ruhr.</p>
                                <p>It is believed that the French Government will maintain their
                                    position during the London talks and that a serious crisis will
                                    be precipitated if we insist on the above negative position.</p>
                                <p>The present French proposal is believed to be close to United
                                    States thinking on the Ruhr problem. It appears that the basic
                                    conception behind the American approach to the Ruhr problem at
                                    Moscow may be realized, at least in Western Europe, through the
                                        <persName corresp="#p_CMS1">Marshall</persName> Plan which
                                    aims at a coordinated and equitable utilization of key
                                    industrial resources in the interest of European economic
                                    recovery. The fundamental difference then between the present
                                    French Ruhr proposal and the United States position lies in the
                                    means for assuring the equitable distribution of Ruhr resources.
                                    The French propose positive and direct control through an
                                    international allocations board, whereas the United States
                                    suggest control by an international agency with jurisdiction to
                                    act only upon request and if German administration of the
                                    resources fails to meet just requirements of other countries. It
                                    is clear that the French and United States proposals have one
                                    common objective. They differ only in the method proposed for
                                    accomplishing this objective.</p>
                                <p>Accordingly, the United States and French positions are so close
                                    that it should be possible to formulate an agreement in
                                    principle which would leave for further settlement the method of
                                    accomplishing the common objective. Such an agreement should not
                                    commit us to acceptance of any particular method of
                                    implementation, particularly since we must be mindful of the
                                    fact that the agreement will not come into effect until a much
                                    later date, at which time the political conditions of France may
                                    be very different from today. Furthermore, it is believed that
                                    any international control of the Ruhr alone should be limited in
                                    time, on the grounds put forth at the Moscow Conference that it
                                    would be impossible to expect a country to develop along
                                    democratic lines with a group of deeply interested foreign
                                    countries in indefinite control of its prime resources.</p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>