<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The United States Deputy for Germany at the Council of Foreign
                        Ministers (
                        Murphy
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d6</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">6</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-01-25T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-01-25T07:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec_world_war_ii" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="world-war-ii" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148273" lcsh-match="exact">Paris Peace Conference</term>
                    <term ref="recP1TxBSuFrpDZ2S" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="confidence-building-measures" subject="interim-agreement" lcsh-match="no_match">Interim agreement</term>
                    <term ref="rec577cb840b7a9a75" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="potsdam-agreement">Potsdam Agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Reparations</term>
                    <term ref="rec8b79a8b95ce4a65" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="atlantic-charter">Atlantic Charter</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-01-25T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-01-25T07:00:00-05:00" n="6" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d6">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Council/1–2547: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Deputy for Germany at the Council of Foreign
                        Ministers</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MRD1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-01-25T12:00:00+00:00">January 25, 1947—noon</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>531. <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1140 from <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>. Although <persName corresp="#p_GFT1">Gousev</persName> in high-handed exercise of deputies chairmanship
                    Wednesday evening<note n="20" xml:id="d6fn1">The 6th Meeting of the Deputies for
                        Germany, January 23, 1947, 3:30 p.m.</note> unilaterally instructed
                    Secretary General <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> to notify Australian
                    representative that he could not speak on procedural question. <persName corresp="#p_HCWR1">Hodgson</persName>, Australian Minister to France, at
                    January 23 hearing presented Australian views in uninhibited fashion, mixing
                    some remarks on substantial German issues with lengthy consideration of
                    procedural question.<note n="21" xml:id="d6fn2">Minister <persName corresp="#p_HCWR1">Hodgson</persName>’s statement of the general views
                        of the Australian Government on the preparation of the peace treaty with
                        Germany was subsequently circulated to the Deputies for Germany as document
                            <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>(D) (47) (G)25, January 24, 1947, not
                        printed. The views of the Australian Government on the substance of a German
                        settlement were set forth in a memorandum circulated to the Deputies for
                        Germany as document <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>(D) (47) (G)61,
                        February 14, 1947, not printed. Summaries of the views of the Australian
                        Government on the principal aspects of the German problem were included in
                        the Report by the Deputies for Germany to the Council of Foreign Ministers,
                        February 25, 1947, <ref target="#pg_40">p. 40</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Australian representative grounded interest of his Government in German problem
                    in fact that twice in 25 years Australia has sent its <pb facs="0044" n="10" xml:id="pg_10"/> manhood overseas to fight in European wars. Australian
                    Government regards as a duty to its people full participation in peace
                    settlement with Germany. His Government was also concerned lest there be
                    repetition of Paris Peace Conference, which had not been preceded by adequate
                    consultation between the four powers and other allies, and where consequently
                    allies had been presented with <hi rend="italic">fait accompli</hi> in form of
                    agreed clauses, with no amendment possible unless four powers agreed.</p>
                <p>Australian Government appreciates fact that in contrast with Paris procedure,
                    views of active belligerents are now being heard at start of consideration
                    German problem. He requested adoption of liberal attitude toward Australian
                    proposal regarding procedure for hearings. (<gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1112, January 16; <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss>
                    1115, January 17<note n="22" xml:id="d6fn3">Telegram 315, <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1112, January 16, from London, is
                        printed on <ref target="#pg_5">p. 5</ref>. Telegram 346, <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1115, January 17, from London, is not
                        printed, but see footnote 11, <ref target="#pg_6">p. 6</ref>.</note>). Three
                    major requests were: (1) Access to all documentation by representatives of
                    countries invited to hearings; (2) Presence at all hearings of representatives
                    of all invited countries; (3) Participation of representatives in general
                    discussion with deputies. Allied countries in question can only play useful part
                    in preparation of German peace settlement, if they engage in discussion of
                    issues and are enabled thereby obtain from outset clear picture of views of
                    others. Australian representative declared that two major facts regarding German
                    problem had to be taken into account: (1) There is no government in Germany,
                    similar to government in Italy and Austria. The longer Germany remains divided
                    in separate zones, more remote becomes time when there will be one German
                    Government to accept terms of peace settlement. (2) Germans are at present unfit
                    to govern themselves. Nothing would be worse than to hasten formation of central
                    German Government in order, for convenience of certain allies, to enable early
                    signing of peace treaty. A German Government forced prematurely to sign peace
                    treaty would, as consequence, lose at once confidence of German people and would
                    be set aside as happened in period after Versailles.</p>
                <p>Before propitious time for a peace treaty is reached, interim agreement signed by
                    all allies and imposed on Germans is needed. This interim agreement should
                    establish central German administration, not central government, and outline
                    form of future German state. Such interim agreement is necessitated because
                    impossible to distinguish between problems properly those of AC eventual peace
                    treaty and problems properly those of current occupational administration.
                    Interim agreement is envisaged as an enlarged Potsdam agreement, having what
                    Potsdam lacked, the authority and sanction of all belligerents.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="11" xml:id="pg_11"/>
                <p>Australian representative assumed <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> would work
                    out general principles for interim agreement and peace settlement at Moscow.
                    Regarding association and consultation of active belligerents with four powers,
                    he proposed following: (1) Active belligerents would comment upon and discuss
                    with deputies general directive received from <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>. (2) Assuming diverse committees would be set up under
                    deputies, e.g. political and territorial, disarmament and security, reparations
                    and restitution, etc., representatives of active belligerents would be closely
                    associated in work of some or all of these committees.</p>
                <p>Australian representative regarded fixing of German frontier as major political
                    issue. He urged decisions be based on Atlantic Charter and Charter of UN, with
                    reservation respecting application Article II of Atlantic Charter<note n="23" xml:id="d6fn4">The reference here is to the Joint Statement by President
                            <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> and Prime Minister
                            <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName>, August 14, 1941, <ref target="frus1941v01#pg_367">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1941, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 367</ref>. For documentation regarding
                        the preparation of the Atlantic Charter, see <ref target="frus1941v01#pg_341">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 341</ref> ff.</note> to Germany in
                    view of security and certain economic considerations. Regarding how obtain
                    facts, information should be obtained by above-mentioned committees from Allied
                    Control Authority in Germany. Final decision on such questions as eastern
                    frontier, Saar, etc., should rest with full conference of all belligerents.
                    There should be full discussion of final text and free right to introduce
                    amendments. However, this stage should be a formal matter, since through
                    continuous consultation appropriate unanimity should have been achieved. In
                    closing, Australian representative emphasized that above are his general
                    comments on German problem, that later Australian Govt will present views on
                    specific aspects.</p>
                <p>Referring to Australian representatives remarks on question of procedure, Soviet
                    deputy insisted deputies were acting under precise instructions from <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> in New York and deputies were not instructed to
                    discuss substance of German problem now but just to hear views. Also he objected
                    strenuously to Australian charge that Allied powers were presented with <hi rend="italic">fait accompli</hi> at Paris, since four powers had only
                    prepared drafts, respecting which Paris Conference had full opportunity to make
                    comments and many proposals of Paris Conference had been accepted for inclusion
                    in final treaties.</p>
                <p>When Australian representative interposed that he could not understand why four
                    powers had arrogated to themselves authority to draft peace treaties, <persName corresp="#p_GFT1">Gousev</persName> answered that this right had been bought
                    with great amount of blood. He declared that apparently Australian
                    representative was not pleased with agreement between four powers on peace
                    treaty, insinuating that Australian representative does not desire see continued
                    cooperation in peace of four powers. <persName corresp="#p_HCWR1">Hodgson</persName> hotly rejected <persName corresp="#p_GFT1">Gousev</persName>’s insinuation as misconstruction of Australian view.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="12" xml:id="pg_12"/>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> welcomed closest association with
                    Australian representatives as with representatives of all other allies in our
                    work here pointing out that the closer the association of all the Allies in the
                    preparation of the peace settlement, the closer will be their cooperation in
                    enforcing peace treaty. British deputies voiced sympathy with Australian view on
                    question of procedure for current hearings as well as later meetings and
                    promised to do best to secure final solution along such lines. Deputies
                    discussed how answer letter dated January 20 from Canadian High Commissioner
                        (<gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1128, January 22<note n="24" xml:id="d6fn5">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_7">p. 7</ref>.</note>,) since
                    High Commissioner has sent further letter asking postponement Canadian hearings
                    scheduled afternoon January 25, in view no response to his letter of January 20.
                    Soviet deputy declared no assurances of any kind could be given Canadian Govt re
                    future opportunity to discuss German settlement either with deputies or with
                        <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>. I suggested that Canadian Govt did not
                    desire formal guarantee but rather indication of type of discussion they can
                    expect to have with <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> or deputies, in
                    particular re London hearings and that in answer we should offer them benefit of
                    as full discussion of German problem here as could be agreed to by all deputies.
                    Although deputies unable agree on tenor of answer, Secretary General was
                    instructed to draft a reply for consideration at next meeting.<note n="25" xml:id="d6fn6">Telegram 629, <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1157,
                        January 29, from London, not printed, reported that the Deputies for
                        Germany, at their 9th Meeting, January 28, had been unable to agree upon a
                        written response to the Canadian letter. The Deputies agreed, however, that
                        the Chairman should orally inform the Canadian High Commissioner that the
                        instructions to the Deputies would not permit giving the assurance on the
                        question raised by the Canadian Government but that the Deputies would be
                        glad to hear the Canadian views (740.00119 Council/1–2947).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Deputies will hear views of South African representative afternoon January 24 and
                    of Yugoslav representative afternoon January 25.<note n="26" xml:id="d6fn7">
                        <p>The views of the South African Government were presented to the Deputies
                            for Germany at their 7th Meeting, January 24, by <persName corresp="#p_SEK1">E. K. Scallan</persName>, Acting South African
                            High Commissioner in the United Kingdom. Summaries of the views of the
                            South African Government on the principal aspects of the German problem
                            were included in the Report by the Deputies for Germany to the Council
                            of Foreign Ministers, February 25, 1947, <ref target="#pg_40">p.
                                40</ref>. The South African Delegation also presented to the
                            Deputies for Germany a memorandum outlining proposals for the
                            association of the active belligerent Powers with the further
                            considerations on the problem of Germany. This memorandum, which was
                            subsequently circulated to the Deputies as document <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>(D) (47) (G) 26, January 28, 1947, not
                            printed, set forth proposals similar to those already advanced by the
                            Australian Government.</p>
                        <p>The Yugoslav representatives made their presentation at the 9th Meeting
                            of the Deputies for Germany, January 28. Summaries of the views of the
                            Yugoslav Government on the principal aspects of the German problem were
                            also included in the Report of the Deputies for Germany.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Repeated <gloss target="#t_USPolAd1">USPolAd</gloss> Berlin 38.</p>
                <closer>[<signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
