<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Minutes of a Conversation between the Secretary of State and
                        the President of France (
                        Auriol
                    )
                        The source text is accompanied by a cover sheet from the American Embassy
                            in Paris reading as follows: 
                                “The following is a free translation of the French minutes of
                                    conversation between Secretary of State Marshall, and President
                                        Auriol and Monsieur
                                        Teitgen, Acting
                                    Foreign Minister, of France, which has been cleared by both, and
                                    text of which was only completed and given to us late this
                                    afternoon, March 8.”
                            
                        
                        According to telegram 1036, March 7, from Paris, not printed, the
                            Secretary of State, who arrived in Paris at 12:40 p. m. March 6, called
                            on President Auriol and Acting
                            Foreign Minister Teitgen at 6:30
                            p. m. The Secretary left Paris by plane for Germany at 2 p.m. March 7
                            (740.00119 Council/3–747).</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d71</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">71</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-03-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="71" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d71">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Council/3–647</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of a Conversation between the Secretary of State and
                        the President of France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_AV2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Auriol</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="58" xml:id="d71fn1">
                        <p>The source text is accompanied by a cover sheet from the American Embassy
                            in Paris reading as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The following is a free translation of the French minutes of
                                    conversation between Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName>, and President
                                        <persName corresp="#p_AV2">Auriol</persName> and Monsieur
                                        <persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Teitgen</persName>, Acting
                                    Foreign Minister, of France, which has been cleared by both, and
                                    text of which was only completed and given to us late this
                                    afternoon, March 8.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>According to telegram 1036, March 7, from Paris, not printed, the
                            Secretary of State, who arrived in Paris at 12:40 p. m. March 6, called
                            on President <persName corresp="#p_AV2">Auriol</persName> and Acting
                            Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Teitgen</persName> at 6:30
                            p. m. The Secretary left Paris by plane for Germany at 2 p.m. March 7
                            (740.00119 Council/3–747).</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-03-06">March 6,
                            1947</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>After having welcomed General <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName>,
                    personally and in the name of the French people, <hi rend="smallcaps">President
                            <persName corresp="#p_AV2">Auriol</persName>
                    </hi> said:</p>
                <p>“Monsieur <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName>, as you know, was obliged
                    to leave for Moscow before you arrived, but I know you will see a great deal of
                    him there.</p>
                <p>“Actually France is faced with two grave problems: reconstruction and security.
                    With your aid, the people of France have made considerable efforts. They must
                    accomplish even more. The installation of our permanent democratic institutions,
                    the agreement which exists among the different elements of our government, the
                    efforts of <persName>Leon Blum</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RP1">Ramadier</persName>, have allowed us to begin our uphill climb; but the
                    French people are still subject to harsh privations which, if prolonged too
                    long, could give birth to uneasiness, leading in the political realm to further
                    uncertainty with grave consequences.</p>
                <p>“Our problem, General <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName>, is coal.
                    Our annual production is actually 50 million tons, which exceeds the production
                    of 1938. At that time we imported 25 million tons: at the present time we no
                    longer receive such importations. In 1946 we imported 12 million tons: 6 million
                    from the United States and 6 million from Poland and Germany. In 1938 we had at
                    our disposal 73 million tons; we now have only 61 million tons. To reach the
                    total figures of 1938, which we need in order to exist, we must find 12 million
                    more tons: to commence our work of reconstruction we need much more than this.
                    Furthermore, I should add that we were able to produce 50 million tons of coal
                    by utilizing labor furnished by prisoners of war. If this labor is taken away
                    from us we must further increase our importations. The most modest estimate of
                    our vital coal needs for this year is an importation from Germany of 500,000
                    tons per month, and for next year 1,000,000 tons per month. We do not wish to
                    deal a death blow to Germany, but it seems to us that the figures I have just
                    given only represent what equity calls for. It would be useful, I believe, to
                    study the conditions necessary to increase the production of the Ruhr mines, and
                    it seems to <pb facs="0225" n="191" xml:id="pg_191"/> me desirable that American
                    and French technicians be consulted in this regard. The new formula of coal
                    distribution recently adopted does not seem to have taken into account the
                    promises which were made by the British Foreign Minister.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Monsieur <persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Teitgen</persName>
                    </hi>, Acting Foreign Minister, then continued:</p>
                <p>“The situation is actually as follows: our minimum coal requirements of German
                    coal for 1947 are 500,000 tons per month, and we are actually receiving 235,000
                    tons. Germany is only exporting 10 per cent of its production and of that
                    percentage France is only receiving 235,000 tons per month, which is less than
                    half of our indispensable minimum requirements. In recent conversations, though
                    it is true there were no formal engagements, it was understood that if (German)
                    production was increased the percentage made available for export would also be
                    increased. Production has increased, and we were hoping to have the allocation
                    of coal to France increased in the same proportion. We have obtained an increase
                    of 25,000 tons per month, making a total monthly allocation of 260,000 tons,
                    which is entirely insufficient. (<persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Teitgen</persName>
                    added that allocations are already fixed for March, April and May.)</p>
                <p>“In such conditions, the problem is a vital political question for France. Our
                    entire reconstruction is in the balance. The future of our country can depend on
                    the negotiations being conducted regarding Germany. If essential dispositions
                    are not taken in time, Germany will be restored much more quickly than France.
                    This question of French reconstruction and of German reconstruction dominates,
                    in my opinion, the political picture. If we were to receive precise guarantees
                    on coal, the political problems themselves would perhaps appear to us more
                    simple. (<persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Teitgen</persName>’s remark actually was:
                    ‘If the United States could find a way to meet French views on German coal
                    exports, the French would find it possible to go along with the United States
                    views on other German problems’.)</p>
                <p>“It is for this reason that the French Government instructed <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName>, who represents France at Moscow, to
                    raise the question of coal before considering the other political and economic
                    problems concerning Germany.</p>
                <p>“Such is the French situation in so far as reconstruction is concerned. This
                    question is not a purely French problem, but exists for all Europe. In all
                    equity, Germany should not be reconstructed before France and the other
                    countries that it ravaged. I will add that a strong France is indispensable to
                    Europe and the world, a France surrounded by members of the French union, and I
                    should like to say in passing that I formulate the wish that as a result of the
                    efforts which we have made to create democratic and fraternal ties between
                    members of this same <pb facs="0226" n="192" xml:id="pg_192"/> family (French
                    Union), to see disappear the difficulties in this regard which have arisen in
                    the organization of the United Nations.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The President</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_AV2">Auriol</persName>), who (said he) did not want to refer in detail to the
                    various memoranda given by the Foreign Minister to the diplomatic
                    representatives of the Governments of the United States, of the United Kingdom
                    and of the Soviet Union concerning the future organization of Germany and of the
                    Ruhr, reminded General <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName> of the
                    unanimous agreement reached in the French Parliament concerning these documents
                    and concerning French foreign policy in general. He said he would limit himself,
                    if he might, to a reference to his already ancient recollections as a
                    statesman:</p>
                <p>“I must admit”, said the President of the Republic, “that in 1919 I believed in
                    the strength of democracy in Germany, and, a Socialist myself, I believed in
                    social democracy. I was convinced that a democratic spirit could develop in
                    vanquished Germany. Nothing came of it. I would not like us to make the same
                    mistakes once again. Doubtless the Versailles Treaty specified that weapons of
                    all kinds would be turned over to the Allied powers and reports of Marshal
                        <persName>Foch</persName> and of General <persName>Nollet</persName> had
                    allowed room for some optimism. The German armed forces for the (German)
                    territory as a whole had been reduced to 100,000 men. This figure was soon
                    increased to 200,000 men by the SPA decisions. Weapons, most of them, under
                    pressure of the Control Commissions, were surrendered but Germany, preserving
                    her industrial potential, was nevertheless capable of building modern and
                    efficient weapons. Adopting the theories which <persName>Jean Jaures</persName>
                    had expressed in <hi rend="italic">The New Army</hi>, the German staff taught
                    the small army at its disposal and turned it into a remarkable cadre of
                    officers. At the right moment the Third Reich found troops which had received
                    their physical training in sport clubs and in youth organizations, troops whose
                    morale had been built up in the German schools. At the opportune moment the
                    industrial trusts and the banks gave their support to the spirit of revenge and
                    aggression which smashed democracy. A Germany, stronger than ever, had sprung up
                    from the Treaty of Versailles. It is no longer possible to leave Germany the
                    possibility of using similar methods and of transforming tomorrow its police
                    forces into instruction cadres and to rebuild its military potential. We
                    consider (continued the President) that centralized power in Germany constitutes
                    a real danger for peace in the constitutional period. It is not necessary to
                    refer to the Weimar Constitution and to where this constitution led Germany.
                    Federalism could be a remedy to the danger of centralization. It is not possible
                    for the security of Europe to leave the Ruhr in the hands of industrial
                    magnates. Only international control could remove this danger. M. <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Georges Bidault</persName> will go into greater <pb facs="0227" n="193" xml:id="pg_193"/> detail, but it was appropriate that I
                    should point out the lessons gained from a bitter and painful personal
                    experience and from the aggression of a nation which can once again think of
                    revenge tomorrow.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName>
                    </hi> then spoke. He first took up the question of coal.</p>
                <p>“I am happy to be here”, said the Secretary of State. “I came to Paris purposely
                    to obtain first hand information concerning the situation of France, the state
                    of her economy and of her reconstruction and to gather also at first hand
                    information concerning the reorganization of Europe. Many things which I shall
                    tell you, Mr. President, I have already said to the Prime Minister a half an
                    hour ago.</p>
                <p>“I would like you to be convinced that I realize perfectly well the critical
                    character of the present situation. I know that France wishes to secure that
                    efficient tranquility which would permit her to restore her economy. I will not
                    go into any details, Mr. President. I intend to meet with General <persName corresp="#p_CLD1">Clay</persName> in Berlin, to inform myself concerning the
                    coal problem in Germany and in France. I trust, Mr. President, that you not lose
                    sight of the fact that I fully appreciate the privations and the sufferings of
                    the people of France and the consequences which may result from them. I spent
                    two and one-half years in France myself during the First World War. Two of these
                    years before joining General <persName>Pershing</persName> I spent in the
                    country side by side with artisans, workers and peasants. I was able to gauge
                    the work of destruction wrought by the Germans and the sufferings and the
                    courage of the French population. I was in France some while back during the
                    recent battles and once again I saw German destruction and French suffering.
                    During the entire occupation of your country, Mr. President, and within the
                    field of the responsibilities which had been assigned to me, the liberation of
                    France was my great concern. I can tell you without boasting that among the men
                    who are not Frenchmen I know as much as anyone else about the sufferings of this
                    country, about its present situation and its worries. It is through my own
                    personal experience that I look at your problems perfectly conscious of the
                    situation wrought in France through the fault of Germany.</p>
                <p>“I come back to the question of coal. I want to be informed about this. I was
                    happy to obtain directly your views on this matter. I would like to say that I
                    shall give it my full attention.</p>
                <p>“As you just did a few moments ago, Mr. President, I am taking the liberty to
                    refer to the political reactions to which you have alluded. We, representatives
                    of the American Government, must take into consideration the situation of the
                    occupied nations as well as of the liberated nations. It is a question of
                    finding a balance between the urgent needs of France and the urgent needs of
                    Germany. There is the <pb facs="0228" n="194" xml:id="pg_194"/> question of
                    avoiding that the United States of America be compelled to continue paying the
                    heavy contributions which Germany is now costing the American taxpayer. The
                    situation is the same in Japan. The problem is not an easy one for in addition
                    it is a question of finding a happy balance between these political and economic
                    considerations and the political situation within the United States.</p>
                <p>“I must therefore size up, with precision, France’s situation and gather
                    information from our representatives in Germany.</p>
                <p>“I must be able to inform American public opinion in order to justify what we
                    shall decide to do. In France there are very direct reactions towards
                    Germany—reactions which are not easy to guide from a governmental point of view.
                    I realize that this state of affairs renders difficult any satisfactory
                    solution.</p>
                <p>“I can assure you, Mr. President, that I shall forget nothing of what you have
                    told me and more particularly of what you have told me concerning the problem of
                    coal. I shall take it up at once with our representatives in Berlin. It is an
                    urgent question which belongs to today and not to tomorrow.</p>
                <p>“I now come to the problem on security. The President of the Council of Ministers
                    reminded me of France’s painful experiences.<note n="59" xml:id="d71fn2">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName> had a
                        forty-minute meeting with French Premier <persName corresp="#p_RP1">Ramadier</persName> just prior to his conversation with President
                            <persName corresp="#p_AV2">Auriol</persName>. A translation of the
                        French minutes of the meeting with <persName corresp="#p_RP1">Ramadier</persName> were sent to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName> by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName> on March 17, 1947 (711.51/3–1747). In his
                        conversation with <persName corresp="#p_RP1">Ramadier</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName> emphasized the importance the
                        United States placed in the strengthening of the United Nations and in the
                        conclusion of the proposed Four-Power treaty on German disarmament.</note>
                    The Government of the United States places vital importance on the question of
                    providing for security until the organization of the United Nations becomes
                    sufficiently strong. We believe that security lies in a treaty signed by the
                    four major powers. Any regional agreement such as the one which has been signed
                    recently at Dunkirk must, we believe, come within the framework of a wider
                    security. It is this basic security that a treaty between the four powers could
                    insure. This treaty implies the commitment of the American Government, which
                    means a complete change of American policy when compared to the events which
                    followed the First World War. Rather than separate proposals, it would be
                    desirable to have such a document define the control clauses over German war
                    potential and establish the broad principles of disarmament and of
                    demilitarization.</p>
                <p>“I know what happened after Versailles. I was placed in charge of a school with
                    400 officer students, most of whom have since taken part as officers in high
                    command, in the liberation of your country. At that time we could know nothing
                    of what was going on in Germany: the War Department had no information on the
                    subject. I decided to send <pb facs="0229" n="195" xml:id="pg_195"/> to Europe
                    some of my professors on their vacations. One of them visited <persName>von
                        Blumberg</persName>, who was in command in East Prussia. This officer
                    brought back to us information which left no doubt as to the intensive
                    development of German aviation. This was later brought to the world’s attention
                    by the Lindbergh visit to Germany and attendant publicity. That was in 1931. All
                    of these military visitors agreed as to the military training to which German
                    youth was subjected and as to the use of the methods about which you have just
                    spoken: the Germans were training 100,000 officers. I know these German methods:
                    just like compulsory military service, they date back to the Napoleonic
                    wars.</p>
                <p>“Mr. President, once again I come back to the necessity of guaranteeing security.
                    An agreement is needed which offers reasonable guarantees and which can assure
                    lasting peace in Europe: and that agreement is to be found in the Four Power
                    treaty. I am not a diplomat: I mean exactly what I say and there is no use
                    trying to read between the lines because there is nothing to be read there.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
