<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>15. Note From Soviet Leaders to President to President Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-02-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Détente</term>
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recAynYh8uzxYGQRH" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Strategic arms</term>
                    <term ref="recMrVNgNJpQ8DjcR" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037301"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deterrence</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="recr08QgEMEm1Bk04" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011308"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ballistic missiles</term>
                    <term ref="recMqCyaCVCS2rBsP" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Equal security</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec43c89ba39282f56" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="vietnam-conflict" subject="vietnam-conflict">Vietnam conflict</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-02-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="15"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d15">
                <head>15. Note From <gloss type="from">Soviet Leaders</gloss> to President <persName
                        corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d15fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 340, Subject Files, <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> Memcons <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                            >Dobrynin</persName>/President 2/17/69. No classification marking. On
                        January 31, <persName corresp="#p_SB2">Sedov</persName> told <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> that the Soviets were
                        “considering putting out ‘something’ to indicate they will not use the
                            <gloss target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss> as an excuse for intervening in the
                        domestic affairs of others” and that they “are also putting together a
                        ‘package’ on their views re political settlement. <persName
                            corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> may bring this back with him about
                        February 15.” (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                        1967–69, POL 1 <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>) This note was the
                        “package” promised <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and
                        given him by <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> on February 17.
                        The date is handwritten on the note.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1969-02-17"
                            >February 17, 1969</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The attention has been paid in Moscow to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                        >Nixon</persName>’s statements in which he set forth his views on questions
                    of peace and international cooperation.</p>
                <p>As is known, the Soviet Union pursues and will pursue the policy of peace. We are
                    prepared to develop relations of peaceful cooperation with all states which on
                    their part strive for the same end, and we think that if both the Soviet Union
                    and the United States in their actions proceed from exactly that principle
                    basis, thereby there will be created the widest opportunities for mutual
                    agreement and Soviet-American cooperation in solving the urgent international
                    problems. We would like to particularly stress here, that although the great
                    powers <pb facs="0076" n="43" xml:id="pg_43"/> bear special responsibility for
                    preserving peace, in their intentions and actions they—like all other
                    participants of international intercourse—must respect the inherent rights of
                    other states, big and small, for sovereign and independent development, they
                    must proceed from the real situation existing in the world. If you agree with
                    such understanding of major principles of our relations, we on our part can
                    fully subscribe to your statement to the effect that “after a period of
                    confrontation, we are entering an era of negotiation”.</p>
                <p>That is what we would like to say to the President right now in order to exclude
                    any misunderstanding on the American side of our approach to one or another
                    question.</p>
                <p>We do not see any other principle basis on which the Soviet-American relations
                    could be built in the present world.</p>
                <p>We are deeply convinced that if such approach be followed then despite all
                    differences of views, social and political systems and of state interests there
                    can be no such situation that would lead with fatal inevitability to direct
                    confrontation between our countries.</p>
                <p>All this, of course, presumes a certain level of confidence and mutual
                    understanding that should also be present in searching ways to solving urgent
                    world problems. It implies, of course, not only formal agreements but also
                    opportunities provided by parallel or complementary actions including those
                    based on the principle of “mutual example” and so on.</p>
                <p>We are convinced that by their mutual efforts the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss> and the USA together with other states could achieve a
                    situation when international negotiations would serve first of all the purpose
                    of preventing conflicts rather than finding ways out of them after peace and
                    international security had already been endangered. It is of particular
                    significance also because there are a lot of temptations to set our countries
                    against each other. It may cause additional complicating elements in the process
                    of development of Soviet-American relations which is not simple even as it
                    is.</p>
                <p>At present there has accumulated a number of big international problems which are
                    under discussion now, and the peoples have been waiting for a long time for
                    their solution in the interests of consolidation of peace.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">First</hi>. We believe that all possible efforts
                            should be made to have the Treaty on non-proliferation of nuclear
                            weapons start effectively operating. This is a question of war and peace
                            of the future. The Treaty that had been worked out to a considerable
                            degree due to the joint efforts of the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                                >USSR</gloss> and the USA has not been signed yet by a number of
                            states and this, naturally, strengthens the positions of the opponents
                            of the Treaty and casts doubts upon the possibility of solving the
                            problem of non-proliferation. If, however, a number of nuclear states
                            grow <pb facs="0077" n="44" xml:id="pg_44"/> the risk of new conflicts
                            will increase with most dangerous consequences for universal peace.</p>
                        <p>In Moscow, there is readiness to continue consultations with the U.S.
                            Government to work out coordinated measures on securing the signing of
                            the Treaty by a maximum number of states and its earliest entering into
                            force.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Second</hi>. It is believed in Moscow that the
                            termination of the war in Vietnam providing the Vietnamese people with
                            the opportunity to solve their internal affairs by themselves without
                            any interference from outside will not only eliminate the most dangerous
                            hotbed of war tension in the world, but also will serve as a convincing
                            proof of a real possibility for settling even most acute and difficult
                            problems. It is hardly doubtful that the political settlement of the
                            Vietnam conflict on the basis of respect for legitimate national
                            aspirations of the people of that country and the complete withdrawal of
                            the American troops from the territory of Vietnam will affect in a most
                            positive way the Soviet-American relations.</p>
                        <p>The Soviet Government welcomed the beginning of the Paris talks aimed at
                            the political settlement of the Vietnam problem and it thinks that these
                            talks should continue. We would like the talks to bring about positive
                            results. This will be possible, of course, only if there is a realistic
                            appraisal of the political forces acting in Vietnam and the recognition
                            of their right for equal position in the negotiations. If the Paris
                            negotiations develop in such a direction we shall render them all and
                            every support.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Third</hi>. Great anxiety is caused by the tense and
                            unsettled situation in the Middle East. We have already presented to
                            President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> our views on the
                            causes of the situation created there that may lead to most undesirable
                            consequences not only for the states of this area but far away outside
                            it. The Soviet Government seeking for durable peace and security in this
                            area with due regard for legitimate rights and interests of the Arab
                            states—victims of aggression, put forward a concrete plan for the
                            settlement there which fully corresponds to the spirit and content of
                            the resolution unanimously adopted by the Security Council on November
                            22, 1967.<note n="2" xml:id="d15fn2">See <ref target="#d2fn4">footnote
                                    4, Document 2</ref>.</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> has been informed about
                            this plan.</p>
                        <p>We proceed from the necessity, on the one hand, that the Arab territories
                            occupied by Israeli troops be liberated, and, on the other hand, that
                            the existence of Israel as an independent state be guaranteed. If the
                            government of Israel considers these principles unacceptable for the
                            political settlement of the conflict then it means that Israel continues
                            to follow aggressive and expansionist aims and remains on an adventurist
                                <pb facs="0078" n="45" xml:id="pg_45"/> position. Neither Israel nor
                            anyone else can have any reason to expect that the Arab countries and
                            the states supporting them will agree with such Israeli policy.</p>
                        <p>We are confident that if the Soviet Union and the United States combining
                            their efforts with the efforts of other states concerned make full use
                            of their possibilities and influence in order to find just and lasting
                            settlement in the Middle East it will also greatly contribute to the
                            general relaxation of international tensions. We are ready for the
                            exchange of views on the bilateral basis with the U.S. Government on the
                            problems of the Middle East with the aim of achieving the necessary
                            agreement on the settlement of the conflict. We said that before. But
                            for some reasons not depending on the Soviet side such exchange of views
                            didn’t get due development. We also declare our readiness for the
                            exchange of views on the problems of the Middle East among the four
                            powers—permanent members of the Security Council—the <gloss
                                target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, the USA, France and Great
                            Britain.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Fourth</hi>. We are strongly convinced that the
                            following premise has a first-rate importance for the character and
                            prospects of the relations between the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                                >USSR</gloss> and the USA: that is, whether both our countries are
                            ready to proceed in their practical policies from the respect for the
                            foundations of the post-war structure in Europe, formed as a result of
                            the Second World War and the post-war development, and for the basic
                            provisions, formulated by the Allied powers in the well-known Potsdam
                            Agreements. There is no other way to peace in Europe but to take the
                            reality into consideration and to prompt the others to do the same. It’s
                            impossible to regard the attempts to undermine the post-war structure in
                            Europe otherwise than an encroachment on the vital interests of our
                            country, of its friends and allies—the socialist countries.</p>
                        <p>At one time, and in particular in 1959–1963, when the Soviet and U.S.
                            Governments were discussing the complex of German affairs, we were not
                            far apart in understanding of that with regard to some important
                                problems.<note n="3" xml:id="d15fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> wrote “what?” in
                                the margin of this paragraph.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Soviet Union regards with particular watchfulness certain aspects of
                            the development of the F.R.G. and its policy not only because the past
                            German invasion cost us many millions of human lives. President
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> also understands very
                            well that revanchism begins not when the frontier marks start falling
                            down. That’s the finale, the way to which is leading through the
                            attempts to gain an access to the nuclear weapons, through the
                            rehabilitation of the past, through the provocations similar to those
                            which the F.R.G. commits from time to time with regard to West
                            Berlin.</p>
                        <pb facs="0079" n="46" xml:id="pg_46"/>
                        <p>It became almost a rule that the F.R.G. stirs up outbursts of tensions
                            around West Berlin, which didn’t and doesn’t belong to it, involving the
                            Soviet Union, the USA and other countries into complications. It’s
                            hardly in anyone’s interests to give the F.R.G. such a possibility.
                            Anyhow the Soviet Union can’t let the F.R.G. make such provocations.</p>
                        <p>We would like the President to have complete clearness and confidence
                            that the Soviet Union has no goals in Europe other than the
                            establishment of the solid foundations of security in this part of the
                            world, of the relations of détente between the states of East and
                            West.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Fifth</hi>. If we agree that we should aim not at the
                            collision between the USA and the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                            but on the contrary—at the elimination of the war threat, then the
                            containment and curtailing of the arms race and first of all of the
                            rocket—nuclear arms race is necessary. As you know, Mr. President, the
                            stockpiles of nuclear weapons already at the disposal of the <gloss
                                target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and the USA, are more than enough to
                            bring down a catastrophe upon the whole mankind, and this places special
                            responsibility upon the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and the
                            USA before all peoples of the world.</p>
                        <p>A significant step in the field of the containment of the arms race and
                            the reduction of a war threat could be made as it is believed in Moscow
                            through the achievement of an agreement between the <gloss
                                target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and the USA on the limitation and
                            subsequent reduction of strategic arms, both offensive and
                            defensive.</p>
                        <p>In the course of the exchange of views on this question which has already
                            taken place between the Governments of the USA and the <gloss
                                target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> we agreed with the proposal of the
                            American side that the general objectives in this field should be
                            primarily the achievement and maintenance of a stable U.S.-Soviet
                            strategic deterrence by agreeing on limitations on the deployment of
                            offensive and defensive strategic armaments and also the provision of
                            mutual assurance to each of us that our security will be maintained,
                            while at the same time avoiding the tensions, uncertainties and costs of
                            an unrestrained continuation of the strategic arms race.</p>
                        <p>It was also agreed that the limitation and reduction of the strategic
                            arms should be carried out in complex, including both the systems for
                            delivering offensive strategic weapons and the defensive systems against
                            ballistic missiles, and that the limitation and reduction of these arms
                            should be balanced in such a way that neither side could obtain a
                            military advantage and that the equal security for both sides be
                            assured.</p>
                        <p>The Soviet Government confirms its readiness to continue the exchange of
                            views with the U.S. Government on the questions of containment of the
                            strategic arms race.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Sixth</hi>. It would seem that broad and full-scale
                            relations between the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and the USA
                            in the field of international policy should be <pb facs="0080" n="47"
                                xml:id="pg_47"/> accompanied by an adequate scope of their bilateral
                            relations. The mutually advantageous potentialities which exist in this
                            area also speak for the development of connections and cooperation
                            between our countries in most various fields, such as science,
                            technology, economy, culture. The extent of the realization of these
                            potentialities depends, of course, on the general political atmosphere
                            in our relations.</p>
                        <p>If the U.S. Government is of the similar opinion then it could be
                            possible to specifically look upon the opportunities existing now for
                            the further development of the Soviet-American bilateral relations, to
                            determine the succession of things to be done and to proceed with their
                            implementation. As some of the examples, there could be mentioned
                            possibilities for combined efforts in solving urgent problems of
                            medicine, in space research in exploration and exploitation of the World
                            ocean, in creation of the universal satellite communication system,
                            etc.</p>
                        <p>As a whole, it is possible apparently to speak not only about usefulness
                            but also about real feasibility of a constructive dialogue between the
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and the USA on the wide range
                            of questions. Indeed, it is in this sense that in Moscow there were
                            taken President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s
                            statements about the vital importance of the relations between the
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and the USA for the cause of
                            peace and general security, about the necessity to eliminate a
                            possibility of military conflict between our countries and about the
                            preparedness for negotiations with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                                >USSR</gloss> at all levels.</p>
                        <p>The thoughts on the above mentioned questions as well as on other
                            questions which President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                            may wish to express will be considered in Moscow with full
                            attention.</p>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
