<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>28. Letter From President Nixon to Chairman of the Council of Ministers of
                    the Soviet Union to Chairman of the Council of Ministers of the Soviet Union
                    Kosygin</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-03-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-03-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="rec43c89ba39282f56" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="vietnam-conflict" subject="vietnam-conflict">Vietnam conflict</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Disarmament</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-03-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-03-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="28"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                <head>28. Letter From President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="from"
                        >Nixon</persName> to Chairman of the Council of Ministers of the Soviet
                    Union <persName corresp="#p_KAN1" type="to">Kosygin</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d28fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 433, Backchannel
                        Files/Backchannel Messages, <persName corresp="#p_BJD1">Beam</persName>
                        Instructions, 3/26/69 (Amb to Moscow). No classification marking. The date
                        is handwritten. This letter was attached to a March 26 covering memorandum
                        from <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> to <persName
                            corresp="#p_BJD1">Beam</persName>, which is not printed. Also attached
                        but not printed were instructions from <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                            >Nixon</persName> for <persName corresp="#p_BJD1">Beam</persName> to use
                        when he delivered the letter to <persName corresp="#p_KAN1"
                            >Kosygin</persName>. On April 22, <persName corresp="#p_BJD1"
                            >Beam</persName> presented the letter to <persName corresp="#p_KAN1"
                            >Kosygin</persName>; see <ref target="#d40">Document 40</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1969-03-26">March 26, 1969</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Dear Mr. Chairman:</p>
                <p>I should like to use the occasion of Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BJD1"
                        >Beam</persName>’s assumption of his duties as my Ambassador in Moscow to
                    share with you my thoughts on the future of relations between our two
                    countries.</p>
                <p>First of all, I should like to assure you that Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_BJD1">Beam</persName> has my complete confidence and is fully
                    familiar with my views. You may be certain that he will communicate to me
                    promptly and in complete confidence any views that you and your colleagues may
                    wish to convey to me at any time.</p>
                <p>Because of the awesome power our two countries represent we, as heads of
                    government, carry the gravest responsibilities for the peace and safety of the
                    world. I am prepared to explore with you and your colleagues every available
                    avenue for the settlement of international problems, particularly those that
                    involve the danger of confrontation or conflict. I am determined to see us enter
                    an era of negotiations and to leave behind the tensions and confrontations of
                    the past.</p>
                <p>I am encouraged by the contacts that have already been initiated by our two
                    governments on the problems of the Middle East. It is essential that both our
                    countries exert a calming influence on this situation which, <pb facs="0131"
                        n="98" xml:id="pg_98"/> as the past has shown, is fraught with profound
                    dangers for peace not only in the immediate area in question but for the rest of
                    the world. I believe that no outside power must seek advantages in this area at
                    the expense of any other; on the contrary it is, in my view, the duty of all
                    outside powers, especially the great powers, to help create conditions in which
                    the opposing sides can find a solution that protects their essential and
                    legitimate interests, as foreseen in the Security Council resolution of November
                    1967. I believe that the willingness of our two countries to exert a responsible
                    and beneficial influence in the Middle East is an essential element in building
                    the confidence that must be the basis of serious and productive
                    negotiations.</p>
                <p>I am aware of the constructive role which your government has played at certain
                    stages of the search for a peaceful settlement of the Vietnam conflict. I am
                    aware also of the great influence which you possess in North Vietnam by virtue
                    of your military support to that country. In the spirit of candor which I hope
                    will mark communications between us, I would ask you to continue using that
                    great influence in the direction of peace. For peace is what I am striving to
                    achieve, patiently and in a spirit of conciliation. The effort toward peace
                    cannot of course be confined exclusively to the conference table; it must be
                    reflected in Vietnam itself. As Commander in Chief I am responsible for the
                    safety of American troops and I must also meet solemn commitments to the
                    Government of the Republic of South Vietnam. But my country has demonstrated its
                    readiness for moderation that takes into account the legitimate concerns of the
                    Government of North Vietnam. Moderation, however, must be mutual and I believe
                    that you can be influential in that direction. In any event, it is my conviction
                    that the era of negotiation which I believe we both wish to embark upon would be
                    seriously burdened if the day of peace in Southeast Asia cannot be brought
                    closer.</p>
                <p>I believe, Mr. Chairman, that our responsibilities also require the avoidance of
                    crises and the removal of threats to peace in Europe. I was disturbed by the
                    recent flare-up of tensions in Berlin. As I pointed out to your Ambassador, my
                    country is committed to the integrity of West Berlin; it is committed also to
                    fulfilling the obligations and exercising the rights stemming from four-power
                    agreements. Here as elsewhere, unilateral attempts to change the existing
                    situation to the advantage of one side would place obstacles on the road to
                    peace. I believe that any change must be the result of agreement and should
                    improve on the unsatisfactory aspects of the existing situation. If you have
                    suggestions that would make the situation in Berlin mutually more satisfactory,
                    I would, of course, be interested in hearing them.</p>
                <p>More generally with regard to Europe, I would hope that there, too, negotiation
                    rather than confrontation will mark our future relations. I am conscious of the
                    great suffering endured by the Soviet people in the past because war was carried
                    to your soil across your <pb facs="0132" n="99" xml:id="pg_99"/> Western
                    frontier. It is undoubtedly the responsibility of the Soviet Government to
                    ensure that such a disaster does not occur again. At the same time, I am bound
                    to say that last year’s events in Czechoslovakia produced a profound shock in
                    American opinion. Our commitments to our European allies are solely for defense
                    and for the production of their legitimate security interests. This should not
                    be an issue between us.</p>
                <p>As countries with the largest arsenals of modern weapons in the world, we carry a
                    special responsibility for the control of armaments. The era of negotiation to
                    which I have referred must clearly include efforts toward disarmament. I am
                    confident that progress toward the solution of the great political problems that
                    engage our interests can be matched by progress toward curbing competition in
                    arms; for there can be no doubt that such competition, especially if
                    unrestrained, is utterly wasteful and would not, ultimately, enhance anyone’s
                    security. I can assure you that my decisions in this area will be guided solely
                    by the principle of “sufficiency,” that is, by the principle that our military
                    strength will be only that which is required to ensure the safety of this
                    country and meet the commitments to our allies. We base this on the assumption
                    that you will adhere to a similar policy for your country. Military requirements
                    depend, among other things, on the crises and dangers that confront us in the
                    world. As the dangers recede, I am convinced so can the levels of arms in our
                    arsenals. These are the simple and, I believe, realistic principles that will
                    guide me in negotiations on disarmament. It is my sincere hope that in the years
                    of my Administration you and we can increasingly cooperate so that the burden of
                    arms that our people bear can be lessened.</p>
                <p>If I may sum up the approach to our relations that I have sought to convey to you
                    in this message, it is simply that I intend to safeguard the interests of my
                    country with due regard to the interests of yours; that in this spirit we should
                    join together, wherever and whenever possible, to curb the dangers and eliminate
                    the sources of conflict. I would like to remain in frequent and candid
                    communication with you through our Ambassadors and otherwise; my representatives
                    stand ready, and indeed have already begun, to explore with you the whole range
                    of issues that confront us and the means to make our relations increasingly
                    cooperative and constructive.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Richard Nixon</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
