<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>52. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Kissinger) to the President’s Assistant for Domestic Affairs () to the
                    President’s Assistant for Domestic Affairs (Ehrlichman))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d52</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">52</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-06-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-06-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recORcNZq5ClDOVNg" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046356"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exhibit</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-06-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-06-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="52"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d52">
                <head>52. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>) to the
                    President’s Assistant for Domestic Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_EJD1"
                        type="to">Ehrlichman</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d52fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 709,
                        Country Files, Europe, <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, Vol. II. No
                        classification marking. Sent for information. Drafted by Lesh on June 2.
                        Sent under a covering memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_SHH1"
                            >Sonnenfeldt</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> with the recommendation that he sign it. <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> signed the memorandum; an
                        invitation to Khrushchev was apparently never issued.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1969-06-05">June 5, 1969</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Comment on Suggested Invitation to Khrushchev</item>
                </list>
                <p>I am afraid Bill Safire is being optimistic when he calculates that his
                    suggestion has one chance in a hundred of working out.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d52fn2">On May 28, William Safire, speechwriter to President
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, sent the following message
                        to <persName corresp="#p_HHR1">Haldeman</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_EJD1">Ehrlichman</persName>: “Here is a far-out thought with
                        a chance in a hundred of working out. We are planning some kind of reunion
                        celebrating the 10th anniversary of the Kitchen Conference on July 24. What
                        about approaching the Soviet[s] about inviting Khrushchev? Not so wild as it
                        sounds—they might just go along if it suits their interests.” (Ibid.)</note>
                    I do not <pb facs="0206" n="173" xml:id="pg_173"/> think there is any chance
                    that the Soviets would permit Khrushchev to come to the US for a reunion of the
                    participants of the 1959 “Kitchen Debate,”<note n="3" xml:id="d52fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> attended the American
                        Exhibition in Moscow in July 1959. During a stop in the model kitchen at the
                        Exhibition, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and Khrushchev had
                        an impromptu debate, over the relative merits of each nation’s economic
                        system. <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s description of the
                        “Kitchen Debate” is in <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss target="#t_RN1">RN</gloss>: The Memoirs of <persName
                                corresp="#p_NRM1">Richard Nixon</persName>
                        </hi>, pp. 208–209.</note> and in fact I recommended against sending an
                    invitation, for the following reasons: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Khrushchev is close to being an un-person in the <gloss
                                target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. In a great advance over past Soviet
                            practices, he is still alive and is fed and housed in comfort. But he is
                            a political pariah, allowed one brief and closely guarded public
                            appearance each November to vote in his local district elections.
                            Knowing Khrushchev’s penchant for oratory, the Soviets would never
                            permit him to travel abroad, especially to the US.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Furthermore, since Khrushchev was deposed by a coup in 1964, it would
                            be diplomatically unwise either to ask the current Kremlin leaders—who
                            were his deposers—to let him come to Washington, or to circumvent them
                            by asking Khrushchev directly. (As you may know, the present leaders
                            have bridled at previous attempts by prominent Americans to contact
                            Khrushchev.)</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>In general I recommend that you place the major emphasis in your plans on the
                    tenth anniversary of the first US national exhibit in Moscow and the President’s
                    trip to the Soviet Union, rather than on the “Kitchen Debate” per se. While we
                    look back on the episode with a certain nostalgia, the Soviets do not regard the
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>–Khrushchev encounter as one of
                    the high points in Soviet-American relations. In fact the “Kitchen Debate” was
                    associated in the past with a strong anti-<persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                        >Nixon</persName> line in the Soviet press—now conveniently forgotten.
                    Because of these overtones, the Soviets might not even let Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> participate unless we characterize the
                    occasion as commemorating the President’s trip as a whole (rather than only the
                    “Kitchen Debate”).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
