<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>99. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d99</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">99</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-11-06T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-11-06T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077241"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Linkage</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-11-06T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-11-06T12:00:00-05:00" n="99"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d99">
                <head>99. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d99fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 711,
                        Country Files, Europe, <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, Vol. VI. Top
                        Secret; Sensitive; <gloss target="#t_NODIS1">Nodis</gloss>. The conversation
                        was held in <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s office.
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> sent this memorandum of
                        conversation to the President under a November 24 covering note.
                        (Ibid.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1969-11-06T12:00:00-05:00"
                            >November 6, 1969</date>, noon.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>I began the conversation by saying that the President had wanted to make sure
                    that <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> understood the speech<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d99fn2">On November 3, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                            >Nixon</persName> gave an address to the nation on Vietnam that was
                        broadcast on national television. The address came to be known as the
                        “silent majority speech,” for <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s
                        appeal for support for his policy from “the great silent majority of
                        Americans” to counter the large-scale anti-Vietnam war demonstrations. For
                        text, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                                >Nixon</persName>
                        </hi>, 1969, pp. 901–909. For additional background information, see <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v06#d144">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume VI, Vietnam,
                            January 1969–July 1970, Document 144</ref>.</note> properly: (1) the
                    President wanted to point out the seriousness of the threat in case of
                    escalation; (2) that <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> should not
                    be confused by the various arguments he had heard with respect to linkage—we
                    considered linkage a fact and not a policy, and foreign policy was made in the
                    White House and nowhere else; and (3) the President wanted to reiterate that we
                    were in favor of major improvements in Soviet-US relations but not until
                    considerable progress had been made on the Vietnam issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said with respect to the first
                    question that they had made their point of view clear and that any escalation by
                    us would have dangerous consequences. I told him that we had taken it into
                    account and that anything we did would not be directed against the Soviet Union,
                    they were the best judge of their own interests and would have to decide what to
                    do when the time came.</p>
                <p>With respect to the second point, he said he had no illusions about the linkage
                    problem, and he saw not much point in repeating our well-known position. I said
                    I just wanted to make sure that he understood and was not confused by the
                    conflicting statements he read. I pointed to the <hi rend="italic">Izvestia</hi>
                    article, which had called attention to these statements. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said <hi rend="italic">Izvestia</hi>
                    had only repeated what the factual situation was and had not made any editorial
                    comments. I did not argue the point, in the belief that propaganda was one thing
                    and their assessment of their policy was another.</p>
                <pb facs="0335" n="302" xml:id="pg_302"/>
                <p>With respect to the third point, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>
                    said that his government was now beginning to understand the seriousness with
                    which we took the position we had indicated, and had given up the illusion that
                    they had held earlier in the year that major progress was possible even while
                    the Vietnam war was going on. He added a little plaintively that he could not
                    understand our attitude because the Soviet Union was not making trouble for us
                    in Vietnam; they were not trying to embarrass us; but they could not get us out
                    of a war into which we had gotten ourselves. I said I thought our position was
                    clear, and there was no sense reiterating it.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> told me that the NLF was looking
                    at our position from the point of view that any election would be won by the
                    government organizing it, and that we were trying to get at the conference table
                    what we had failed to get on the battlefield. I said that we had specifically
                    rejected such a proposition and that they knew very well that we were prepared
                    to discuss with them how to organize the political process—they even knew how to
                    do it.</p>
                <p>I told <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> I had been intrigued by a
                    comment he had made the last time I had seen him; namely, that Hanoi had found
                    the conversation with me constructive. What was it that they had considered
                    constructive in that conversation? <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> said that they found my attitude and my personality
                    constructive—not the specific proposals which they thought repeated well-known
                    themes.</p>
                <p>The meeting ended with an understanding that we would meet again in about two
                    weeks, the initiative to be left with <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName>.<note n="3" xml:id="d99fn3">On November 6 at 4:35 pm,
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> spoke on the telephone about this
                        meeting: “<gloss target="#t_K1">K</gloss> said he [<persName
                            corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>] didn’t have very much. He came in
                        and talked about this linkage problem and I just said to him what the
                        President had said before. <gloss target="#t_K1">K</gloss> said he would
                        write it up and send it to R. He told D that it is a fact of life that there
                        is some relationship but it is conditional. <persName corresp="#p_RWP1"
                            >Rogers</persName> felt that that was the way to play it. … <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> said we have never laid down any
                        conditions on <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>. On the other hand, if
                        we are actually having confrontation in the Middle East, it would be
                        difficult to engage in meetings with friendly atmosphere in Helsinki. <gloss
                            target="#t_K1">K</gloss> indicated that D had come in to get
                        clarification in his own mind since something had been mentioned in <hi
                            rend="italic">Time</hi> magazine 6 months ago that <gloss target="#t_K1"
                            >K</gloss> had that concept. <persName corresp="#p_RWP1"
                            >Rogers</persName> said it might be helpful if he knew when <gloss
                            target="#t_K1">K</gloss> was having these meetings. <gloss
                            target="#t_K1">K</gloss> said he would call next time.” (Transcript of
                        Telephone Conversation, Library of Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box 361, Telephone
                        Records, 1969–1976, Telephone Conversations) (Ellipsis in source
                        text)</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
