<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1909-06-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1909-06-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="173" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d173">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 5315/334–335.</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">Reid</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1909-06-25"><hi rend="italic">June 25,
                                1909</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 953.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my dispatch No. 941, of
                            the 15th instant, and previous correspondence on the subject of
                            participation of American financiers in the Hankow-Szechuen Railway
                            loan, I have the honor to inclose herewith a copy of a note from the
                            foreign office, dated the 23d instant, in reply to mine of the 12th
                            instant (a copy of which was sent to the department in my dispatch 941
                            mentioned above).<note n="1" xml:id="d173fn1">Not printed.</note> The
                            substance of the note of the 23d instant was cabled to the department on
                            the same day.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Whitelaw Reid.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Minister for Foreign
                                        Affairs</gloss> to Ambassador <persName type="to">Reid</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1909-06-23"><hi rend="italic">June 23,
                                        1909</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to
                                acknowledge the receipt of your note of the 12th instant on the
                                subject of the proposed participation of American financiers in the
                                Hankow-Szechuen Railway loan.</p>
                            <p>I entirely agree with all that your excellency says as regards the
                                danger that would arise in China from the pursuit of conflicting
                                interests and the consequent disagreements among western
                                nations.</p>
                            <p>As I had the honor to explain verbally to your excellency, I also
                                concur entirely in your view that, as a doctrine of international
                                law, one of two joint concessionaires has no power to fix the term
                                when the right of the other to its share in a concession should
                                lapse through nonuser. I suggest, however, to your excellency that
                                in certain matters of business that do not admit of indefinite delay
                                circumstances arise which justify, and indeed compel, one party to a
                                bargain to assume that the other party no longer desires to adhere
                                to the arrangement if the latter party, after reasonable notice,
                                gives no indication of its wishes. In the present case several
                                years’ notice was given, and it was not until the negotiations
                                between China and the European groups concerned had been proceeding
                                quite openly for many months and had, subject to imperial sanction,
                                reached a successful issue that any claim to participation was put
                                forward on behalf of American financiers.</p>
                            <pb facs="0240" n="168" xml:id="pg_168"/>
                            <p>The agreement which has been reached between British, French, and
                                German financial groups and the Chinese Government is to the
                                following effect:</p>
                            <p>A loan of £5,500,000 is to be raised by the three groups in equal
                                shares for the construction of railways in Hupeh and Hunan.</p>
                            <p>The portion of the Hankow-Canton Railway which lay in these Provinces
                                is to be constructed by a British chief engineer.</p>
                            <p>About 500 miles of the Hankow-Szechuen Railway, including branches,
                                all in Hupeh, is to be constructed by a German chief engineer, and
                                the remainder of the lines in Hupeh by a French engineer.</p>
                            <p>It is further agreed between the three groups that endeavors should
                                be made to secure an extension of the line to Ch’eng-tu, the capital
                                of Szechuen, to be constructed partly by a French and partly by a
                                British chief engineer in such a manner that of the whole line from
                                Hankow to Ch’eng-tu about a third each should be intrusted to
                                German, French, and Bhitish chief engineers.</p>
                            <p>I venture again to express the hope that the American group will
                                place no difficulties in the way of securing imperial sanction for
                                the agreement which has been reached.</p>
                            <p>As regards, however, the participation of American capital in
                                financial loans in China, I have the honor to suggest that the
                                American group should place themselves in communication with the
                                British, French, and German syndicates concerned.</p>
                            <p>His Majesty’s Government entirely approve and welcome in principle
                                the participation of American capital in Chinese railway loans, and
                                they hope that an arrangement may yet be arrived at for an equal
                                participation between the American and other foreign banks in the
                                loan in question, leaving undisturbed the agreement concluded by the
                                British, French, and German groups.</p>
                            <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">E. Grey.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>