<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>104. Draft Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1989-92v31</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d104</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">104</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1990-04-06T08:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1990-04-06T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003001255"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Launchers</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1990-04-06T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1990-04-06T08:30:00-05:00" n="104"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d104">
                <head>104. Draft Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d104fn1">Source: Department of State, Verification, Compliance and
                        Implementation, Lot 06D436, Verification, Compliance and Implementation
                        Subject Files, 1983–2005, Box 25, Ministerials: Washington April 4–6 1990.
                        No classification marking. The meeting took place in the <gloss
                            target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss> Conference Room.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1990-04-06T09:30:00-04:00" to="1990-04-06T13:00:00-04:00">April 6,
                            1990, 9:30 a.m.–1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <list>
                            <head>U.S.</head>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BRR_1">Richard Burt</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BLF_1">Linton Brooks</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_IEM_1">Edward Ifft</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SDJ_1">David Smith</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <list>
                            <head>Soviet</head>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_NY_1">Yuriy Nazarkin</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Lem Masterkov</item>
                            <item>Gennadiy Khromov</item>
                            <item>Yuriy Roslyakov</item>
                            <item>Victor Koltunov</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BRR_1">Burt</persName>: I would like to raise some
                    questions with regard to road-mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s.
                    Mr. Khromov at our first meeting raised one idea for verifying road-mobile
                        <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s, i.e., a small restricted area (5
                    square kilometers), and a large deployment area (16,000 square kilometers).
                    Notification of movement outside the restricted area would be for visits to
                    maintenance facilities, etc. Yesterday you proposed a new approach. Please
                    explain the second, and its relationship to the first.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NY_1">Nazarkin</persName>: The two are alternatives; they
                    are independent of each other. Col. Koltunov will explain them.</p>
                <p>Koltunov: In the second variant, the territory of the restricted area is
                    determined by the number of launchers in it: 1–2 road-mobile launchers per 25
                    square kilometers. Routine movement and training would be within the deployment
                    area. Notification would be provided when a road-mobile launcher leaves its
                    restricted area for routine movement if, at the moment when the launcher leaves
                    the restricted area, the total number outside the restricted area is greater
                    than 50% of the total number in that restricted area. Notification would take
                    place no later than 24 hours after the launcher left the restricted area. There
                    would be no limit on the number of road mobile launchers outside the restricted
                    area, but all would be in the deployment area.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BRR_1">Burt</persName>: Thank you for the very clear and
                    competent presentation. I have a few questions. Personally, I am attracted to
                    several elements of the proposal, particularly that having to do with
                    notification. But I am confused about several things. First, in the paper<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d104fn2">Not found.</note> you talk about a restricted area on
                    the basis of 1–2 mobile launchers for each 25 square kilometers. What does that
                    mean for the total size of the Soviet restricted area; for example, if you are
                    talking about 10 launchers?</p>
                <pb facs="0656" n="629" xml:id="pg_629"/>
                <p>Koltunov: It would never exceed 250 square kilometers or ten missiles. The
                    minimum would be 125 square kilometers for 10 missiles. However, if a restricted
                    area contains fewer than 10, the total territory of the restricted area becomes
                    smaller. If the restricted area contains 1–2 launchers, its size would be 25
                    square kilometers, not less.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BRR_1">Burt</persName>: Your old position was that the
                    restricted area should be 100 square kilometers, with notification of all out of
                    area deployments.</p>
                <p>Koltunov: Yes, but there was no deployment area. We have accepted the deployment
                    area, and are trying to solve the problem with notification.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BRR_1">Burt</persName>: The restricted area is far too
                    large.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_IEM_1">Ifft</persName>: What is the relationship between
                    the existence of a deployment area and deployment out of the restricted
                    area.</p>
                <p>Koltunov: The same as before. There is no change in our position.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_IEM_1">Ifft</persName>: But when a launcher comes out of
                    the restricted area, it has to stop at the edge of the deployment area, or if
                    there is no deployment area, it can go further. What does that have to do with
                    notification out of the restricted area?</p>
                <p>Koltunov: In this option, if the number of launchers outside the restricted area
                    is greater than 50%, each next launcher leaving the restricted area would have
                    to be notified. I emphasize that all routine movements would be covered under
                    the MOU; the launchers would not leave the confines of the deployment area. But
                    you’re right—no deployment area means no confines on movement.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BRR_1">Burt</persName>: I note that in your old position,
                    you would give notification prior to movement from the restricted area; in this
                    option, after.</p>
                <p>Koltunov: You are right. The purpose of the notification is to verify the number
                    of launchers in any restricted area. If notification is done before, then for
                    one reason or another, launchers would not leave the deployment area. The
                    notification process would be encumbered. It’s better to provide notification
                    after.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_IEM_1">Ifft</persName>: Would notification also be
                    possible after the launcher returns to the restricted area?</p>
                <p>Koltunov: In principle, we do not exclude that type too.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BLF_1">Brooks</persName>: If a side has 10 launchers in
                    the deployment area and 4 were outside the restricted area and 2 more go outside
                    for 24 hours we would be notified—that I understand. But suppose you go out and
                    come back within 24 hours—would there be notification?</p>
                <p>Koltunov: You would be notified of their departure if at that moment in time over
                    50% of the launchers of that restricted area were outside of it—for the 6th,
                    7th, 8th launchers, etc.</p>
                <pb facs="0657" n="630" xml:id="pg_630"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BLF_1">Brooks</persName>: Notification would be made
                    regardless of how long they were outside?</p>
                <p>Koltunov: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BLF_1">Brooks</persName>: I am confused on the size
                    questions. For each 10 launchers, the restricted area would be no more than 250
                    square kilometers and not less than 125 square kilometers. But if five years
                    from now you wanted a smaller restricted area, why should that not be
                    allowed?</p>
                <p>Koltunov: It is not excluded even now.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BLF_1">Brooks</persName>: One more question on size. The
                    size of each restricted area would be specified in the MOU and limited by the
                    size outlined here.</p>
                <p>Koltunov: Absolutely right.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Horn</persName>e: Please explain why notification
                    only takes place after 50% of the launchers are outside the restricted area.</p>
                <p>Koltunov: The reasoning is simple. We believe that with the existence of
                    deployment areas and restricted areas, and with all training activities taking
                    place within those boundaries, verification would be effective. But since the
                    U.S. side insisted on this notification approach, we have come forth with this
                    proposal.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Horn</persName>e: My understanding of the 100
                    kilometer square restricted zone was that all the launchers would be there, and
                    that notification would occur when they moved outside that area. Help me to
                    understand why, with a larger restricted area, you could not notify of all
                    movements outside the restricted area.</p>
                <p>Koltunov: We have lots of options: a 5 square kilometer restricted area, 25,
                    100—a complete spectrum. Our original option is still on the table, i.e., a
                    restricted area of 100 square kilometers is still on the table.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Horn</persName>e: So there is no military reason for
                    the inability to notify all movement under the last proposal?</p>
                <p>Koltunov: We are not dealing with military reasons, but with what should be
                    verified under the limits of the treaty we are working out. All of the options
                    are based on the goal of keeping mobile systems mobile and establishing
                    effective verification. That is why there are various options.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BRR_1">Burt</persName>: We will return in Geneva to this
                    subject.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
