<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1990-05-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1990-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="119" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d119">
                    <head>119. National Security Directive 40<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d119fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_BGHW_1">George H.W.
                                Bush</persName> Library, <persName corresp="#p_BGHW_1">Bush</persName> Presidential Records, National Security Council,
                            H-Files, NSD Files, OA/ID 90004–014, NSD–40—May 140, 1990—Decisions on
                            START Issues. Secret.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1990-05-14">May 14,
                            1990</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>MEMORANDUM FOR</head>
                        <item>THE VICE PRESIDENT</item>
                        <item>THE SECRETARY OF STATE</item>
                        <item>THE SECRETARY OF DEFENSE</item>
                        <item>THE SECRETARY OF ENERGY</item>
                        <item>THE DIRECTOR, OFFICE OF MANAGEMENT AND BUDGET</item>
                        <item>THE A<gloss target="#t_SSI_1">SSI</gloss>STANT TO THE PRESIDENT FOR
                            NATIONAL SECURITY AFFAIRS</item>
                        <item>THE DIRECTOR OF CENTRAL INTELLIGENCE</item>
                        <item>THE CHAIRMAN, JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF</item>
                        <item>THE DIRECTOR, ARMS CONTROL AND DISARMAMENT AGENCY</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Decisions on START Issues (U)</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>At the upcoming U.S.-Soviet summit, I hope to reach substantive agreement on
                        all of the major <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> issues on a basis
                        that will advance U.S. national security interests and promote international
                            <pb facs="0711" n="684" xml:id="pg_684"/> stability. The following
                        decisions are designed to help achieve that goal by making a best faith
                        effort to resolve the issues that they address. (C)</p>
                    <p>1. <hi rend="strong"><gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s and <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>s.</hi> Building on current areas of
                        agreement with the Soviet Union and existing guidance, the U.S. can accept a
                        package that includes the following elements:</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital"><gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>600 km range threshold provided that non-nuclear <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s such as Tacit Rainbow are excluded
                            from <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> limits. (S)</item>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>Except as provided in subparagraph (d) below, current and future U.S.
                            heavy bombers equipped for nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s will be counted at 10 nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s per bomber and will not be equipped
                            for more than 20 nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s
                            per bomber. (S)</item>
                        <label>c.</label>
                        <item>Except as provided in subparagraph (d) below, current and future
                            Soviet heavy bombers equipped for nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s will be counted at 8 nuclear-armed
                                <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s per bomber and will not be
                            equipped for more than 12 nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s per bomber. (S)</item>
                        <label>d.</label>
                        <item>Subject to a mutually acceptable definition of “as equipped,” the U.S.
                            may agree that any U.S. heavy bombers equipped for nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s in excess of 150–180 will count
                            against the 6000 warhead limit on an “as equipped” basis. Soviet heavy
                            bombers equipped for nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s in excess of 140 percent of the 150–180 threshold
                            also will count against the 6000 warhead limit on an “as equipped”
                            basis. (S)</item>
                        <label>e.</label>
                        <item>As an alternative to subparagraph (d), the U.S. may accept a sublimit
                            on the number of U.S. heavy bombers equipped for nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s that adequately protects options
                            for the duration of the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> Treaty.
                            Under this approach, the Soviets may deploy up to 40 percent more heavy
                            bombers equipped for nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s than the U.S., subject to other <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> constraints, including the
                            1600/6000 <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> limits. (S)</item>
                        <label>f.</label>
                        <item>The U.S. requires a continuing right to convert up to 100 non-modern
                            heavy bombers to “former heavy bombers” that would not be counted within
                            the 1600/6000 <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> aggregates. The
                            U.S. may propose that “non-modern” heavy bombers be defined as being
                            those of a type that has been deployed longer than 10–15 years.
                            (S)</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital"><gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>s</p>
                    <p>As part of the <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss> package, the U.S. may propose that each
                        side make a declaration of policy concerning nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>s with ranges in excess of 600 km that
                        includes the following elements: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>A statement that the declaration will be politically binding.
                                (S)</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>A specification of the maximum number of nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>s that will be deployed for each
                                of the next five years. This specification would be updated
                                annually. (S)</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>A statement that no more than 875–1000 nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>s will be deployed at any one
                                time for the duration of the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> Treaty. (S)</item>
                            <pb facs="0712" n="685" xml:id="pg_685"/>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>Information about which types of surface ships and submarines are
                                capable of deploying nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>s. (S)</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>An annual exchange of data on nuclear <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>s with ranges between 300 and 600 km. (S)</item>
                            <label>f.</label>
                            <item>A statement that nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>s with multiple independently targeted warheads
                                will not be produced, or deployed. (S)</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>2. <hi rend="strong">Verifying Non-Deployed Mobile Missile Production.</hi>
                        The U.S. may offer an approach to Perimeter Portal Continuous Monitoring
                            (<gloss target="#t_PPCM_1">PPCM</gloss>) based on the following
                        principles: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Numerical reciprocity. (S)</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Up to approximately four facilities in each country may be subject
                                to <gloss target="#t_PPCM_1">PPCM</gloss>. (S)</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>The Soviet facilities at which <gloss target="#t_PPCM_1">PPCM</gloss> should be established is a combination of up to
                                approximately four solid propellant rocket motor production
                                facilities and final assembly facilities that would give us the
                                highest confidence in monitoring the production of mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s. (S)</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Solid rocket motor production facilities in both countries at which <gloss target="#t_PPCM_1">PPCM</gloss> is not established should be subject to
                        an annual quota of mandatory, short-notice inspections if they are
                        determined to be capable of producing first-stage motors for mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s. All other solid rocket motor
                        production facilities in both countries at which <gloss target="#t_PPCM_1">PPCM</gloss> has not been established should be subject to periodic,
                        scheduled tours to confirm that they have not been given the capability to
                        produce first-stage motors for mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s. (S)</p>
                    <p>The U.S. and Soviet Union should first exchange lists of all their facilities
                        that currently produce first stage motors of mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s and other facilities at which they are
                        prepared to accept <gloss target="#t_PPCM_1">PPCM</gloss>. These lists will
                        be mutually agreed. The two sides will then agree to establish <gloss target="#t_PPCM_1">PPCM</gloss> at specified facilities on these lists.
                        (S)</p>
                    <p>The U.S. and Soviet Union will also exchange lists of all solid propellant
                        rocket motor production facilities. Following the identification of those
                        facilities at which <gloss target="#t_PPCM_1">PPCM</gloss> will be
                        established, an exchange of data and one-time tours of all solid propellant
                        rocket motor production facilities in both countries should be conducted to
                        determine which facilities will be subject to mandatory short-notice
                        inspections, and which will be subject to periodic, scheduled tours. (S)</p>
                    <p>In order to implement this regime in the Soviet Union as soon as possible,
                        the U.S. may accept the simultaneous implementation of such a regime in the
                        United States, even if mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s are
                        not yet in production in the U.S. at that time. (S)</p>
                    <p>The U.S. should propose that questions about activities at facilities that
                        are not subject to either short-notice inspections or periodic, scheduled
                        tours may be raised in the Joint Compliance and Inspection <pb facs="0713" n="686" xml:id="pg_686"/> Commission (JCIC). The two sides may agree in
                        the JCIC to inspect such facilities to aid in resolving any compliance
                        concerns. (S)</p>
                    <p>3. <hi rend="strong">Limits on Heavy <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s.</hi> On the understanding that the U.S. will seek the
                        ultimate elimination of heavy <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s in
                        follow-on negotiations, the U.S. may accept a package of constraints on
                        heavy <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s consisting of: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>A maximum of 1540 <gloss target="#t_RV_1">RV</gloss>s on 154 heavy
                                    <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s. (S)</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>A ban on new types of heavy <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s. (S)</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>A ban on mobile heavy <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s.
                                (S)</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>Such limitations on the modernization of existing types of heavy
                                    <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s as may be agreed between
                                the two sides. (S)</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>4. <hi rend="strong">Limits on Mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s
                            and Mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_RV_1">RV</gloss>s.</hi> The U.S. should propose a
                        subceiling of 800–1200 on the number of deployed mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>
                        <gloss target="#t_RV_1">RV</gloss>s permitted in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>. The U.S. will not seek a subceiling on the number of
                        deployed mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s permitted in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>. (S)</p>
                    <p>5. <hi rend="strong">Backfire.</hi> The Intelligence Community has determined
                        that the Backfire is an intermediate-range bomber and that the Soviets plan
                        to employ it in a theater role. Although the Backfire, under certain
                        conditions, has a technical capability to conduct strikes against targets in
                        the U.S., the Intelligence Community notes that the Soviets do not plan and
                        would be unlikely to employ Backfire in such a role. (S)</p>
                    <p>Accordingly, the U.S. should address the Backfire issue by seeking Soviet
                        undertakings in the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> context that
                        would provide added confidence that it will remain dedicated to theater
                        missions, and will not be employed as a strategic bomber. These should
                        include, at a minimum, an undertaking that Backfire will not be given a
                        capability to operate at intercontinental ranges. (S)</p>
                    <p>Additionally, the U.S. should seek a Soviet commitment to include all
                        Backfires based in the ATTU region in <gloss target="#t_CFE_1">CFE</gloss>
                        limits on aircraft. (S)</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">George
                        Bush</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>