<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1991-11-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1988-03-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="51" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d51">
                    <head>51. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>On September 23, 1989, Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_BJA_1">James
                            Baker</persName> and Soviet Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Eduard Shevardnadze</persName> and their delegations met at the AMK
                        Ranch in Jackson Hole, Wyoming, from 11:30 a.m.–1:00 p.m., to consider the
                        reports of the ministerial’s bilateral working groups on bilateral and
                        transnational issues. The memorandum of conversation is scheduled for
                        publication in <ref target="frus1989-92v03"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                Relations</hi>, 1989–1992, vol. III, Soviet Union, Russia, and
                            Post-Soviet States: High-Level Contacts</ref>.</p>
                    <pb facs="0398" n="371" xml:id="pg_371"/>
                    <p>Later that day, the U.S. and Soviet delegations released a Joint Statement,
                        which included the following passage on the Nuclear and Space Talks (all
                        brackets are in the original):</p>
                    <p>“Regarding <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> [antiballistic missiles] and
                        space, the Soviet side introduced a new approach aimed at resolving this
                        significant issue. Both sides agree that the Soviet approach opens the way
                        to achieve and implementing a <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>
                        [strategic arms reduction talks] treaty without reaching a defense and space
                        agreement. The sides agreed to drop the approach of a nonwithdrawal
                        commitment while continuing to discuss ways to ensure predictability in the
                        development of the U.S.-Soviet strategic relationship under conditions of
                        strategic stability to reduce the risk of nuclear war. The U.S. side said it
                        would consider carefully the other aspects of the overall Soviet approach.
                        Both sides agreed that their negotiators would consider these issues in
                        Geneva. They also agreed that the negotiations would discuss the U.S.
                        invitation for Soviet Government experts to visit two U.S. facilities
                        involved in strategic defense research.</p>
                    <p>“The Soviet side stated that, guided by its longstanding goal of
                        strengthening the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty regime, it had
                        decided to completely dismantle the Krasnoyarsk radar station. The U.S. side
                        expressed satisfaction with this announcement. At the same time, the Soviet
                        side stressed again the necessity of removing its concerns about the U.S.
                        radar stations in Greenland and Great Britain. The U.S. side promised to
                        consider these concerns, in consultation with its allies.</p>
                    <p>“In the interest of promoting progress in the negotiations, the Secretary
                        announced that the U.S. side was withdrawing its proposal to ban mobile
                            <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s [intercontinental ballistic
                        missiles] in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>, contingent on the
                        funding by the U.S. Congress of U.S. mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s. The Soviet side expressed satisfaction with this
                        announcement, and the two sides agreed on the need further to develop
                        provisions for effective verification for limits on mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s. In this connection, they also reached
                        agreement on additional elements of common ground regarding the verification
                        of mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s, building on the elements
                        agreed at the Moscow summit and subsequent work in Geneva.</p>
                    <p>“Both sides noted the need to resolve the <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> [air-launched cruise missiles] and <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss> [sea-launched cruise missiles] issues.
                        On <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s, the Soviet side put forward a
                        new idea concerning its approach on how to deal with <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>s and heavy bombers.</p>
                    <p>“On <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>s, the Soviet side offered new
                        approaches for dealing with this difficult problem. The Soviet side raised
                        the possibility of dealing with <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>s in a
                        broader naval arms context. As for the nuclear and space talks, the Soviet
                        side appealed to the American side to concentrate on verification and said
                        that in the context of a verification system for <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>s, these weapons could be limited outside of the text of a
                            <pb facs="0399" n="372" xml:id="pg_372"/>
                        <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> treaty on the basis of reciprocal
                        obligations. While reiterating its willingness to study the Soviet ideas,
                        the U.S. side, for its part, emphasized its doubts about the feasibility of
                        a workable verification system for <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>s
                        and noted its longstanding view that there are serious problems involved in
                        any discussion of the limitation of naval arms.</p>
                    <p>“The Soviet side responded positively to President Bush’s June initiative on
                        verification and stability measures. In this regard, the Secretary and the
                        Foreign Minister had a thorough exchange on the details of the initiative
                        and signed an agreement encouraging the development of such measures and
                        outlining principles for implementing them. They also completed an agreement
                        on the advance notification of major strategic exercises. The sides examined
                        the other verification and stability measures and agreed to explore these
                        further in Geneva.</p>
                    <p>“The sides also agreed that, for purposes of the 1,600 <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> limit, ballistic missiles will be
                        defined in terms of missiles and their associated launchers, thus resolving
                        a longstanding issue.</p>
                    <p>“New instructions will be issued to negotiators to take account of the
                        exchanges on these and other <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>
                        issues.” (Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, November
                        1989, pp. 5–6).</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>