<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>106. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, February
                    3, 1956, 3:30 p.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v20</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-02-03T15:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-02-03T15:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recSj13D27GJZ1DiT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Allocations</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec626bb089a1004d2" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons">Atomic
                        weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recdPycISbXW2cCGh" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85103582"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Plutonium</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-02-03T15:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-02-03T15:30:00-05:00" n="106"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d106">
                <head>106. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, February
                    3, 1956, 3:30 p.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d106fn1">Source: Department
                        of State, Atomic Energy Files: Lot 57 D 688, <gloss target="#t_IAEA1"
                            >IAEA</gloss>—General. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_FPJ1"
                            >Farley</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1956-02-03T15:30:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 3, 1956, 3:30 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>International Atomic Energy Agency</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>Adm. <persName corresp="#p_SLL1">Strauss</persName>, Chairman, Atomic
                        Energy Commission</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SHE1">Stassen</persName>, Special Assistant to
                        the President on Disarmament</item>
                    <item>Maj. Gen. <persName corresp="#p_LMGHB1">Loper</persName>, Assistant to the
                        Secretary of Defense (Atomic Energy)</item>
                    <item>Amb. <persName corresp="#p_WJJ1">Wadsworth</persName>, U.S. Representative
                        for <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Merchant</persName>, <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BRR1">Bowie</persName>, <gloss target="#t_SP1"
                            >S/P</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Hall</persName>, <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName>, <gloss target="#t_IO1"
                            >IO</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SRI1">Spiers</persName>, <gloss target="#t_IO1"
                            >IO</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Smith</persName>, <gloss target="#t_SAE1">S/AE</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FPJ1">Farley</persName>, <gloss target="#t_SAE1"
                            >S/AE</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Smith</persName> recalled that the meeting had been called at the
                    invitation of the Secretary to consider plans for the twelve-nation discussions
                    of the International Atomic Energy Agency beginning February 27, 1956.<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d106fn2">See <ref target="#d120">Document 120</ref>.</note>
                    Preliminary discussions with the U.K. and Canada were scheduled to commence on
                    February 6. The basic question with regard to the United States position was
                    whether the Agency should operate with limited controls designed merely to
                    insure that nuclear assistance was not diverted to military uses, or whether the
                    U.S. objective should be to attempt to keep fourth countries from producing
                    nuclear weapons.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SLL1">Strauss</persName> said that, in the Commission’s
                    view, the U.S. should as a minimum require controls to prevent diversion of
                    Agency assistance to military purposes. Certain minimum controls—guarantees by
                    recipients against diversion of assistance, and provision for inspection and
                    accounting for nuclear materials—should be made mandatory in the Agency’s
                    Statute. The Agency should be given statutory authority to exercise broader
                    controls, but these should not be mandatory in the Statute and the U.S. should
                    seek to achieve that by persuasion rather than coercion.</p>
                <p>With regard to U.S. support for the Agency, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SLL1"
                        >Strauss</persName> said that the Commission had just taken a decision that
                    one thousand kilograms of U–235 should be allocated to the Agency. He added that
                    consideration was being given to making this a donation; the value of this <pb
                        facs="0336" n="308" xml:id="pg_308"/> material would be approximately
                    twenty-five million dollars. In addition, the Commission believed that the U.S.
                    should offer to match all other contributions of material (on a reimbursable
                    basis) for a period of perhaps five years. Unclassified technical information
                    and assistance necessary for the Agency’s operations would also be provided. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_SLL1">Strauss</persName> said also that the Commission
                    believed that a sizable amount of material should be earmarked for <gloss
                        target="#t_EURATOM1">EURATOM</gloss> as an effective way of demonstrating
                    U.S. support for European integration.</p>
                <p>With regard to the proposals of the State Department for more comprehensive
                        <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss> control, he said that he believed a
                    “no weapons” pledge would not be feasible, and that France in particular could
                    not accept such a pledge. Agency inspection of the United States power reactor
                    program appeared difficult to accept. The United States would not accept
                    sufficiently strict inspection and control of its own programs to satisfy
                    prudent requirements for safeguards abroad, and reciprocal inspection would thus
                    serve as an excuse for other countries to limit inspection and control to what
                    the U.S. would accept.</p>
                <p>The Secretary asked whether the one thousand kilograms for the Agency to which
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SLL1">Strauss</persName> referred was a ceiling within
                    which we would match contributions by other countries. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SLL1">Strauss</persName> said that the Commission proposed
                    allocating twenty thousand kilograms for foreign atomic energy activities. One
                    thousand kilograms would be earmarked initially for the Agency, and in addition
                    the U.S. would match allocations from other countries. He pointed out that the
                    U.K. would be able to make only small allocations for some time, so that in
                    effect the U.S. was offering to match allocations from the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. Thus, the remaining nineteen thousand
                    kilograms might be used to match allocations to the <gloss target="#t_IAEA1"
                        >IAEA</gloss> by the U.K. and <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, to
                    supply <gloss target="#t_EURATOM1">EURATOM</gloss>, and to cover requirements
                    under bilateral agreements. The proposed allocation of 20,000 kilograms of U–235
                    to foreign programs had been reported to the Joint Committee on Atomic Energy.
                    The view of the Department of Defense was currently being solicited. Gen.
                        <persName corresp="#p_LMGHB1">Loper</persName> said that the Department of
                    Defense had not yet received notice of the proposed allocation, but that the
                    matter had been given general study and he thought that a twenty thousand
                    kilogram foreign allocation over a period of eight to twelve years would be
                    consistent with military requirements. The Department of Defense understanding
                    was that this material would be earmarked but not withdrawn from stock until
                    needed by foreign users.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Smith</persName> observed that any reference to <gloss
                        target="#t_EURATOM1">EURATOM</gloss> in the U.S. announcement of the
                    allocation would require careful handling. Amb. <persName corresp="#p_WJJ1"
                        >Wadsworth</persName> said that he felt this announcement would have very
                    great effect on <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss> negotiations and that this
                    effect should not be dissipated <pb facs="0337" n="309" xml:id="pg_309"/>
                    through premature release. Adm. <persName corresp="#p_SLL1">Strauss</persName>
                    said that he thought the announcement would have to be made soon for practical
                    reasons and that it would establish an excellent atmosphere for later steps.</p>
                <p>The Secretary asked for Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SHE1">Stassen</persName>’s
                    views as to the extent of controls over the atomic energy programs of other
                    countries which the U.S. should seek. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SHE1"
                        >Stassen</persName> said that he believed the objective of the U.S. should
                    be to prevent or retard the development of nuclear weapons in fourth countries.
                    As a practical matter, the United States could not get the necessary controls
                    unless the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> agrees. We should propose a
                    comprehensive control system and let the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                    bear the onus of rejection. The Secretary recalled that the United States had
                    recently sent a note asking the Russians for their specific proposals as to
                    effective inspection and control.<note n="3" xml:id="d106fn3">The Secretary is
                        apparently referring to the U.S. note to the Soviet Union, January 27; see
                        Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, October 22, 1956, pp.
                        628–629.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Smith</persName> pointed out that, if the U.S. objective is the
                    prevention of new atomic weapons programs, then the minimum controls proposed by
                        <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> would be ineffective. Assistance from
                    the Agency, even though limited to peaceful purposes, would simply free the
                    other resources of a nation to support a parallel weapons program. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SLL1">Strauss</persName> indicated personal agreement with this
                    view but pointed out that it appeared extremely difficult to get agreement on a
                    broader control.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that it would be difficult for nations to forego permanently
                    their right to make nuclear weapons while the U.S., <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss> and U.K. continued to make them. He thought it might be
                    possible to get agreement by other countries to forego weapons production as an
                    interim measure, looking toward the institution of international control of
                    atomic energy which would apply to all countries including the present military
                    atomic powers. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SHE1">Stassen</persName> agreed and
                    pointed out that the U.S. should not be in the position of appearing to plan to
                    manufacture nuclear weapons forever. Our approach should be to ask other
                    countries to forego manufacture of nuclear weapons for a specified period, while
                    we and the other major powers continue to work toward effective comprehensive
                    control. It was in this spirit that he had recommended, as a priority
                    disarmament objective of the U.S., that we <hi rend="italic">prevent,
                        retard</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">minimize</hi> the development of nuclear
                    weapons programs in other countries.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Smith</persName> said that we should consider what steps the U.S.
                    might take at this time in anticipation of eventual broad agreement on control
                    and as an earnest of our intentions. He proposed as one such measure a U.S.
                    policy of using by-product plutonium from U.S. civilian power reactors solely
                    for peaceful purposes, and thus separating the emerging U.S. civilian power
                    program from our military weapons <pb facs="0338" n="310" xml:id="pg_310"/>
                    program and putting it on the same basis as the peaceful uses programs of other
                    countries. He pointed out that the present U.S. military program did not rely on
                    plutonium from civilian power reactors; thus the only sacrifice for the U.S. in
                    separating our peaceful and military programs would be the possible need to
                    spend some money on additional military plutonium reactors if needed.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SLL1">Strauss</persName> doubted that the U.K. would be
                    able to accept such a proposal. … Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SLL1"
                        >Strauss</persName> said that the idea was one which appealed to him and one
                    which he thought the President would support. General <persName
                        corresp="#p_LMGHB1">Loper</persName> asked whether plutonium would have any
                    substantial use for peaceful purposes. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SLL1"
                        >Strauss</persName> said that while the present use as a reactor fuel was
                    insignificant, it would probably become an important fuel once it was available
                    for non-military use.</p>
                <p>The Secretary indicated doubt as to the value of the proposed gesture. Countries
                    such as India were concerned with whether or not the U.S. continued to produce
                    nuclear weapons and would not care where we got the plutonium for such weapons.
                    Mr. <persName>Smith</persName> said that the measure appeared important to him
                    mainly as an earnest of our eventual disarmament intentions and of our sincerity
                    in pressing ahead with negotiations for control of atomic energy. The Secretary
                    said that if this matter appeared important on further study, it should be
                    raised again, but that at present he did not think the U.S. should make such an
                    offer. We should attempt to get other countries to accept a standstill agreement
                    for say a five-year period, while the major powers attempt to work out effective
                    initial control of both military and peaceful uses of atomic energy. He warned
                    that there would be many problems to meet in negotiating agreement with the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> on an effective inspection operation
                    even limited to peaceful uses of atomic energy.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_LMGHB1">Loper</persName> said that Mr.
                        <persName>Robertson</persName> would shortly send a letter outlining the
                    following Department of Defense position.<note n="4" xml:id="d106fn4">See <ref
                            target="#d107">
                            <hi rend="italic">infra.</hi>
                        </ref>
                    </note> The Department of Defense favors a flexible approach to the control of
                    peaceful uses of atomic energy. It believes that the arms control problem, which
                    required stricter controls, should be kept distinct from Agency activities, and
                    that Agency controls should not apply to military programs. We should seek a
                    modest control arrangement initially; otherwise the establishment of the Agency
                    might well be delayed. The present draft Statute appeared generally acceptable
                    to the Department of Defense. The Joint Chiefs of Staff are presently studying
                    the military risk which would be caused by diversion of nuclear materials so
                    that fourth states would obtain nuclear weapons. If this risk appears
                    significant, then more rigid mandatory controls might be required rather than
                    permissive controls. The Department of Defense agrees generally with the <gloss
                        target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> views on support of the Agency, including the
                    concept of matching <pb facs="0339" n="311" xml:id="pg_311"/> contributions from
                    other nations. The Department of Defense does not approve the proposal for a
                        <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>-US-<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                    agreement that no material from their peaceful uses programs will be used for
                    military purposes. Such an agreement would require inspection of the U.S.
                    programs which should not be undertaken under the Agency but only under a broad
                    arms regulation agreement.</p>
                <p>The Secretary agreed with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WJJ1"
                        >Wadsworth</persName>’s suggestion that the problem of controls be discussed
                    with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> before February 27.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WJJ1">Wadsworth</persName> said that it would be
                    necessary to work out carefully the provisions which should be written into the
                    charter to advance our objective of preventing other countries from developing
                    nuclear weapons. The Secretary said that the Agency charter should be written to
                    give necessary authority to the Agency but not to make obligatory the
                    commitments we are seeking. He conceived the suggestion standstill agreement as
                    a parallel agreement rather than one built into the charter. Mr.
                        <persName>Smith</persName> observed that we have our most effective
                    bargaining position at this time and we should seek to obtain control authority
                    before we make firm commitments. He said that one approach which was being
                    considered was to stipulate that Agency assistance would go only to countries
                    not engaged in nuclear weapons production. The Secretary said that he was
                    convinced countries would not come into the Agency if required to commit
                    themselves for all time not to make weapons. What we must ask is that they
                    agree, for a specified period of time, as a self-denying move, not to complicate
                    the problem of nuclear disarmament by engaging in atomic weapons production,
                    while the great powers try to bring the world situation and their own stocks of
                    these weapons under control.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
