<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-12-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-01-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="263" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d263">
                        <head>263. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> visited Canada
                            July 26–28, then flew from Ottawa to London to participate in
                            disarmament discussions July 29–August 2. Although President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> and
                                <persName>Dulles</persName> had often discussed the prospect of
                                <persName>Dulles</persName> making a trip to London, it was not
                            until after he left for Canada on July 26 that the decision was finally
                            made for the Secretary to continue on to London. The President and the
                            Secretary agreed that the talks had reached the stage where
                                <persName>Dulles</persName> should report the United States position
                            firsthand and obtain personally the allies’ views. As
                                <persName>Dulles</persName> later explained, it was the “mass of
                            cables coming in about these complicated subjects from so many points”
                            that persuaded <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> to send
                            him to London. “No particular incident,” he added, brought <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> “to that conclusion, but
                            merely recognition of the fact that there were so many points to be
                            buttoned up at the same time. It could be done more effectively with me”
                            in London. (Background briefing for the British press, reported in
                            telegram 903 from London, August 2; Department of State, Central Files,
                            330.13/8–257)</p>
                        <p><persName>Dulles</persName> apparently wished to ensure there would be no
                            confusion about his role at the disarmament talks, for on July 26,
                            Acting Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>
                            sent the following memorandum to the President: “In the course of his
                            telephone call this morning, the Secretary suggested that it might be
                            useful for him to have some further delegation of authority from you. I,
                            therefore, suggest to you the memorandum for the Secretary of State
                            enclosed.” (Undated memorandum; <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                            700.5611/7–2657) <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>
                            initialed <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>’s draft without
                            change. <persName>Dulles</persName>’ instructions thus read: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“In the course of your consultations on the disarmament question
                                    during your mission in Europe beginning July 29, 1957, I believe
                                    that you should have a reasonable degree of flexibility.
                                    Accordingly, you are authorized during this mission to make such
                                    modifications or elaborations in the United States position as
                                    approved in the document dated June 11 as you deem to be within
                                    the spirit of that document and essential to the achievement of
                                    a sound and coordinated Western position for presentation in the
                                    United Nations Disarmament Subcommittee.” (Memorandum from
                                        <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> to
                                        <persName>Dulles</persName>, July 26; <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 330.13/7–2657)</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>In a telephone call that evening, <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> informed <persName>Dulles</persName>, who had
                            arrived in Ottawa, that he had just discussed the Secretary’s
                            instructions, the press release to be given out in connection with
                                <persName>Dulles</persName>’ trip to London, and a letter from
                                <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> about the trip (<ref target="#d264"><hi rend="italic">infra</hi></ref>) with the
                            President. <persName>Dulles</persName> approved all these matters. In
                            addition, “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> said that
                            the President had stressed he hoped we could have the utmost flexibility
                            in regard to testing.” (Memorandum <pb facs="0693" n="665" xml:id="pg_665"/> of a telephone conversation, July 26, 6 p.m.;
                            Eisenhower Library, Dulles Papers, General Telephone Conversations)
                            Afterwards, <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> sent
                                <persName>Dulles</persName> the following memorandum: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“This memorandum is a reamplification of my rather cryptic
                                    message on the telephone. While reviewing the memorandum of
                                    instructions to you with regard to flexibility, the President
                                    said that he hoped that we could maintain considerable
                                    flexibility with regard to nuclear testing both as to the length
                                    of time and the many conditions with which it is coupled since
                                    he feels that we are at a continuing propaganda disadvantage in
                                    appearing to have too rigid a position.” (July 26; <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> Whitman File,
                                        <persName>Dulles</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> Series)</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Additional documentation on <persName>Dulles</persName>’ visit is in
                            Department of State, Central Files, 110.11–DU and 330.13.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>