<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-09-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-09-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="180" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d180">
                    <head>180. Memorandum From Members of the Inter-Agency Group on Surprise Attack
                            (<persName corresp="#p_KGB2" type="from">Kistiakowsky</persName> and
                            <persName>Minshull</persName>) to the President’s Special Assistant for
                        Science and Technology (<persName corresp="#p_KJRJ1" type="to">Killian</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d180fn0"><p>Source: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>
                                Library, White House Office Files, Additional Records of the Special
                                Assistant for Science and Technology, Surprise Attack Policy.
                                Secret. The interagency group was formed pursuant to <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s July 14 request.
                                (Letter from <persName corresp="#p_KGB2">Kistiakowsky</persName> to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName>, August 15; <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Surprise Attack Panel)</p>
                            <p>In an April 28 letter to <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName>, President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> suggested that as a means of moving
                                toward disarmament, the United States and the Soviet Union should
                                instruct their technical experts to study among other things the
                                practical problems and feasibility of inspecting against surprise
                                attack. (<hi rend="italic">Documents on Disarmament, 1945–1959,</hi>
                                pp. 1006–1007) After a lengthy exchange of correspondence on the
                                subject (letters from <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>, May 9 and July 2; notes from the U.S.
                                Embassy to the Soviet Foreign Ministry, July 31 and September 8; and
                                a note from the Soviet Foreign Ministry to the U.S. Embassy,
                                September 15; all <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., pp. 1036–1041,
                                1084–1090, 1126, and 1129–1131), the two sides were close to an
                                agreement on a technical conference that would include experts from
                                countries other than the United States and the Soviet Union. On
                                October 10, the United States agreed to a meeting of experts at
                                Geneva, beginning on November 1, 1958. (Note from the U.S. Embassy
                                to the Soviet Foreign Ministry, October 10; <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., pp. 1145–1146)</p></note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-09-30">September 30,
                            1958</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Surprise Attack Policy Considerations</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>In 1955 the President made the Geneva “Open Skies” proposal.<note n="1" xml:id="d180fn1">The text of the proposal, which <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> made at Geneva on July 21,
                            1955, is <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., pp. 486–488.</note> At that time
                        aerial inspection coupled with an “exchange of military blueprints” and the
                        most rudimentary form of ground inspection could have provided an effective
                        safeguard against a surprise attack. Furthermore, if such an inspection
                        system had been implemented, it would have tested inspection techniques
                        that, if successful, could have formed the framework for monitoring future
                        phases of disarmament.</p>
                    <p>In addition, the proposal was attractive to this country for three quite
                        different secondary reasons. First, by making such a proposal this country
                        was in a position to test Soviet intentions in the disarmament field.
                        Secondly, the proposal provided an excellent propaganda move for this
                        country, indicating our good faith and sincere desire for peace. Finally, it
                        was realized that if an inspection system were implemented, it would provide
                        a means for raising the Iron Curtain and increasing the chances for hard
                        intelligence from <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>It should be recognized that if the Soviets had accepted the 1955 proposal,
                        it would have been for one or both of the first two reasons. The final three
                        reasons were important to this country but could not have appealed to the
                        Soviet Union.</p>
                    <pb facs="0697" n="667" xml:id="pg_667"/>
                    <p>Advances in weapon technology in the past three years and the advances
                        expected in the next few years will greatly modify the value of an
                        inspection system <hi rend="italic">as a safeguard against surprise
                            attack.</hi> The advent of the <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss> and
                        the greatly increased readiness capability of manned bombers makes it
                        necessary to go one step beyond inspection and toward limited disarmament
                        before one can obtain a substantial reduction in the danger of surprise
                        attack or accidental war. The Inter-Agency Working Group on Surprise Attack
                        appointed by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>,
                        Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MENH1">McElroy</persName>, and Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KJRJ1">Killian</persName> concluded that to obtain an
                        effective safeguard against surprise attack from modern manned bombers would
                        require an inspection system that <hi rend="italic">monitored</hi> and
                        agreed upon limitation of bomber readiness (for example, an agreed upon
                        maximum number of bombers airborne at any given time). In the case of <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss>’s the Working Group felt that an
                        inspection system that <hi rend="italic">monitored</hi> and agreed upon
                        maximum force level (i.e., total number of missiles) would be required to
                        afford real protection against surprise missile attack. The Inter-Agency
                        Group concluded that the value of an inspection system without such arms
                        controls is limited to the secondary values that existed in 1955.<note n="2" xml:id="d180fn2"><p>On September 30, at 9:30 a.m., <persName corresp="#p_KJRJ1">Killian</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> discussed the work of
                                the Inter-Agency Group as follows:</p>
                            <p>“Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KJRJ1">Killian</persName> said that the
                                study group is having a very hard time on the Surprise Attack
                                project. It is very difficult to get prepared for the discussions.
                                One key question is as to the scope of the project, i.e., as to what
                                should be monitored, and specifically as to whether limitation of
                                arms and control of size of forces should be among the things being
                                monitored. The President thought the first step is to determine what
                                are the fields or areas wherein by certain actions we could limit or
                                eliminate the danger of surprise attack. Then, what are the means of
                                doing this, i.e., through observation or inspection; then what
                                programs should be carried out to establish these means; then
                                finally in what areas or in what respects could these measures be
                                expected to be effective. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KJRJ1">Killian</persName> concluded by saying that the President may
                                have to decide, before the matter is resolved, as to whether to
                                include limitation of arms and inspection of such limitation in the
                                Surprise Attack proposal” (Memorandum of conference with the
                                President by <persName corresp="#p_GGAJ1">Goodpaster</persName>,
                                October 2; <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>
                                Library, <persName corresp="#p_WAC1">Whitman</persName> File,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Diaries) See
                                the Supplement.</p></note></p>
                    <p>In the test cessation technical discussions, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_FJB1">Fisk</persName> had an easily definable technical objective. It was to
                        determine the technical feasibility of designing and operating an inspection
                        system to monitor a test cessation agreement. It was only because of this
                        simple, easily definable technical objective that the talks were successful,
                        and that Dr. <persName corresp="#p_FJB1">Fisk</persName> was able to keep
                        the meeting from digressing into political areas. If the forthcoming Geneva
                        talks on surprise attack are to be successful, they too must have an equally
                        simple technical objective.</p>
                    <p>In 1955 such a technical objective would have been easily defined. It would
                        have been to determine the technical feasibility of designing and operating
                        an inspection system to monitor or “to see that there is no dangerous
                        concentration of military land forces or of air or naval forces.” The
                        advances in weapons technology have made such an objective obsolete. <pb facs="0698" n="668" xml:id="pg_668"/> No country needs to mass a
                        “dangerous concentration” of military equipment to launch a surprise attack.
                        Thus, if the forthcoming discussions are to be productive, the technical
                        objective must be modified.</p>
                    <p>The conclusions of the Inter-Agency Working Group indicate that a reasonable
                        technical objective for the forthcoming meeting would be <hi rend="italic">to determine the technical-military feasibility of designing and
                            operating an inspection system</hi> to monitor agreements that would
                        result in reducing the danger of surprise attack. If the Geneva discussions
                        parallel the Inter-Agency Group’s thinking, some of the “agreements that
                        would result in reducing the danger of surprise attack” might involve
                        limitations on bomber readiness, limitations on total numbers of ballistic
                        missiles, and limitations on the deployment of conventional land forces.</p>
                    <p>If this country were to go to Geneva to discuss only the technical
                        feasibility of an inspection system as a safeguard against surprise attack
                        in an environment of totally unrestricted military forces, the delegation
                        would find itself in a very difficult position. First of all, as the
                        Inter-Agency Working Group has indicated, an inspection system without force
                        limitation is practically useless as a means of safeguarding against
                        surprise attack. The very attractive secondary effects (for this country) of
                        an inspection system, employed within the Soviet Union, are such that they
                        cannot form the basis of technical discussions. Furthermore, the past Soviet
                        discussions on the matter of inspection and disarmament indicate that
                        Soviets feel that an inspection system by itself provides little protection
                        against surprise attack. Thus, if during the course of the meeting, the
                        Soviets pursue the effect of limited arms control or partial disarmament and
                        we refuse, we would provide the Soviets with an important propaganda
                        wedge.</p>
                    <p>The actual agreements on limitations of forces are political in nature and
                        therefore <hi rend="italic">no discussions of them</hi> will be accepted in
                        the forthcoming meeting. By this are meant discussions of force levels of
                        both sides, location or types of air bases or missile sites, etc.</p>
                    <p>Since, however, it is clear that surveillance of unrestricted forces provides
                        but a small measure of relief from the threat of massive surprise attack,
                        the meetings may, upon a successful completion of discussions of
                        surveillance without limitations, turn to the discussion of techniques of
                        monitoring of hypothetical situations in which limitations on forces are
                        imposed. No discussion of specific limitations, e.g., number of missile
                        sites on both sides will be allowed, but the problem of monitoring an
                        undefined restriction on the number of operational missiles may be proper
                        under conditions defined above.</p>
                    <pb facs="0699" n="669" xml:id="pg_669"/>
                    <p>Unless the delegation has the freedom to actually explore the technical
                        feasibility of such safeguards against surprise attack, they will be [<hi rend="italic">3½ lines of source text not declassified</hi>].</p>
                    <closer><signed><list>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_KGB2"><hi rend="strong">G.B.
                                            Kistiakowsky</hi></persName></item>
                                <item><persName><hi rend="strong">W.H. Minshull</hi></persName>,
                                    Jr.</item>
                            </list></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>