<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-08-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-08-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="227" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d227">
                    <head>227. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d227fn0">Source: Department of State, Secretary’s Memoranda of Conversation: Lot
                            64 D 199. Secret; Limit Distribution. Drafted by Morris and approved by
                                <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> on August 24. For
                                <persName corresp="#p_KGB2">Kistiakowsky</persName>’s account of
                            this meeting, see <hi rend="italic">A Scientist at the White House,</hi>
                            pp. 36–37.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1959-08-13">August 13, 1959</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Meeting of the Principals—Geneva Nuclear Test Negotiations</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">State Department</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName></item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName>Sullivan</persName>—<gloss target="#t_SAE1">S/AE</gloss></item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName>Morris</persName>—<gloss target="#t_SAE1">S/AE</gloss></item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName>Borg</persName>—<gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><gloss target="#t_DOD1"><hi rend="italic">D.O.D.</hi></gloss>
                            <list>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GTSJ1">Gates</persName></item>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_LGHB1">Gen. Loper</persName></item>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_FGAP1">Gen. Fox</persName></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">White House</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG6">Gordon Gray</persName></item>
                                <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KGB2">Kistiakowsky</persName></item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KSMJ1">Keeny</persName></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><gloss target="#t_AEC1"><hi rend="italic">A.E.C.</hi></gloss>
                            <list>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName></item>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_SAD2">Gen. Starbird</persName></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss></hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName></item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName>Brent</persName></item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> stated that he had called
                        the group together to bring them up to date on developments at the nuclear
                        test conference and to present State Department ideas on tactics for the
                        immediate future. He mentioned that we have received word that the <persName corresp="#p_KJRJ1">Killian</persName> technical discussions with the
                        British in London went well and that agreement was reached between our
                        scientists on the technical assessment of the underground problem.<note n="1" xml:id="d227fn1">Reference is to the report of the Joint
                                U.S.–<gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> Technical Group To Review
                            Technical Aspects of Nuclear Weapons Test Detection, which met in London
                            August 10–11. (<persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>
                            Library, <persName corresp="#p_WGTD1">White</persName> House Office
                            Files, Additional Records of the Special Assistant for Science and
                            Technology) See the Supplement.</note> Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KJRJ1">Killian</persName> is expected to brief the group in Washington in the
                        very near future. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FPJ1">Farley</persName> has gone
                        on to Geneva to inform Amb. <persName corresp="#p_WJJ2">Wadsworth</persName>
                        and the U.S. Delegation of the result of the discussions.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said that we have had the
                        impression from discussions during the last two or three weeks with the
                        British Chargé here that the <pb facs="0796" n="766" xml:id="pg_766"/>
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.K.</gloss> was very wary of making any significant
                        move in the Geneva negotiations until after their general elections, which
                        may be held around October 20. More specifically, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HCAJ1">Herter</persName> last weekend received a letter from
                        Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LJSB1">Lloyd</persName><note n="2" xml:id="d227fn2">Dated August 7. (Department of State, Presidential
                            Correspondence: Lot 66 D 204, <persName corresp="#p_LJSB1">Lloyd</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_HCAJ1">Herter</persName>)</note> which contained the following proposals: <list>
                            <label>1)</label>
                            <item>That the U.S. and <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> take no
                                action at Geneva until the scientists have had an opportunity to
                                report to their Governments on the result of the London discussions
                                and until the Governments have had time to consider the situation in
                                the light of their reports.</item>
                            <label>2)</label>
                            <item>That the best course would seem to be to wait until the President
                                and the Prime Minister meet in London, when they can thoroughly
                                review the situation together and decide on the best strategy and
                                tactics.</item>
                            <label>3)</label>
                            <item>That we should bear in mind the probability that the conference
                                will be discussed by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> when he visits Washington.</item>
                            <label>4)</label>
                            <item>Finally, <persName corresp="#p_LJSB1">Lloyd</persName> proposed
                                that the conference recess for a “summer holiday” from the last week
                                in August for a period of about 3–4 weeks.<note n="3" xml:id="d227fn3">The conference was in recess from August 28 to
                                    October 27.</note> This would allow the conference to reconvene
                                before the United Nations General Assembly really gets down to
                                work.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said that we, for different
                        reasons, had likewise concluded that a recess would be advantageous at this
                        time. Among these was the President’s decision to appoint Amb. <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> to escort Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> during his visit here. Since
                            <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> would be absent from the
                            <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> during the first two weeks of the
                        General Assembly, it will be necessary for Amb. <persName corresp="#p_WJJ2">Wadsworth</persName>, his Deputy, to return to this country to head the
                        U.S. Delegation to the General Assembly. For this reason it would seem wise
                        to extend the recess until October 12, a date which would allow adequate
                        turnover time for Amb. <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> in New
                        York and allow Amb. <persName corresp="#p_WJJ2">Wadsworth</persName> to be
                        briefed in Washington prior to returning to Geneva. This date, however,
                        raised a new element in our thinking with regard to our public posture in
                        the test negotiations. The Soviets have of late made much of various
                        statements in the American press that we were preparing to resume testing
                        after October 31. A six-weeks’ recess would bring us back to the
                        negotiations close to October 31 and expose us to Soviet charges that the
                        recess was nothing but a delaying tactic, since it would be obvious that no
                        conclusion could be reached in the negotiations prior to the October 31 date
                        which we had previously set for our unilateral moratorium. In view of this
                        situation and since the President will probably not visit Moscow until
                        November or early December, the State Department had come to the conclusion
                        that it might be the best course for the U.S., when requesting the recess,
                        to make a unilateral statement <pb facs="0797" n="767" xml:id="pg_767"/>
                        that because of the length of the recess we intend to continue to refrain
                        from nuclear testing until December 31 of this year.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said that when discussing
                        the <persName corresp="#p_WJJ2">Wadsworth</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> problem, and before the State
                        Department views had been expressed, the President had expressed the strong
                        feeling that we should propose to extend our moratorium until the end of the
                        year. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> had said that he
                        felt likewise but that he would like to discuss such a move with the other
                        principals. The President had replied that this would of course be in order,
                        but reiterated that he felt strongly on the matter.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said that there therefore
                        seemed to be two courses open at the moment: <list>
                            <label>1)</label>
                            <item>To agree to a recess and a suitable announcement concerning the
                                extension of our voluntary moratorium. In any case the <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> had expressed doubts during the
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KJRJ1">Killian</persName> discussions in
                                London as to how we might best present our argument for a more
                                limited agreement to the Soviet Union. They want to consider the
                                problem further. Thus we probably could not get <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> agreement to raise the <persName corresp="#p_BRF2">Bacher</persName> Panel data in Geneva prior
                                to the President’s visit to London.</item>
                            <label>2)</label>
                            <item>If any of the other agencies strongly disagree with this course,
                                then they should reopen the question with the President in
                                Gettysburg.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GTSJ1">Gates</persName> said he felt this move
                        constituted a major change in the position agreed upon at the July 23
                        meeting with the President.<note n="4" xml:id="d227fn4">See <ref target="#d225">Document 225</ref>.</note> This would mean that the
                        new scientific argument militating against a complete underground test
                        cessation would not be presented before mid-October. He felt that we should
                        at least either inform the Soviet Delegation that we intended to discuss the
                        technical problems of underground detection when the conference reconvenes
                        or alternatively give them a paper setting forth the problem which they
                        could study during the recess. In any event it would be important to get
                        something on our intentions in the record before the recess. He further felt
                        that the decision to extend our voluntary moratorium would have unfortunate
                        consequences on our weapons development program. He would prefer to delay
                        any extension announcement until it became clear that such a move was
                        necessary.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said he expected that the
                        President would be under such pressure during the exchange of visits that he
                        will feel it necessary to make some announcement. With regard to the July 23
                        decision, it had been his understanding that this course of action was
                        subject to working out the arrangements with the <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> Clearly the U.S. would have extreme difficulties in
                        proceeding without the <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss></p>
                    <pb facs="0798" n="768" xml:id="pg_768"/>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> said he felt that we would
                        continue to get a soft line from the <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> as
                        long as they were worried about their elections. Moreover, if we delay our
                        presentation on the limited agreement we run the risk that our colleague at
                        the conference table will represent a different <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> Government, should Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MHS2">Macmillan</persName>’s party be defeated in the election. He believed
                        that the basic <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> desire was to reach
                        agreement on a total cessation of testing regardless of whether it were
                        completely safeguarded. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GTSJ1">Gates</persName>
                        said he could not see why the basically sound phased limited cessation
                        agreement we had proposed would be so disastrous to the <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> elections. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> replied that of course the <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> was the best judge of that and emphasized that they have
                        been quite emphatic in their desire for no shift in the negotiations before
                        the President’s meeting with <persName corresp="#p_MHS2">Macmillan</persName> in London.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said that some U.S.
                        scientists, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KGB2">Kistiakowsky</persName> in
                        particular, have continued to study the limited agreement and have developed
                        some serious reservations concerning our proposal for a joint developmental
                        or exploration program to improve our knowledge of seismic detection. They
                        feel the best way to approach the new problem is to continue the
                        negotiations in the present pattern but to ask for a high quota of
                        inspections—somewhere around the 375 events which would be outstanding each
                        year in the Soviet Union.</p>
                    <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KGB2">Kistiakowsky</persName> explained that he was
                        very much afraid that from a purely technical point of view the U.S. would
                        be open to a rather devastating attack if we proposed an agreement to ban
                        atmospheric and high altitude tests while exempting underground testing. The
                        experts in Geneva had expressed in their report the possibilities for
                        evading detection in outer space—albeit at very high cost. Thus, while on
                        the one hand we are saying that we cannot agree to ban underground tests
                        because of a theoretical possibility of evasion, on the other we would be
                        agreeing to ban tests in outer space where there was a more certain
                        possibility for evasion. Furthermore, he felt it would be very difficult to
                        present the Bacher report in Geneva, particularly a description of the
                        intelligence factors involved. The sum of these considerations led him to
                        believe that the U.S. would be open to the accusation that we are being
                        inconsistent technically. Another area of concern is that a joint
                        investigation of possible means for evading an underground ban would be very
                        difficult to arrange timewise. Such an investigation would be a continuing
                        type of undertaking rather than simply one or two shots to prove or disprove
                        a theory. The Soviets are unlikely to agree to anything without a definite
                        termination date.</p>
                    <p>In response to a suggestion by <persName corresp="#p_LGHB1">Gen.
                            Loper</persName> that perhaps the best course would be to return to our
                        old position that we only ban what can be controlled and thus withdraw from
                        including high altitude tests in the <pb facs="0799" n="769" xml:id="pg_769"/> agreement, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said that he
                        had understood that the possibility of evasion exists only in far space.</p>
                    <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KGB2">Kistiakowsky</persName> said that this was
                        indeed the case. In view of the rather substantial weights which would be
                        carried by the 1–1/2-million-lb.–thrust or the 6-million-lb.-thrust engines
                        under development now in this country, and presumably in the Soviet Union,
                        one will in a very few years be able to carry devices with heavy shields to
                        these far distances.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> said that it would seem to
                        him that if such powerful vehicles would be available they would be able to
                        carry practically any weight bomb we have already, and thus it would not be
                        necessary to test to develop lighter weapons for use with our less powerful
                        missiles.</p>
                    <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KGB2">Kistiakowsky</persName> said he completely
                        agreed with this thought. He believes that nuclear testing in outer space
                        for developmental purposes would be the quickest way of pauperizing oneself
                        he knows. Such tests may cost hundreds of millions of dollars each and,
                        since the amount of information which would be obtained from outer space
                        would be slim, we would require many such tests. Of course, the principle
                        remains that evasion in far space is possible. He is worried as a technical
                        person about the inconsistency of the U.S. position in refusing to deal with
                        the underground situation while at the same time agreeing to an outer space
                        ban where there is a loophole.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> commented that if indeed
                        the question of evasion of an underground agreement is a never-ending
                        possibility, he believes there is a strong argument in support of returning
                        to our original position of a complete cessation and handling the
                        underground situation by proposing 375 on-site inspections in the Soviet
                        Union each year. <persName corresp="#p_SAD2">Gen. Starbird</persName>
                        pointed out that even if the Soviet Union were to agree to such a number of
                        inspections we would still have no guarantee against small underground tests
                        by means of which the Soviet Union could push their weapons development
                        quite far.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> expressed his concern that
                        the proposed extension of our unilateral moratorium would be one more step
                        in the erosion of our position. He felt we have already lost the threshold
                        because we have not squarely proposed it in the negotiations. If we now
                        extend our moratorium to December 31 because of the very real pressures
                        which exist vis-à-vis the <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss>, other crises
                        in the future can be expected to militate toward further extensions. He did
                        not believe that the U.S. could afford to take the position, as the <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> seemed determined to do, that all testing
                        must be stopped, unless we were absolutely sure that the Soviet Union is
                        doing the same.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said that we were faced
                        with the necessity of this recess. The question remaining is the tactics to
                        be used.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GTSJ1">Gates</persName> again expressed his concern
                        about the extension move. He felt it has considerably more implications than
                        merely an extension until <pb facs="0800" n="770" xml:id="pg_770"/> the end
                        of this year. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> said that
                        in the future it would be easy to argue for similar extensions because of
                        our own election year, and then because of our elections, and then because a
                        new President will be assuming office. This continuing uncertainty had
                        considerable impact on our testing program. Eighteen months’ lead time is
                        required for a large-scale series of tests in the Pacific, and even for
                        underground tests in Nevada for which we already have tunnels we would need
                        three months’ lead time. <persName corresp="#p_SAD2">Gen.
                            Starbird</persName> added that no significant preparation in Nevada can
                        be taken without the fact becoming public information.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said that in any case he
                        did not believe that the President would be able to reach a decision to
                        resume testing before the end of December. Mr. <persName>Sullivan</persName>
                        noted that our willingness to extend our voluntary moratorium may very
                        likely be the sine qua non to Soviet agreement to a recess. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said he thought that if as he
                        believed we would not be in a position because of the <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> visits to test anyway, it would be best to make
                        an announcement along the lines suggested by the President.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> proposed that perhaps a
                        more satisfactory way to handle an extension, if it is indeed necessary,
                        would be merely to have Amb. <persName corresp="#p_WJJ2">Wadsworth</persName>, when proposing a recess, say that we recognize
                        that the recess would last so close to the Oct. 31 deadline we could not
                        expect agreement before that time and that the U.S. is therefore willing
                        after October 31 to allow a reasonable period of time for progress in the
                        negotiations before deciding on a resumption of testing.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_SAD2">Gen. Starbird</persName> said he wished to bring
                        to the attention of the group the fact that he expects a tremendous letdown
                        on the part of the weapons laboratory scientists who are looking toward Oct.
                        31 for clarification of our intentions toward further testing. <persName corresp="#p_LGHB1">Gen. Loper</persName> said he felt it would be unwise
                        for the President to take such a decision without having an evaluation of
                        the decrease in our defensive readiness posture this no-testing situation is
                        causing. The situation should not be passed over lightly. <persName corresp="#p_SAD2">Gen. Starbird</persName> explained that even though
                        the laboratories could certify the worth of certain weapons, proof tests
                        were necessary for the Department of Defense to have full confidence in the
                        weapons.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said that if Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GTSJ1">Gates</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> feel they must present their opinions to the
                        President, the best course would be to seek an early meeting with the
                        President so that an answer to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJSB1">Lloyd</persName> might be sent by Monday evening, August 17.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GTSJ1">Gates</persName> said he wished to discuss
                        the situation further with his staff and with the Joint Chiefs. He was very
                        concerned that what was really being discussed was a complete cessation of
                        testing rather than <pb facs="0801" n="771" xml:id="pg_771"/> merely an
                        extension of the moratorium to December 31.<note n="5" xml:id="d227fn5">On
                            July 26, the Department of State announced an extension of the
                            moratorium until December 31. For text of the statement, see <hi rend="italic">Documents on Disarmament, 1945–1959,</hi> pp.
                            1439–1440.</note> There will always be a reason why a resumption of
                        tests should be deferred.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said he believed that any
                        basic conclusions on the need for resuming testing will be based on the
                        report of the <persName corresp="#p_KGB2">Kistiakowsky</persName> Panel,
                        which is expected by August 21. This report will detail the consequences to
                        the United States of delaying testing. He would think in any case that the
                        possibility of a definite decision by the President on the basis of this
                        report would be unrealistic prior to his departure to Europe on August 26.
                        Thus there could be no decisions before sometime in September.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Brent</persName> asked whether the Department of Defense was
                        proposing to resume testing to improve our defense posture vis-à-vis the
                        Soviet Union. Were they assuming that the Soviet Union would not itself
                        resume testing and that we would thus improve our two-year lead time?</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> said it was worthwhile to
                        discuss this point. The United States bases its defense policy on nuclear
                        weapons to offset the manpower advantage of the Sino-Soviet bloc. If this
                        policy is good, then we must be in the best possible technological position.
                        This requires continued development and testing. We can reduce the fear of
                        fallout by testing underground and in the upper atmosphere. But to withdraw
                        any further than that would be to allow the basis of our defense policy to
                        erode away. He did not think that the Soviet Union is aiming only toward a
                        cessation of testing. Rather they seek to get a lead on all nuclear weapons,
                        thus leaving the free world to the mercy of their defense superiority. The
                        United States must decide whether it will allow itself to be forced into
                        this course.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Sullivan</persName> pointed out that we were not proposing to
                        shift away from the limited agreement approach, but only revising our
                        timing. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> affirmed this.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_SAD2">General Starbird</persName> noted that when
                        nuclear weapons leave development laboratories and are deployed by the armed
                        forces the possibility of espionage is increased. We have indications that
                        the Soviet Union has been able to gain considerable useful information on
                        specific weapons. There are, however, no parallel cases on the part of the
                        United States.</p>
                    <p>After some discussion of the report expected from the <persName corresp="#p_KGB2">Kistiakowsky</persName> Panel, it was agreed that it
                        would be best for the panel to report in writing to Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KGB2">Kistiakowsky</persName>, who would then brief the
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>, orally rather than by circulating a
                        written document. This would avoid undue dissemination and the possibility
                        of leaks.</p>
                    <pb facs="0802" n="772" xml:id="pg_772"/>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said that if we are to
                        approach the Soviet Union next week concerning a recess we will need to be
                        able to reply to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJSB1">Lloyd</persName>’s message
                        by August 17 at the latest. It would thus be necessary to see the President
                        on August 17 at Gettysburg if any of the principals wished to dispute the
                        proposed tactics. The State Department would therefore draft a reply to
                            <persName corresp="#p_LJSB1">Lloyd</persName> accepting a recess and
                        indicating that we will announce our intention to continue to refrain from
                        testing for a reasonable time after October 31. He would expect this evening
                        or tomorrow morning a clarification of the views of the Department of
                        Defense.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG6">Gray</persName> said he thought we should make
                        an effort to present the <persName corresp="#p_BRF2">Bacher</persName> data
                        before the recess, or at least put the Soviets on notice that we consider a
                        discussion of the technical problem essential when we return from the
                        recess.</p>
                    <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KGB2">Kistiakowsky</persName> said he felt that the
                            <persName corresp="#p_BLV1">Berkner</persName> report had made our
                        concerns to the Soviets clear. Couldn’t we just make clear to them our
                        intention to return to this matter?</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Sullivan</persName> pointed out that any advance indication
                        that we intended to press for discussion of the technical problems would
                        probably cause the Soviets to refuse to agree to a recess. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said that in any case we should plan
                        to raise the matter as soon as the Conference reconvenes.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>