<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-03-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-03-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="55" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d55">
                    <head>55. National Security Council Report<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d55fn0">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files: Lot 62 D 1,
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5904 Series. Top Secret; Limited
                            Distribution. A cover sheet is not printed.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-03-17">March 17,
                            1959</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                        5904/1</seg></opener>
                    <p rend="center">NOTE BY THE EXECUTIVE SECRETARY TO THE NATIONAL SECURITY
                        COUNCIL ON U.S. POLICY IN THE EVENT OF WAR</p>
                    <list type="references">
                        <head>REFERENCES</head>
                        <item>A. <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5410/1</item>
                        <item>B. Memo for <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> from Acting Executive
                            Secretary, subject: “Basic Military Planning Concept to Govern Planning
                            and Development of the Mobilization Base”, dated March 1, 1957<note n="1" xml:id="d55fn1">This memorandum enclosed a memorandum dated
                                February 25, 1957, from Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_WCE2">Charles E. Wilson</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_LJSJ1">Lay</persName>. For text, see <ref target="frus1955-57v19#pg_419"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1955–1957, vol. XIX, pp. 419</ref>–<ref target="frus1955-57v19#pg_424">424</ref>.</note></item>
                        <item>C. <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5810/1</item>
                        <item>D. Memo for <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> from Executive
                            Secretary, subject: “Review of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            5410/1”, dated January 7, 1959</item>
                        <pb facs="0238" n="208" xml:id="pg_208"/>
                        <item>E. <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 2039</item>
                        <item>F. Memos for <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> from Executive
                            Secretary, subject: “<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5904”, dated
                            March 3 and 9, 1959</item>
                        <item>G. <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 2056</item>
                        <item>H. <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5904</item>
                        <item>I. <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 2057</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The National Security Council, the Secretary of the Treasury, the Director,
                        Bureau of the Budget, and the Acting Chairman, Atomic Energy Commission, at
                        the 398th and 399th <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Meetings on March 5
                        and 12, 1959, adopted the statement of policy in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5904, as amended by <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                        Actions Nos. 2056–b and 2057–b.</p>
                    <p>The President has this date approved the statement of policy in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5904, as adopted by the Council and
                        enclosed herewith as <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5904/1; and
                        directed its use as a planning guide by all appropriate Executive
                        departments and agencies of the U.S. Government, subject to the
                        understanding that it will be reviewed annually.</p>
                    <p>The enclosed statement of policy, as adopted and approved, supersedes <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5410/1.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">It is requested that special security precautions be
                            observed in the handling of the enclosure, and that access to it be
                            strictly limited on a need-to-know basis.</hi></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_LJSJ1"><hi rend="strong">James S. Lay,
                                    Jr.</hi></persName><note n="2" xml:id="d55fn2">Printed from a
                                copy that bears this typed signature.</note></signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <note rend="inline" type="source"><hi rend="strong">Enclosure</hi></note>
                        <head>STATEMENT OF U.S. POLICY IN THE EVENT OF WAR</head>
                        <p rend="center">Section A: U.S. Policy in the Event of General War</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Special Note:</hi> This section of the policy statement
                            addresses itself only to the contingency of <hi rend="italic">general
                                war</hi>; it does not apply to situations of local aggression or
                            so-called “limited war”.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Objectives</hi></p>
                        <p>1. To prevail, and survive as a nation capable of controlling its own
                            destiny.</p>
                        <p>2. To reduce, by military and other measures, the capabilities of the
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and Communist China to the
                            point where they have lost their will and ability to wage war against
                            the United States and its allies.</p>
                        <pb facs="0239" n="209" xml:id="pg_209"/>
                        <p>3. To render ineffective the control structure by which the enemy regimes
                            have been able to exert ideological and disciplinary authority over
                            their own peoples and over individual citizens or groups of citizens in
                            other countries.</p>
                        <p>4. To preserve and retain as many of our allies as possible.</p>
                        <p>5. So far as consistent with the above objectives, to avoid destruction
                            and casualties in all countries not involved in war.</p>
                        <p>6. To retain in the United States a capacity for quick recovery from
                            nuclear assault.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Policy Guidance</hi></p>
                        <p>7.<note n="3" xml:id="d55fn3">Paragraph 7 contains the controlling policy
                                guidance with respect to military action to attain the foregoing
                                objectives. [Footnote in the source text.]</note> The United States
                            should utilize all requisite force against selected targets in the
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>—and as necessary in Communist
                            China, European Bloc and non-European Bloc countries—to attain the above
                            objectives. Military targets in Bloc countries other than the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and Communist China will be attacked
                            as necessary. (<hi rend="italic">Note</hi>: It is assumed that the
                            peoples of the Bloc countries other than the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and Communist China are not responsible for the acts
                            of their governments and accordingly so far as consistent with military
                            objectives military action against these countries should avoid
                            non-military destruction and casualties.)</p>
                        <p>8. If, in the course of the hostilities, an enemy country asks the United
                            States for peace terms, the United States should not accept any terms
                            unless they remove the threat to U.S. security posed by such
                            country.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Post-War Objectives</hi></p>
                        <p>9. To prevent, so far as practicable, the formation or retention after
                            the war of military power in potentially hostile states sufficient to
                            threaten the security of the United States.</p>
                        <p>10. To seek the eventual establishment in nations of the Sino-Soviet Bloc
                            of friendly governments founded upon broad-based, popular support.</p>
                        <p>11. To maintain after the cessation of hostilities sufficient U.S. and
                            allied military strength to deter aggression and to accomplish other
                            postwar objectives.</p>
                        <p>12. To establish effective international arrangements for the
                            preservation of peace.</p>
                        <pb facs="0240" n="210" xml:id="pg_210"/>
                        <p rend="center">Section B: U.S. Policy in the Event of a War in Which the
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> is Not a Belligerent<note n="4" xml:id="d55fn4">Present U.S. policy is based upon the
                                assumption that any war with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> would be general war. The validity of the
                                foregoing assumption is not an issue in this paper, but will be
                                susceptible of re-examination in the course of review of basic
                                policy (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5810/1). [Footnote in
                                the source text. This footnote was later deleted; see <ref target="#d95">Document 95</ref>.]</note></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Objectives</hi></p>
                        <p>13. To reduce, by military and other measures, the capabilities of the
                            enemy to the point where it has lost its will or ability to wage war
                            against the United States and its allies.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Policy Guidance</hi></p>
                        <p>14. The United States should be prepared to utilize such force as is
                            requisite to attain its objectives. If during the course of hostilities
                            general war becomes a clear probability, the United States will have to
                            decide in the light of the circumstances then existing whether it is in
                            the U.S. interest to alter its original objectives.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>