<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-10-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-10-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="37" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d37">
                        <head>37. Current Foreign Relations<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d37fn0">Source: Department of State, <hi rend="italic">Current Foreign
                                    Relations:</hi> Lot 64 D 189. Secret. <hi rend="italic">Current
                                    Foreign Relations</hi> was a weekly classified periodical
                                circulated by the Executive Secretariat of the Department of State
                                to offices in the Department and diplomatic and consular posts
                                abroad.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">Issue No. 43</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-10-29">October 29, 1958</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">NORTHERN EUROPEAN CHIEFS OF MISSION MEET<note n="1" xml:id="d37fn1">The meeting was held October 6–8. An agenda for the
                                meeting, a list of participants, and other preparatory papers are
                                    <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Central File 120.1441. No other
                                record of the discussion at the meeting has been found.</note></p>
                        <p>At a meeting in London this month our Chiefs of Mission in the British
                            Commonwealth and Northern European countries reviewed the political and
                            economic situation in each country in the area. They received an
                            evaluation of current Soviet policy and strategy from our Ambassador in
                            Moscow and heard briefings on the Far East, European integration and the
                            Free Trade Area, and Middle East development. In addition, they
                            discussed current <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            military-political problems, the Icelandic fisheries problem and a
                            second conference on the law of the sea. The following were the
                            principal conclusions of the discussions:</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Canada</hi>—Recent developments in Canadian domestic
                            politics and foreign policy make it clear that United States relations
                            with Canada cannot be taken for granted. Future United States-Canadian
                            difficulties may be more political than economic since the principal
                            economic frictions have receded. However, there is a considerable
                            protectionist attitude in the Canadian Government and some Canadian
                            anxiety about the extent of United States control over the Canadian
                            economy. Politically, Canada feels it necessary to assert independence
                            from the United States, and the Conservative Party is sentimentally
                            attached to the United Kingdom.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Denmark</hi>—The Danish political situation is stable
                            with the Social Democrats and their allies in power probably until 1961.
                            Denmark’s monetary contribution for defense and therefore its support of
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> is less than it can afford but
                            is not likely to be increased. Denmark’s support of our foreign policy
                            is generally good, and Denmark’s provision, without charge, of base
                            rights to the United States in Greenland and facilities in the Faroes
                            Islands is of inestimable importance. Denmark regards our attitude
                            toward Communist China as illogical, believing that the Chinese
                            Communist regime should be admitted to the United Nations and recognized
                            by the United States.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Finland</hi>—Finland is independent, anti-Communist,
                            anti-Russian, and pro-western, but its proximity to the USSR forces the
                            Finns in international <pb facs="0106" n="70" xml:id="pg_70"/> affairs
                            to keep out of big power disputes and take a neutral position. The
                            present coalition government could well last for two or three years if
                            it can survive economic difficulties this winter. Finland would like to
                            join a Scandinavian customs union as a stepping stone to the Free Trade
                            Area. Inability to join a Free Trade Area, if it is formed, would mean
                            increased economic dependence on the USSR.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Iceland</hi>—The fisheries dispute dominates Icelandic
                            politics, and the present three party coalition including the
                            Communist-front Labor Alliance is held together by the reluctance of all
                            three parties to face elections in the light of the fisheries issue. The
                            Conservative opposition fully supports the 12-mile fisheries limit. In
                            the light of the Icelanders’ present temper, there is no prospect of
                            fruitful negotiations on the fisheries dispute. A temporary, tacit modus
                            vivendi might be effected if the present cat-and-mouse tactics at the
                            12-mile limit could be called off. The general economic situation in the
                            country has deteriorated during the past year, and all parties will seek
                            markets and financial assistance from any quarter, including the USSR,
                            with consequent danger to our base rights.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Ireland</hi>—Ireland is basically anti-Communist.
                            Ireland’s leaders are sensitive and are isolated from world problems, a
                            condition aggravated by Irish neutrality and the fact that the United
                            States often appears to ignore Irish views. The Irish military is
                            pro-American and pro-western, and it hopes for our aid and training.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Norway</hi>—In Norway the Labor Party has been in power
                            for over 20 years except for a coalition government during the war, and
                            there is no real alternative to a Labor Party government. In foreign
                            affairs, while the Norwegians firmly support <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> they strongly desire a reduction in tensions and favor
                            positions permitting step by step progress in negotiations and the
                            consideration of schemes for disengagement in Europe. [<hi rend="italic">4½ lines of source text not declassified</hi>] The Norwegians’
                            distrust of military solutions makes them apprehensive of American
                            activities and policies which may involve the use of force.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Sweden</hi>—Sweden’s basic foreign policy is
                            nonalignment and avoidance of involvement in a world war. [<hi rend="italic">5 lines of source text not declassified</hi>] Sweden
                            is deeply interested in the problem of disarmament and believes it
                            essential that Communist China be admitted to the United Nations to
                            allow stationing of inspection posts in China. This attitude comes in
                            part from fear of atomic annihilation and a desire to avoid the
                            necessity of enormous expenditure of funds for atomic weapons, which
                            could then be devoted to social welfare programs. The Swedes believe
                            that no effort at disengagement such as the Rapacki plan should be
                            lightly disposed of.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">United Kingdom</hi>—British-American relations are
                            exceptionally close and are increasingly coordinated through working
                            parties. The British people generally support this close working
                            relationship, and <pb facs="0107" n="71" xml:id="pg_71"/> the only real
                            disagreement is over our policy toward the Far East—i.e., Chinese
                            representation, recognition of the Chinese Communists, and defense of
                            the offshore islands. A potential problem for close United
                            States-British relationship is the possibility that the Labor Party, in
                            order to try to overcome the Conservative Party’s present popularity,
                            may take positions much more left-of-center on issues such as nuclear
                            disarmament, bases and negotiations with the USSR.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Soviet Policy and Strategy</hi>—The principal aims of
                            the Soviet people are a better standard of living and a relaxation of
                            the controls over them by their leaders. The principal aims of the
                            Soviet leaders are world domination, break-up of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and acceptance of the status quo in
                            Europe. The recent more aggressive nature of Soviet action in the
                            foreign policy sphere has been influenced by the Hungarian uprising.
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s efforts to gain
                            support of the broad mass of the Soviet people have alienated smaller
                            but influential groups and have thereby increased strains within the
                            Soviet system. The United States should gain increased opportunities to
                            make its influence felt by pointing up how little the Soviet people have
                            been given by their leaders. An increased demand by the Soviet people
                            for consumer goods and relaxation of controls, which would be in our
                            interests, might well be stimulated by further expanding activities
                            under the United States–USSR exchange agreement and the American exhibit
                            of our science, technology and culture in Gorki Park next summer.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                                Military-Political Problems</hi>—<gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> is passing through a difficult phase. Because of
                            stresses arising out of such disputes as Cyprus and Icelandic fisheries
                            and the unwillingness or inability of many <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> countries to meet <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>’s minimum force requirements, there are major problems
                            to be overcome. Nevertheless, the wider political consultation taking
                            place in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> has proceeded well. The
                            special close relationship between the United States and the United
                            Kingdom presents problems for our relations with France and other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> countries. It would be most helpful
                            if there could be national acceptance of the concept of balanced
                            collective <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> forces.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">The Free Trade Area</hi>—Although some of the obstacles
                            which have impeded progress on the Free Trade Area are in the process of
                            being reduced, further concessions from all parties will probably be
                            required before the Free Trade Area can come into effect. It is now
                            recognized that this will probably not be possible by January. We favor
                            the Free Trade Area on condition that it does not relax the impetus
                            toward the Common Market and general liberalization of trade. We will
                            try to be helpful but direct intervention and pressure are regarded as
                            counterproductive. The Scandinavians basically appear to be most
                            interested and favorable toward the Free Trade Area, but each has
                            special problems <pb facs="0108" n="72" xml:id="pg_72"/> and they have
                            various degrees of interest in a Scandinavian Common Market as an
                            alternative to, or avenue toward, the Free Trade Area.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Icelandic Fisheries</hi>—All the Scandinavian countries
                            consider that the technical aspects of the Icelandic fisheries problem
                            have been exhausted, and that what is required are political decisions.
                            Time is running against us in Iceland. It is our position that a second
                            law of the sea conference should consider territorial limits and fishing
                            limits separately from other questions. Our Navy is interested in
                            keeping narrow territorial seas. It prefers three miles but will
                            possibly compromise on six.</p>
                        <p>[Here follow other articles on unrelated subjects.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>