<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Exhibit No. 5.. 5.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1902app2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d58</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">58</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1851-12-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1852-10-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85076761"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">License</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recORcNZq5ClDOVNg" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046356"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exhibit</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1852-10-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1851-12-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="58"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d58">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Exhibit No</hi>. 5.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1851-12-20" to="1852-10-08" type="content-date">December 20,
                            1852–October 8, 1852</date>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table cols="2" rows="30">
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peticiones que ha hecho al Supremo Gobierno el Y.
                                Sr. Obispo de Californias en su nota de</hi> 7 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >del corriente y carta particular de la misma fecha.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">petitions which were made to the supreme government
                                by the bishop of californias in his note of the</hi> 7<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">th of the present month and in a private letter of
                                the same date.</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Desde que se quitaron á los misioneros las temporalidades que ellos
                            mismos crearon y aumentaron, con su trabajo personal y sus sinodos,
                            entraron á disfrutar los bienes de las, misiones los seculares y sus
                            familias y entre el los algunos que no conozco á quienes no se podia
                            fiar ni aun una pequena cantidad. Ya se deja entender la ruina de tales
                            bienes en semejantes manos. En el ministerio de V. E. deben exister los
                            reclamos, que sobre eso tengo hechos, y por los que el congreso general
                            dio una ley suspensiva de la que mandaba la secularization de misiones,
                            la que hasta ahora segun entiendo no se ha cumplido quizas por justas
                            considerations del gobierno. En posteriores reclamos que hice en el año
                            treinta y seis, informé al Supremo Gobierno de los males que los
                            misioneros padecen y entre ellos no es el menor, qui los administradores
                            de la misiones se apoderaron de las casas en que vivian los padres; unas
                            casas fabricadas por los religiosos, y en cuya construction invirtieron
                            los sinodos que percibian y el trabajo de sus manos. Se han visto
                            reducidos a vivir allí como arruinados y con bastante incomodidad <pb
                                facs="0420" n="412" xml:id="pg_412"/> como yo mismo lo ví. Tienen en
                            la misma habitacion á unas gentes que en muchas noches no los dejan
                            descanzar por las embriagueses, juegos óbailes que con escandalo estan
                            presenciando los neo fitos! Vida insufrible ciertamente! Vida
                            amarguisimapara unos religiosos recoletos, y tanto que muchos de ellos
                            han pensado abandonar las misiones, y retirarse á butscar la
                            tranquilidad y paz de sus espiritus! Vida penosa que ha retraido y
                            retrae à muchos de ir á las misiones por no exponere á tantos
                            padecimentos y desprecios de su caracter! Mas no se crea por esto que
                            quiero se lleve á efecto la entregada de las temporalidades á los
                            religiosos. Sé muy bien y aun lo tengo dicho al gobierno que dentro de
                            breve tiempo ya no nabra nada de los bienes que tenian aquellas
                            opulentas misiones los que recibieron los administradores cuando los
                            padres las entregaron. Lo que quiero es que para las misiones nuevas que
                            se vayan estableciendo, se tomen medidas legislativas para que no se
                            repitan las graves desordenes. De otro modo, Que padre misionero habrá
                            que quiera trabajar por aumentar los bienes de los Yndios infelices si
                            sabe por experieneia que se les han de quitar á sus legitimos dueños, y
                            se han de entregar á otros para que los disfruten, roben, y tiren sin
                            haberles costado ningun trabajo? Cual será el religioso que quiera hacer
                            casa ni plantar huerta para su recreo y sueomodidad, si ha visto que con
                            la moyor injusticia se las quitan, y entran á poseerlas hombres que
                            antes se socorrian con limosnas por los mismos misioneros y que
                            repentinamente se mudan los Señores y tienen los infelices padres que
                            vivir á sus espensas? En lo que insisto é insistiré siempres es, en que
                            queden á los misioneros las casas y huertas que ellos ó sus antecesores
                            hicieron que estan contiguas a las iglesias y con inmediata comunicacion
                                <pb facs="0421" n="413" xml:id="pg_413"/> á ellas. Los
                            administradores (como que tienen á su disposicion á los Yndios y los
                            intereses de las misiones) pueden hacer casa para elles, y dejar á los
                            padres quietos y en paz. Esta medida la juzeo tan necesaria que sino se
                            toma no tabra quien quiera ir á servir las misiones, yo desde ahora lo
                            prevengo al Supremo Gobierno; y si para los misioneros es una medida tan
                            necesaria, que se debe decir con respecto al Obispo? Esto será une cosa
                            bien dura que mientras puede edificar su casa, no tenga en donde
                            recogerse con su familia ni en donde poner sus estudiantes y ministros,
                            ni en donde dar principio á su seminario? Por esto pues suplico al
                            Supremo Gobierno.</cell>
                        <cell>Since there has been taken from the missionaries the properties which
                            they established and increased by their personal la bors and with their
                            allowances, the secular and their families have begun to enjoy the
                            properties of the missions, and among them some I am not acquainted with
                            and who could not be trusted with even the smallest amount. Already the
                            ruin of the properties has begun in such hands. In the department of
                            your excellency there must be the reclamations which I have made, and
                            for which the General Congress made a law suspending that which ordered
                            the secularization of the missions, which up to this time, as I
                            understand, has not been carried out, perhaps through just
                            considerations of the Government. In the later reclamation which I made
                            in the year 1836, I informed the Supreme Government of the injuries
                            suffered by the missionaries, and not the least of them was that the
                            administrators of the missions took possession of the houses in which
                            the fathers were living; some houses having been built by the religious,
                            and in whose construction were applied the allowances which they
                            received and the work of their own hands. They were compelled to live in
                            them as ruined and with great inconveniences as, I myself saw. There
                            were in the same building some persons who, many nights, would not allow
                            them to rest for their drunkenness, games, and dances in which the
                            neophytes scandalously indulge! A life most distressing for religious
                            recluses; indeed, so very distressing that many of them have thought of
                            abandoning the missions and retiring in search of tranquility and peace
                            of spirit! This painful life has dissuaded and does dissuade many from
                            going to the missions, not wishing to expose themselves to such abuses
                            and depreciations! But it must not be thought by this that I wish to
                            cause the transfer of the properties to the religious. I know very well,
                            and yet I have told the Government that within a short time there will
                            remain nothing of the properties which belonged to those such missions
                            and which were received by the administrators when the fathers turned
                            them over. What I wish is that for the new missions which are about to
                            be established legislative measures be taken to prevent the repetition
                            of such serious disorders. Otherwise, what missionary father is there
                            who wants to labor to increase the properties of the unfortunate Indians
                            if he knows by experience that they are to be taken from their
                            legitimate owners and are to be delivered to others to enjoy, plunder,
                            and waste without having cost them any exertion? Where could be found
                            the religious who would wish to erect a house or plant a garden for his
                            diversion and convenience, if he has seen them taken from him with the
                            greatest injustice and men entering into their possession who had
                            formerly been aided with alms by the same missionaries, and suddenly the
                            superiors are changed and the unfortunate fathers have to live at their
                            own expense. What I insist on and always will insist is that there shall
                            belong to the missionaries the houses and gardens they or their
                            predecessors made which are contiguous to the churches and immediately
                            communicating with them. The administrators (inasmuch as they have under
                            their control the Indians and the interests of the missions) can build a
                            house for them, and leave the fathers in quiet and peace. This measure I
                            consider so necessary that unless it be taken there will be no one to go
                            to serve the missions, of which fact I now warn the supreme Government;
                            and if this measure be so necessary for the missionaries, what should be
                            said with regard to the bishop? Would it not indeed be a hardship if
                            while he might build his house he would have no place in which to bring
                            his family nor in which to place his students and ministers, nor in
                            which to start his seminary? Therefore I petition the supreme
                            Government:</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1°. Que se da una orden (la misma que yo llevaré) para que se
                            entreguen á los misioneros las casas y huertas de las misiones, y que la
                            de San Diego ó la de San Luis Rey sea ocupada interinamente por el
                            obispo y sus familiares juntamente con el padre misionero, hasta que el
                            obispo pueda hacer su casa episcopal y el edificio para su
                            seminario.</cell>
                        <cell>1st. That an order be given (the same as I shall deliver) that the
                            houses and gardens of the missions be delivered to the missionaries, and
                            that that of San Diego or that of San Luis King be occupied temporarily
                            by the bishop and his associates, together with the father missionary,
                            until the diocese can erect its episcopal house and the building-for its
                            seminary.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2°. Los administradores niegan por lo regular los servicios de los
                            Yndios á los padres, y esto aun pagandoles lo justo. Esto exige otra
                            disposicion del Supremo Gobierno para que se me franqueen sirvientes con
                            sus salarios equitativos y no arbitrarios. Juntamente suplico se me dé
                            el terreno para edicif ar mi iglesia, mi casa y mi seminario.</cell>
                        <cell>2nd. The directors commonly withheld the services of the Indians from
                            the fathers, even though they paid them a just compensation. This
                            necessitates another arrangement on the part of the Supreme Government
                            in order that servants may be allowed me with equitable and not
                            arbitrary salaries. At the same time I pray that land be allowed me in
                            order that I may build my church, my house, and my seminary.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <pb facs="0422" n="414" xml:id="pg_414"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>3°. Bien sabe el Supremo Gobierno que no tengo en mi obispado mas
                            eclesiasticos que los religiosos Fernandinos, Zacaltecanos y Dominicos
                            de esta Provincia de Mexico, y si los prelados de estas corporaciones
                            nos quitan a sus subditos las gracias que por misioneros tienen en su or
                            den., y esta medida influiria mucho para que aquellos vinieron y para
                            que otros no vayan á las misiones, y debe extraerles la consideracion de
                            que los sacrificios que hacen le son inutiles en su religion. Vengo pues
                            al Supremo Gobierno que oficio al Reverendo Padre Provincial para que no
                            se haga innovacion alguna y que sigan los misioneros lo mismo que estan
                            hasta que el obispo tenga clerigos que puedan ocupar su lugar, y ellos
                            puedan dedicarse á las conversiones vivaces. Quiero ademas que el
                            Gobierno me recomiende con los Reverendos Padres Guardianes de Guadalupe
                            de Zacatecas y San Fernando para que me auxilien con religiosos, y que
                            si algunos me quieren acompanar no se les impida.</cell>
                        <cell>3d. The Supreme Government well knows that I have not in my bishopric
                            other priests than the Franciscans, Zacaltecans, and Dominicans of this
                            province of Mexico, and if the prelates of these orders deprive us of
                            the privileges which their brethren have as missionaries in their
                            orders, this measure would be of great influence, so that the latter
                            might not and others would not come to the missions, and that the
                            considerations that the sacrifices which they make are of no avail in
                            their order ought to be removed from them, I appeal further to the
                            Supreme Government that it may intervene with the reverend fathers
                            provincial in order that no change be made and that the missionaries
                            pursue their present course until the bishop may have priests who can
                            take their places and the former may apply themselves to new
                            conversions. Furthermore, I wish that the Government would aid me with
                            the reverend father superiors of Guadelupe de Zacatecas and San Fernando
                            in order that they may aid me with priests, and that if any wish to
                            accompany me they be not hindered.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>4°. El Supremo Gobierno pidió al Santo Padre por conducto de nuestro
                            enviado á Roma, que se me concediera llevar á mi obispado á cuantos
                            sacerdotes quisieran accompañarme y fueran de mi aprobaeion sin que sus
                            respectivos prelados pudieran estorbarlo. Tal facultad no vino entre las
                            que tengo en mi poder. Quisiera por tanto que se le reclamara al Señor
                            Montaya sobre el particular y en el entretanto que Gobierno se
                            interesara con los prelados, cuando alguno, ya sea del clero secular ó
                            regular le escriba que quiere acompanarme y yo diga al mismo Gobierno
                            que es de mi aprobaeion.</cell>
                        <cell>4th. That the supreme Government ask of the Holy Father, by means of
                            our envoy to Rome, that I be allowed to receive in my bishopric as many
                            priests as wish to accompany me as I may approve without their
                            respective superiors being able to prevent it. Such power does not come
                            within those which I possess. I desire therefore that a demand be made
                            of Señor Montaya on this particular point and that in the meantime the
                            Government interest itself in those priests, when any of them, secular
                            or regular, who writes that he wishes to accompany me and I notify the
                            Government of my approbation.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>5°. Como una de mis principales miras debe ser la convercion de <pb
                                facs="0423" n="415" xml:id="pg_415"/> los gentiles y propagation de
                            la fé, es indespensable pue tenga operation para el logro de mis deses.
                            Los colegios aprobados de la republica estan acabando, excepto el de
                            Guadelupe y de Zacatecas, y apenas podrá cubrir las diez misiones de que
                            se tiene cargo. Creo pues de necesidad que me conceda liciencia para
                            fundar en mi obispado colegio de misioneros para que estos sigan
                            formando nuevas misiones ó pueblos, y suplico al Gobierno que por
                            conducto de nuestro enviado á Roma impetre del Santo Padre pueda yo
                            proceder á la fundacion aunque sea con un solo religioso para que este
                            de habitos y propriones á los que quieran dedicase á la importantisima
                            conversion de gentiles. Ygualmente suplico se me dé para local de este
                            colegio la isla llamada de los Angeles ú otro terreno aproposito.</cell>
                        <cell>5th. Since one of nry principal objects ought to be the conversion of
                            the heathen and the propagation of the faith, it is necessary that 1 may
                            have the necessary assistance to succeed in my desires. The colleges
                            approved by the Republic are falling off, except that of Guadelupe and
                            Zacatecas, and that can scarcely take care of the ten missions which it
                            has in its charge. I think, therefore, that it is necessarjr that
                            license be granted me to found in my bishopric a college of
                            missionaries, in order that they may continue founding new missions or
                            villages, and I pray the Government that by means of our envoy to Rome
                            it intercede with our Holy Father that I may be allowed to proceed with
                            this foundation, although it be with but one priest, so that he may
                            afford an example to those who wish to devote themselves to the most
                            important conversion of the heathen. Likewise I pray that there be given
                            mo for the site of this college Angel Island, or another suitable
                            place.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6°. Las niñas en general han carecido de education y de eseñanza para
                            que sean utiles á la sociedad: quiero pues fundar en el lugar de mi
                            residencia un colegio de educandas, para el que tambien necesito terreno
                            suficiente.</cell>
                        <cell>6th. The girls in general have lacked the education and learning that
                            would make them beneficial to society; I wish, therefore, to found in
                            the neighberhood of my residence a school for girls, and fcr this, also,
                            there is need for sufficient land.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>7°. Por una anomalia que no entiendo se ha estado cobrando ne mi
                            obispado los diezmos por parte del Gobierno civil de Sonora. Debe pues
                            prohibirse esto á aquellas autoridades para que queden los fieles libres
                            para darlos á la Yglesia en lo sucesivo, lo que aunque paucos ayundarán
                            á los grandes proyectos de publicabeneficencia que tengo
                            formados.</cell>
                        <cell>7th. By some disobedience of rules, which I do not understand, tithes
                            have been collected in my bishopric by the government of Sonora. This
                            ought to be forbidden those authorities, in order that the faithful may
                            be free to give them to the church in the future, and which, although
                            small, will be of assistance to the great projects of public welfare
                            which I have formed.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>8°. El Gobierno gravó al Fondo Piadoso de mi Yglesia con un prestamo
                            que hizo el Señor Teren de sesenta mil pesos el ruinoso lucro de dos por
                            ciento mensuales, se comprometió el Gobierno á abanar dos cientos y mas
                            pesos diarios (segun estoy informadó) <pb facs="0424" n="416"
                                xml:id="pg_416"/> para estinguir esta deuda ominosa. Cumplió este
                            promiso por un poco de tiempo y despues lo ha dejado al cargo del Fondo
                            quien por no perder su capital arnenazado por las mismas condiciones del
                            prestamo ha estado haciendo sacrifios asi para amortizar la deuda como
                            para pagar los reditos mensuales. En tales circunstancias se halla dicho
                            Fondo sin arbitrios para dar los sinodos á los misioneros cuyos
                            libramientos tiene pendientes y sin poderme ayudar á mi en los gastos
                            que debo hacer para marchar á mi diocesis, los que son muchos como no se
                            oculta á la penetracion de V.E. Es pues justicia que pido el que se
                            arbitre algunos medios por el Gobierno para cubrir cuanto antes la deuda
                            del Señor Teran para que quede libre el Fondo.</cell>
                        <cell>8th. The Government has burdened the Pious Fund of my church with a
                            loan which Señor Teran made of $60,000 with the ruinous interest of 2
                            per cent per month. The Government promised to pay daily installments of
                            200 odd dollars (as I am informed) in order to extinguish this
                            threatening debt. It fulfilled this promise for a short time and
                            afterwards left it to the charge of the fund, which, in order that it
                            may not lose its capital by the very terms of the loan, has been making
                            sacrifices not only that it may extinguish the debt, but also pay the
                            monthly interests. Said fundisinthesecircumstances without means of
                            paying the salaries of the missionaries whose drafts it has outstanding,
                            and without being able to help me in the expenses which I ought to incur
                            to my diocese, which are great, as is not unknown to your excellency. In
                            justice, therefore, I ask that some means betaken by the Government to
                            discharge, as soon as possible, the debt of Señor Teran, in order that
                            the fund may remain unincumbered.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>En mi oficio se me pasó decir que deseo poner mis edificios, ó mas
                            bien fundar una poblacion en un xancho que se halla f rente de San Diego
                            asi por la comodidad que presenta de agua, de leña; como por no estar
                            litoral y espuesto á la invasion de algun pirata. Es ademas de muy buen
                            temperamento. Si el Gobierno quisiera poner alli alguna fuérza militar
                            seria de suma importancia para la comunicacion con Senora, pues
                            contendria a los Yndios del Rio Colorado, y tambien seria muy al caso
                            para intentar la reduccion de estos probrecitos y on felicidad
                            espiritual y temporal. Estoy persuadido que con esta medida se
                            facilitaria la comunicacion con el interior de nuestra republica, y el
                            Gobierno tendria mas frecuentes noticias de aquel departamerito.</cell>
                        <cell>In my official letter I forgot to say that I wish to erect my
                            buildings, or rather to establish my settlement, on a ranch which is
                            situated opposite to San Diego, not only on account of the supply of
                            water and wood which it affords, but also because it is not near the
                            coast and exposed to the invasion of any pirate. Besides, it has a very
                            good climate. If the Government should desire to place a military force
                            there, it would be of the greatest importance in communicating
                            withSonora, becauseit would be a check to the Indians of the Colorado
                            River, and also it would be material in the reduction of those
                            unfortunates and to their spiritual and temporal welfare. I am persuaded
                            that by this means the communication with the interior of our Republic
                            would be facilitated and that Government would have more frequent
                            advices from that region.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Nov. 17 de 1840. El Exmo. Presidente se ha servido proveer de conf
                            ormidad con todo lo pedido por el Reverendo obispado de Californias en
                            esta nota hasta donde alcanzan las atribuciones de S. E. <pb facs="0425"
                                n="417" xml:id="pg_417"/> y da lugar el decreto del congreso de 7 de
                            Nov. de 1835, que mando reponer las misiones á su antiguo stado; á cuyo
                            fin se estenderá orden general al Señor Gobernador de Californias, para
                            que por medio de las autoridades subalternas se restituya sin dilation
                            ni embarazos á los Padres Misioneros las posesiones y bienes que usaban
                            bajo su administracion para la conversion de los infieles, y esa y las
                            demas ordenes que ban de espedirse en obsequio de la petition del
                            Reverendo Obispo se pondran en mano de S. Y. para su meior exito, y se
                            le dará otra orden, á fin de que el Señor Gobernador le auxilie en
                            cuanto importe á la fundaeion del obispado. Y por lo toea á los terrenos
                            de que no esté ó hayan estado en posesion de las misiones librese oficio
                            á la Junta Directiva del (Ramo?) á fin de que acuerde con S. Y. hasta
                            dondo pueda su notoria piedad lo que mas facilite sus peticiones; y en
                            lo que no alcanzan los arbitrios del (Ramo?) le manifiesta al Gobierno
                            para que se inicie al Poder Legislativo á se provea como haya lugar en
                            derecho: y contestese con este decreto al Reverendo Obispo.</cell>
                        <cell>Nov. 17/1840. His Excellency the President has seen fit to grant
                            everything which has been asked by the reverend bishop of the
                            Californias in his note as far as his excellency’s powers extend, and he
                            is permitted by the decree of Congress of the 7th of November, 1835,
                            which ordered that the missions be restored to their old standing, to
                            which end a general order will be transmitted to the governor of the
                            Californias in order that by means of the subordinate authorities the
                            possessions and properties which they were accustomed to use under their
                            administration for the conversion of the heathen be restored to the
                            missionary fathers without delay or hindrance, and this and the other
                            orders which are to be given in accordance with the petition of the
                            reverend bishop shall be placed in your excellency’s hands in order that
                            it may be better carried dut, and another order will be given you to the
                            end that the governor may aid you as much as may be necessary in the
                            foundation of the bishopric, and that he may give an order to the
                            directive board of the department with respect to the lands of which the
                            missions are not or may not have been in possession, to the end that it
                            may agree with your highness in so far as his well-known piety may be
                            able to further your desires, and concerning that to which the powers of
                            the department do not extend he may make it known to the Government in
                            order that the legislative authority may be properly invoked and answer
                            the reverend bishop with this decree.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Es copia. Mexico, Nov. 21 de 1840.</cell>
                        <cell>A copy. Mexico, November 21, 1840.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>(Firmado) <hi rend="smallcaps">Y. Yturbide.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>(Signed) <hi rend="smallcaps">Y. Yturbide.</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Oct. 8 de 1852</hi>.
                            Conforme.</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Oct. 8, 1852</hi>.
                            Compared.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>[<hi rend="smallcaps">sello.</hi>] <hi rend="smallcaps">José M.
                                Duran.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>] <hi rend="smallcaps">José María
                                Duran</hi>.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>(A stamp of one real, 1852–1853.)</cell>
                        <cell>(Sella cuarto un real 1852, 1853.)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Office of the U. S. Surveyor-General for
                                California.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1, surveyor-general of the United States for the State of California,
                                <pb facs="0426" n="418" xml:id="pg_418"/> and as such, having in my
                            office and in my charge and custody a portion of the archives of the
                            former Spanish and Mexican Territory or Department of Upper California,
                            as also the papers of the late board of commissioners to ascertain and
                            settle the private land claims in California, by virtue of the powers
                            vested in me by law, do hereby certify that the seven preceding and
                            hereunto annexed leaves, numbered from one to seven, inclusive, and
                            written on one side only, exhibit a true, full and correct copy of the
                            original “Exhibit No. 1, P. L., annexed to deposition of José Miguel
                            Gomez, Dec. 29, 1854. Joseph S. Alemany. Lands of the Catholic Church
                            (C.) filed in office Dec. 29, 1854. Geo. Fisher, Recorder in Rec. of
                            Evid., Vol. 18, p. 571 to 574,” and also “Exhibit No. 2, P. L., annexed
                            to deposition of José Miguel Gomez, Dec. 29, 1854. Joseph S. Alemany.
                            Lands of the Catholic Church. Filed in office Dec. 29, 1854. Geo.
                            Fisher, Recorder in Record of Evidence, Vol. 18, pp. 775 and 779,” and
                            now on file in this office and in my custody; that I have carefully
                            compared the same with said originals, and that the same are a correct
                            transcript therefrom and of the whole of such originals.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>In testimony whereof I have hereunto signed my name officially and
                            caused my seal of office to be affixed at the city of San Francisco,
                            this twenty-fifth day of August, 1902.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">W. S. Graham</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">U. S. Surveyor-General for California.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Seal surveyor-general’s office, California.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>(Endorsed on back): Exhibit No. 5 to the deposition of John T. Doyle.
                            Jas. T. O’Keefe, notary public. For identification: John T.
                            Doyle.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <pb facs="0427" n="419" xml:id="pg_419"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>El infrascrito oficial major del Ministerio de Eielationes Certifica:
                            ser autentica la firma que antecede (de) del Sr. D. José Ma. Duran
                            official mayor del Ministerio de Justia.</cell>
                        <cell>The undersigned, chief clerk of the department of foreign relations,
                            certifies that the foregoing seal of Don José Maria Duran, chief clerk
                            of the department of justice, is authentic.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Mexico, Octubre 8 de 1852.<lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Miguel Arroyo.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Mexico, October 8, 1852.<lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Miguel Arroyo.</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ministerio de la interior.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of the interior.</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ylmo. Sor</hi>: Dada cuenta al E. S. Presid<hi
                                rend="superscript">te</hi> con el oficio de V. S. Y. cle 7 del
                            corriente é impuesto de todo cuanto en él expone con el objeto de dar
                            lleno á sus graves onligaciones como obispo de Californias, se ha
                            servido proveer de conformidad con todo lo pedido en el citado oficio y
                            con lo que tambien solicitó en carta separada de igual fecha hta. donde
                            el alcanzan las atribuciones de S. E. y dá lugar el decreeo del congreso
                            grāl de 7 de Novb. de 835 que dispuso se mantubieran las misiones en el
                            estado que tenian antes de la Ley de 17 de Agosto de 1833 á cuyo fin se
                            libra orden por este Minist<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. al E. S. Gobr.
                            de Californias para que por medio de las autoridades subalternas se
                            restituya sin dilaciones ni embarazos á los Padres Misioneros las
                            posesiones y bienes Hue estaban bajo su administracion para la
                            conversion de los infieles.<lb/>Y lo digo á V. S. Y. en contestation.<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Dios y Lihertad, Mexico</hi>.<lb/>Novb. 17 de
                                1840.lb/&gt;<hi rend="smallcaps">Marin</hi>. (Rúbrica.)<lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Y. S. Obispo de Californias.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Esteemed Sir</hi>: Information having been given to
                            His Excellency the President by the official letter of your highness of
                            the 7th instant, and taking into account all that is expressed in it
                            with a view to accomplishing your weighty obligations as bishop of the
                            Calif ornias, he has been pleased to concur with all that is asked in
                            the said letter, as well as with that which was asked in a separate
                            letter of the same date, as far as his power extends, and as he is
                            authorized by the decree of the General Congress of the 7th of November,
                            1835, which ordered that the missions be continued in the state which
                            they had before the law of the 17th of August, 1833, to which end an
                            order has been made by this department to his excellency the governor of
                            the Californias, so that by means of the inferior authorities he may
                            restore without any delays or hindrances to the missionary fathers the
                            possessions and properties which were under their administration for the
                            conversion of the heathen. And I say this to your excellency by way of
                            answer.<lb/>God and liberty, Mexico.<lb/>November 17,
                            1840.<lb/>(Rubric.) <hi rend="smallcaps">Marin.</hi>
                            <lb/>His Excellency the <hi rend="smallcaps">Bishop of the
                                Californias.</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>A pedimento del Señor Obispo de Calif ornias, certifico por la
                            presente quo la firma agreda á este documento es la del Ministro del
                            Interior, de aquella época del <pb facs="0428" n="420" xml:id="pg_420"/>
                            Señor Marin segun me consta por otros documentos oficiales, que he visto
                            de dieho Señor.</cell>
                        <cell>At the request of the bishop of the Californias I certify by these
                            presents that the seal attached to this document is that of the minister
                            of the interior of that time, Senor Marin, as appears to me by other
                            official documents, which I have seen of said officer.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>San Francisco, Diciembre 20, 1851.<lb/>[Rúbrica] W. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Schleiden</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Vice-Consul de la Mepublica Mejicana en San
                                Francisco.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>San Francisco, December 20, 1851.<lb/>[signed]<lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">W. Schleiden</hi> (Rubric),<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Vice-Consul of the Mexican Republic in San
                                Francisco.</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>(Sello. Viceconsulado de la Republica Mejicana en San
                            Francisco.)</cell>
                        <cell>[Seal vice-consulate of the Mexican Republic in San Francisco.]</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
