<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 129.Mr. Avery to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1875v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d133</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">133</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1874-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1874-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="133"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d133">
                <head>No. 129.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Avery</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-11-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 12, 1874</date>. (Received January 28,
                        1875.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 6.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herewith (inclosure
                    1) a translation of a communication from Prince Kung, under date of November 6,
                    giving the terms of the agreement lately effected between China and Japan, which
                    is referred to in my No. 3 and Mr. Williams’s No. 70, both sent by this mail,
                    together with a copy of my reply to Prince Kung, (inclosure 2.) There is a
                    feeling of relief here that all danger of host lilies growing out of the Formosa
                    trouble is now happily ended. I trust that the course of this legation in
                    contributing to this result will meet your approval.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>BENJ. P. AVERY.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 6.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Prince <persName type="from">Kung</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Avery</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Tungchi</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date
                                calendar="chinese-era chinese-lunisolar                         gregorian"
                                when="1874-11-06">13<hi rend="italic">th year</hi>, 9<hi
                                    rend="italic">th moon</hi>, 28<hi rend="italic">th day</hi>,
                                (November 6, 1874.)</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Prince Kung, chief secretary of state for foreign affairs, herewith makes a
                        communication.</p>
                    <p>It being well known that the Japanese government had taken a military force
                        to that part of Formosa occupied by the aborigines, and as the first article
                        of the American treaty of 1857 contains a stipulation “that, if another
                        nation should act unjustly or oppressively, the United States, on being
                        informed of the case, will exert their good office; to bring about an
                        amicable arrangement of the question, thus showing their friendly feelings,”
                        it was in accordance with its spirit that the foreign office last August
                        transmitted to Mr. Williams a copy of the correspondence which had then
                        passed between this government and the Japanese ministers. An arrangement
                        having now been effected with the Japanese, involving the withdrawal of
                        their troops and settlement of the affair, it has been decided to regard all
                        the documents which have passed <pb facs="0312" n="222" xml:id="pg_222"/>
                        between us in relation to this affair as <hi rend="italic">non avenu</hi>,
                        recalling and canceling them all, so that hereafter they may not be quoted
                        as valid or as a precedent.</p>
                    <p>Seeing that the territory occupied by the aborigines in Formosa, the subdued
                        as well as the savage, all equally forms part of His Majesty’s dominions, it
                        is, of course, incumbent oh this government to take measures to restrain
                        those people, and prevent them from ever again injuring or killing mariners
                        who may be cast among them. By this means friendly relations will be
                        confirmed between us.</p>
                    <p>I have now the honor to inclose a copy of the articles of agreement and the
                        stipulations about the payments, for your excellency’s information, and
                        shall be gratified to receive your early reply.</p>
                    <p>To His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Benjamin P. Avery</hi>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">United States Minister.</hi>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in 1 in No. 6.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The following preamble and articles of agreement having been carefully
                        discussed and assented to, copies of them have been exchanged as evidence
                        [of the terms of settlement.]</p>
                    <p>As the people of every country are bound to protect others within its
                        borders, and see that they suffer no injury, it is consequently obligatory
                        on each country to take such measures as will secure this protection; and if
                        wrongs have been suffered, the country which has the grievance should look
                        to the other for redress. Now, therefore, seeing that the aborigines of
                        Formosa had destroyed and barbarously injured certain people under the
                        protection of Japan, it was the purpose of that government to call them to
                        account for these acts, and to this end they dispatched troops to that
                        region to punish them and bring them to order. The whole matter having now
                        been fully discussed with the Chinese government, the three following
                        stipulations, relating to the withdrawal of the troops and the manner of
                        preventing like outrages in future, have been agreed upon by the two
                        parties.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>I.</label>
                        <item>As Japan had in view the protection of her subjects in all that she
                            has now done, [in Formosa,] China does not regard those acts as
                            wrong.</item>
                        <label>II.</label>
                        <item>China binds herself to pay an indemnity to the families of the
                            sufferers; and, as she desires to retain the improvements made there in
                            opening roads, erecting houses, and in other things done there, she
                            hereby agrees beforehand that she will pay a sum to recoup this outlay,
                            the amount to be hereafter determined upon.</item>
                        <label>III.</label>
                        <item>All the documents which have passed between the two parties in
                            relation to this-affair are hereby recalled and canceled, so that they
                            may not hereafter be quoted as precedent. China will take every proper
                            measure to restrain the aborigines of that region, so that hereafter no
                            injuiries shall be suffered by unhappy mariners who may be cast ashore
                            among them.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Terms in relation to indemnity for the Formosan
                            outrages.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>His excellency T. F. Wade, her Britannic Majesty’s minister, having now
                        clearly stated all the points at issue between our two countries, the
                        following stipulations for the payments have been signed and copies
                        exchanged this day:</p>
                    <p>China will first pay 100,000 taels to Japan, as indemnity to the families of
                        the men who were killed in Formosa. She will farther pay 400,000 taels to
                        Japan when the troops now in Formosa have been withdrawn, and take
                        possession of the roads opened, houses erected, and other things done there.
                        The money for the last will be all paid on the 20th of December next, on
                        which day the troops will all leave, each party fulfilling his own part
                        without fail. If Japan does not withdraw all her troops on that day, the
                        money will not all be paid up. A copy of this agreement has been signed by
                        each party, in testimony of its adoption.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 6.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Avery</persName> to Prince
                                <persName type="to">Kung</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-11-10">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 10, 1874</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge your
                        communication of the 6th instant, informing me that in August last you had
                        forwarded to Mr. Williams a copy of the correspondence which had then passed
                        between the imperial government and the Japanese <pb facs="0313" n="223"
                            xml:id="pg_223"/> relative to the Formosan affair, trusting to the good
                        offices of the United States for help in the matter, in accordance with the
                        friendly assurance in the American treaty of 1857; and also informing me
                        that an amicable arrangement has now been made with Japan whereby that
                        nation formally recognizes the sovereignty of China over the whole of
                        Formosa and agrees to withdraw her troops therefrom, China admitting on her
                        part that Japan was justified in seeking to punish the savages, and agreeing
                        to make compensation for the wrongs inflicted by the latter, and for the
                        roads, buildings, and other works made by Japan on the island. You had a
                        right to expect the friendly offices of the United States, and it gives me
                        pleasure to state that they have been exerted, both here and in Japan, by
                        the representatives of my Government, in the way of preventing our citizens
                        from engaging in warlike operations against a nation with which we are at
                        peace; in advising against any invasion of the sovereignty of China; and
                        inlending support to proposals for a peaceful settlement on a basis alike
                        honorable and just.</p>
                    <p>It is with sincere satisfaction that I have read the terms of settlement with
                        Japan, which are inclosed in your highness’s communication, and which prove
                        the readiness of the imperial government to concede all that was just when
                        assured that the territorial rights of China would be respected. The
                        admission made in the preamble that “it is incumbent on this government to
                        take measures to restrain the Formosan savages and prevent them from ever
                        again killing or injuring mariners cast among them,” is only a righteous
                        recognition of the duties of sovereignty and humanity, and is no more than
                        China can honorably admit or than other great nations admit and practice. It
                        is a natural sequence of this that a country suffering wrongs from any
                        failure on the part of another to restrain its savage subjects “should look
                        to the other for redress, China affords this redress in the case of Japan by
                        allowing a money compensation.. The whole settlement, therefore, comports
                        with the obligations and dignity of the imperial government. Doubtless, the
                        efforts that will hereafter be made to subdue the Formosan savages will lead
                        to such a development of the resources of the island and such an increase of
                        commerce as will redound largely to the profit of the Chinese people and
                        government.</p>
                    <p>In conclusion, allow me to congratulate your highness that the danger of war
                        on this subject has been so happily averted, and that the imperial
                        government is free to study how it may advance the peaceful progress of
                        China.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your imperial highness’s obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>BENJ. P. AVERY.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Imperial Highness Prince <hi rend="smallcaps">Kung</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
