<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 135.Mr. Avery to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1875v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d139</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">139</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1874-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1874-12-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-12-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="139"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d139">
                <head>No. 135.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Avery</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-12-17">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 17, 1874</date>. (Received February 24,
                        1875.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 13.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: As illustrating the happy effects of a judicious
                    but firm insistance upon strict compliance with treaty obligations on the part
                    of local Chinese officials, I have the honor to inclose copy of a letter from
                    our consul at Tien-tsin, covering a voluntary testimonial from the Rev. John
                    Maclntyre, a British missionary, as to the good results of the settlement of the
                    Chimi affair by Mr. Sheppard. Your approval of the latter’s course has already
                    been signified to him.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>BENJ. P. AVERY.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 13.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Sheppard</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Avery</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Tien-tsin</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-12-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 14, 1874</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit herewith copy of
                        a letter from the Rev. John Maclntyre, testifying to the good effects
                        produced upon the Chinese by reason of the official action which was taken
                        at Che-foo last summer, and resulted in the trial and punishment of the
                        ringleaders of the riotous attack upon an American missionary at Chimi.</p>
                    <p>I should not feel warranted in troubling you with this letter, but for the
                        fact that it comes gratuitously from an intelligent, disinterested witness,
                        and represents fairly what I believe to be the result of the joint trial of
                        the Chimi rioters by the Taotai and myself at Che-foo, and of the
                        proclamation which was issued and made public respecting the same.</p>
                    <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ELI T. SHEPPARD, <hi rend="italic">Consul.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Benj. P. Avery</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Minister.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0327" n="237" xml:id="pg_237"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure in No. 13.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">MacIntyre</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Cornabé</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Che-foo</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-10-15">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 15, 1874</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. A Cornabé</hi>, Esq.:</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Sir</hi>: I shall take it kind if you will
                        express my thanks in the proper quarter, where it is due, for the protection
                        and immunity from insult, which, as a British subject, I have this summer
                        enjoyed, through the successful management of the Chimi affair, One has to
                        go but a short way into the interior to find even district magistrates
                        affecting ignorance of most important provisions of the treaty; and under
                        such circumstances it is but natural that the common people should look upon
                        the foreigner as an unauthorized intruder, and refuse to exercise toward us
                        that courtesy which so eminently characterizes the Chinese nation. I have
                        been long convinced that only one step remained to be taken to put all
                        classes upon their good behavior, and that is, an official notification by
                        every prefect and district magistrate Such as that so happily issued at
                        Che-foo last July.</p>
                    <p>The Chinese are a people willing to be governed, and, with good governors,
                        few nations would even now surpass them in order and behavior. Let the
                        Chinese authorities, therefore, but declare the provisions of the treaty,
                        giving the people honestly to understand that they themselves shall see the
                        same enforced, and there will be an end to this shuffling policy on the part
                        of individual magistrates, and to the uncertainty on the part of the people.
                        As to the status of the foreigner, it has hitherto been too often impossible
                        for a district magistrate to act fairly towards him, lest it should
                        prejudice him with his superiors, and present him in an unpatriotic aspect
                        to the common people. For the same reason influential civilians must either
                        forego intercourse with educated foreigners or enjoy it under circumstances
                        which counterbalance its advantages I have repeatedly heard such sentiments
                        from the Chinese themselves since the Taotai’s proclamation was issued. The
                        proclamation has been well received over the entire district, and more than
                        one influential person has declared that we ought from the first to have
                        been furnished with such a document, or before ever we came into the inter
                        or. I think it due to say that the Chinese authorities have acted most
                        honorably in the matter. Not only has the proclamation received every
                        publicity, but the people clearly understand that it must be respected.</p>
                    <p>I n need not say how much this has contributed to my personal comfort,
                        sojourning, as I do, many days’ journey from the seaport. But I rejoice now
                        in the higher consideration that the Chinese authorities have taken such a
                        worthy step in the direction of good government.</p>
                    <p>I am yours, very sincerely,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JOHN MACINTYRE,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mission of United Presbyterian Church, Scotland.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
