<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1875-02-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1875-02-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="148" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d148">
                    <head>No. 144.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Avery</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Pelting</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-02-19"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 19, 1875</date>.
                            (Received May 1.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 30.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In my No. 12, of December 10, attention was
                        called to the fact that Li Hung Chang, governor-general of the province of
                        Chihli, had sent abroad an agent to procure the machinery for working
                        coal-mines. It is now in my power to give more detailed information on the
                        subject. Regret is sometimes expressed that the Chinese authorities are much
                        more inclined to expend money on the warlike inventions of foreigners than
                        on the arts and appliances of peace, which tend to build up instead of
                        destroying; and it is doubtless true that an equal readiness to introduce
                        our improved machinery in their manufactures, mining, and <pb facs="0356" n="266" xml:id="pg_266"/> transportation would be more beneficial to the
                        people and the government. But it is worth observing that such experience of
                        the value of foreign arts and appliances as they gain in establishing
                        arsenals, powder-works, and founderies, and in adopting our war-steamers,
                        cannon, and small-arms, is also teaching them the superiority of the same
                        arts and appliances in the ordinary industry and traffic of the empire. Thus
                        Li Hung Chang was doubtless led by his arsenal-works to appreciate the
                        necessity of obtaining large supplies of coal by more economical methods
                        than manual labor and mule or camel transportation. Indeed, as early as
                        1868, Tsang-kwoh-fan, who was at that time the highest in rank of the
                        provincial governors-general, had nearly induced the central government to
                        allow him to make the experiment of working the coal-mines near Nanking, or
                        Chin-kiang, with foreign machinery. Dr. Williams wrote of this to the
                        Department, saying: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>If once this experiment is tried, I think its success in developing a
                                vast industry will prove a strong inducement to try other mines, as,
                                for instance, those near Peking and north of Canton, and this source
                                of wealth being once opened prosperously, a rail or tram road, to
                                carry the coal to the boats or a market, would follow under more
                                promising inducements than can now be expected. It is worth
                                mentioning in this connection that the great stimulus to Stephenson
                                in opening his railroad was to get coal to market.</p>
                        </quote></p>
                    <p>These remarks have a special relevancy to the experiment now actually
                        undertaken by Li Hung Chang, concerning which Mr. E. T. Sheppard, our consul
                        at Tien-tsin, has procured for me the following facts, given in nearly his
                        own language. The coal-fields at Tzin Chow, which Li Hung Chang proposes to
                        operate with foreign machinery, are situated in the v eastern slope of the
                        range of hills which runs northeast and southwest, along and across the
                        western border of this province, (Chili,) at a point near its southwestern
                        extremity, and near the border of Shantung and Honan. They may be marked on
                        the map as lying in latitude 36° 15′ north, and longitude 114° 45′ east.
                        These mines are very rich in coal of a soft bituminous variety, though
                        anthracite is also present, and have been worked since and during the Ming
                        dynasty with greater or less success. Iron-ore and limestone exist in great
                        abundance in the adjacent hills. The distance from Tien-tsin, by ordinary
                        course of travel, is about 250 miles, and from Peking a little farther.
                        These mines were selected for working by Li Hung Chang, as he says,
                        according to Mr. Sheppard, because of their <hi rend="italic">remoteness</hi> from Peking, which place now gets its coal-supplies
                        from mines only two days’ journey distant by camel or mule. The
                        governor-general observes that, should he attempt to put foreign machinery
                        in the mines at Men-ton-kow or Chien Tang, he would be met by serious
                        opposition from the capital. Remote from Peking, he is nearly
                        independent.</p>
                    <p>In October last, Li Hung Chang engaged Mr. James Henderson, of Tien-tsin, to
                        go to Great Britain and secure experts and machinery for opening the mines
                        selected, a steam-engine being included in the order. Mr. Henderson left
                        Tien-tsin for England about the 10th of October, and expects to return by
                        July next. For the purpose of conveying the coal rapidly and cheaply from
                        Tzii Chow to Tien-tsin, the governor-general proposes to construct a
                        tram-way, either for horse or steam power, from Tzii Chow to the nearest
                        accessible point of connection with the river Chang Ho, which flows into the
                        Grand Canal, and which passes Tzii Chow about thirty miles to the eastward,
                        thus making a continuous line of communication between the mines and
                        Tien-tsin, at which latter place, or near it, are the Chinese arsenal and
                        steamships, to say nothing of numerous foreign steamers. Mr. Sheppard thinks
                        this mode of transportation, although a great improvement on the present,
                        will prove <pb facs="0357" n="267" xml:id="pg_267"/> inadequate, and that,
                        to insure economical and profitable working, Li Hung Chang will find himself
                        obliged to make his tram-road a railroad, and extend it to Tien-tsin. He
                        gives me the following facts in illustration of this idea: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>Coal at the mines named can now he bought in any reasonable quantity
                                at 90 cents to $1.25 per ton. So great is the cost of
                                transportation, and so limited are the means, that the coal doubles
                                for each ten miles it is carried, so that by the time it reaches
                                Tientsin it cannot be sold for less than about $14 per ton. Indeed,
                                it is found that Australian and Cardiff coals, notwithstanding the
                                great cost of shipping them hither, compete favorably with the
                                native coal, which is found in such great abundance in this
                                province. With railroad communication between here and the mines,
                                native coal would be laid down in such quantities, and at such a low
                                figure, as to drive all foreign coals at once and forever from the
                                market. This fact will soon suggest itself to the Chinese, for it is
                                capable of mathematical demonstration. I have said that the viceroy
                                (governor-general) is mistaken in supposing that he can transport
                                coal from the mines to Tien-tsin with a tram-way and in boats via
                                the Grand Canal in paying quantities. My reason for thinking so is
                                this: The Chang Ho, which connects with the Grand Canal, is a
                                shallow stream at best, and on an average, I am informed, it is not
                                navigable, even for small passenger-boats, more than about six
                                months of each year. During that time, therefore, no coal can be
                                transported. The result will be just what is true at present, viz,
                                that coal will be abundant and dirt-cheap at the mines, but the
                                facilities for carrying it to market will be so inadequate as to
                                render the working of the mines a practical failure. The viceroy
                                will, however, get just taste-enough of the mineral wealth to make
                                him greedy for more. He will see the rich treasures of coal and iron
                                here in his own province, and he has sagacity enough to see also how
                                those treasures can be made available. Railroads are the logic of
                                the whole business.</p>
                        </quote></p>
                    <p>Whatever may be the issue of the mining experiment, Li Hung Chang is not a
                        man likely to abandon it, and as he gains rather than loses influence with
                        the central government, he may rely with the more confidence on being left
                        free to carry out his project by whatever means may be necessary to insure
                        its success. He has lately been advanced to the head position in the grand
                        secretariat, which is a special mark of imperial favor, there being only
                        four members of this body, and the usage being for the Manchus and Chinese
                        composing it to alternate in a way that gave the former precedence.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>BENJ. P. AVERY.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>