<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1875-03-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1875-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="152" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d152">
                    <head>No. 148.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Avery</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-03-19"><hi rend="italic">March</hi>, 19, 1875</date>.
                            (Received May 7.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 40.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to send herewith copies of
                        dispatches and inclosures sent to this legation by M. M. De Lano, esq., our
                        consul at Foo-chow, giving a complete history, with documentary evidence, of
                        the Foo-chow-Amoy telegraph project. His first dispatch, No. 42, with eight
                        inclosures, bearing date January 25, 1875, is a curious exhibition of
                        duplicity and tergiversation on the part of the local officials. In spite of
                        all their double-dealing and bad faith, however, one gratifying fact is
                        evident: they really want the telegraph, but not in foreign hands. Probably
                        the line would have been allowed to go on to completion by the Danish
                        company, but for a letter from the Tsung li Yamen, (marked H in the
                        inclosure,) directing the provincial authorities to buy it for the
                        government. This letter was sent to Foo-chow late last tall, and the local
                        officials have ever since been playing a game of obstruction, instead of at
                        once making a frank tender of purchase possibly with a view to getting a
                        cheaper bargain.</p>
                    <p>The Yamen would seem to have been prompted to effect a purchase of the line
                        by a desire to evade the fulfillment of an old promise to the Russian
                        minister, that when China permitted another country to put up a telegraph
                        she would also allow Russia to do so. Hearing of the Foo-chow-Amoy project,
                        and believing a perfect concession had been obtained for it, which was not
                        the fact, Mr. de Bützow, the present Russian minister; reminded the Yamen of
                        their promise, and hence, doubtless, the sudden withdrawal of favor from the
                        Danish line. Owing to the peculiar territorial relations of the two
                        countries, China regards with apprehension any attempt on the part of Russia
                        to facilitate communication along her borders, and the Yamen has doubtless
                        been encouraged by certain foreign interests here to frown upon the Russian
                        project for a telegraph from Peking to Kiachta as something dangerous.</p>
                    <p>However this may be, the Foo-chow-Amoy line is to be bought for the
                        government. Since the decision to this effect was formally communicated to
                        the Danish minister, who has now gone to Shanghai to arrange for the sale,
                        Mr. De Lano writes me of another attack upon the line, by the local
                        officials, who caused twenty miles of it to be destroyed. This rash
                        proceeding will have no other effect than to increase the indemnity to be
                        paid the Danish company, and necessitate an extra outlay for the completion
                        of the line should the government desire to maintain and use it, as
                        supposed. In reference to this subject, I wrote to Mr. De Lano, under date
                        of March 6, as follows:</p>
                    <pb facs="0369" n="279" xml:id="pg_279"/>
                    <p>“It is evident that continued unity of action in favor of foreign telegraph
                        enterprise cannot be expected from the diplomatic and consular bodies, and,
                        lacking that, the Peking government will do nothing to promote such
                        enterprise on a large scale. Rid of foreign rivalries and importunities,
                        however, and managing telegraphs for itself, this government may sooner
                        learn their value and extend their use. To such a result, if it comes about,
                        I think we may justly claim that American influence has largely contributed
                        by the disinterested support it has given to initial telegraph effort, no
                        matter by what nationality made, in the interest, solely, of commerce,
                        civilization, and progress. I congratulate you that your own name will be
                        honorably connected with so good a cause.”</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>BENJ. P. AVERY.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 40]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">De Lano</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Avery</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Consulate</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Foo-chow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-01-25"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 25,
                                1875</date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 42.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your dispatch of December 30 in which you ask me, in case it
                            is consistent with my inclinations and with my other duties, to take
                            temporary charge of the Danish vice-consulate at this port.</p>
                        <p>I have to say, in reply, that it does not seem to be consistent for me to
                            do so, and for the following reasons: First, Mr. Young, when he left
                            here, left the consulate in charge of Mr. Harton, one of his employés,
                            who would not of course give over the charge, except on the order of Mr.
                            Young or of the Danish legation at Peking. Second, I could not,
                            consistently with my position, accept the post of ‘acting vice-consul.’
                            If the Danish government have a consulate here, the incumbent should be
                            either consul or acting consul, and I would be willing, in case I was
                            named with the knowledge and assent of Mr. Young, to accept charge as
                            acting consul, at the request of the Danish minister and with your
                            consent, pending the approval of the State Department, in which case the
                            Tsung li Yamen would have to notify the provincial authorities here of
                            my appointment.</p>
                        <p>There is no doubt that Danish interests are suffering greatly through
                            their having no consul here, and I know by actual experience that the
                            position at this moment would be an onerous one, for I have conducted
                            most of the correspondence with the authorities for the incumbent since
                            early in September, because Mr. Young, as a merchant, has not had the
                            facilities for doing it. You will understand very readily that when the
                            officials refuse to enter into official correspondence with a
                            merchant-consul, he can have but little influence for the good of the
                            nationals for whom he affects to act. I have done all I could do in the
                            interest of the Danes, and shall continue to do so, though I am forced
                            to use great care lest I damage my influence with the authorities for
                            the good of my own countrymen. My action in connection with the
                            telegraph projects has, as you will understand, been in the general
                            interest of commerce, civilization, and progress; and, having first
                            brought the subject conspicuously to the notice of the Chinese
                            officials, and induced them to take the initiative in the matter, it has
                            seemed to me to be proper that I should continue my efforts in
                            furtherance of the project. This has involved me in controversies with
                            the officials which have not always been pleasant, though in the main I
                            have preserved friendly relations with all those who have behaved
                            honorably in the matter.</p>
                        <p>You ask me to keep you advised as to the exact status of telegraphic
                            affairs here, which I shall be glad to do. I have hitherto written
                            freely to Mr. Seward on the subject, giving him particulars as to my
                            action and the general tendency of things as far as time and opportunity
                            have permitted; and Mr. Seward has, I presume, communicated all
                            important points to you.</p>
                        <p>I shall try now to give you a <hi rend="italic">résumé</hi> of what has
                            been done here, and in as concise a manner as possible. I may premise by
                            saying that since I arrived first in Foochow I have embraced every
                            favorable opportunity to impress upon the officials with whom I have
                            been brought in contact the importance of the telegraph, and often
                            discussed with them the feasibility of erecting a line between the
                            foreign settlement in the city and Pagoda anchorage. A means of quick
                            communication between the two points has been often a matter of great
                            moment to foreign interests, and the Chinese themselves <pb facs="0370" n="280" xml:id="pg_280"/> not unfrequently feel the need of it.
                            Being on the most friendly terms with the late chief of the Chinese
                            committee of foreign trade, the Taotai Luh, and finding him favorably
                            disposed toward the introduction of western sciences and improvements, I
                            brought this subject of a telegraph to the anchorage conspicuously to
                            his notice in March last. He received it with favor, but said, “While I
                            am personally in favor of your project, I am only one man. I fear that
                            my co-officials will not favor it; and, further, that the people will
                            not allow the poles to be erected on their lands.”</p>
                        <p>Soon after this the Great Northern Telegraph Company, through their
                            agent, Mr. Henningsen, applied to me to procure for them official
                            sanction to the construction of this same line. Thinking it to be
                            important to the success of the scheme that there should be co-operation
                            on the part of the consuls, I requested the British consul, as the
                            senior consul at the port, to move in the matter, and he accordingly
                            united with the French consul and myself in a joint dispatch to the
                            trade committee, basing our request, however, upon a memorial addressed
                            to us by the Foo-chow Chamber of Commerce.</p>
                        <p>Much to our surprise, the permission was readily given; the line soon
                            became an established fact; and I do not know that the right of the
                            local officials to give this permission has even been questioned.</p>
                        <p>The Chinese officers often avail themselves of the privilege of using the
                            line at pleasure, and readily admit its great utility.</p>
                        <p>I now come to the projected Foo-chow-Amoy line. On the 25th of July I
                            addressed a letter to Luh, embracing propositions of the Great Northern
                            Company to erect it, (inclosure 1.)</p>
                        <p>On the 28th July I received his reply, (inclosure 2.) On the 1st of
                            August I received-a second communication, (inclosure 3,) in which
                            permission to erect the line was un, derstood to be given, and, although
                            it does not appear as clearly as could be desired the subsequent acts
                            and admissions of the Chinese officials in connection with the matter
                            clearly prove that they were at the moment acting in good faith, and
                            desired to have the scheme consummated. As proof of this, I inclose copy
                            of instructions (in Chinese) issued by the trade committee to the Taotai
                            at Amoy, (inclosure 4.) Similar instructions, issued to the Min district
                            magistrate, and his proclamation issued in obedience to said
                            instructions, (inclosure 5.) I may add, that I am in possession of the
                            copies of similar instructions and proclamations published by nearly all
                            the district magistrates between Foo-chow and Amoy. A further proof of
                            their earnestness in the matter is found in their promptness in
                            appointing deputies to proceed with the company’s engineer to Amoy to
                            locate the line, and in the fact they immediately sent several young men
                            (Chinese) to the offices of the company in Foo-chow and at the anchorage
                            to be instructed in the art of telegraphy.</p>
                        <p>On the 12th of August, I introduced the company’s engineer and the
                            Foochow agent to the trade committee, and we, together, settled all the
                            details of the scheme, as fully set forth in a draught of an agreement
                            drawn up by myself, which document is, I believe, now in the hands of
                            General Raasloff, and may be seen by you. It was agreed that this
                            document should be put in proper form, and be signed at convenience, but
                            as the details were fully understood by both parties, the work of survey
                            should be commenced at once, and the company should take all the steps
                            necessary to insure the early construction of the line, such as ordering
                            the material, &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>It was my purpose to have the agreement signed simultaneously with the
                            movement of the surveying party, and to that end I put it in form as
                            quickly as possible, sent it to the Chinese for signature August 15,
                            when, much to my surprise, they began to raise objections to it, which
                            immediately gave rise to suspicions in my mind that a spirit of
                            opposition to the project was cropping up in some quarter unknown to me.
                            Certain amendments to the agreement were proposed, which, as they did
                            not change the tenor of the terms agreed upon, were accepted by the
                            company, and the document rewritten.</p>
                        <p>About this time the surveying party started for Amoy, and I was also
                            informed verbally, by a member of the trade committee, that instructions
                            had been received from the imperial commissioner, Shan, then in Formosa,
                            that telegraph-lines in China were to be built and owned by the Chinese;
                            but the impression was distinctly conveyed to me that the
                            governor-general did not concede to Shan the right to interfere in
                            matters pertaining to the province (Fuhkien) on the main-land, and that
                            the scheme under notice should be carried out. Nevertheless, the signing
                            of the agreement was delayed, and I soon learned the cause, by being put
                            in possession, through an underground channel, of certain instructions
                            issued by the governor-general to the committee. (Inclosure 6.)</p>
                        <p>Matters remained <hi rend="italic">in statu quo</hi> for a time, and
                            finding that the committee would not be moved to sign the agreement, and
                            hearing rumors of a division of sentiment amongst the Chinese officials,
                            which might, perhaps, defeat the project, I wrote a letter to the
                            governor-general, August 29, in which I made an earnest appeal to him to
                            allow no obstacles to intervene to prevent the consummation. (Inclosure
                            7.) This letter was answered indirectly by the committee, and I was
                            informed by Luh that the opposing <pb facs="0371" n="281" xml:id="pg_281"/> power behind the scenes was the Tartar general. I
                            thereupon solicited an interview with him and his two colleagues, the
                            governor-general and governor, which was accorded to me early in
                            September. At this interview the whole matter was discussed, and it was
                            agreed that if the company would fix an approximate price at which they
                            would convey the line to the provincial government when completed, the
                            agreement should be signed, and the work might proceed.</p>
                        <p>This the company did, and the work was immediately commenced with the
                            knowledge and assent of the trade committee. Soon after, about the
                            middle of September, orders came from the Tsung li Yamen to the
                            officials here to purchase the Foo-ebow-Pagoda line. (Inclosure 8.)
                            Suddenly, Luh, the Taotai, was superseded by the present incumbent, Pan,
                            a man notoriously anti-foreign, and opposed to all foreign innovations;
                            and soon afterward the governor-general was called to Amoy. Then
                            commenced a settled policy of resistance to all the demands of the
                            company, made through the Danish vice-consul and myself upon the
                            officials, to afford protection and carry out the terms of the
                            concession as agreed upon.</p>
                        <p>The company went steadily on with the work of construction until about
                            thirty miles of the line were completed, when, in obedience to positive
                            orders from the authorities, they suspended operations, hoping thereby
                            to come to some understanding with them by which protection might be
                            secured. After a delay of three weeks, at great expense to the company,
                            they found that no terms could be made; they therefore resumed work day
                            before yesterday, but were attacked by a mob of about fifty men from a
                            village near by, and driven from their ground.</p>
                        <p>Captain Haskin, being near the spot, went yesterday morning and had a
                            consultation with the people of the village, who frankly told him that
                            they had no objection to the telegraph being built, but had received
                            orders from the mandarins at Foo-chow not so allow it to be done.</p>
                        <p>This brings me up to the present moment. The company’s agents believe
                            that if the authorities would withdraw their opposition and say “Let the
                            line be completed,” the work would proceed without any opposition which
                            could not easily be overcome by them as they moved forward. I do not
                            hope for any change for the better, unless the Tsung li Yamen can be
                            induced to issue positive instructions to the Tartar general here to
                            withdraw his opposition and give the project his moral and active
                            support. You are perhaps advised as to whether such a step is likely to
                            be taken by the Yamun.</p>
                        <p>I shall wait with deep anxiety for your reply to this, in which I beg you
                            will tell me what may be hoped for from the Peking government.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer><signed>M. M. <hi rend="smallcaps">De</hi> LANO,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Consul.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Benj. P. Avery</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Minister, Peking.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in 1 in No.
                            40.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">De Lano</persName> to
                                    <persName type="to">Luh Taotai</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Consulate</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Foo-chow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-07-25"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 25,
                                1874</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">To <hi rend="smallcaps">Luh Taotai</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">President of the Committee of Foreign Trade:</hi></p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Great Northern Telegraph Company of
                            Denmark, having completed a contract with the imperial commissioner
                            Shĕn, for the construction of an electric telegraph line—overland and
                            submarine—from Foo-chow to Tai-wan-foo, via Tamsui, it is now thought
                            that the high provincial authorities at this port will look with favor
                            upon a proposition to erect a line overland between this and Amoy; and
                            in order that the subject maybe placed squarely and plainly before the
                            governor-general for his consideration, I have been requested by the
                            agent of the company to submit to you three separate propositions for
                            the construction of such a line.</p>
                        <p>The company will be glad to undertake the construction of a
                            telegraph-line between Foo-chow and Amoy on terms named in either of the
                            propositions clearly set forth below: <list>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">First proposition.</hi>—If the provincial
                                    authorities will give the company permission to erect poles
                                    along the government road, or by the most feasible route, and
                                    will take the necessary steps to secure their protection, the
                                    company will transmit all official dispatches from the Foo-chow
                                    authorities to the authorities at Amoy, Shanghai, and Hongkong
                                    over the line to Amoy, when the line is erected, free of
                                    charge.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Second proposition.</hi>—The company will
                                    undertake to erect the line (poles) under government protection
                                    as above stated, and will place upon the poles two wires, one of
                                    which shall be entirely under the control of the Chinese
                                    authorities, to be worked by their own operators and in their
                                    sole interest, while the other wire shall belong to the <pb facs="0372" n="282" xml:id="pg_282"/> company and shall he
                                    protected by the Chinese government authorities. In this case
                                    the company would even work the government line free of charge
                                    until some of your own people were sufficiently instructed in
                                    the art of telegraphy to manage it.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Third proposition.</hi>—The company will
                                    undertake to erect the line for the provincial government,
                                    entirely at government expense, following the directions of the
                                    authorities, under a contract to be concluded with them,
                                    supplying them with engineers and operators to work it when
                                    completed, the Chinese paying their salaries. In this case the
                                    company would furnish them with an office at Amoy free of
                                    charge, and in any case the company would undertake to teach
                                    Chinese the art of telegraphy and of telegraph engineering,
                                    provided the authorities would supply for the purpose men of
                                    intelligence and education who could read and write the English
                                    and French languages. This they would do free of charge.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The proposed line between Foo-chow and Formosa will only place Foo-chow
                            in communication with Formosa, whereas a line between Foo-chow and Amoy
                            would, when the Formosa line has been finished, place both Foo-chow and
                            Formosa in direct communication with the coast cities of China, with
                            Europe, America, and nearly all parts of the world.</p>
                        <p>An opportunity is offered in the second proposition of the company for
                            the provincial authorities to become the owners of a land-wire from
                            Foo-chow to Amoy without any outlay of money, merely by giving the
                            company permission to erect it, and by making the necessary arrangements
                            with the country people along the route for its construction and
                            protection.</p>
                        <p>I beg you will lay the matter before his excellency the viceroy, together
                            with the three propositions herein submitted, at your earliest
                            convenience, and that you will advise me at the earliest possible moment
                            what action, if any, the provincial government will take in the
                            matter.</p>
                        <p>Be pleased to accept the assurances of my high regards, and believe
                            me,</p>
                        <p>Yours, respectfully,</p>
                        <closer><signed>M. M. <hi rend="smallcaps">De</hi> LANO,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Consul.</hi></signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <dateline rendition="#left"><date ana="#date_conversion-issue-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="chinese-era chinese-lunisolar" notAfter="1874-07-31T23:59:59+08:05" notBefore="1874-06-15T00:00:00+08:05">Tungchi, 13th year, 6th
                                    moon, 12th day</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in 1 in No. 40.—Free
                                translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">trade committee</gloss> to
                                    <gloss type="to">United States consul</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date ana="#date_conversion-issue-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="chinese-lunisolar" notAfter="1874-07-31T23:59:59+08:05" notBefore="1874-06-15T00:00:00+08:05"><hi rend="smallcaps">Sixth
                                        Moon</hi>, 15th day</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">a direct reply.</hi></p>
                        <p>We have received and read your letter embodying the request of the Great
                            Northern Telegraph Company, which has deliberated and settled on three
                            propositions or proposed conditions for building a telegraph-line from
                            Foo-chow to Amoy. Your honor the consul regards the second of these as
                            very proper (or trustworthy) and you request us to lay the subject
                            before the viceroy for his consideration, and return answer.</p>
                        <p>It appears that you, on a former occasion, applied to us for permission
                            to construct a line of telegraph from the city and from Nantai to the
                            Pagoda anchorage, and that that matter has already been initiated and
                            settled.</p>
                        <p>Also, we have received the consent of the imperial commissioner, Shen, to
                            establish a line between Tai-wan-foo and Foo-chow. Now primarily, (of
                            itself considered,) the erection of a line between Foo-chow and Amoy can
                            be effected, but the distance is great, and it is feared it will be
                            difficult to afford full protection, in accordance with the
                            circumstances, (in accordance with your request,) we have petitioned the
                            viceroy, the provincial governor, and the Tartar general to investigate
                            the matter.</p>
                        <p>On receiving their instructions we will at once inform you. This is our
                            special reply; please examine it.</p>
                        <p>We add our respectful salutations.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in 1 in No. 40.—Free
                                translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss type="from">Foreign trade committee</gloss>
                                to <gloss type="to">United States consul</gloss></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date ana="#date_conversion-issue-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="chinese-lunisolar" notAfter="1874-07-31T23:59:59+08:05" notBefore="1874-06-15T00:00:00+08:05"><hi rend="smallcaps">Sixth
                                        Moon</hi>, 18th day</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">a direct letter to inform.</hi></p>
                        <p>We received your former letter touching request of the Great Northern
                            Telegraph Company for permission to construct a land-line between
                            Foo-chow and Amoy, and requesting us to communicate the same to the
                            governor-general for his consideration. To that letter we have already
                            replied, and you have doubtless received and examined (the reply).</p>
                        <pb facs="0373" n="283" xml:id="pg_283"/>
                        <p>Yesterday Prefect Chew brought word that he had a personal interview with
                            you, at which the advantages which would accrue to China were fully
                            discussed, and that you charged him to report to me, the Taotai, that
                            you advised that permission should be given to construct the Amoy line,
                            and that the work should be commenced forthwith. From this your friendly
                            and benignant intentions are very manifest. I feel much pleased, and
                            must, as in duty bound, report to the high officials your excellent
                            intentions to aid to consummate this good matter.</p>
                        <p>But a business of such magnitude takes time; hence, in its inception we
                            must not weary of the minutia, (or the preliminaries;) the distance
                            between Amoy and Foo-chow is considerable, and unless safe plans are at
                            first adopted, it may well be apprehended that full protection cannot be
                            given.</p>
                        <p>The role, then, is first to send our deputies to your office to consult
                            with the officers of the company as to rules. I, on the one hand, will
                            depute trusty officers to travel with them over the route and examine
                            it. Besides, I send you this special communication, trusting that you
                            will give your attention to the matter, and name a day when the deputies
                            may call to hold a personal consultation. You on the other hand should
                            direct the company’s officers to go with the deputies over the route
                            from Foo-chow to Amoy to examine carefully and locate the line, and care
                            must be taken not to injure (impede, hinder, obstruct) the people’s
                            fields, houses, and graves. Maps should be drawn to accompany the
                            reports (of survey) so the business may be easily (readily) managed.</p>
                        <p>We add our respectful salutations.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in 1 in No.
                            40.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Résumé of orders sent to the intendant of the
                                circuit of Hing-hwa, Tsuenchau, and Yung-chun prefectures by the
                                trade committee at Foo-chow.</hi></head>
                        <p>Mr. De Lano, the United States consul, has, on behalf of the Great
                            Northern Tele graph Company, applied for leave to put up a line between
                            Amoy and Foo-chow, for the accommodation of officials and merchants. As
                            the British and French consuls previously united with him in asking for
                            liberty to erect one from the city overland to Pagoda anchorage, which
                            is now in operation, and a submarine line is to be laid on as far as
                            Formosa, it is also decided by the provincial authorities to allow
                            this.</p>
                        <p>In order to carry out this project, a deputy named Yu Tsi-tsing is to
                            accompany a man from the company to examine the route, and see that it
                            does not interfere with the fields, houses, or graves of the people in
                            erecting the posts and stretching the wire.</p>
                        <p>However, as the matter is of much importance, and lest the ignorant
                            villagers may break the line in their willfulness, you are required to
                            intimate distinctly to the local authorities the need of issuing public
                            notifications upon the matter, so that they may understand it, and the
                            line may not be injured.</p>
                        <p>This is the particular object of this communication, to which please give
                            attention.</p>
                        <p>August 7, 1873.</p>
                        <p>I have received the following directions from the governor-general, in
                            response to the report sent him about the request made by Consul De Lano
                            that a telegraph-line be put up between Amoy and Foo-chow: “The erection
                            of a line between these two cities will be very advantageous in military
                            operations, and should therefore be permitted. Let an officer be soon
                            ordered to go over the whole line and see that the telegraph nowhere
                            interferes with the fields, gardens, houses, or graves of the people.
                            Let rules be drawn up with the company’s agent, and orders be sent also
                            to the local officers to give attention to the protection of the wire,
                            so that it may last long. All these things must be carefully arranged,
                            and afterward made known to the various officers interested.” I have
                            also received a reply from the governor agreeing in substance.</p>
                        <p>From the above, it is plain that in carrying out such an enterprise every
                            care must be taken to have the line run clear of peoples’ fields and
                            houses, and the posts set so as not to interfere with things; and this
                            was provided for by appointing you as a special agent to see to it. The
                            preceding responses having been received, it will also be best for the
                            end in view to send another official, of a higher rank, with you and the
                            company’s agents to go along the whole route and confer with the local
                            authorities, explaining everything, drawing plans of the course the line
                            goes, and having a general oversight throughout. It is supposed that Pan
                            Wan-fung, an officer of the internal revenue in Kan-Kiang, will be a
                            suitable person to appoint for this mission.</p>
                        <p>I shall report all these things to the high provincial authorities, and
                            have now also the honor to make known to you the steps which have been
                            taken, so that you may act upon them.</p>
                        <closer><dateline rendition="#left"><date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-08-15">August 15, 1874</date>.</dateline></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>To the <hi rend="smallcaps">Intendant</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">of Hinghwa, Tsüenchau, and Yungchun circuit, at
                                    Amoy.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <pb facs="0374" n="284" xml:id="pg_284"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 5 in 1 in No.
                                40.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Proclamation of Ching, of the district of
                            Min.</hi></head>
                        <p>Ching, acting magistrate of the district of Min, in Foo-chow prefecture,
                            hereby issues a plain proclamation for general observance.</p>
                        <p>On the 9th of August, 1874, I was honored by the following orders through
                            the committee of trade:</p>
                        <p>We have received a communication from Mr. De Lano, United States consul,
                            in relation to the request from the Great Northern Telegraph Company to
                            erect a line from Amoy to Foo-chow, in order to facilitate the
                            operations of government and trade. As the British, French, and American
                            consuls have already asked for permission to erect a line from the city
                            to the anchorage, which has been begun; and a continuation thence of a
                            submarine cable over to Formosa has been decided upon by the high
                            provincial officers, this request of a line to Amoy has been agreed to.
                            A deputy, Yu Tsi-tsing, has been associated with the telegraph company’s
                            agent to go over the whole road, in order to see where the line can best
                            go without interfering with the grounds, houses, or graves of the
                            people, placing the posts and arranging everything in mutual accord. But
                            as this matter is very important in its connection with the military
                            operations of the government, and there is fear lest the people, in
                            their ignorance, may wantonly break or injure the line, it is proper
                            that special cautions be given to the local authorities respecting its
                            careful protection. You will therefore instruct the deputy set apart for
                            this duty, and immediately take measures to issue public notice in your
                            jurisdiction to this end, ordering the people to be careful and not
                            wantonly hurt the line, which is of the highest importance. You will
                            also confer with Yu as to his survey of the road and the disposal of
                            policemen for carrying out the orders. When all has been arranged, you
                            will make a detailed report of what has been settled upon.</p>
                        <p>In compliance with the above orders, I hereby make known, in this
                            proclamation, to all soldiers and people, these things for their
                            information and obedience. When-ever the agents of the foreign company
                            come to a place with Yu, for the purpose of erecting posts and running
                            the wire, it is of the highest importance that they be protected; let no
                            one, on any pretense, injure or molest them, lest he subject himself to
                            examination. An important special notification.</p>
                        <closer><dateline rendition="#left"><date ana="#date_imprecise-inferred-from-date-rules" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1874-08-31" notBefore="1874-08-01"><hi rend="smallcaps">August</hi>,
                                    1874</date>.</dateline></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 6 in 1 in No.
                                40.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <p>The high commissioner Shan writes:</p>
                        <p>The telegraph-line erected between Amoy and Foo-chow is put up chiefly
                            for the use it will be in carrying on military operations; but I wish
                            you would think over this idea of mine. Everything in this world which
                            is of great use carries within itself some feature or some result which
                            is very disadvantageous. In any proposal coming from foreigners, it is
                            very important that the advantages and profit be not left in their
                            hands; we must not yield the management (of this) to others. In order to
                            secure this, we must defray its cost. If a line be allowed to be
                            erected, the merchants will wish to send messages over it, and the
                            outlay can be recouped by the charges on them.</p>
                        <p>The foreign employés on the line can be taken at a salary; they then
                            would have no ground for complaints, and all after-trouble would be
                            avoided.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 7 in 1 in No.
                                40.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">De Lano</persName> to
                                Governor <persName type="to">Li</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Consulate</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Foo-chow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-08-29"><hi rend="italic">August</hi> 29,
                                1874</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The undersigned, consul for the United
                            States, residing at Foo-chow, has the honor to submit to your excellency
                            the following representation:</p>
                        <p>On the 25th of July last he presented to the foreign trade committee, for
                            transmission to the high provincial officials, a communication in which
                            he strongly recommended the construction of a telegraph-line from
                            Foo-chow overland to the city of Amoy. He may here state that he had
                            three separate reasons for recommending the construction of the
                            telegraph, as above stated.</p>
                        <p>First. He believed that in view of the unsettled state of affairs between
                            China and <pb facs="0375" n="285" xml:id="pg_285"/> Japan, the line
                            would .he of incalculable benefit to the provincial government by
                            affording it facilities for quick communication with Formosa and all the
                            Chinese coast ports, as well as with foreign countries. Second. It would
                            be of great advantage to foreign commercial interests at the ports. And
                            third, the Great Northern Telegraph Company desired to construct the
                            line as a feeder to their submarine cable, which is now landed at
                            Hong-kong, Amoy, Shanghai, Nagasaki, and Vladivostock, in Russia.</p>
                        <p>In this first communication to the committee, the undersigned submitted,
                            for the consideration of the Chinese authorities, three separate
                            propositions of the Great Northern Telegraph Company to erect this
                            telegraph-line. One of them was to erect it on the company’s account,
                            and give the Chinese government a separate wire, to be used by them for
                            government purposes only, they agreeing to give the necessary protection
                            to the line during its construction and after its completion, but
                            reserving the light to purchase it at any time at its actual cost,
                            adding such a rate of interest from the date of completion to that of
                            sale as they and the company could agree upon.</p>
                        <p>The undersigned was advised, on the 28th of July, by the Taotai, that his
                            communication, containing the proposals of the telegraph company, had
                            been submitted to his superiors for their consideration; and again on
                            the 1st August he received another letter, informing him that the
                            provincial authorities had accepted the company’s proposal to erect the
                            line, on the terms above stated, and that a deputy would be immediately
                            appointed to confer with their agents, and make the necessary
                            arrangements for a preliminary survey of the route to Amoy. The
                            telegraph company, believing it to be important to the Chinese
                            government that the line should be erected and put in operation at the
                            earliest possible moment, immediately telegraphed to the directors in
                            Denmark to ship the wire and other material needed for the line without
                            delay, and send a corps of engineers and operators to construct and work
                            it. Consequently, on the 15th instant, the wire and other material and a
                            staff of engineers and operators started from London, in the steamer
                            Hong-kong.</p>
                        <p>Six days after the undersigned had received the Taotai’s letter,
                            acquainting him that permission had been given by your excellency to the
                            company to erect the line. Mr. Hoffmeyer, their chief engineer in China,
                            arrived here from Shanghai, prepared to commence the survey. On the 12th
                            instant, the undersigned called with him and Mr. Henningsen, the
                            Foo-chow agent, on the trade committee. At this interview all the
                            stipulations to be observed by the company, as well as by the Chinese
                            authorities, in regard to the construction and management of the line,
                            were distinctly and separately stated and agreed upon, after which it
                            was agreed that all the stipulations as orally stated should be clearly
                            written down in the form of an agreement, and should be signed by the
                            company’s agent (Mr. Henningsen) on its behalf, and by the trade
                            committee on behalf of the provincial government.</p>
                        <p>Immediately after this visit to the committee the company’s agent entered
                            into contracts for the telegraph-poles, to be delivered along the line,
                            for laborers to dig the holes, carry the poles, and erect them, thereby
                            involving an outlay of $30,000. He also arranged for the purchase of
                            ground in Nantai for a telegraph-station and erection of buildings on it
                            at a cost of about $12,000 more, while Mr. Hoffmeyer prepared for the
                            journey to Amoy.</p>
                        <p>In the mean time the undersigned drew up the written agreement (as
                            stated) in Chinese and English, which was signed by the company’s agent
                            on the 15th of August, and the same day handed in for the seal of the
                            trade-committee. The latter declined to stamp the document, and
                            suggested alterations which were written down. It was then rewritten and
                            embodied all the alterations which had been suggested by the committee
                            agreeably to your excellency’s instructions.</p>
                        <p>On the 17th instant, the written agreement, as amended, was again
                            submitted to the committee for approval, which again declined to sign
                            it. The next day, Chu, the sub-director of the trade-committee, called
                            at the consulate to introduce another deputy named Pan, who had also
                            been appointed to superintend the first survey of the route to Amoy, and
                            while he was there, Chu said that your excellency had received a letter
                            from Shan-Pao-Chan, the imperial commissioner to Formosa, stating that
                            this telegraph-line to Amoy should b’3 erected by the Chinese
                            government, and advised that the survey should be delayed. Nevertheless,
                            the surveying party was permitted to leave for Amoy on the following day
                            to make the survey.</p>
                        <p>Inasmuch as the trade-committee still declines to sign the agreement so
                            that all the terms shall be a matter of record, and now desires that the
                            company’s agent shall first name a price at which the Chinese may buy
                            the line when it is completed, the undersigned has been requested to
                            write this letter to your excellency, stating all these particulars. He,
                            at the same time, assures your excellency that this last request of the
                            committee is unreasonable, for, never having erected a land-line in
                            China, excepting the two short ones between Nantai and Mamoi, and
                            between Shanghai and Woosung, it is impossible for the company to state
                            howmuch the Foochow and Amoy line will cost.</p>
                        <p>The company, by their agent, Mr. Henningsen, assures the undersigned, and
                            he is willing to make this promise a clause in the agreement, that they
                            will, both in their own interest and that of the Chinese government,
                            construct the line as cheaply as a <pb facs="0376" n="286" xml:id="pg_286"/> good and serviceable line can possibly be
                            constructed, and in case the latter wishes to purchase it the company
                            will produce a correct statement, showing the exact cost of its
                            construction, and will then hand it over to them accordingly, as is
                            clearly stated in the article of the agreement. The company assert, and
                            the undersigned believes them, that they can erect the line cheaper than
                            any other company or person can possibly erect it, while, too, they will
                            put up none but a substantial and first-class line, using only the best
                            material.</p>
                        <p>In view, therefore, of the foregoing facts, and of the further fact, too,
                            that the company are now ready to commence the construction of the line
                            on the terms verbally agreed upon, and have already incurred heavy
                            expenses in making the survey and the purchase of the materials,
                            &amp;c., the undersigned begs that your excellency will order the
                            written agreement to be signed by the committee, so that the company can
                            at once begin the work of erecting the line, and he ventures to remind
                            your excellency that inasmuch as the agreement was verbally concluded
                            previous to your excellency’s receipt of the letter from Commissioner
                            Shan, the provincial officials ought, in good faith, to carry out their
                            said agreement with the company.</p>
                        <p>The undersigned also assures your excellency that the Great Northern
                            Telegraph Company is composed of high-minded and honorable men, who will
                            in all things deal honorably and justly with your excellency in this
                            matter. He, therefore, begs that your excellency will fairly consider
                            it, and favor him with an early reply. The undersigned avails himself of
                            this occasion to renew his respects.</p>
                        <closer><signed>M. M. DE LANO,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States
                                    Consul</hi>,</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Li,</hi><lb/><hi rend="italic">Governor-General of Fokhien and Chekiang.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 8 in 1 in No.
                                40.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Letter from the Tsung li Yamen about the purchase of
                                the line to the Pagoda, anchorage.</hi></head>
                        <p>We have recently seen in the newspapers this notice: “A telegraph line
                            has been erected overland from Foo-chow more than 20 <hi rend="italic">li</hi> long; it is entirely under the direction £ of the Great
                            Northern Telegraph Company, and the Chinese authorities have nothing to
                            do with it.”</p>
                        <p>We have no certain knowledge of the truth of this statement; but if it be
                            so, and the facts are rightly stated, then let the local officers be
                            directed to buy in the line and manage it themselves. It is probable
                            that the Yamen will have more definite and reliable information. We have
                            already fully discussed this matter of telegraph-lines with the foreign
                            ministers, and our permission only extended to laying a submarine line.
                            We have recently memorialized that the Danes be permitted to lay a line,
                            in order to expedite intercourse; but it is important that we ourselves
                            put up both the land and sea lines. Formerly the Russian minister,
                            Meu-ting Kashgar, erected a line in Peking, and the Yamen then replied
                            that when China permitted another country to put up a telegraph, she
                            would first allow the Russians to do so.<note n="*" xml:id="d152fn1">This and the last sentence are both obscure. General Vlangali had a
                                wire stretched across his legation, to show Prince Kung and others
                                its operation, in 1866.</note> The Russians have now written to us,
                            claiming the permission, but as we cannot say expressly in respect to
                            this Foo-chow line, and the correctness of the newspaper report, we
                            write to inquire about it. It is of the very highest urgency that this
                            line should be bought in, so that we can have somewhat to go upon as
                            proof in making them a reply.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 40.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">De Lano</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Avery</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Consulate,</hi><lb/><hi rend="italic">Foo-chow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-02-19"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 19,
                                    1875</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I regret to inform you that the opposition
                            of the Tartar general to the Foo-chow-Amoy telegraph scheme has
                            culminated in an order being issued by the viceroy—under pressure, no
                            doubt—to certain of his subordinates, who, at the time the permission to
                            erect the line was first given, were members of the foreign trade
                            committee, “to proceed to the spot and tear down the poles,” and that
                            the order has been so far executed that all of the second and third
                            sections, each ten miles of the line, have been destroyed. The first
                            section of ten miles still stands intact.</p>
                        <pb facs="0377" n="287" xml:id="pg_287"/>
                        <p>The officers who have so far executed these orders are a man named
                            Chew-Seng-e, lately subdirector of the trade committee, and a military
                            mandarin stationed inland. The information which I gather from Chinese
                            sources, believed to be reliable, is to the effect that the first attack
                            made on the company’s workmen, January 23d, was by a squad of soldiers
                            in disguise. Subsequently the greatest liberty seems to have been given
                            the people in respect of plundering the company’s property, and that of
                            their employés, but they have carefully avoided offering personal
                            violence to the European staff who have steadily retreated toward the
                            settlements as the work of destruction and plunder has progressed. The
                            authorities here have been advised from day to day by the acting Danish
                            consul of what was going on, and demands made upon them for protection
                            to life and property, but they have persisteutly declined to move in the
                            matter, declaring that the whole opposition came from the people, who,
                            they say, they have not the power to control, while the people have
                            frankly stated that they were proceeding under official direction; that
                            they did not wish to harm any one, but that being <hi rend="italic">allowed</hi> to take the company’s property, the opportunity could
                            not be lost. In one instance about 150 telegraph-poles, which were lying
                            at one of the company’s stations, were taken possession of by the
                            villagers, who said to the superintendent of construction, “If you
                            settle this affair and the Foo-chow mandarins allow you to build the
                            line, we will return the poles, otherwise we will use them to build a
                            joss-house with.” The two officials alluded to above have kept in the
                            background, not having at any time been seen by the company’s men.</p>
                        <p>The Europeans (Danes) have been most prudent and forbearing, having
                            almost entirely avoided altercations with the people, the result being
                            that the peasantry are still without objections to the line being
                            constructed through their country. It is nevertheless impossible to
                            calculate upon the extent of opposition which might be met with from the
                            local officials, and the literati further inland, were the line
                            hereafter to be built.</p>
                        <p>I am still of the opinion that the Tartar general is the opposing power,
                            and that neither the viceroy or Taotai are inimical to the telegraph. It
                            is a singular fact, that the officials have not based their opposition
                            to the scheme upon the want of imperial sanction, but solely upon the
                            alleged opposition of the country people.</p>
                        <p>The Foo-chow-Pagoda line has been repeatedly interrupted of late, it is
                            believed by thieves, who have cut the wire and carried off sections of
                            it, doubtless for gain, but the officials decline to order their arrest,
                            notwithstanding they have promised in an official dispatch to use all
                            means in their power to give that line full and complete protection.</p>
                        <p>In short, I may say that the officials have acted, and are now acting, in
                            very bad faith towards the company, and without being able, I think, to
                            justify their conduct, while the representatives of the company have
                            pursued a wise and most commendable policy, thereby avoiding the serious
                            difficulties which would have resulted from a collision with the country
                            people. They will try by all honorable means to maintain the Pagoda line
                            and the section of the Amoy line which have been left standing.</p>
                        <p>I am sending you by this opportunity a Foo-chow newspaper which contains
                            two or three articles on the subject under notice.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, &amp;c., &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>M. M. DE LANO.<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States
                                    Consul.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Benj. P. Avery</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Minister, Peking.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>