<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 183.Mr. Seward to Mr. Cadwalader.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1875v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d187</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">187</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1875-03-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1875-03-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1875-03-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1875-03-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="187"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d187">
                <head>No. 183.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Seward</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Cadwalader</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate-General</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-03-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 15, 1875</date>. (Received May
                        7.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 899.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: You will have learned, perhaps, through the
                    public press, that the Chinese government has recently made several loans from
                    foreigners. In this connection I have the honor to transmit to you several
                    editorial articles from the North China Daily News. You will observe that the
                    rates of interest stipulated for are high. I regard this as indicating not so
                    much want of confidence in the capacity of China to carry loans, or in her good
                    faith, as her lack of skill in the negotiation of the inconsiderable loans
                    mentioned.</p>
                <p>The fact that the government has come forward to borrow money of foreigners may
                    be held to indicate that the financial straits of China are great, and more or
                    less that the old unreasoning dislike and jealousy of foreigners is less strong
                    than heretofore.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GEORGE F. SEWARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosures in No. 899.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Newspaper extracts on the Chinese loan</hi>.</head>
                    <p rend="center">1.</p>
                    <p>If the rumor is true that a new Chinese loan is to be placed on the London
                        market, it will be interesting to see at what rate it can be floated as
                        compared with the two loans contracted by Japan. The small portion offered
                        in London of the loan made lately through the Hong-kong Bank hardly affords
                        a criterion. Otherwise the public seem to have fixed the interest in that
                        case at a little over 8 per cent. The difference between this rate and that
                        of the more recent loan from the Oriental Bank, which is reported to be 10½,
                        seems at a first glance to be startling; but it is, we believe, as regards
                        the rate paid by the Chinese government, more apparent than real. The high
                        rate of exchange which was charged by the Hong-kong and Shanghai Bank fully
                        covers the difference between 8 and 10½ per cent, as a total charge on the
                        loan. What we have now to do with, however, is the market value of the
                        stock, and it is curious to note that the Chinese 8 per cent, stock is
                        quoted here at exactly the same rate which the Japanese 7 per cent, stock
                        commands in the London market. Unless, therefore, we assume that a higher
                        value will be eventually put upon the Chinese stock in London than it
                        commands here, we may take it that Japanese credit is 1 per cent, better <pb
                            facs="0499" n="409" xml:id="pg_409"/> than the Chinese in the money
                        market. The comparison is hardly flattering to China, and it remains to be
                        seen how her apparent inclination to increase her debt will affect; her
                        future credit. She is actually paying now, at the outset of her career, very
                        nearly as much (10½ per cent.) as Turkey, which is thought to be nearing the
                        end of its financial tether. The public are apparently willing, as yet, to
                        let her have money more cheaply. But the loans are thus far secured on the
                        revenue of the foreign customs, and if the government goes on much longer at
                        the present rate and in its present mood, all available receipts from this
                        source will be soon completely pledged; and we may be sure that, this limit
                        once reached, a much higher rate of interest would be at once required. It
                        would not be a little strange if the result of the so-called patriotic
                        agitation in China should be to turn all the direct income derived from
                        duties on foreign trade back into the pockets of the foreigner himself.</p>
                    <p>At the time of the threatened difficulty with Japan, the Chinese professed to
                        look down with contempt upon the-little state which was galling them.
                        Rightly judging money to be the sinews of war, it seemed surprising that a
                        country undeniably possessing considerable financial resources should not be
                        able to make a better show in that transaction than did their own. We have
                        recently shown what have been the true reasons of the collapse of China in
                        both its military and financial aspects. In neither has she that confidence
                        in herself without which a nation cannot be prosperous. Rudely disturbed in
                        its dreams of universal pre-eminence, the Chinese government discovered that
                        its troops, armed with the antiquated weapons of the Middle Ages, were no
                        match against European levies. It saw the necessity of reform, but commenced
                        the reform at the wrong end. It endeavored to imitate the external aspects,
                        of those forces to which it had to succumb, but left out the fundamental
                        principles of action by which such forces are regulated. So in finance.
                        Finding that its revenues from trade, in place of displaying the elasticity
                        which the return of the empire to a state of internal tranquillity would
                        have naturally produced, were actually falling off, it took the course, not
                        of alleviating the incidence of those taxes, but of endeavoring to increase
                        their amount. Warnings have been given from all quarters of the effect of
                        those measures. One province after another has protested against the manner
                        in which it has been forced to increase the burdens upon the resources of
                        the people. To all this there has been but the one stereotyped reply,
                        desiring the provincial officers to see that their subordinates do not
                        squeeze. As it is necessary, in order to meet the demands upon them, that
                        the higher officials should exact as much as they possibly can from those
                        below them, and those in return have recourse to their own inferiors for a
                        similar purpose, it needs no special prescience to foretell the result. We
                        do not mean to say that there are no well-meaning officials in China. The
                        occasional able and straightforward memorials which appear in the Peking
                        Gazette are sufficient proof to the contrary. The best of men, however,
                        works with the millstone of an utterly corrupt system round his neck, and in
                        some respects the higher the office the more corrupt does the system seem to
                        become. In nothing does this position of affairs appear in more unenviable
                        light than in the rescripts to the memorials which from time to time appear
                        in the Peking Gazette. Possibly an utter want of power to grasp the true
                        bearings of the subject submitted is at the bottom of the unmeaning verbiage
                        with which important memorials are quietly shelved. If a memorial be of too
                        important a nature to be thus quietly put to one side, the device, not
                        unknown indeed in other quarters, is adopted of referring it to one or other
                        of the boards. Thus it is that the memorial of Hu Ting-kwei, to which we
                        referred some time ago, is delegated to the board of revenue. Hu, our
                        readers are aware, requested that the revenue and expenditure of the various
                        provinces should be stringently audited, and that a travelling commission to
                        inquire into abuses be formed. We doubt if the board of revenue, or the
                        government in its present state of comparative feebleness, could give effect
                        to such a sweeping proposition. It could, however, do much. At all events,
                        it could commence reforms near home, but there is no symptom of the purpose
                        or the will to do even this.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <p rend="center">2.</p>
                    <p>If getting in debt be a sign of progress, the Chinese government has made a
                        small step in that direction. The new Chinese loan of two millions and a
                        quarter taels, secured as it is on the foreign customs’ revenue, will
                        doubtless meet with ready acceptance at the proposed rate of nearly 8½ per
                        cent. Economically speaking, the proposed loan has much to recommend it; but
                        it is characteristic of the false position which China holds among nations,
                        and the bad name its government has earned for itself, that it has had to go
                        into the market at a rate so much less favorable than has the government of
                        Japan. The securities offered are, as we have stated, ample, provided care
                        is taken that the revenues assigned are duly placed aside for the intended
                        purpose. There is no reason to believe that the Chinese governnment is other
                        than <pb facs="0500" n="410" xml:id="pg_410"/> desirous to do its duty in
                        this respect; in fact we believe that those who control the executive are
                        quite sensible that in a matter of this sort thorough honesty is their best
                        and only policy, and their good intentions are guaranteed by the statement
                        that a certain portion of the customs’ revenue is assigned to the
                        introducers of the loan, the Hong-kong and Shanghai Bank, in trust for the
                        bondholders. So far we believe the loan to be satisfactory, but there is a
                        question to be asked, the reply to which is not of so clear a nature. We are
                        not told the object of the loan, nor what are the circumstances which have
                        impelled China to go into the market and become a debtor to Europe. Were the
                        money raised to be devoted to some useful project, as in Japan, we have
                        little doubt that China bonds would rapidly become a favorite in the market
                        It has been our unpleasant duty lately to comment on the extremely
                        unsatisfactory state of Chinese finance, and the issue of this loan lends
                        considerable proof to the arguments that we have advanced, that China in
                        this respect has fallen into a position whence she sees little hope of
                        extricating herself. Yet this condition of affairs has occurred in a time of
                        profound peace, when the empire is settled—so far as China can for years
                        hope to be settled within the eighteen provinces—and when the only external
                        foe to be guarded against is the Ameer of Kashgar. It is true, that the
                        threatened rupture with Japan cost a good deal of money; but it augurs ill
                        for the finances of a power like China that the few weeks of preparation
                        really undertaken should, have so utterly exhausted its resources as to need
                        an application to foreigners for capital. Had the finances of China been in
                        a moderately sound condition, they should without difficulty have borne this
                        strain; but so involved had they become that it rendered necessary the
                        present appeal to right them again. These circumstances are not hopeful for
                        the future of the empire, as the government is at present administered; and
                        now that China is about to take the first leap, and become a debtor to the
                        would at large, it will behoove her to see that her revenues are
                        administered in a less extravagant manner than at present. That the empire
                        is capable of occupying a high financial position, no one who has studied
                        the economy of the country, its resources both mineral and agricultural, and
                        the character of the people, can doubt. But all those things are rendered
                        nugatory by a government feeble and yet grasping, and which, by unluckily
                        always adopting the very worst means to an end, has succeeded in involving
                        itself in its present complication. The break-down of Chinese finance when
                        exposed to the light strain put upon it by the threatened rupture with
                        Japan, cannot, however, but have left its impress on the minds of those who
                        direct the government.</p>
                    <p>If the mere rumor of a war with a small power like Japan so seriously
                        interfered with the car of state, the consequences of any serious difficulty
                        with one of the great powers would be overwhelming. When China was ignorant
                        of the ways of the rest of the world, as at the outbreak of the first war,
                        it seemed but a slight thing to offend a power like England. Men there were
                        in abundance, and the rude munitions of war within the experience of Chinese
                        mandarins were readily obtainable without any very great expenditure of
                        money or discomfort to the country. Experience has twice shown China that
                        things have changed, and that even such measures as might have been
                        effective in 1840, in 1875 would be of no avail. Even within that brief
                        space the expense of war has probably quadrupled, and what China was unable
                        to do then, with a comparatively uncrippled exchequer, is now altogether
                        beyond her utmost endeavors. As we have pointed out, the very measures
                        recently adopted to increase the revenue of the empire are in reality
                        sapping its existence; but we fear that, although known to many Chinese
                        officials, these unpleasant facts have not yet presented themselves in their
                        nakedness to the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> government of China. The
                        present loan may afford a breathing space to enable some relief to be
                        introduced, but we fear that this will hardly be its result. To amend its
                        ways, unless under the extremest pressure, would be contrary to all the
                        traditions of China’s policy. The slight relief afforded will, we
                        anticipate, not be turned to the most useful, or to any useful purpose. The
                        terms of the loan are, as we have stated, fair, but one point attracts
                        comment. Issued at £95 per £100 bond, the repayment of the principal by lot
                        will effectually prevent the scrip ever rising above par. The future
                        quotations of the loan will thus never be a fair criterion as to public
                        opinion with regard to Chinese financial resources. Perhaps, on the whole,
                        this will be an advantage; though it might, on the other hand, be useful if
                        the Chinese government had some external means of ascertaining the effect on
                        its own credit of amelioration in its exchequer.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <p rend="center">3.</p>
                    <p>A humorous picture was drawn in an English paper, at the time of the first
                        Turkish loan, of the delight and astonishment of the Mussulman at finding
                        such a mine of wealth in the easy confidence of the Giaour. It was only in
                        1854, at the time of the Crimean war, that the first Turkish loan was
                        contracted—under, we believe, the joint guarantee <pb facs="0501" n="411"
                            xml:id="pg_411"/> of England and France—and the subsequent course of
                        Turkish finance has fully justified the satire we have quoted. In 1858,
                        1862, 1863, twice in 1865, in 1869, 1871, and 1873, the Turkish government
                        has appeared again and again as a borrower in the European market. What can
                        be simpler? They have only to ask and the money comes. True they have now to
                        pay the high rate (for Europe) of 11½ per cent.; but they can borrow afresh
                        if they go in arrear. Ministers do not hold office long in Constantinople.
                        Each one says, <hi rend="italic">Aprés moi le déluge</hi>, and gives the
                        ball another roll. There must be a limit; it will reach a size one day, when
                        all the strength of the finance department will fail to give it another
                        turn, and it will be very apt then to roll back and crush those who make the
                        effort; but in the mean time it moves with comparative ease. We should be
                        sorry to think China will, twenty years hence, have landed herself in the
                        same financial slough; and we have recalled the experience of Turkey chiefly
                        because we imagine the feeling at Constantinople in 1854 is paralleled
                        twenty years later at Peking. What a relief must it be to a government
                        embarrassed by the legacies of foreign and civil wars, its revenue checked
                        by oppressive taxation, and its resources drained by unprofitable
                        expeditions, to find an outlet from embarrassment in the wealth and
                        generosity of the barbarian. Was it embarrassed by the result of the Formosa
                        muddle? A loan of a million sterling at once smoothed the difficulty. Do the
                        troops in the northwest ask for pay and provisions as an inducement to march
                        on Turkestan? A loan of three million taels will send them on their way
                        rejoicing. And if it should occur to Li Hung-chang that another three
                        millions would be usefully spent in armor-plating the Taku forts, no doubt
                        the money could be at once obtained. The sums are small, in comparison with
                        European loans, but they must be a great relief to embarrassed financiers;
                        and their very smallness suggests how real must be that embarrassment.</p>
                    <p>China is not like other countries, where a man’s money is recognized as his
                        own, and he can only be made to contribute to the wants of the state by
                        taxes imposed with popular sanction, or by loan offered in the open market.
                        The paternal government of China claims a profound interest in the property
                        of its subjects. The only limit to taxation is the rebellion of the taxed,
                        or the attainment of a point at which taxation chokes the sources of
                        revenue. And do not memorials in the Peking Gazette indicate that each limit
                        has been attained in several provinces of the empire? And does not the
                        resort for money to extraneous sources seem to confirm the tale? Besides,
                        what could be more simple? Foreigners supply both principal and interest.
                        Foreigners lend the money, and taxation on foreign goods supplies the
                        necessary interest. We can imagine this is exactly the specious way in which
                        the transaction commends itself to the mental vision of Chinese statesmen.
                        That taxation on trade impedes trade, and thereby hinders the prosperity of
                        their people, is a fact of which they are ignorant or careless. And, really,
                        a loan of two millions sterling would be a very trifle to such a country as
                        China, if it were not for the indications we have noticed, of grave
                        financial embarrassment. The resources of the empire are enormous, if only
                        they were allowed to be developed. Its mineral wealth and commercial
                        capabilities are practically unlimited, if only it were intelligently
                        governed. That such a country should be reduced to borrowing so paltry a sum
                        is the strongest possible commentary on the incapacity of a government which
                        we persist in treating as an equal. Properly governed, China could support a
                        great debt with ease, and it would be an intelligent act on the part of her
                        rulers to borrow largely for the purpose of developing her resources. Any
                        movement in this direction would facilitate her operations by the greater
                        financial promise it would open up, and by the greater confidence it would
                        give in a government that showed an intelligent appreciation of its duties.
                        But loans contracted to replace money squandered on arsenals, and to supply
                        funds for profitless expeditions, only go to increase embarrassments.
                        Already there is a rumour of a third loan, to be brought out on the London
                        market, and we should not be surprised at any moment to hear the report
                        confirmed. One good effect may possibly ensue. Attention will be drawn to
                        China. People will want to know what she is doing with this money; and may
                        urge their rulers to demand some guarantee in the shape of progress for the
                        money which she asks them to lend. If the result of these loans should be to
                        impart some vigour to our relations with Peking, the gain would be great to
                        both foreigners and Chinese.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
