<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 248.Mr. Davis to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1875v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d252</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">252</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1875-08-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1875-08-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051619"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fraud</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1875-08-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1875-08-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="252"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d252">
                <head>No. 248.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Davis</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-08-23">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 23, 1875</date>. (Received September
                        15.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 164.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: To-day closes the first year since I took charge
                    of this legation. I have gathered together in a paper, which is inclosed
                    herewith, a concise statement of the various military cases which have occupied
                    our attention during the year. They present an interesting picture of the
                    practical operation of the naturalization treaties.</p>
                <p>I have omitted from this list the various cases in which parties have appealed to
                    the legation for protection against their own fears, and confine myself to the
                    cases in which the German authorities have actually set up a claim, either to
                    the military services of a naturalized citizen, or to the recovery from him of a
                    fine for the non-performance of military duty, or both. Including five cases in
                    which representations were originally made to the German government by my
                    predecessors, and which were pending on my arrival, there are thirty-five such
                    cases in all. Eleven of these are either known to have been adjusted without the
                    intervention of the legation, or are supposed to have been so adjusted from the
                    fact that nothing has been heard about them for some months. In three cases I
                    have declined to intervene.</p>
                <p>In Starts’s case I declined to do so, because at the time of his emigration he
                    was actually on the army-rolls, and was absent on furlough; he was actually a
                    deserter from the Bavarian army. In a parallel case in the Army of the United
                    States, he would undoubtedly have been held to be a deserter. His offense
                    appeared to me to be a purely military offense, not affected by the treaty. I
                    therefore decided to report it to the Department, and to await instructions.</p>
                <p>In Rosenthal’s case I refused, because upon his own statement he procured his
                    naturalization through a fraud. He had been but little over four years in the
                    country when he was naturalized, and he had never served in the Army of the
                    United States.</p>
                <p>Steinkauler’s case needs no comment. The Attorney-General has sustained my views
                    of public law, and the Department has approved my action in this case. The
                    remaining twenty-four cases were brought to the notice of the German government
                    by the legation, and have been the subject of more or less correspondence.</p>
                <p>Three cases only are still pending. In the cases of Bamberg and Ottinger, the
                    notes were sent to the foreign office only day before yesterday. In Würst’s
                    case, Mr. von Bulow has promised me to ask his colleague of the war office to
                    give a speedy answer. Seven persons have been released from fines imposed upon
                    them for not reporting for military duty, namely: Gewecke, Guth, Kater, Asch,
                    Grubel, Valpel, and Wohlgemuth.</p>
                <p>Eight persons have been released from the assumed obligation to perform military
                    service in the German army, namely: Weiss, Weidel, Gerding, Weil, Karl,
                    Trojanowski, Beckmau, and Zantzeu. Two have been released from military service,
                    and have also had their fines remitted, namely, Graffenberger and Arndt.</p>
                <p>In one case, that of Neumarche, the German government has refused to return a
                    fine which had already been collected, on the ground that the money was
                    originally paid by the father without protest or without making known the status
                    of the son, and on the further ground that there was not sufficient proof of a
                    five-years’ residence in the United States.</p>
                <pb facs="0657" n="567" xml:id="pg_567"/>
                <p>In three eases it has refused to release parties from service in the army,
                    namely: in the cases of Mumbour, Selbaeh, and Weich.</p>
                <p>In Mum hour’s case the refusal is made mainly, if not entirely, upon the ground
                    that he had returned to Germany to reside and without an intent to return to
                    America, and that under the treaty this operated as a renunciation of his
                    naturalization. The proof of this fact was his own statement to that effect,
                    made before the tribunal occupied with the investigation of his case.</p>
                <p>In Selbach’s case, it appeared that immediately after obtaining his
                    naturalization he had returned to Germany, and had gone into business in
                    Mannheim with his father 5 that the authorities had notified him shortly before
                    the expiration of a two years’ residence in Germany that should his residence be
                    prolonged beyond the two years, he would be regarded as having forfeited his
                    naturalization; that alter the expiration of the two years he was ordered into
                    military service, but was also again offered the opportunity to return to
                    America, and that he declined the offer, and was then put into service. He
                    remained in the service a short time and then deserted, pending the decision
                    upon his application. It is perhaps not a subject for astonishment that the
                    decision was adverse to him under such circumstances.</p>
                <p>In the third case, Weich had been actually summoned to perform military duty in
                    the army of Baden when he emigrated. He was, therefore, on his return, held by
                    the military authorities to be a deserter, and the decision was adopted by the
                    foreign office in its note to the legation. Even before the conclusion of the
                    naturalization treaties, Mr. Cass had instructed this legation that, where a
                    person had before emigration been actually summoned to do military duty and had
                    disregarded the summons, he became subject to the military jurisdiction,
                    notwithstanding subsequent naturalization. This decision, therefore, did not
                    appear open to objection. I apprehend that this brief review of the year’s work
                    will satisfy the Department that the German government is disposed to regard the
                    rights of our naturalized citizens as defined by the treaties.</p>
                <p>The Almanach de Gotha of this year gives the number of citizens of the United
                    States residing in Germany, and counted among its “population,” as 10,698. There
                    is good ground for believing that a decided majority of these are naturalized
                    citizens. Twice a week from New York, and once a fortnight from Baltimore,
                    German steamers are sailing for Germany, each time bringing back numbers of
                    native-born Germans who have been naturalized in the United States. And yet,
                    great as is the number of naturalized citizens returning to Germany, only
                    thirty-five cases have come to the knowledge of the legation in which the
                    military authorities have questioned the status of any of them. Three cases only
                    have been decided adversely, and these upon principles or facts which it will be
                    difficult to question.</p>
                <p>Europe is now an armed camp in time of peace. The successes of Germany in the
                    wars of 1866 and 1870 have worked and are still working a revolution in the
                    organization of European armies. France will soon have a force which, including
                    reserves and navy, will number, when on a full war-footing, about 1,700,000. The
                    Almanac de Gotha gives the effective force of the Russian army in time of war at
                    1,520,000 men—a number which I apprehend the existing reforms are decidedly
                    augmenting. Italy has 760,000; England 550,000; Austria about the same; and, in
                    fine, the whole force of the armies of Europe, outside of Germany, is estimated
                    to amount to the immense number of 7,500,000 men. The same authority which I
                    have quoted gives the entire war force <pb facs="0658" n="568" xml:id="pg_568"/>
                    of Germany, when on a war-footing, as 1,370,000. The army, when put on a
                    war-footing, includes the army proper; that is to say, the men who serve for
                    three years, commencing with the completion of their twentieth year. (As 1
                    understand the treaty, persons who are actually enrolled for this period of
                    service, or who have actually been summoned for it, cannot emigrate without
                    committing a military offense.) Next come the reserves, which include all who
                    have served three years, and who are then placed for four years on the list of
                    reserves. These are the first to be called upon in time of war, when the
                    ordinary forces are insufficient. (I understand that the treaty leaves persons
                    on this list free to emigrate, except when the force is called out.) The
                    landwehr and the seawehr constitute the next class, in which all persons are
                    enrolled for a period of five years alter the termination of the reserve period.
                    Lastly there is the landsturm, in which all who have served in the active army,
                    in the reserves, and in the land or seawehr, are again classed until the
                    expiration of their forty second year. The legislation of the last session of
                    the Reichstag increases the efficiency of these forces. With a whole male
                    population under forty-three thus in arms, either actually or constructively,
                    and with jealous neighbors on every side equally armed to the teeth, perhaps one
                    ought not to wonder that when the officers charged with the care of the recruits
                    find a native-born German residing in Germany, and claiming to be exempt from
                    the common duty which all Germans owe to the state, they should scrutinize his
                    claims with some strictness, and should occasionally put the claimant to the
                    proof of them through his legation. Whenever such a challenge has been given,
                    the legation has done its best to protect and maintain the just rights of our
                    naturalized citizens. The German government, in the cases which I now report,
                    appear to have been disposed to construe the last half of the fourth article of
                    the treaty as it was construed by my predecessor, who negotiated it. “I have
                    insisted,” he wrote to the Department on the 29th June, 1874, “that the
                    naturalized American who has the appearance of having obtained naturalization
                    solely to escape military service, should have a right to establish his
                    sincerity by electing to take up his residence in the United States.”</p>
                <p>This right was in fact offered both to Selbach and to. Bamberg. Arndt’s case was
                    decided favorably on the ground that he had not resided two years in Germany
                    when arrested. Hersch also reports a notice to him that after a two years’
                    residence in Germany he would be regarded as having renounced his
                    naturalization. In all these cases the necessity of some reasonable preliminary
                    notice of an intent to put in force the provisions of the treaty appears to have
                    been recognized.</p>
                <p>The release from fine, or arrest, or both, which has followed several of the
                    applications of the legation, has been granted, when granted at all, by the use
                    of the royal prerogative of pardon. It has not been regarded as a right which
                    can be asserted and enforced under German law by the injured party. In some
                    cases the inquiries which preceded the exercise of the prerogative have been
                    prolonged beyond the patience of the parties in interest. But on the whole the
                    operation of the treaties during the year has been beneficial and just. Those
                    who have deserved protection have been protected. Those who have not been
                    protected were either seeking to use their acquired citizenship for the
                    perpetration of a fraud, or had been guilty of a military offense against which
                    the treaty is no protection.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. C. BANCROFT DAVIS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0659" n="569" xml:id="pg_569"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 161]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of military cases at the legation of the United
                            States in Berlin from August</hi> 24, 1874, <hi rend="italic">to
                            August</hi> 23, 1875, <hi rend="italic">both inclusive.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Jacob Weiss.—</hi>This case was begun in Mr.
                            Bancroft’s time. Weiss having been summoned to perform military duty,
                            application was made for his release; and this being granted, he
                            returned his thanks to the legation August 30, 1874.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Leo Graffenberger.</hi>—Complained September 27, 1875,
                            to legation. He went to America in 1887, when seventeen years old;
                            resided there more than five years; was naturalized in August, 1873;
                            returned to Germany in August, 1874; found that he had been lined in his
                            absence for non-performance of military duty, and that he was threatened
                            with proceedings to compel him to perform military duty September 30.
                            These facts were stated in a note to the foreign office, and request was
                            made for steps to protect him from further molestation. January 28,
                            1875, the foreign office informed the legation that the steps had been
                            taken against Graffenberger in ignorance of his acquired citizenship,
                            and that they would be discontinued and that the fine would be
                            remitted.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Robert Weidel.</hi>—This case was begun in Mr. Fish’s
                            time. He was released August 27, 1874, and expressed his thanks
                            September 6, 1874.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Robert Gewecke.</hi>—Emigrated to the United States in
                            January, 1869, being eighteen years old; was naturalized March 25,1874,
                            returned to Germany in April, 1874, and was fined for unallowed
                            emigration. He stated his case to the legation September. 13, 1874; a
                            note was addressed to the foreign office September 17, 1874, and after
                            several interviews with Mr. von Billow and some correspondence with Mr.
                            Gewecke, the legation was informed, February 9, 1875, that the fine and
                            costs were remitted.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Frederick A. Arndt.</hi>—Was born in 1835; in 1855 he
                            presented himself for enrollment, and being a sailor was enrolled in the
                            navy to serve until his 39th year. From 1855 to 1863 he served by
                            permission on several merchant vessels. In 1868 he took up his residence
                            in New York, remained there over rive years, and became naturalized. In
                            1874 he returned to Germany and entered into business at Danzig. He was
                            condemned to a tine of 20thalers, and to six years’ service in the navy
                            for unauthorized emigration, and for not responding to the call in 1870.
                            He notified the legation September 7, 1874. The legation intervened for
                            him verbally on the same day, and again by note September 11. On the
                            11th October, 1874, the foreign office informed the legation that the
                            sentence was reversed and the fine remitted.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Herman Guth.</hi>—This case was begun by Mr. Fish July
                            29,1874. He represented to the foreign office that Guth was a
                            naturalized citizen of the United States, and that on returning to
                            Germany he had been illegally arrested, and a fine of 50 thaler had been
                            exacted from him. Again on the 8th of October representations were
                            repeated by the legation in a second note, and on November 27 further
                            verbal representations were made. On the 12th December the foreign
                            office, by note, informed the legation of the remission of the sentence
                            and fine.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Henry Mumbour.—</hi> Served three years in the
                            Prussian army. His name was then placed among the reserves, and he
                            obtained a leave of absence for a year. In April, 1869, he went to the
                            United States. While there France declared war against Germany, and the
                            reserves were called out. He heard of the call in Pittsburgh, and
                            decided to remain in America, and to become naturalized. He remained
                            five years in America, became naturalized, and, in 1874, returned to
                            Germany. He was arrested for desertion here, convicted, and sentenced to
                            a year’s imprisonment. He appealed to the legation, and on the 8th of
                            February a note in his behalf was addressed to the foreign office. On
                            the 7th of March the foreign office answered that Mumbour, on
                            examination, had admitted that he was residing in Germany without intent
                            to return to the United States, and therefore that he had, under the
                            treaty, renounced his naturalization, and that he could not be regarded
                            as among the number of those who, as <hi rend="italic">bona-fide</hi>
                            American citizens, return here temporarily. They therefore declined to
                            remit his sentence.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Carl F. Selbaeh.</hi>—Arrived in the United States in
                            June, 1837; was naturalized June 26, 1872; arrived in Germany in July,
                            1872; took up his residence at Mannheim, and became assistant to his
                            father in business; was notified in June, 1874, by the German
                            authorities that if he should reside in Germany longer than two years
                            from the date of his return to Mannheim he would be regarded as having
                            renounced his naturalization. He did remain. On the 20th August, 1874,
                            he was taken for military service; was again told by the Germans he
                            would be discharged if he would leave for America; declined, and
                            appealed to the legation. On the 28th September the legation asked for
                            his discharge. On the 17th of November the foreign office replied that
                            the circumstances would seem to indicate that Selbaeh had renounced his
                            naturalization, but as he had deserted from the army the matter appeared
                            to be settled for the present.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Kater.</hi>—This case was begun in Mr.
                            Bancroft’s time. The legation asked for the return of a fine improperly
                            imposed upon Kater for the non-performance of military duty. On the 17th
                            of November the foreign office informed the legation that the money
                            would be refunded.</item>
                        <pb facs="0660" n="570" xml:id="pg_570"/>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Wolff Herz Asch</hi>—This case was begun in Mr. Fish’s
                            time. The legation asked for the remission of a penalty and the return
                            of a line of fifty thaler. On the 7th of September the request was
                            repeated verbally. On the 22d of November the foreign office informed
                            the legation that the penalty and costs would be remitted and the fine
                            paid back.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Paul Weissbach.</hi>—A naturalized citizen; wrote the
                            legation November 26, 1874, that he had been lined for non-performance
                            of military duty, and feared he would be enrolled as a soldier. The
                            legation replied informing him of his rights, suggesting that he should
                            first apply to the local authorities, and should that prove to be
                            unsuccessful, informing him what facts he should send proof of to the
                            legation. As nothing more was heard from the case it is supposed that it
                            was satisfactorily adjusted.</item>
                        <label>12.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Franz Homan.</hi>—Wrote the legation December 15,
                            1874, that he was a naturalized American citizen, and that he had reason
                            to fear that he would be called upon to do military service in the
                            German army. On the 13th of February he wrote that he was arrested and
                            was about to be forced into service. His rights, however, were
                            subsequently recognized, and no official action was necessary in his
                            behalf. On the 16th of February he wrote that he had been discharged.
                            His papers were returned to him February 18, 1875.</item>
                        <label>13.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Ferdinand Böge.</hi>—Wrote the legation that he was a
                            naturalized American citizen, and that on his return to Germany he had
                            been fined fifty thaler for non-performance of military duty. The
                            legation replied to his letter, making suggestions and asking for
                            further information. On the 17th of February Mr. Böge wrote asking for
                            the return of his papers. As nothing more has been heard of the case, it
                            is supposed to have been adjusted satisfactorily.</item>
                        <label>14.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Jacob Weick.</hi>—Was summoned in 1869 to do military
                            duty in Baden. Instead of responding, he went to the United States,
                            where he resided five years and became a citizen. During his absence a
                            fine of two hundred thalers was imposed upon his estate. On his return
                            he was arrested for desertion. Pending the examination he escaped into
                            Switzerland, and invoked the intervention of the legation through the
                            consul at Basle. A note was written in his behalf, to which, on the 27th
                            of February, reply was made that he had been adjudged to be a deserter,
                            and the sentence would be enforced should he come again within the
                            jurisdiction.</item>
                        <label>15.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Edward Grubel.</hi>—On the 6th of January, 1875, the
                            legation represented to the foreign office that Grubel had emigrated to
                            America in 1867, at the age of 17; that he had resided there over seven
                            years and became naturalized, and that on his return to Germany, in
                            1874, he had been made to pay a fine of 150 marks, and committed to
                            prison in delimit of immediate payment. His discharge and remission of
                            the sentence were asked for. On the 15th of May the legation was
                            notified that the fine was remitted and Grubel discharged.</item>
                        <label>16.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Theodore Vopel.</hi>—On the 11th of February, 1875,
                            made affidavit at the legation that he was born in Berlin; that he
                            served in the German army once for a period of three years, and once for
                            a period of three months, in each case receiving his discharge on
                            leaving; that he emigrated to America, resided there five years, and
                            became naturalized; that he returned to Berlin in October, 1874, and
                            that on the 30th January, 1875, he had been summoned to pay a fine of
                            231.75 marks (including costs) for emigrating without permission. The
                            legation on the same day addressed a note to the foreign office,
                            asserting his exemption as an American citizen. On the 3d of May the
                            foreign office said that proceedings had been stayed, and asked for
                            further papers in the case, which were furnished. On the 14th of July
                            the foreign office notified the legation of the remission of the
                            fine.</item>
                        <label>17.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Charles H. A. Gerding—</hi> On the 19th of
                            February,1875, the legation received a letter from Mr. Gerding, dated
                            the 18th, stating that he emigrated to America in 1867, when 20 years of
                            age; that he remained there five years and two months, and became
                            naturalized; that he had returned to his old home to sell some property
                            which he had inherited, intending to return to America when that should
                            be done; and that he had been arrested, and after examination before an
                            officer had been forced into the Prussian army. On the 19th of February
                            the legation transmitted a copy of this letter to the foreign office
                            with a note asking for redress, and on the 18th and 20th March further
                            notes were addressed to the foreign office in this case. On the 15th of
                            May the foreign office notified the legation that Gerding’s discharge
                            had been ordered.</item>
                        <label>18.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Philip Humpert—</hi> Born in 1840; served one year in
                            the Prussian army; emigrated to America in March, 1868; was naturalized
                            there, and returned in December, 1874. On the 21st of January, he
                            notified legation that he had been fined fifty thaler for nonperformance
                            of military duty. The legation acknowledged the letter, and sent him
                            copies of the treaties, &amp;c., to be shown to the court in his
                            defense. On the 1st of March, acknowledging this, he said that he was a
                            doctor of medicine, and had returned to Germany “to live for a longer or
                            shorter time and practice his profession.” The legation replied that
                            such language implied residence in Germany without intent to return to
                            America, and required him to state, under oath, that he intended to
                            return to America. He has not done so, and it is to be presumed that he
                            could not take that <pb facs="0661" n="571" xml:id="pg_571"/> oath, or
                            that he has not been further molested, or that he has concluded to pay
                            the fine.</item>
                        <label>19.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Simon Weil</hi>.—Was born at Bisheim, in Alsace, in
                            1853; emigrated to the United States in 1868; was naturalized at Mobile,
                            June 19, 1874; returned to Bisheim July 18, 1874, and was ordered to
                            appear on the 12th of March for military duty in the German army. On the
                            3d March, Weil wrote, invoking the intervention of the legation. The
                            letter was received on the 6th, and on the same day a note was addressed
                            to the foreign office. Weil was shortly afterward discharged, and on the
                            6th of June the foreign office notified the legation that he was not
                            regarded as a German subject. On the same day Weil wrote the legation,
                            asking if he could not stay in Alsace “for always,” and go into business
                            there.</item>
                        <label>20.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Arthur Steinkauler.</hi>—Father emigrated to America
                            in 1848, and became naturalized there in 1854. Arthur was born at Saint
                            Louis, in 1855. In 1859, the father and his wife and family, including
                            Arthur, returned to Germany, and took up their residence at Wiesbaden,
                            and have since resided there continuously. The father admits that he
                            does not intend to return to America, and says, “according to the treaty
                            of 1868, I, myself may now be considered a Prussian citizen.” On the 2d
                            April, 1875, the father laid these facts before the legation, and said
                            that Arthur had been summoned to do military duty, and asked the
                            intervention of the legation. The legation declined to intervene, unless
                            the son would give a personal statement of his election to be a citizen
                            of the United States, and an assurance of his intention to return to
                            America at some reasonable date to be fixed by him. The father, on his
                            behalf, declined to do so.</item>
                        <label>21.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Lewis Wohlgemuth.</hi>—On the 28th of April, 1875,
                            wrote the legation that he emigrated to the United States when eighteen
                            years of age; remained there seven years; became naturalized; returned
                            the week before the date of his letter, and had been summoned to pay 50
                            thaler penalty for non-appearance in 1870–71 and 1872. On the 29th of
                            April the legation addressed a note to the foreign office. On the 1st of
                            June the foreign office informed the legation that it appeared on
                            investigation that the fine had already been paid by Wohlgemuth’s
                            father, and that it would be repaid upon Wohlgemuth’s proving his
                            naturalization and residence five years in the United States.</item>
                        <label>22.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Adolph Karl.</hi>—On the 30th of April, 1875, the
                            legation informed the foreign office by note that Adolph Karl, a German
                            naturalized in the United States, who had resided there six years, had,
                            on his return to Germany, been arrested and placed in the imperial army.
                            An immediate inquiry was asked for. On the 4th of May a further
                            communication was made. On the 11th of August the foreign office replied
                            that instructions had been given to restore to Mr. Karl his papers, and
                            to throw no more obstacles in the way of his sojourn in his native
                            place.</item>
                        <label>23.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Francis Trojanowski.</hi>—This case was brought to the
                            attention of the legation by telegraph and letter on the morning of the
                            4th of May, 1875, and on the same day the legation transmitted the
                            original papers to the foreign office, with a request that the proper
                            steps might be taken in the matter. It appeared that Trojanowski had
                            resided five years in America, and been naturalized there, and on return
                            to Germany had been forced to do military duty. Another note was
                            addressed to the foreign office on the 18th of May, and a third on the
                            4th of June. On the 15th of June the foreign office informed the
                            legation that Trojanowski had been released, and returned the original
                            papers.</item>
                        <label>24.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">B. Blumenthal.</hi>—On the 7th of May, 1875, the
                            legation informed the foreign office that Blumenthal, a naturalized
                            citizen of the United States, had resided more than five years in the
                            United States, and had returned to Germany about two months previously.
                            He had been fined fifty thalers for not reporting himself for military
                            duty in 1873, and had been told that in case of non-payment he would be
                            imprisoned. The legation asked to have the case inquired into, and to
                            have Blumenthal’s rights respected. Nothing having since been heard of
                            it, it is supposed that this fine was not enforced, and that
                            Blumenthal’s rights have been respected.</item>
                        <label>25.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Martin Beckmann.</hi>—Emigrated to America when he was
                            nineteen years old; resided there six years, was naturalized, became a
                            land-owner in Nebraska, returned to visit his father at Kiel, and was
                            forced into the German army. On the 12th of May, 1875, the legation was
                            informed of some of these facts through the consulate-general at Berlin.
                            Further information was desired, which was given, and on the 18th of May
                            a note was addressed to the foreign office asking for Beckmann’s
                            discharge. On the 2d of July the legation was officially informed of his
                            release.</item>
                        <label>26.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Morris A. Neumarch.</hi>—Was a native Prussian, who
                            resided more than five years in the United States, and was naturalized
                            there. On his return to Germany he found that a fine of 150 marks for
                            non-performance of military duty had been imposed upon him during his
                            absence, and had been paid by his father. “He informed the legation of
                            these facts on the 18th May, 1875, and on the same day proper
                            representations were made to the foreign office by note. On the 21st of
                            June the foreign office declined to return the fine, on the ground that
                            when the father paid the fine he had not protested or given notice of
                            the acquired citizenship of the son, and on the further ground that the
                            five years’ residence in America had not been satisfactorily
                            proved.</item>
                        <pb facs="0662" n="572" xml:id="pg_572"/>
                        <label>27.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Moses Baum.</hi>—A native of Oldenberg, emigrated to
                            America in 1886, became naturalized in 1872, and returned to Germany in
                            1875, on a visit. On the 27th of May, 1875, he informed the legation
                            that he had been fined 50 thalers for not presenting himself for
                            military duty, while in the United States; that he had been summoned to
                            do military duty, and that he had escaped into Belgium in order to avoid
                            process. The legation answered that, should he return, it would be the
                            duty of the legation, if the facts stated were true, to protect him as
                            far as possible. He returned, and upon a restatement of the case by his
                            counsel, received on the 8th of June, he was informed on that day by
                            letter that if he would transmit to the legation the evidence of his
                            citizenship the legation would lay the matter at once before the foreign
                            office; since then nothing has been heard from him, from which it is
                            presumed that the case has been adjusted.</item>
                        <label>28.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Carl Johann Erwin Behrens.</hi>—A native of Brunswick,
                            naturalized in New York July 14, 1873, took out a passport from the
                            Department of State August 6, 1873, returned to Brunswick September,
                            1873; took charge of his father’s business there, but declared that he
                            intended to return to America. He was summoned to do military duty, and
                            he asked the intervention of the legation, through the consul at
                            Brunswick, on the 28th of May, 1875. The legation answered, the same
                            day, that it would intervene on receiving the proper proof of
                            citizenship, and the oath of an intent to return to America. Nothing
                            more heard of the case.:</item>
                        <label>29.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Charles S. Rosenthal.</hi>—Born in Prussia, March 13,
                            1847; went to the United States in July, 1865; was naturalized in the
                            United States district court for the district of Massachusetts, November
                            16, 1869. He invoked the intervention of the legation to relieve him
                            from a fine of fifty thalers for non-performance of military duty. This
                            application was declined, upon the ground that his naturalization was
                            improperly obtained, he not having resided five years in the United
                            States, nor served in the Army of the United States.</item>
                        <label>30.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">David Wurst.</hi>—A native of Frankfort; resided in
                            the United States six years; naturalized October 30, 1872, then returned
                            to Germany; resided here more than two years; was then summoned to do
                            military duty. He claimed his rights as a citizen of the United States,
                            and was told it was too late. He expressed a desire to return to
                            America, but permission was refused him. He then invoked the
                            intervention of the legation through the consul-general at Frankfort.
                            The legation addressed the foreign office July 12, 1875, asking that
                            steps might be promptly taken for Wurst’s release. No answer has, as
                            yet, been received. On the 21st instant a verbal request was made by Mr.
                            Davis for an answer.</item>
                        <label>31.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mathias Bamberg.</hi>—Emigrated to America in 1887,
                            remained there six years, was naturalized, and returned to Germany in
                            July, 1873. In May, 1875, he was told by the German authorities that
                            should he remain in Germany over two years he would be regarded as a
                            Prussian, and be made to do military duty. He said that he must remain,
                            in order to look after an inheritance, and did remain. On the 9th of
                            July he was enrolled in the Prussian service. On the 12th of July the
                            legation received a letter setting forth these facts, and asking
                            intervention, to enable him to remain in Germany until the end of
                            November, in order to finish the business about his inheritance. The
                            legation replied, asking the exact date of his return to Germany in
                            1873, the date in May on which his sojourn was called in question, the
                            manner in which it was done, the name of the officer who notified him to
                            leave, and he was told that these questions were asked in his own
                            interests, and to make for himself the best case he could. An answer was
                            received to these questions, and a note was addressed to the foreign
                            office on his behalf on the 21st instant. There has not yet been time
                            for an investigation and reply.</item>
                        <label>32.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">C. H. F.Jantzen.</hi>—A native of Mecklenburg;
                            emigrated to the United States in 1888; resided there until April 27,
                            1875; was naturalized April 24, 1875; left for Germany in the Schiller,
                            and in the shipwreck of that vessel lost his passport and his
                            citizen-paper. He returned to his native place, and on the 8th July was
                            summoned to do military duty. He made a statement of these facts to the
                            legation in a letter dated July 13, 1875. On the 15th, the legation
                            asked of the foreign office suspension of proceedings, to enable him to
                            procure from America proof of his citizenship. On the 11th of August,
                            the foreign office notified the legation that Jantzen had satisfactorily
                            proved his citizenship, and that he was free.</item>
                        <label>33.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Charles Ottinger.</hi>—On the 29th July,
                            1875,’informed the legation that he had emigrated to America, resided
                            five years in the United States, and became naturalized. During his
                            residence there a fine had been imposed upon him, which had been paid
                            under protest. To a letter of the legation making further inquiries, he
                            replied that, before going to America, he had been summoned to perform
                            military duty, had reported himself, had been examined, his physical
                            condition unfavorably reported on, and his case had been adjourned for a
                            year, and he had been ordered to report the following year. Instead of
                            complying with the order, he went to America. A note in his behalf was
                            addressed to the foreign office August 21; 1875. There has not yet been
                            time for investigation of the case by the German government.</item>
                        <label>34.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Hilar Fresch.</hi>—Communications about this case were
                            received on the 30th of July, <pb facs="0663" n="573" xml:id="pg_573"/>
                            and the 6th, 16th, and 17th of August, 1875, so illegibly-written as to
                            make it difficult to understand them. It appeared, however, that Mr.
                            Fresch was a naturalized citizen, who had returned to Germany, and
                            resided in Wurtemberg nearly two years, and had been notified that,
                            should he continue to reside there more than two years, it would be
                            considered as a renunciation of his naturalization. The legation advised
                            him that, after the expiration of the two years, it would be much more
                            difficult to protect him, and counseled him to go to America.</item>
                        <label>35.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Anton Stack.</hi>—Served in the Bavarian army two
                            years and four months; left on furlough and emigrated to America. He
                            says that he was naturalized there, and returned here in 1875. He has
                            been arrested for desertion. The facts were communicated to the legation
                            on the 16th August. The legation answered that it could not intervene
                            without instructions from the Department of State, as Stach was actually
                            in the army when he emigrated.</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
