<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-08-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-08-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="88" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d88">
                    <head>No. 84.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Fish</persName> to
                            Mr. <persName type="to">Williamson</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-08-24"><hi rend="italic">August</hi> 24,
                            1874</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 108.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your dispatch No. 149, of the 7th of May last,
                        has been received. It asks for further instructions in regard to the
                        breaking into the consulate at Omoa, and insult to the flag of the United
                        States in July, 1873, by a military force in the service of Honduras.</p>
                    <p>In your No. 107<note n="*" xml:id="d88fn1">See <ref target="frus1874#pg_142">Foreign Relations for 1874, page 142</ref>.</note> of the 19th of
                        February last you represented that you had expressed to the Honduras
                        government an opinion that this Government might be satisfied with an
                        apology for the acts of the military commander of Honduras, adverted to, in
                        addition to a salute of twenty guns to the consular flag when it was again
                        raised at Omoa, and a decree forever prohibiting that officer from again
                        holding a military or civil office of profit, trust, or honor under that
                        government.</p>
                    <p>The receipt of this dispatch was acknowledged by the Department’s instruction
                        of the 9th of April last, in which you were informed that the satisfaction
                        which you said would be expected, would be sufficient, if honestly and fully
                        rendered. You will demand that accordingly, but need not insist on any
                        pecuniary amends, the material damage to the consulate having, as you say,
                        been inconsiderable.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>HAMILTON FISH.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>