<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 89.Mr. Williamson to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1875v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d93</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">93</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1874-09-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1874-09-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-09-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-09-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="93"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d93">
                <head>No. 89.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williamson</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation in Central America</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-09-09">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 9, 1874</date>. (Received October
                        13.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 233.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that the presidential
                    election which is to take place in Honduras in November next, is beginning to
                    excite attention. The candidates are the present provisional incumbent, Ponciano
                    Leiva, Manual Colindres, and Ramon Midence.</p>
                <p>The election is to be held under the constitution of 1865, which, as reported in
                    my No. 161<note n="*" xml:id="d93fn1">See <ref target="frus1874#pg_167">Foreign
                            Relations for 1874, page 167</ref>.</note> was adopted by the Congress
                    of Honduras as the organic law of that state.</p>
                <p>Of President Leiva I have so often written that it appears unnecessary to say
                    more of his political status than that he appears not to be a partisan, but a
                    moderate man of intelligent and liberal views.</p>
                <p>Colindres is called a reactionist now. He is the person who was proclaimed
                    President of Honduras in August, 1873, at the island of Utilla, by the military
                    party under the charge of Don Henry Palacios.</p>
                <p>He was a warm friend of ex-President Medina, whom, from my information, I would
                    be disposed to call one of the firmest liberals in Central America. He is at
                    present a high official in the administration of President Leiva.</p>
                <p>Ramon Midence is called a liberal. He is, so far as I can learn, without
                    political antecedents of note.</p>
                <p>Leiva appears to be the favorite of the people of Honduras, both on account of
                    his personal popularity and his political professions. He may be defeated by the
                    division of the vote with Colindres—I think not.</p>
                <p>The influence of Guatemala will be covertly, and perhaps openly, thrown against
                    Leiva particularly, and in favor of Midence, the so-styled liberal.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, it is believed in well-informed circles, Leiva will have the
                    cordial and public support of the government of Salvador.</p>
                <p>This election derives additional importance from the fact that it may present the
                    occasion for an open rupture between the governments of Guatemala and
                    Salvador.</p>
                <p>As I stated in my No. 174, there is no doubt, in my mind, the chiefs of the two
                    governments are not in harmony, although publicly they profess to be so.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GEO. WILLIAMSON.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
