<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>163. Intelligence Memorandum</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d163</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">163</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-12-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recAPhAIrM8XS4R2T" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec9i482eX195qnGX" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recfab616ca717a635" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="decolonization" subject="colonialism">Colonialism</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="guerrilla" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrillas</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-12-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="163"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d163">
                <head>163. Intelligence Memorandum<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d163fn1">Source:
                        Johnson Library, National Security File, Country File, Cambodia, Vol. IV,
                        Memos, 10/65–9/67. Secret. Drafted in the Office of Current Intelligence,
                        Directorate of Intelligence.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">OCI No. 2946/65</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-12-01">December 1, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">CAMBODIAʼS FOREIGN POLICY</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The often unfathomable, sometimes senseless and frequently amusing
                        fluctuations which have characterized the day to day conduct of Cambodiaʼs
                        foreign policy over the past 12 years have obscured what, in fact, has been
                        a remarkably coherent and consistent policy. The discrepancy lies in the
                        fact that Cambodiaʼs policy has Prince <persName corresp="#p_SPN1"
                            >Sihanouk</persName> as both its author and chief practitioner. The
                        confusion between style and substance, between neurotic fantasies and
                        logically reasoned arguments, [<hi rend="italic">1 line of source text not
                            declassified</hi>] has put in question the credibility of Cambodiaʼs
                        foreign policy.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The primary motivation of Cambodiaʼs foreign policy is the preservation of
                        Cambodia as a nation state. Although survival is, in the final analysis, the
                        root policy of all nations, the difference is that Cambodia feels that its
                        continued existence is in real and constant jeopardy. In recent years this
                        preoccupation has been in part an expression of <persName corresp="#p_SPN1"
                            >Sihanouk</persName>ʼs emotional response to factors beyond his
                        control—the discrepancy in population and power between Cambodia and its
                        neighbors Thailand and Vietnam—but it also has been based on certain
                        historical facts which no Cambodian nationalist can ignore.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>To <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> and other Cambodians,
                        the key factor in the modern history of the Indochina peninsula has been the
                        unrelenting pressure exerted on Cambodiaʼs territory from Thailand and
                        Vietnam. Other factors, French colonialism and the shadow struggle between
                        the US and Communist China, have been important too. In the final analysis,
                        however, these latter are overlays to the fundamental problem of Vietnamese
                        and Thai imperialism.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>In fighting for its territorial integrity, Cambodia has been handicapped
                        by its relative weakness; it simply cannot match the power of Vietnam and
                        Thailand. The Cambodians therefore have been forced to rely on the less
                        reliable skills of diplomatic maneuver. In the nineteenth century, with its
                        back to the wall, Cambodia called on France to protect it from its more
                        powerful neighbors. The French protectorate, from the Cambodian perspective,
                        was no euphemism. If France exacted a high price for its protection, if its
                        control impinged heavily on Cambodiaʼs sovereignty, that was unfortunate. It
                        was more important that Cambodia be preserved.</item>
                    <pb facs="0404" n="362" xml:id="pg_362"/>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The situation changed in the 1950s. The postwar wave of nationalism which
                        swept Indochina also claimed many young educated Cambodians, including
                            <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>. Cambodia could not
                        continue as a French colony forever. More important, however, was the fact
                        that the power realities in Indochina were changing. To the Cambodians,
                        France was a spent force, and a new constellation would have to be brought
                        into being if Cambodiaʼs integrity was to be preserved.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> is no ideologue, and when he
                        espoused “neutralism” as the right path for Cambodiaʼs foreign policy, it
                        was from practical rather than theoretical considerations. “Neutralism” was
                        a fashionable posture for the newly independent nations in the early fifties
                        and <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> undoubtedly thought it
                        prudent to keep Cambodia in step. More importantly, in its emphasis on
                        diplomatic rather than military solutions to problems, and its emphasis on
                        avoiding entanglement in the cold war, “neutralism” was consonant with
                        Cambodiaʼs traditional position and the realities in Indochina. <persName
                            corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> put his own stamp on “neutralism,”
                        however. As he viewed it, neutrality enabled the small nation to exert a
                        disproportionate amount of influence by playing off one great power against
                        another.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> played this game adroitly
                        for ten years. He managed to keep his relations with the US in good repair,
                        although he felt that the US was involved with Thai and South Vietnamese
                        plotting against his government. At the same time, however, he was slowly
                        improving relations with Communist China. This balance began to be disrupted
                        in the early sixties by the growing strength of the Communists in South
                        Vietnam.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>At some point, perhaps as early as 1961, <persName corresp="#p_SPN1"
                            >Sihanouk</persName> became convinced that the Viet Cong were going to
                        win in South Vietnam. He viewed with alarm what he regarded as US obtuseness
                        to the real situation in South Vietnam and continuing US reliance on the
                        Diem government, which he regarded as doomed to failure. His prescription
                        was negotiation with the guerrillas while their strength was still limited.
                        The object of the negotiations would be to “neutralize” South Vietnam, which
                        in <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>ʼs terms meant to keep
                        Vietnam divided. His persistent calls for a Geneva-type conference from 1962
                        to the present reflect this policy.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Cambodiaʼs swing to the left, underway from at least 1961, became more
                        pronounced in 1963. Phnom Penhʼs relations with the US deteriorated,
                        principally because the US would not support negotiations with the
                        Communists. At the same time <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>
                        was laying the groundwork for what he was coming increasingly to believe was
                        a necessary accommodation with Hanoi and Peking. The problem for <persName
                            corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> was shaping up as one of
                        timing—when the Diem government fell in November.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>The reverberations in Phnom Penh were almost totally unexpected. It is
                        still unclear why <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> acted as
                        he did. The most persuasive <pb facs="0405" n="363" xml:id="pg_363"/> theory
                        is that <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> was frightened by
                        what he regarded as the US-sanctioned murder of Diem, and his most immediate
                        concern was to reduce drastically US presence in Cambodia. <persName
                            corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> may also have calculated that the
                        disruption in Saigon would shorten the time before the Viet Cong victory;
                        hence there would be less time for Cambodiaʼs accommodation. At any rate,
                            <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> renounced US military
                        and economic aid, sent home the 100-man US military advisor contingent and
                        encouraged a cut-back in the size of the US Embassy in Phnom Penh. A
                        17-month period of strained relations ensued which culminated in Cambodiaʼs
                        breaking relations with the US in May 1965.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>One of the problems resulting from the termination of US aid was the
                        necessity of finding an alternate source of military hardware. <persName
                            corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> naturally turned to France, the
                        one country in the West with which Cambodia has maintained good relations,
                        to the Soviet Union, which had already supplied Cambodia with four
                        obsolescent jet fighters, and to its new “number one friend,” Communist
                        China. In late 1964, Peking agreed to supply Cambodia with enough small arms
                        to equip 27,000 men, in effect agreeing to supplant the US as the
                        quartermaster for the Cambodian armed forces. In the past week, Peking has
                        agreed to supply small arms for an additional 10,000 men as well as some
                        antiaircraft weapons and 11 obsolescent planes, including a few jet
                        fighters.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>For <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>, Chinese military aid
                        serves two purposes. It has enabled the Cambodian armed forces to improve
                        its defensive posture along the Thai and South Vietnamese borders. It also
                        underscores, in a material way, Pekingʼs not entirely convincing public
                        promises for “all-out support” if Cambodia is “invaded.” <persName
                            corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> has been willing to pay for
                        Pekingʼs support by taking the Chinese line on a whole series of
                        international issues of secondary interest to Cambodia. He has been far less
                        responsive on matters directly affecting Cambodian interests.</item>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>He took an exceptionally hard line with the North Vietnamese and the Viet
                        Cong, for example, during talks in Peking late last year. When the
                        Communists refused to knuckle under to some of <persName corresp="#p_SPN1"
                            >Sihanouk</persName>ʼs more extravagant demands, the talks broke down.
                        To <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>, the episode was but
                        another example of Vietnamese perfidy, a warning that the Vietnamese,
                        whatever their political persuasion, were a threat to Cambodia. In a
                        remarkable speech in Phnom Penh early this year, at a time when he was
                        hosting the leftist Indochinese Peoples Conference, <persName
                            corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> warned the Cambodian military that
                        “Vietnamese imperialism” of whatever political coloration was the real
                        danger to Cambodia.</item>
                    <label>14.</label>
                    <item>As long as <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> believes that
                        the Viet Cong will win in South Vietnam, and that the US will be forced to
                        negotiate its way out, we can expect Cambodia to hold to its present
                        leftward course. By continuing to call Cambodia “neutral,” however,
                            <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> indicates that he is not
                        yet ready to burn all his bridges. He has already discovered that breaking
                            <pb facs="0406" n="364" xml:id="pg_364"/> relations with the US and
                        curtailing his contacts with the West have severely reduced his room for
                        diplomatic maneuver. There are strong indications that <persName
                            corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> hopes to repair some of the damage
                        by improving Cambodiaʼs relations with Great Britain and Australia. A more
                        fundamental change in Cambodiaʼs course will depend to a great extent on the
                        course of the war in South Vietnam.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
