<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-04-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="233" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d233">
                        <head>233. Memorandum From the Deputy Director for Intelligence of the
                            Central Intelligence Agency (<persName corresp="#p_SB1" type="from">Smith</persName>) to the Presidentʼs Special Assistant (<persName corresp="#p_RWW1" type="to">Rostow</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d233fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                                Security File, Country File, Vietnam, 5E (2)a, 1/68–10/68, Cambodia.
                                No classification marking.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-04-22">April 22, 1968</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Attached in response to your request this morning are copies of two
                            recent memoranda<note n="2" xml:id="d233fn2">No documents were attached.
                                The information memorandum of March 7 was apparently an attachment
                                and its summary is printed as an attachment. (Ibid.) The other
                                attachment was apparently <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>
                                memorandum <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> No. 01939/68, April 4,
                                1968, a more detailed 14-page account of North Vietnamese/Viet Cong
                                use of Cambodia, not printed. (Ibid.)</note> which discuss the
                            increasing evidence that Vietnamese Communists are receiving substantial
                            amounts of military equipment via Southern Cambodia.</p>
                        <p>Joe Alsop has undoubtedly drawn upon <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> sources for his article in todayʼs Washington Post. We
                            believe, however, that his tonnage estimates are too high.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName>
                                    <hi rend="strong">R.J. Smith</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Attachment<note n="3" xml:id="d233fn3">Secret.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-03-07">March 7, 1968</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="strong">Intelligence Memorandum Prepared by the
                                    Directorate of Intelligence</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">RECENT COMMUNIST USES OF CAMBODIAN TERRITORY</p>
                            <p rend="center">Summary</p>
                            <p>The Communists continue to use Cambodian territory for tactical
                                sanctuary, for base areas, for the infiltration of personnel, and as
                                a source <pb facs="0561" n="519" xml:id="pg_519"/> of rice,
                                medicines, and sundry supplies. Communist base areas on the eastern
                                border of Cambodia have continued to expand as the tempo of the war
                                in South Vietnam has increased. We do not believe, however, that the
                                step-up in military activity since the Tet offensive has taxed the
                                capability of the established supply route from North Vietnam via
                                Laos and the trail system along the Cambodian border.</p>
                            <p>There is a growing body of circumstantial evidence, however, that the
                                Communists may have stepped up the acquisition of supplies through
                                southern Cambodia. The appearance of new weaponry in the IV Corps
                                area, along with the heavy expenditure of ammunition in the III and
                                IV Corps areas, point to an increasing likelihood that Cambodia may
                                be used to at least augment the military equipment which is reaching
                                this area over more established routes from North Vietnam via Laos
                                and the trails into South Vietnam.</p>
                            <p>[Here follow the body of the memorandum and a map entitled: “Major
                                Vietnamese Communist Infiltration Routes and Base Areas Along the
                                Cambodian Border.”]</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>