<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-06-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-06-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="273" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d273">
                        <head>273. Memorandum for the Record<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d273fn1">Source: Department of Defense, <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> Official Records, 9510 (1 June 64).
                                Top Secret. The meeting in Honolulu, June 1–2, was primarily to
                                discuss Vietnam and was attended by 55 people including the top
                                civilian and military advisers. This is a record of the Opening
                                Plenary Session of the Honolulu meetings. Certain portions of the
                                plenary session on Vietnam are printed in <ref target="frus1964-68v01#d187">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1964–1968, vol. I,
                                    Document 187</ref>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Honolulu</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-06-01">June 1, 1964</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>[Here follows discussion of South Vietnam and Laos.]</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">C. Thailand</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">1.</hi>
                            </label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Political situation and attitudes:</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName>
                                    expressed the judgment that the Thanom regime in Thailand has
                                    smoothly consolidated its power and is operating well. It is
                                    operating more as a collegial institution than the personally
                                    authoritarian regime of Sarit<note n="2" xml:id="d273fn2">Sarit
                                        Thanarat, Prime Minister of Thailand until his death on
                                        December 8, 1963.</note> ever did. There has been
                                    considerable decentralization, and delegations to the
                                    Ministeries have noticeably speeded up the decision making
                                    process.</p>
                                <p>Contrary to general expectations in December, <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> seems to be clearly in
                                    charge and is publicly deferred to by General Praphat. The
                                    personal and family relationships between these two permit an
                                    intimate behind-the-scene which is obviously effective.</p>
                                <p>The cabinet is still basically unchanged since the original
                                    appointment of Pote Sarasin to the vital post of Minister of
                                    National Development. His public position, his integrity and his
                                    ability are a definite asset.</p>
                                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName> believes
                                    that Praphat has persuaded <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> to make two changes in the Cabinet before
                                    Praphat departs for the U.S. in mid-June for an eye operation at
                                    Walter Reed. One will be the elevation of General Chitti to the
                                    post of Minister of Agriculture and the other will be the
                                    replacement of the present Minister of Industry. Praphat has
                                    concentrated the major portion of his time and energies on
                                    restoring his position and power in the Royal Thai Army from
                                    whose councils he had been systematically excluded by Sarit. In
                                    the Embassyʼs judgment, he has had a fair amount of success.
                                    Dawee, as Deputy Minister of Defense and Chief of Staff Supreme
                                    Command, is playing an increasingly important and useful role in
                                    over-all coordination of military affairs.</p>
                                <p>While coup rumors are endemic, the frequency of their circulation
                                    has been greatly reduced. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName> does not expect this sort of trouble in
                                    the foreseeable future. The most significant substantiation of
                                    this estimate is the confidence displayed by Thanom and Praphat
                                    in <pb facs="0632" n="590" xml:id="pg_590"/> permitting the
                                    latter to be absent 4 to 6 weeks in June and July. It is
                                    therefore expected that the present regime, with occasional
                                    changes in Cabinet portfolio, will continue in control. It is
                                    probable that Thanom will retire in the next two or three years,
                                    perhaps after the promulgation of a new constitution, and that
                                    he will be succeeded by Praphat.</p>
                                <p>The principal internal emphasis of this new regime is on the
                                    economic and social development of Thailand. Although it is
                                    concerned over the increasing amount of domestic resources being
                                    absorbed in these programs, it will continue this emphasis.</p>
                                <p>For the present, the principal ingredient of Thai foreign policy
                                    is its reliance on the <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_TK1">Thanat</persName> communiqué<note n="3" xml:id="d273fn3">Joint statement issued in Washington on March 6, 1962. For
                                        text, see American Foreign Policy: Current Documents, 1962,
                                        pp. 1091–1093.</note> as constituting a virtual defense
                                    alliance with the U.S. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName> has had recent occasion, as have his
                                    predecessors, to remind Washington that this policy—this degree
                                    of commitment—is a very great variant from the whole sweep of
                                    Thai history, of Thai traditions, and basic Thai instincts. In
                                    their relations with world powers they are quite conscious that
                                    they were almost the prototype of the non-aligned, non-committed
                                    nations. While they had to deliver large parts of modern Laos
                                    and Cambodia to the French and parts of modern Malaysia and
                                    Burma to the British, they nevertheless maintained their
                                    independence. They have a certain confidence that their old
                                    skills are still present and that if required, they would be
                                    able to repeat the process again.</p>
                                <p>They would vastly prefer to continue to maintain their reliance
                                    on the U.S. Yet it is now quite clear that certain questions are
                                    being posed concerning the effect on Thailandʼs vital interests
                                    on the totality of Thailandʼs open commitment to the U.S.</p>
                                <p>These questions do not involve qualms about our military
                                    capacity. Through many channels they are sure not only that our
                                    nuclear power is overwhelming, but also that our conventional
                                    military power has been greatly strengthened over the past three
                                    years. They know it is now a multi-faceted, flexible, pliant
                                    instrument of U.S. National Policy permitting the U.S. to use it
                                    if desired in a coldly pin-pointed way, in an almost surgically
                                    precise way, to achieve any specific objective within a vast
                                    spectrum.</p>
                                <p>They recognize that our conventional military power has only
                                    recently provided us with this new and flexible capacity. On the
                                    matter of our military capacity, they seem to have two basic
                                    questions: (1) whether we have yet developed an effective common
                                    doctrine on its use, and (2) whether the Communist Chinese
                                    believe we have the will to use it. Both of these questions
                                    depend on their analysis of our present basic attitudes towards
                                    Southeast Asia. This analysis is not yet completed. They are not
                                        <pb facs="0633" n="591" xml:id="pg_591"/> yet certain
                                    whether we are really prepared to use force to achieve our
                                    policy aims in Southeast Asia. They are concerned whether we
                                    will merely threaten to do so, while our real intent is to seek
                                    only the best political solution we are able to negotiate. If
                                    they become convinced that we will use force if necessary as the
                                    underlying sanction of our policy, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName> has no doubt of their
                                    complete cooperation and their willingness to go with us all the
                                    way. But until they are certain that we have the will to use
                                    such force as appears appropriate, they will wait to see how the
                                    situation unfolds. They will not this time be willing to use
                                    their real estate as an American base without a clear view of
                                    the end of the road. They will demand advanced consultation, and
                                    if this is not forthcoming, the very large degree of cooperation
                                    which now exists will be seriously jeopardized.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">2.</hi>
                            </label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Military Appraisal:</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> asked
                                    whether the Thai Government was prepared to put forces into Laos
                                    to counter a PL advance. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName> said that this subject was currently
                                    under serious consideration in Bangkok. Five companies had
                                    already been deployed to the northern border area and plans for
                                    their augmentation are being prepared. There appears to be a new
                                    philosophy growing within the Thai Armed Forces to the effect
                                    that they can and should deploy their own forces to meet their
                                    own security requirements without necessarily waiting for the
                                    deployment of American troops in advance.</p>
                                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> asked Adm
                                    Felt what he thought of the capability of the Thai forces to
                                    offer material help to Souvanna Phouma. Adm Felt said that this
                                    report that the Thaiʼs were considering putting forces across
                                    the Mekong was new to him. Personally he doubted that they would
                                    be prepared to go this far unless U.S. forces accompanied them.
                                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> asked
                                    Adm Felt how many ground forces he thought would be required to
                                    give any meaningful support to Souvannaʼs government. Adm Felt
                                    replied that within the context of the present situation
                                    somewhere between 2 and 3 divisions would be needed.</p>
                                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName>
                                    explained that the Thai military do not believe that the mere
                                    crossing of the Mekong will bring them into extensive contact
                                    with the Pathet Lao. Their current thinking seems to be that
                                    they could make such a military move without obtaining prior
                                    U.S. concurrence and still be able to count on the over-all
                                    protection of the U.S. nuclear umbrella should this action
                                    provoke a major Communist attack against Thailand. After
                                    discussing the time and space factor involved, the general
                                    conclusion was that while the Thai might occupy Lao towns on the
                                    Mekong, a major move of Thai forces deep into Laos was
                                    unlikely.</p>
                                <p>Adm Felt pointed out that it has always been Thai policy to hold
                                    a division in reserve to protect Bangkok. As far as Thailandʼs
                                    national interest in Laos goes, Adm Felt stated that his
                                    conversations with Thai military <pb facs="0634" n="592" xml:id="pg_592"/> leaders indicated they were primarily
                                    concerned with re-occupying the former Thai territory lying in
                                    Laos to the west of the Mekong River. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName> said both of these
                                    observations were undoubtedly true under Saritʼs regime, but
                                    that Thanom had different ideas.</p>
                                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>
                                    suggested that we need closer joint U.S.-Thai planning for the
                                    movement of military forces into the key towns in the Mekong
                                    valley should such deployments become necessary. Ambassador
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName> agreed and
                                    said he would take the matter up with <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> when Washington indicated it was
                                    ready.</p>
                                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> asked for an
                                    estimate of the fighting qualities of the Thai army. Adm Felt
                                    said that no one really knew how effective they would be in
                                    combat. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName>
                                    drew attention to the fact that the Thai unit that fought in
                                    Korea under the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> flag acquitted
                                    itself very well in battle. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWE1">Colby</persName> added that the Thai officers provided the
                                    leadership element for the Meo tribesmen fighting behind the
                                    Communist lines in Laos. In this capacity, they have shown high
                                    qualities of initiative and aggressive leadership. General
                                        <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> indicated
                                    that the general estimate was that the Thais could handle the PL
                                    all right but there was some doubt as to whether they could face
                                    up to a trained North Vietnamese military force. Secretary
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> stated that
                                    his impression was that the Thai have a very limited military
                                    capability to meet any major combined Communist attack. Adm Felt
                                    supported this conclusion. As to the combat air capability, he
                                    cited the low caliber of senior leadership in the Thai Air
                                    Force.</p>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>[Here follows discussion of North Vietnam.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>