<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>312. Telegram From the Ambassador to Thailand (Martin) to the Deputy Under
                    Secretary of State for Political Affairs () to the Deputy Under Secretary of
                    State for Political Affairs (Johnson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d312</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">312</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-05-07T07:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-05-07T07:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recJwYAJf2vdRiALq" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85039539"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Mobility</term>
                    <term ref="recRywIrZWsI9yUJ7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2007010556"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Helicopter</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-05-07T07:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-05-07T07:30:00-05:00" n="312"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d312">
                <head>312. Telegram From the Ambassador to Thailand (<persName corresp="#p_MGA1"
                        type="from">Martin</persName>) to the Deputy Under Secretary of State for
                    Political Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_JLB1" type="to"
                        >Johnson</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d312fn1">Source:
                        Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27
                        THAI. Secret; Eyes Only. [<hi rend="italic">text not
                        declassified</hi>]</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Bangkok</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1966-05-07T12:30:00+00:00">May 7, 1966, 1230Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>6327. Eyes only Under Secretary Johnson.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>In your considerations today<note n="2" xml:id="d312fn2">Apparent
                            reference to a meeting which eventually took place on May 17. See <ref
                                target="#d313fn2">footnote 2, Document 313</ref>.</note> of some of
                        the issues which will be vital to the direction Thai policy takes in the
                        future, I venture to place before <pb facs="0713" n="671" xml:id="pg_671"/>
                        you and the Secretary the following observations. Although they contain
                        little not already reported, perhaps they will make small contribution in
                        cutting through the many irrelevancies to the root of the matter.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>My primary immediate concern is rotary air lift for Thai
                        counter-insurgency forces. This problem divides itself into these primary
                        segments. <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>Provision of 10 CH34ʼs already programmed and funded in <gloss
                                    target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 66 Thai <gloss target="#t_MAP1"
                                    >MAP</gloss>. <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item>Last summer, I requested and received authority to
                                        announce to Thai basic level and major investment hardware
                                        items. I told Thai of basic level but delayed announcement
                                        hardware items until Stilwell could review program. He did
                                        and these 10 CH34ʼs were significant item in lists he
                                        presented to Thai. Upon receipt <gloss target="#t_OSD1"
                                            >OSD</gloss> funding approval, Thai were notified as we
                                        were authorized to do.</item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item>In August I frankly told <persName corresp="#p_TK2"
                                            >Thanom</persName> US dissatisfied with performance
                                            <gloss target="#t_RTAF1">RTAF</gloss> and we saw little
                                        chance improvement under Marshal Boonchoo. I was told on my
                                        return, <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> called
                                        him in and told him he must go. After emotional scene and
                                        copious tears, <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName>
                                        gave him one more chance. Boonchoo has been on the wagon
                                        ever since. Drunk or sober he is not exactly the greatest
                                        leader that ever lived. But the change did snap <gloss
                                            target="#t_RTAF1">RTAF</gloss> out of doldrums and all
                                        qualified professional observers attest to the dramatic
                                        improvement.</item>
                                    <label>(3)</label>
                                    <item>Deficiencies in rotary air lift capability were
                                        dramatically impressed on Thai in Phu Phan range operation
                                        at turn of year. Thai do not—and I repeat with emphasis—do
                                        not want US directly involved in insurgency operations any
                                        more than is absolutely essential. They have scrapped all
                                        precedent to produce maximum number pilot trainees for both
                                        US and local training. The 10 CH34ʼs which have been
                                        committed by US in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 66 are
                                        essential for this training and no juggling of statistics
                                        across the river can obscure this fact. Additional to these
                                        critical practical considerations is the rather simple
                                        matter of the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> honoring
                                        its promises. As you know, I cleaned up all the old broken
                                        promises which had accumulated after your departure and
                                        before my arrival, raised enough hell with <gloss
                                            target="#t_JUSMAG1">JUSMAG</gloss> to insure we promised
                                        absolutely nothing we were not absolutely sure we could
                                        deliver. In this specific case, I made very clear point with
                                        Pentagon that if I was given authority I requested to
                                        announce these items to Thai, I must have absolute assurance
                                        the commitments would be meticulously honored. This just
                                        must be done.</item>
                                    <label>(4)</label>
                                    <item>The only remaining problem is the source. I understand
                                        reluctance to withdraw anything more from Europe. But there
                                        is a simple solution—borrow if necessary from <gloss
                                            target="#t_SVN2">SVN</gloss>. I know there is a
                                        statistical shortage in CH34 requirements. But
                                        “requirements” are regarded much <pb facs="0714" n="672"
                                            xml:id="pg_672"/> more realistically in the field. Westy
                                        understands the urgent necessity here, and I am sure out of
                                        the 2200 he has he will let me have ten.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>
                                <p>(1) The second segment of this problem is the problem between now
                                    and January when Thai will be able to carry major burden
                                    themselves. In 27 April letter from Bill Bundy he said: “Our
                                    delay and repeated requests for additional information have, I
                                    am sorry to say, been due in part to the negative reactions
                                    triggered in many quarters by the very fact that your latest
                                    requests came to Washington in such dramatic fashion, and
                                    carried to many people here the flavor that high-level visitors
                                    had been subjected to a heavy assault by the Thai which seemed
                                    to go beyond realistic needs as we saw them”.</p>
                                <p>(2) I would have thought a few words from him could have
                                    dissipated any such reaction. As you and the Secretary recall
                                    Honolulu was a rather dramatic affair which caused certain
                                    concerns here. I cabled Secretary at Honolulu asking if you
                                    might come here to put conference in proper perspective. (In
                                    addition to official reasons Jennifer and I would have both been
                                    delighted to see you.) Instead of you alone, I got instead the
                                    Vice-President, <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MLH1">Marks</persName>, Valenti, Hand,
                                    and <persName corresp="#p_CCL1">Cooper</persName> accompanied by
                                    50-odd representatives of news media.</p>
                                <p>(3) Their arrival coincided with reappraisal of Thai after Phou
                                    Phan sweep (2A3 above). Rotary lift to multiply effectiveness of
                                    scarce manpower by greater mobility was obviously first
                                    priority. Thai have great and growing disinclination to have US
                                    directly involved. But there is simply no other way to keep
                                    pressure on insurgents in interim until Thai pilots and choppers
                                    available without asking for our assistance in unmarked
                                    helicopters. They did so, not stridently or with suggestion of
                                    quid pro quo, but with seriousness and dignity and quiet closing
                                    of subject by <persName corresp="#p_TK1">Thanat</persName>: “We
                                    are not trying to put our hands in your pocket. We simply want
                                    to know whether you can give us this assistance we rather
                                    desperately need at the moment.” While I outrank the
                                    Vice-President here and did the honors including the toast to
                                    the King, etc. I do not know that I should have over-ruled his
                                    instructions to address his report to the President. I thought I
                                    was skating on rather thin ice when I had message sent through
                                    State rather than Army <gloss target="#t_SS1">SS</gloss>
                                    channels as directed thinking Ben Read would do what seemed
                                    appropriate on routing. In any event, although I could do very
                                    little to curtail “dramatics” inherent in visit, I do not really
                                    see what this has to do with merits of objective judgment on
                                    realistic needs. Recent reporting seems to conclusively
                                    establish that even with complete fulfillment of <gloss
                                        target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> recommendation we could still
                                    effectively utilize more.</p>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>In addition to “dramatics” and “need”, I understand it is argued that this
                        interim help would be too visible. This is not the case. From Udorn we are
                        now dispatching all manner of helicopter lift. <gloss target="#t_USAF1"
                            >USAF</gloss> unmarked rescue craft, Air America support operations for
                        Laos, <gloss target="#t_USAF1">USAF</gloss>
                        <pb facs="0715" n="673" xml:id="pg_673"/> support for certain <gloss
                            target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SOG1">SOG</gloss>
                        operations with which you are familiar. This is simply not a problem.
                        Another factor allegedly is that providing this help will slow down Thai
                        efforts to help themselves. The exact contrary is true. I would suppose the
                        “realists” argue against additional commitment. With enormity of US air
                        strength in N.E., I would think we should rather be thinking in terms of
                        protecting that investment by assisting in every way possible the
                        acceleration on Thai momentum in their campaign to contain and eliminate
                        subversion now.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>I am well aware that we are going through the periodic exercise of
                        “failure scenarios” and the climate of defeatism. The Secretary may remember
                        the early days in G–2 when Col. Truman Smith who had been our military
                        attache in Berlin simply refused to credit the fact that the Russians were
                        beginning to chop up some of his former clients panzer armies. The analogy
                        is not exact but I sometimes fear we become so captivated with the logic of
                        this type of scenario, that we overlook hard objective facts that might
                        disturb the even flow of the logic.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I do not for a moment discount the hard days ahead but I believe we are on
                        the verge of breaking the back of the Communists capability to mount or
                        sustain regimental or battalion sized engagements. By this time next year we
                        could be very well back at Geneva or, far preferably, we will have seen
                        repetition of Greek and Malaysian pattern where hostilities gradually
                        tapered off into a manageable police problem.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>It seems to me that it would be a very grave error to lose the momentum we
                        have so painstakingly built up here. For reasons which as far as I can see
                        are either wholly irrelevant or based on ancient misinformation.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>I have carried this as far as I can alone, I have given all the
                        information we have. I believe it should permit favorable decision to be
                        made on basis of objective evaluation of all factors involved. I hope that
                        decision will be made by the Secretary, or if this not possible, that it
                        will be taken to the President.<note n="3" xml:id="d312fn3">Printed from an
                            unsigned copy.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
