<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-10-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-10-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="32" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d32">
                        <head>32. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of Defense for
                            International Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_WPC1" type="from">Warnke</persName>) to the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                                (<persName corresp="#p_WGEG1" type="to">Wheeler</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d32fn1">Source: Washington National
                                Records Center, RG 330, <gloss target="#t_OASDISA1">OASD/ISA</gloss>
                                Files: FRC 71 A 4919, 381 Malaysia, 1967. Top Secret. Drafted by
                                Nuechterlein on October 12.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">I–36036/67</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-10-13">October 13, 1967</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Australian Request for Consultations Regarding Future Security
                                Arrangements in Malaysia/Singapore</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>On 10 October 1967 the Australian Minister for External Affairs,
                                <persName corresp="#p_HPMC1">Paul Hasluck</persName>, called on the
                            Secretary of Defense<note n="2" xml:id="d32fn2">See <ref target="#d30">Document 30</ref>.</note> and presented him with a paper
                            entitled “Memorandum on the Defence of Malaysia” (copy enclosed). This
                            document has also been given to the Secretary of State. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPMC1">Hasluck</persName> stated that Prime Minister
                                <persName corresp="#p_HHE1">Holt</persName> wished to make a
                            statement in Parliament during the next four to eight weeks on his
                            governmentʼs intentions regarding Australian forces in Malaysia and
                            Singapore, following the British withdrawal. Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_HHE1">Holt</persName> desires to know, before making
                            this statement, to what extent the United States would be prepared to
                            support Australia if it decides to retain its military presence in this
                            area after the British depart.</p>
                        <pb facs="0121" n="79" xml:id="pg_79"/>
                        <p>In order that the Secretary of State and the Secretary of Defense may be
                            in a position to respond to the Australian Governmentʼs request for
                            consultations on this matter, it is requested that the Joint Chiefs of
                            Staff provide the Secretary of Defense with their views and
                            recommendations concerning strategic/military implications of the
                            Australian Foreign Ministerʼs memorandum. In formulating these
                            recommendations, it is requested that attention be given to the
                            following additional questions: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>What is the strategic importance of the Malacca Strait area to
                                    the United States?</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>What are the principal advantages and disadvantages, from a
                                    military point of view, of the U.S. encouraging Australia and
                                    New Zealand to assume primary responsibility for the security of
                                    Malaysia and Singapore after the British withdraw?</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>To what extent could the U.S. military services make use of
                                    military facilities in Singapore and Malaysia, if these
                                    facilities were under Australian/New Zealand control, following
                                    the British withdrawal, and if it were determined to be in the
                                    U.S. interest to make use of such facilities?</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>In view of the Australian Ministerʼs request to the Secretary that this
                            matter be “closely held”, it is requested that special care be taken to
                            restrict dissemination of the enclosed memorandum. The views of the
                            Joint Chiefs of Staff are desired by 6 November 1967.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WPC1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Paul C. Warnke</hi>
                                </persName><note n="3" xml:id="d32fn3">Printed from a copy that
                                    indicates <persName corresp="#p_WPC1">Warnke</persName> signed
                                    the original.</note>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Attachment</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-10-09">October 9,
                                1967</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="strong">Memorandum on the Defence of Malaysia by the
                                    Australian Minister for External Affairs</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">A</p>
                            <p>Regional security needs to be a total security stretching from Korea
                                to the Indian Ocean. Hitherto the United Statesʼ guarantees have
                                formed a line as far as Thailand and the British have guaranteed the
                                security of Malaysia and Singapore.</p>
                            <pb facs="0122" n="80" xml:id="pg_80"/>
                            <p>The new situation with which we have to deal has two different
                                timetables: <list>
                                    <label>(a)</label>
                                    <item>Before and after the total British withdrawal in the
                                        mid-seventies.</item>
                                    <label>(b)</label>
                                    <item>Before and after the end of hostilities in Vietnam.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>We do not know whether these two timetables will coincide or whether
                                we have to make suppositions about further variations on them.</p>
                            <p>Broadly, we can talk of the “short-term” problem and the “long-term”
                                problem in Malaysia and Singapore but these phrases at present can
                                mean little more than “in the next few years” (say four, five or
                                six) and “afterwards”.</p>
                            <p rend="center">B</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">In the short-term</hi> the military need in
                                Malaysia and Singapore may not be great and no <hi rend="italic">immediate</hi> threat from outside (except possibly insurgency
                                from the Communist remnant in southern Thailand) can be seen. But
                                the argument for a continuing Australian presence in Malaysia is
                                strong.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>(a)</label>
                                <item>Malaysia and Singapore expect something from us.</item>
                                <label>(b)</label>
                                <item>Morale, both in these countries and surrounding countries,
                                    needs to be maintained.</item>
                                <label>(c)</label>
                                <item>A continuing presence may assist the effective development of
                                    self-defence capacity by Malaysia and Singapore.</item>
                                <label>(d)</label>
                                <item>Once we went out we would probably be out for good and it
                                    would certainly be harder to get back in the event of an
                                    emergency.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center">C</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">In the long-term</hi> the general case for
                                maintaining a presence in Malaysia is the same as the case for
                                maintaining a guaranteed security in other parts of the region and
                                the one cannot be separated from the other. It would be hard for us
                                to stay in Malaysia as the only white-faced troops on the mainland
                                and it would be equally hard for the United States to stay in other
                                parts of Asia, even though the need existed, if we had pulled out of
                                Malaysia.</p>
                            <p>The decisions both our governments make on any phase of regional
                                security are intertwined. At this stage we seek consultation. We
                                need understanding rather than commitments but, without these
                                necessary understandings at this stage, difficulties could
                                arise.</p>
                            <p rend="center">D</p>
                            <p>Among the questions we raise for discussion are the following: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Australia believes it is important for us to stay in
                                        Malaysia, but we certainly are unable to take over British
                                        responsibility or to replace Britain. <pb facs="0123" n="81" xml:id="pg_81"/> We can only develop our own role (side
                                        by side, we hope, with New Zealand) up to the limits of our
                                        capacity, having regard to other commitments. What is to be
                                        that role? Does the United States agree that we should
                                        develop such a role?</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Australia has already decided and announced a decision to
                                        give defence aid of $20 million (Australian) to encourage
                                        the development of Malaysian and Singapore defence over the
                                        next three years ($16 million to Malaysia and $4 million to
                                        Singapore). What else will be available (e.g. from Britain)
                                        either for economic assistance or for defence?</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Australia has not yet made a final decision on its own
                                        military presence but the scale of this support will
                                        probably be of the same order as the present forces (a
                                        battalion, plus an <gloss target="#t_AA1">A/A</gloss>
                                        battery, plus some aircraft and a naval presence). New
                                        Zealand also has not made a decision but the indications are
                                        that their battalion, which has already been drawn upon for
                                        the Vietnam contingent, may be further reduced. In the
                                        short-term is this sufficient?</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>In the event of the need for any build-up of forces or
                                        movement and supply of larger numbers of forces, problems of
                                        logistic support may arise. Hitherto there has been some
                                        dependence on the British. Will there be a need for other
                                        logistic support?</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>In the event of hostilities or (in prospect of an
                                        increased threat) in the event of building up and movement
                                        of forces to meet such a threat, the question of the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> commitment will arise.
                                        It has been our tacit understanding that Australia should
                                        not place herself in positions in which the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> commitment might be
                                        involved without consulting the United States and that the
                                        United States will indicate its own views of how the
                                        commitment applies. Do we need to have further
                                        understandings about the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> commitment if Australia and New Zealand
                                        stay in Malaysia? Both of our countries have political
                                        difficulties to face. When the Australian Prime Minister
                                        announced an intention to stay in Malaysia he would be
                                        likely to meet questions about the position under <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>. On the other hand, at
                                        the present juncture, there would be difficulties for the
                                        United States Administration in Congress if it were to
                                        declare another commitment overseas. Can we consult on
                                        finding a suitable formula to express our understanding? The
                                        Australian Government would want to be able to reassure
                                        Parliament that in entering into commitments we had full
                                        understanding from the United States Government.</item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>The Malaysians and the Singaporeans may seek some
                                        assurance or guarantees from us or set conditions on our
                                        continued presence in their territory. Our presence there
                                        now is only covered by a letter from the Australian
                                        Government associating itself with the Anglo-Malaysian
                                        Defence Agreement. (This will give a legal basis to our
                                        presence there until about 1970.) At present, with most of
                                        our own forces engaged in <pb facs="0124" n="82" xml:id="pg_82"/> Vietnam, it would be hard for Australia
                                        to give any assurances or guarantees that relied for
                                        performance on our own resources.</item>
                                    <label>7.</label>
                                    <item>In any arrangement made with Malaysia and Singapore for
                                        retaining our forces there we would certainly hope to be
                                        able to commit the same forces to <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> plans in Thailand without forfeiting the
                                        right to return.</item>
                                    <label>8.</label>
                                    <item>The matters mentioned in paragraphs 6 and 7 have been
                                        brought under notice at this stage because they may be
                                        raised in the five-power (or four-power) talks the <persName corresp="#p_TAR1">Tunku</persName> has proposed to the
                                        United Kingdom, Australia, New Zealand and Singapore. The
                                        Australian Government is still examining questions that will
                                        arise if any proposal is made for a defence agreement with
                                        us, but one consideration that weighs with us is that, at
                                        this stage, while we want to stay in Malaysia we should keep
                                        open our options for the future. Has the United States any
                                        comments to make on such a subject?</item>
                                    <label>9.</label>
                                    <item>In all matters relating to defence aid to Malaysia we have
                                        the current diplomatic problem of handling Indonesia. We
                                        want to maintain good relations; we do not want to alarm
                                        them or give an impression that we are arming Malaysia
                                        against them; and we hope that they would see any decision
                                        as a necessary part of the answer to Chinese expansion. We
                                        would also wish to build a road towards future co-operation
                                        with Indonesia for mutual security, even though the
                                        realisation of that hope may at present seem remote. If our
                                        hopes that Indonesia will follow peaceful courses are not
                                        realised we need to have some defensive or deterrent
                                        capacity.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>In summary we want: <list>
                                    <label>(a)</label>
                                    <item>As much British defence effort in the East as can be
                                        contrived—but we are not optimistic.</item>
                                    <label>(b)</label>
                                    <item>Effective Malaysian and Singaporean self-defence, as early
                                        as possible. This [portion of text missing] Malaysia and
                                        Singapore. Our confidence is qualified by many
                                        doubts.</item>
                                    <label>(c)</label>
                                    <item>To maintain the credibility of <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>
                                        <list>
                                            <label>(i)</label>
                                            <item>to reassure Thailand;</item>
                                            <label>(ii)</label>
                                            <item>to give U.S. President the freedom of action that
                                                a treaty gives;</item>
                                            <label>(iii)</label>
                                            <item>to give ourselves a legal basis for being in
                                                Asia.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>(d)</label>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>To keep <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> alive as
                                            the principal guarantee of Australiaʼs own security.</p>
                                        <p>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Hence</hi>
                                        </p>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>(e)</label>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>The closest possible understanding with U.S.A. on all
                                            matters affecting a continued American interest and
                                            presence in the region.</p>
                                        <p>
                                            <hi rend="italic">We need to know:</hi>
                                            <list>
                                                <label>(a)</label>
                                                <item>More details about British intentions, plans
                                                  and <hi rend="italic">capacity</hi> in respect of
                                                  <pb facs="0125" n="83" xml:id="pg_83"/>
                                                  <list>
                                                  <label>(i)</label>
                                                  <item>the run down in Malaysia and
                                                  Singapore;</item>
                                                  <label>(ii)</label>
                                                  <item>aid to Malaysia and Singapore as
                                                  promised;</item>
                                                  <label>(iii)</label>
                                                  <item>the honouring of their commitments both
                                                  under <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> and
                                                  the Anglo-Malaysian Defence Agreement.</item>
                                                  </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <label>(b)</label>
                                                <item>More specific information about Malaysian and
                                                  Singapore proposals in respect of <list>
                                                  <label>(i)</label>
                                                  <item>the relationships to each other;</item>
                                                  <label>(ii)</label>
                                                  <item>their self-defence preparations;</item>
                                                  <label>(iii)</label>
                                                  <item>their willingness to give some sort of legal
                                                  basis to our own defence and</item>
                                                  <label>(iv)</label>
                                                  <item>their attitudes to the U.S.A.</item>
                                                  </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <label>(c)</label>
                                                <item>Further indications of American thinking both
                                                  in the period before the ending of hostilities in
                                                  Vietnam and after the ending of hostilities,
                                                  recognising of course that what happens after that
                                                  point of time depends on the way in which
                                                  hostilities end.</item>
                                            </list>
                                        </p>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Throughout all these discussions there arises the question of the
                                timing of successive moves.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>