<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>327. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    Thailand</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d327</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">327</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-10-10T19:49:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-10-10T19:49:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec_world_war_ii" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="world-war-ii" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148273" lcsh-match="exact">World War II</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-10-10T19:49:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-10-10T19:49:00-05:00" n="327"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d327">
                <head>327. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in Thailand</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d327fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 THAI. Secret; Immediate; <gloss
                            target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_PLG1"
                            >Pickering</persName> and approved by Bundy. Bundy prepared a briefing
                        memorandum for <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> for this meeting
                        with <persName corresp="#p_PS1">Pote Sarasin</persName>, October 10. (Ibid.,
                            <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> THAI–US)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1966-10-10T20:49:00-04:00">October 10, 1966, 8:49 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>63401. 1. Following is report of main points of bilateral discussion October 10
                    between Secretary and Minister <persName corresp="#p_PS1">Pote
                        Sarasin</persName> held prior to Secretaryʼs luncheon for Pote. They are
                    uncleared, <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss> only, <gloss target="#t_Noforn1"
                        >Noforn</gloss>, subject to revision upon review.</p>
                <p>2. Pote said <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> was such a
                    well-known name in Thailand because of the <persName corresp="#p_FJW1"
                        >Fulbright</persName> Scholarships and his Chairmanship of the Foreign
                    Relations Committee that his statements about Thailand took on special
                    importance. He felt strongly that the President or the Secretary should during
                    their visit to Bangkok make a statement explicitly divorcing the US Government
                    from the <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> position on Thailand.
                    Secretary said he thought Manila conference and Presidentʼs visit to Thailand
                    would be facts which would make this completely clear. Pote agreed but said they
                    badly need something on the record directly addressed to the point. Secretary
                    cautioned that such a statement might simply build up the importance of original
                        <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> statements and could result
                    in his making new ones. Pote said he hoped some formula could be worked out
                    which made it clear that, while the Senator was of course entitled to hold
                    dissenting views, the US Government did not share them. The Secretary said we
                    would think about possible ways to deal with this one.</p>
                <p>3. Pote asked why <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> had singled
                    Thailand out. The Secretary said that <persName corresp="#p_FJW1"
                        >Fulbright</persName> was a born dissenter, and that his remarks on Thailand
                    should be viewed as part of his general objection to our Vietnam policy.</p>
                <p>4. Pote then turned to question of some restatement of our commitment. Such
                    restatement should a) note that Thailand would continue to provide facilities
                    and support to meet aggression, and that while this entailed some additional
                    risks for Thailand of a Chinese Communist attack, the US would in that case come
                    to Thailandʼs support, and b) make it clear that the commitment would apply even
                    in the unlikely event of a change some years hence to an administration which
                    wanted to pull out of Southeast Asia. He said no treaty or formal agreement was
                    needed, but some written reassurance was.</p>
                <p>5. The Secretary said he wished to be very frank on two points. First, he said he
                    simply could not understand how anyone could question the American commitment
                    when we had not failed to fill any commitment <pb facs="0758" n="716"
                        xml:id="pg_716"/> since 1945 and when we are suffering 100 casualties per
                    week in Southeast Asia and had suffered 180 thousand casualties keeping
                    commitments since the end of World War II. Secondly, he said that the Thai
                    should not try to use an international instrument to solve a US domestic
                    problem. They should leave that to us.</p>
                <p>6. The Secretary then said that the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>
                    Treaty and the joint resolution of August 1964 said more than any document which
                    we could possibly add to the record at this time. He emphasized that the Treaty
                    commitment was a national commitment, entered into by the Eisenhower
                    administration and observed by the Kennedy and Johnson administrations. With
                    reference to the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> Treaty, Pote mentioned
                    the difference between the commitment it contained and that in the <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Treaty. The Secretary said that as Secretary
                    Dulles had explained at the time the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>
                    Treaty was ratified, the practical difference between these formulas was not
                    substantial. Pote said that the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> Treaty
                    did not require an automatic US reaction. The Secretary observed that the Thai,
                    because of positions taken by the French and others, had sometimes shown a
                    tendency to downgrade <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>. He said this was
                    a serious mistake since <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> provides the
                    Constitutional basis for what we are doing in Southeast Asia today. He said the
                    undermining of <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>ʼs standing had been done
                    by the Thai, not the US.</p>
                <p>7. On the question of committing a successor government, the Secretary said that
                    it was not possible to deal with this problem with a piece of paper, that if a
                    successor government either in Thailand or in the United States took a different
                    view of the situation, the paper would have no effect. Pote did not dispute this
                    but continued to argue that if a future administration were to leave Thailand in
                    the lurch the leadership of Thailand wanted to be sure that it could show it had
                    done everything possible to commit the US to its defense. He said that unless
                    this unlikely event transpired, the reiteration of the commitment need not ever
                    be made public.</p>
                <p>8. The Secretary said he was not saying “no” to Pote, but he did want to be sure
                    that Pote understood all the implications of such a statement which could be
                    regarded as certifying lack of confidence. Pote said there was absolutely no
                    question about Thai confidence in the present administration. He felt that since
                    the increased risks entailed by permitting US planes to use Thai bases had led
                    to concern in Thailand that the US should be prepared to reiterate the
                    commitment. He emphasized that no addition to the commitment was needed—merely a
                    reiteration.</p>
                <p>9. The Secretary asked whether the concern in Thailand would decrease if we
                    reduced the level of our forces there. Pote said “no”, that on the contrary the
                    more we have there the more secure they felt.</p>
                <p>10. The Secretary concluded by saying that he understood Poteʼs point of view,
                    that we would think about it further, but he wanted to be <pb facs="0759"
                        n="717" xml:id="pg_717"/> completely certain that we did not take an action
                    showing lack of confidence. Pote said he understood and that he would regard the
                    conversation as completely confidential between himself and the Secretary.</p>
                <p>11. Conversation, while somewhat intense, was friendly and cordial throughout, as
                    was luncheon which followed.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
