<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-05-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-05-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="37" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d37">
                        <head>37. Memorandum From the Presidentʼs Special Assistant (<persName corresp="#p_RWW1" type="from">Rostow</persName>) to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_JLB1" type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d37fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                                Security File, Country File, Australia, Visit of Prime Minister
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName>, May 27–28, 1968.
                                Secret. There is an indication on the source text that the President
                                saw the memorandum.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-05-25">May 25, 1968</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Visit of Australian Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> May 27–28</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Attached is a memorandum from Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> and the briefing book on this visit.<note n="2" xml:id="d37fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>ʼs May 24 memorandum to
                                the President is ibid., and the Department of State copy is in
                                Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 AUSTL. The briefing book was attached to a May 2
                                memorandum from Read to <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName>, ibid.</note>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0135" n="93" xml:id="pg_93"/>
                        <p>I passed on to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WJK1">Waller</persName>
                            your hope that <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> would
                            attend the <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> luncheon, and your
                            intention to find a way to give the visit a tone of particular
                            cordiality. As the schedule has shaped up, it may be rather difficult to
                            do this. Your second meeting with <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> is taking place at 11:30 a.m. on Tuesday. It
                            cannot be a long visit because <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> is due at the National Press Club at 12:15. You
                            may have your own plan for giving the visit a public note of unusual
                            cordiality, but if you want suggestions I have three, in ascending order
                            of effectiveness.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>You could “spontaneously” accompany <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> to the luncheon at the State Department
                                following your first meeting with him on Monday. This is not a
                                public luncheon but your departure from the schedule would become
                                known and attract some public comment.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>You could “spontaneously” accompany <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> to his speech at the National Press Club on
                                Tuesday, introducing him with some warm words. This would, of
                                course, get heavy press coverage.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>If you go through with your tentative plans to go to the Ranch on
                                Wednesday, you could have <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> as a weekend guest. As it now stands,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> is due to start
                                back to Australia on Friday afternoon after a heavy schedule in New
                                York. He could instead fly to the Ranch, spend the weekend with you,
                                and catch an Australian airline flight from San Francisco on Sunday,
                                June 2, at 8:00 p.m. This, of course, would be by far the most
                                effective way of dramatizing your special regard for
                                Australia.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> will have three main
                            concerns: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Our political situation and its implications
                                        for our Asia policy</hi>. I suggest you review the situation
                                    fully, stressing that the facts do not warrant a conclusion that
                                    the U.S. is about to retreat from Asia.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <p>
                                        <hi rend="italic">The situation in Vietnam and Paris</hi>.
                                        He will expect a full exchange and has been very sensitive
                                        in the past about the need for full and prior consultation
                                        before we take any new departures. He will want to hear your
                                        thoughts about what to do if the talks continue to be
                                        unproductive, and your plans in regard to the bombing pause
                                        under the various contingencies.</p>
                                    <p>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> has publicly
                                        ruled out any increases in Australian forces in Vietnam,
                                        barring some major change in the situation. (The Australians
                                        have about 8,000 men—three infantry battalions, an artillery
                                        battalion, one bomber squadron, two helicopter squadrons and
                                        a tank squadron.)</p>
                                </item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> withdrawal from
                                        Malaysia-Singapore</hi>. <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> seems to be backing away from the earlier
                                    Australian plan to maintain a force in Malaysia after the
                                    British withdrawal in 1971. He has talked publicly about the
                                    possibility of a “Fortress Australia” approach. He may press
                                    hard on the idea that Australia cannot undertake commitments in
                                    the Malaysia-Singapore area without a firm guarantee of U.S.
                                    support and protection under the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Treaty. I suggest you adhere to our previous
                                    line that: <pb facs="0136" n="94" xml:id="pg_94"/>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>—we think a continued Australian military presence
                                            would be a valuable stabilizing factor;</item>
                                        <item>—we realize questions about the application of <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> might arise in
                                            connection with such deployments;</item>
                                        <item>—we would like to stay in close consultation about the
                                            matter;</item>
                                        <item>—but we cannot give a blanket guarantee.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>You should be aware that this whole problem may come to a head at the
                            Five-Power Commonwealth meeting (<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>,
                            Australia, New Zealand, Malaysia, and Singapore) scheduled for Kuala
                            Lumpur in June.</p>
                        <p>All of the above points are covered well and in more detail in Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>ʼs memo to you.</p>
                        <p>You might discuss with <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> your
                            plans for announcing an Ambassador to Australia.</p>
                        <p>A particular point of interest: Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> was born in Great Barrington, Massachusetts; grew
                            up in Bangor, Maine; and still retains her American citizenship. She is
                            dual national, also having Australian citizenship.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> is a very different kind
                            of fellow from <persName corresp="#p_HHE1">Harold Holt</persName>.
                            Rather than ruling by consensus with his Cabinet, <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> is attempting to dominate his
                            colleagues. He is also attempting to handle foreign and defense affairs
                            directly from the Prime Ministerʼs office, cutting the External Affairs
                            and Defense Ministers out. Thus it is that he is accompanied only by
                            members of his personal staff.<note n="3" xml:id="d37fn3">The Embassy in
                                Australia prepared an assessment of the <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> government which concluded that it had
                                internal problems despite its strong public support. <persName corresp="#p_GJG1">Gorton</persName> was more likely than the
                                late Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_HHE1">Holt</persName> to
                                view issues narrowly in terms of Australiaʼs self interests.
                                (Telegram 5576 from Canberra, May 13; ibid.; <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 15–1 AUSTL) The Embassy also prepared a list of
                                anticipated topics for the visit. (Telegram 5575, May 13; ibid.,
                                    <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 AUSTL)</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Walt</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>