<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>387. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for East Asian and
                    Pacific Affairs (Bundy) to the Presidentʼs Special Assistant () to the
                    Presidentʼs Special Assistant (Rostow))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d387</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">387</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-05-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-05-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87007171"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Summit meeting</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-05-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-05-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="387"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d387">
                <head>387. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for East Asian and
                    Pacific Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BWP1" type="from">Bundy</persName>) to
                    the Presidentʼs Special Assistant (<persName corresp="#p_RWW1" type="to"
                        >Rostow</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d387fn1">Source:
                        Johnson Library, National Security File, Files of Walt Rostow,
                            President-<persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> meeting, May, 8,
                        1968. Secret; Eyes Only. According to the Presidentʼs Daily Diary, the
                        meeting lasted from 12:14 to 1 p.m. (Ibid.) Transmitted to the White House
                        on May 20.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-05-08">May 8, 1968</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Notes of Presidentʼs Conversation with <persName corresp="#p_TK2"
                            >Thanom</persName>, May 8, 12:00–1:00 p.m.</item>
                </list>
                <p>I am sending you in this single copy my notes of the Presidentʼs conversation
                    with <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> at this first meeting. For
                    working purposes, I <pb facs="0900" n="858" xml:id="pg_858"/> gave a quick
                    summary of the highlights to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1"
                        >Rusk</persName> and to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_CC1"
                        >Clifford</persName> for their use in their follow-up conversations. I also
                    informed Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_Unger1">Unger</persName> in a general
                    sense.</p>
                <p>As the conversation went, <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> and Thanat
                    met privately with the President for about 10–15 minutes, after which the
                    President invited Ambassador Duke and myself to join.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Presidentʼs Decision/Selection of Paris</hi>. When I
                        entered, the President stated that he had already briefly discussed the
                        reasons for his personal decision with <persName corresp="#p_TK2"
                            >Thanom</persName>, and that he had particularly wished to do this
                        privately. He also reported that he had briefly discussed the reasons for
                        the selection of Paris for the talks, and that he had already got Than-omʼs
                        assurance that the Thai would continue with their troop commitment this
                        year. The dates the President mentioned—without contradiction from the
                        Thai—were not later than July for the first contingent, and November (sic)
                        for the second contingent. (I believe in later conversations the second
                        contingentʼs time of arrival was more generalized and in any case to be
                        before the end of the year.)</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Possible <gloss target="#t_TCC1">TCC</gloss>
                                Summit</hi>. <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> raised
                            this issue, asking simply whether the President thought a summit meeting
                            might be useful in the next few weeks. The President responded that he
                            would be in a better position to judge by July 1st. He was expecting to
                            see Thieu and all the other <gloss target="#t_TCC1">TCC</gloss> heads by
                            then; he mentioned that it was Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_MF1"
                                >Marcos</persName> he expected to see, but made a remark to the
                            effect that <persName corresp="#p_MF1">Marcos</persName> did not have
                            much of a stake anyway. (He did not spell out any plan for seeing
                            Holyoake.)</p>
                        <p>The President went on that he could most conveniently go to Honolulu, and
                            would hold his schedule flexible to make this possible on fairly short
                            notice. He was prepared in principle to meet with any two or more of the
                                <gloss target="#t_TCC1">TCC</gloss> if this were useful. At the same
                            time, we all had to be on our guard lest the press interpret such a
                            meeting as having a crisis flavor.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> responded that he himself
                            was ready to come to Honolulu whenever the President judged it useful
                            and wise to do so, and would hold himself flexible.</p>
                        <p>The President then said that we might have a better judgment in 2–4
                            weeks, and asked whether <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName>
                            had any special date in mind.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> responded that he did not,
                            and that “we will follow your convenience.”</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Comment</hi>: My feeling was that the President had
                            expressed just the right blend of sympathy and reserve, and it seemed to
                            be quite clear that <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> was not
                            pressing very hard. There was no mention of the idea later proposed by
                            Thanat, of a Foreign Ministers meeting in Bangkok.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Prospects for the Paris Talks</hi>. <persName
                            corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> asked how the President saw the Paris
                        talks unfolding, and the President said that of course stopping the bombing
                        might be the immediate issue. We would press quite hard <pb facs="0901"
                            n="859" xml:id="pg_859"/> for clear indications of what Hanoi would do,
                        and take a very firm position. If Hanoi did not give us such indications, we
                        might at some point face the question of stopping the bombing on a trial
                        basis to see what happened. However, the President made clear that this was
                        a most tentative forecast, and that all that he could say definitely was
                        that we were going into the talks in a firm position. As I recall, the
                        President made some mention of our recent military successes, political
                        improvements in Saigon, and the gentle feeling that we were in a fairly
                        strong position.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Balance of Payments</hi>. The President then brought
                            up the question of the Thai assisting us on our balance of payments
                            problem by transferring some of their reserves into longer-term US
                            securities. At the Presidentʼs request, I described the proposal in
                            general terms—as involving a transfer from present short-term holdings
                            to longer-term holdings bearing a higher rate of interest. I noted that
                            of course such an arrangement would require technical discussions.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> reacted sympathetically to
                            the Presidentʼs suggestion, and said that his government would be
                            entirely willing to discuss this further in a forthcoming spirit. He
                            indicated that there were other monetary questions that needed
                            discussion, without specifying what these were.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Comment</hi>: The matter was further pursued by
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> with <persName
                                corresp="#p_TK1">Thanat</persName> (with Assistant Secretary of the
                            Treasury Petty present), and more informally by Mr. <persName
                                corresp="#p_BRW1">Barnett</persName> with Pote. The Thai
                            subsequently agreed to the visit now being carried out by <persName
                                corresp="#p_BRW1">Barnett</persName> and Treasury
                            representatives.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> Program</hi>. The President brought
                        this matter up, saying that he had just received a recommendation from
                        Defense that we go ahead to furnish a half of the cost of a frigate for the
                        Thai Navy, along the lines the Thai had suggested. He said that he was
                        giving a firm go-ahead on this, and that <persName corresp="#p_TK2"
                            >Thanom</persName> could now understand that this request was approved.
                            <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> reacted with obvious
                        pleasure to this disclosure. (The matter was further discussed by Secretary
                            <persName corresp="#p_CC1">Clifford</persName> at the afternoon meeting
                        that day.)</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Satellite Conversation. The President then alluded briefly to the plan
                        that he and <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> should inaugurate
                        the Satellite circuit with a conversation after the dinner to be held that
                        night. Again <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> reacted with
                        obvious pleasure.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>Thai Counter-Insurgency Program. The President then asked <persName
                                corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> how the insurgency situation was
                            going. <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> responded that the
                            Laos Government was being more cooperative in the northern areas, and
                            that things were generally going better. He particularly referred to the
                            capture of key Communist leaders, and said that this had provided a
                            wealth of information on the way the apparatus worked. He did note that
                            they were still unable to find out what the source of funds was.</p>
                        <pb facs="0902" n="860" xml:id="pg_860"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> also noted that the
                            situation in the northeast had cooled down, and said that the real cure
                            there and elsewhere lay in economic and social measures. In response to
                            the Presidentʼs question whether there were any gaps in our own
                            assistance, <persName corresp="#p_TK2">Thanom</persName> said that
                            things were in satisfactory shape, although he also mentioned that they
                            were concerned that our programs remain adequate in respect to the hill
                            tribes effort, the volunteer defense corps, and the village security
                            force. The President said we would have a look at these, to be sure they
                            were adequate. He made no commitments, and this discussion was in
                            general terms.</p>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BWP1">
                            <hi rend="strong">WPB</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
