<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-08-15T05:41:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-08-15T05:41:00-05:00" n="403" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d403">
                        <head>403. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Thailand</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d403fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, DEF 1 ASIA <gloss target="#t_SE1">SE</gloss>-US. Secret;
                                    <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>. Repeated to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> for Admiral McCain and
                                Vientiane for Ambassador only.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Bangkok</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-08-15T10:41:00+00:00">August 15, 1968,
                                1041Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>18940. Department also pass SecDef for action. Subject: Future of US
                            Military Establishment in Thailand. State for Secretary Bundy.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Once hostilities in Vietnam have substantially declined, we assume
                                that (a) a large proportion of US forces now in the region will be
                                needed for commitments elsewhere, in addition to important political
                                and financial reasons for a phasedown, and (b) there will remain
                                serious grounds for concern about renewal by North Vietnam of
                                actions like those which led to our <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss> involvement in the first place, including increased
                                threats to Thailand, Laos and/or Cambodia.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>US interest in deterring (b) indicates the need for retaining a
                                credible force in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>, whereas (a)
                                will require that the force be carefully tailored, located and
                                politically emplaced so as to meet the new regional environment,
                                which often will be made as difficult by our friends as by our
                                enemies, not to speak of undefinables like <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The obvious, political, diplomatic, and financial requirements for
                                a lean post-hostilities US force—lean especially in terms of numbers
                                of US personnel—from the perspective of Thailand argue against US
                                deployment of ground combat forces in garrisons on the <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss> mainland, in the post-hostilities
                                period. In the case of Thailand they argue also against continued
                                reliance on ground-force oriented contingency plans, such as OPlan
                                1–66 of Project 22. While in 1966 it probably seemed logical to plan
                                for four US brigades and supporting forces to occupy Laotian
                                bridgehead towns in the Mekong lowlands, in response to a <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> attack, with the Thai having lesser
                                roles on the flanks, we have a somewhat more sober concept today of
                                what is really involved in engaging North Vietnamese ground forces
                                300 miles from the nearest seaport, from a base area already
                                affected by the Thai insurgency. We suspect that Thai leaders have
                                also been chastened by their experience with the insurgency in North
                                Thailand, in contemplating the costs of the major Thai movement and
                                there into neighboring Laos called for in Oplan 1–66. While this
                                plan is useful for the present, especially while a shooting war
                                continues in <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss>, not only as a factor
                                of reassurance to the Thai but as a factor of uncertainty in the
                                schemes of Hanoi, and while we should not sow doubts in Thai minds
                                about OPlan 1–66 until we have something better in hand, we believe
                                our own forward planning should be developing alternative, more <pb facs="0942" n="900" xml:id="pg_900"/> realistic ways of
                                reassuring our allies and deterring the Communists in the Thai-Lao
                                area.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The US posture in Thailand—post-Vietnam hostilities—should be
                                premised on a Thailand able to carry a major share of the military
                                defense burden itself, given what are the probable threats, with the
                                US helping out in special fields (principally air) where Thai
                                capability is not developed. Given this premise it is essential that
                                US help <gloss target="#t_RTG1">RTG</gloss> build up effective
                                defense forces, through <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> materiel
                                assistance and training appropriate to Thai forces, which are geared
                                to likely threats to Thai territory. On this basis the US posture
                                which takes the best account of many conflicting local and regional
                                considerations, as we now see it, is retention of a substantial
                                though reduced US aviation capability on the less-exposed Thai
                                bases, in support of what are likely to be at least sporadic
                                operating requirements in Laos. Surveillance of any settlement in
                                Vietnam, and visible demonstration to Hanoi of US readiness to
                                support Asian resistance to renewed aggression in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>. Frequent major ground force
                                exercises (probably in rear areas), involving hyper-modern air and
                                naval capability for fast deployment from Pacific bases, would add
                                the necessary ground force substance to our deterrence, while
                                retaining great flexibility for the US in determining how and when
                                any actual US involvement should occur.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>At present the Thai Government is very prudent about forward
                                deployment of its land forces. Washington is well aware of the
                                limitations of the Thai armed forces which prevent the RTG from
                                assuming a major share of any contingency role in Laos in response
                                to an NVN attack. We cannot, of course, say that the RTG would not
                                immediately demand full implementation of OPlan 1–66 if its
                                triggering assumptions were enacted by NVN: What we do observe is
                                that RTG budget priorities, military dispositions and readiness
                                posture are not today aimed in this direction, and the RTG may be
                                amenable to a new approach to contingency planning.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>All factors considered, therefore, a post-Vietnam posture in
                                Thailand of continued presence of substantial US air assets, backed
                                by occasional demonstrations of fast troop deployment capability, in
                                support of contingency planning which envisages primarily (a)
                                supporting Thai efforts to contain an <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> intrusion into Thailand and (b) US-Thai efforts in
                                support of Laotian contingencies emphasizing material assistance to
                                RLG and clandestine operations would best answer US strategic
                                requirements, following a Vietnam settlement, as we can now foresee
                                them. This does not overlook <gloss target="#t_JUSMAG1">JUSMAG</gloss> type activities and maintenance of logistic
                                infrastructure which would continue.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>New military command arrangements would be desirable to emphasize
                                the factors of strength in this new approach, and to develop <gloss target="#t_RTG1">RTG</gloss> support for it, lest it be seen as
                                merely a way-stop in retreating from any <pb facs="0943" n="901" xml:id="pg_901"/> commitment to Thai security. In order to
                                represent most effectively the US forces which would be the resident
                                expression of US security support for Thailand and Laos, and the new
                                orientation contingency planning, designation of a <gloss target="#t_USAF1">USAF</gloss> General officer as the next
                                    <gloss target="#t_COMUSMACTHAI1">COMUSMACTHAI</gloss> would
                                appear desirable. (Naturally the selectee should have had broad
                                politico-military experience.) I would also raise for consideration
                                the carrying of the proposal one step further, in the interest of
                                rationalizing the US Command structure in Thailand, by according him
                                authority over US Air Forces in the pattern of the US Command in
                                Japan.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>MACTHAI has had since its inception three US Army Generals at its
                                head, who with their special skills answered many valid needs of the
                                period, including setting up the training of the Thai troop
                                commitment to Vietnam, modernization of the <gloss target="#t_RTA1">RTA</gloss>, and development of OPlan 1–66. However, indefinite
                                succession of leadership from a single service is not conducive to
                                development of MACTHAI as a truly Joint Command, which it must be
                                increasingly in the 1969–71 period, and alternation of MACTHAI
                                Command among US services would reinforce this broader view. I do
                                not believe that the <gloss target="#t_RTG1">RTG</gloss> would take
                                amiss such a change, particularly, if, as I believe is essential, we
                                had very able, experienced US Army general officer as deputy <gloss target="#t_COMUSMACTHAI1">COMUSMACTHAI</gloss> to continue
                                MACTHAIʼs efforts to modernize the <gloss target="#t_RTA1">RTA</gloss>, in conjunction with the Army Advisory Group, and
                                to assist in the smooth transition of contingency plans.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_Unger1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Unger</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>