<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-04-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-04-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="58" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d58">
                        <head>58. Memorandum From the Presidentʼs Special Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BWP1" type="from">Bundy</persName>) to President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1" type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d58fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National Security File,
                                Memos to the President, <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge
                                    Bundy</persName>, Vol. IX. Secret.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-04-01">April 1, 1965</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Southeast Asia Economic Development Planning</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I wonʼt bore you with the long papers that have been worked up in staff
                            sessions this week. Their essence is as follows: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>There is great advantage in continuing US leadership to get a
                                    regional Southeast Asia development operation going.</item>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>For this purpose, we can well blow a second and somewhat
                                    louder blast enlarging the general proposition you set forth in
                                    your statement on Vietnam at the Cabinet meeting last week.<note n="2" xml:id="d58fn2">See <ref target="#d57fn2">footnote 2,
                                            Document 57</ref>.</note>
                                </item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>We should not at this stage give a precise description of the
                                    form of the development organization or a commitment in dollar
                                    terms. There are two disadvantages in such a course now: <list>
                                        <label>a.</label>
                                        <item>A long forward pass would probably be incomplete, if
                                            we do not line up some receivers down-field. This could
                                            make us look silly.</item>
                                        <label>b.</label>
                                        <item>Quite soon we will want to separate Southeast Asia
                                            development planning from the Vietnamese crisis, in
                                            operating terms. We want the real political effect of an
                                            effort for regional economic development, but we can get
                                            that effect better if we do not tie the two issues too
                                            tightly together. We do not want it thought that we are
                                            interested in economic development only because we are
                                            trying somehow to get out of our mess in Vietnam. The
                                            Marshall Plan was helpful in dealing with Soviet
                                            pressure on Europe, but it was not designed or presented
                                            to the Europeans in those terms.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>These considerations lead us to suggest that we should use language like
                            Goodwinʼs in your next statement on Vietnam. But right after that, we
                            should separate the regional economic problem from the Vietnamese
                            problem in day-to-day operations.</p>
                        <p>We think we should try to get <persName corresp="#p_UT1">U
                                Thant</persName> to pick up the ball and organize some Asian
                            responses. We also think the project should be given to <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> to work on, both with
                                <persName corresp="#p_UT1">U Thant</persName> and in relevant Asian
                            capitals. This will give it visibility and standing because of his
                            history as a Marshall Plan leader, his international prestige and his
                            position as a liberal.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">After</hi> we get some Asian responses and perhaps the
                            skeleton of a new Southeast Asia development organization, we should
                            expect to consider <pb facs="0192" n="150" xml:id="pg_150"/> a
                            contingent US commitment like our Alliance for Progress commitments of
                            four years ago. A scenario of this kind will allow plenty of time for
                            Congressional consultation in advance of any such US pledge.</p>
                        <p>These are the essential elements of a quite complex and difficult
                            enterprise. This plan has been reviewed with Tex Goldschmidt, as well as
                            the bureaucrats, and it has his warm support.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName>
                                    <hi rend="strong">McG.B.</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>