<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>69. Memorandum From the Director of the Office of Soviet Union Affairs (Toon)
                    to the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs () to the Assistant
                    Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs (Bundy))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d69</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">69</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-11-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-11-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-11-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-11-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="69"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d69">
                <head>69. Memorandum From the Director of the Office of Soviet Union Affairs
                        (<persName type="from">Toon</persName>) to the Assistant Secretary of State
                    for Far Eastern Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BWP1" type="to"
                        >Bundy</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d69fn1">Source:
                        Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 1
                        ASIA <gloss target="#t_SE1">SE</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss>. Confidential; Limdis. Drafted by J. Stapleton Roy and
                        Vladimir I. Toumanoff of EUR/SOV.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-11-04">November 4, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Soviet Objectives in Southeast Asia</item>
                </list>
                <list type="references">
                    <head>REF</head>
                    <item>Vientianeʼs 437<note n="2" xml:id="d69fn2">
                            <ref target="#d68">Document 68</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>We assume that in due course Embassy Moscow will comment on the attached cable
                    from Vientiane,<note n="3" xml:id="d69fn3">The Embassy presented its analysis in
                        telegram 1593 from Moscow, November 15. Although admitting that the United
                        States and the Soviet Union both desired stability in Southeast Asia, the
                        Embassy did not see “significant practical results” from this “coincidence
                        of views in the foreseeable future.” (Department of State, Central Files,
                            <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 1 ASIA <gloss target="#t_SE1"
                            >SE</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>)</note> but in the
                    meantime, I wish to draw your attention to our views of Soviet policy in
                    Southeast Asia, which differ from some of Ambassador Sullivanʼs ideas.</p>
                <p>In essence, we do not think that in the long run there is much hope for useful
                    US-Soviet cooperation in Southeast Asia. Limited exceptions may arise on these
                    occasions when Soviet efforts to supplant Communist Chinese presence coincide
                    with our own actions to contain and reduce it. Since the Sovietsʼ purpose is
                    also to reduce our influence, and replace it with their own, we can in general
                    continue to expect Soviet efforts in the region to be hostile to ours.</p>
                <p>In this connection, it should be noted that Soviet interests in the Indian
                    subcontinent and in Southeast Asia differ markedly. The former is of immense
                    geopolitical importance to the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and
                    involves very heavy Soviet investments of many yearsʼ duration. The <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> can afford to be far less concerned with
                    Southeast Asia, and Soviet policies there are more opportunistic and flexible.
                    We do not believe it is valid to extrapolate from one area to the other.</p>
                <p>We are also less sanguine than Ambassador Sullivanʼs cable with respect to the
                    long run effect of the Soviet presence on US relations with Laos. Nor are we
                    hopeful about the prospects for Soviet cooperation in forestalling DRV
                    encroachments there.</p>
                <p>Finally, while we concur in general with the cableʼs assessment of the Soviet
                    stance in Laos as being loose and flexible for the present, we <pb facs="0219"
                        n="177" xml:id="pg_177"/> are reluctant to read too much into this as an
                    indicator of Soviet policy in Vietnam. The two situations are altogether too
                    different.</p>
                <p>Perhaps it is unnecessary to add that we too view Soviet policy in Southeast Asia
                    as being essentially on the make, but we see ourselves as being one of the
                    principal Soviet targets.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
