<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>77. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern
                    Affairs (Bundy) to Secretary of State ) to Secretary of State Rusk</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-07-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-07-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="foreign-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic assistance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-07-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-07-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="77"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d77">
                <head>77. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern
                    Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BWP1" type="from">Bundy</persName>) to Secretary
                    of State <persName corresp="#p_RD1" type="to">Rusk</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d77fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 8 Asia <gloss target="#t_SE1"
                            >SE</gloss>. Confidential. Drafted by Paul H. Kreisburg of FE/ACA with
                        the concurrence of Assistant Secretary of State for Congressional Relations
                        Douglas A. MacArthur. Read sent this memorandum to <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName> on August 8.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1966-07-20">July 20, 1966</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Princeton Study on Neutralization in Southeast Asia Prepared for the
                        Senate Foreign Relations Committee</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Problem:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Senator Fulbright has sent a study prepared at the request of the Senate Foreign
                    Relations Committee by four scholars at Princeton University (Cyril E. Black,
                    Richard A. Falk, Klaus Knorr, and Oran Young) on Neutralization in <gloss
                        target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>: Problems and Prospects (Tab A)<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d77fn2">Attached, but not printed.</note> to the President with the
                    comment that “the recommendations, which are sober and sensible, merit the
                    attention of you and your staff.”<note n="3" xml:id="d77fn3">Fulbright made
                        these comments in a June 6 letter to President Johnson, attached but not
                        printed.</note> The President has requested you to discuss the best
                    disposition of the study with Senator Fulbright.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. We have reviewed the study and conclude that while it contains some thoughtful
                    observations on the general problems and myriad complexities of neutralization
                    in Southeast Asia, it is based on a general premise of dubious accuracy: to wit,
                    that “big-power confrontation” can be prevented by neutralization, the price of
                    which may be the acceptance of communist states which emerge as a result of
                    “purely domestic communist pressure.” The study suggests the sketchy outlines of
                    a “neutralization” model which underscores the difficulty of implementing such a
                    plan. Finally, the study suggests that at the right time and under the right
                    conditions, the US should consider exploring such a “neutralization” plan
                    privately with the countries of the area.</p>
                <p>2. The study begins with a review of the concept of neutralization and the
                    historical experience of neutralized states. It recognizes that the key problem
                    is not containing direct aggression but indirect aggression and concludes that
                    it would be extremely difficult to calculate how neutralization night affect the
                    pursuit of indirect aggression by states outside a neutralized zone. It
                    discusses the maintenance of neutralization <pb facs="0237" n="195"
                        xml:id="pg_195"/> and the concept of control and control mechanisms,
                    acknowledging the difficulty and complexity of such control, the discouraging
                    precedents (e.g. Vietnam and Laos) for effective control machinery, the
                    difficulty of sealing off borders from outside infiltration, and concludes that
                    control problems for any neutralization plan in Southeast Asia would be very
                    great.</p>
                <p>3. The study assumes (p. 17) that the object of neutralization is to prevent the
                    neutralized zone from becoming “an important focus of confrontation between
                    powers external to the zone.” It concludes that “if violations mean only that
                    the internal strife within the zone can continue largely without interference
                    from outside, this may represent as much as we can hope for.” This point is not
                    elaborated but appears to mean that violations from one “neutralized” state
                    against another “neutralized” state may have to be accepted as “tolerable”.
                    (i.e., from Vietnam to Laos or Cambodia.) We find this argument difficult to
                    accept.</p>
                <p>4. The study discusses at some length the problem of ascertaining whether a
                    violation of neutrality has taken place, the question of unanimity on the part
                    of the control mechanism, and the means by which a guarantor state could take
                    unilateral action or the neutralized state could request help. The discussion
                    underlines the complexity of the problem, admits the possibility of cheating and
                    leads the authors to conclude that if the control mechanism is unable to agree
                    on a violation, the only recourse may be for the neutralized state to renounce
                    its neutrality.</p>
                <p>5. The study concludes that the basic requirements for neutralization are (a).
                    “minimal political stability within the neutralized state or states”, (b). a
                    balance of forces among relevant external powers—at least the US, <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, and Communist China, and (c). an effective
                    control mechanism. It points out the advantages and disadvantages to the three
                    powers in (b) above of a neutralized Southeast Asia. The key advantages cited
                    for the US are realization of the US objective of enabling the neutralized
                    states to develop their own destinies themselves and to receive economic
                    assistance at the same time that substantially fewer US troops would be required
                    in the area (the maintenance of “adequate forces in neighboring areas to fulfill
                    its responsibilities as a guarantor power” is assumed in the study). The main
                    disadvantage would be the need for the US to accept communist takeovers in the
                    guaranteed states “as along as they resulted—without appreciable foreign
                    assistance—from the evolving balance of domestic political forces” (p. 30),
                    including the use of violence. We see this as a critical disadvantage, indeed,
                    and question the quantification of “appreciable foreign assistance.”</p>
                <p>6. The authors acknowledge their doubts as to the sincerity with which Peking
                    would enter any agreement for neutralization. The advantages for Peking are
                    listed mainly as the removal of US troops from the neutralized area (although it
                    is assumed Peking would accept US troops <pb facs="0238" n="196" xml:id="pg_196"
                    /> in neighboring areas) and the possibility of gaining US acquiescence in
                    “indigenous” communist revolutions. Soviet interests are seen primarily in terms
                    of Soviet desire not to be drawn into any conflict in <gloss target="#t_SEA1"
                        >SEA</gloss>. Since Soviet interests in neutralization are seen essentially
                    as negative, the studyʼs implicit argument that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss> might be an effective guarantor state seems itself
                    dubious.</p>
                <p>7. The study acknowledges that the hurdles in the way of any agreement would be
                    formidable, that at best neutralization in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>
                    would not be as effective as in Europe, and that civil strife and political
                    revolutions would probably continue in the area. It argues, however, that under
                    neutralization these would be less likely to lead to international conflicts
                    than otherwise.</p>
                <p>8. The study urges that private, preliminary, exploratory negotiations be
                    conducted by the US to “test existing national policies in regard to <gloss
                        target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>.” It is not completely clear what is meant by
                    this and in view of the risks in terms of proper timing described in the study
                    itself (p. 37), it is difficult to ascertain how and when the authors of the
                    study would envisage proceeding. The study does note, however, that if both we
                    and the communists envisaged “stalemate or worse” in Vietnam, the advantage of
                    neutralization would look impressive.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi>
                    <note n="4" xml:id="d77fn4">
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> initialed approval of all
                        recommendations on July 26.</note>
                </p>
                <p>9. a. That Ambassador MacArthur or myself review with Carl Marcy<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d77fn5">Carl Marcy, Chief of Staff of the Senate Foreign Relations
                        Committee.</note> our general reactions to the Princeton Study as set forth
                    above. Marcy would be told that the Department has itself been examining and
                    will continue to study this subject and welcomes the contribution to an
                    extremely difficult and complex problem made by the study. Marcy would also be
                    informed that you would be prepared to discuss the matter directly with Senator
                    Fulbright, if the Senator so desires.</p>
                <p>b. That the attached Department memorandum (Tab B)<note n="6" xml:id="d77fn6"
                        >Attached, but not printed.</note> on “Neutralization and Southeast Asia”
                    prepared for Senator Lausche last month be passed to the Committee through Marcy
                    as an example of the Departmentʼs thinking on this subject.</p>
                <p>c. That a copy of this memorandum be sent to <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt
                        Rostow</persName> in the White House.</p>
                <p>d. That no presentation be made to the Cabinet on the subject at this time;
                    and</p>
                <p>e. That Marcy be told the Department has no objection to the study being
                    circulated to all members of the Committee and that, while we agree it might be
                    preferable that the study not be published because of <pb facs="0239" n="197"
                        xml:id="pg_197"/> the general complexity of the subject and some of the
                    deficiencies of the study, we would not object if the Committee decided to make
                    it public.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
