<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-12-05T09:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-12-05T09:30:00-05:00" n="102" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d102">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of State Atomic Energy Files</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Minutes of a Meeting at the United States Mission at the
                            United Nations, New York, December 5, 1949, 9:30 a. m.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1949-12-05T09:30:00-05:00">December 5, 1949, 9:30 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <table cols="4" rows="9">
                            <row>
                                <cell>Present:</cell>
                                <cell>Ambassador Gross<note n="1" xml:id="d102fn1">Ambassador Ernest
                                        A. Gross, Deputy United States Representative at the United
                                        Nations.</note>
                                </cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Noyes<note n="2" xml:id="d102fn2">Charles P. Noyes, Deputy
                                        United States Representative to the Interim Committee of the
                                        United Nations General Assembly.</note>
                                </cell>
                                <cell role="brace" rows="3">}</cell>
                                <cell rows="3">during part of the meeting</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. J. Hyde<note n="3" xml:id="d102fn3">James N. Hyde,
                                        Adviser, United States Mission at the United Nations.</note>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Maffitt<note n="4" xml:id="d102fn4">Edward P. Maffitt,
                                        Adviser, United States Mission at the United Nations.</note>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. B. H. Brown<note n="5" xml:id="d102fn5">Benjamin H. Brown,
                                        Chief of the Reporting and Documentation Division, United
                                        States Mission at the United Nations.</note>
                                </cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Lt.-General W. D. Crittenberger—<gloss target="#t_USA1">USA</gloss>
                                </cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Lt.-General H.E. Harmon—<gloss target="#t_USAF1">USAF</gloss>
                                </cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Vim Admiral B. H. Bieri<note n="6" xml:id="d102fn6">Vice Adm.
                                        B. H. Bieri, United States Naval Representative to the
                                        United Nations Military Staff Committee.</note>—<gloss target="#t_USN1">USN</gloss>
                                </cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Brig.-General Robert M. Bathurst<note n="7" xml:id="d102fn7">Brig. Gen. R. M. Bathurst, Deputy United States Army
                                        Representative to the United Nations Military Staff
                                        Committee.</note>—<gloss target="#t_USA1">USA</gloss>
                                </cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross opened the meeting by explaining that Ambassador Austin on
                        Friday had asked him to review the history of developments under Article 43
                        and to prepare a Mission position on General McNaughton’s suggestion that
                        this question be reviewed during his presidency of the Security Council in
                        December. Ambassador Gross said the meeting had been called to discuss the
                        problem in the light of Ambassador Austin’s view that the U.S. Government
                        should be receptive to any developments which promised progress in this
                        field. Ambassador Gross had spent the weekend diligently reviewing the file
                        on the subject but felt that he still had much to do in the way of
                        preparation. He had noted a May, 1948, <gloss target="#t_SANACC1">SANACC</gloss> memorandum<note n="8" xml:id="d102fn8">The memorandum
                            under reference has not been specifically identified; for documentation
                            on the question of forces to be placed at the disposal of the United
                            Nations Security Council, see <ref target="frus1948v01p1#pg_311">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol, <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, Part 1, pp. 311</ref> ff.</note>
                        indicating that the Military establishment at that time had considered
                        unsound a State Department proposal that the possibility be explored of the
                        United States making an offer under Article 43. The point was made that as
                        long as Russia was in a position to veto decisions in the Security Council,
                        there could be little use in making forces available to the Council. It was
                        also felt that, due to commitments undertaken by the United States to
                        allocate forces for other purposes, the furnishing of troops under Article
                        43 might be difficult.</p>
                    <pb facs="0262" n="232" xml:id="pg_232"/>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross went on to say that the most recent policy statement by the,
                        State Department seemed to be in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss>
                        No. 6 [<hi rend="italic">5</hi>], January 6, 1949, 7:00 p. m., stating that
                        there was serious reservation as to whether it would be advantageous to
                        press for implementation of Article 43 at that time, and whether the United
                        States could in fact make armed forces available. The telegram concluded
                        that under these circumstances, Security Council discussions were definitely
                        undesirable.</p>
                    <p>More recently, Ambassador Gross continued, General McNaughton had raised the
                        question of possible discussions during his presidency in December. The
                        Department, in reply to the Mission’s query, had stated in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 621, November 29, 6:00 p. m.<note n="9" xml:id="d102fn9">Not printed.</note> that the U.S. position with
                        respect to Article 43 forces was now under review. The telegram expressed
                        the thought that while the United States might welcome conversations as
                        suggested by General McNaughton, it appeared unlikely that we would be
                        prepared to discuss the problem during the Canadian presidency.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross concluded his introductory remarks by stating that he hoped
                        to have a brief general discussion of the problem to ascertain the present
                        position in the light of all relevant factors. He wondered whether General
                        Crittenberger might take up the matter from there.</p>
                    <p>General Crittenberger said he also understood that we remained under the
                        guidance of <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> No. 6 [<hi rend="italic">5</hi>] of January 6. He thought there might have been
                        changes since that time, but nevertheless the instructions stood. General
                        Crittenberger had spent the past week with General Bradley,<note n="10" xml:id="d102fn10">General Omar N. Bradley, Chairman of the Joint Chiefs
                            of Staff.</note> who had, remarked that if, from a political standpoint,
                        it was desirable to discuss Article 43 in the Security Council, the safest
                        course would be to confine the discussions to general principles, which the
                        Council had had under discussion for some time. General Crittenberger
                        personally was of the opinion that the Military position was sound. The
                        North Atlantic Treaty represented a large commitment and made it
                        questionable whether forces could be made available under Article 43. If it
                        proved to be politically desirable to undertake discussions with other
                        members of the Council, General Crittenberger saw no harm in doing so, if
                        the conversations were private and not public, but he could not express
                        optimism that anything realistic would be accomplished.</p>
                    <p>Admiral Bieri, agreeing with General Crittenberger, remarked that when one
                        thought of the purposes for which Article 43 forces would be used, it was
                        plain that nothing could be gained by establishing such forces as long as
                        the Soviet Union remained in a position to veto their use. He agreed that
                        implementation of Article 43 had been made exceedingly <pb facs="0263" n="233" xml:id="pg_233"/> difficult in view of the military commitments
                        of the United States under the North Atlantic Treaty.</p>
                    <p>General Harmon also concurred in the above analysis. He thought that to
                        reopen the question at this time would merely stir up acrimonious
                        debate.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross asked the representatives of the Military Staff what they
                        thought might be behind General McNaughton’s suggestion. General
                        Crittenberger replied that in his estimation General McNaughton was a
                        sincere man acting from high motives. Something like fifty-five members of
                        the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> had supported a declaration in favor
                        of world peace, and in General McNaughton’s mind, one of the means of making
                        good this declaration was implementation of Article 43. General
                        Crittenberger thought General McNaughton sincerely desired to exhaust all
                        possibilities in this connection. General Crittenberger recalled that during
                        the Canadian presidency in January, 1949, the question had been raised, and
                        indeed it was that which had prompted the statement of policy in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> No. 6 of January, 1949.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross said he wanted also to get an expression of opinion on the
                        relationship between the work of the <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss>,
                        the <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> and efforts to implement Article 43.
                        He wondered whether any general analysis or synthesis had been made putting
                        these various elements in their proper relationship one to the other.
                        Specifically, he wondered what consideration had been given to
                        implementation of Article 43 in terms of the U.S. positions in the <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Noyes remarked that the majority of the <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss> had agreed on the principle that no further progress could
                        be made toward the control of conventional armaments until the Five Powers
                        found it possible to move forward under Article 43. The <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss> had made this statement of principle at the
                        suggestion of the United States. Unfortunately, the USSR thus was able to
                        claim that the United States was setting up barriers which it knew in
                        advance were insuperable. In other words, they claimed we made progress in
                        the <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss> conditional on implementation of
                        Article 43, and at the same time we had abandoned efforts to fulfill this
                        condition. The USSR argued that the majority should drop this stipulation in
                        the <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss> or get on with business in the MSG
                        and Security Council with a view toward implementation of Article 43. Mr.
                        Noyes recalled that the <gloss target="#t_MSC1">MSC</gloss> had got
                        two-thirds of the way through its consideration of general principles and
                        that during this phase it was the Russians who were holding things up. Since
                        that time, however, the effort to complete agreement on general principles
                        had been dropped, and the Russians were asking why. Mr. Noyes said the
                        difficulty plagued us in many ways. For example, in working out a substitute
                        for the Soviet Peace Pact Proposal,<note n="11" xml:id="d102fn11">For
                            documentation on the “Essentials for Peace” Resolution, see <ref target="frus1949v02#pg_72">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp.
                                72</ref> ff.</note> it had been necessary <pb facs="0264" n="234" xml:id="pg_234"/> to avoid reference to the implementation of Article
                        43, although many other instances were mentioned where the cooperation of
                        the Great Powers might advance the cause of peace. Mr. Noyes said his point
                        was that if the United States left a record which could be interpreted as
                        preventing implementation of Article 43, we would not leave as good a
                        picture as we might. He thought that if the United States went ahead and got
                        a nine-to-two vote on general principles and then stopped, the position
                        would be a sound one. As it was, failure to complete the effort to get
                        agreement on general principles created an embarrassing situation which was
                        hard to justify.</p>
                    <p>General Crittenberger agreed that from a propaganda standpoint this might be
                        unfortunate. He observed, however, that the fact remained it was the
                        Russians who had really blocked progress in getting full agreement on
                        general principles.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Hyde said he had heard that a group of New York lawyers had been
                        corresponding with Congressional leaders, urging that a string be attached
                        to money appropriated under the North Atlantic defense arrangements so that
                        forces supplied from these funds might be made available to the Security
                        Council in carrying out its responsibilities under the Charter. Judging from
                        the response they had received, the group felt that this possibility was not
                        foreclosed.</p>
                    <p>General Harmon said he thought it was necessary to review some of the more
                        basic questions which underlay all policy considerations with respect to
                        implementation of Article 43. In his own personal opinion, General Harmon
                        thought it had been a mistake to incorporate Article 43 in the Charter. He
                        felt that implementation of this Article might conceivably create a false
                        sense of security in the public mind. At the same time, if the Five Powers
                        could really agree, there would be no need for an international force.
                        General Harmon was unable to see how such an international force could have
                        been used in any of the situations with which the Security Council had
                        dealt, including Palestine and Indonesia. He thought the practical
                        difficulties of organizing such an international force were well-nigh
                        insurmountable. He wondered whether at the present time it was in the best
                        interests of the United States to continue efforts to implement Article 43
                        or whether it would not be better to play it down and, instead, advance the
                        idea that implementation was no longer necessary. General Harmon himself
                        favored the latter course and felt that the ground should be prepared so
                        that thought and opinion would be ready to accept this idea.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross recalled that the idea of implementing Article 43 had been
                        reaffirmed time and again by United States representatives at the very
                        highest level. He was interested in getting a concensus on this question:
                        Would it be advantageous or disadvantageous to discuss with the United
                        Kingdom and France the question of general principles at this time? In other
                        words, would there be tactical and propaganda <pb facs="0265" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"/> advantages (or, on the other hand, disadvantages from
                        the military standpoint) if the three Powers were to discuss their
                        differences of opinion with respect to general principles?</p>
                    <p>General Crittenberger said there might be political advantages and that so
                        far as he could see there would be no military disadvantages, so long as the
                        conversations were restricted to the Three Powers named.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross said he had been struck by the thought that the signature of
                        the Atlantic Treaty might have important implications with respect to
                        implementation of Article 43. He wondered whether the North Atlantic Treaty
                        arrangement, with its implied integration of armed forces, might not affect
                        the position with respect to Article 43 in the sense that forces could now
                        be made available on a regional basis. Under the Atlantic Pact, the armed
                        forces of the signatories would presumably be arranged in such a way as to
                        be able to respond to a quick call by the Council under the Treaty.
                        Similarly, might not these pooled forces—or at least those of France, the
                        United Kingdom and United States as the three members of the <gloss target="#t_MSC1">MSC</gloss> who have signed the Atlantic Treaty—be made
                        available under Article 43, if the necessary prior agreements could be
                        reached?</p>
                    <p>Admiral Bieri said he did not see how the signature of the Atlantic Pact
                        altered the situation. As long as Russia remained the real threat to peace,
                        there was really no use in endeavoring to set up armed forces in company
                        with hers.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross said he had in mind how the Atlantic Treaty arrangements
                        might affect our dealings with the United Kingdom and France. He wondered if
                        we did not have a different problem now with respect to these two Powers and
                        if, together with them, we might not advance a common front on Article 43 in
                        the light of the new treaty relationship. After all, the Atlantic Pact
                        forces would have responsibility for policing the North Atlantic area. This
                        suggested the possibility that forces might conceivably be made available to
                        the Security Council from this regional group. Ambassador Gross said he had
                        not yet gone very far in his study of Article 43; he simply threw out this
                        suggestion for discussion, wondering if it might not have something in it.
                        He thought possibly it was an item for consideration by the Defense
                        Committee or Council under Article 9 of the Atlantic Treaty.</p>
                    <p>General Bathurst recalled that he had raised the question some months ago
                        with his military, colleagues and it had seemed at that time impractical
                        from a military standpoint to alter our approach to Article 43 as long as
                        the veto existed. It was generally felt that there would be no profit in
                        exploring this question further, and the proposal got nowhere. Perhaps this
                        had been the wrong answer, but it was the answer arrived at at the time.</p>
                    <pb facs="0266" n="236" xml:id="pg_236"/>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross said he did not mean to suggest that this was the wrong
                        answer. His thinking was tentative. He merely raised the question, on what
                        basis should the US, the UK and France approach the question of Article 43
                        implementation? He wondered whether it was not important that the three
                        Powers reach a solid front on general principles with respect to Article 43.
                        He thought this was the point which Mr. Noyes had made before leaving the
                        meeting, and he wished to invite discussion of it.</p>
                    <p>General Crittenberger asked whether the idea was to stimulate discussion in
                        the Security Council or to promote private discussion among the three
                        Powers. Ambassador Gross said he would judge that <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 621 ruled out discussion in the Security Council at the
                        present time. The next question in his mind was, would it be of value to get
                        a tripartite position in discussions with the UK and France—in other words,
                        to form a common front on the question of general principles.</p>
                    <p>General Crittenberger repeated that there might be political advantages in
                        this course and that he personally could see no corresponding military
                        disadvantage. He asked what the other <gloss target="#t_MSC1">MSC</gloss>
                        representatives thought.</p>
                    <p>Admiral Bieri stated that in his opinion there would be no objection to
                        discussion along these lines so long as it did not go beyond the three
                        Powers named. Actually, the US, UK and France were not far apart on general
                        principles. It might also be useful to ascertain the attitude of these
                        powers toward the idea which General Harmon had expressed that it would be
                        unwise, under present circumstances, to proceed with efforts to implement
                        Article 43.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Maffitt said that so far as he could recall there were only three out of
                        some forty-odd principles which had not yet been agreed by the US, UK and
                        France.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross said it was General Harmon’s idea which had prompted him to
                        raise the possibility of discussion with the UK and France. His question
                        derived, in fact, from the point General Harmon had raised. He had in mind
                        that we might sound out these two Powers as to their general attitude, from
                        a military standpoint, on the implementation of Article 43.</p>
                    <p>General Crittenberger said it was the hard lot of the Military
                        representatives always to carry a heavy bucket on each shoulder. One was the
                        commitment of the United States to support the United Nations and all its
                        works; the other was the military security of the United States. He
                        questioned whether such a discussion as Ambassador Gross had suggested
                        could, with propriety, be initiated in this small group or whether it was
                        not properly a matter for the President and Congress, who might <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be disposed to recede from the position so
                        frequently taken in public on Article 43.</p>
                    <pb facs="0267" n="237" xml:id="pg_237"/>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross said he wanted to make it clear that he could not agree or
                        disagree at present with the ideas advanced by General Harmon. Frankly, he
                        was not sufficiently familiar with the matter to take a position. He had
                        noted, however, that since 1946, when the matter had first arisen, the
                        Mission and the Department in turn had from time to time tentatively put a
                        foot in the water and, upon finding it too cold, had withdrawn. He referred
                        to <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> No. 381, August 29, 1947, to
                        Embassy, London.<note n="12" xml:id="d102fn12">For the text of the telegram
                            under reference which was sent to the Embassy in the United Kingdom as
                            3762 and repeated to the United States Mission in New York, see <ref target="frus1947v01#pg_623">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1947, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 623</ref>.</note> It was here stated
                        that in pursuit of the U.S. objective of getting forces allocated to the
                        Security Council as soon as possible, consideration was being given to
                        proposing that the General Assembly, at its regular 1947 Session, consider
                        accelerating the implementation of Article 43, and, specifically, that the
                        Assembly recommend (1) to <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> Members that
                        they tender offers of forces before March 31, 1948, and (2) to the Security
                        Council that it accept such offers as agreements, thus effectuating a
                        provisional implementation of Article 43, pending completion of <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> consideration of general principles. This
                        suggestion had been discussed with the British Foreign Office, and
                        Ambassador Gross understood that they had turned it down cold. Again, in
                        1948, the Department in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> No. 384,
                        June 11, 1948, to <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss><note n="13" xml:id="d102fn13">Not printed.</note> had stated it was considering
                        whether or not some action in the Article 43 field should be taken in the
                            <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> prior to the 1948 Session of the
                        General Assembly. Judging from these cables, it seemed that it had been the
                        Department of State which wished to stimulate activity in this sphere.
                        However, <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 166 [<hi rend="italic">5</hi>], January 6, 1949, seemed to indicate otherwise.</p>
                    <p>General Harmon said he wanted to have it understood that nothing in his
                        previous remarks should be taken to indicate that he represented a
                        subversive element in the meeting. He conceded that the policy question of
                        whether or not to implement Article 43 was a matter for the President, the
                        Secretary of State and Congressional leaders. It would have to be decided at
                        the highest level, and not in an informal meeting such as the present one.
                        In General Harmon’s personal opinion, however, a good deal of altruistic
                        thinking had gone into the writing of the Charter. In response to a question
                        by Mr. Maffitt, General Harmon said he did not feel that altruistic ideas
                        were necessarily impractical ideas. He was not a student of diplomacy, but
                        he recalled that in the days of the League of Nations these same questions
                        had been discussed and that many people had the mistaken idea that the
                        League had failed because it had not been possible to supply an
                        international force. Actually, he thought the failure of the League lay in
                        other causes altogether.</p>
                    <pb facs="0268" n="238" xml:id="pg_238"/>
                    <p>Admiral Bieri said he personally was inclined to agree with General Harmon.
                        He had found no indication that the authors of Article 43 had given any
                        serious thought to the important question, who was expected to upset the
                        peace? In considering a military program, it was necessary to make certain
                        assumptions. One always asked: from what quarter is trouble to be
                        anticipated? If no assumption were made, the military aspects of the problem
                        could be considered only in the abstract and not realistically.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross said that without having made any historical investigation
                        to find out what was in the minds of the authors, he thought it was pretty
                        certain, in view of subsequent statements and developments, that there never
                        had been any intention to use forces contemplated under Article 43 outside
                        or beyond the veto system. The main difficulty in his mind was the
                        relationship between Article 43 and the general question of the control of
                        armaments. One policy statement after another had underscored the fact that
                        in the U.S. view no control of armaments could be achieved without prior
                        progress in implementing Article 43. Secretary Marshall, in his opening
                        address at the 1947 <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>,<note n="14" xml:id="d102fn14">For the text of Secretary Marshall’s speech at the
                            82nd Plenary Meeting of the General Assembly, September 17, 1947, during
                            the general debate phase of the 2nd Regular Session, see United Nations,
                                <hi rend="italic">Official Records of the General Assembly, Second
                                Session Plenary Meetings</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp.
                            19–27.</note> had used the word “presuppose”, saying that the regulation
                        of armaments “presupposed” the implementation of Article 43. Ambassador
                        Gross said he thought General Harmon’s comment should be considered in
                        relation to this pronouncement by the Secretary of State and similar
                        statements by other government leaders. If U.S. policy with respect to
                        Article 43 were reviewed and if the conclusion suggested by General Harmon
                        were adopted, would it then be necessary to discard all hopes of armament
                        control?</p>
                    <p>General Crittenberger asked whether the purpose of the present meeting was
                        not to determine the attitude the United States should take in the Security
                        Council in December on the question of Article 43 forces. The question was
                        to talk or not to talk. If it were felt politically advisable to enter into
                        the discussions suggested by General McNaughton, that was one thing. Senator
                        Austin had said we would be receptive to any ideas General McNaughton or
                        others might advance. This was a political question. From a military point
                        of view, General Crittenberger could see no advantage in such
                        discussions.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross said the Department’s November 29 telegram seemed to
                        indicate that there would be no discussion of Article 43 in the Security
                        Council in December. He thought it put a stopper on that. He believed it was
                        a correct interpretation of Senator Austin’s <pb facs="0269" n="239" xml:id="pg_239"/> view to say that we should keep an open mind, but not
                        plunge precipitously. Ambassador Gross felt there was much of value in
                        having a frank and open discussion of this nature by those concerned with
                        the problem in the U.S. Mission and in the U.S. Military Staff.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Maffitt said the British apparently had told the Canadians that they did
                        not wish to discuss the question in the Security Council at the present
                        time. The French, he understood, were consulting their Foreign Office and
                        did not yet have instructions.</p>
                    <p>General Crittenberger said he did not wish to take exception to Senator
                        Austin’s statement that the United States should be “receptive”. He fully
                        agreed that we should have an open mind on these questions and often had
                        said this to Ambassador Austin. At the same time, the broader aspects of the
                        problem should not be forgotten. It was important to know in what way
                        Article 43 forces were to be employed. So far as he could see, there was no
                        way to employ them to any effect as long as decisions were subject to veto.
                        As General Harmon had observed, it was inconceivable that Security Council
                        forces, had they been available, would have been used in Palestine or
                        Indonesia. General Crittenberger wondered whether the United States would be
                        willing to have <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> forces employed in the
                        Caribbean. Would the UK be willing to have them in the Mediterranean or the
                        North Sea? Would the USSR allow them in the China Sea? These were admittedly
                        difficult questions, but General Crittenberger wondered if Ambassador Gross
                        had any thoughts regarding them.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross said he fully realized the difficulties pointed out by
                        General Crittenberger and that he had no thoughts to offer. In his view the
                        question at hand was tactical and psychological. Ambassador Gross recalled
                        that during the past week, at the Department’s request, he had chaired a
                        meeting in Washington of private citizens who were asked to come in as
                        consultants and give their views on World Federalism and related topics and
                        on the possibilities of amending the Charter. Hamilton Fish Armstrong,<note n="15" xml:id="d102fn15">Director of the Council on Foreign
                            Relations.</note> Justice Roberts,<note n="16" xml:id="d102fn16">Owen J.
                            Roberts, Justice of the Supreme Court of the United States.</note>
                        Harold Urey<note n="17" xml:id="d102fn17">Dr. Harold C. Urey, Professor of
                            Chemistry and Member of the Staff of the Institute for Nuclear Studies,
                            University of Chicago.</note> and Robert Hutchins,<note n="18" xml:id="d102fn18">Chancellor of the University of Chicago.</note> among
                        others, had attended. It was clear from these discussions that the idea of
                        World Federalism was gaining. A hundred and ten members of the House of
                        Representatives had indicated their support of the principle. In this
                        connection, the question of implementing Article 43 always came up. It was a
                        question on which public opinion was highly sensitive. At the next <pb facs="0270" n="240" xml:id="pg_240"/> session of the Congress, both the
                        Senate Foreign Relations Committee and the House Foreign Affairs Committee
                        would start hearings in connection with the resolutions before the two
                        Houses. The Department of State had already been asked to be ready to
                        present its views. All in all, there would have to be discussion as to where
                        Article 43 fitted in with the general question of world government and of
                        the sacrifice of national sovereignty. Ambassador Gross hoped that a series
                        of meetings such as the present one would help to clarify everyone’s
                        thinking, and he hoped such a suggestion would not be considered out of
                        order.</p>
                    <p>General Crittenberger said the suggestion was not at all out of order. The
                        MSG representatives had thought about these matters and would welcome an
                        opportunity to discuss them with the political representatives.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross said he was interested in the matter on two counts. In the
                        first place, Ambassador Austin had asked him to handle the question of
                        Article 43 forces if, as, and when it came up in the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>. He was also assisting the Department in formulating a
                        position on World Federalism and related suggestions.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Maffitt asked whether it was agreed that <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> Political Advisers might discuss the question of Article
                        43 privately with the British, French and Canadians. General Crittenberger
                        said he did not see how such discussions could be avoided. Ambassador Gross
                        said that, not being familiar with procedures generally followed in New
                        York, he wished to know whether it would not be in order for representatives
                        of the Military Staff to accompany political officers when these
                        conversation were conducted.</p>
                    <p>General Crittenberger said he thought each case should be decided on its own
                        merits. The Military Staff representatives were always available. He had
                        consistently taken the position, however, that he and his colleagues
                        represented the military point of view and that it might not be understood
                        by other Delegations if they stepped out of bounds to discuss political
                        questions. For this reason, he had opposed the suggestion, which had been
                        made at one time, that Military representatives should be used as political
                        liaison officers.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross said that this was a matter of procedure in connection with
                        which the established pattern should be followed. He agreed with General
                        Crittenberger that each case should be decided on its own merits.</p>
                    <p>General Bathurst said he wanted to clarify the situation by pointing out that
                        while these questions had a political aspect which should be handled
                        primarily by the political experts, the Military Staff representatives <pb facs="0271" n="241" xml:id="pg_241"/> realized that there was a military
                        side too and that since the dividing line was not always clear, the Military
                        representatives were more than glad to be consulted when it was felt that
                        their advice would be useful.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Maffitt said he took the consensus to be that the question of deciding
                        whether or not to discuss Article 43 questions with the UK and France should
                        be decided by <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> political officers, as
                        well as the question whether it would be necessary to get prior Departmental
                        clearance. It was so agreed.</p>
                    <p>General Harmon, reviewing what had been said concerning the relationship
                        between US policy in the <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss> and in the
                            <gloss target="#t_MSC1">MSC</gloss>, remarked that in his opinion it was
                        important and urgent to consider whether, if the effort to form Article 43
                        forces were abandoned, some progress toward control of armaments might not
                        nevertheless be made.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross said that, although U.S. policy had heretofore been based on
                        the idea that progress in the <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss>
                        presupposed progress under Article 43, he could not conceive that this
                        formula would be applied so literally as to block all possibility of control
                        of armament, in the event that our position on Article 43 were revised. He
                        could not imagine that a way would not be found to continue efforts in the
                        field of armament control. He said, however, that General Harmon’s warning
                        note was appreciated and had been noted.</p>
                    <p>General Crittenberger said he had been told that Mr. Nash on Saturday,
                        December 3, had expressed the opinion that the U.S. Delegation should meet
                        with the UK and France to discuss whether or not to take up the question of
                        Article 43 forces in the month of December.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Gross said he thought this matter was of general concern in the
                        Mission and in the Department and that everyone involved should get in on
                        the act in an appropriate way. In reviewing the U.S. position, Washington,
                        in Ambassador Gross’ estimation, should take into account the views
                        expressed by those who were handling this and related matters in New
                        York.</p>
                    <p>At the close of the meeting, General Crittenberger said he had particularly
                        welcomed the opportunity to participate in the discussion, since on
                        Thursday, December 8, the <gloss target="#t_MSC1">MSC</gloss> would convene
                        under his chairmanship and it would be helpful to him to be apprised of all
                        developments. He said he would be grateful if he could be kept informed of
                        any new developments that might occur before the <gloss target="#t_MSC1">MSC</gloss> meeting.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>B. H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Brown</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>