<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Draft Report by the National Security Council Staff
                    
                        In NSC 20, a report to the National
                            Security Council circulated on July 12, 1948, Secretary of Defense James
                            Forrestal requested the formulation of a comprehensive statement of
                            national policy regarding the degree and character of military
                            preparedness required by the world situation. For text of NSC 20, see 
                                Foreign Relations, 1948, vol. i, Part 2, p. 589.
                        At its 17th Meeting, August 5, 1948, the National Security Council
                        
                            a. Agreed that the Department of State will
                            prepare for Council consideration the following studies: 
                                (1)
                                A current estimate of the existing or foreseeable threats to
                                    our national security, with particular reference to the USSR,
                                    including the probable nature and timing of these
                                    threats.
                                (2)
                                A statement of the objectives which this nation should pursue
                                    in the foreseeable future in order to safeguard its national
                                    security and to counter the existing or anticipated threats to
                                    that security.
                            
                        
                        
                            b. Directed the NSC Staff to prepare the following study after completion
                            of the above studies:
                        A program of specific measures which, in the light of our existing
                            commitments and capabilities, should and can be planned at this time to
                            promote the achievement of our current national security objectives,
                            with particular reference to those measures which should be included in
                            our planning for the fiscal year 1950. (Department of State Executive
                            Secretariat Files: NSC Action No.
                            88)
                        Pursuant to Part A of Action 88, the NSC
                            adopted report NSC 20/4, “U.S.
                            Objectives with Respect to the USSR to Counter Soviet Threats to U.S.
                            Security,” November 23, 1948. That report, approved by President Truman
                            on November 24, 1948, is printed 
                                ibid., p. 662.
                        The draft report printed here was prepared by the NSC Staff in accordance with Part B of Action 88. An
                            earlier version, dated January 11, 1949, not printed, was circulated to
                            the Consultants of the NSC
                            (representatives of the constituent government agencies concerned) with
                            the suggestion that if the report were concurred in by the Consultants
                            and adopted by the Council, it be submitted to the President with the
                            recommendation that he approve the report and direct its implementation
                            by appropriate Departments and agencies. The Secretary of State was to
                            be particularly responsible for paragraphs 6, 7, 8, and 9 a and b (Department of
                            State Executive Secretariat Files). The Consultants met on January 17 to
                            consider the January 11 version of the draft report; regarding that
                            meeting, see Kennan’s memorandum of April 14, p.
                                282. The present text was circulated to the Under Secretary of
                            State’s Meeting as document UM D–28,
                            April 14, and was considered by that body on April 15 (see p. 283).</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d112</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">112</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-03-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-03-30T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-03-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-03-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="112" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d112">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Policy Planning Staff Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Draft Report by the National Security Council Staff</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d112fn1">
                        <p>In <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 20, a report to the National
                            Security Council circulated on July 12, 1948, Secretary of Defense James
                            Forrestal requested the formulation of a comprehensive statement of
                            national policy regarding the degree and character of military
                            preparedness required by the world situation. For text of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 20, see <ref target="frus1948v01p2#pg_589">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, Part 2, p. 589</ref>.</p>
                        <p>At its 17th Meeting, August 5, 1948, the National Security Council</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. Agreed that the Department of State will
                            prepare for Council consideration the following studies: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>A current estimate of the existing or foreseeable threats to
                                    our national security, with particular reference to the USSR,
                                    including the probable nature and timing of these
                                    threats.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>A statement of the objectives which this nation should pursue
                                    in the foreseeable future in order to safeguard its national
                                    security and to counter the existing or anticipated threats to
                                    that security.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. Directed the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff to prepare the following study after completion
                            of the above studies:</p>
                        <p>A program of specific measures which, in the light of our existing
                            commitments and capabilities, should and can be planned at this time to
                            promote the achievement of our current national security objectives,
                            with particular reference to those measures which should be included in
                            our planning for the fiscal year 1950. (Department of State Executive
                            Secretariat Files: <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No.
                            88)</p>
                        <p>Pursuant to Part A of Action 88, the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            adopted report <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 20/4, “U.S.
                            Objectives with Respect to the USSR to Counter Soviet Threats to U.S.
                            Security,” November 23, 1948. That report, approved by President Truman
                            on November 24, 1948, is printed <ref target="frus1948v01p2#pg_662">
                                <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 662</ref>.</p>
                        <p>The draft report printed here was prepared by the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff in accordance with Part B of Action 88. An
                            earlier version, dated January 11, 1949, not printed, was circulated to
                            the Consultants of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            (representatives of the constituent government agencies concerned) with
                            the suggestion that if the report were concurred in by the Consultants
                            and adopted by the Council, it be submitted to the President with the
                            recommendation that he approve the report and direct its implementation
                            by appropriate Departments and agencies. The Secretary of State was to
                            be particularly responsible for paragraphs 6, 7, 8, and 9 <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b</hi> (Department of
                            State Executive Secretariat Files). The Consultants met on January 17 to
                            consider the January 11 version of the draft report; regarding that
                            meeting, see Kennan’s memorandum of April 14, <ref target="#pg_282">p.
                                282</ref>. The present text was circulated to the Under Secretary of
                            State’s Meeting as document <gloss target="#t_UM1">UM</gloss> D–28,
                            April 14, and was considered by that body on April 15 (see <ref target="#pg_283">p. 283</ref>).</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-03-30">March 30,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Measures Required To Achieve</hi> U.S. <hi rend="smallcaps">Objectives With Respect to the</hi> USSR</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Introduction</hi>. To counter the threats to our national
                    security and well being posed by the USSR and to achieve our general objectives
                    with respect to Russia, the following measures are deemed essential. In
                    implementing these measures, care must be taken to avoid unduly impairing our
                    economy and the fundamental values and institutions inherent in our way of life.
                    (See paragraph 11 below.)</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Military readiness</hi>. The United States should develop a
                    level of military readiness adequate as a basis for immediate military
                    commitments and for rapid mobilization should war prove unavoidable. This <pb facs="0302" n="272" xml:id="pg_272"/> level should be such that it can be
                    maintained as long as it is necessary for United States forces to act as a
                    deterrent to Soviet aggression.</p>
                <p>In essence, the basic objectives should be to meet at least the requirements for
                    effective emergency action and, to every practicable extent, to provide for
                    extension of the scope of such measures to all-out war effort without avoidable
                    delay.</p>
                <p>To this end the National Military Establishment should, to the extent permitted
                    by budget limitations, provide for the following: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Forces in being or capable of prompt activation for the accomplishment
                            of the following tasks: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>To insure the integrity of the Western Hemisphere and to
                                    promote and develop its war-making capacity.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>In conjunction with our allies to secure such base areas as
                                    are essential for the projection of offensive operations.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>To secure, maintain, and defend in conjunction with our allies
                                    such bases, land and sea areas, and lines of communication as
                                    are required for the prosecution of the war.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>To conduct, at the earliest practicable date, a strategic air
                                    offensive against the vital elements of the Soviet war-making
                                    capacity, and other air offensive operations as are required for
                                    the prosecution of the war.</item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>To initiate development of the offensive power of the armed
                                    forces for such later operations as may be necessary for
                                    achievement of the national war objectives.</item>
                                <label>(6)</label>
                                <item>To support the war efforts of our allies by the provision of
                                    all feasible military assistance.</item>
                                <label>(7)</label>
                                <item>To exploit at the earliest practicable date the psychological
                                    warfare plans developed under the provisions of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 43 series<note n="2" xml:id="d112fn2">
                                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 43, “Planning for
                                        Wartime Conduct of Overt Psychological Warfare,” approved by
                                        the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> on March 23, 1949,
                                        and <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 43/1, “General
                                        Principles Governing the Conduct of Overt Psychological
                                        Warfare in the Initial Stages of War or Emergency,” August
                                        2, 1949, upon which the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                        took no final action, are not printed.</note> and the
                                    activities planned under the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                    10 series,<note n="3" xml:id="d112fn3">No documents in the
                                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 10 Series have been
                                        found in the files of the Department of State.</note> and to
                                    conduct other special operations.</item>
                                <label>(8)</label>
                                <item>To fulfill our occupational functions and other international
                                    commitments.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Improvement of our strategic potential to the extent practicable under
                            existing or future agreements by arranging for the coordination of
                            military effort between the United States and nations likely to be
                            associated with us, and through appropriate reciprocal
                            assistance.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Improvement and exploitation of our technical potential through
                            development of new or improved material and methods.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Economic potential and mobilization</hi>. The United States
                    should develop and maintain a constant state of peacetime economic preparedness,
                    a prerequisite for which is the continuous balancing of military, war-supporting
                    industrial, and civilian requirements against the resources <pb facs="0303" n="273" xml:id="pg_273"/> to be available for meeting them. Policies should
                    be shaped toward the following essentials: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Economic stabilization measures designed to strengthen the U.S.
                            peacetime economy plus readiness measures which can be quickly invoked
                            in the event of emergency.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Industrial facilities and essential utilities sufficient to meet
                            immediate requirements in the event of war, plus plans for additional
                            capacity to meet peak war requirements and to offset estimated losses
                            caused by sabotage or direct enemy action.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Strengthening of the U.S. industrial potential thru encouragement of
                            scientific research and technological improvements.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Development of transportation and communication facilities adequate to
                            serve current needs, plus planned reserves for estimated war
                            requirements. Elimination of present bottlenecks where
                            practicable.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Dispersion of industries, services, governmental and military
                            activities now dangerously vulnerable, without undue detriment to
                            essential operations.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Development of dependable sources of critical and strategic
                            materials.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">g</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Stockpiling in appropriate areas of essential quantities of critical
                            and strategic materials.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">h</hi>.</label>
                        <item>More efficient utilization through conservation, substitution, and
                            limitation in use, of materials in short supply.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">i</hi>.</label>
                        <item>More effective utilization and expansion where necessary of the
                            nation’s health resources.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">j</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Preparations for the provision and efficient utilization of manpower
                            which will be capable of satisfying contemplated civilian and military
                            requirements in the event of war.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">k</hi>.</label>
                        <item>A program for housing and community facilities which will meet the
                            requirements for economic mobilization and provide in so far as
                            practicable for the relief of war-damaged areas.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">l</hi>.</label>
                        <item>A program for economic warfare and related wartime economic
                            activities.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">m</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government to provide for
                            efficient transition from peace to war and war to peace.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">n</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Standby emergency powers legislation and executive orders required in
                            the event of war.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Intelligence</hi>. The United States should increase and
                    improve U.S. intelligence and counter-intelligence activity, and in particular
                    assure that activities both at home and abroad are closely coordinated.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Internal security</hi>. In accordance with the provisions of
                    the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 17 series,<note n="4" xml:id="d112fn4">None of the documents in the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 17 Series,
                        which dealt with the internal security of the United States, is
                        printed.</note> the United States should establish and maintain the-highest
                    practicable state of domestic security preparedness, recognizing that further
                    measures will be required in the event of war. The essential minimum
                    requirements include: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Establishing and maintaining more effective controls to prevent the
                            penetration of the United States by potentially or actually dangerous
                            persons through legal or illegal entry.</item>
                        <pb facs="0304" n="274" xml:id="pg_274"/>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Providing closer controls of imports and exports as well as of
                            incoming and outgoing travellers for the purpose of: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Preventing the introduction into the United States of sabotage
                                    and espionage devices.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Preventing the removal from the United States of information,
                                    materials and equipment which if in the possession of
                                    potentially hostile powers would adversely affect the national
                                    security.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Scrutinizing, curtailing, and counteracting, to the maximum extent
                            possible, the open and clandestine activities of communists and other
                            subversive groups, whether party members or not.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Safeguarding critical governmental, industrial and other installations
                            and utilities, affording priority to those considered absolutely
                            essential.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Readying for application in the event of war, civil defense machinery
                            to aid existing agencies in the protection of the nation’s population
                            and resources.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Insuring that the various statutes in the United States Code
                            pertaining to internal security, particularly the Espionage Act of 1917,
                            provide an adequate legal basis for the internal security of the United
                            States in the light of present and probable future conditions.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">g</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Readying a program for controlling the activities, in the event of a
                            war-related emergency, of U.S. citizens and aliens who constitute
                            threats to the nation’s internal security, by apprehension and detention
                            or by other appropriate measures, this program to provide the greatest
                            practicable procedural safeguards to the individual.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">h</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Preparation of a censorship program to be invoked in the event of war
                            or at such time as the Congress may authorize.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Collective strength of non-Soviet nations</hi>. The United
                    States should take the lead in increasing the collective strength of non-Soviet
                    nations by: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Effectively implementing the provisions of the North Atlantic
                            Pact.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Seeking both through measures to increase production and prevent
                            inflation and through the development of favorable trade, credit, and
                            exchange relations, to facilitate economic recovery and promote
                            multi-lateral commercial and financial relations among all parts of the
                            non-Soviet world, to the end that their economic strength shall be
                            mutually increased and self-sustained.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Developing a balanced and coordinated program of economic and military
                            assistance to selected nations of the non-Soviet world able and willing
                            to make important contributions to our security. Such a program should
                            include: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Continuing the Economic Cooperation program so long as U.S.
                                    security is thereby enhanced, to the extent that recipient
                                    nations demonstrate their ability and willingness by self-help
                                    and mutual cooperation to utilize U.S. assistance in
                                    establishing political and economic stability and thereby
                                    increasing the overall potential of the non-Soviet world.</item>
                                <pb facs="0305" n="275" xml:id="pg_275"/>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Providing a flexible and comprehensive program of military
                                    assistance in the form of supplies, equipment and technical
                                    advice in accordance with the approved conclusions of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 14 series.<note n="5" xml:id="d112fn5">For text of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 14/1, July 1, 1948, “Report by the National
                                        Security Council on the Position of the United States with
                                        Respect to Providing Military Assistance to Nations of the
                                        Non-Soviet World,” approved by President Truman on July 10,
                                        1948, see <ref target="frus1948v01p2#pg_585">
                                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, Part 2, p.
                                        585</ref>.</note>
                                </item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Coordinating the economic and military assistance programs and
                                    establishing flexibility of transfer between them, with a view
                                    to furnishing each recipient over-all assistance balanced to
                                    conform to changing circumstances and the requirements of U.S.
                                    security.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Engaging in economic mobilization planning with selected nations when
                            appropriate.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                        <item>To the extent that it increases world stability and U.S. security: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Strengthening world organization by encouraging development of
                                    the United Nations and other international organizations, both
                                    regional and functional.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Wherever practicable, utilizing international organizations
                                    for the handling of international problems and disputes.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Securing, as soon as politically feasible, timely access to and use of
                            those areas throughout the world considered strategically essential to
                            U.S. security.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>7. <hi rend="italic">Political and economic activities</hi>. The United States
                    should by all available means conduct an intensified campaign to: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Encourage in all appropriate ways the political and economic
                            unification of Europe.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Seek to make the Kremlin fear that it is ideologically dangerous to
                            keep an army abroad.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Develop internal dissension within the USSR and disagreements among
                            the USSR and Soviet orbit nations.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Encourage, develop and support anti-Soviet activist organizations
                            within the Soviet orbit.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Defeat communist activities in countries outside the Soviet orbit
                            where such activities constitute a serious threat to U.S.
                            security.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Minimize the export of strategic materials and equipment from the
                            United States and other non-Soviet nations to areas within the Soviet
                            sphere, and conversely, increase the flow of strategic materials now
                            needed for U.S. production and stockpiling purposes.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">g</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Prevent the USSR from achieving a dominant economic or political
                            position in countries in which trade with the United States is essential
                            to our national security.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>8. <hi rend="italic">Foreign information program</hi>. The United States should
                    strengthen, maintain and intensify for as long as necessary, a vigorous
                    coordinated foreign information program directed primarily toward the USSR and
                    its armies, Soviet satellites, countries where there is <pb facs="0306" n="276" xml:id="pg_276"/> a serious communist threat, and countries not sufficiently
                    aware of real Soviet objectives. This program should: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Stress the fact that the Western way of life increasingly offers the
                            greatest and most enduring benefits to the individual, and is therefore
                            destined to prevail over the communist ideology with its inevitable
                            police state methods.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Strive to eradicate the myth by which people remote from direct Soviet
                            influence are held in a position of subservience to Moscow, and to cause
                            the world at large to see and understand the true nature of the USSR and
                            the world communist party, and to adopt a logical and realistic attitude
                            toward them.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Endeavor to strain the relationships between Moscow and satellite
                            governments by encouraging the latter to take independent action within
                            the United Nations and elsewhere.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Encourage the revival of the national life of major national groups
                            within the USSR without committing us to irrevocable or premature
                            decisions respecting independence for national minorities.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Discreetly convey to the Russian and Satellite peoples and soldiers
                            the feeling that Americans are friendly to them, though not to their
                            governments.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>9. <hi rend="italic">Psychological warfare</hi>. In accordance with the
                    provisions of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 43 series, the United
                    States should plan and make preparations for the conduct of foreign information
                    programs and overt psychological operations abroad, in the event of war or
                    threat of war as determined by the President. Such plans and preparations should
                    be consistent with U.S. policy and be coordinated with related planning under
                    the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 10 series and with approved plans for
                    military operations.</p>
                <p>10. <hi rend="italic">Domestic information</hi>. The United States should
                    establish programs to: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Keep the United States public fully informed of Soviet aims and
                            tactics and the threats to our national security arising therefrom, so
                            that the public will be prepared to support measures which we must
                            accordingly adopt.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Explain and support the need of: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>U.S. world leadership and U.S. willingness to assume the
                                    responsibilities arising therefrom.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Non-partisan support of our foreign policy.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Keep the U.S. public informed of the specific nature and types of
                            domestic security threats existing, and of the measures which should be
                            adopted to counteract them.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Provide for a wartime domestic information service in accordance with
                            the provisions of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 43
                            series.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>11. <hi rend="italic">Economic soundness</hi>. In carrying out the above
                    measures, the greatest possible attention must be paid to evaluating essential
                    military, foreign aid, and other national security requirements in the light of
                    the ability of the United States to support such requirements, with <pb facs="0307" n="277" xml:id="pg_277"/> the realization that military
                    preparedness and foreign aid on a scale larger than we have been accustomed to
                    may have to be continued indefinitely. The relative share of government in the
                    total national product and the direction of investment at home and abroad must
                    be carefully scrutinized. The size, timing, and distribution of drafts on
                    materials, facilities, and manpower must be articulated with the operating needs
                    and practices of industry, commerce, and finance so as not to fan inflation,
                    demoralize markets, or weaken incentives to production, any one of which would
                    eventually impair our military capability.</p>
                <p>The United States should endeavor to restrict national security programs from
                    going beyond the level at which fiscal and monetary measures, selective
                    voluntary allocation and standby mandatory allocations meet the needs. If it
                    should be decided to raise expenditures beyond this sensitive zone, this should
                    be done with the full awareness that more comprehensive controls, including
                    price and wage controls may be required, which if long continued might develop
                    resistance to decontrol.</p>
                <p>12. <hi rend="italic">Postwar objectives</hi>. In the event of war the National
                    Security Council should, as soon as possible after the outbreak thereof,
                    formulate measures to accomplish the postwar objectives indicated in paragraphs
                    22 and 23 of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 20/4.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
