<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minutes of the Special Committee of the National Security Council on Atomic
                    Energy Policy With Respect to the United Kingdom and Canada, Department of
                    State, Washington, March 2, 1949, Noon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d163</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">163</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-03-02T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-03-02T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec8a611f7fa402cf8" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic Energy Act of</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-03-02T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-03-02T12:00:00-05:00" n="163"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d163">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of State Atomic Energy Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Special Committee of the National Security
                        Council on Atomic Energy Policy With Respect to the United Kingdom and
                        Canada, Department of State, Washington, March 2, 1949, Noon</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1949-03-02T12:00:00-05:00">March 2, 1949, noon</date>
                </dateline>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Present:</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">Members</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Secretary of State, Dean Acheson, Chairman</item>
                        <item>Secretary of Defense, James V. Forrestal</item>
                        <item>The Acting Chairman, Atomic Energy Commission, Sumner T. Pike</item>
                        <item>Executive Secretary, Sidney W. Souers</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0472" n="442" xml:id="pg_442"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">By Invitation</hi>
                </p>
                <table cols="3" rows="8">
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="3">General Dwight D. Eisenhower<note n="1" xml:id="d163fn1"
                                >President of Columbia University; Principal Military Adviser and
                                Consultant to the President and the Secretary of Defense, February
                                11, 1949–August 11, 1949, during which time he served as Presiding
                                Officer of the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>George F. Kennan</cell>
                        <cell role="brace" rows="2">}</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">Department of State</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>R. Gordon Arneson</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>William Webster</cell>
                        <cell role="brace" rows="2">}</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">National Military Establishment</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Maj. Gen. Kenneth D. Nichols</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Carroll L. Wilson</cell>
                        <cell role="brace" rows="3">}</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">Atomic Energy Commission</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Joseph Volpe</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Ralph Johnson</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p rend="center">I. <hi rend="smallcaps">Consideration of Report to the
                        President</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Committee had before it for action a report for the President prepared, under
                    the direction of Mr. Souers, by representatives of the Department of State, the
                    National Military Establishment, and the Atomic Energy Commission. Certain
                    textual changes proposed by Mr. Pike on behalf of the Commission were <hi
                        rend="italic">approved</hi>. The Committee <hi rend="italic">approved</hi>
                    the report as modified and <hi rend="italic">agreed</hi> that it should be
                    transmitted, through Mr. Souers, to the President with the Committee’s
                    recommendation for approval.</p>
                <p rend="center">II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Method of Implementation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Committee <hi rend="italic">agreed</hi> that, provided the President approved
                    the proposal set forth in the report, the Secretary of State should discuss with
                    the President methods of implementation, particularly as regards consultations
                    with the Congress. Mr. Acheson suggested that it might be appropriate to have
                    the President call together the Chairmen and ranking minority members of the
                    Joint Committee on Atomic Energy and the Senate and House Foreign Relations
                    Committee for one or more informal meetings to discuss the problem. At this
                    stage the proposed U.S. negotiating position would be discussed in general
                    terms. If these leaders were found to be in favor of the general line of action
                    proposed, informal soundings, noncommitting in nature, should then be taken with
                    the British and Canadians to determine in general whether the proposed
                    arrangements would be acceptable to them. If so, the matter might then go to
                    executive session of the full committees for consideration. Appropriate action
                    would be sought from the Congress in order that formal negotiations could be
                    undertaken.</p>
                <p>Mr. Acheson remarked that the studies of the working group concluded that the
                    arrangements proposed with the United Kingdom and Canada were based on the
                    grounds of promoting the common defense and security. The question arose
                    whether, in view of the provisions of the Atomic Energy Act of 1946, this
                    conclusion should be reflected in some positive action by the Congress as for
                    example a joint resolution.</p>
                <pb facs="0473" n="443" xml:id="pg_443"/>
                <p>General Eisenhower expressed the view that the proposed arrangement would restore
                    that mutual trust and confidence among the three nations so essential to the
                    strengthening of our own common defense and security. He stated that he was
                    prepared to testify at any time to the effect that the proposed arrangement
                    would greatly strengthen the common defense and security.</p>
                <p rend="center">III. <hi rend="smallcaps">Interim Status of Technical Cooperation
                        Under the “Modus Vivendi”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In response to a question by Mr. Pike whether technical cooperation as provided
                    for in the <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> of January 7, 1948 should be
                    continued as presently laid down, Mr. Acheson stated that to seek at this
                    juncture to attempt to restrict technical cooperation might have a serious
                    effect on the success of prospective negotiations. The Committee agreed that
                    existing technical cooperation within the approved areas should continue.</p>
                <p>The meeting adjourned at 1:05.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>R. <hi rend="smallcaps">Gordon Arneson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
