<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Paper Prepared in the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d316</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">316</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-07-31T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-08-22T22:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86005172"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific research</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-08-22T22:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-07-31T23:00:00-05:00" n="316"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d316">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Under Secretary’s Meetings: Lot 53D250</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Paper Prepared in the Department of State</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d316fn1">Neither the source text nor an identical copy
                        included in Executive Secretariat Files, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                        21 Series, bears any indication of drafting or originating office or
                        officers, but the paper appears to have been prepared in the Division of
                        Northern European Affairs. The source text was circulated to the members of
                        the Under Secretary’s Meeting (top officers of the Department of State who
                        met as often as each week under the chairmanship of Under Secretary of State
                        James Webb to consider major policy problems) as document <gloss
                            target="#t_UM1">UM</gloss> D–52, August 1. For the subsequent
                        disposition of this paper, see the memorandum of August 22 by Assistant
                        Secretary of State Perkins to Under Secretary of State Webb, <hi
                            rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates"
                            calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1949-08-22T23:59:59-04:00"
                            notBefore="1949-08-01T00:00:00-04:00">undated</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Antarctica</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">problem</hi>
                </p>
                <p>To decide upon the next steps to be taken for the implementation of policy on
                    Antarctica.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">background</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In June 1948 a policy paper on Antarctica was prepared by <gloss target="#t_SP1"
                        >S/P</gloss> and approved (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>–21 paper of
                    July 13, 1948<note n="2" xml:id="d316fn2">For text of the policy paper under
                        reference here, <gloss target="#t_PPS1">PPS</gloss> 31, June 9, 1948, see
                            <ref target="frus1948v01p2#pg_977">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, Part 2, p. 977</ref>.</note>). The gist of
                    this was that control of territory in the Antarctic region is not essential to
                    the security of the United States; the potential worth of Antarctica is chiefly
                    scientific; in view of renewed activity and interest in the area and
                    increasingly acute conflicts of interests, a settlement is desirable. The paper
                    recommended that the United States support in principle the establishment of an
                    international status for Antarctica; that upon agreement by the other interested
                    governments to negotiate an international settlement, the United States in order
                    to make its status uniform with that of the other nations concerned, announce a
                    claim. This paper was accepted by the Joint Chiefs of Staff with the comment
                    that control of the Antarctic area should be maintained in the hands of friendly
                    powers and that possible enemies of the United States should be excluded from
                    possession of any part of the area and from participation in any international
                    administration.</p>
                <p>Identical <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoires</hi> were handed on June [<hi
                        rend="italic">August</hi>] 9 and 10, 1948 to the missions in Washington of
                    Argentina, Australia, Chile, France, Great Britain and Norway suggesting that a
                    solution of the Antarctic territorial problem be discussed on the basis of
                    internationalization (condominium). At the same time it was stated orally and
                    confidentially to these missions that the United States would expect to announce
                    an Antarctic claim in the near future.<note n="3" xml:id="d316fn3">For text of
                        the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> under reference here, see <ref
                            target="frus1948v01p2#pg_996">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 996</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The British accepted our proposal as a basis of discussion. The New Zealanders
                    indicated favorable interest. The Norwegian reply (possibly <pb facs="0831"
                        n="801" xml:id="pg_801"/> not a firm position) viewed internationalization
                    as unnecessary and as presenting certain national and international
                    difficulties. French thinking is similar to the Norwegian. The Australians have
                    indicated approval of scientific cooperation, skepticism about the necessity for
                    internationalization but a desire to cooperate in working out a solution.
                    Argentina rejects our proposal even as a basis for discussion, on grounds of
                    national sovereignty, but offers assurances of its desire to cooperate in
                    seeking a solution of the problem.</p>
                <p>Chile found our proposal unacceptable on grounds of national sovereignty, alleged
                    inconsistency of the proposal with the Rio Defense Treaty, and doubts as to the
                    wisdom of internationalization. Chile proposed consideration of a <hi
                        rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi>, a freeze of the <hi rend="italic">status
                        quo</hi> as to claims for a period of 5–10 years, and an agreement for
                    scientific cooperation.</p>
                <p>The United States Navy is planning an expedition for the 1949–50 season. (The
                    expedition has not received final Naval approval.) The Department has obtained
                    permission for use by the Navy of port, landing and fuel facilities in New
                    Zealand.</p>
                <p>The British appear anxious for the United States to announce its claim, probably
                    because of their interest in placing the United States in a position similar to
                    the British vis-à-vis Argentina and Chile. The British have also said that if
                    the United States does not plan to follow up on its suggestion, they will
                    consider undertaking bilateral settlements with the Argentines and with the
                    Chileans.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">proposed course</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The positions of the various countries listed above indicate the impossibility of
                    obtaining agreement now on our proposal. <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss> and
                        <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss> have therefore been studying the
                    possibility for action which might lead to ultimate agreement upon
                    internationalization. The best prospect seems to be offered by the Chilean
                    suggestion, modified in order to bring it more closely into line with the United
                    States proposal and to channel its operation towards a final settlement
                    consistent with the terms proposed by the United States.</p>
                <p>Briefly, an interim <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> along the lines of the
                    Chilean proposal, as the United States would desire to modify it, would: Declare
                    the desire of the eight signatories to avoid conflicts in Antarctica; state that
                    they are engaged in conversations looking toward a solution and are disposed to
                    consider and discuss suggestions for methods of settling the territorial
                    problem; that for a period of 5 or 10 years (possibly longer) any activities
                    carried out in the area will not prejudice such territorial rights as now exist
                    [the United States would, of course, make its claim before entering this
                        arrangement]<note n="4" xml:id="d316fn4">Brackets appear in the source
                        text.</note>
                    <pb facs="0832" n="802" xml:id="pg_802"/> and will not be invoked against other
                    signatories as a basis for claims to sovereignty; that the signatories will
                    grant to government and nationals of each of the other signatories permission to
                    conduct exploration and scientific research in the area of its claim; that
                    exchange of scientific information will be carried out amongst the signatories,
                    which signatories will encourage the dispatch of scientific and technical
                    expeditions to the area; and that the signatory governments will create a
                    commission to assist in coordinating plans for expeditions and to have the
                    authority on behalf of the signatory countries to grant permission to countries
                    other than the signatories to conduct explorations and scientific investigations
                    in the area; the signatories will act in cooperation for the advancement of
                    their common interests and protection of their rights in the area; prior to the
                    expiration of the arrangement, the governments will consult regarding the
                    advantages of meeting in an Antarctic conference.</p>
                <p>In April 1949, <gloss target="#t_NOE1">NOE</gloss> drafted a recommendation,
                    concurred in by <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>, that the United States
                    attempt to obtain an interim arrangement along the above lines (although it is
                    far from certain that the proposal would be accepted by Argentina). In May 1949
                    this recommendation was reviewed by <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>, which
                    considered that the proposed line of action falls within the general scope of
                    the basic policy decision, and that the details require no further action by
                        <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>.</p>
                <p>If this line of action is to be followed, the next steps would be (1) to consult
                    with the British as to their general attitude, and if the British raise no
                    serious objection, (2) consult with the Chileans concerning the manner of
                    bringing the suggestion actively to the attention of the governments concerned.
                    (It seems preferable that this be done by the Chileans if they are agreeable.)
                    For purposes of easing the political tensions which recur annually during the
                    season when expeditions are in the area, it would be desirable to have this
                    suggestion under active consideration this fall.<note n="*" xml:id="d316fn5"
                        >Although the principal objectives of the proposed Naval expedition for the
                        1949–50 season are cold weather training, exploration and scientific
                        research, the planned flights will afford a basis for strengthening and
                        expanding the prospective United States claim. However, in the somewhat
                        unlikely event of an agreement along the above lines being concluded prior
                        to the 1949–50 season, the activities of the expedition could not be used
                        for this latter purpose. (The Department, in its exchange of communications
                        with the Navy on this project, pointed out that an international solution
                        was under discussion and that if a solution were reached before the date of
                        the expedition, the expedition would, naturally, have to conform to its
                        terms.) [Footnote in the source text.]</note> Moreover, the Chileans have
                    recently taken up their suggestion in its original form with the British, whose
                    reply will be influenced by our attitude. It is therefore desirable that a
                    decision be made.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">recommendations</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is recommended that the line of action summarized above be approved.</p>
                <pb facs="0833" n="803" xml:id="pg_803"/>
                <p>It is recommended that a letter be addressed to the Secretary of Defense
                    informing him of the proposed step, and the reasons therefor.<note n="†"
                        xml:id="d316fn6">In view of the <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss> opinion
                        cited above that this line of action falls within the scope of the basic
                        policy decision, it is believed that the <gloss target="#t_NME1">NME</gloss>
                        need not be consulted as to this action, especially as it takes full account
                        of the JOS desire that control be retained in friendly hands and that
                        probable enemies be excluded. [Footnote in the source text.]</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
