<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting United States Representative at the United
                        Nations (
                        Ross
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d37</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">37</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-06-29T18:19:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-06-29T18:19:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="regulation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662" lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-06-29T18:19:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-06-29T18:19:00-05:00" n="37" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d37">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.<gloss target="#t_BC1">BC</gloss>
                    Armaments/6–2949: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Acting United States Representative at the United
                        Nations</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ross</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-06-29T19:19:00-04:00">June 29, 1949—7:19 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>788. Following is sent with reference to current consideration by <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss> of <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> resolution
                    of November 19, 1948 and future work of <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss>.</p>
                <p>On May 26 French introduced as their paper based on <gloss target="#t_RAC1">RAC</gloss> D–34<hi rend="italic">e</hi> (<gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>.3/<gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>.3/21).<note n="1" xml:id="d37fn1">For text, see Report of the
                        Commission for Conventional Armaments to the Security Council (<gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>/1372), August 9, Sections I and II, <ref target="#pg_107">pp. 107</ref> and <ref target="#pg_109">109</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>On June 20, <gloss target="#t_RAC1">RAC</gloss> D–34/2d was given to
                    representatives of France, Canada and UK as possible section III to complete
                    French paper in accordance with <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 319 of
                    June 6 [<hi rend="italic">16</hi>].<note n="2" xml:id="d37fn2">Telegram 319 to
                        New York, June 16, not printed, indicated that document <gloss target="#t_RAC1">RAC</gloss> D–34/2d, not printed, was being transmitted
                        to the United States Mission for discussion with French, British, and
                        Canadian representatives preparatory to its introduction if possible by the
                        French in the Working Committee as Section III of their working paper
                            (501.<gloss target="#t_BC1">BC</gloss> Armaments/6–1649).</note>
                </p>
                <p>In view of strong and clear position taken by Soviet member in working committee
                    attacking proposal of census and verification of conventional armaments and
                    effectives as called for by <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> resolution,
                    unlikely that <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss> deliberations will go beyond
                    majority approval of set of general proposals consisting substantially of
                    present French proposals plus something like our proposed section III. In view
                    further of shortness of time which exists for formulation of such proposals, it
                    is also felt that this would be about as much as could be expected in order to
                    submit report on that resolution to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> and 4th
                    session of <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>. We feel that this will be
                    sufficient to indicate on one hand an honest set of proposals within framework
                    of <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> resolution considered and approved by
                    majority, and on other hand fundamental nature of opposition to <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> resolution by Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>Under these circumstances it appears possible to vote on proposals during latter
                    part of July and thus have majority approved proposals for report to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> on subject
                        <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> resolution which we would be prepared to
                    support in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>. After that has been done <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss>
                    could revert to discussions based on its approved plan of work with realization,
                    however, that <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss> will probably be unable to
                    formulate plans for establishment of system for regulation of armaments which
                    will be acceptable to all since Soviet Union has failed to agree with majority
                    on principles considered to be basic to formulation of plans for such
                    regulation.</p>
                <p>It is also hoped that prior to next <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> session,
                        <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss> may be able to submit to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> second progress report (<gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>.3/32/Rev. 1) which includes
                    findings on items one and two of plan of work.<note n="3" xml:id="d37fn3">See
                        footnote 3, <ref target="#pg_12">p. 12</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0109" n="79" xml:id="pg_79"/>
                <p>In preliminary conversations on this subject, representatives of France, Canada
                    and UK have expressed themselves unofficially in general agreement with views
                    expressed above.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ross</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
