<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Joseph S. Sparks, Adviser, United States Delegation to the
                            General Assembly</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d93</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">93</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-11-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-11-09T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-11-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-11-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="93" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d93">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">IO Files: US/A/AC.31/207</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. <persName type="from">Joseph S. Sparks</persName>, Adviser, United States Delegation to the
                            <gloss type="to">General Assembly</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-11-09">November 9,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I met Sir B. N. Rau this morning prior to the opening of the <hi rend="italic">Ad
                        Hoc</hi> Political Committee and Mr. Hickerson’s address,<note n="1" xml:id="d93fn1">For the record of the 32nd Meeting of the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Political Committee, November 9, see <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>(IV), <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc Political Committee</hi>, p.
                        179.</note> to explain to him our position in connection with the Indian
                    resolution on Atomic Energy.</p>
                <p>I told Sir B. N. Rau that we had given the most thorough and careful
                    consideration to his resolution, and that we had also examined very carefully
                    Mr. Malik’s address of yesterday afternoon.<note n="2" xml:id="d93fn2">At the
                        31st Meeting of the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Political Committee,
                        November 8, Yakov A. Malik, the Soviet Representative, submitted draft
                        resolution A/AC.31/L.28. This proposal specifically assigned responsibility
                        to the United States and the United Kingdom for the failure of the United
                        Nations Atomic Energy Commission to reach agreement and read in operative
                        part as follows: “[The General Assembly] Instructs the Atomic Energy
                        Commission to resume its work to give effect to the General Assembly
                        resolutions of 24 January and 14 December 1946 and forthwith to proceed to
                        the preparation of a draft convention for the prohibition of atomic weapons
                        and a draft convention for the control of atomic energy, it being understood
                        that both conventions should be concluded and put into effect
                        simultaneously.” For full text, see <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>(IV),
                            <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc Political Committee, Annex</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 69. For the record of the 31st Meeting, see
                            <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>(IV), <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc
                            Political Committee</hi>, p. 173.</note> I said <pb facs="0248" n="218" xml:id="pg_218"/> that it was evident to us from Mr. Malik’s address that
                    the Soviet bloc had not moved in any way from its stubborn and unproductive
                    position, and that we had reluctantly concluded that it was not possible for us
                    to support the Indian resolution. I said that we were particularly sorry about
                    this decision because of our great esteem and respect for Sir B. N. Rau and our
                    recognition of the constructive motives which were behind his resolution, but
                    that we felt that any approach to the Atomic Energy question which did not
                    include a complete about-face in the Russian stand would be futile and perhaps
                    even dangerously misleading. I said that because of our great personal respect
                    for Sir B. N. Rau, Mr. Hickerson would refrain from mentioning the Indian
                    resolution in his address this morning, and that we hoped that it would not
                    become necessary for us to actively oppose it.</p>
                <p>Sir B. N. Rau said that he understood our position, and that he had not really
                    expected the United States to support the Indian resolution. He said, however,
                    that he was convinced in his own mind that his resolution would not hurt us at
                    all, and that it would actually help us. He said that as he would probably
                    observe later in the debate, it seemed to him that the delegations on this
                    question were divided between those who sought to make whatever headway they
                    could, and those who were unimaginative and opposed to partial headway. He said
                    that in particular he felt that the New Zealand Delegation fell in this last
                    category. I said that I was confident that his observation of the United States
                    in the United Nations as a whole had convinced him that we, at least, did not
                    belong in this category. He said that that was so.</p>
                <p>Sir B. N. Rau said that he particularly hoped that the United States would leave
                    other countries alone to make up their minds on this question independently. He
                    referred to an experience which he had last year, in which the Greek Delegation
                    told him on a particular question that they had wanted very much to support it,
                    but were not permitted to do so. I assured Sir B. N. Rau that the United States
                    hoped to be able to avoid anything even approaching a campaign against the
                    Indian resolution, but told him that should we be asked by other delegations
                    what our position was, we would, of course, have to make it perfectly clear that
                    we were in support of the French-Canadian resolution as the only measure which
                    we felt productive at this time. Sir B. N. Rau said that this was agreeable to
                    him, and that he very much appreciated the frankness of our discussion and the
                    basis on which we had determined our position. He said that he had listened most
                    anxiously to the Soviet speech yesterday, as he had been afraid that the USSR
                    might support his resolution. Had they done so, he said that, of course, the
                    resolution would have been killed thereby.</p>
                <p>Sir B. N. Rau repeated the statement which he has made several times before in
                    private conversation, that the majority plan, in effect, <pb facs="0249" n="219" xml:id="pg_219"/> contemplates a form of world government. He said that as
                    ardent a devotee to the concept of eventual world government as he might be, he
                    was sufficiently realistic to know that world government in any form would not
                    come into existence during his lifetime. It was apparent that our various
                    explanations on this point have made no impression on Sir B. N. Rau and I should
                    be surprised if he did not at least mention this aspect of the problem prior to
                    conclusion of the debate.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
