<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Secretary of State to
                        the Legation in Hungary</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d18</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">18</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-09-17T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-09-17T14:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-09-17T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-09-17T14:00:00-05:00" n="18" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d18">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 EW(Peace)/9–1747: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Legation in Hungary</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-09-17T15:00:00-04:00">September 17, 1947—3 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>990. Following is guidance for exercise duties devolving on Heads of Mission in
                    peace treaty. <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>In general you should take firm positive attitude towards these
                            responsibilities. It is assumed ex-satellite Govts will attempt to avoid
                            their obligations to western countries and will be aided and abetted in
                            this by Soviets. Since Sovs will control key governmental ministries we
                            anticipate serious difficulties in dealing satisfactorily with Govt
                            directly. On other hand experience gained in previous dealings with Sovs
                            on tricornered basis has demonstrated procedural pitfalls and
                            frustration which would result in setting up formal tripartite council.
                            You should therefore in initial stages avoid seeking concert in your
                            approach to Govt on treaty matters, particularly in regard to obtaining
                            info. You should interpret third para of first article of Part VIII to
                            give you firm right to receive all info necessary to fulfill your duties
                            under treaty through ordinary dipl channels.</item>
                        <pb facs="0044" n="30" xml:id="pg_30"/>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Question of freedom of movement should not be raised with Govt or Sovs
                            as US Reps should assume right to travel freely within country, except
                            in Sov troop areas during 90-day evacuation period. Travel in latter
                            areas should be avoided since we do not wish to establish precedent of
                            having to ask for travel permits. When restrictive action by Sovs or
                            Govt forces issue, report to <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> for
                            instructions.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Part II of treaty. You will be instructed separately what action US
                            will take re specified implementation political clauses, particularly
                            violation of human rights article.<note n="1" xml:id="d18fn1">For
                                documentation on the action of the United States in protesting to
                                the Rumanian Government the violation of political and civil
                                liberties in Rumania, see <ref target="#pg_471">pp. 471</ref>–<ref target="#pg_513">513</ref>
                                <hi rend="italic">passim</hi>.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Part III and IV. Instructions on military clauses being transmitted
                            separately by cable and airmail.<note n="2" xml:id="d18fn2">Telegram
                                1037, October 2, to Budapest, repeated to Sofia as 410, to Bucharest
                                as 601, to Moscow as 1803, and to London as 4255, not printed,
                                stated that the State–War–Navy Coordinating Committee and the Joint
                                Chiefs of Staff had approved the instructions relative to the
                                military clauses of the peace treaties, as well as the general
                                background documents on the treaty negotiations which were being
                                sent to the various posts by airmail. The telegram added the
                                following instructions: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“As indicated therein, in order to establish basis gauge
                                        compliance treaty, Govt should now be requested to inform
                                        you (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) present strengths, location
                                        and composition of country’s armed forces and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) plans for implementing treaty
                                        articles which should include proposed Table of Organization
                                        and Equipment.” (740.0011 EW (Peace)/9–1747)</p>
                                </quote>
                            </note>
                        </item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Part V, VI and VII. Tentative implementation guidance for economic
                            clauses being airmailed. Pending receipt final guidance,<note n="3" xml:id="d18fn3">Draft instructions for reporting on and ensuring the
                                execution of the economic clauses of the Peace Treaties with
                                Hungary, Rumania, and Bulgaria, as prepared by the Balkan Committee
                                of the Department of State, were transmitted to the Legation in
                                Budapest and the Missions in Bucharest and Sofia by air mail during
                                September. After these draft statements had been commented upon by
                                the posts, they were revised, placed in final form and sent as
                                instructions 55 to Budapest, 18 to Bucharest, and 385 to Sofia, all
                                December 10, none printed. These instructions, each of which
                                included more than 30 typewritten pages, are included in file
                                740.0011 EW (Peace)/11–447).</note> Mission should advance treaty
                            work by collection of all relevant data on US claims and violations
                            property restoration and general economic relations articles.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>When info at your disposal indicates a treaty violation report to
                                <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> for instructions.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Sent Budapest, rptd Sofia, Bucharest, Moscow; and London for <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss>.<note n="4" xml:id="d18fn4">This telegram
                        was repeated to Sofia as 381, to Bucharest as 573, to Moscow as 1744, and to
                        London as 4031.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
