<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Chief of the
                        Division of Southern European Affairs (Barbour)</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d226</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">226</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-06-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="226" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d226">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">864.00/6–647</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Chief of the
                        Division of Southern European Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Barbour</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-06-06">June 6,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>The Hungarian Minister, Aladár Szegedy-Maszák;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Matthews and Mr. Hickerson, EUR;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Barbour, <gloss target="#t_SE1">SE</gloss>.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The Hungarian Minister called on the afternoon of June 5 at the request of
                    Messrs. Matthews and Hickerson. Mr. Matthews was not able to be present at the
                    first part of the conversation and Mr. Hickerson had to leave before the
                    conversation was concluded.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hickerson received the Minister and informed him that the purpose in
                    requesting him to call was merely in order that Messrs. Matthews and Hickerson
                    could express to him personally their admiration for the courageous step he had
                    taken in the light of recent developments in Hungary. Mr. Hickerson went on to
                    elaborate on his realization of the difficulties of the Minister’s position and
                    the gravity of the issues involved. Mr. Hickerson added that the Department was
                    contemplating, subject to final approval, action in the Allied Control
                    Commission and subsequently possibly in the United Nations. He referred to the
                    statements made by the President at his press conference earlier in the
                        day.<note n="1" xml:id="d226fn1">At his press conference on June 5,
                        President Truman characterized the situation in Hungary as an outrage and
                        stated that the United States would not stand by idly. For the text of the
                        transcript of the press conference, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of
                            the Presidents of the United States: Harry S. Truman, 1947</hi>
                        (Washington: U.S. Government Printing Office, 1963), pp. 262–266.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0328" n="312" xml:id="pg_312"/>
                <p>The Minister then raised the question of his status vis-à-vis the United States.
                    Referring to his note informing the Department that he did not regard the
                    present Hungarian Government as a free agent and was consequently not prepared
                    to execute its orders, he stated that he has not resigned and that he hoped to
                    continue relations with the US Government. He inquired concerning our intentions
                    with regard to Minister-designate Chapin.<note n="2" xml:id="d226fn2">Selden
                        Chapin’s nomination as Minister to Hungary had been confirmed by the Senate
                        on April 9. He left the United States on June 27 and arrived in Budapest on
                        July 2.</note> Mr. Hickerson expressed the opinion that Mr. Chapin would
                    proceed to Budapest and take up his position as Minister as planned. Mr.
                    Szegedy-Maszák, demonstratively dejected, indicated that, in these
                    circumstances, the US would consider his Mission as terminated and that he had
                    resigned. He drew a parallel between his status and the status of the Czech
                    Minister in this country when the Nazis overran Czechoslovakia in 1939 and made
                    it clear that he strongly hoped that a comparable arrangement could be made for
                    him. Giving it as his opinion that the continuance of relations between the
                    United States and the new Government would be contrary to the course
                    contemplated by this Government to protest developments which led to the
                    Government’s installation, the Minister seemed unable to comprehend our
                    intention that Mr. Chapin assume his post. Mr. Matthews, who had returned to the
                    conversation, said that the US is determined to follow the course which seems
                    best for Hungary and inquired whether the Minister would feel that we would be
                    serving that end in withdrawing our representation from Hungary as would be
                    necessary if we continued to maintain official relations with him. The Minister,
                    after profound reflection, said “no”, that we should by all means maintain
                    ourselves in Hungary but that he had hoped that some middle course could be
                    found whereby it would be possible “to keep the door open”. Mr. Matthews pointed
                    out that we could not have it both ways and that we had to take one course or
                    the other. Mr. Matthews assured the Minister, at length, that we would be happy
                    to have him continue to reside in this country with such members of his staff as
                    would wish to do so as private citizens and that we would welcome friendly
                    contact with him in that private capacity. Mr. Matthews added that we hope the
                    Minister wall be disposed to keep in touch with us and to make available to us
                    such information as he receives from time to time which would be of
                    interest.</p>
                <p>The Minister, although obviously depressed, assured Mr. Matthews of his
                    appreciation of this Government’s courtesies to him while on official mission,
                    of his constant desire not to embarrass the US Government in any way and
                    declared on leaving that in all the circumstances he considers his official
                    mission as concluded.</p>
                <pb facs="0329" n="313" xml:id="pg_313"/>
                <p>In the course of the conversation, the Minister also stated that he contemplated
                    giving a press conference on June 6 and asked whether the Department had any
                    objection to his releasing for publication the note he had addressed to the
                    Secretary on June 2 concerning the latest developments in Hungary.<note n="3" xml:id="d226fn3">Ante, <ref target="#pg_304">p. 304</ref>.</note> Mr.
                    Matthews replied that the Department did not have objection to such
                    publication.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
