<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the United States Mission at the United
                    Nations in New York</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d265</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">265</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-09-25T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-09-25T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-09-25T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-09-25T18:00:00-05:00" n="265"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d265">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB/9–2547: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">United States Mission</gloss> at the United Nations in
                        New York</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-09-25T19:00:00-04:00"
                            >September 25, 1947—7 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>422. Assistant Secretary Armour today received former Prime Minister Nagy of
                        Hungary<note n="1" xml:id="d265fn1">A memorandum of conversation dealing
                        with this meeting, prepared by Frederick T. Merrill of the Division of
                        Southern European Affairs and dated September 25, is filed separately under
                        501.BB/9–2547.</note> who stated he was going to New York this afternoon to
                    join his colleagues the Bulgarian Agrarian politician Dimitrov<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d265fn2">Dr. George M. Dimitrov, head of the Bulgarian National
                        Agrarian Union, in exile.</note> and the Croat peasant leader Machec<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d265fn3">Dr. Vladko Maček, head of the Croatian Peasant Party,
                        in exile.</note> in an attempt, to interest several <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> Delegations including Cuba, Brazil and Australia to introduce in
                    this session of the Assembly a Resolution based on Article 14 raising the
                    question of Soviet indirect aggression in Eastern Europe. The Cuban Ambassador
                    has apparently given them an indication that he is receptive but made it clear
                    that he would be reluctant to introduce so controversial a question unless
                    assured in advance of substantial support from other Delegations. Nagy requested
                    that the <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> not oppose any such resolution
                    should it be put forward and even asked if it might not be possible for the
                        <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> to indicate discreetly to these
                    delegations that we would give it support. Mr. Armour replied that although he
                    was sympathetic he could of course give no opinion or encouragement in advance
                    of knowing exactly <pb facs="0398" n="382" xml:id="pg_382"/> what the three
                    Agrarians were proposing. Nagy promised us a copy tomorrow.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d265fn4">A copy of the paper under reference here, a communication
                        from the Central Committee of the International Peasant Union to the
                        President of the General Assembly of the United Nations, is attached to the
                        memorandum of conversation cited in footnote 1, above. The communication was
                        transmitted to the General Assembly by the International Peasant Union on
                        September 28, but no action was taken on it.</note>
                </p>
                <p>We feel that in view of the surcharged agenda of this Assembly and of the number
                    of important items put down by the <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> which
                    are obviously construed by USSR as inimical to its interest, it would be
                    unfortunate for this additional and highly controversial subject to be brought
                    before the Assembly at this session. Our previous thinking has been that
                    problems of clandestine aggression might more suitably be dealt with by the
                    proposed interim commission.</p>
                <p>At the same time, and in light of the President’s statement characterizing the
                    change in power in Hungary as an “outrage”, we do not feel that the Delegation
                    should openly oppose a resolution along the lines suggested by Nagy, Dimitrov
                    and Machec. You are authorized, however, in private conversation with other
                    delegations to intimate our feeling that, in view of the technical legal grounds
                    on which the Russians might base a convincing if spurious case, and in view of
                    the other important matters pending before this session, we should not be
                    unhappy if the question of Russian covert aggression against Hungary and other
                    Southeastern European states were left over for the interim commission.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
