<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Poland ( (Lane) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d287</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">287</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-02-24T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-02-24T04:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="reckOJp7RF2apAIO3" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85004558"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Amnesty</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recYmlCrc3Fe9WvIx" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028935"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Offenses</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-02-24T04:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-02-24T04:00:00-05:00" n="287"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d287">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">860C.00/2–2447: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Poland</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lane</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Warsaw</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-02-24T10:00:00+01:00"
                            >February 24, 1947—10 a. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>313. For the Secretary. In farewell talk with Mikolajczyk Feb 20 he said to me
                    new “little” constitution recently passed by Sejm puts absolute power in hands
                    of councils of state as follows:</p>
                <p>National Council of State composed of President of Republic Bierut (Communist);
                    Marshal of Sejm Kowalski (Communist); three vice <pb facs="0436" n="420"
                        xml:id="pg_420"/> marshals Zambrowski (Communist), Barcikowski (Communist)
                    and Szwalbe (Socialist partial to Communists) and three members to be elected by
                    Sejm (probably will be Communists); Councils of State in each wojwostwo;
                    Councils of State in each powiat; and Councils of State even in the smallest
                    villages. According to Mikolajczyk this govt by councils of state will put
                    complete control of nation in hands of Communists and will remove from Council
                    of Ministers and from Sejm last vestige of authority. He said that from now on
                    there is absolute dictatorship in Poland.</p>
                <p>Foreign observers including certain diplomatic representatives have expressed to
                    me frankly apprehension re steps which are obviously in direction of
                    Sovietiziation of Poland. I concur with them and with Mikolajczyk (and also with
                    Zulawski former head of old Socialist Party whose last speech at Sejm
                    complaining re deletion first speech was completely expunged from congressional
                    record) that Communists feeling themselves firmly seated in saddle will now
                    gradually take over complete control. Socialists for time being will be
                    permitted, these observers comment, to have the impression they are still a
                    potent factor in govt but as matter of fact it is probable [Cyrankiewicz?] will
                    be allowed merely preside over meetings Cabinet which in any case will not be
                    able make decisions of policy.</p>
                <p>It would be foolish on my part to predict whether or not Poland eventually will
                    be incorporated within Soviet Union. But it is clear that whatever the technique
                    employed the policy of Poland’s Communist masters is to bring Poland more and
                    more under Communist domination. The “little” constitution clearly demonstrates
                    this intention.</p>
                <p>Mikolajczyk and others have also commented to me re misleading provisions of
                    amnesty decree. They recognize govt’s gesture to reassure Polish people by
                    forgiveness for their political opposition but they say that these persons
                    released temporarily under amnesty law in order that govt may obtain advantages
                    (such as credits from US) can of course be rearrested as soon as need
                    arises.</p>
                <p>On Feb 22 made farewell calls on <gloss target="#t_ForMin1">ForMin</gloss>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d287fn1">Zygmunt Modzelewski.</note> and on other <gloss
                        target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> officials. When Modzelewski referred to
                        Mine’s<note n="2" xml:id="d287fn2">Hilary Mine, Minister of Industry and
                        Commerce and a leader in the Polish Workers’ Party (Communist), who had
                        headed a Polish economic delegation which visited the United States in
                        November–December 1946.</note> recent trip to US and to satisfaction of
                    Polish Govt’s results I took occasion to mention that while International Bank
                    could not under its charter be influenced by political considerations in
                    granting or refusing credits it could and in my opinion would be influenced by
                    fact that good faith or lack of <pb facs="0437" n="421" xml:id="pg_421"/> good
                    faith is an element to be considered as to whether a govt requesting credits is
                    or is not a good credit risk.</p>
                <p>I took occasion to express my personal opinion on this my last visit to <gloss
                        target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> that Polish Govt had made great mistake
                    despite my repeated pleas since August 1945 to continue its attacks thru the
                    press and otherwise against US. I expressed personal hope that govt would adopt
                    more friendly attitude to US and concluded with statement that altho we desired
                    friendship with Poland I thought US could still continue as great power without
                    friendship of Polish Govt, that I doubted whether Poland could thrive without
                    support of US.</p>
                <p>Modzelewski said that press attacks were merely propaganda and that we should not
                    regard them too seriously. He said that as soon as the western frontiers are
                    settled conditions would quickly be normalized. Amnesty for political offenses
                    would also accelerate pacification which would include <hi rend="italic">inter
                        alia</hi> amelioration of relations with east (cynicism of this remark is so
                    patent as to require no comment on my part).</p>
                <p>I again urge <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> as well as our Govt’s
                    representative on International Bank to give no favorable consideration to any
                    request for economic or financial assistance to Poland until I have had an
                    opportunity to discuss whole problem in Washington.</p>
                <p>Keith was present at above mentioned talks with Mikolajczyk, Zulawski,
                    Modzelewski and other <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> officials.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lane</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
