<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-04-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-04-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="288" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d288">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.60C/4–347</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the
                                Division of Eastern European Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Thompson</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-04-03">April 3, 1947</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Ambassador<note n="1" xml:id="d288fn1">The Polish Ambassador, Jozef
                                Winiewicz.</note> said that he was very much disturbed at the course
                            which Polish-American relations were taking and that he wished to talk
                            quite frankly about them. In the course of a very long discussion the
                            Ambassador expounded the thesis that there was a division in the Polish
                            Government. One group felt that if Poland tied itself to the Soviet
                            Union economically it would be brought down to the economic level of
                            that country and that Poland should therefore develop its relations with
                            the west to the maximum extent possible. The other group, and he
                            observed that this included many non-communists, felt that Poland was
                            already so far in the Soviet orbit that it would be impossible to hope
                            for any assistance from the west and that the only possibility was for
                            Poland to throw its lot in completely with that of the Soviet Union. The
                            Ambassador observed that the <pb facs="0438" n="422" xml:id="pg_422"/>
                            recent developments in American-Polish relations furnished ammunition to
                            the latter group. He mentioned specifically the following: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Polish inability to secure American assistance for the
                                    purchase of American cotton.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>The difficulty in purchasing ships under the Ships Purchase
                                    Act.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>The fact that former Ambassador Lane had held a press
                                    conference at which he bitterly attacked the Polish Government,
                                    at the State Department, in circumstances which implied that his
                                    remarks were inspired and supported by the Department of
                                        State.<note n="2" xml:id="d288fn2">On March 25, the
                                        Department of State announced the resignation of Ambassador
                                        Lane effective March 31. For the texts of Ambassador Lane’s
                                        letter of resignation to President Truman, dated March 21
                                        and the President’s reply of March 25, see Lane, <hi rend="italic">I Saw Poland Betrayed</hi>, pp. 301–302.
                                        The Ambassador’s personal press conference at the Department
                                        of State referred to here occurred on April 1.</note>
                                </item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>Indications which he had received in discussions with
                                    Congressmen that Poland might not even be able to obtain food
                                    relief.</item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>Our failure to sign the agreement on compensation for the
                                    nationalization of American property in Poland. His government
                                    had thought that the negotiation of this agreement would be one
                                    of the most useful things it could do to diminish friction
                                    between the two governments but we had not ratified the
                                    agreement because of some legal technicality.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Ambassador said he was fully aware of our position that the Polish
                            elections had not come up to American standards but that he felt they
                            had been as fair as possible in view of the necessity, imposed by
                            circumstances, of preventing violent anti-Soviet elements from gaining
                            control.</p>
                        <p>He added that he felt it was his duty as Ambassador to do everything
                            possible to improve relations and he asked my opinion as to whether I
                            though it would be useful for him to have a frank discussion of these
                            problems with Mr. Acheson.</p>
                        <p>In reply, I confined myself chiefly to commenting upon the specific
                            points the Ambassador had raised.</p>
                        <p>I said that with respect to the Polish desire to purchase ships, I
                            understood that the Polish Government now desired to purchase one of
                            these ships for cash. I said that one of the factors in determining
                            which of the claimants should have priority was the extent to which the
                            tonnage of the country’s shipping had already been restored. I said that
                            in this respect Poland was comparatively not badly off. I said, however,
                            that I understood that the Polish request was under active consideration
                            and that there appeared to be a very good possibility that the only ship
                            now available would be allotted to Poland.</p>
                        <p>With respect to Mr. Lane’s remarks, I pointed out that Mr. Lane had
                            carefully explained to correspondents that he was receiving the press at
                            the State Department solely as a matter of convenience because <pb facs="0439" n="423" xml:id="pg_423"/> he was keeping his office
                            there for a few days in order to clean up some of his affairs. I agreed
                            that it was unfortunate that, despite this, the press had played up the
                            fact that the conference was held in the State Department.</p>
                        <p>With respect to relief, I said I did not think I needed to assure him of
                            the genuineness of the humanitarian feelings of the American people and
                            government. I pointed out that the Department had included Poland in the
                            countries for which authorization to grant relief had been requested,
                            but said that of course actual relief would depend upon need and, in any
                            event, this was now a matter for congressional action. I remarked that
                            there were many people in Congress and a large part of the American
                            public that thought that, because of the abuses that had taken place and
                            the political misuse of American relief funds, we were frequently played
                            for suckers and that there was therefore a natural tendency to wish to
                            insure that no one took advantage of our humanitarian instincts.</p>
                        <p>With respect to the question of the compensation agreement, I said I
                            could assure him of our desire to complete this agreement and that the
                            legal point that had arisen was not a pretext. I showed him a copy of an
                            opinion from the Legal Adviser in this matter that had just reached my
                            desk, and said that we were holding almost daily meetings in an effort
                            to see how this difficulty could be overcome. I said that despite our
                            anxiety to complete the agreement we felt that we were obliged
                            scrupulously to live up to our obligations under the Charter of the
                            United Nations.</p>
                        <p>With respect to the general question of Polish-American relations, I said
                            I thought their improvement would depend largely upon two things. The
                            first was the trend of developments in the general international
                            situation, and the second was the course of developments within Poland
                            itself. Pointing out that I was now speaking personally, I said that our
                            policy was based upon a genuine interest in the Polish people and that
                            if the Polish Government would succeed in winning the support of the
                            Polish people and develop within Poland the individual liberties to
                            which this country was so attached I was sure it would have a favorable
                            effect on Polish-American relations. I said I did not think that this
                            country would be willing to try to “buy” Polish orientation to the west
                            but rather that it was up to Poland, by its actions, to merit assistance
                            from this country.</p>
                        <p>I said that while I would be glad to request an appointment with Mr.
                            Acheson for him at any time my personal opinion was that it would be
                            better to defer the conversation until somewhat later.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador said that while he would regard my remarks as personal he
                            would be glad if I would bring his remarks to Mr. Acheson’s
                            attention.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Llewellyn</hi> E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Thompson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>