<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Smith) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d367</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">367</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-02-24T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-02-24T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receKRNx87Ug7K5bW" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106111"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Pravda</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-02-24T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-02-24T10:00:00-05:00" n="367"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d367">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.00B/2–2447: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-02-24T18:00:00+03:00"
                            >February 24, 1947—6 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>523. Emb 450 February 18.<note n="1" xml:id="d367fn1">Not printed.</note> One of
                    the most hopeful signs we have recently seen is article in February 17 <hi
                        rend="italic">Pravda</hi> on schism in working class movement. But before
                    commenting further, we would say something by way of background.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding failures and disappointments during past 30 years, Kremlin still
                    places great reliance upon mobilization of world proletariat to advance Soviet
                    expansion. While Kremlin no longer entertains illusions that it can engineer
                    world revolution at one stroke, it has good reason to believe that if through
                    its propaganda and international agents it succeeds in winning support of even
                    bare majority of workers of world and then harnessing them to its program, it
                    will have gone long way towards subjecting rest of world to its will. Aggressive
                    Soviet sponsorship of <gloss target="#t_WFTU1">WFTU</gloss> and attempts to
                    manipulate it in furtherance of Soviet political aims is evidence of Soviet
                    intentions in this direction.</p>
                <p>Soviet attempts to mobilize world proletariat encounter two general forms of
                    active opposition. One is repressive; for example, policy of Chinese and Greek
                    Governments. Other is competitive; for example, activities of British Labor
                    Government and <gloss target="#t_AFL1">AFL</gloss>. Repression is effective
                    where government is firmly established and workers weak and unorganized, as in
                    Turkey. But in most other countries outside Soviet orbit, repressions often
                    boomerang, sometimes disastrously.</p>
                <pb facs="0552" n="536" xml:id="pg_536"/>
                <p>Competition for proletarian support by strong, independent and nationalist labor
                    organizations is fundamentally more effective because it offers an affirmative
                    alternative to Communism and thus exerts an attractive influence on proletariat
                    nullifying possibility that proletariat gravitate en masse toward reliance upon
                    and subjection [to] USSR. Finally competition does not—as repression does—feed
                    sense of persecution, the psychological state most suspectible to Soviet
                    exploitation.</p>
                <p>It is with foregoing in mind that we say <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> article on
                    schism in working class is hopeful sign. Soviet anxiety revealed in that article
                    is indication that British Labor Party and Government are competing effectively
                    for proletarian support not only in Britain but also in Europe. Possibility that
                    large segments of western and central European workers look to British rather
                    than to USSR for guidance and support threatens major set-back to Kremlin
                    plans.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_AFL1">AFL</gloss> has played somewhat similar role in Germany,
                    Latin America and Japan and has as consequence drawn bitter attacks in Soviet
                    press. If <gloss target="#t_AFL1">AFL</gloss> activities along these lines are
                    increased and skillfully pursued, they, too, will constitute major impediment to
                    Kremlin efforts to capture workers of the world.</p>
                <p>Department repeat to Tokyo, Nanking, London as Moscow’s 59, Paris 45, Berlin
                    50.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
