<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chargé in Yugoslavia
                        (Cabot)Transmitted to
                        the Department as enclosure 2 to despatch 673, March 3, from Belgrade, not
                        printed.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d536</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">536</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-03-01T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-03-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="536" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d536">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.60H/3–347</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chargé in Yugoslavia</hi>
                        (<hi rend="italic">Cabot</hi>)<note n="1" xml:id="d536fn1">Transmitted to
                        the Department as enclosure 2 to despatch 673, March 3, from Belgrade, not
                        printed.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Belgrade</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-03-01">March 1,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>General Velebit gave me an appointment at my request to continue our
                    conversations of February 25.<note n="2" xml:id="d536fn2">See Cabot’s memorandum
                        of conversation, <ref target="#pg_765">p. 765</ref>.</note> I said that in
                    our previous talk I had asked him to mention any further specific grievances he
                    had and make suggestions as to what might be done. He immediately referred again
                    to Trieste. I pointed out that this was a matter which had already been
                    determined and that nothing could be done about it. I said that the only matter
                    which he mentioned that I thought anything might be done about was the question
                    of war criminals. He said that another very important matter for Yugoslavia was
                    the question of reparations. Yugoslav representatives had been to the British
                    and American Zones in Germany but had not been able to get any German machinery
                    and equipment as payment in kind for reparations. Yugoslavia was a poor country
                    which had been much devastated by the war and desperately needed these German
                    assets. Why should the United States block their delivery?<note n="3" xml:id="d536fn3">For documentation regarding the attitude of the United
                        States on the problem of German reparations, see <ref target="frus1946v05#pg_481">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1946, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 481</ref> ff.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0788" n="772" xml:id="pg_772"/>
                <p>I replied that I frankly was not familiar with the matter but that I would
                    immediately inquire about it. With regard to the broad matter of reparations we
                    were paying large sums of money to keep the German and Italian people from
                    starvation and we therefore did not want reparations to be paid indirectly out
                    of our relief funds. We also had a claim to reparations, but we were not
                    pressing it.</p>
                <p>General Velebit launched into a lengthy dissertation about how Yugoslavia needed
                    reparations and how unnecessary they were to the United States. He pointed out
                    that American productive capacity had increased very much during the war, and
                    that the United States did not need the German reparations, whereas Yugoslavia
                    did. He said that at the recent Brussels Conference Yugoslavia had received but
                    6,000 tons of shipping, despite the fact that their merchant fleet had sunk from
                    450,000 to 80,000 tons. Despite the enormously greater American expenditures and
                    losses, Yugoslavia should receive more proportionately in reparations because of
                    its greater needs.</p>
                <p>Having let this talk run its course, when he ended I pointed out that I had
                    mentioned our right to reparations only to illustrate the fact that we had an
                    interest in reparations and in the demilitarization of the fascist powers which
                    conflicted at only the one point I had mentioned with Yugoslavia’s. I said that
                    I would immediately seek to ascertain what my Government’s views were in regard
                    to the use of German machinery and equipment for Yugoslav reparations. General
                    Velebit emphasized that Yugoslavia had been waiting for two years for these much
                    needed reparations.</p>
                <p>I asked whether he had any other matters to mention and he said that there were
                    many other matters but that these were the principal ones. He again insisted
                    that the fundamental point was that we had been unrelentingly hostile to them
                    and that this had awakened a deep resentment in Yugoslavia. He referred again to
                    the Trieste ultimatum and said in answer to a question on my part that Marshal
                    Tito had only promised General Alexander<note n="4" xml:id="d536fn4">British
                        Field Marshal Sir Harold Alexander served as Supreme Allied Commander,
                        Mediterranean Theater, 1944–1946.</note> to keep open Allied communication
                    lines with Austria, not to stay out of Trieste.</p>
                <p>I then said that I would like to mention some of our grievances to him. I said
                    that from our viewpoint Yugoslavia had shown unfriendliness to the United States
                    before the United States had shown any unfriendliness to Yugoslavia. I
                    remembered how at the San Francisco Conference<note n="5" xml:id="d536fn5">Chargé Cabot had served as a member of the United States Delegation to the
                        United Nations Conference at San Francisco, April–June 1945. For
                        documentation on that conference, see <ref target="frus1945v01">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> Yugoslavia had invariably voted with the Soviet Union. At
                    that time relations between the United States and the Soviet Union <pb facs="0789" n="773" xml:id="pg_773"/> were relatively friendly but as they
                    deteriorated it was natural that relations between the United States and
                    Yugoslavia should also have deteriorated. Yugoslavia was an independent nation
                    which had every right to choose whatever course in international affairs it
                    chose to adopt, as it conceived its national interests. Any nation had that
                    privilege but any nation having adopted a course must accept its implications as
                    they affected its national interests for better or for worse. I said that this
                    situation had been accentuated by a number of incidents which had arisen between
                    the United States and Yugoslavia and which had resulted in lasting resentment
                    against Yugoslavia.</p>
                <p>General Velebit showed signs of annoyance and said that if that was the reason I
                    had come to talk to him that it was quite useless; that he had thought I was
                    anxious to clear up the disagreements between Yugoslavia and the United States
                    but that this was an entirely different matter.</p>
                <p>I said that I had merely wished to speak frankly on the situation as I saw it. I
                    had no desire to discuss the general framework of the international relations
                    but I believed that even within that framework it would be possible to take
                    constructive action to relieve the tension. I hoped that by clearing away
                    specific grievances something might be accomplished. I said that the United
                    States deplored the controversies which had arisen with Russia and hoped that
                    they might be settled because we fully recognized that the peace and prosperity
                    of the world depended on understanding and cooperation between the two greatest
                    powers in the world. I said that we felt it was particularly unfortunate that
                    misunderstandings should now have arisen when there had never before been a
                    serious clash of interests between our two nations. Unfortunately that was, of
                    course, a situation which I could do nothing about, but that I did hope that
                    constructive action might relieve the tension in the area of Yugoslav–American
                    relations. I said that I would like to mention to him some of the specific
                    matters which gave us concern.</p>
                <p>I first mentioned the whole matter of the Embassy immunities. I pointed out that
                    all Embassies were entitled to certain immunities and that they were given
                    others by binding international custom. These immunities had been invaded, in my
                    opinion, in a series of cases. In the Wedge case,<note n="6" xml:id="d536fn6">On
                        May 1, 1946, William A. Wedge, who had for some time been employed as a
                        guard by the Embassy at Belgrade, ran into and killed a Yugoslav officer
                        while driving an Embassy jeep without authorization and allegedly under the
                        influence of alcohol. Wedge was taken into custody by the Yugoslav police,
                        and in early September 1946, he was tried and convicted by a Yugoslav court
                        and sentenced to 8 years in prison. The United States Government considered
                        that Wedge was entitled to diplomatic immunity, regardless of the
                        circumstances attending the incident in which he was involved, and continued
                        to press the Yugoslav authorities to recognize that immunity and to effect
                        Wedge’s release. In this connection, see the record of the conversation of
                        September 17, 1946, between the Acting Secretary of State and the Yugoslav
                        Ambassador, <ref target="frus1946v06#pg_951">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1946, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 951</ref>. In March 1947, Wedge’s
                        sentence was reduced to 6-years imprisonment. Wedge was finally released
                        from prison and allowed to leave Yugoslavia in March 1949.</note> although
                    Wedge was undoubtedly guilty of serious <pb facs="0790" n="774" xml:id="pg_774"/> misconduct there were many precedents establishing that the nationals of a
                    country sending a mission who was attached to that mission in any capacity
                    enjoyed immunity. We had offered an indemnity, and we felt that Wedge’s immunity
                    should be recognized.</p>
                <p>I went on to say that one Embassy translator had been shot and two were now in
                    prison. With regard to the man who had been shot, he was dead and the officer
                    who was alleged to have connived with him (although he denied it) was no longer
                    in the service. That was a closed issue. But with regard to the other two
                    translators I said I had no information regarding the charges against one and
                    the other was vaguely charged with “inciting against the regime”. In the absence
                    of clear evidence of a serious crime by these translators we naturally felt in
                    the Embassy that these arrests were an effort to harass us and impede our
                    legitimate activities.</p>
                <p>I went on to point out quite apart from any question of Embassy immunities I
                    could not understand how it was practically advantageous to the Yugoslav
                    authorites to act as they had in these cases. These incidents awakened a
                    resentment wholly out of proportion to their intrinsic importance not only in
                    the Embassy but also in Washington. He had referred to our hostility to
                    Yugoslavia in major questions; it was difficult for officials in making policy
                    decisions to overlook incidents which though petty were nevertheless very
                    irritating.</p>
                <p>I said that a relatively minor matter which I wanted to raise was the restriction
                    placed by the Yugoslav authorities on travel by Americans in this country. I
                    pointed out that the Treaty of 1881 (Commerce and Navigation)<note n="7" xml:id="d536fn7">Department of State Treaty Series No. 319.</note> clearly
                    prohibited such restrictions and I consequently hoped that it would be possible
                    to rescind these restrictions. I said with a smile that they were particularly
                    annoying for Embassy personnel who liked to leave the city for a picnic. General
                    Velebit’s only comment was that he was familiar with the treaty.</p>
                <p>I said that another source of petty annoyance to us was the fact that we had not
                    been able to obtain visas for the men assigned to the Graves Registration Unit.
                    We were anxious to clear this matter up and I hoped that they would shortly be
                    forthcoming. We greatly appreciated the courtesy of the Yugoslav authorities in
                    offering 400 soldiers to help with the Graves Registration work. I mentioned
                    that I had given instructions that the 75 Yugoslavs who were going to <pb facs="0791" n="775" xml:id="pg_775"/> Austria to bring back the Yugoslav
                    river boats should be granted visas even though it might have been possible to
                    have held these visas up until we received visas for the Graves Registration
                    work. He said rather testily that the United States occupied Austria on behalf
                    of the Allied Powers. I replied that there was a more important consideration in
                    my decision; since we had agreed to the return of the river boats I felt that
                    our good faith was involved in facilitating the men’s departure. Nevertheless I
                    felt that this evidenced my desire to prevent unnecessary controversies.</p>
                <p>I said that one other matter I wished to mention to him was our plans for our
                    celebration of Memorial Day. Last year an unfortunate incident had arisen and I
                    said that we would be very sure that nothing like that happened again this year.
                    We were planning a simple ceremony but would appreciate any participation which
                    the Yugoslav civil and military authorities might wish to take in this ceremony.
                    I would appreciate it if he would let me know the views of the Yugoslav
                    authorities in this connection.</p>
                <p>By clearing up these relatively minor matters I hoped that we might get to some
                    more important ones such as the Yugoslav gold and our claims. General Velebit
                    said that we were going at the problem from entirely different angles. He wanted
                    major problems dealt with first whereas I was suggesting that we handle minor
                    ones. I said whereas it was true that I had brought up relatively minor ones, at
                    the same time I had, as I already informed him, telegraphed to find out the
                    Department’s views regarding the war criminals situation<note n="8" xml:id="d536fn8">See footnote 9 to Cabot’s memorandum of conversation, <ref target="#pg_768">p. 768</ref>.</note> and I would immediately try to
                    ascertain the Department’s views regarding German reparations in kind.</p>
                <p>General Velebit rather brusquely mentioned that he had an appointment at one
                    o’clock and the conversation then ended. The entire conversation was distinctly
                    less affable than our conversation of February 25.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi> M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Cabot</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
