<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Reinsch to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1916</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d100</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">100</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1916-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1916-07-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-07-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="100"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d100">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.00/2512</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Reinsch</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1155</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-07-31">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 31, 1916</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In continuation of my despatch No. 1143 of the
                    14th instant, I have the honor to submit further observations on the present
                    political situation. It is difficult to give any clear and definite information,
                    as there are a great many currents and countercurrents of intrigue and
                    influence, but the following notes are submitted for any value they may have in
                    keeping the Department informed.</p>
                <p>There are enclosed herewith two clippings from the <hi rend="italic">Peking
                        Gazette</hi> of to-day, dealing with the present situation.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d100fn2">Not printed.</note> The breach between the Chin Pu Tang and
                    the Kuo Min Tang has become still more apparent, and for the time being the
                    advantage of political tactics seems to lie with the latter party. The rump
                    parliament, which is to be convened to-morrow, will probably be controlled by
                    the Kuo Min Tang leaders, who have secured the allegiance of His Excellency Sun
                    Hung-yi, Minister of the Interior. This politician is not generally credited
                    with a very high character; he formerly had Chin Pu Tang affiliations, but
                    recently a violent wordy encounter occurred between him and Tang Hua-lung in
                    Shanghai, in which they expressed quite frankly their opinion of each other.
                    This sign of an evident breach was followed by Sun’s allying himself with the
                    Kuo Min Tang, under Tang Shao-yi. It is believed that he carried with him nearly
                    fifty per cent of the Chin Pu Tang parliamentarians, most of whom arrived under
                    his aegis in Peking last week.</p>
                <p>The game of the Chin Pu Tang to have their men appointed governors of the
                    provinces in order to control the next parliamentary election has evidently
                    aroused the other party, which now aims at not only controlling the present rump
                    parliament, but the entire Government, including the provinces. The Chin Pu Tang
                    members in parliament seem to be flirting with the monarchical members. The
                    monarchists are, however, at heart entirely suspicious of and thoroughly opposed
                    to both of the revolutionary parties.</p>
                <p>His Excellency Tuan Chi-jui is kept in the Cabinet in order to control the
                    military. It is believed that Tang Shao-yi desires to make His Excellency Feng
                    Kuo-chang Minister of War. The other generals would, however, not be favorable
                    to such a proposal. The military are maintaining a waiting attitude. Most of
                    them seem to be persuaded that, with all the partisan bickerings and intrigues
                    likely to be consequent upon the assemblage of Parliament, neither of the
                    revolutionary parties will be able to maintain itself and that the balance of
                    power will be in the hands of the military. Some of the latter are plainly in
                    favor of a monarchical restoration. His Excellency Hsu Shih-chang, the
                    ex-Premier, appears to be busier than he has been for years; his visitings and
                    activities are believed to be relative to his loyalty to the Ching Family.</p>
                <p>A Cabinet Minister stated to me that telegrams had been discovered which revealed
                    an intrigue on the part of Liang Chi-chao to put Tuan Chi-jui in the place of
                    President Li. Such a policy if <pb facs="0167" n="91" xml:id="pg_91"/> really
                    pursued could only be accounted for by a desire of Liang Chi-chao to ally
                    himself with the military, utilizing the control exercised by General Tuan.</p>
                <p>It is generally expected that should Tang Shao-yi become Premier, he would try
                    entirely to dominate the political situation, with the result of thoroughly
                    antagonizing the military party. In order to strengthen himself, he has come to
                    an understanding with the most radical wing of the Kuo Min Tang, including Sun
                    Yat-sen and Huang Hsing. He has of late constantly expressed himself as
                    persuaded that the Japanese Government has entirely changed its attitude toward
                    China; and that, having realized that a conquest or coercion of China is
                    practically impossible, Japan will now pursue a policy of friendly cooperation.
                    It would therefore appear that Mr. Tang is actually desirous of giving the
                    Japanese the impression that he desires to cooperate with them. What his
                    attitude would be after he should feel himself assured in power with certain
                    assistance from Japanese sources, would remain to be seen. It is also believed
                    here that before accepting the premiership, Mr. Tang would assure himself
                    specifically of financial support from Japanese or other sources.</p>
                <p>The situation for the next few weeks and also the political future of China in
                    general is therefore quite uncertain. It is to be hoped that Parliament will
                    disappoint its critics by not attempting to interfere with every branch of the
                    Government, and that it may submit to the leadership of responsible and
                    experienced men, themselves animated by a desire to put an end to factional
                    fights and to begin constructive work. Most observers would say that this is
                    probably too much to expect, yet there is undoubtedly a chance at hand to take a
                    step in advance in the working of representative institutions in China,
                    notwithstanding all the difficulties in view.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Paul S. Reinsch</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
