<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-12-22T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-12-22T16:00:00-05:00" n="1277" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1277">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 817.51/855</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                Minister <persName type="to">Jefferson</persName>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram—Extract]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-12-22T16:00:00-05:00">
                                    <hi rend="italic">December 22, 1916, 4 p.m.</hi>
                                </date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Your December 14, 2 p.m.</p>
                        <p>1. Conference was held in Washington on December 18 between
                            representatives of State Department and of bankers of Nicaragua under
                            the auspices of the Pan American Permanent Nicaraguan Committee of the
                            United States with Mr. W. L. Saunders as chairman, looking toward a
                            satisfactory settlement of Nicaragua’s financial situation.</p>
                        <p>As a result of the conference the Department expressed itself as not
                            being opposed to the performance of Nicaragua’s contract with Ethelburga
                            and that Ethelburga’s interest and sinking fund up to January 1, 1917,
                            should be paid out of the Canal fund, thereby releasing funds held by
                            collector of customs and allowing Nicaragua to receive that part of the
                            customs receipts which have been held for Ethelburga.</p>
                        <p>The Department is endeavoring to arrange postponement for three years of
                            future interest and sinking fund payment in order to release further
                            funds. These funds should meet pressing needs of Nicaraguan Government
                            and enable Chamorro to enter upon his term of office with a fairly clean
                            slate.</p>
                        <p>2. The Department has also given its consent to the practical performance
                            of the bankers’ wishes based on their contract of December 2, 1914, by
                            means of a general arrangement to include the settlement of all of
                            Nicaragua’s indebtedness to the satisfaction of all concerned as far as
                            possible.</p>
                        <p>The final sense of the conference was as follows: That the arrears of the
                            Ethelburga debt should be paid out of the Canal fund as soon as
                            possible; that the claims adjudicated by the Mixed Commission and all
                            domestic and foreign claims against the Government should be
                            investigated by a commission, consisting of two Americans and one
                            Nicaraguan, and scaled down as far as possible; and that upon the
                            results of this investigation combined with the already ascertained
                            amounts of the foreign debts, as a basis of liquidation, the whole
                            Nicaraguan debt should be practically refunded by an arrangement
                            involving the assistance of the bankers and the issue of bonds secured
                            by a second lien on the customs, and a first lien on 49% of the stock of
                            the railroad and National Bank, and the payment of claims by the
                            delivery of such bonds where possible.</p>
                        <p>Department also considers it imperative that legislative decree be issued
                            immediately forming commission to study conditions of indebtedness and
                            ample scope must be given commission to compel disclosure of facts and
                            give all facilities to ample investigation.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Lansing</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>