<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-03-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="349" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d349">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 814.032/6</note>
                        <head ana="#head_untitled-inferred-from-preceding-sibling-head">[Untitled]</head>
                        <dateline>[<date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1916-03-01">March 1,
                            1916</date>]</dateline>
                        <p>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Note.</hi>—The message was read to the Assembly on
                            March 1, 1916, and transmitted to the Secretary of State on March 14,
                            1916, by the American Minister. The following are the only passages
                            referring to the United States.]</p>
                        <p rend="center">[Translation]</p>
                        <p>Guatemala took a brilliant part in the Panama-Pacific International
                            Exposition, opened on February 20 and closed on December 4, 1915,
                            celebrating the completion of the canal which unites the two oceans and
                            makes an open road for all the commerce of the world—an accomplishment
                            achieved by the gigantic effort of the United States of North
                            America.</p>
                        <p>On account of the liberal tendency of her people, who admire every great
                            thing, Guatemala was the first to accept the President’s courteous
                            invitation, not only because of the magnitude of the undertaking but
                            also because she could thus show to the noble American people the esteem
                            in which they are held by the people and the Government of
                            Guatemala.</p>
                        <p>All the ceremonies held in the Guatemalan pavilion were very popular, as
                            we gather from the American press, especially the dedication of the
                            pavilion on March 15, Guatemala Day, September 15, and Coffee Day,
                            November 20. On these occasions the officials of California, the board
                            of directors of the exposition, and San Francisco society expressed high
                            praise of Guatemala and her Government. In all the congresses held
                            during the exposition this Republic was represented by delegates who in
                            many cases received the high distinction of honorary presidents, which
                            was an undoubted honor to our country; but the most important
                            distinction was the grand prize awarded to the coffee, bananas, cocoa
                            and rubber of Guatemala, in competition with the best products of other
                            nations, which is indeed gratifying to our patriotic pride. Besides the
                            above-mentioned grand prizes, we were awarded 32 medals of honor, 69
                            gold medals, 99 silver medals, 88 bronze medals, and 327 honorable
                            mentions, without counting the commemorative diplomas.</p>
                        <p>In accordance with a resolution of the Pan American Financial Congress
                            held in Washington from the 24th to the 29th of May, it was decided to
                            establish a financial committee in each of the participating countries.
                            Therefore, by a decree issued on August 7, the Guatemalan Committee was
                            organized under the chairmanship of the Secretary of Finance and Public
                            Credit. The above-mentioned committee is at present studying the
                            subjects that are to be dealt with in the Buenos Aires conference which
                            is to meet on the 3d of next April, from which is expected a real
                            benefit to the commerce and finances of America.</p>
                        <p>The European war has demonstrated to the nations of America that theirs
                            should be a policy of close friendship, good understanding and unity.
                            The spirit of Pan Americanism has taken hold in every one of these
                            nations and Guatemala felt that she should participate in this movement
                            which is a consequence of obvious needs, stands for noble aspirations
                            and interprets the ancient and patriotic <pb facs="0385" n="309" xml:id="pg_309"/> ideals of the great men of the three Americas, who
                            dreamt of the real and practical union of the free nations comprising
                            them.</p>
                        <p>Consistent with these ideas, the Government of the Republic participated
                            through its representatives in the deliberations of the financial
                            conference held at Washington in the month of May, in which all the
                            American countries discussed financial questions, both economic and
                            commercial, and at the same time initiated a new era in business, which
                            will undoubtedly be beneficial to the mutual interests of the
                            participating countries.</p>
                        <p>A spirit of fraternity and cooperation was also manifested in their
                            memorable deliberations. I refer to the Second Pan American Scientific
                            Congress, which met in the latter part of last year in the City of
                            Washington; in it a road was opened where justice would obtain in all
                            the nations by founding an American Institute of International Law, and
                            a new situation arose in the political life of these nations, the
                            suitability of all uniting as one, reciprocally to safeguard their
                            complete political independence and their territorial integrity, the
                            solution of their frontier questions, the settlement of their
                            misunderstandings and disputes by means of arbitration; of all agreeing
                            that no one of the American countries would allow revolutionary
                            expeditions to leave its soil to attack another American State, nor
                            permit revolutionists of one American State to supply themselves with
                            war munitions in any other. Based upon such principles, treaties will be
                            entered upon in legal form by the respective Governments.</p>
                        <p>Another beneficial result of these ideals is the joint action of several
                            American Governments to procure the pacification of Mexico. The
                            Government of Guatemala was invited to participate in the mediation
                            together with the United States, the Argentine Republic, Bolivia,
                            Brazil, Chile and Uruguay. The situation of Mexico was discussed at a
                            number of meetings held in the cities of Washington and New York; as a
                            result, the Government of General Carranza was recognized as a <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> government, considering that he had
                            under his authority the greater part of Mexican territory. It is to be
                            hoped that this step, which was immediately ratified by the remaining
                            countries of America and afterwards by the European Powers, may
                            contribute to the reestablishment of peace in the neighboring Republic.
                            As States immediately adjoining Mexico, Guatemala and the United States
                            of North America have suffered some of the consequences of the troubled
                            conditions of that nation, both Governments having been obliged to take
                            the proper precautions to have neutrality respected and to protect the
                            inhabitants of the frontier localities; and, thanks to such measures, I
                            am very glad to inform you, Gentlemen of the Congress, that the
                            perturbations resulting from such a state of affairs have been
                            suppressed energetically and quickly, and therefore peace and order
                            follow their normal course.</p>
                        <p>The ties which unite us to the United States are every day growing closer
                            and more cordial. I have already mentioned some of the congresses of a
                            Pan American nature which have brought together the governments of the
                            continent, with one another and very specially with their originator—the
                            Government of the United States—and with the political and economic
                            elements of the Great Republic.</p>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>