<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Secretary of Legation Davis to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1916</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d352</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">352</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1916-01-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1916-01-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recbmmC3Qhr3E4JGh" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112309"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Political refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec8uqG4zFwFzxdlO" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104422"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Political prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recItilmdY8wKocmo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005329"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Conservation</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-01-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-01-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="352"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d352">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 838.00/1375</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Secretary of Legation <persName type="from">Davis</persName>
                        to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-01-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 12, 1916</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to submit herewith a memorandum
                    of the events attending the overthrow of President Vilbrun Guillaume Sam and the
                    happenings immediately thereafter.</p>
                <p>I regret that press of work at the Legation made it impossible for me to prepare
                    this report during the time I was on duty at Port au Prince as Chargé
                    d’Affaires. I have now prepared the same from notes and memoranda made at the
                    time.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">R. B. Davis, Jr.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0387" n="311" xml:id="pg_311"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">memorandum</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Summary of conditions existing in the Republic of Haiti
                        immediately prior to the overthrow of the Government of President Vilbrun
                        Guillaume Sam, and of events attending the overthrow of that Government</p>
                    <p>Pursuant to the request that I prepare a statement of the events attending
                        the overthrow of the Government of President Vilbrun Guillaume Sam and of
                        his assassination, I have the honor to submit the following report:</p>
                    <p>Since 1886—when General Salomon completed his first term of office—there have
                        been twelve Presidents of Haiti, no one of whom has served his full term of
                        seven years. Of these twelve, four have been killed and six driven from
                        office.</p>
                    <p>Below is given a list of these Presidents with the duration of their
                        respective terms: <table cols="2" rows="13">
                            <row>
                                <cell>General Salomon</cell>
                                <cell>1879–1886 (full term)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>General Salomon</cell>
                                <cell>1886–1888 (killed after two years)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>General Hippolyte</cell>
                                <cell>1889–1896 (died near close of term)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>General Simon Sam</cell>
                                <cell>1896–1903 (overthrown)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>General Nord</cell>
                                <cell>1903–1908 (overthrown)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>General Antoine Sam</cell>
                                <cell>1908–1911 (overthrown)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>General Cincinnatus Leconte</cell>
                                <cell>1911–1912 (killed in office)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>General Tancrede Auguste</cell>
                                <cell>1912–1913 (killed in office)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>General Michel Oreste</cell>
                                <cell>1913–1914 (overthrown)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>General Oreste Zamor</cell>
                                <cell>1914—Jan. to December (overthrown)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>General Davilmar Theodore</cell>
                                <cell>1914–1915—Dec. to April (overthrown)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>General Vilbrun Guillaume Sam</cell>
                                <cell>1915—April to July (killed in office)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Senator Sudre Dartiguenave</cell>
                                <cell>1915–</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>Before recounting the events of the 27th and 28th of July, 1915, when the Sam
                        Government was overthrown and the President assassinated, I beg to recall
                        briefly to your attention the conditions which existed in the Republic of
                        Haiti immediately prior to this time, conditions which alone made possible
                        the appalling atrocities accompanying the overthrow of this Government.</p>
                    <p>At the time of my arrival at Port au Prince in August, 1914, General Davilmar
                        Theodore, at the head of a revolutionary army, was attempting the overthrow
                        of the Zamor Government.</p>
                    <p>This rebellion had been in progress since the inauguration of President
                        Oreste Zamor, who, as a successful revolutionary chief, only a few months
                        prior to this time, had overthrown the Government of President Michel
                        Oreste, after which the Haitian Congress had met and elected him President
                        of Haiti. Prior to my arrival, the revolution of Theodore had assumed such
                        alarming proportions that President Zamor had left Port au Prince personally
                        to assume command of the Government troops in the north.</p>
                    <p>The Davilmar Theodore Revolution, as are all revolutions in Haiti, was
                        successful. President Zamor after having been forced to retreat as far south
                        as the town of Gonaives, with the remnant of his army which had not already
                        deserted and joined the revolutionists, was there surrounded; and seeing
                        that further resistance was futile he abandoned his army, boarded a steamer
                        and left the Island without ever having been able to return to the
                        Capital.</p>
                    <p>As soon as the news that President Zamor had quit the country reached Port au
                        Prince, the members of his Cabinet, who in his absence had been charged with
                        the conduct of the affairs of the Government, at once abandoned their posts
                        and sought asylum in the foreign Legations, and for three days chaotic
                        conditions prevailed in Port au Prince as well as in all other parts of the
                        Island. There was no Government of any sort, and in the Capital a
                        self-appointed Committee of Public Safety was the sole authority to which
                        one might look for protection and prevention of pillage, burning, and other
                        forms of disorder. These conditions prevailed until the arrival of General
                        Theodore at the head of his army. He was at once elected President, taking
                        the oath of office on November 10, 1914.</p>
                    <p>From the outset the Theodore Government found itself confronted by
                        insurmountable obstacles; the treasury empty, revolutionary debts
                        multitudinous, and practically all of the Government revenues, already
                        diminished by the stagnation of business and agriculture resultant from
                        continued revolutions, <pb facs="0388" n="312" xml:id="pg_312"/> pledged for
                        the payment of loans contracted by previous Governments. One instance will
                        suffice to illustrate the penniless condition of this Government. A
                        schooner, loaded with coal destined for the use of the Haitian gunboats, <hi
                            rend="italic">Pacifique</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Nord Alexis</hi>, lay
                        for weeks at the dock with its cargo undischarged because the Government was
                        unable to secure the relatively small sum necessary to pay for the same.</p>
                    <p>Various expedients were resorted to by the Government in its efforts to
                        rehabilitate the finances of the Republic. An issue of 8,000,000 gourdes,
                        paper currency, was authorized; but the pressing need of money to be
                        immediately available made it impossible for the Government to await the
                        arrival of these bills, which were being manufactured in the United States.
                        To tide over the time until they should become available another issue of
                        bills, to be printed at Port au Prince, was authorized. This proved to be a
                        most disastrous move, the only result being still further to depress the
                        value of the Haitian currency, and to increase popular dissatisfaction
                        against the Government. These bills, printed on cheap white paper, and
                        having nothing of the appearance of the money to which they were accustomed,
                        would not be accepted by the Haitians of the ignorant classes. As the
                        soldiers were paid in this currency, innumerable petty difficulties arose as
                        a result of their attempts to force its acceptance in payment for food
                        stuffs in local markets and other places. This money was no more acceptable
                        to the better classes. Knowing that there was in existence a contract
                        entered into between the Haitian Government and the National Bank of Haiti,
                        which gave to that organization the exclusive right to issue currency, and
                        realizing the weakness of the Theodore Government, it was feared that a
                        succeeding Government would repudiate this issue; and therefore it was
                        accepted only when refusal to do so might lead to trouble with the
                        Government.</p>
                    <p>Under these conditions the Theodore Government, upon the outbreak of a
                        revolution, could offer no effective resistance, and General Vilbrun
                        Guillaume Sam, at the head of a revolutionary army held together by promises
                        of reward to be had on arrival at Port au Prince, marched to the capital
                        from Cape Haitien meeting with practically no resistance.</p>
                    <p>Although incapable of offering any real opposition, President Theodore
                        stubbornly refused to resign, until it was feared by the people of Port au
                        Prince that he intended, with the few Government troops which remained, to
                        attempt to prevent the Sam forces from entering the city, and thereby cause
                        at this place a repetition of the happenings at the town of Gonaives during
                        the previous year, when in a fight in the streets between warring
                        revolutionary factions a number of the townspeople had been shot and the
                        town partially burned.</p>
                    <p>However, before the arrival of General Sam with the main body of
                        revolutionary troops, several smaller bands arrived outside of the town,
                        closed the roads to prevent any food stuffs from being brought into the town
                        and at the same time cut off the water supply of the city. A message was
                        sent to the President that until he resigned these conditions would
                        continue. After three days, during which time no food stuffs or water came
                        into the city, resulting in great suffering among the poorer classes, the
                        President sent his resignation to the Senate, and embarking on a Dutch ship
                        which was in the harbor sailed for Curasao. Shortly thereafter General Sam
                        entered the city at the head of the revolutionary troops, and once more the
                        Haitian Congress met in the joint session for the election of a Presdent.
                        Naturally, as General Sam had several thousand troops with him within the
                        town, the election was a mere matter of form, and on March 4, 1915, he was
                        declared President of Haiti.</p>
                    <p>All of the above-referred to revolutions were undertaken solely for the
                        purpose of gratifying the personal ambition and desire of the leaders for
                        power. There was no real grievance against any of the constituted
                        Governments, nor any reason for their overthrow which rose above the plane
                        of a desire for power of some revolutionary chief. With certain groups of
                        foreigners willing to advance funds for the prosecution Of revolutions, when
                        assured that upon the successful conclusion thereof they would be repaid at
                        an enormous rate of interest, the temptation for an ambitious politician,
                        whose conception of patriotism was to use the country for his own personal
                        advancement, was irresistible; especially as he was practically sure that at
                        the head of a revolutionary army he would be able to overthrow the
                        Government and place himself in power. The fact that the advances of funds
                        for conducting these revolutions were made at enormous interest rates,
                        sometimes going to the extreme of advancing gourdes to be repaid by an equal
                        number of dollars <pb facs="0389" n="313" xml:id="pg_313"/> was not taken
                        into consideration by revolutionary chiefs when contracting these loans.
                        Upon the successful termination of a revolution its debts are always assumed
                        by the Government; therefore the chiefs, inasmuch as the debts in no way
                        affect them personally, would accept any conditions as long as the money for
                        conducting the revolution was forthcoming.</p>
                    <p>During the early days of the Sam administration, the hope and the belief that
                        this Government” would be stable was very current. There were several causes
                        contributing to this impression. The President was supposed to be very
                        popular in the North, in which section all revolutions have their beginning,
                        and it is also true that the people generally desired nothing more than to
                        see an end of revolutionary conditions. Financially the condition of the Sam
                        Government was very much better than that of the two preceding Governments.
                        The arrival of a portion of the issue of paper money authorized by the
                        preceding Government, and the passage of a law taking away from the National
                        Bank of Haiti the service of the Treasury and placing its management in the
                        hands of the Government itself, gave the latter sufficient funds with which
                        to meet current demands. It is true that after the Government took over the
                        service of the Treasury it applied to its own use all of the revenues
                        collected, including the large proportion pledged for the payment of
                        existing debts, and thereby subjected itself to the probability of future
                        complications with foreign creditors who had loaned money on the faith of
                        these guarantes. Still it was believed that by its use of these funds, even
                        temporarily, the Government would establish itself sufficiently firmly to be
                        able to put down any revolution which might be begun.</p>
                    <p>Although the Government itself was in a less desperate condition financially
                        than had been the preceding Governments, the opposite was true of the
                        people. Since each succeeding revolutionary army passed that portion of the
                        Island between Gape Hatien and Port au Prince, living on the country as it
                        went, all of that section was completely devastated and agriculture was
                        practically at a standstill. Chaotic financial conditions reacted upon the
                        business in the cities, and rapid fluctuations in currency caused
                        practically a stagnation of all business enterprises.</p>
                    <p>The belief that the inauguration of President Sam would mean an end of
                        revolutions and that the country would have time to recover to some extent,
                        at least, from the enormous drain occasioned by the continual state of
                        revolution, did not prove to be the case.</p>
                    <p>In the spring the North was again in arms; this time under the leadership of
                        Dr. Ronsolvo Bobo, and although the Government sent a large number of troops
                        to that section and weekly expended from 120,000 to 140,000 gourdes in
                        maintaining this army, it seemed impossible to put down this revolution. As
                        time went on and there was no change in revolutionary conditions in the
                        North, there was a marked change in the policy of the Government at Port au
                        Prince.</p>
                    <p>While every Haitian Government maintains itself by its military strength,
                        during the latter part of the Sam administration militarism was carried to
                        such lengths as to make the name “Republic” a farce. In effect the people
                        lived under a military monarchy of the most absolute kind, with the
                        President exercising a practically unhampered and unlimited authority, a
                        condition which produced results at Port au Prince which became well-nigh
                        unbearable. This was particularly true after it became known that a certain
                        body of conspirators, whose identity was unknown to the Government, was
                        furnishing financial aid to the revolutionists in the North. Every one was
                        suspected, every one was spied on, and a denunciation by a Government agent
                        was sufficient for throwing the suspect into prison, without according him
                        either the formality of a trial or any opportunity to prove his innocence.
                        Under these conditions some 200 men were imprisoned, while foreign Legations
                        and Consulates were filled with those who, having been warned that they had
                        been denounced, had taken refuge before the Government had had an
                        opportunity to secure their arrest. Practically all of these prisoners and
                        refugees were from the better classes, but conditions were no less
                        unbearable for the laboring people.</p>
                    <p>Forced military service became so rigid that the men of the poorer class
                        feared to go upon the streets, as the Government seized practically every
                        man of this class capable of rendering military service, and in some cases
                        seized boys from thirteen to fourteen years of age. Squads of soldiers were
                        sent out into the country to search for men to augment further the ranks of
                        the <pb facs="0390" n="314" xml:id="pg_314"/> Government troops, and
                        returning would drive their recruits, arms pinioned behind them and tied
                        together, to the barracks to await their time to be sent to the North.</p>
                    <p>The above set out conditions caused the Government to lose what little there
                        remained of its popularity; yet so rigid had become its policy that no one
                        contemplated any attempt at organized resistance or open rebellion against
                        Port au Prince.</p>
                    <p>Under these conditions I, in common with every one else, was at an absolute
                        loss to account for or understand its significance when on the morning of
                        July 27 I was awakened by terrific firing down in the town. It was evident
                        from the sound that the firing was somewhere in the neighborhood of the
                        palace. At first I believed that it was a demonstration begun by the
                        Government. In Haiti this is not an unknown means of inducing political
                        refugees to leave the Legations and Consulates in which they are seeking
                        shelter, and thereby giving to the Government an opportunity either to
                        apprehend or shoot them. After the firing had continued for more than an
                        hour I became convinced that this was not the case, but that it was an
                        uprising against the Government. The firing continued for two hours without
                        cessation, and spasmodically throughout the day. At about 8 o’clock I drove
                        down into the town and attempted, on my way to the Legation, to discover
                        what had happened. The streets were filled with armed men and in the one
                        before the palace was an overturned engine which I found had been used by
                        the attacking party as a barricade from behind which they first opened fire.
                        I was informed that Charles de Delva and some fifty other men, all of whom
                        had been refugees in various Consulates and Legations, had managed in some
                        way to communicate with each other and had planned the outbreak of that
                        morning. They had secured control of the machine guns which were in the
                        grounds of the palace, it was reported, by having some of their sympathizers
                        enroll themselves as members of the palace guard, and had turned the same on
                        the guards shortly after the attack had begun, putting them to flight with a
                        loss of about fifty men killed and 200 wounded.</p>
                    <p>The President himself and several of his officers had taken refuge in the
                        palace and barricaded themselves there, where they were at the time that I
                        got down into the city. I was further informed that it was the intention of
                        the revolutionists to burn the palace and thereby force him to attempt to
                        escape. The oil had already been sent for which was to be used, and all
                        smaller buildings which might afford him a means of protection, should he
                        attempt to leave the palace, had either been burned or torn down. As I went
                        further down into the city I found squads of soldiers at practically every
                        corner, but it was not until later in the day that I learned that these were
                        Government troops and that the military posts in the lower part of the town
                        held out for the Government until about eleven o’clock.</p>
                    <p>Shortly after this hour some one rushed into the Legation and said that the
                        President had succeeded in escaping from the palace and was at that time,
                        along with his family, a refugee in the French Legation, whose grounds
                        adjoin those of the palace. He further stated that the President had ordered
                        General Oscar, in command at the prison, to kill every political prisoner in
                        case the revolutionists succeeded in driving him from the palace, and, that
                        following these orders, General Oscar with the assistance of the jailers,
                        had massacred all the political prisoners who were in the jail, and that
                        General Oscar himself, who had taken refuge in the Dominican Legation, had
                        been followed there by the father of three boys who were among those killed,
                        had been dragged into the streets and shot before the door of the
                        Legation.</p>
                    <p>Putting little credence in this rumor, as in revolutionary times in Haiti one
                        always hears rumors of the wildest sort, I went around to the Dominican
                        Legation, which is just around the corner from the American, to ascertain
                        whether there was any truth in the report. Arriving there I found a crowd
                        collected before the door, in the midst of which lay the body of General
                        Oscar, already mutilated by blows from the infuriated people. So intense was
                        the feeling of the people against Oscar that no one could be found who would
                        touch the body to carry it away for burial, and for the rest of that day,
                        and until some time the following morning, it lay in the gutter to be spat
                        upon and mutilated by passers-by, when, after being saturated with oil, it
                        was burned in the streets.</p>
                    <p>The report of the massacre at the jail proved to be no less correct, and I
                        found that almost two hundred men had been butchered in an indescribably
                        brutal manner. General Oscar, with a few jailers, had gone from cell to cell
                            <pb facs="0391" n="315" xml:id="pg_315"/> opening them one by one, and
                        driving the prisoners out into the court had there despatched their victims.
                        The bodies lay piled together just as they had fallen, and from their
                        appearance it looked as if every sort of weapon had been used in
                        accomplishing the slaughter. Among the prisoners there were a few who
                        escaped to recount later the horrors through which they had passed. One told
                        me that when the murderers had arrived at his cell, no key could be found
                        which would open the door. By standing back in the corner he was out of gun
                        range, and could not be reached by a machete. After several attempts the
                        jailers had passed on to the next cell and for some reason did not return.
                        He was released several hours later, when the jail was entered by those who
                        discovered the massacre. Another was struck by a machete as he stepped from
                        his cell, and just as he fell wounded the body of another man who had been
                        shot fell across him, shielding him from further blows. By lying perfectly
                        still and feigning death—even the jailers, simulating a rescue party, called
                        out for all who were not dead to seize the opportunity to escape, and
                        thereby discovered several who like himself had fallen wounded but not
                        killed—he escaped the fate which befell those who betrayed the fact that
                        they were still alive. He said that even more vivid than the horror of the
                        hours which he spent lying upon the floor soaked in his own blood and that
                        of the dead man who had fallen across him, was the memory of the agonized
                        prayers for death of a young boy of about eighteen whose cell was opened
                        prior to his. He said that the jailer, whose enmity this boy had in some
                        manner incurred, before killing him had taken a pair of tweezers and pulled
                        out his teeth, one by one, and then gouged out his eyes. The cries of this
                        boy as he begged the man to use his machete, he said was his one indelible
                        impression of all the horror.</p>
                    <p>As soon as the news of the massacre in the prison became current and the
                        people began to realize what had happened, the town became absolutely
                        hysterical. An enormous crowd collected around the jail and everywhere that
                        one looked in the streets could be seen little processions headed by two men
                        carrying on a plank on their heads the body of some victim, followed by the
                        friends and relatives whose curses against the President mingled with those
                        of the people who stood in the streets and watched.</p>
                    <p>Between two and three o’clock I left the Legation and drove back through the
                        town on the way to my house. A very marked difference in the attitude of the
                        people was apparent. While in the morning everybody had been in the wildest
                        state of excitement, there was not apparent at this time any of the surly
                        vindictiveness which was noticeable later on in the day. Just how it had
                        become generally known that the massacre was the result of an order given by
                        the President, I was unable to ascertain. But even at this hour there seemed
                        to be a conviction in everyone’s mind that the President himself was
                        directly responsible for the outrage. Shortly after my arrival at my house,
                        which was in a portion of the city very much removed from the scene of the
                        outrage and comparatively quiet, I received a note from the French Legation
                        saying that they were having a good deal of difficulty in preventing a mob
                        from entering and forcibly taking out the President, and requesting that I
                        come down and render such assistance as I could.</p>
                    <p>I went at once, passing on my way numerous groups of people of all classes,
                        and the excitement and indignation against the President was at even higher
                        pitch than it had been when I passed through the town an hour earlier.</p>
                    <p>Arriving at the French Legation, I discovered that a leaderless mob had
                        already invaded the Legation grounds and that the French Minister with the
                        assistance of Mr. Kohn, the British Chargé d’Affaires, had with the greatest
                        difficulty succeeded in getting them to disperse without entering the
                        Legation and doing bodily harm to the President. Naturally everyone was very
                        apprehensive, especially as Madame Girard and the two daughters of the
                        French Minister were at the Legation.</p>
                    <p>Inside the Legation I found the President, his wife, and several small
                        children, four officers of the army, the Ministers of Finance and Foreign
                        Relations, and numerous servants of the President. The President himself was
                        in a perfect frenzy of fear, creeping about the house like a hunted animal,
                        so terror stricken that when passing an open window he would crawl on all
                        fours for fear some one on the outside would see him and shoot him.</p>
                    <p>During the afternoon several small crowds invaded the Legation grounds, but
                        were gotten rid of without a great deal of difficulty. Just before nightfall
                        a friend of the two Ministers who were seeking refuge in the Legation came
                        and after some conversation with him both of them left. Through this man <pb
                            facs="0392" n="316" xml:id="pg_316"/> we got the report that an
                        organized mob would come to the Legation that night, take out the President
                        and assassinate him. We had already heard this rumor from a number of
                        different sources, but when we saw that the two Ministers preferred to leave
                        the asylum which they had gained at the Legation and trust to passing
                        through the streets unharmed, rather than remain there during the night, we
                        became convinced that the warnings which we had received of the coming of
                        the mob that night were true. This conviction was strengthened when General
                        Charles Zamor, who for ten months prior to that day, had been a refugee in
                        the French Legation, came and told the French Minister that although he had
                        previously told him that he would return to the Legation that night, so that
                        in case anything should happen the Minister might have his assistance, he
                        regretted that he had found it impossible to fulfill that promise, adding at
                        the same time that the populace was so enraged and so out of hand that no
                        one’s influence would be of any weight if they should attempt any act of
                        violence against the President.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Kohn and myself remained at the Legation that night but for some reason
                        no demonstration of any kind against the President was attempted, and in the
                        morning the town was more than usually quiet. Between nine and ten o’clock I
                        left and went down to the American Legation to see if there was any reply to
                        my cable asking that a ship be sent. The British Chargé and myself had
                        decided that we go to our respective Legations, one by one, so as not to
                        leave the French Minister alone at his Legation, although all of us thought
                        that as the excitement of the previous day had somewhat calmed, the danger
                        at the French Legation was passed. Arriving at the American Legation I found
                        a telegram stating that the U. S. S. <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi> would
                        arrive sometime in the forenoon, which assured me that the vessel which was
                        just visible on the horizon when I came down to the town was the United
                        States warship.</p>
                    <p>I then started back to the French Legation so as to allow Mr. Kohn to leave
                        and go to the British Legation to see if he had a reply to his telegram of
                        the day before, when he and the French Minister both had cabled for ships.
                        Before I had reached the Legation there was one terrific howl of fury from
                        that direction. Turning into the street which runs behind the French
                        Legation, I found my way completely blocked by a mob which filled the street
                        from wall to wall, making it an absolute impossibility for me to reach the
                        gates of the Legation. I could see that something or somebody was on the
                        ground in the center of the crowd, just before the gates, and when a man
                        disentangled himself from the crowd and rushed howling by me, with a severed
                        hand from which the blood was dripping the thumb of which he had stuck in
                        his mouth, I knew that the threatened assassination of the President was
                        accomplished. Behind him came men with the feet, the other hand, the head,
                        and other parts of the body displayed on poles, each one followed by a mob
                        of screaming men and women. The portion of the body that remained was
                        dragged through the streets by the crowd.</p>
                    <p>I finally managed to turn, and, going around the block, entered the Legation
                        from the other side. There I learned what had transpired in the Legation
                        building itself.</p>
                    <p>After my departure everything had remained perfectly quiet, so quiet that Mr.
                        Kohn, deciding that it was useless for him to wait until my return, left for
                        his Legation. The French Minister, his wife, and two daughters were sitting
                        in the drawing room, which runs entirely through the building, and from
                        which can be seen the gates at either end of the grounds. As these gates are
                        some hundred and fifty yards from the house, the doors were left open.
                        Before anyone knew that there was even a threat of danger, a mob of some 75
                        or 80 men were on the porch. They had entered an adjoining property, climbed
                        the wall at one side of the house, and were actually at the door before
                        anyone had even an intimation of their presence. This mob was composed of
                        young men of the best class of Haitians of Port au Prince, and we learned
                        later that they had assembled immediately after attending the funeral
                        services of the three sons of General Polynice, all of whom had been victims
                        of the massacre of the day before. The Minister, assisted by Madame Girard
                        and his two daughters, attempted to close the heavy doors and bar the mobs
                        entrance, but they were inside of the house before this could be done.</p>
                    <p>The leaders of the mob demanded that the French Minister tell them where the
                        President was hiding, which he refused to do, whereupon they immediately
                        began to search the house. A man, who resembled the President very much and
                        who had taken refuge in the Legation the day before, was seized by several
                        members of the mob who thought him to be the President, dragged <pb
                            facs="0393" n="317" xml:id="pg_317"/> from his place of hiding and into
                        the drawing room where he would have been killed had it not been that
                        someone recognized him and apprised his captors of their mistake, just in
                        time to save his life.</p>
                    <p>The first search of the house was fruitless and the leaders again demanded
                        that the Minister give up the President. He repeated his refusal and another
                        search was begun.</p>
                    <p>Shortly before the arrival of the mob, a doctor had been at the Legation—in
                        fact was there at the time the mob entered, making his escape as soon as he
                        learned what was happening. He had just finished dressing the bullet wound
                        which the President had received in his leg the previous day, and in the
                        dressing had used iodoform. It was the odor of this drug that betrayed the
                        hiding place of the President. The members of the mob knew that the
                        President himself was the only wounded person within the Legation, and on
                        entering the bed room of the French Minister and noticing the odor of this
                        drug in the room, they began a more careful search there and discovered that
                        there was a closed door behind the head of the bed, which had been moved so
                        as to hide it. The President was found in the bath room into which this door
                        opened. He was seized by the mob, stabbed two or three times in his face,
                        knocked down and dragged by his heels down the stairs, through the drawing
                        room and out into the grounds, vainly protesting that he was innocent of any
                        connection with the massacre of the day before, and begging most piteously
                        for his life. No attention was paid to his protestations, and before the
                        eyes of his wife and children he was dragged down the long driveway which
                        leads to the gates. As he was being dragged along he clutched the spokes of
                        a wheel of a buggy which stood at one side of the driveway, attempting to
                        free himself from his captors. A blow of a club broke his arm and loosened
                        his grip.</p>
                    <p>While these events were transpiring within the Legation itself, another mob
                        composed of the rabble of Port au Prince had collected in the street before
                        the Legation. Arriving at the gates, which were locked, the President was
                        thrown over to the mob that waited on the outside. No sooner had his body
                        touched the ground than it was literally torn to pieces, as above recounted.
                        No injury was clone to anyone else within the Legation, although if it had
                        not been for a few members of the mob less bloodthirsty than the rest, the
                        suggestion that the President’s wife and children be killed also would have
                        been accepted.</p>
                    <p>Although the French Legation was the center and objective point of mob’s
                        activities, the wildest disorder prevailed in all the city. There was
                        absolutely no semblance of authority, and there was no one who could be
                        called upon for protection. Every man had to depend upon himself for the
                        protection of himself and property, and there was the gravest apprehension,
                        not only among the foreigners but also among the Haitians themselves. The
                        people were in an absolute frenzy of excitement and rage, and it was feared
                        that, maddened by the bloodshed of those two days, this opportunity would be
                        seized by the people to settle old scores. Besides this there was a great
                        deal of actual suffering, amounting almost to starvation, among the poorer
                        classes, and pillage down in the city was feared. It was believed that the
                        mob would invade the British Legation where Philogene, Chief of the Secret
                        Police under the Sam administration, was in hiding. He was intensely hated,
                        as a number of the victims of the massacre of the day before were in prison
                        as the result of his denunciation, and his assassination would almost
                        certainly have followed that of the President had it not been for the timely
                        arrival of the U. S. S. <hi rend="italic">Washington.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>For foreigners the situation was extremely critical. The foreign Legations,
                        up to this time, had never been invaded, but the invasion of the Dominican
                        Legation, where General Oscar had taken refuge, followed the next day by the
                        invasion of the French, took away this last safeguard against violence from
                        the natives. The ignorant classes, having seen these Legations violated with
                        apparently no evil results to the invader, could not be expected to respect
                        their inviolability as they had in the past; and as a result there remained
                        no place of safety, nor was there any Haitian authority which could be
                        looked to for protection.</p>
                    <p>Under the conditions above briefly set forth, it was believed that for the
                        protection of life and property and the maintenance of law and order, in the
                        absence of constituted authority, it was an absolute necessity that the
                        American forces be immediately landed to assume control of the city until
                        such a time as there should be formed a constitutional government capable of
                        maintaining itself and of affording protection to Haitian and foreign life
                        and property.</p>
                    <pb facs="0394" n="318" xml:id="pg_318"/>
                    <p>After the landing of these forces it was realized that before order could be
                        restored it would be necessary to disarm the native soldiers and police who,
                        in the absence of authority, had become simply an armed rabble. The average
                        Haitian soldier is utterly ignorant, usually unable to either read or write,
                        and as long as such men were allowed to carry arms, roaming at will as they
                        were in the city, no assurance of safety or orderly conditions could be
                        given.</p>
                    <p>It was also found necessary to assume control of the customs service in order
                        to assure the conservation of the funds derived from this source and to
                        secure their proper and full collection.</p>
                    <p>As there existed in the other towns of the republic conditions similar to
                        those existing at the capital, it was necessary to take similar action in
                        these places as troops became available.</p>
                    <p>In the light of all the facts and under the then existing conditions it is
                        respectfully submitted that any action short of that taken could have been
                        but temporary in effect and could neither have produced lasting results nor
                        offered any solution of the questions involved.</p>
                    <p>There had to be considered:</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">First, a means of affording immediate protection to
                            foreign and American life and property.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>As has been above set forth, at the time of the arrival of Rear Admiral W. B.
                        Caperton aboard the U. S. S. <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>, the head of
                        President Sam was being carried on a pole through the city and what remained
                        of his body was being dragged through the streets by a mob, mad from the
                        sight of blood, and at the same time emboldened by having assassinated the
                        arch oppressor without having experienced the swift retribution which, in
                        the past, had been visited upon those who dared oppose one in authority.</p>
                    <p>During the thirty-six hours preceding the arrival of the American warship,
                        two Presidents had been murdered, ex-President Zamor having been one of the
                        victims of the massacre in the prison. Two foreign Legations had been
                        violated. There was no authority to which one could look for protection save
                        a self-appointed revolutionary committee whose powers were simply nominal.
                        Mob law held sway, jeopardizing the lives and property of foreigners.</p>
                    <p>There was no immediate prospect of a change in these conditions. The leaders
                        of the outbreak at Port au Prince declared themselves to be adherents of Dr.
                        Bobo, who at this time was in the vicinity of Cape Haitien, in the extreme
                        north of the Island, and who could not be expected to arrive for some days
                        at the capital to assume in person the reins of Government and to attempt,
                        with the assistance of his revolutionary army, to produce some semblance of
                        order out of existing chaotic conditions.</p>
                    <p>Each hour which elapsed with the mob rule unchecked added to the danger for
                        Americans and foreigners and largely increased the chance that property
                        would be destroyed and looting begun by the half-starved natives.</p>
                    <p>In this emergency which could neither have been foreseen nor provided for,
                        the immediate landing of the American forces was deemed absolutely necessary
                        to meet the pressing demands of the situation.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Second, the administration and maintenance of civil order
                            pending the establishment of a constitutional Government.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>During the period which lapsed between July 28, the day on which the American
                        forces were landed, and August 12, the day on which President Dartiguenave
                        was elected, there was no Government of any description, as in Haiti the
                        overthrow of a President, <hi rend="italic">ipso facto</hi>, dissolves his
                        Government. There was, it is true, the self-appointed revolutionary
                        committee with whose consent the American forces had been landed and with
                        whom, as far as it was possible, Rear Admiral Caperton cooperated in
                        maintaining order and administering the affairs of Government.</p>
                    <p>However, when this committee arbitrarily declared the Senate and Chambers
                        dissolved, its action could neither be approved nor permitted to be
                        effective. The members of the Haitian Senate and Chambers of Deputies had
                        been in office the four preceding administrations and it could not be
                        admitted that a band of professional revolutionists had either the right or
                        power, in the furtherance of their own ends, arbitrarily to dissolve these
                        bodies.</p>
                    <p>It was known that the action of the committee was taken as a result of its
                        fear that these bodies, in the exercise of the duty imposed upon them by the
                        Haitian constitution, would elect some other than Doctor Bobo to the
                        Presidency. Knowing that he would not be allowed to lead his army through
                        the <pb facs="0395" n="319" xml:id="pg_319"/> country and into the capital
                        and, by its presence, force the Legislative Bodies to name him President,
                        and fearing the action they might take unless so coerced the revolutionary
                        committee issued a proclamation declaring the Senate and Chambers
                        dissolved.</p>
                    <p>The members of these bodies were notified shortly after the appearance of the
                        proclamation that the action on the part of the committee was not recognized
                        by the United States and the assurance was given that they should convene
                        for the election of a President. This promised protection was accorded, and
                        on August 12th Sudre Dartiguenave, President of the Senate, was elected
                        President of the Republic. This election could not and would not have been
                        held unless the members had been protected when they met for the purpose of
                        choosing a President. It was only the presence of the United States marines
                        on guard throughout the city and around the Legislative Chambers which
                        prevented the revolutionary committee from attempting to prevent the
                        election by force.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Third, the support and maintenance of constituted
                            authority.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>After the Haitian Congress had met and under the protection of the American
                        forces held an election for the presidency, possibly for the first time
                        exercising this right freely and not as some chief, backed by his army,
                        dictated, it was seen that it was impossible for this Government, regularly
                        and freely elected, unaided to sustain itself.</p>
                    <p>Although a general disarmament had been undertaken there were still forces
                        under arms in the Island. The new Government had no military strength. The
                        President was not from the military class and had no army to enforce his
                        authority. Doctor Bobo and his adherents were very much dissatisfied and
                        disgruntled that he had not been the choice of the Congress in its election
                        of a President. A withdrawal of the armed support of the United States would
                        immediately have resulted in the overthrow of the Dartiguenave Government,
                        probably with the repetition of the outrages which accompanied the overthrow
                        of the preceding President. That its existence was dependent upon the
                        support of the United States was an accepted fact by the members of this
                        Government, and it was realized by everyone in touch with the situation that
                        withdrawal of this support would be tantamount to signing the death warrant
                        of the President and members of his Government.</p>
                    <p>Aside from the necessity of supporting the new Government temporarily, and
                        until it became sufficiently strong to maintain itself, it was incumbent
                        from a humanitarian viewpoint to aid the Haitian people to free themselves
                        from the hopeless conditions which continued revolution and a policy of
                        despotic militarism had produced. In a large portion of the Island
                        agriculture was practically abandoned and in those sections through which
                        successive revolutionary and Government armies had passed the country was
                        devastated, nothing remaining of the crops of the small landowners, as the
                        armies lived on the country as they went. The absolute prostration of the
                        country districts reacted on business in the cities and business was almost
                        at a standstill.</p>
                    <p>Following the American intervention, and as soon as the ignorant classes
                        found that they were not to be made slaves and their lands confiscated, as
                        the politicians, seeing in foreign intervention an end of conditions which
                        had permitted their exploitation of the country for personal gain, had
                        taught them to believe, conditions rapidly began to improve. Believing that
                        an end of revolution, so long desired, was at last a reality, the landowners
                        began again to cultivate their farms. The men, who under the old régime,
                        through fear of forced military service, had remained at their homes, began
                        to appear upon the streets and to attempt to secure employment. Work of
                        various sorts was resumed, giving employment to laborers and thereby to some
                        extent alleviating the suffering among this class which at times amounted to
                        actual starvation.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Fourth, a means of enabling constituted authority
                            permanently to maintain itself.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Before it could be expected that orderly conditions could prevail in Haiti
                        and a Government possess any degree of stability, or the strength to
                        maintain itself, it was necessary to discover a means of permanently putting
                        an end to revolutionary uprisings.</p>
                    <p>If this was to be accomplished it was essential that militarism be abolished,
                        that the funds derived from the customs be in some way safeguarded, and <pb
                            facs="0396" n="320" xml:id="pg_320"/> their expenditure for the payment
                        of debts contracted by revolutionary chiefs in the prosecution of a
                        revolutionary operations, made impossible.</p>
                    <p>As has already been pointed out, certain groups of foreigners have financed
                        the successive Haitian revolutions, advancing the money for their
                        prosecution at enormous interest rates and with the assurance that these
                        loans would be regarded as Government obligations and provision made for
                        their payment upon the successful termination of the revolution.</p>
                    <p>Naturally if a means be found to make such procedure impossible, the
                        procuring of funds for the prosecution of revolutions would no longer be a
                        thing so easy of accomplishment, and without funds no revolution can
                        succeed.</p>
                    <p>Those who have been on the Island and who, in consequence, have had an
                        opportunity to observe existing conditions, believe that under the operation
                        of the treaty, signed between the United States and Haiti, these results
                        would be accomplished.</p>
                    <p>The article of the treaty which contemplates the abolition of the army and
                        the establishment of a constabulary to be composed of native Haitians,
                        officered by Americans, presents a plan which should put an end to the
                        militarism which has been productive of so much unrest and suffering in the
                        Island. This not only does away with the menace of a large armed force, the
                        maintenance of which is an enormous drain upon the resources of the country,
                        but the elimination of Haitian officers removes the possibility that some
                        one of them might use military strength to overthrow the President and place
                        himself at the head of the Government.</p>
                    <p>The articles of the treaty which contemplate American customs control and the
                        appointment of an American Financial Adviser provide, it is thought, an
                        effective means of preventing the use of Government revenues for the payment
                        of revolutionary obligations, and give the assurance that they will be
                        expended only for legitimate demands.</p>
                    <p>Therefore, with the army abolished and the finances of the country so
                        safeguarded as to make it impossible for them to be considered and counted
                        on as security for loans made by those who consider the financing of a
                        revolution a legitimate business enterprise, it should not be difficult for
                        the Government to sustain itself, and with the support of the constabulary
                        to maintain order, a condition which must exist if the Republic of Haiti is
                        to overcome the well-nigh insurmountable difficulties which a constant state
                        of revolution has produced.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
