<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-02-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="386" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d386">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 838.51/483</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Minister of Haiti</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of Haiti</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-02-24">
                                    <hi rend="italic">February 24, 1916</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: I have the honor to
                            inform your excellency that a contract for the repairing of the streets
                            and wharves of Port au Prince dated October 15, 1912, and flowing from a
                            concession deed approved by the Legislative Body on August 27, 1910,
                            granted to a corporation styled Compagnie Haitienne de Construction a
                            special appropriation bearing on “all the important duties yielded by
                            oils and essential oils of all kinds (kerosene, turpentine and others)
                            paint, matches, tar, rosin and coal tar.” The said appropriation was
                            estimated at not less than seven thousand dollars a month and if falling
                            short of that amount, the difference was to be made good by the duties
                            on “coffee and coffee sorting,” collected <hi rend="italic">ex
                                officio</hi> by the National Bank of the Republic of Haiti.</p>
                        <p>The construction company has been receiving since September 1915, seven
                            thousand dollars a month to be applied to the settlement of work under
                            way. But these monthly payments which helped to keep running work going
                            are not enough to cover a balance of $45,372.12 due the company since
                            its last settlement with my Government. It has agreed to receive up to
                            that amount monthly instalments of 5,000 dollars and to begin work on
                            new sections at once. But it has met with a refusal on the part of Mr.
                            Charles Conard, Collector of Customs, who, though admitting that the
                            work is urgently needed, declared that he was without instructions from
                            Washington in the matter.</p>
                        <p>On hearing of the objection, my Government has instructed me to bring the
                            facts to your excellency’s knowledge in the hope that the Compagnie
                            Haitienne de Construction may be given the means of carrying on a work
                            whose usefulness cannot be overstated.</p>
                        <p>Be pleased [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Solon Ménos</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>