<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-04-16T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-04-16T16:00:00-05:00" n="645" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d645">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 812.00/17886</note>
                        <head ana="#head_untitled-inferred-from-preceding-sibling-head">[Untitled]</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">El Paso</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-04-16T14:00:00-07:00">
                                    <hi rend="italic">April 16, 1916, 2 p.m.</hi>
                                </date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Following from Letcher, via Edwards: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p rend="center">I</p>
                                <p>Have just talked by phone with General Pershing, who now has
                                    received full report of attack upon his troops at Parral on
                                    12th, which is substantially as follows:</p>
                                <p>On the 11th instant an officer from the garrison of Parral
                                    visited Major Tompkins, whose column was then ten miles distant
                                    from Parral, and invited him to enter city, which invitation was
                                    accepted on the 12th, when the column entered city and Major
                                    Tompkins was received by military commander and civil
                                    authorities. Later, column left city, Major Tompkins being
                                    accompanied by General Lozano; but upon reaching outskirts it
                                    was attacked by citizens and soldiers whom General Lozano vainly
                                    tried to disperse. The column continued to retreat under attack
                                    for fifteen miles, meanwhile two soldiers being killed, six
                                    wounded and one missing. As already reported, apparently
                                    trustworthy unofficial reports place Mexican dead at forty.
                                    Officers believe attack was preconcerted and that ambush was
                                    deliberately planned. General Pershing’s official report will
                                    follow.</p>
                                <p rend="right">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Letcher</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="center">II</p>
                                <p>From Pershing:</p>
                                <p rend="right">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Palomas</hi>, <hi rend="italic">April 15, 1916</hi>.</p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Commanding General,
                                        Southern Department</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Houston,
                                        Texas:—</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>“My telegrams of yesterday confirmed. Full report from Brown and
                                    Tompkins this morning. Tompkins column two troops, M and K, 13th
                                    Cavalry, entered Parral 11 a.m., 12th instant. Tompkins
                                    preceded, was cordially received by higher civil and military
                                    officials. Military commander, General Lozano, accompanied Major
                                    Tompkins on way to camp. At the outskirts of town groups of
                                    native troops and civilians following, jeered, threw stones and
                                    fired on column. Tompkins took defensive position north of
                                    railroad but was soon flanked by native troops and forced
                                    further retire. About 300 Carranza troops joined in pursuit and
                                    Tompkins continued to withdraw to avoid further complications
                                    until he reached Santa Cruz, eight miles from Parral. Fighting
                                    ceased at fifteen miles from town. Tompkins deserves great
                                    praise for his forbearance. General Lozano attempted to control
                                    his men when firing began but failed. Brown, with Young’s
                                    squadron 10th Cavalry, eight miles away when notified, and
                                    joined Tompkins 7 p.m. Camping place recommended near Parral was
                                    no doubt purposely selected to take advantage of Tompkins’
                                    command. Officers believe whole affair planned beforehand but
                                    probably without knowledge commanding general. Reported
                                    privately 40 Mexicans killed, all soldiers including one major.
                                    One civilian wounded. Americans killed, two; wounded, six;
                                    missing, one. Major Tompkins slightly wounded in chest by spent
                                    bullet. Major Howze arrived Parral yesterday from San Borja and
                                    Balleza having had several skirmishes with Villistas. One man
                                    killed, two wounded.</p>
                                <p>Report Villa in mountains southwest San Borja. No food, no
                                    forage, officers’ description vicinity Santa Cruz, where troops
                                    now are. Shall withdraw them by easy marches in direction of
                                    Satevo. Can now [not?] supply them from San Antonio.</p>
                                <p>I am <hi rend="italic">en route</hi> to Namiquipa.</p>
                                <p rend="right">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">“Pershing”</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="right">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Letcher</hi>
                                </p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Cobb</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>