<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-11-13T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-11-13T10:00:00-05:00" n="805" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d805">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 812.00/19848</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Vice Consul <persName type="from">Blocker</persName>
                                to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Eagle Pass</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-11-13T09:00:00-06:00">
                                    <hi rend="italic">November 13, 1916, 9 a.m.</hi>
                                </date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Confirmation of reports that General Francisco Murguia with 6,000 <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> troops is advancing north of Escalon was
                            brought to border by an American citizen arriving Sunday. He reports <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> forces are arriving in considerable
                            numbers at Torreon from south and are being rushed to front as quickly
                            as possible. General Murguia is commanding operations. Just prior to
                            leaving Torreon last Friday fighting was reported in progress north of
                            Escalon between outposts indicating Villistas are in charge of Jimenez
                            and probably several towns north of there. On Thursday a Chinaman
                            arrived in Torreon from Jimenez having left there several days before in
                            order to escape execution by Villistas. Chinamen brought news that
                            thirteen Chinese, two Arabs and one American were killed by Villistas
                            upon their entry into Jimenez and that foreigners were being shown no
                            mercy by the bandits. While nothing authentic is known in Torreon as to
                            operations north of Escalon it is believed there that Villistas are
                            still occupying the towns of Parral, Santa Rosalia, Jimenez and Santa
                            Barbara.</p>
                        <p>Informant states <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> forces are repairing
                            railroad track and telegraph wires as they advance, that it will
                            probably be some time, in the event they are successful, before any
                            information will be obtained regarding Parral. Immediate vicinity
                            Torreon reported quiet and no fear exists of attack on that city by
                            bandits. Consulate has had no later telegrams from General Murguia
                            regarding Americans reported killed at Parral nor is it believed Murguia
                            has occupied Parral as he advised Consulate on Friday last.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Blocker</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>