<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-06-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-06-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="97" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d97">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.00/2462</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Reinsch</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1119</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-06-14">
                                    <hi rend="italic">June 14, 1916</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that on June
                            12, the American Consul in charge at Tientsin telegraphed to the effect
                            that the Japanese had asserted that the French commandant had requested
                            the placing of Japanese troops to guard the railway station in the
                            native city and the Yangtsun bridge on the railway to Peking; the
                            American commandant had been requested to reply as to his concurrence in
                            the plan.</p>
                        <p>I instructed the Consul to advise the American commandant to reply that
                            any proposal relating to changes in the force patrolling the railway,
                            should be reported to the Dean of the Diplomatic Corps in order to be
                            submitted to the Ministers interested for their discussion and eventual
                            approval.</p>
                        <p>On the merits of the case, there does not seem to be any need for foreign
                            military at the railway station at Tientsin. The placing of a Japanese
                            guard there would only tend to irritate the Chinese, although the
                            Japanese would probably consider it as contributing materially to their
                            prestige.</p>
                        <p>It is somewhat difficult to understand the motive of the proposal of the
                            French commandant. However, during the apparent uncertainty of
                            conditions of June 6, the French Minister brought to Peking about sixty
                            of the French Indo-Chinese troops stationed at Tientsin. The commandant
                            there may feel that from a military point of view his forces are
                            insufficient. The political aspects of the matter, however, are such
                            that it is not in the interest of France, or any other western Power, to
                            make a change which in the eyes of the Chinese will seem a support of
                            the pretensions of Japan.</p>
                        <p>If the change is actually proposed by the French Minister and commandant,
                            it will, of course, have to be accepted.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Paul S. Reinsch</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>