<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Conger to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1906p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d222</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">222</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1904-08-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1904-08-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028935"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Offenses</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1904-08-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1904-08-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="222"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d222">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Conger</persName> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking, China</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1904-08-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 15, 1904</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1681.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to your No. 797 of May 19 last, I have
                    the honor to transmit herewith a copy of the trade-mark regulations which have
                    now received imperial approval and will be put tentatively in force on the 23d
                    of October next.</p>
                <p>I inclose also copies of correspondence with the foreign office and with
                    Consul-General Goodnow concerning them.</p>
                <p>I have the honor, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">E. H. Conger.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">trade-mark regulations.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Anyone, no matter whether Chinese or foreigner, who desires to have
                            the exclusive use of a trade-mark must first register the same according
                            to these regulations.</item>
                        <label/>
                        <item>A distinctive design, inscription, and emblem, either all three
                            employed in combination or any one or two of them, constitute the
                            essential characteristics of a trade-mark.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The board of commerce will establish a bureau of registration to
                            attend especially to matters of registration, and the customs at
                            Tientsin and Shanghai will serve as branch offices for receiving
                            applications to the greater convenience of those who apply, who may
                            present their petitions at the place nearest to them.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Applicants for registration may either send their applications direct
                            to the bureau of registration or forward them through a branch office of
                            application.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Every application must be accompanied by a description, in which there
                            shall be inclosed three impressions of the trade-mark. The description
                            shall clearly and correctly explain in a general way the pattern of the
                            trade-mark and tell on what sort of goods it is to be used, and to what
                            class they belong according to the classification appended to the
                            subordinate rules annexed to these experimental regulations. If the
                            application be forwarded through a branch office of application,
                            duplicates must be made both of the application and the
                            description.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>The bureau of registration, having received an application, and having
                            found nothing in it contrary to the requirements, shall file the same
                            for six months, and if within that time no person shall have petitioned
                            against the registration, the said trade-mark shall be
                            registered.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>If applications be made for the registration of trade-marks which are
                            similar to one another and which are to be used upon the same sort of
                            goods, registration must be granted to the one first making application.
                            If the several applications be presented at the same time on the same
                            day, permission to register must be given to all.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>In case of a trade-mark already registered in a foreign country, if
                            application for its registration in China be made within four months
                            from the date of its registration abroad, the date of such registration
                            abroad may be recognized.</item>
                        <pb facs="0344" n="238" xml:id="pg_238"/>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>Trade-marks of the character specified below shall be refused
                            registration: <list>
                                <label>(i)</label>
                                <item>Those which destroy respect for rank, do injury to the customs
                                    of the country, and (are likely to) deceive the people.<note
                                        n="a" xml:id="d222fna">For instance, such as use official
                                        emblems or employ pictures which Chinese may regard as
                                        improper.</note>
                                </item>
                                <label>(ii)</label>
                                <item>Those which imitate the impressions of seals especially
                                    reserved for the use of the Government (such as the Imperial
                                    seal and the oblong lead seals of the various yamens), or which
                                    imitate the designs of the Imperial flag, the military banners,
                                    or decorations conferred for merit.</item>
                                <label>(iii)</label>
                                <item>A trade-mark identical with one already registered belonging
                                    to another person or identical with one in public use in China
                                    more than two years before the present application shall have
                                    been made, or trade-marks similar to either of the above, if
                                    used upon the same sort of goods.</item>
                                <label>(iv)</label>
                                <item>Those which can not be recognized by some distinctive
                                    feature.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>The term during which any merchant, Chinese or foreigner, may be
                            allowed exclusive use of a trade-mark shall be twenty years, beginning
                            with the date of registration by the bureau. But trade-marks already
                            registered in another country and for whose registration here
                            application shall have been made according to the regulations, shall be
                            allowed a term of exclusive use corresponding to that provided for in
                            the registration abroad. (But in no case shall such term extend beyond
                            twenty years.)</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>If, after the expiration of the term of exclusive use, it should be
                            desired to extend such term, and application for a renewal of
                            registration be made within six months before the expiration of the term
                            of exclusive use, such application for renewal may be allowed.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>Should the owner of a trade-mark already registered desire to sell to
                            some one else the right to its exclusive use, or should he find it
                            necessary to share its exclusive use with others, he must at once make
                            application at the bureau of registration for registration of the
                            change.</item>
                        <label>12.</label>
                        <item>If any trade-mark already registered shall be found to violate the
                            provisions of (i), (ii), and (iv) of regulation 8, the bureau of
                            registration may cancel the registration of such trade-mark.</item>
                        <label>13.</label>
                        <item>If a trade-mark already registered shall be found to violate the
                            provisions of regulation 6, or those of (iii) of regulation 8, the
                            injured party may make application to have the registration of such
                            trade-mark annulled. But this provision shall not apply to any
                            trade-mark already registered for three years.</item>
                        <label>14.</label>
                        <item>If, upon application having been made for the registration of a
                            trademark, the bureau of registration shall find that such trade-mark
                            does not comply with the requirements the bureau shall indorse clearly
                            upon the rejected application the reasons for refusing
                            registration.</item>
                        <label>15.</label>
                        <item>Any person unwilling to submit to the refusal mentioned in the
                            preceding regulation may within six months after the date of the said
                            refusal present a statement of facts and request the bureau of
                            registration to reconsider the application.</item>
                        <label>16.</label>
                        <item>If, in any application for the registration of a trade-mark, the owner
                            of the trade-mark shall not be in China, or if he should reside at a
                            considerable distance from the bureau of registration, he must select a
                            reliable friend and report him as his agent or representative.</item>
                        <label>17.</label>
                        <item>Should anyone desire to make a copy of any records in the trade-mark
                            registration files, or examine the same, he may make application for
                            such privilege either at the bureau of registration or at one of the
                            branch offices. If he shall reside at a considerable distance his agent
                            or representative may make such application.</item>
                        <label>18.</label>
                        <item>The bureau of registration shall publish trade-mark reports announcing
                            therein, for the information of the public, what trade-marks have been
                            registered and the circumstances connected with the cancellation of any
                            registration.</item>
                        <label>19.</label>
                        <item>Should anyone infringe the right to the exclusive use of a trade-mark
                            the owner thereof may bring suit against the offender, who shall be
                            required to pay damages if investigation sustain the charges
                            made.</item>
                        <label>20.</label>
                        <item>In case of a suit for the infringement of a trade-mark procedure shall
                            be as follows: (1) If the defendant be a foreigner, the local magistrate
                            shall send a dispatch informing the consul of defendant’s nationality,
                            and shall sit with him in a trial of the case. (2) If the defendant be a
                            Chinese, the consul concerned shall send a dispatch informing the local
                            magistrate, and shall sit with <pb facs="0345" n="239" xml:id="pg_239"/>
                            him in a trial of the suit. (3) If both parties to the suit should be
                            foreigners, or if both parties should be Chinese, immediately upon
                            information being given of the infringement, the court or officer having
                            jurisdiction will take action as required, so that due protection may be
                            given.</item>
                        <label>21.</label>
                        <item>Anyone guilty of any of the following offenses may be punished with
                            not more than one year’s imprisonment and not more than 300 taels fine,
                            but no action shall be taken against any such offender except after suit
                            duly brought by the injured party. <list>
                                <label>(i)</label>
                                <item>Imitation of another’s trade-mark with the purpose of using
                                    such imitation upon the same sort of goods as that on which the
                                    original is used, or selling such imitation.</item>
                                <label>(ii)</label>
                                <item>Making an imitation of another’s trade-mark and using the same
                                    upon the same sort of goods as those upon which the original is
                                    used, or, with a knowledge of the circumstances, selling such
                                    goods or storing them with the intention to sell.</item>
                                <label>(iii)</label>
                                <item>Using the imitation of another’s trade-mark as a shop sign in
                                    advertisement or placard.</item>
                                <label>(iv)</label>
                                <item>While knowing that the receptacle used by another (such as
                                    large or small box, bottle, jar, etc.) or the wrapper bears a
                                    registered trade-mark, yet using the same for goods of the same
                                    sort as the originals, or, while knowing the circumstances,
                                    selling such goods.</item>
                                <label>(v)</label>
                                <item>Purposely importing such goods into any port, knowing well
                                    that such action will injure (the sale of) another’s goods which
                                    bear a registered trademark.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>22.</label>
                        <item>When on account of the circumstances set forth above such counterfeit
                            trade-marks, or the instruments used in making them, are seized and
                            confiscated, the goods, receptacles, and signs bearing such trade-mark,
                            since it can not be distinguished from the genuine, shall all be
                            destroyed.</item>
                        <label>23.</label>
                        <item>Fees for application, registration, and issue of certificates, etc.,
                            shall be paid by all persons, whether Chinese or foreign merchants, as
                            follows: <list>
                                <label>(i)</label>
                                <item>Application fee, Kuan-p’ing taels 5 each mark.</item>
                                <label>(ii)</label>
                                <item>Fee for registration and issue of certificate, Kuan-p’ing
                                    taels 30 each mark.</item>
                                <label>(iii)</label>
                                <item>Registration of transfer of rights, by contract of sale or
                                    partnership, Kuan-p’ing taels 20 each.</item>
                                <label>(iv)</label>
                                <item>Application for extension of expired term and renewal of
                                    registration, Kuan-p’ing taels 25 each.</item>
                                <label>(v)</label>
                                <item>Copy of record of registration of trade-mark, Kuan-p’ing taels
                                    2 (for every 100 characters over 100, 50 tael cents
                                    additional).</item>
                                <label>(vi)</label>
                                <item>Examination of records, for each half hour, Kuan-p’ing taels
                                    1.</item>
                                <label>(vii)</label>
                                <item>Duplicate lost certificate, Kuan-p’ing taels 10 each.</item>
                                <label>(viii)</label>
                                <item>Filing complaint of infringement, Kuan-p’ing taels 5
                                    each.</item>
                                <label>(ix)</label>
                                <item>Application for reconsideration of rejected trade-mark,
                                    Kuan-p’ing taels 5 each.</item>
                                <label>(x)</label>
                                <item>Application for cancellation of registry, Kuan-p’ing taels 30
                                    each.</item>
                                <label>(xi)</label>
                                <item>Transfer of certificate to heirs, Kuan-p’ing taels 5
                                    each.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>24.</label>
                        <item>These regulations shall be of force from and after Kuanghsu XXX Year,
                            Ninth Moon, 15th Day (October 23, 1904).</item>
                        <label>25.</label>
                        <item>Inasmuch as mutual protection is required by the treaties, if, before
                            the bureau of registration shall have entered upon its duties, request
                            for the registration of any trade-mark shall have been presented at any
                            yamen having jurisdiction the bureau shall regard the application as
                            having been already properly made.</item>
                        <label>26.</label>
                        <item>If within six months after the bureau shall have commenced operations
                            application shall be made for the registration of trade-marks which were
                            already registered in another country before the bureau began its work,
                            the bureau shall recognize such trade-marks as entitled to
                            precedence.</item>
                        <label>27.</label>
                        <item>Although before the bureau shall have been established various
                            officials may have issued proclamations giving protection to various
                            trade-marks, such marks shall not receive the benefit of protection
                            unless within six months after the opening of the bureau application
                            shall have been made for registration according to the provisions of
                            these regulations.</item>
                        <label>28.</label>
                        <item>The provisions of the three regulations immediately preceding are
                            independent of the requirements of regulation 5.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>All of the above regulations are to be put into operation experimentally.
                        Matters not fully provided for in them may be taken into consideration and
                        rules referring to them be added after these shall have gone into
                        effect.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
