<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to Minister Rockhill.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1906p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d233</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">233</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1905-08-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1905-08-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1905-08-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1905-08-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="233"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d233">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        Minister <persName type="to">Rockhill</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-08-17">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 17, 1905</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 42.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Mr. Conger, with his No. 1842 of March 28
                        last,<note n="a" xml:id="d233fna">Not printed.</note> inclosed a pamphlet
                    containing proposals for amending the trade-mark regulations governing the
                    registration of trade-marks in China, published by the Deutsche Vereinigung, and
                    with his 1877 of May 5 last<note n="a" xml:id="d233fnb">Not printed.</note> he
                    inclosed a copy of a project formulated by the diplomatic representatives in
                    China of Great Britain, Germany, Italy, and Austria, intended to serve as a
                    basis for negotiations on the subject of the registration of trade-marks in
                    China.</p>
                <p>These two dispatches have been considered by the Secretary of the Interior and
                    the Commisisoner of Patents, and I inclose herewith for your information and
                    guidance their views thereon.<note n="a" xml:id="d233fnc">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>You will observe that they find that the project inclosed with Mr. Conger’s No.
                    1877 is in accordance with the general construction of the trade-mark laws of
                    this country and most European countries, and that it is not objectionable in
                    any material regard, excepting section 25, which reads as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>All demands of registration made by means of the competent Chinese
                            authorities before the going into force of the present regulation shall
                            be considered as having been made the day of the regulation going into
                            force.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>It is pointed out that this section may destroy the effect of registrations
                    effected by American owners of trade-marks under the trademark regulations
                    heretofore published. It would appear just that the effect of such regulations
                    should not be impaired.</p>
                <p>They also call attention to the fact that section 22 of the project referred to,
                    which reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>One can not be prosecuted in any case who shall prove that he first
                            lawfully in any country made the use which he “loyally” continues, of
                            the same mark before the registration opposed to him in China,</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0354" n="248" xml:id="pg_248"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">has been replaced in the pamphlet published by the Deutsche
                    Vereinigung (inclosure 2 in No. 1842) by an article providing for the
                    destruction of counterfeit trade-marks and the receptacles and signs bearing
                    such trade-marks.</p>
                <p>The Commissioner of Patents points out that the retention of section 22 of the
                    project is of the greatest consequence from the American point of view; that its
                    exclusion by the Deutsche Vereinigung represents the German view of trade-mark
                    in which the property right arises from and depends upon registration; while the
                    American trade-mark position is and always has been predicated upon the origin
                    of the property right in adoption and use.</p>
                <p>In view of the opinion expressed by the Secretary of the Interior and the
                    Commissioner of Patents, that it is desirable that some adequate system be
                    adopted by the Chinese Government at the earliest possible time, you will, as
                    desired by them, offer no objection to the adoption of the project further than
                    to the probable effect of section 25, as herein pointed out.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Alvey A. Adee</hi>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Acting Secretary.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
