<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1906-08-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1906-08-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="243" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d243">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Rockhill</persName>
                                to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking,
                                        China</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-08-30"><hi rend="italic">August 30,
                                1906</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 384.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your instruction, No. 159, of June 30, with regard to the
                            rights of American merchants who applied for the registration of
                            trade-marks during the short time that the tentative trade-mark
                            regulations were in force.</p>
                        <p>On receipt of the above dispatch I communicated immediately with the
                            consuls in Shanghai and Tientsin, directing them to ascertain the
                            feeling of Americans in their respective ports on this subject and the
                            importance they attached to rights based on such applications. The
                            replies were naturally very vague, as the situation has never been clear
                            to anyone. As soon as they reached me I sent my conclusions in my
                            telegram of August 17, which I confirm, as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">August</hi> 17, 5 p.m.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary State</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Washington:</hi></p>
                                <p>In reference to your instructions 159, I have inquired through
                                    our consuls Tientsin and Shanghai. They say American merchants
                                    are inclined to believe they may have acquired some rights by
                                    filing under provisional regulations. Chinese foreign office
                                    note of December 22, 1904, inclosed, does not apparently affect
                                    the fact that for several days application for registration was
                                    lawful. Japanese probably filed very many more than Americans;
                                    other nationalities may have also. For reasons given, page 2,
                                    paragraph 2 of your instructions, I advise acceptance German
                                    proposal.</p>
                                <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rockhill.</hi></p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>I have the honor to refer once more to the legation’s dispatch No. 1788
                            of January 7, 1905, and to state that, though I consider the stand taken
                            by the American Government from the outset has been right and just, I do
                            not think that, as far as can be judged in the <pb facs="0365" n="259" xml:id="pg_259"/> prevailing confusion, American acquired rights
                            would suffer materially if the Government were in the interests of
                            harmony to modify its attitude and come to an agreement with Germany and
                            the other powers.</p>
                        <p>In gauging the importance of this discussion we should not lose sight of
                            the fact that the purpose of these regulations is to prevent the
                            manufacture and sale of spurious foreign articles by the Chinese. As a
                            matter of fact, the Chinese do not manufacture fraudulent imitations of
                            foreign articles, and a very simple enactment would be sufficient to
                            avert this danger for a long time to come. As for the sale of spurious
                            goods of foreign manufacture, redress should lie in taking action in the
                            country of their origin or in the consular courts of those countries
                            whose nationals import such goods and sell them to the Chinese, and with
                            whom we have concluded by exchange of notes arrangements for this
                            purpose.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">W. W. Rockhill.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>