<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ambassador Hengelmüller von Hengervár to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1906p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d34</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">34</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1906-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1906-06-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1906-06-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1906-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="34"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d34">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">Hengelmüller von
                            Hengervár</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                        State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Imperial and Royal Austro-Hungarian Embassy</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Bar Harbor</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-06-10">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 10, 1906</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1002.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: In a note, F. O., No. 124, dated in
                    Vienna, December 30, 1904,<note n="a" xml:id="d34fna">Not printed. See <ref
                            target="frus1904#pg_89">Foreign Relations, 1904, pp. 89</ref>–<ref
                            target="frus1904#pg_91">91</ref>.</note> the then ambassador of the
                    United States, by direction of the State Department, lodged in the imperial and
                    royal foreign office a complaint against the alleged confiscation by the
                    Hungarian authorities of a “prepaid ticket” belonging to the American citizen
                    Marie Hornyak and preferred an indemnity claims.<note n="a" xml:id="d34fnb">Not
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The imperial and royal foreign office did not fail to ask the Hungarian ministry
                    of the interior to cause the matter to be investigated.</p>
                <p>The investigation, as I am informed by my Government, has shown, contrary to some
                    of Marie Hornyak’s statements, the facts in the case to be as follows.</p>
                <p>On the 13th of September, 1904, the said Hornyak, with her three children, called
                    on the agent of the Cunard Steamship Company at <pb facs="0157" n="51"
                        xml:id="pg_51"/> Kassa, Hungary, and, after producing her certificate of
                    American citizenship, asked for four steamship tickets for New York via Fiume,
                    which were assigned to her upon payment of 160 kronen. She left the same day
                    from Kassa. On her arrival at Fiume she called, on the 19th of September, 1904,
                    at the office of the Steam Navigation Company, the <hi rend="italic">Adria</hi>,
                    agent for the Cunard Line, and asserted that her husband had sent her a prepaid
                    ticket by the way of Bremen, which had been since confiscated. Her request to
                    the <hi rend="italic">Adria</hi> that her husband be cabled to send by telegram
                    the amount wanted to make up the full cost of the tickets from Fiume to Eckley,
                    Pa., was not complied with in view of her having but 80 kronen ready money at
                    her disposal, but she was promised at the same time that her matter would be
                    satisfactorily arranged.</p>
                <p>Thereupon Mrs. Hornyak sought the intervention of the American consular agent at
                    Fiume, Mr. Dela Guardia, who found among her papers the prepaid ticket via
                    Bremen that she said had been confiscated.</p>
                <p>As the woman objected to undertaking at that time the trip from Fiume to Bremen,
                    Mr. Dela Guardia, to whom she had turned over the prepaid ticket via Bremen,
                    succeeded in his effort to induce the regular agent of the Cunard Line at Fiume,
                    upon security for the full payment of the ticket from Fiume to Eckley, Pa., to
                    accommodate Mrs. Hornyak and her children on board the steamship <hi
                        rend="italic">Ultonia</hi>, sailing on September 22, 1904, for New York, and
                    she did make the trip on that ship.</p>
                <p>It appears from the foregoing: <list>
                        <item>First. That Mrs. Hornyak was not compelled to sail via Fiume;</item>
                        <item>Second. That her prepaid ticket by the way of Bremen was not
                            confiscated;</item>
                        <item>Third. That the unpleasantness she underwent can only be ascribed to
                            her ignorance or inexperience.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Under the circumstances the Royal Hungarian Government—and your excellency’s true
                    sense of justice will readily concur therein—does not hold itself liable to Mrs.
                    Hornyak for an indemnity.</p>
                <p>While venturing to beg that your excellency will kindly acknowledge the receipt
                    of this note, I avail, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hengelmüller.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
