<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Chargé Sleeper to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1906p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d390</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">390</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1906-08-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1906-08-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1906-08-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1906-08-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="390"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d390">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Chargé <persName type="from">Sleeper</persName> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Habana, Cuba</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-08-21">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 21, 1906</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 157.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that, as foreshadowed
                    in legation No. 1478, of February 27, 1906,<note n="a" xml:id="d390fna">Not
                        printed.</note> an armed uprising against the Government exists in the
                    provinces of Pinar del Rio and Habana.</p>
                <p>The strength of the insurrectionists in Pinar del Rio is said to be between 1,000
                    and 1,500 men, under the command of Col. Pino Guerra, a liberal member of the
                    present Congress and a veteran of the war of independence. In the province of
                    Habana about 250 men are under arms, under the leadership of Gen. Quintin
                    Banderas (colored), who also served in the revolutionary army. Both of these
                    bands are daily receiving new recruits.</p>
                <p>The Government relies chiefly upon the rural guard, in which, it must be
                    confessed, there is some disaffection. In one instance a detail of about 30 men
                    sent against the insurrectionists deserted to them. It is commonly reported that
                    this disaffection extends to nearly one-half of the entire guard, and for this
                    reason, as well as on account of the necessity for increasing the armed forces,
                    the President, on the 20th instant, issued a decree, translation inclosed
                    herewith, providing for the immediate recruiting of some 2,000 men, most of whom
                    will be veterans of the last war, who will form a force which may be relied
                    upon.</p>
                <p>Up to the present time the insurgents have confined themselves to marauding, the
                    cutting of telephone and telegraph wires, and other petty acts. Several minor
                    encounters have taken place (the outcome of which has not been divulged by the
                    Government), but no serious fighting has as yet been reported. I was yesterday
                    informed by good, but not official, authority that the town of Consolacion del
                    Sur, near Pinar del Rio, the capital of Pinar del Rio Province, has been
                    invested by the insurgents, who compelled the small garrison of rural guards
                    there stationed to entrench themselves in the town church.</p>
                <p>The Government has made many arrests and seems to be acting with energy and
                    determination. Among those in custody are Generals Carlos Garcia Velez,
                    ex-minister to Mexico, Demetrio Castillo Duany, José de Jesus Monteagudo, and
                    Mr. Juan Gualberto Gomez; these last three Liberals.</p>
                <pb facs="0561" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/>
                <p>Gen. José Miguel Gomez, the central figure in the last uprising, is this morning
                    reported, on good authority, to have taken the field against the Government.</p>
                <p>Doctor O’Farrill, now acting secretary of government, informed me yesterday that
                    the Government feels fully able to cope with the situation, and while I believe
                    the outbreak to be more serious than the Government cares to admit, I also
                    believe public opinion throughout the island to be clearly against any
                    disturbance of the public order, and can see no reason why the Government should
                    not crush the revolt with the resources at its disposal.</p>
                <p>I confirm on the overleaf my telegrams of yesterday and to-day, and inclose
                    herewith pertinent clippings from the Habana Post and Daily Telegraph of this
                        date.<note n="a" xml:id="d390fnb">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Jacob Sleeper.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">department of government.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The Honorable President of the Republic has issued the following decree:
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p rend="right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi>, <hi rend="italic">August 20,
                                    1906</hi>.</p>
                            <p>In view of the abnormal state of affairs existing at present in some
                                localities, and acting under clause 1 of article 68 of the
                                constitution, which authorizes the President of the Republic to
                                issue such orders and decrees that may be deemed necessary for the
                                government of the state, and circumstances may so demand, and also
                                in accordance with the provisions of paragraph 17 of article 68,
                                authorizing the President to take whatever measures may be necessary
                                for the preservation of public order and safety, on the advice of
                                the secretary of state and justice, ad interim of Government, and
                                after consultation with the Cabinet, I hereby decree:</p>
                            <p rend="right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">August</hi> 20, 1906.</p>
                            <list>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1. To increase the strength of
                                    the rural guard to 2,000 more members, their personnel to be
                                    appointed by its chief brigadier, and said members shall serve
                                    in the various regiments at present constituting the rural
                                    guard.</item>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 2. Said personnel shall be
                                    provided for from the appropriation made for the rural guard,
                                    according to the regulations in force, and said expense and
                                    other contingencies necessary for the execution of this decree
                                    to be paid out of the national treasury.</item>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 3. The secretary of government
                                    shall give the necessary instructions for the execution of this
                                    decree, and shall report his action to Congress immediately upon
                                    the reconvening thereof.</item>
                            </list>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">T. Estrada Palma.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Juan F. O’Farrill</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State and Justice ad Interim of
                                Government.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
