<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Morgan to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1906p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d465</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">465</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1906-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1906-05-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1906-05-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1906-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="465"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d465">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Morgan</persName> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Habana</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-05-05">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 5, 1906</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 59.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit in original and
                    translation the text of a convention between the Republics of France and Cuba
                    regarding the protection of trade-marks and industrial property, which was
                    ratified at Habana upon the 11th of April last by the duly accredited
                    representatives of both nations.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Edwin V. Morgan.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">thomas estrada palma, president of the republic of
                            cuba.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">To the inhabitants thereof, be it known:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>That on the 4th day of June, 1904, there was concluded and signed in the city
                        of Habana, by duly authorized plenipotentiaries, a convention referring to
                        the protection of industrial property between the Republic of Cuba and the
                        French Republic, to wit:</p>
                    <p>The President of the Republic of Cuba and the President of the French
                        Republic, desiring to facilitate the commercial relations between the two
                        countries, have resolved to conclude a convention referring to industrial
                        property, and have appointed for that purpose the following
                        plenipotentiaries:</p>
                    <p>The President of the Republic of Cuba, Mr. Carlos de Zaldo, and Beurmann,
                        secretary of state and justice; and</p>
                    <p>The President of the French Republic, Mr. Francois Edmond Bruwaert, minister
                        resident of France at Habana, officer of the Legion of Honor; who, after
                        having communicated to each other their respective full powers, found in
                        good and due form, have agreed upon the following articles:</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article I</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The citizens of each of the high contracting parties shall have in the
                        territory of the other the same rights as the natives in respect to patents,
                        designs, or industrial models, trade-marks, labels, samples, and trade
                        names, as well as to names of places and statements of origin.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article II</hi>.</p>
                    <p>To enjoy the protection guaranteed by the preceding article the persons
                        subject to the jurisdiction of one and the other State shall not be obliged
                        to establish their domicile, their residence, or a commercial house in the
                        country wherein protection is claimed; but they shall fulfill the other
                        conditions and formalities prescribed by the laws and regulations of that
                        country.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article III</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The present convention shall be applied in Cuba to trade-marks legally
                        acquired in France by manufacturers and merchants using them; and
                        reciprocally it shall be applied in France to trade-marks legally acquired
                        in Cuba by manufacturers and merchants using them.</p>
                    <p>It is understood, however, that each of the two States reserves the right to
                        refuse to register and to prohibit the use of any trade-mark which is, by
                        its nature, immoral or detrimental to public order or good manners.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article IV</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Commercial names, firm names, and samples shall be protected in the two
                        States even though unregistered.</p>
                    <pb facs="0628" n="522" xml:id="pg_522"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article V.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The act of placing or causing to be placed on an article a false statement of
                        origin, indicating, directly or indirectly, as country or place of origin
                        one of the contracting States or a place situated therein, shall be punished
                        in accordance with the laws of each country.</p>
                    <p>If the case is not provided for by any law, it shall be subject to the
                        regulations existing against the falsification of trade-marks.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article VI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The provisions contained in Articles III and V shall be enforced at the
                        request of the Government or of the interested party, individual or firm, in
                        accordance with the legislation of each State.</p>
                    <p>Every manufacturer, merchant, or producer, occupied in the manufacture, sale,
                        or production of the article and established in the city, locality, region,
                        or country falsely given as the place of origin, shall be considered an
                        interested party.</p>
                    <p>The authorities shall not be obliged to effect the seizure during
                        transit.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article VII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The present regulations shall not bebar the vender from placing his name and
                        address on products originating in a different country from the one in which
                        they are sold, but, in such case, the address or the name must be
                        accompanied by an exact statement—in large letters—of the country or of the
                        place of manufacture or production.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article VIII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The courts of each country shall decide what kind of names are, on account of
                        their generic character, as for instance, brandy, vermouth, and cologne
                        water, to be excluded from the terms of the present convention. Statements
                        as to districts of origin of wine products are not included, however, in the
                        exception prescribed herein.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article IX</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The present convention shall be ratified and the ratifications shall be
                        exchanged in Habana immediately after the fulfillment of the formalities
                        prescribed by the constitutional laws of the contracting States.</p>
                    <p>It shall be declared in force from the date of the aforesaid exchange and it
                        shall remain in force until one of the two contracting parties shall have
                        advised the other—six months in advances—of its intention to terminate
                        same.</p>
                    <p>In faith whereof the respective plenipotentiaries have signed and sealed the
                        present convention.</p>
                    <p>Done at Habana, in two originals, June 4, 1904.</p>
                    <p rend="right">(Signed) <hi rend="smallcaps">Carlos de Zaldo</hi>. [<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>]</p>
                    <p rend="right">(Signed) <hi rend="smallcaps">Edmond Bruwaert</hi>. [<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>]</p>
                    <p>The preceding convention was approved by the Senate of the Republic of Cuba
                        the 15th day of September, 1904.</p>
                    <p>And the ratifications were exchanged at this capital to-day.</p>
                    <p>Therefore I order its publication and that it be duly carried out.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>Habana</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1906-04-11">April 11, 1906</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">T. Estrada Palma.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Juan F. O’Farrill</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State and Justice.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
