<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Dawson to the Secretary of State..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1906p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d482</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">482</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1906-01-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1906-01-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85115805"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rule of law</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1906-01-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1906-01-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="482"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d482">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Dawson</persName> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Santo Domingo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-01-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 2, 1906</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 202.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Continuing the subject of my No. 199<note n="a"
                        xml:id="d482fna">Printed in <ref target="frus1905#pg_410">Foreign Relations,
                            1905, p. 410</ref>.</note> of December 20, political conditions in this
                    Republic, I have the honor to report that in pursuance of my efforts to avoid a
                    breach between the cabinet on the one side and the president and the Jimenista
                    authorities on the other, I sent a letter on December 21 to the American
                    consular agent to Monte Christi. (Copy inclosed.) Mr. Petit is in constant and
                    amicable relations with Governor Arias, and I hoped the information given in
                    regard to the determination of the cabinet not to interfere with the status quo
                    in Monte Christi might tend to restrain the governor from rash action.</p>
                <p>On the evening of the 21st I received the following telegram from the commander
                    of the U. S. S. <hi rend="italic">Nashville</hi>, then at Puerto Plata: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Puerto Plata</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 21,
                                1905.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Minister</hi>:</p>
                        <p>Have received authentic information the vice-president coming here to
                            remove forcibly present governor of Puerto Plata. He will resist
                            defending constitutional government. Please communicate immediately with
                            President.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chambers.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Early in the morning of the 22d I called on the minister of foreign affairs, who
                    told me that the vice-president did not intend to go immediately to Puerto
                    Plata, that no action looking to the removal of Governor Perez had been taken,
                    and none would be, at least until the receipt of further advices as to his
                    attitude. I also called on the President, who said that no government decree on
                    the subject had been adopted, that he hoped that the vice-president would not
                    attempt to expel Perez without legal authority, because Perez would surely
                    resist in such a case. I asked him to use his influence with Perez to avoid any
                    violence, and he said that he, as in the past, would do everything in his power
                    to prevent disturbances and civil war.</p>
                <p>I thereupon sent the following telegram: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 22,
                                1905.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nashville</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Puerto
                                Plata:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Inform consul Government gives assurance to me Caceres has no intention
                            forcibly to remove governor. Full letter has been forwarded to you from
                            me on <hi rend="italic">Seminole.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dawson.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0643" n="537" xml:id="pg_537"/>
                <p>On the afternoon of the 23d I was informed by the minister of foreign affairs
                    that Governor Perez had ordered the arrest of the Horacista, commandante de
                    Puerto, who had resisted and been shot; that the Government had thereupon
                    adopted a decree removing Perez, but would give him every opportunity to comply
                    before proceeding forcibly to put it into effect.</p>
                <p>I thereupon telegraphed you as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 23,
                                1905.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Dominican Government informs me governor of Puerto Plata since this
                            morning barricaded in citadel and arresting Horacistas, causing general
                            alarm.</p>
                        <p>The Dominican Government thereupon named his successor; resistance
                            feared. The Dominican Government intends act with caution and
                            legally.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dawson.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>This bad news was confirmed early the next morning by the following telegram from
                    the consul at Puerto Plata: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Puerto Plata</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 23,
                                1905.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Minister</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Santo
                                Domingo:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Captain of Port Miguel Ramirez was shot and wounded at noon resisting
                            order of arrest from governor. Government position apparently strong.
                            Anticipate further trouble.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Handley.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">which was followed shortly by this: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Puerto Plata</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 23,
                                1905.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Consul</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Santo
                                Domingo:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Unless President will direct governor to comply with order of minister
                            interior to vacate in favor of Cocco, trouble will ensue. Can you advise
                            President to send order?</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Handley.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>I sent for the minister of foreign affairs and asked him if the decree removing
                    Perez had been adopted. He answered in the affirmative, saying that not only had
                    the official order signed by the minister of interior been telegraphed, but that
                    Morales himself had also telegraphed over his own signature. He added that no
                    doubt Perez was urging Morales to break with the cabinet and that, hoping to get
                    personal and secret orders to ignore the official telegrams, he might believe
                    that the President’s signature had been placed to the telegram without his
                    consent. I thereupon showed the minister the messages I had received from the
                    consul and told him I proposed, in the interest of peace, at Puerto Plata to
                    transmit to the consul a copy of any telegram which President Morales might
                    inform me he had already sent, and to grant Perez temporary asylum if he should
                    want it. The latter measure would, of course, tend to facilitate the peaceful
                    transfer of the governorship, and the minister said that he and the President
                    would be pleased if I should take it.</p>
                <p>Accordingly I addressed a note to President Morales asking him to be kind enough
                    to send me a copy of the telegram, if, in fact, he had sent one.</p>
                <p>Later in the afternoon I received the copy in question and thereupon telegraphed
                    the consul as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 24,
                                1905.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Consul</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Puerto
                                Plata:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>President informs me he sent following telegram: “Gobernador. Entregue á
                            Manuel Cocco conforme telegramma anterior. Morales.”</p>
                        <p>If Perez wishes asylum you may give it. Government will not object. Keep
                            me informed.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dawson.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0644" n="538" xml:id="pg_538"/>
                <p>Except the copy of his telegram I received that afternoon no message either
                    written or by telephone from the President, and had no reason to think that he
                    had changed his mind since my interview with him two days before. Indeed I since
                    learn that he had spent most of the afternoon of the 24th in amicable
                    conversation with Ministers Tejera and Velasquez.</p>
                <p>At 7 o’clock that evening he left the city alone, walked out 2 miles where 25 or
                    30 young men assembled on the pretext of a Christmas eve “sancoche” or supper
                    were awaiting him. Only three of his bodyguard met him on the outside, and his
                    most intimate political and personal friends, such as ex-Minister Sanchez and
                    Pichardo, knew nothing of his intention.</p>
                <p>Morales and his party seized some government cavalry horses from a pasture near
                    our legation and about 8 or 9 o’clock rode west, arriving at the Jaina River, 10
                    miles distant, about 11. There they stopped for the night and were quickly
                    joined by Rimaldo and Cesario Pimentel, two famous Jimenista jefes, who live in
                    that neighborhood and can raise a considerable body of followers at a moment’s
                    notice.</p>
                <p>The news of Morales’s departure became known in town about 10 o’clock, and
                    immediately the whole city was in an uproar. Early next morning a hundred or so
                    government troops went in pursuit, and news soon came that fighting was going on
                    this side of the Jaina.</p>
                <p>I thereupon telegraphed you as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 25,
                                1905</hi>.</p>
                        <p>President left city suddenly and secretly last night. Government force
                            pursuing him; general disturbances likely.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dawson.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The minister and the governor informed me that I had better remove my family into
                    the city since my house is situated on the road along which the night scouting
                    parties of both sides would advance. Accordingly I and the other residents of
                    the Guibia suburb brought our families into the city.</p>
                <p>There was a great deal of firing along the line of the Jaina that night, but the
                    Morales people seem to have confined their efforts to holding the Government
                    forces back.</p>
                <p>On the afternoon of the 25th the minister of foreign affairs sent a circular note
                    to all foreign representatives, inclosing a resolution of the cabinet
                    (translations herewith) calling the vice-president to the capital to take charge
                    of the Presidency temporarily during the absence of the President.</p>
                <p>I thereupon telegraphed you as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 26,
                                1905</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Dominican minister for foreign affairs notifies diplomatic corps that
                            President having clandestinely abandoned capital leaving Government
                            without acting head cabinet has called vice-president to take charge
                            pending temporary failure of President to exercise his functions. See
                            article forty-six Dominican constitution. Send instructions. City quiet.
                            Cabinet exercising functions without interruption. President reported at
                            Jaina among revolutionists; fighting there reported. New governor
                            peacefully installed Puerto Plata.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dawson.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">and answered the minister’s note saying that I would ask for
                    instructions from my Government. (Copy inclosed.)</p>
                <pb facs="0645" n="539" xml:id="pg_539"/>
                <p>The chargé d’affaires of France and Spain and the consuls of Germany and England
                    asked me how I had answered the note, and I understand that their answers are
                    practically identical with mine. The Haitian minister takes the position that
                    without instructions he is justified in recognizing that the presidency became
                    temporarily vacant and that the vice-president is legally exercising its
                    functions.</p>
                <p>It seemed to me, however, that there existed no immediate necessity for foreign
                    representatives to express themselves in regard to what is primarily a point of
                    Dominican constitutional law, i. e., whether Morales or Caceres is at this
                    moment the legal head of the Government. The cabinet formerly named by President
                    Morales is still in possession and exercising their functions. The only power
                    given the President by the Dominican constitution is that of naming and removing
                    the cabinet ministers. Once named they are the executive, and until they are
                    removed or attempted to be removed by either Morales or Caceres, or are expelled
                    from the capital and government offices, the question of who has the right to
                    remove them is largely academic.</p>
                <p>In the meantime Perez, finding that public opinion in Puerto Plata was against
                    him in his intention to resist the installation of the new governor, had given
                    up. On the evening of the 24th, after the President had left, but before I knew
                    of his departure, I received the following telegram from the United States naval
                    officer in command at Puerto Plata: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Puerto Plata</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 24,
                                1905.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Scorpion</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Santo
                                Domingo:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Urgent: For American minister. Interior has appointed Manual Cocco, very
                            popular, as governor; is satisfied present governor desires to attack
                            constitutional authority, but having positive direct order from the
                            President to resist vice-president and not to give up, he can not vacate
                            without battle. If you can persuade the President to issue positive
                            order, governor will obey gladly.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chambers.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>On the morning of the 26th came the following telegram from Consul Handley:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Puerto Plata</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 26,
                                1905.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Minister</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Santo
                                Domingo:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Cocco in charge Gobernación. Perez sailed for Turks Island yesterday.
                            Caceres arrive to-day.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Handley.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Perez did in fact sail for Turks Island, but immediately left there for Monte
                    Christi, accompanied by ex-Vice-President Eugenio Deschamps, Gen. Joaquin Barba,
                    and other Jimenista exiles.</p>
                <p>In the afternoon I was handed by a person unknown to me a letter from President
                    Morales, of which the following is a translation: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 24,
                                1905.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">T. C. Dawson</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister of the United States, City</hi>.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Distinguished Sir</hi>: The brutal insults to the
                            constitution and my dignity as President of the Republic have forced me
                            to absent myself from this city with the purpose of reestablishing the
                            rule of law. As soon as I reach an important center of population I
                            shall constitute the capital and remove the cabinet that is personally
                            hostile to me.</p>
                        <p>I salute you,</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Morales</hi> L.,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">President of the Republic.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0646" n="540" xml:id="pg_540"/>
                <p>To this I answered.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 26,
                            1905.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Señor <hi rend="smallcaps">Carlos F. Morales</hi>, L., etc.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir and Friend</hi>: I am in receipt of your
                        personal letter of the 24th instant in regard to your intention to absent
                        yourself from this capital, an intention which I am informed you have since
                        carried into effect.</p>
                    <p>I will telegraph its contents to Washington and ask for instructions.</p>
                    <p>Yours, most respectfully,</p>
                    <p rend="right">(Signed) <hi rend="smallcaps">T. C. Dawson.</hi>
                    </p>
                </quote>
                <p>I thereupon telegraphed you as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 27,
                                1905</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Have received letter of President dated the 24th, saying that he is about
                            to absent himself from capital in order to reestablish legal procedure,
                            and later on will declare another city temporary capital, and will then
                            name a new cabinet. He is reported to be 15 miles west, fighting. Troops
                            sent by cabinet. American citizens interior alarmed, fearing that
                            landing American seamen would be followed by violence to themselves.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dawson.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>On midnight of the 26th I received the following telegram: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Puerto Plata</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 26,
                                1905.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Minister</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Santo
                                Domingo:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Your cable forwarded. Caceres sent commission Monte Christi on <hi
                                rend="italic">Dubuque</hi> to confer with Rodriguez.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Handley.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>And on the 28th following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Puerto Plata</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 28,
                                1905.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Minister</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Santo
                                Domingo:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Commission to Monte Christi failure. Rodriguez concentrating forces
                            Guayubin, Horacistas, Santiago, and Navarrete. Perez arrived Monte
                            Christi.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Handley.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>I thereupon telegraphed you as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 28,
                                1905</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Jimenistas advancing from Monte Christi against Santiago. The President
                            still fighting near Jaina. His force small. City quiet, but
                            apprehensive.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dawson.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>On the 29th the U. S. S. <hi rend="italic">Dubuque</hi> arrived here from Monte
                    Christi, bringing me a copy of Governor Arias’s proclamation, which I inclose
                    for your information, with the translation thereof.</p>
                <p>The same day the minister of foreign affairs informed me that the gunboat <hi
                        rend="italic">Independencia</hi> had left Macoris at 9 p.m. of the 26th with
                    orders to carry $8,000 in cash, 60,000 rounds of rifle cartridges, 100 rifles,
                    and some shells to the governors of Sanchez and Puerto Plata, but that her
                    commander had disobeyed and taken his ship to Monte Christi, where he had placed
                    himself under the orders of Governor Arias. The arrival of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Independencia</hi> at Monte Christi was confirmed by telegrams received by
                    the commander of the <hi rend="italic">Dubuque</hi>, and I accordingly
                    telegraphed you as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 29,
                                1905.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sec. State</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Washington:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Gunboat <hi rend="italic">Independencia</hi>, sent by cabinet to Sanchez
                            with munitions, has deserted and gone to Monte Christi. Will probably
                            bring expedition against Macoris or other point. Whereabouts of the
                            President unknown. The vice-president arrives here to-day.</p>
                        <p>French chargé d’affaires offers, if agreeable to the American Government,
                            to send Martinique for war ship to aid in protecting lives foreigners,
                            which might be endangered by landing American seamen.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dawson.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0647" n="541" xml:id="pg_541"/>
                <p>The French telegraph line across the island had been cut various times since the
                    24th, and I had been trying to get my messages through by the government line to
                    Puerto Plata. I could not, however, be sure that you have received my telegrams,
                    and was relieved to receive your cable, as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 29,
                                1905</hi>.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dawson</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Santo Domingo:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Your cable December 29.</p>
                        <p>Instructions in my cable of December 6 should be followed strictly. In
                            that case there will be no landing of troops under any such
                            circumstances as to justify apprehension of danger to lives of
                            foreigners.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Root.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>On the 30th I received two notes from the minister of foreign affairs, the first
                    asking that our naval forces detain the <hi rend="italic">Independencia</hi>,
                    and the second that she be prevented from carrying arms about the coast for the
                    purpose of fomenting civil war. Copies and translations inclosed. I told the
                    minister that I had no authority to give any orders to our naval vessels nor to
                    give him any assurances on the subject; that such orders would be given from
                    Washington. I agreed, however, at his urgent request to telegraph you and did
                    so, as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December 30,
                                1905</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Dominican minister for foreign affairs requests that naval orders be
                            given to prevent gunboat <hi rend="italic">Independencia</hi> from
                            carrying arms, et cetera, from revolting governor of Monte Christi to
                            other ports for the purpose of disturbing public order. Have answered
                            that I have no such authority. This telegram sent you at his urgent
                            request.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dawson.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>After receiving your telegram of December 29, I answered Señor Tejera’s notes in
                    regard to the <hi rend="italic">Independencia</hi>, calling his attention again
                    to the fact that I would continue to act in accordance with your instructions to
                    me of December 6 (7). Copy inclosed.</p>
                <p>On the morning of the 29th, Vice-President Caceres and a large number of members
                    of Congress arrived. The Congress met in special session on the afternoon of the
                    30th. An accusation for high treason against the President had been begun by the
                    minister of interior, and a bill for a decree declaring him under impeachment
                    was introduced in Congress and passed its first reading on the 31st.</p>
                <p>I thereupon telegraphed you as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">January 1,
                                1906.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Forward following telegram:</p>
                        <p>“Congress yesterday passed first reading impeachment of the President.
                            President’s whereabouts still unknown here.”</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dawson.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Yesterday the bill passed a second reading, and to-day its third and final
                    reading. If possible before the mail closes I will inclose copy. Its effect is
                    to declare that the vice-president shall be acting president pending the trial
                    of the president before the supreme court.</p>
                <p>I inclose copy of a note from the minister of foreign affairs, announcing the
                    passage of the bill just as I finish this dispatch. I have also sent you the
                    following telegram: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">January 2,
                                1906</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Dominican minister for foreign affairs has informed me that to-day,
                            January 1, Dominican Congress has declared the President in state of
                            impeachment, and that by virtue of this and of article 46 Dominican
                            constitution the vice-president will exercise temporarily functions of
                            president.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dawson.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0648" n="542" xml:id="pg_542"/>
                <p>This I send by a Dominican Government steamship to Mayaguez because all
                    telegraphic and telephone communication with the United States is interrupted
                    since this morning by the cutting of the lines in the vicinity of Puerto
                    Plata.</p>
                <p>Of the events at Puerto Plata you are probably better informed than I through the
                    telegrams to the Navy Department. All I know at present is that the <hi
                        rend="italic">Independencia</hi> is in front of Puerto Plata threatening
                    bombardment, has landed forces near the town, and that there has been some
                    fighting.</p>
                <p>There is no news yet as to the whereabouts of President Morales.</p>
                <p>I have not had time to prepare translations of the inclosures herewith and beg
                    that they may be translated in the department if necessary.</p>
                <p>I also inclose marked copy of the Dominican constitution, calling your attention
                    to the following provisions applicable to the question raised by the President’s
                    action in leaving the capital: Article 6; article 25, section 4; articles 38,
                    39, 45, 46, 47, 50, 59; and article 69, section 2.<note n="a" xml:id="d482fnb"
                        >Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">T. C. Dawson.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Dawson</persName> to the
                            American Consular Agent <persName type="to">Petit</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Santo Domingo</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-12-21">
                                <hi rend="italic">December 21, 1905</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Petit</hi>: Fearing that exaggerated rumors of
                        the events of November 27 and December 6 and their consequences may have
                        reached Monte Christi, I think it best to inform you briefly of the
                        truth.</p>
                    <p>There was a difference of opinion between the President and a majority of his
                        cabinet about certain appointments and policies. Feeling arose to a
                        dangerous point, the President was counseled to make a radical change in his
                        cabinet, and certain extreme Horacistas advocated his resignation and a
                        refusal to ratify the convention. Happily better counsels prevailed on both
                        sides. The President determined to retain his cabinet, except Mr. Sanchez,
                        and the opinion of Caceres and Emiliano Tejera prevailed with the
                        Horacistas. They will sustain the President to the end of his term, and the
                        convention will be ratified. The guaranties to Governor Arias remain as they
                        were. Morales especially stipulated as to this.</p>
                    <p>I hear disquieting rumors from Monte Christi, but do not credit them,
                        especially as I have not heard from you.</p>
                    <p>You may show this letter at your discretion. Please present my respects to
                        Governor. Arias.</p>
                    <p>Yours truly,</p>
                    <closer>(Signed) <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">T. C. Dawson.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Dawson</persName> to the
                                <gloss type="to">Dominican Minister of Foreign Affairs</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Santo Domingo</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-12-26">
                                <hi rend="italic">December 26, 1905</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                        receipt of your note of yesterday inclosing a copy of the resolution of the
                        council of secretaries of state taken on account of the departure of
                        President Morales.</p>
                    <pb facs="0649" n="543" xml:id="pg_543"/>
                    <p>I shall immediately transmit its contents to my Government, and upon
                        receiving the instructions that may be sent me will communicate with you
                        further in answer to your note.</p>
                    <p>In the meantime I improve the opportunity to renew, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">T. C. Dawson.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">desiderio arias, civil and military governor of the
                            district of monte christi.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Fellow-citizens</hi>: The President of the Republic
                        being alarmed by the actions of the Horacista party, which until yesterday
                        shared with him the functions of government, had ordered me to be on the
                        lookout for what might occur.</p>
                    <p>A series of gross impositions on the sovereignty of the nation in the person
                        of its chief magistrate have just occurred, causing a rupture between the
                        President of the Republic and his cabinet.</p>
                    <p>As a matter of fact, dominating the army in the capital, the rebels prevented
                        the President from exercising his constitutional rights, by which he was
                        obliged to leave the city on the night of the 24th of this month, in order
                        to establish in some other place a new cabinet, making use of the powers
                        conferred upon him by article 50 of the constitution of the nation.
                        Fellow-citizens, it is the duty of all good Dominicans to further by every
                        means in their power the preservation of public order and the respect for
                        the constitution and the laws.</p>
                    <p>I shall not spare any means to produce a legal reaction after the facts which
                        I have just mentioned.</p>
                    <p>I invite you in the name of the sacred interests of the country, villainously
                        trampled upon by the ambitions of those in authority, to lend your aid for
                        the reestablishment of legal order, thus saving the Republic from the
                        dangers which threaten it. Fellow-citizens, the responsibility for the
                        present historical moment rests, and will rest, upon those wicked people,
                        who, dazzled by the power which they were using to gratify their personal
                        ambitions, turned their backs upon a national honor and throw the country
                        into anarchy and into the horrors of a fratricidal fellow-citizens! Long
                        live the constitution and let us save the Republic!</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Given in the government house of
                                <placeName>Monte Christi</placeName> on <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1905-12-25">the 25th day of December, 1905</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/> (Signed) <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Desiderio Arias.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
