<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1906-01-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1906-01-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="559" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d559">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                Chargé <persName type="to">Carter</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-01-04"><hi rend="italic">January 4,
                                1906</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 120.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to acknowledge the receipt of your
                            No. 111 of the 20th ultimo, confirming your telegram of the same date,
                            which transmits information reported to Sir Edward Grey through the
                            inspector of customs, Mr. Joseph O’Reilly, of the enlistment of
                            Newfoundland fishermen by American vessels on the advice of Mr.
                            Alexander, of the <hi rend="italic">Grampus</hi>, and also inclosing a
                            copy of Mr. O’Reilly’s letter, upon which your telegram was based.</p>
                        <p>Your telegram was communicated in full to the Secretary of Commerce and
                            Labor, who, in reply, stated that Mr. Alexander would be called upon for
                            a statement in regard to the matter upon his return to Washington, where
                            he is expected to arrive during the present week.</p>
                        <p>Meanwhile, under date of the 29th ultimo, Secretary Metcalf has
                            transmitted to me a letter dated December 21, 1905, from Mr. Alexander,
                            which, while not in direct reply to the allegations contained in your
                            telegram of December 20, denies that at any time since this season’s
                            fishing began have Newfoundland fishermen been shipped by American
                            vessels in territorial waters, or that men have been in any way assisted
                            by American masters to cross the 3-mile limit for enlistment.</p>
                        <p>I inclose copy of this letter. Its contents may be made known to Sir
                            Edward Grey.</p>
                        <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Elihu Root.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of Commerce and
                                        Labor</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Commerce and Labor,<lb/>Office of the
                                            Secretary</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-12-29"><hi rend="italic">December 29,
                                        1905</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: There is transmitted herewith copy of
                                a letter just received from fisheries agent A. B. Alexander, dated
                                Bay of Islands, Newfoundland, December 21, 1905.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">V. H.
                                Metcalf.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Alexander</persName>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Commissioner of
                                Fisheries</gloss>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Bay
                                            of Islands, Newfoundland</hi></placeName>,<lb/><date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-12-21"><hi rend="italic">December 21, 1905.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your letter of the 8th instant with
                                inclosed copy of telegram from the American ambassador at London to
                                the Secretary of State transmitted to the Secretary of Commerce and
                                Labor, together with his reply addressed to the Secretary of State,
                                was only received yesterday, it having been sent by mistake to St.
                                Johns, causing a delay of several days.</p>
                            <p>In reply to the dispatch received by the Secretary of State I would
                                repeat what has been stated in my letter of November 20 to the
                                Secretary of Commerce and Labor that at no time since the herring
                                fishery began this season at Bay of Islands have the laws of
                                Newfoundland been evaded by shipping men on American vessels in the
                                manner to which special attention is called. The schooners <hi rend="italic">Independence II</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Oregon</hi> enlisted Newfoundland men in the same manner that
                                men were shipped on the schooners <hi rend="italic">Gossip, Carrie
                                    W. Babson</hi>, and other American vessels engaged in the
                                herring fishery this season.</p>
                            <pb facs="0771" n="665" xml:id="pg_665"/>
                            <p>In the dispatch considerable stress is laid upon alleged facts
                                regarding taking men acress the 3-mile limit for enlistment and
                                bringing them back. In no instance has such a method been employed.
                                The men, each time, have rowed and sailed in their own boats outside
                                territorial waters, not going on board the vessel on which they were
                                shipped until they were beyond the 3-mile limit, and were previously
                                engaged by agents for owners and not by the masters of said vessels,
                                neither was assistance rendered to either vessel in the enlistment
                                of men other than being a witness that the transaction was legally
                                performed. Not until the receipt of your letter was I aware that any
                                question had been raised regarding the method of procedure. It will
                                be remembered that at the time men were shipped on the schooner <hi rend="italic">Gossip</hi> a report reached St. Johns,
                                Newfoundland, and shortly after was sent to Washington and
                                Gloucester that unlawful methods had been employed in enlisting the
                                men. Whoever circulated the report had no grounds for making such
                                charge. It may be that the second report, which is equally false,
                                emanated from the same source.</p>
                            <p>A letter, dated December 16, from the Secretary of Commerce and Labor
                                with inclosed copy of letter from the Secretary of State addressed
                                to the Secretary of Commerce and Labor with reference to freezing
                                herring on shore, fishing with various kinds of apparatus, etc., was
                                received yesterday. The information bearing upon the points in
                                question has been imparted to masters and owners of vessels. The
                                American captains now fully understand the interpretation the
                                Government places upon the questions involved, both as regards to
                                curing on shore, methods of capture, etc., and conforming to days
                                and seasons.</p>
                            <p>The vessels are now fishing in Middle and Goose arms, where,
                                probably, they will remain until loaded. The captains will now have
                                little or no communication with Birchy Cove, and only a limited
                                amount of information concerning their movements and catches made
                                can be obtained.</p>
                            <p>The herring fishery will end in about three weeks. Should vessels
                                remain later, they are likely to be frozen in the arms. If a
                                suitable steam vessel were on the ground near the end of the fishing
                                season, she no doubt would be of considerable service. In past years
                                vessels have frequently remained on the ground a day or two longer
                                than they should in order to obtain full cargoes, and by so doing
                                were caught in the ice, where they had to remain until the following
                                spring. Had assistance been near, the cargoes would have been
                                saved.</p>
                            <p>Fifteen American vessels have sailed with full cargoes and a number
                                of others are nearly loaded. Ten American vessels this season have
                                shipped 136 men outside 3-mile limit.</p>
                            <p>Very respectfully,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">A. B.
                                Alexander.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>