<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Earl of Elgin to Governor Sir W. MacGregor.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1906p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d612</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">612</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1906-09-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1906-09-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048668"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fishery</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1906-09-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1906-09-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="612"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d612">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Earl of Elgin</gloss> to Governor Sir
                            <persName type="to">W. MacGregor</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Downing Street</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-09-20">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 20, 1906</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 30.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your telegram of the 15th instant, in which your ministers complain of the
                    action of His Majesty’s Government in the matter of the proposed fishery modus
                    vivendi with the United States Government.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Your ministers submit that any arrangement involving the suspension of the
                        foreign fishing vessels act, 1906, is an interference with the internal
                        affairs of the colony, which violates the pledge given by the late Lord
                        Salisbury in the House of Lords in 1891, to the effect that the colony had
                        been given unlimited power with respect to its internal affairs.</item>
                    <pb facs="0848" n="742" xml:id="pg_742"/>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>In the speech referred to, Lord Salisbury drew a clear and precise
                        distinction between the internal affairs of the colony and matters of
                        international and outside interest, and insisted strongly on the right of
                        the Imperial Government to intervene in questions touching the relations of
                        the empire with foreign states. I am compelled, therefore, to infer that
                        your ministers regard the enforcement of the provisions of the foreign
                        fishing vessels act, 1906, on United States fishermen as a matter of purely
                        local concern.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I am at a loss to discover the grounds on which they hold that view, and I
                        regret that I am unable to record my assent to it. It will be within your
                        recollection that when you informed me, in February last, of the intention
                        of your ministers to propose to the colonial legislature additional
                        legislation to prevent British subjects resident in the colony from fishing
                        for American vessels, and suggested that such legislation would be regarded
                        by His Majesty’s Government as a matter of local concern, I replied that I
                        held the contrary view and that His Majesty’s Government, as responsible for
                        the proper carrying out of the provisions of Article I of the convention of
                        1818, were closely and directly interested in any legislation intended to
                        define the conditions on which the rights of the inhabitants of the United
                        States under that article were to be exercised.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Your ministers state that the act of 1906 was passed after consultation
                        with His Majesty’s Government. This remark appears to me to require
                        qualification. The only provisions of the act with which His Majesty’s
                        Government have identified themselves are those which exempt vessels
                        exercising treaty rights of fishery from the application of section 3 and
                        the first part of section 1 of the act of 1905. It is true that all the
                        other amendments of the act of 1905 drawm up by your ministers were
                        submitted to His Majesty’s Government, and that in order to remove certain
                        obvious objections to your ministers’ proposals His Majesty’s Government
                        suggested some alterations which were eventually embodied in the act of
                        1906. But His Majesty’s Government was careful at the same time to explain
                        that its action in suggesting these alterations was not to be understood as
                        in any way prejudicing the consideration of the act when passed or as in any
                        way identifying His Majesty’s Government with the policy of your ministers,
                        which they did not approve and which they did not believe to be in the
                        interests even of the colony itself.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The act as passed provided that it should not be brought into operation
                        until approved and confirmed by His Majesty in council. In the circumstances
                        which I have described it was at least uncertain whether His Majesty’s
                        Government would be prepared to take upon themselves the responsibility of
                        bringing the act into operation, and when the reply of the United States
                        Government to the British memorandum was received and it became necessary,
                        owing to the great divergence of view between the two governments which it
                        disclosed, to arrange a modus vivendi, it was clearly out of the question to
                        complicate the situation, which it was the object of the modus vivendi to
                        relieve, by imposing on United States fishermen the additional restrictions
                        contemplated by the act.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>It would be a source of great regret to me if in this or any other matter
                        His Majesty’s Government should fail either in respect for the
                        constitutional rights of the colony or in courtesy toward your <pb
                            facs="0849" n="743" xml:id="pg_743"/> ministers. As to the right of His
                        Majesty’s Government to allow the act to remain in suspense there can, I
                        submit, be no doubt, and the decision to do so was communicated to you at
                        the same time as to the United States ambassador.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>I asked in my telegram of August 8 whether your ministers had any
                        suggestions to make as to the nature of the proposed modus vivendi. By your
                        telegram of August 19 your ministers informed me that they could not consent
                        to any relaxation of the laws of the colony in favor of United States
                        fishermen, and that they strongly deprecated any provisional arrangement
                        with the United States Government, and urged that the act of 1906 should be
                        brought into force at once. In your telegram of August 22 your ministers
                        again urged that the act of 1906 should be brought into force and again
                        deprecated any provisional arrangement. The question of the payment of light
                        dues, they added, might remain in abeyance, but they could not acquiesce in
                        any evasion of the customs and fishery laws. His Majesty’s Government were
                        thus left to their own unaided devices to discover and arrange, in the very
                        short time remaining before the commencement of the fishery, a basis for a
                        modus vivendi with the United States Government, but the proposals which
                        they made to the United States Government on the 3d instant included no
                        concessions which your ministers were not prepared to make, apart from the
                        suspension of the act of 1906, and that, as I have already pointed out, was
                        entirely within the discretion of His Majesty’s Government. It was not until
                        some days after these proposals had been submitted to the United States
                        Government that your ministers evinced any readiness to consider a modus
                        vivendi. They then informed me that provided the act of 1906 was brought
                        into force they were prepared to give way on practically all the questions
                        in dispute. This intimation unfortunately came too late, and while I regret
                        that the proposals made to the United States Government do not commend
                        themselves to your ministers, I can not but feel that in the circumstances
                        no blame can fairly be imputed to His Majesty’s Government.</item>
                </list>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Elgin.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
