<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-02-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-02-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="138" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d138">
                        <head>138. Memorandum From <persName type="from">John Negroponte</persName>
                            of the National Security Council Planning Group to the Director of the
                            Planning Group (<persName corresp="#p_KRT1" type="to">Kennedy</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d138fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Institutional Files (H-Files), Box H–209, National
                                Security Decision Memoranda, <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>
                                2. Confidential.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-02-02">February 2, 1971</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>The Under Secretaries Committee</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Introduction</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>In its 2 year existence, the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Under
                            Secretaries Committee has put out some 91 <gloss target="#t_U1">U</gloss>/SMs (analogous to our <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss>s). Topics covered have varied greatly. About 60
                            percent of them have been in what one might call the political/military
                            category. Scientific and technical issues represent about 20 percent and
                            economic ones the remaining 20 percent.</p>
                        <p>Following the terms of its original charter in <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> 2,<note n="2" xml:id="d138fn2">
                                <ref target="#d11">Document 11.</ref>
                            </note> the Committee’s work has flowed mostly from matters referred to
                            it by the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Review Group (now
                            supplanted by the Senior Review Group) and matters referred to it
                            jointly by the Under Secretary of State and Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>. The Secretary of State also
                            has the authority to refer matters pertaining to interdepartmental
                            activities overseas to the Committee, although he uses it sparingly.</p>
                        <p>Almost by definition, the Committee does not handle matters of major
                            policy which require <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> or Presidential
                            consideration. Thus while Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> is a standing member, he rarely attends its
                            meetings. He is normally represented by a member of his staff.</p>
                        <pb facs="0325" n="294" xml:id="pg_294"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staffing of the Under
                                Secretaries Committee</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Once a topic has been assigned, the Under Secretaries Committee staffs it
                            by drawing on the resources of interdepartmental or ad hoc groups.
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff participation in the
                            process is determined by functional specialization. Thus <persName corresp="#p_BCRM1">Behr</persName> will be responsible when science
                            and technology is involved, <persName corresp="#p_BCF1">Bergsten</persName> for economic matters, etcetera. The usual
                            practice seems to be that staff members will follow the progress of a
                            project using their own judgment as to when—if at all—Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> should be informed of how
                            issues are developing.</p>
                        <p>Where guidance is required, it is usually requested in a memorandum
                            analysing the problem and suggesting what is considered to be the
                            appropriate guidance. When a meeting of the Under Secretaries Committee
                            itself is in question there is sometimes a recommendation as to whether
                            Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> himself should
                            attend the meeting. My impression is that the recommendation cannot help
                            but be influenced by the knowledge that Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> normally prefers not to attend.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Problem Areas</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>There appear to be no dramatic difficulties with respect to the Under
                            Secretaries Committee. Some problem areas are worth signalling: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Substance of the Committee’s Work</hi>
                                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>There are occasional complaints that the kind of work
                                            assigned to the Committee is not important enough and
                                            that it is simply a sort of catch-all for problems other
                                            elements of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                            system do not want to deal with.</p>
                                        <p>Despite these occasional grumblings, my impression from
                                            talking to <persName corresp="#p_HAA4">Art
                                                Hartman</persName> was that this is not a serious
                                            bone of contention at this time. The Committee accepts
                                            its role and the kind of work it is doing. And if it has
                                            any concrete proposals for altering the substance of its
                                            work in any way, <persName corresp="#p_HAA4">Hartman</persName> did not mention or infer them to
                                            me.</p>
                                        <p>As far as the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> is
                                            concerned, I can see no compelling reason for any change
                                            in the kind of work delegated to the Committee.</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Duplication of Effort</hi>
                                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>In a way there is a built-in check against duplication of
                                            effort since much of the staff work done by the Under
                                            Secretaries Committee is accomplished by the same people
                                            who staff other constituent parts of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>. There are, however,
                                            occasional instances where a new <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> will appear to
                                            duplicate efforts planned or underway in the Committee.
                                                <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 112<note n="3" xml:id="d138fn3">
                                                <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 112, “U.S.
                                                Post-Vietnam Policy on Use of Riot Control Agents
                                                and Herbicides in War,” January 15, 1971. (National
                                                Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Institutional Files
                                                (H-Files), Box H–179, National Security Study
                                                Memoranda, <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss>
                                                112.)</note> on the use of riot control agents and
                                            herbicides in future <pb facs="0326" n="295" xml:id="pg_295"/> wars is one such example. This
                                                <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> was issued at
                                            just the same time as the Under Secretaries Committee
                                            was about to recommend a similar study. (There is a
                                            background to this and the issuance of the <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> may have been
                                            inevitable.)</p>
                                        <p>What the <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 112
                                            experience does suggest is that before a <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> is issued we be
                                            doubly sure that it does not cross wires with projects
                                            planned or under way and which might adequately be
                                            handled elsewhere. Any decision to cross wires like this
                                            should at least be made consciously and not
                                            inadvertently.</p>
                                        <p>One way to handle this would be to require that in
                                            submitting draft <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss>s,
                                            staff officers attach a listing of similar high-level
                                            studies being conducted elsewhere in the government and,
                                            where it seems appropriate, an explanation why these
                                            studies would not serve the purposes of the contemplated
                                                <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss>.</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <p>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Systematic Staffing</hi>
                                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                                            <p>The present <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                                staffing of the Under Secretaries Committee appears
                                                to have no major shortcomings. Principal problems
                                                would appear to relate to the demands on Dr.
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s
                                                own time. Since he cannot attend as many meetings as
                                                some would like, it is important that he at least
                                                have time to focus on the relevant papers and be
                                                properly represented at the meetings.</p>
                                        </quote>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>It is perhaps not wise to set out too elaborate or rigid a
                                        mechanism for staffing the Committee. The present informal
                                        system appears to be working fairly well and any excessively
                                        formalized procedures might end up being honored in the
                                        breech.</p>
                                    <p>However, it might be worth considering establishment of a few
                                        ground rules which, if approved, could be circulated to the
                                        staff in the form of a memorandum. Among the points we would
                                        want to make would be the following. <list>
                                            <label>1.</label>
                                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> is interested in being kept
                                                informed of important developments in the work of
                                                the Under Secretaries Committee.</item>
                                            <label>2.</label>
                                            <item>Staff officers should continue their practice of
                                                summarizing issues to be discussed at Committee
                                                meetings and, where appropriate, recommend what
                                                position we should take on them. There should also
                                                be a recommendation as to whether or not he should
                                                attend the meeting. Briefing papers of this kind
                                                should reach Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s office a week before the
                                                scheduled meeting.</item>
                                            <label>3.</label>
                                            <item>In the event Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> does not attend a scheduled
                                                Under Secretaries Committee meeting, representation
                                                from the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> should
                                                be at the Senior Staff level.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </p>
                                </item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Council on International Economic
                                        Policy</hi>
                                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>Though not directly germane to this discussion, <persName corresp="#p_HAA4">Art Hartman</persName> mentioned
                                            that the creation of this new council would involve a
                                            period of adjustment as we sort out which issues are
                                            handled where. This is something that will have to be
                                            worked out as time goes by, and will probably affect the
                                            work of the Under Secretaries Committee only
                                            slightly.</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>