<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-02-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="139" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d139">
                        <head>139. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>)
                            to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RWP1" type="to">Rogers</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d139fn1">Source:
                                National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 148, State/WH
                                Relationship, Vol. 5. Secret; Exclusively Eyes Only. A handwritten
                                note at the top of page 1 reads: “Dispatched by hand to Ted Eliot,
                                2–5–71.”</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-02-05">February 5, 1971</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>State–White House Clearance Procedures</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>In recent weeks a number of outgoing State cables, which have not been
                            coordinated with the White House, in my view needed clearance in order
                            to comply with the President’s directives on clearance procedures. As
                            you know, the President described his wishes concerning White House
                            clearance in his Colorado Springs memorandum of September 1, 1969,<note n="2" xml:id="d139fn2">
                                <ref target="#d70">Document 70.</ref>
                            </note> and reaffirmed them in his memorandum of December 21, 1970,
                            Subject: “Disclosures of Classified Information and Coordination and
                            Clearance of Official Statements.”<note n="3" xml:id="d139fn3">A copy is
                                in the National Security Council, Secretariat, Directives, 1970,
                                Directive #154.</note> In both directives the President stated that,
                            “Should there be any uncertainty as to Presidential or interdepartmental
                            interests, it will be resolved in favor of clearance.”</p>
                        <p>The following cables are examples of cables which appear to have violated
                            the spirit of the President’s instructions: State 209304 (Dec. 24);
                            State 005063 (Jan. 12); State 005520 (Jan. 13); State 006930 (Jan.
                                14);<note n="4" xml:id="d139fn4">In a January 16 memorandum to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> which is attached
                                to a January 16 cover note stating “Do not send! Hold per Gen
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName>,” <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> called <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>’ attention to the
                                Presidential directives on White House clearance in light of
                                telegram 006930 to Cairo: According to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, “a message to the Egyptian Foreign
                                Minister repeated to six Ambassadors abroad as well as our
                                Ambassador to the United Nations and authorizing the latter to show
                                it to Ambassador Jarring by definition involves national policy and
                                requires White House clearance under the provisions of the
                                President’s directives.” (National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                                Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 148,
                                State/WH Relationship, Vol. 4)</note> State 007936 (Jan. 15); State
                            007497 (Jan. 15); State 007861 (Jan. 15); State 008169 (Jan. 17); State
                            016543 (Jan. 30) and State 016548 (Jan. 30). Many of these messages,
                            undoubtedly, were dispatched without your being made aware of the
                            clearance process followed. I noted, for example, that in the case of
                            State 016543 you had only cleared the message in substance.</p>
                        <pb facs="0328" n="297" xml:id="pg_297"/>
                        <p>I know that you share my interest in insuring adherence to the clearance
                            and coordination procedures established by the President. In the future,
                            if there is doubt as to White House interest or insufficient time for
                            following formal procedures, I would welcome a phone call on outgoing
                            cables dealing with policy issues.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Henry A. Kissinger</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>