<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-12-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-12-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="14" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d14">
                        <head>14. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>At the first meeting of the National Security Council, held on January
                            21, 1969, the President directed that regular attendance at <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meetings be limited to statutory
                            members, the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, the Under Secretary
                            of State, and, on an ad hoc basis, the Secretary of the Treasury (see
                                <ref target="#d15">Document 15</ref>). In a February 3 letter to
                            Nixon, the U.S. Advisory Commission on Information requested that U.S.
                            Information Agency Director <persName corresp="#p_SFJJ1">Frank
                                Shakespeare</persName> be included on a regular basis at <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meetings. (National Archives, Nixon
                            Presidential Materials, White House Central Files, Subject Files, FG
                            6–6) In his February 23 reply, Nixon stated that <persName corresp="#p_SFJJ1">Shakespeare</persName> would be invited to “all
                            meetings in which matters of particular concern to <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss> are under discussion” but that to use
                            the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> forum effectively he must limit
                            regular attendance to statutory members. (Ibid.)</p>
                        <p>In a telephone conversation between <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and Attorney General <persName corresp="#p_MJN1">John Mitchell</persName>, January 23 at 2:35
                            p.m.:</p>
                        <p>“Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJN1">Mitchell</persName> noted his exclusion
                            from <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meetings, ‘which was wonderful
                            for him.’ <gloss target="#t_HAK1">HAK</gloss> said it is the President’s
                            intention to bring <pb facs="0068" n="37" xml:id="pg_37"/> him in
                            gradually, and wants him to be fully briefed, but reason he hasn’t been
                            at the meetings up to now is that the Pres wants to exclude some of the
                            Cabinet members who are not statutory members, and in order to have a
                            basis to do that, he has confined the list to statutory members. <gloss target="#t_HAK1">HAK</gloss> will make sure Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJN1">Mitchell</persName> is kept informed—for example,
                            there is some by-play in Paris which doesn’t appear in reports and when
                            it jells he will be in touch.” (Library of Congress, Manuscript
                            Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box
                            359, Telephone Conversations, Chronological File)</p>
                        <p>On April 28, however, <persName corresp="#p_HHR1">H.R.
                                Haldeman</persName> notified <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry
                                Kissinger</persName> that the President had directed that henceforth
                            Attorney General <persName corresp="#p_MJN1">John Mitchell</persName> be
                            automatically included in all Council meetings. (National Archives,
                            Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files,
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Institutional Files (H-Files),
                            Box H–299, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> System, National Security
                            Council Vol. II, 4/1/69–5/30/69)</p>
                        <p>Secretary of the Treasury <persName corresp="#p_KDM1">David
                                Kennedy</persName> expressed dismay over his limited participation
                            in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meetings in a January 20, 1970,
                            letter to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, and
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> admitted in
                            response that at times they may have been overzealous in restricting
                            attendance. (See <ref target="#d94">Document 94</ref> and <ref target="#d94fn2">footnote 2 thereto</ref>) A year and a half later,
                            in National Security Decision Memorandum 123, July 27, 1971, the
                            President directed that the Secretary of the Treasury (<persName corresp="#p_CJBJ1">John Connally</persName>, who had replaced
                                <persName>Kennedy</persName> in February 1971) as well as the
                            Attorney General participate in all regular <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meetings. Upon Attorney General <persName corresp="#p_MJN1">Mitchell</persName>’s resignation in February
                            1972, however, it was determined that his successor, <persName corresp="#p_KRG1">Richard Kleindienst</persName>, would be not be
                            invited to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meetings. (Memorandum
                            from <persName corresp="#p_DJW1">Davis</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName>, March 2, 1972; National
                            Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            Institutional Files (H-Files), Box H–299, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> System, National Security Council Vol. I,
                            1/20/69–3/31/69) On the other hand, it was decided to invite <persName corresp="#p_CJBJ1">Connally</persName>’s successor at Treasury,
                                <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">George Shultz</persName>, to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meetings, but <persName corresp="#p_CJBJ1">Connally</persName>’s proposal in May 1972, on
                            the eve of his departure, that the Secretary of the Treasury be made a
                            statutory <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> member was ignored.
                            (Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_DJW1">Davis</persName> to
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, June 4, 1972;
                            ibid., Vol. III, 6/1/69–12/31/69)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>