<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>187. Memorandum From Director of Central Intelligence Helms to Secretary of
                    Defense to Secretary of Defense Laird and the Deputy Secretary of Defense ( and
                    the Deputy Secretary of Defense (Packard))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d187</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">187</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-02-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-02-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="reccKWZw7wcZPbjV8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001281"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconnaissance</term>
                    <term ref="rec0tfPbYHg7imwab" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067175"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Intelligence community</term>
                    <term ref="recKJAN9jjd9CGYNt" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00001972"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">DCI</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-02-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-02-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="187"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d187">
                <head>187. Memorandum From Director of Central Intelligence <persName
                        corresp="#p_HRM1" type="from">Helms</persName> to Secretary of Defense
                        <persName corresp="#p_LMR2" type="to">Laird</persName> and the Deputy
                    Secretary of Defense (<persName corresp="#p_PDM1" type="to"
                        >Packard</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d187fn1">Source:
                        Central Intelligence Agency, Executive Registry Files, Job 80–R01284A, Box
                        14, Folder 8, <gloss target="#t_DCI1">DCI</gloss> Chron 1969. Top Secret;
                        Handle via Byeman Comint Channels.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1969-02-27">February 27, 1969</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Major Intelligence Problems, Particularly in the <gloss
                            target="#t_SIGINT1">SIGINT</gloss> Field</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>With further reference to my memorandum of 18 February,<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d187fn2">Not found.</note> I am enclosing a paper which outlines
                        my views on the Government’s <gloss target="#t_SIGINT1">SIGINT</gloss>
                        activities.</item>
                    <pb facs="0409" n="378" xml:id="pg_378"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>In July 1967 the President directed that a special review of these
                        activities be conducted by the Director of Central Intelligence. The purpose
                        of the review was to assess the efficiency of these operations and their
                        responsiveness to national needs at minimum necessary cost. To assist me I
                        appointed a special study group chaired by Mr. Frederick M. Eaton, which
                        submitted its report in August 1968. Since then I have received comments on
                        the report from various elements of the Department of Defense as well as
                        from the Director of the Bureau of the Budget. A copy of the Eaton report is
                            attached.<note n="3" xml:id="d187fn3">Not attached. Documentation on the
                            Special Study Group (known as the Eaton Group) is in the Central
                            Intelligence Agency, Executive Registry Files, Job 80–R01580R, Sigint
                            Study Group. Copies of the report are ibid., Job 86–B00269R, Box 8,
                            Folder 39, Eaton Report—16 August 1968; and ibid., Box 14, Folder 125,
                            The Eaton Report, Comint and Elint Program, 16 Aug 68.</note> The other
                        members of the study group were Mr. Livingston Merchant, General Lauris
                        Norstad, and Mr. Eugene Fubini.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The annexed memorandum sets forth in rather general terms some of the
                        conclusions which I have reached after considering the Eaton recommendations
                        and the various comments on them. I propose ultimately to transmit my
                        recommendations concerning possible measures to improve the organization and
                        administration of the <gloss target="#t_SIGINT1">SIGINT</gloss> effort to
                        the President through you. Before putting such recommendations in final
                        form, however, I would like to discuss with you personally the broad
                        outlines of the main problem as I see them. In anticipation of such a
                        discussion, the attached paper provides a summary of my views. When you have
                        had a chance to review it, I should appreciate an opportunity to talk to you
                        about specific actions that may be taken.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Richard Helms</persName>
                        </hi>
                        <note n="4" xml:id="d187fn4">Printed from a copy that indicates <persName
                                corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> signed the original.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Attachment</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                                ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates"
                                calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1969-02-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                                notBefore="1969-02-18T00:00:00-05:00">undated</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="strong">Memorandum From Director of Central Intelligence <persName
                                corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">Conclusions Concerning Possible Improvements in the
                        Organization and Administration of U.S. <gloss target="#t_SIGINT1"
                            >SIGINT</gloss> Programs</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>There is a need to bring together review of the three major
                            intelligence programs of the Department of Defense (the Consolidated <pb
                                facs="0410" n="379" xml:id="pg_379"/> Cryptologic Program, the
                            Consolidated Intelligence Program and the National Reconnaissance
                            Program). As you know, these account together for something on the order
                            of 85% of the total resources devoted to national intelligence. In the
                            past these programs have been considered by separate reviewing
                            authorities, which has complicated the problem of identifying gaps and
                            redundancies in the intelligence effort as a whole. Better arrangements
                            are needed for identifying and evaluating all the resources and
                            activities committed to the coverage of particular targets and problems,
                            particularly where high cost systems are involved. It is also important
                            that all of the Defense Department’s intelligence programs at the
                            national level should be kept under more or less continuous review and
                            that this be done with full recognition of the relationship of each to
                            the others and to the total efforts of the community. In this way it
                            should be possible to assess more clearly the intelligence impact of
                            resource decisions. It was largely to facilitate the process of
                            continuing review of the totality of the Defense Department intelligence
                            effort that I recommended that you appoint a senior official to act as a
                            Special Assistant to the Deputy Secretary for intelligence resource
                            matters.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Resources must be more closely related to intelligence needs than they
                            now are. I believe that we have made considerable progress in trying to
                            achieve this. Among the more important steps is the establishment of the
                            National Intelligence Resources Board (<gloss target="#t_NIRB1"
                                >NIRB</gloss>), consisting of top representatives of the principal
                            intelligence producers, i.e., <gloss target="#t_DIA1">DIA</gloss>, State
                            and <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>, chaired by the Deputy Director
                            of Central Intelligence. The purpose of this Board is to provide me with
                            informed advice concerning the real need for particular systems or
                            activities when the information which they produce, or are likely to
                            produce, is balanced against their cost. We have established a Target
                            Oriented Display (TOD) to assist the <gloss target="#t_NIRB1"
                                >NIRB</gloss> in identifying and assessing the totality of resources
                            applied to particular national intelligence needs. In this connection,
                            we will need your help in persuading certain elements of the
                            intelligence community to conduct their business so that they can be
                            adequately responsive to calls for information on the resources which
                            they deploy, including cost data.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>We are also endeavoring to devise more effective means of arriving at
                            an accurate assessment of the true value of the intelligence which is
                            eventually produced as a result of the operation of particular
                            resources. This is a most complex problem and we have been trying to
                            attack it in several different ways, including the use of advanced
                            methods of systems analysis.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The mechanism of the U.S. Intelligence Board (<gloss target="#t_USIB1"
                                >USIB</gloss>) and its functional committees has been useful in
                            developing intelligence requirements in the first instance. A good deal
                            of progress has been made <pb facs="0411" n="380" xml:id="pg_380"/> in
                            developing procedures to provide a continuing assessment and refinement
                            of these requirements with the objective of keeping the flow of raw
                            intelligence information within reasonable and effective bounds. This
                            problem has been exacerbated by the steadily increasing technical
                            effectiveness of collection systems. Here we have encountered a certain
                            amount of natural reluctance to make hard selective decisions concerning
                            what data is really essential or at least important. I suggest that we
                            will all have to work together to achieve a proper balance between the
                            “nice to know” and the “need to know.”</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Much thought has been given to the desirability of attempting to
                            formulate a long term national intelligence plan to determine the
                            objectives, targets and priorities of the intelligence effort. A plan,
                            in the conventional sense of the word, is probably too elaborate and
                            rigid a format for the provision of practical guidance for intelligence
                            activity. It is hard to conceive of a planning document which would be
                            very helpful in projecting the intricate and multitudinous activities
                            contemplated for American intelligence activity over an appreciable
                            period of time. An alternative would be a series of program memoranda
                            related to the intelligence effort against the more important areas.
                            Such memoranda could define the objectives of the effort in the area,
                            describe the resources committed and recommend the maintenance of a
                            particular level of effort and the allocation of particular resources to
                            this effort. The recommendations of the memoranda, insofar as they
                            relate to resources, would be based, in part at least, on the results of
                            systems evaluations completed during the course of a program year.
                            Preparation of such program memoranda would be the joint responsibility
                            of the <gloss target="#t_DCI1">DCI</gloss>’s staff and designated
                            elements of the Defense Department.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>One of the most difficult problems in the <gloss target="#t_SIGINT1"
                                    >SIGINT</gloss> field is to achieve a proper allocation of
                                resources as between those devoted to national requirements and
                                those which are necessary to support military units, particularly in
                                the case of ELINT. Under <gloss target="#t_NSCID1">NSCID</gloss>
                                    6,<note n="5" xml:id="d187fn5">Reference is to <gloss
                                        target="#t_NSCID1">NSCID</gloss> 6, Communications
                                    Intelligence and Electronic Intelligence, September 15, 1958,
                                    and January 18, 1961; neither found.</note> NSA is assigned the
                                mission to provide “an effective unified organization and control of
                                the COMINT and ELINT intercept and processing activities of the
                                U.S.” This would appear to be ample authority for NSA but in
                                practice this centralized control has been eroded. At the heart of
                                the problem is the fact that almost all the collection resources of
                                the <gloss target="#t_CCP1">CCP</gloss> are operated by one of the
                                three service cryptologic agencies (<gloss target="#t_SCA1"
                                    >SCA</gloss>’s). The <gloss target="#t_SCA1">SCA</gloss>’s are
                                oriented in large measure to the needs of their respective parent
                                services. Thus, while NSA nominally has tasking authority over all
                                COMINT and ELINT collection facilities, it has perforce delegated
                                    <pb facs="0412" n="381" xml:id="pg_381"/> control of a
                                substantial portion of these facilities to the <gloss
                                    target="#t_SCA1">SCA</gloss>’s so they might fulfill the
                                intelligence needs placed upon them by their parent services.
                                Particularly in the area of ELINT collection, resources programmed
                                against national requirements are at times diverted to meet the
                                tactical needs of local military commanders without the consent of
                                the Director, NSA. The result has been that a portion of the
                                resources of the <gloss target="#t_CCP1">CCP</gloss> which are
                                allocated and justified on the basis of national intelligence needs
                                are subsequently tasked to meet other requirements.</p>
                            <p>There are some resources which are now clearly and unequivocally
                                being tasked for exclusively tactical needs. Such resources should
                                be identified by careful study, then removed from the <gloss
                                    target="#t_CCP1">CCP</gloss> and assigned to the sole
                                jurisdiction of the military commands they are serving, as elements
                                essential to military operations and readiness. Criteria should be
                                not the nature of the equipment but the purpose it serves. They
                                should be funded through normal service channels rather than under
                                one of the national intelligence programs. By undertaking such
                                action, I believe that some of the tugging and hauling for resources
                                that now goes on between NSA and the military services can be
                                eliminated.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>The authority of the Director, NSA over all resources, other than
                            those transferred to the military services or commands on the grounds
                            that they serve essentially tactical purposes, should be confirmed and
                            strengthened.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>It would be desirable to do away with the present subordination of the
                            Director of NSA to <gloss target="#t_DDRE1">DDR&amp;E</gloss>, and to
                            have him report directly to the Deputy Secretary, recognizing that
                            additional staff support in the form of the senior assistant proposed
                            will be necessary. The establishment of a cryptologic career within the
                            services should be encouraged and supported. Steps toward this objective
                            have already been taken but further progress is possible.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>The capability of the Director, NSA for direction and guidance of the
                            cryptologic community should be strengthened by the assignment of senior
                            officials with experience and competence in planning and
                            programming.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>Existing arrangements between the National Reconnaissance Office
                                    (<gloss target="#t_NRO1">NRO</gloss>) and the rest of the
                                intelligence community, including NSA, appear to me generally
                                satisfactory. The <gloss target="#t_NRO1">NRO</gloss> agreement was
                                negotiated with considerable difficulty with a view to accommodating
                                conflicting interests. It has provided an increasingly effective
                                mechanism through which the potentialities and capabilities of
                                various agencies of the Government for overhead reconnaissance have
                                been exploited. Design, development and operational control of
                                overhead sensors has proceeded under the overall direction and
                                coordination of the Director, <gloss target="#t_NRO1">NRO</gloss>.
                                Guidance to this effort is established through the appropriate
                                    <gloss target="#t_USIB1">USIB</gloss> mechanisms which determine
                                the number, frequency <pb facs="0413" n="382" xml:id="pg_382"/> and
                                objectives of missions required from particular sensors, e.g., the
                                resolution of photography for certain purposes, frequencies, band
                                widths and general characteristics of signals to be intercepted, is
                                determined as a result of a dialogue between the substantive
                                elements of the community (acting through <gloss target="#t_USIB1"
                                    >USIB</gloss>) and the appropriate echelons of the <gloss
                                    target="#t_NRO1">NRO</gloss>. [<hi rend="italic">less than 1
                                    line of source text not declassified</hi>] is adequately
                                represented in <gloss target="#t_USIB1">USIB</gloss> and maintains
                                effective working relationships, at the technical level, with the
                                    <gloss target="#t_NRO1">NRO</gloss>.</p>
                            <p>The processing facilities of NSA play an essential part in the
                                exploitation of data collected from <gloss target="#t_SIGINT1"
                                    >SIGINT</gloss> satellite operations just as the National
                                Photographic Interpretation Center (<gloss target="#t_NPIC1"
                                    >NPIC</gloss>) plays an essential part in the exploitation of
                                overhead photography. Action to ensure that facilities for
                                processing the take from overhead reconnaissance activities are
                                adequate can be taken through the appropriate <gloss
                                    target="#t_USIB1">USIB</gloss> mechanisms and in any event
                                should be part of the program review responsibilities of the
                                managers of the intelligence programs. The measures recommended
                                above to establish more centralized supervision over the
                                intelligence activities of the Defense Department would help to
                                ensure that appropriate action is taken to relate all processing
                                facilities to all collection activities.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>I believe that these general conclusions can serve as the basis for
                            specific actions to improve the efficiency and effectiveness of the
                            management of all Defense Department intelligence programs, including
                            specifically <gloss target="#t_SIGINT1">SIGINT</gloss>.</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
