<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>206. Memorandum From the Consultant to the National Security Council
                    (Marshall) to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs () to the
                    President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d206</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">206</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-05-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-05-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAynYh8uzxYGQRH" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009928"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Strategic weapons</term>
                    <term ref="rec0tfPbYHg7imwab" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067175"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Intelligence community</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recKJAN9jjd9CGYNt" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00001972"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">DCI</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005651"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monitoring</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military balance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-05-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-05-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="206"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d206">
                <head>206. Memorandum From the Consultant to the National Security Council
                        (<persName corresp="#p_MAW1" type="from">Marshall</persName>) to the
                    President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d206fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Name Files, Box 825, <persName
                            corresp="#p_MAW1">Marshall</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MAW1"
                            >Andrew</persName>, Vol. I, 1969–1971. Top Secret; Sensitive. Sent for
                        action. The tabs are attached but not printed.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-05-01">May 1, 1970</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Intelligence Inputs for Major Issues: A Substantive Evaluation and
                        Proposals for Improvement</item>
                </list>
                <p>When we first talked, you indicated a concern for the quality of the intelligence
                    product you receive on major issues such as the SS–9 program, trends in Soviet
                    strategic forces, etc. During the last two months I have focused on the
                    intelligence product on the Soviet military strategic weapons and forces and the
                    question: How can you get a better product in the future?</p>
                <p>The standard products of the intelligence community do not give you and your
                    staff what you want and what you need. The <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>’s
                    are of little use to top level decision makers and/or their staffs, even though
                    that is their ostensible audience. Their real service is that of supplying an
                    agreed intelligence input to the work of staffs several levels down in the
                    bureaucracy, and as a starting point for the NIPP (now the DIPP, Defense
                    Intelligence Projections for Planning).</p>
                <p>Other products vary in usefulness. The new President’s Quarterly Report on Soviet
                    Strategic Forces is factual, concise, and well presented. Some of the Caesar
                        series<note n="2" xml:id="d206fn2">In the margin <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> wrote: “What’s the Caesar series?”</note> provide
                    valuable background on Soviet leaders, the structure and functioning of the
                    upper level bureaucracy. But most of the product, when it goes beyond the
                    reporting of factual information, or immediate inferences from it, is not very
                    impressive.</p>
                <p>The analysis of hard data and factual reporting on Soviet forces is good; indeed,
                    we now know a great deal more about today’s Soviet military posture and <gloss
                        target="#t_RD1">R&amp;D</gloss> programs than we knew about the 1960 Soviet
                    force posture and programs in 1960. Intelligence on Soviet forces and programs
                    is better today than in the past; but it can still be improved. Intelligence
                    reporting and analysis can and should do a better job of assisting top level
                    decision makers.</p>
                <p>The weakest point I find is in the judgments of intelligence analysts and
                    estimators about plausible or likely Soviet behavior, in particular their
                    understanding of the decision processes that influence <pb facs="0465" n="434"
                        xml:id="pg_434"/> Soviet military posture. The explicit or implicit
                    assumptions and hypotheses concerning the roots of Soviet behavior seem much too
                    simplified, and rely too frequently upon a model of the Soviet government as a
                    single unified actor pursuing an easily stated strategy.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d206fn3">Nixon drew parallel lines in the margin next to this
                        paragraph.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Presumably the governmental decision-making process there is just as complex as
                    ours, involves the interaction of contending bureaucratic elements, and can
                    attain only a limited measure of rationality. None of this shows through in the
                    standard intelligence product, except in those paragraphs designed to protect
                    against future developments falsifying the estimate or judgment. These include
                    sentences listing the factors that may also influence future Soviet behavior:
                    economic difficulties, bureaucratic conflicts, bloc political problems, etc. A
                    form of defensive writing in the spirit of defense driving.</p>
                <p>The fact that intelligence analysts’ judgments about likely Soviet behavior do
                    not seem that much better than those of less involved persons is disappointing.
                    In principle, they should be the real experts, and in some ways they are. But I
                    have long felt that intelligence analysts have not devoted enough effort to
                    studying past Soviet behavior with regard to military posture formation; have
                    not sufficiently focused upon understanding the structure and objectives of the
                    various organizations involved in the relevant decision-making processes.</p>
                <p>In my view, if we are to understand past Soviet force posture decisions, or to
                    improve our forecasts of alternative future force postures, we have to entertain
                    more complicated hypotheses about the sources of Soviet behavior regarding
                    military force posture formation.</p>
                <p>Substantially improving the intellectual quality of the analysis of Soviet
                    behavior is a longer term goal. I hope some effort can be made to push forward
                    in this area. But let me return to the more immediate problem of getting you a
                    better product.<note n="4" xml:id="d206fn4">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> wrote an illegible word in
                        the margin next to this and the previous sentence.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">What Do You Really Need?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is hard for me to answer that question completely. Only you, <persName
                        corresp="#p_LLEJ1">Larry Lynn</persName>, and others immediately concerned
                    with specific decisions and problem areas can do it. However, I would suggest
                    that on a few issues each year <list>
                        <item>—where a great deal is at stake,</item>
                        <item>—where there are contending views on which option to choose,</item>
                        <item>—where major uncertainties almost certainly exist as to the future
                            evolution of Soviet strategic forces,</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>you need a different sort of intelligence product than you now get.</p>
                <pb facs="0466" n="435" xml:id="pg_435"/>
                <p>For at least these few problems you need in-depth intelligence studies that
                    surface the uncertainties, display and argue alternative explanatory hypotheses
                    regarding past Soviet behavior and future projections. These studies should give
                    you <list>
                        <item>—as much separation of facts and judgments as is possible,</item>
                        <item>—where major judgments are made, argument as to the basis of the
                            judgment.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>On these really important issues you should dig into the intelligence analysis as
                    deeply as you can before making decisions. You have to understand what is behind
                    it before you can accept it. The only alternative is boxscoring of experts. In
                    general that is not a feasible procedure.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">What Can Be Done?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>A number of things can be done to get you better, more useful products. I believe
                    you ought to use the following strategy: <list>
                        <item>—Improved communication of your and your staff’s needs. <hi
                                rend="italic">You are not getting through loudly and clearly
                                now</hi>.<note n="5" xml:id="d206fn5">In the margin next to this
                                sentence <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> wrote: “On
                                what issues.”</note> Clear and persistent statement of needs should
                            lead to an improved product. Put the burden on <persName
                                corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> and the community to find the
                            ways to satisfy you.</item>
                        <item>—Initiate discussion with <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>
                            aiming at a major review of the intelligence community’s support of
                            yourself, the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> decision-making
                            process.</item>
                        <item>—Develop new procedures to get non-standard products now for a few
                            selected problems of highest importance to you.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Specifics of the strategy are covered below. Note that it is designed to get a
                    better product for you, not to improve the structure and functioning of the
                    intelligence community in the short run. It attempts to bypass, for the moment,
                    the probable sources of the problem. You might prefer a more intrusive strategy
                    that tries to influence the structure and functioning of the community at an
                    early date. If so, see Tab A.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Better Communication of Your Needs</hi>
                </p>
                <p>One general observation to begin with: Causes of product deficiencies lie on both
                    sides of the producer-consumer interface. Top level needs have not been
                    expressed clearly or persistently enough. There is little feedback or criticism
                    of the intelligence product.</p>
                <p>The community misperceives some of the needs of top level people, and a doctrine
                    that limits their response. Moreover, the intelligence community does nothing
                    that could be called research on customer needs. The organization of the
                    interface between the two groups does not facilitate communication of customer
                    needs, and discussion of how to match needs and producer capabilities.</p>
                <pb facs="0467" n="436" xml:id="pg_436"/>
                <p>I recommend the following: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Preparation of a statement to <persName corresp="#p_HRM1"
                                >Helms</persName> expressing your needs (see Tab B for some things
                            it should say), coordinated with guidance on the format and content of
                            the Soviet Military <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>’s. (See memo on
                            that matter from <persName corresp="#p_LLEJ1">Larry Lynn</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_MAW1">A. W. Marshall</persName>.)<note n="6"
                                xml:id="d206fn6">Not found.</note> Probably it would cover some of
                            the same ground, but discuss alternative ways of getting a more useful
                            product as well. <hi rend="italic">Repetition will not hurt. Do not
                                underestimate the communication problem</hi>. Follow up with
                            detailed discussion with <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>
                            and others on how to get the new procedures going.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Use at least one person on your, or the <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                >NSC</gloss>, staff full time as a communication link, mainly to
                                <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_LTK1">Tom
                                Latimer</persName> is coming on board. Consider setting some part of
                            his time aside for this function. Another person might be added to the
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff solely to perform this
                            communication function. I can suggest some names if you are interested.
                            Principle characteristics should be a familiarity with all community
                            organizations, and a personal disposition to consider intelligence as a
                            service to consumers, not an activity with its own goals.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The communication function will be time-consuming, if done right. It is not the
                    standard sort of liaison function that is needed. <hi rend="italic">Frequent
                        trips to <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>, and elsewhere, and extended
                        meetings with people at all levels in the community will be required to keep
                        their view of your needs correctly focused</hi>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> as <gloss target="#t_DCI1"
                            >DCI</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> are the key
                        communication targets. <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> has the best
                        current capability to respond; there is just no where else to go</hi>. But
                    you should communicate your needs also to <gloss target="#t_DIA1">DIA</gloss>
                    (Defense) and <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss> (State).</p>
                <p>Again I stress the difficulty of the communication problem. The procedures to
                    obtain non-standard products, discussed in the section after the next one, are
                    designed to assist the communication problem; indeed, these procedures should be
                    thought of as part of the communication effort.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Steps to Initiate a Major Review of Intelligence Support of
                        the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Decision Process</hi>
                </p>
                <p>While short-run measures are taken to obtain more useful products, a more basic
                    look can be taken at intelligence community organization and functioning in
                    support of you and the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> decision process. The
                    timing for such a review may be good. For example: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>The Office of National Estimates (<gloss target="#t_ONE1"
                                >ONE</gloss>) is going through a transition period. It is at the end
                                of an era. <persName corresp="#p_SAE1">Abbott Smith</persName>, the
                                head of <gloss target="#t_ONE1">ONE</gloss>, will retire as soon as
                                a successor can be picked. <persName corresp="#p_HRM1"
                                    >Helms</persName> and others lean <pb facs="0468" n="437"
                                    xml:id="pg_437"/> toward bringing in someone from the outside;
                                this is an opportunity to add some new blood and leadership. But
                                equally at stake are: What sort of organization should <gloss
                                    target="#t_ONE1">ONE</gloss> be? What should its role be? How
                                should the <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> process operate?</p>
                            <p>You have a major stake in the choice of the successor and the <gloss
                                    target="#t_DCI1">DCI</gloss> conception of what sort of an
                                organization <gloss target="#t_ONE1">ONE</gloss> is to be, what sort
                                of a role <gloss target="#t_ONE1">ONE</gloss> is to have in the
                                future. (See Tab C.)</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The Blue-Ribbon Panel will report on Department of Defense
                            organization and management on 30 June 1970. It will focus in part on
                            the need to change Defense intelligence organization and management. You
                            have a major stake in what is decided, in particular as regards the
                            future development of <gloss target="#t_DIA1">DIA</gloss>. (See Tab
                            D.)</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>I think you will want to rebuild the national intelligence process. At present it
                    is foundering because of the decline in the ONE/BNE role and status, reflected
                    in the virtual <gloss target="#t_DDI1">DDI</gloss> monopoly of the intelligence
                    role in the <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> process, and other causes. One
                    view of what to do about the national process is contained in Tab A. But what is
                    really needed is a full-scale review of the current situation and
                    recommendations for change. The review or study group should include
                    representatives of the intelligence community, of <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> members, and of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff.
                    It is very important that consumer representatives as well as intelligence
                    representatives be involved in the review.</p>
                <p>In the nature of things, the national process, if it involves inputs from several
                    components of the intelligence community, is an adversary process. Special
                    attention will have to be paid to designing a process that works well. More
                    attention than in the past must be given to structuring the incentive systems in
                    the adversary process.</p>
                <p>I suggest you begin discussion with <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>
                    about the design and procedures for a review of the national intelligence
                    process. The aims of the review would be an assessment of its current operation
                    in support of your office, and the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> decision
                    process; and recommendations for future redesign of the national intelligence
                    process.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">New Procedures to Get Non-Standard Products</hi>
                </p>
                <p>You need not only to communicate your needs, and hope for a good response, but to
                    develop procedures to get what you want now.</p>
                <p>I recommend that you: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Limit efforts to improve the <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>’s.
                            Neither the process that produces them nor the performance of ONE/BNE
                            can be changed in the short run. The solution to the <gloss
                                target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> problem is part of the review
                            effort.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>Push for procedures to produce in-depth intelligence studies on a
                                small number of selected intelligence problems each year. Selection
                                    <pb facs="0469" n="438" xml:id="pg_438"/> of problem areas to be
                                yours, perhaps in some cases in conjunction with the Secretaries of
                                State and Defense.<note n="7" xml:id="d206fn7">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> put a checkmark
                                    in the margin next to this paragraph.</note> (See Tab B.)</p>
                            <p>The essential features of these procedures should be: <list>
                                    <item>—Involvement of top level decision makers and/or their
                                        staffs in the selection of study areas, drafting of terms of
                                        reference and the goals of the study.</item>
                                    <item>—Provisions for monitoring of the study as it proceeds and
                                        continued guidance and feedback from upper level people to
                                        all levels in the intelligence community.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Joint decision of upper level representatives and intelligence
                                working level people concerning modification of study efforts to
                                accommodate data and analysis problems and in-course redirection of
                                study.</p>
                            <p>It will be very important that it not seem that the White House is
                                writing its own intelligence estimates. The objective should clearly
                                be to obtain from the intelligence community relevant facts,
                                judgments, etc.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>Continue a study of the SS–9 system initiated 1 April 1970 (see Tab
                                E). It is an attempt to produce a non-standard product; one you or
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LLEJ1">Larry Lynn</persName> might give a
                                good grade. Projected completion is end September. It will take only
                                a day or two per month to follow it and hopefully keep it going in
                                the right direction. <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> has started
                                a good effort in this study. It should be a good test of their
                                current capabilities to explore some more complex, organizational
                                behavior hypotheses in addition to the standard ones.</p>
                            <p>I plan to continue to manage this effort as I visit Washington
                                periodically in the course of other work.<note n="8"
                                    xml:id="d206fn8">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> initialed the
                                    “Approve” option.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Constant attention will have to be given to see that the procedures
                                that are developed continue to function. The intelligence
                                bureaucracy at all levels may resist these methods of operation. No
                                fixed set of procedures may work all of the time. The recent study
                                of the Israeli-Arab military balance, while not a typical
                                intelligence study, may be a good model from which to draw some
                                lessons.</p>
                            <p>In the case of that study, the keys to success appear to have been: <list>
                                    <item>—Study confined to fact finding, technical study, policy
                                        implications played down;</item>
                                    <item>—Full-time involvement of a <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                            >NSC</gloss> staff representative (in this case a
                                        consultant);</item>
                                    <item>—Lots of feedback of specific questions as study
                                        progressed;</item>
                                    <item>—No strong bureaucratic stance of State or <gloss
                                            target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss>/Military Services.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0470" n="439" xml:id="pg_439"/>
                <p>By contrast, a 1968 attempt to evaluate the Israeli-Arab military balance
                    produced only badly split views expressing policy preferences.</p>
                <p>In any case, almost everyone’s experience is that the most rewarding and fruitful
                    way of working with the intelligence community is one in which top level people
                    deal more directly with the working level people than is usual. Both the people
                    and the intelligence input at the bottom are better than the standard
                    product.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Postscript</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Many changes and improvements in intelligence community performance I would like
                    to see are not easily effected by you. For example, as mentioned earlier I
                    believe that major improvement in the analysis of Soviet decision-making
                    processes is possible. But progress is slow and difficult to stimulate from the
                    outside on this and many other areas of possible improvement. Nonetheless, I
                    have appended at Tab F a short sketch of a number of areas that I feel the
                    community should be doing more about. They mainly concern [what the] <gloss
                        target="#t_RD1">R&amp;D</gloss> community could do on the intelligence
                    analysis, estimating, and projection processes. Two substantive studies are also
                    briefly described.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
