<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>231. Memorandum From the Director of the Program Analysis Staff, National
                    Security Council (Smith) to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs () to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d231</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">231</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-05-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKKNyP9NHSwF6fs" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general">Strategic
                        defenses</term>
                    <term ref="recdxnUU66ZyvZBYH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Intelligence estimate</term>
                    <term ref="rec0tfPbYHg7imwab" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067175"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Intelligence community</term>
                    <term ref="recr08QgEMEm1Bk04" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-05-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="231"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d231">
                <head>231. Memorandum From the Director of the Program Analysis Staff, National
                    Security Council (<persName corresp="#p_SKW1" type="from">Smith</persName>) to
                    the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d231fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials,
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Subject Files, Box 360,
                        National Intelligence Estimates. Top Secret; Ruff; Zarff; Umbra; Restricted
                        Data. Sent for action. At the top of page 1 is written “Outside system” and,
                        in <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s hand, “Do note from me
                        to <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>.” A memorandum to <persName
                            corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> was signed by <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> on June 9.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1971-05-14">May 14, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 11–3–71, “Soviet Strategic
                        Defenses”</item>
                </list>
                <p>Attached are:<note n="2" xml:id="d231fn2">None of the attachments are
                        printed.</note>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>A memorandum from you to the President (Tab A) summarizing the
                            national intelligence estimate on Soviet strategic defense forces. Your
                            memorandum to the President also notes that, like the earlier <gloss
                                target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 11–8–70 on “Soviet Forces for
                            Intercontinental Attack,” this <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> is a
                            considerable improvement over last year’s effort, though additional work
                            still needs to be done.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>A detailed analytical summary (Tab B), for your reference, of the
                            major points made in the <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>, with
                            comments on the adequacy of the analysis and on the questions the <gloss
                                target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> still fails to consider.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>A copy of <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 11–3 (Tab C).</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>A copy of my earlier memo to you and your memo to the President on
                                <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 11–8 (Tab D). The memo to you
                            provides some background on the events leading to the changes this year
                            (pages 3–7) and some comments on the difficulties we must overcome in
                            order to get an even better product (pages 8–10).</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Evaluating the <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>
                        11–3–70</hi>
                </p>
                <p>As I indicated in your memorandum to the President, this <gloss target="#t_NIE1"
                        >NIE</gloss>, like <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 11–8, is a major
                    improvement over last year’s efforts. <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Richard
                        Helms</persName> recognized last year’s weaknesses and solicited comments
                    from intelligence consumers. After getting the President’s reaction, you
                    provided comments and had your staff work closely with the intelligence
                    community. The results, as reflected by these two <gloss target="#t_NIE1"
                        >NIE</gloss>s, are encouraging: <list>
                        <item>—There is some frank, clear discussion of the characteristics and
                            purposes of Soviet forces.</item>
                        <pb facs="0549" n="518" xml:id="pg_518"/>
                        <item>—The discussion is backed by considerable detail which is presented in
                            usually very clear ways (e.g., graphics) and which even spills over into
                            a number of annexes.</item>
                        <item>—A wide range of sources is often used to advance the analysis.</item>
                        <item>—One of the best improvements is the development of a wide range of
                            alternative force models based on assumed differences in Soviet
                            objectives, the pace of Soviet technological developments, and the
                            resources which the Soviets are willing to apply. This approach forces
                            everyone to remember that estimates rely heavily on underlying
                            assumptions. However, to avoid the real danger that any point along the
                            wide spectrum would be undifferentiated from any other point, the <gloss
                                target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> designates certain assumptions and
                            their accompanying illustrative force structures as most likely.</item>
                        <item>—All the alternative force models are provided in considerable
                            numerical detail which is essential for an understanding of the
                            differences between the alternatives.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">I believe that <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 11–3 shows
                        even greater improvement than found in the last <gloss target="#t_NIE1"
                            >NIE</gloss> 11–8.</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <item>—It introduced and did a creditable job with a whole new section on Soviet
                            <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> capabilities.</item>
                    <item>—It was more willing to discuss the strategic implications of facts. For
                        instance, with very limited evidence at that time, it analyzed well the
                        significance of the new missile system complex at the Sary Shagan test
                        range.</item>
                    <item>—It considered in detail Soviet command and control which is so essential
                        to effective use of strategic forces, especially for the complex mission of
                        strategic defense.</item>
                </list>
                <p>More work is still required, however. The present <gloss target="#t_NIE1"
                        >NIE</gloss> suffers from two serious weaknesses: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>It fails to draw on all sources and research methods which could
                            advance the analysis. The greatest emphasis is still on observed
                            activity at test ranges, construction sites, and operational bases.
                            However, a variety of other material could be useful—e.g., Soviet
                            doctrinal and strategic writings, economic information, analysis of
                            Soviet institutions.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> often fails to estimate Soviet
                            objectives and strategies, yet such information is fundamental to
                            understanding present Soviet programs and estimating future ones. For
                            instance: <list>
                                <item>—How sophisticated is Soviet strategic thinking? How do
                                    various individuals and groups define “parity” and
                                    “sufficiency?”</item>
                                <item>—What are the likely Soviet war plans? What are the Soviet
                                    views as to the possibility and outcomes of limited strategic
                                    war?</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0550" n="519" xml:id="pg_519"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Obtaining Further Improvements</hi>
                </p>
                <p>While I noted in the memo on <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 11–8 that
                    getting further improvements would not be easy, we are mounting an ambitious
                    campaign.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Of course, the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_OMB1"
                            >OMB</gloss> work on reorganizing the intelligence community has as one
                        of its objectives improving the intelligence product for consumers.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The earlier letter from the President to <persName corresp="#p_HRM1"
                            >Richard Helms</persName> (Tab B of memo to the President)<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d231fn3">
                            <ref target="#d227">Document 227</ref>.</note> congratulating <persName
                            corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> and the intelligence community for
                        their work on <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 11–8–70 has provided some
                        positive feedback which should encourage them. Moreover, it identified the
                        particular strengths of the <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> from your
                        viewpoint.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>As you directed on my memo regarding <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>
                        11–8, I will arrange a meeting in mid- to late May between <persName
                            corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> and you to discuss the new <gloss
                            target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>s. We waited until <gloss target="#t_NIE1"
                            >NIE</gloss> 11–3 was published so that you would have a larger sample
                        to discuss.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>We will continue to send for your signature directives to the intelligence
                        agencies tasking them to do specific work which we are particularly
                        interested in. Already: <list>
                            <item>—You have asked <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> (Tab E) to
                                restart its in-depth study on the SS–9 focusing on Soviet
                                decision-making processes. (Andy Marshall is now working with <gloss
                                    target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> at the staff level.)</item>
                            <item>—Your earlier memo (see Tab F) to <persName corresp="#p_HRM1"
                                    >Helms</persName> in response to the <gloss target="#t_CIA1"
                                    >CIA</gloss> study on the Soviet perception of the U.S. threat
                                has resulted in an inadequate, but good-faith, answer from them. My
                                staff is now working with <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> to
                                improve their work further.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
