<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-02-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-02-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="24" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d24">
                        <head>24. Memorandum From the President’s Military Assistant (<persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1" type="from">Haig</persName>) to the President’s
                            Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d24fn1">Source: Ford Library, National Security Adviser,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>–Scowcroft West
                                Wing Office Files, 1969–77, Box 40, Administrative File, National
                                Security Council Organization (2), 2/7/69–2/11/69. No classification
                                marking.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1969-02-11">February 11, 1969</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Organization of National Security Council Staff and White House
                                Office of the</item>
                            <item>Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>In coordination with Mr. Eagleburger, I have completed an analysis of the
                            organizational structure of the National Security Council staff and of
                            your White House office and am submitting herewith our recommendations
                            for the reorganization of both.</p>
                        <p>The plan provides recommendations in three broad areas: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>Section I—The organization of your White House office.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>Section II—The organization of the National Security Staff
                                    Secretariat and,</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>Section III—The organization of the National Security Council
                                    Staff.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0085" n="54" xml:id="pg_54"/>
                        <p>Within each of these three areas, functional responsibilities are
                            delineated and the interface between all three are outlined.</p>
                        <p>Section I—Organization of the Office of the Assistant to the President
                            for National Security Affairs</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Executive Assistant</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Duties</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Executive Assistant (Larry Eagleburger) would continue to provide
                            full range of personal staff assistance to you. He would maintain
                            complete cognizance of your daily activities and serve as your focal
                            point for the transmission of instructions to and from the Office of the
                            President through the designated Assistants to the President and
                            intergovernmentally at the Special Assistant level and above, and to the
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff through the Military
                            Assistant. Normally, the Executive Assistant will delegate to the
                            Military Assistant liaison at the Special Assistant/Military Assistant
                            level with the Department of Defense, Director, <gloss target="#t_OEP1">OEP</gloss>, and Central Intelligence Agency. It is emphasized that
                            contacts with the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff would be
                            effected through the Military Assistant or in coordination with him with
                            the view toward relieving the Executive Assistant of time consuming
                            coordination with the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff so that
                            he can be totally responsive to the rapid pace of your daily activities,
                            plan ahead to preclude short deadlines in your schedule and foresee
                            potential trouble spots.</p>
                        <p>In processing the flow of business related to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>, the Executive Assistant will, after clearance of
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> substantive papers by the
                            Military Assistant, present them to you with staff assistance as
                            required and in sufficient time to insure assimilation and/or
                            modification prior to consideration by the National Security Council
                            and/or the Review Group.</p>
                        <p>The Executive Assistant would be located in the office adjacent to yours,
                            with the desk against the window so that both of you would have easy
                            access to each other through the interconnecting door, thus avoiding the
                            risks associated with the reception room conduct of business. Entry to
                            your office through the front door would be limited to scheduled
                            visitors as controlled by your private secretary in coordination with
                            you and the Executive Assistant.</p>
                        <p>Approve<note n="2" xml:id="d24fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> checked this
                                option.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Disapprove</p>
                        <p>Other</p>
                        <pb facs="0086" n="55" xml:id="pg_55"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Military Assistant</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Duties</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Military Assistant, Colonel <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName>, will maintain cognizance of the full range of
                            activities handled by the Executive Assistant and will be specifically
                            charged with coordination of and liaison with National Security Council
                            staff through the Staff Secretary or designated senior geographic
                            substantive officers and the designated senior representatives of the
                            Planning and Programming Sections as described in Section III.</p>
                        <p>The Military Assistant will insure that <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> and Review Group papers were available to you on a
                            timely basis and are consistent with substantive guidance which you have
                            provided. In effect, the Military Assistant would serve as the de facto
                            Chief of Staff for substantive <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            affairs and be the single point of contact to insure final review of
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> papers prior to presentation
                            through the Executive Assistant to you.</p>
                        <p>Military Assistant will be responsible for setting up thru the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Secretary or the substantive officer
                            concerned, staff briefings, special briefings and meetings as may be
                            required in the conduct of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            business.</p>
                        <p>Military Assistant would exercise monitorship of the Daily Intelligence
                            Briefing for the President by conducting a daily coordinating meeting
                            with the substantive geographic officers and Mr. McCafferty and an
                            assistant to be designated as outlined below.</p>
                        <p>Military Assistant will monitor 303 Committee agendas and activities
                            working in close coordination with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CFM1">Frank
                                Chapin</persName> and insure you are briefed on this material in a
                            timely manner and that follow-up action is accomplished in timely
                            fashion.</p>
                        <p>Military Assistant will be located with the Executive Assistant and be
                            the point of contact with the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff
                            and will be able, as required, to fill in for the Executive Assistant in
                            his absence.</p>
                        <p>Approve<note n="3" xml:id="d24fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> checked this
                                option.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Disapprove</p>
                        <p>Other</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Administrative Assistant</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Duties</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Administrative Assistant, Bob <persName corresp="#p_HR2">Houdek</persName>, will be the point of receipt for all material
                            forwarded to you from the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff
                            Secretariat <pb facs="0087" n="56" xml:id="pg_56"/> to be relocated in
                                <gloss target="#t_EOB1">EOB</gloss> and described in Section III. He
                            will sort this material into categories such as “Information,” “Action”
                            and “Signature.” He will also receive, for initial screening, material
                            received from the Office of the President or other members of the White
                            House staff and all out-of-house foreign affairs related material of a
                                non-<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> operational nature for your
                            or Presidential action. He will insure that it is properly logged and
                            suspensed by the existing small White House office Administrative
                            Section, dispatch it to the Staff Secretary if appropriate, or refer it
                            to the Executive/Military Assistants. The Executive/Military Assistants
                            will insure that priorities for your attention are established and that
                            the paper work is substantively responsive and coordinated prior to
                            delivery through the Executive Assistant to your desk.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HR2">Houdek</persName> would continue to
                            participate in daily press briefings and provide liaison with the office
                            of the Press Secretary.</p>
                        <p>The Administrative Assistant will continue to be located in the small
                            office to the left of the guard desk in the West Basement.</p>
                        <p>Approve<note n="4" xml:id="d24fn4">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> checked this
                                option.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Disapprove</p>
                        <p>Other</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Information and Intelligence Operations</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Mr. Art McCafferty and one qualified designated Assistant will prepare,
                            based on all source reports (including submissions by the substantive
                            staff) and the daily draft intelligence summary for the President. It
                            will be available by 1730 hours each day in time for the coordinating
                            meeting between you, the Military Assistant and appropriate members of
                            the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff. The meeting will be held
                            in the Situation Room and should include, as necessary, participation by
                            the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> briefer, Mr. [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>].</p>
                        <p>(This meeting will enable <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff
                            members to insure that items presented to the President in the morning
                            brief are accurate, have been subjected to their analysis where required
                            and contain the latest factual data available. Participation by Mr. [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] in this meeting would also
                            permit proper coordination of material contained in the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> Daily Brief with the basic memoranda
                            prepared for the President. It will also go far toward improving the
                            responsiveness of the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> Daily Brief by
                            highlighting special items of Presidential interest. Notwithstanding,
                            there will be occasions when the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>
                            representative will be excused.)</p>
                        <pb facs="0088" n="57" xml:id="pg_57"/>
                        <p>If you are not available for this meeting, it should be conducted by the
                            Military Assistant to insure that the coordination is effected on a
                            timely basis and that a final coordinated draft will be available for
                            your subsequent review prior to your meeting with the President the
                            following morning. The morning update will be conducted for you by the
                            Military Assistant.</p>
                        <p>Approve</p>
                        <p>Disapprove</p>
                        <p>Other<note n="5" xml:id="d24fn5">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> checked the
                                “Approve” option and next to the “Other” option, wrote: “except for
                                    [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] presence.”</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Organization of the White House Office Secretarial
                                Staff</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is essential that the reception room be maintained as an orderly,
                            non-substantive administrative area which is occupied solely by required
                            secretarial support. The following secretarial organization is proposed:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Joan McCarthy</hi>—Personal secretary,
                                    responsible for the maintenance of your daily calendar, in
                                    coordination with the Executive Assistant (a separate analysis
                                    of your personal schedule has been prepared by Mr. Eagleburger
                                    as attached at Tab F).</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Mildred Zayac</hi>—Mrs. McCarthy’s Deputy,
                                    responsive to your personal requirements, with the full
                                    capability of filling in for Mrs. McCarthy so that acceptable
                                    working hours can be established for both.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sally Dahler</hi>—Perform confidential
                                    secretarial duties for you and also fill in as required in
                                    general front office clerical work.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Secretary to be designated for the Executive
                                        Assistant</hi>.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Muriel Hartley—Secretary for the Military
                                        Assistant</hi>.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is anticipated that the above secretarial staff would provide the full
                            time competence required to support you, your Executive Assistant and
                            your Military Assistant (each is capable of filling in for the other).
                            Additional late hour assistance can be provided by Mrs. Lora Simkus to
                            insure that the secretarial staff is not subjected to the excessive
                            workloads of recent weeks.</p>
                        <p>Approve<note n="6" xml:id="d24fn6">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> checked this
                                option.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Disapprove</p>
                        <p>Other</p>
                        <pb facs="0089" n="58" xml:id="pg_58"/>
                        <p rend="center">Section II—System for the Processing of Papers Related to
                            National Security</p>
                        <p>As soon as practicable, the point of receipt of all paper work related to
                            the National Security Council affairs should be designated as the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff Secretariat which will be set up
                            under the supervision of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff
                            Secretary, Mr. Moose, in the Executive Office Building (Mr. Bromley
                            Smith should serve as his adviser and be located with him). It will be
                            the function of this Staff Secretariat to receive, log and establish
                            suspenses for all <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> related paper
                            work. Decision will be made by the Secretariat as to the processing of
                            this paper. Normally, it will entail immediate dispatch to the
                            responsible substantive officer, or to the Planning or Programming
                            Section and also provide for mandatory coordination between all affected
                            staff members. Logging and suspenses will also be established for all
                            correspondence referred to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> for
                            action from your White House office.</p>
                        <p>Approve<note n="7" xml:id="d24fn7">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> checked this
                                option.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Disapprove</p>
                        <p>Other</p>
                        <p>When an issue is urgent and demands your immediate attention, it will be
                            sent simultaneously to your office and to the substantive officer or
                            officers most concerned to minimize delay. Specifically, the Secretariat
                            itself should be organized under Mr. Moose to provide the following: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>Prompt servicing and central control of all <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> action papers or papers
                                    referred to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff by the
                                    White House office.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>A system for guaranteeing coordination between individual
                                    members and staff sections of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff.</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>The provision of administrative support to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff to include clerical
                                    assistance, transportation, personnel services, messenger
                                    service and space control.</item>
                                <label>d.</label>
                                <item>Maintenance of the budgetary, personnel and organization
                                    framework of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff. (Mr.
                                    Moose has already recommended that he be authorized to acquire
                                    the services of a budget specialist to prepare a revised <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> budget. We recommend approval
                                    of this action so that budgetary estimates can be promptly
                                    prepared.)</item>
                                <label>e.</label>
                                <item>Maintenance of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff
                                    communications system which will provide for the rapid
                                    distribution of cables, intelligence publications, and reports
                                    to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff.</item>
                                <pb facs="0090" n="59" xml:id="pg_59"/>
                                <label>f.</label>
                                <item>Maintain liaison with the departments and agencies within the
                                    national security structure at the Staff Secretariat level. As a
                                    rule, a Staff Secretary would not deal with the Assistants to
                                    the principals of the Departments and Agencies. This liaison
                                    should be effected through the Executive Assistant or the
                                    Military Assistant as previously outlined.</item>
                                <label>g.</label>
                                <item>The Staff Secretary will work in close coordination with the
                                    Chief of the Planning Section and especially the Chief of the
                                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Support Group, in the
                                    preparation and timely distribution of all <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> agenda related papers. The
                                    Staff Secretary will insure that all <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> related papers, including <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss>s, <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>s, are standardized as to format and style and
                                    are properly numbered and distributed among the interested
                                    agencies on a timely basis. Based on guidance from the Chief of
                                    the Planning Section, the Staff Secretary will maintain suspense
                                    files, a master calendar of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                    and Review Group work schedules and related calendar of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> business. It is essential that
                                    the reproduction capability of the Secretariat provide for the
                                    rapid reproduction of multiple copies of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> documents so that timely distribution of
                                    material of substantive interest to <hi rend="italic">all</hi>
                                    staff personnel is promptly furnished these officers for comment
                                    as required. The Staff Secretary’s Administrative Assistant must
                                    be capable of insuring this action in coordination with the
                                    Chief of the Planning section who must be equally conscious of
                                    this responsibility.</item>
                                <label>h.</label>
                                <item>Establish a messenger service responsive to the requirements
                                    of your White House office and the interagency requirements of
                                    the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff.</item>
                                <label>i.</label>
                                <item>Serve as the single point of contact between your office, for
                                    all <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> matters, as well as
                                    matters referred by your office to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff.</item>
                                <label>j.</label>
                                <item>Serve as the point of contact for the clearance of cables from
                                    State, Defense, <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> or other
                                    agencies and departments as required. Normal routine would
                                    provide for receipt of the cable initially at the White House
                                    office and dispatch to the Secretariat through Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HR2">Houdek</persName> who will log the message.
                                    Once staff clearance has been obtained, it will be returned to
                                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HR2">Houdek</persName> for your
                                    clearance after which it will be officially cleared by the Staff
                                    Secretary who will also maintain a log and suspense on the
                                        messages.<note n="8" xml:id="d24fn8">In the left margin next
                                        to this sentence, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> wrote: “Within 48 hours.”</note>
                                    Some messages which the staff officer considers routine or
                                    totally consistent with your views should be cleared by him thru
                                    the Secretary without further reference to you. Through this
                                    system, a double suspense will insure no cable clearances are
                                    missed. This system will also enable us to restrict highly
                                    classified or personal traffic to the White House office if so
                                    determined by you or your immediate staff.</item>
                                <pb facs="0091" n="60" xml:id="pg_60"/>
                                <label>k.</label>
                                <item>Serve as the point of contact for the receipt of White House
                                    initiated requirements received by your White House office which
                                    should be referred to the Staff Secretariat for logging,
                                    suspense and assignment of action to the appropriate substantive
                                    officer or staff section. As with cables, a double log and
                                    suspense system would be used, first in your office and
                                    secondly, within the Staff Secretariat to insure a double check
                                    and timely receipt of the response. High priority requirements
                                    of the President or his White House staff would be brought to
                                    the attention of the Military Assistant or the Executive
                                    Assistant by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HR2">Houdek</persName>
                                    prior to or simultaneously with processing through the Staff
                                    Secretariat so that you are aware of the requirement.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>(Mr. Moose has recommended the acquisition of a highly qualified
                            administrative assistant from the Department of State to assist in
                            establishing the Administrative Section within the Staff Secretariat and
                            it is recommended that he be provided with this assistance.)<note n="9" xml:id="d24fn9">Beneath this paragraph (the bottom of page 8),
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> wrote: “OK
                                HK.”</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Section III—Organization of the National Security Council Staff</p>
                        <p>There is an urgent need for a prompt and finite delineation of
                            responsibilities within the substantive <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff. This delineation of responsibilities will
                            unquestionably generate personal resentment on the part of individuals
                            who had been told or who have assumed that they would play a role which
                            would be greater or perhaps somewhat different from what sound
                            organization dictates.</p>
                        <p>Recognizing this, we have spoken to several of the principal officers,
                            with the view towards getting a cross section of attitudes on
                            organizational arrangements, especially as they pertain to the interface
                            between the geographic officers and the Planning and the Program
                            sections. Unfortunately, each visualizes a degree of authority and
                            responsibility which could only be achieved at the expense of adjacent
                            staff section or substantive officer. Thus, hard decisions must be made
                            now which are based on the overall efficiency of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff and more importantly, which
                            provide the kind of balance, expertise and judgment essential at this
                            level.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>—At Tab A is a proposed Organizational Chart of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff.<note n="10" xml:id="d24fn10">Tab A is not attached. Tabs B–F are not printed.</note>
                            </item>
                            <item>—At Tab B is a proposed draft mission statement for the Operations
                                Section.</item>
                            <item>—At Tab C is a proposed draft mission statement for the Planning
                                Section.</item>
                            <item>—At Tab D is a proposed draft mission statement for the Programs
                                Section.</item>
                            <pb facs="0092" n="61" xml:id="pg_61"/>
                            <item>—At Tab <gloss target="#t_E1">E</gloss> is a Procedure Outline for
                                the processing of papers for Review Group and <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Meetings prepared primarily by Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HMH2">Halperin</persName>.</item>
                            <item>—At Tab F is a separate analysis of your personal schedule.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>That you approve in principle the organizational concept outlined;</p>
                        <p>That you convene a meeting of the staff and furnish them with copies of
                            the attachments with the provision that functions are in draft only and
                            are subject to refinement in coordination with the Military
                            Assistant;</p>
                        <p>That, in the interim, the organization be set up as outlined effective
                            February 13, to include execution of all physical moves by the close of
                            business February 13.</p>
                        <p>(Mr. Dave McManis (NSA) is prepared to serve as Intelligence Assistant
                            and can be here on February 13. He would remain on NSA payroll.)<note n="11" xml:id="d24fn11">At the end of the text, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> wrote (presumably
                                referring to the entire memorandum), “want to discuss minor
                                changes—Role of <persName corresp="#p_HMH2">Halperin</persName>
                                etc.”</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>