<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-12-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-12-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="244" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d244">
                        <head>244. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>The White House announcement on Friday, November 5, 1971, of the
                            reorganization of the intelligence community (<ref target="#d242fn2">footnote 2, Document 242</ref>) came as a surprise to two senior
                            Democratic members of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, Stuart
                            Symington (D–Missouri) and its chairman, <persName corresp="#p_FJW2">J.
                                William Fulbright</persName> (D–Arkansas), both of whom publicly
                            complained about the failure of the administration to consult the
                            Congress. (Symington was also a member of the Armed Services Committee,
                            which had a subcommittee on Central Intelligence chaired by Senator John
                            Stennis (D–Mississippi).) A telephone conversation between <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and Symington sometime in the
                            morning of November 11, 1971, went as follows:</p>
                        <p>“K: For somebody I like so much you keep going after me.</p>
                        <p>“S: It’s not you; it’s the policy. You know that.</p>
                        <p>“K: I know. You are a good friend and when we are all out of here you
                            will still be. I’m calling about the intelligence reorganization. First,
                            you are absolutely right; I don’t know why there was no Congressional
                            consultation before. This wasn’t done in my shop. My shop was part of
                            the study … but that is no excuse. What I am going to do is to ask
                                <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">George Shultz</persName> to come up and
                            see you next week when he gets back in town to explain the Office of
                            Management point of view. Secondly, the purpose of this reorganization
                            wasn’t to enhance my office, but to give [get?] other members of the
                            committee to state their aims. I can levy requirements now on behalf of
                            the President; I don’t need a committee to do that. It, if anything,
                            limits me personally, but the major test of it isn’t what it does to me.
                            My role is marginal; it actually tends to enhance the role of <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>.</p>
                        <p>“S: Here is where we got off the track. Friday night it began to get
                            around. People came to me and asked what was going on. I hadn’t seen
                            anything and I said I didn’t know about it. That’s embarrassing to have
                            to say that, but you know this committee hasn’t met once this year, and
                            that has got to be changed. So I’m awakened in the morning by an early
                            call from a reporter and I have to say I don’t know anything about it.
                            Then I read the morning paper. I came to the office. I called <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> and asked to speak to <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>. He was out of the country. There
                            was no one there who would talk with me. I got upset about it. I got
                            home and finally there was a call, and there was a member of the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> staff who was kind enough to deliver
                            the White House press release to me at my house on Saturday afternoon. I
                            said ‘what does it mean?’ He said, ‘we don’t know. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry</persName>, you can’t run a railroad like
                            that. By that time I was getting calls from all over my state.’</p>
                        <p>“K: I don’t know what <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> told
                            his people, but he was fully informed, as was the Foreign Intelligence
                            Advisory Board. We ran it <pb facs="0579" n="548" xml:id="pg_548"/>
                            through the intelligence community many times. But the members of the
                            committee should have been informed. There’s no excuse for it. And I’m
                            not finding fault with what you said.</p>
                        <p>“S: I know you well enough to know you wouldn’t have. There’s no one in
                            the Executive Branch I respect more than you. But if these people there
                            aren’t going to tell us what is going on, who is going to?</p>
                        <p>“K: I will have <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName> give you a
                            briefing.</p>
                        <p>“S: What about my suggestion that Stennis call his committee together and
                            give it to all them.</p>
                        <p>“K: Right. Because we ought to try to keep intelligence from being
                            controversial if we can avoid it.</p>
                        <p>“S: Marchetti (?) said there is steadily increasing pressure … My closest
                            friend was Truman’s legal advisor. He left plans which assured that it
                            couldn’t be administered by the military. Then out comes this general
                            who is a nice guy but as military as they come, who is going to operate
                            it and <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> to coordinate it,
                            and you’ve got a committee with the Joint Chiefs … and they go off to
                            the races.</p>
                        <p>“K: <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> … to maintain control.
                            If <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> is only coordinator then
                            it’s not doing its job. I would complain about that. Some people thought
                            of moving <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> out of the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>; I urged very strongly that he
                            stay.</p>
                        <p>“S: He won’t be a figurehead.</p>
                        <p>“K: No. We want him to have more of a voice in military intelligence.</p>
                        <p>“S: I spent more time with some people on Saturday—so it wasn’t a jumping
                            off of mine.</p>
                        <p>“K: No, you are not immoderate. These are reasonable concerns of a
                            serious man. And I’ll do what I can to get a briefing for the
                            committee.</p>
                        <p>“S: And if the committee doesn’t want it, then I want it for the Foreign
                            Relations Committee.</p>
                        <p>“K: They should have it.” (Library of Congress, Manuscript Division,
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box 370,
                            Telephone Conversations, Chronological File. All ellipses are in the
                            source text)</p>
                        <p>On the same morning at 10:40 a.m. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> called Senator <persName corresp="#p_FJW2">Fulbright</persName>:</p>
                        <p>“K: Two things I’m calling you about. You made some comments about the
                            intelligence reorganization. I agree with you that the committee should
                            have been briefed. This was a slip-up. It was done mostly in the Office
                            of Management and Budget, and the Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board
                            was involved. What I would like to do is when <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">George Shultz</persName> comes back—he is out of
                            town now—have him come up and brief you and Senator Symington. My role
                            has not been enhanced by this at all.</p>
                        <pb facs="0580" n="549" xml:id="pg_549"/>
                        <p>“F: It reads that way.</p>
                        <p>“K: I know it does. And you are not unjust in your comments. Now reports
                            have come to me on behalf of the President. We have got a committee of
                            all the consumers, State and anyone interested, to establish broad
                            guidelines. But the test is whether <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>, his staff and the boards reconstituted for him
                            can get a hold on it and get an integrated approach. It’s not to
                            increase White House influence. You didn’t make a big case of it, so I’m
                            not complaining. <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">George Shultz</persName> is
                            out of town. Are you will to receive him next week to get a run-down on
                            what his intention was?</p>
                        <p>“F: Sure. Certainly. Glad to.</p>
                        <p>“K: The second reason I’m calling is if you ever feel like having lunch,
                            breakfast, or a meeting with me alone so I can answer any questions you
                            might have which are harder to answer in the larger group, I am at your
                            disposal.</p>
                        <p>“F: Good, thank you. A free lunch. I’ll take you up on it.</p>
                        <p>“K: I’ll even come to the Hill and let you take me.</p>
                        <p>“F: When I get this foreign aid off my chest I will be able to. They have
                            me here from 9:00 in the morning until 8:00 at night. But it’s almost
                            over now; we are on the floor with it right now.</p>
                        <p>“K: I will let you go, but whenever you feel you have the time, let me
                            know and I’ll do it wherever it’s most convenient for you.” (Ibid.)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>