<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-05-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="273" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d273">
                        <head>273. Memorandum From President <persName type="from">Nixon</persName>
                            to his Assistant (<persName corresp="#p_HHR1" type="to">Haldeman</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d273fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, White
                                House Special Files, President’s Personal Files, Box 4, Memoranda
                                from the President, 1969–1974, Memos—May 1972. No classification
                                marking. A copy was sent to Malek.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-05-18">May 18, 1972</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>One department which particularly needs a housecleaning is the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>. The problem in the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> is muscle-bound bureaucracy which has
                            completely paralyzed its brain and the other is the fact that its
                            personnel, just like the personnel in State, is primarily Ivy League and
                            the Georgetown set rather than the type of people that we get into the
                            services and the FBI.</p>
                        <p>I want a study made immediately as to how many people in <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> could be removed by Presidential
                            action. I assume that they have themselves frozen in just as is the case
                            with State. If that is the case I want action begun immediately, through
                                <persName corresp="#p_WCW1">Weinberger</persName>, for a reduction
                            in force of all positions in the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> in
                            the executive groups of 50 percent. This reduction in force should be
                            accomplished by the end of the year so <pb facs="0652" n="621" xml:id="pg_621"/> that we can then move to get in some better
                            people. Of course, the reduction in force should be accomplished solely
                            on the ground of its being necessary for budget reasons, but you will
                            both know the real reason and I want some action to deal with the
                            problem.</p>
                        <p>In another area of recruiting I want you to quit recruiting from any of
                            the Ivy League schools or any other universities where either the
                            university president or the university faculties have taken action
                            condemning our efforts to bring the war in Vietnam to an end. We are
                            totally justified in doing this anyway because the government simply has
                            too many Ivy League people in relationship to the percentage of Ivy
                            League graduates compared with the total number of college graduates in
                            the country.</p>
                        <p>In filling our needs I want you to give first priority to those schools
                            who have presidents or faculty members who have wired us or written us
                            their support of what we have done in Vietnam. Have the mail checked
                            very carefully to see which ones these are. After you get past those you
                            can then go to other schools in the Midwest, in the South, and even
                            possibly some in the far West (not, of course, including Stanford or
                            Cal) where we would have a better chance to come up with people who
                            would be on our side. Retired military people are also good for this
                            purpose.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>