<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-04-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="301" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d301">
                        <head>301. Memorandum From the Under Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_REL1" type="from">Richardson</persName>) to Secretary of
                            State <persName corresp="#p_RWP1" type="to">Rogers</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d301fn1">Source: Library of Congress,
                                Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName> Papers, Box 102, Seventh-floor Staff. No
                                classification marking. Printed from an unsigned copy.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1969-04-22">April 22, 1969</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>A Seventh Floor Planning and Coordination Staff<note n="2" xml:id="d301fn2">A Seventh Floor planning and coordination staff
                                    was first proposed to <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName> by two members of his office,
                                    Jonathan Moore and <persName corresp="#p_HAA4">Arthur
                                        Hartman</persName>. Moore forwarded the proposal to
                                        <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName> under
                                    cover of a lengthy explanatory memorandum, March 1, in which he
                                    stated that their “basic pitch” was “to improve analytical,
                                    evaluative and coordinational staffing of the Seventh Floor”
                                    through “better organization of existing resources” and thus
                                    without creating a larger bureaucracy. “A strong feature of the
                                    plan is that it would establish an integrated staff in place of
                                    a system of fragmented, uncoordinated, and even competing staff
                                    elements. This is so, even though small personal staffs would
                                    still remain for each of the principal officers on the Seventh
                                    Floor.” (Ibid.) <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName> discussed the proposal with <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> and on April 2
                                    circulated a draft for comment to <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SND1">Samuels</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RI1">Rimestad</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_PRF3">Pedersen</persName>. (Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName>, April 2; ibid., Box
                                        <gloss target="#t_CL1">CL</gloss> 2, Chron File)</note>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="0706" n="675" xml:id="pg_675"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Problem</hi>:—The Secretary of State, in directing
                            the conduct of foreign policy and advising the President on foreign
                            policy issues, should be in a position to take into account all relevant
                            global, functional, and long-range considerations. The Secretary’s
                            principal Seventh Floor associates, to the extent that they exercise
                            comparable functions, should be in a similar position. They should be
                            able to draw on the resources of a compact staff for analysis and advice
                            not subject to the understandable—and even desirable—parochialism of the
                            regional bureaus. Similarly, they need a centralized organ for
                            substantive follow-up and monitoring of action decisions. As matters
                            stand, the Secretary of State and his principal associates lack the
                            staff back-up necessary to meet these requirements.</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff has the function of seeing
                            to it that all pertinent points of view—not that of any one Department
                            or combination of Departments—are systematically brought to bear on
                            major national security issues requiring Presidential decisions.</p>
                        <p>Within the Department of State, the regional Assistant Secretaries, with
                            the assistance of their deputies and the regional Interdepartmental
                            Group secretary, are able to ensure that recommendations coming up from
                            a country director or ambassador are reviewed in the light of policies
                            applicable to the region as a whole.</p>
                        <p>The Seventh Floor should have a capability which meets broader geographic
                            and more complex functional problems. A regional or functional bureau’s
                            recommendations to the Secretary with respect to a matter affecting its
                            own interests should be looked at from other perspectives.
                            Politico-military recommendations should be considered in the light of
                            their economic implications. Before an immediate operational decision is
                            taken, its longer-range aspects should be examined.</p>
                        <p>The revitalized <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> system, meanwhile,
                            has placed increased responsibility on the Department, notably the
                            Assistant Secretaries, for coordinating the definition of policy issues
                            and options within the Executive Branch. This in turn calls upon the
                            Seventh Floor to provide effective policy guidance and review for the
                            bureaus with respect to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> projects
                            from the standpoint of Seventh Floor interests.</p>
                        <p>The closest we now get to the kind of across-the-board substantive staff
                            backup required for these purposes is through the Policy Planning
                            Council and the staff of the Under Secretaries Committee (formerly the
                                <gloss target="#t_SIG1">SIG</gloss> staff). In fact, however, the
                            deliberations of the Policy Planning Council all too seldom affect
                            operational decisions, and the role of the Under Secretaries Committee
                            staff extends only to matters referred to the Committee by the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Proposal</hi>:—Having now had the chance to
                            observe the operations of the Department for a couple of months and to
                            talk to a good many people, I believe that the Policy Planning Council
                            and the Under <pb facs="0707" n="676" xml:id="pg_676"/> Secretaries
                            Committee staff should be modified and brought into a direct
                            relationship to each other as elements of a Planning and Coordination
                            Staff, which would have the following functions: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>To assist the principal officers of the Department in
                                    reviewing and coordinating bureau recommendations, not only
                                    within their own framework, but also from the perspective of
                                    other regions, other functions, and longer time spans.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>To assist the principal officers in guiding the Department’s
                                    participation in the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> system
                                    through: (a) the substantive review of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_IG1">IG</gloss> papers; (b)
                                    preparation for meetings of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Review
                                    Group, and <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Under Secretaries
                                    Committee; and (c) monitoring the follow-up of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> decisions.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>To carry out planning and program analysis activities
                                    transcending bureau lines—a function which would also back up
                                    and tie in with Departmental research programs.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Modification of the Policy Planning Council, which is an integral element
                            of this proposal, will encounter the objection that it involves a
                            symbolic lessening of the importance State attaches to policy planning.
                            The short answer, I believe, is that it would make policy planning more
                            relevant—and thus more important—by taking it out of limbo and relating
                            it directly to the Department’s on-going responsibilities.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Staff</hi>:—Under a Staff Director with rank
                            equivalent to an Assistant Secretary, the new staff would serve as a
                            collective resource for all of the principal Seventh Floor officers. It
                            would not insert itself in the line of authority between Seventh Floor
                            officers and Assistant Secretaries. Nor would it take on bureau
                            functions for itself. Much of its work, rather, would involve
                            coordination among the bureaus and obtaining a hearing for other
                            viewpoints in the Department outside the regional bureaus.</p>
                        <p>The staff should be composed of high caliber officers of broad-gauge
                            abilities, who can handle both short-range operational problems and
                            longer-range program planning and analysis. Their number should, for the
                            present, be limited to about seventeen in all, including the Staff
                                Director.<note n="3" xml:id="d301fn3">This would be three less than
                                the total number of slots now allotted to the Policy Planning
                                Council (15) and the Under Secretaries Committee (5). [Footnote in
                                the source text.]</note> The staff would be made up of two groups.
                            One would include five officers with expertise in each of the
                            geographical regions, one for politico-military affairs, one for
                            economic assistance, two system analysts, one economist, and one
                            political or social scientist.</p>
                        <p>This permanent group should be supplemented by a separate but connected
                            group of about five Senior Policy Planning Advisers drawn in part from
                            the academic community and research institutions. Those drawn from
                            outside the Department should serve for at least one year.</p>
                        <pb facs="0708" n="677" xml:id="pg_677"/>
                        <p>The senior advisers would undertake particular planning or program
                            evaluation projects. Their role, in general, would be to challenge
                            established points of view, develop new ideas on how to solve difficult
                            programs, and serve as a communications link with academic specialists
                            in foreign affairs.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Staff Role</hi>:—Ideally, the Staff Director
                            should be the Department’s representative on the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Review Group. This is desirable given the staff’s
                            responsibilities in assisting the principal officers in guiding the
                            Department’s participation in the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            system—through briefings for the Secretary and the Under Secretary prior
                            to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meetings, maintaining close
                            liaison with the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_IG1">IG</gloss>s and ad hoc groups, reviewing the output
                            of these groups, and absorbing the functions of the staff of the Under
                            Secretaries Committee.</p>
                        <p>In carrying out its functions, the proposed staff would not compete or
                            overlap with <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>, the other collective,
                            common staff service on the Seventh Floor. <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss> would continue to handle informational and
                            administrative aspects of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            system. In addition, <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss> would see to it
                            that the new staff received all appropriate material going to the
                            Secretary and Under Secretaries. <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss> and
                                <gloss target="#t_JPM1">J/PM</gloss> would remain as sources to be
                            drawn upon by the Seventh Floor and would continue to operate as
                            bureaus.</p>
                        <p>In a word, the staff would supplement, but not supplant, the bureaus. Its
                            aim would simply be to assure that the Seventh Floor will have available
                            on important issues the full spectrum of responsible advice the
                            Department has to offer. It would not be a “layer” between the Assistant
                            Secretaries and the Seventh Floor. It would receive lateral distribution
                            of papers destined for Seventh Floor principals, but would not “clear”
                            such papers.</p>
                        <p>A similar restraint should be observed in its monitoring or follow-up
                            function. In many cases, this would be manifested only in providing
                            assurances to the principals that necessary actions were being taken; in
                            other words, it would exercise a watching brief.<note n="4" xml:id="d301fn4">On July 3 <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> announced the formation of the new Planning
                                and Coordination Staff (<gloss target="#t_SPC1">S/PC</gloss>) and
                                the designation of <persName corresp="#p_CWI1">William I.
                                    Cargo</persName> as its Staff Director. He indicated that the
                                Policy Planning Council’s functions would be “amalgamated into and
                                given special identity within the new staff” and policy planning
                                would thereby gain “more impact on continuing operational
                                decisions.” For text of the announcement, see Department of State
                                    <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, July 28, 1969, pp. 74–75. In an
                                October 13 memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_CWI1">Cargo</persName>
                                notified his staff that henceforth <gloss target="#t_SPC1">S/PC</gloss> would be responsible for coordinating <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> action assignments within the
                                Department. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss>
                                59, Policy Planning Council, Subject Files: Lot 73 D 363, <gloss target="#t_SPC1">S/PC</gloss> Organization) <persName corresp="#p_CWI1">Cargo</persName> discussed his activities and
                                experiences as Staff Director for 4 years in his memoir, <hi rend="italic">Wherever the Road Leads</hi>. (pp. 636–691) He
                                noted that <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName> was a
                                strong supporter of <gloss target="#t_SPC1">S/PC</gloss> but that
                                    <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName>’s successor as
                                Under Secretary, John Irwin, who took office in September 1970,
                                “seemed to have little interest in policy planning” and thus “the
                                relationship of <gloss target="#t_SPC1">S/PC</gloss> to the top of
                                the State Department changed rather radically with <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName>’s departure.” (pp.
                                647–649)</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>