<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-12-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-12-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="388" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d388">
                        <head>388. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>In a December 15, 1971, memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_LJFJ1">John
                                Lehman</persName> of the National Security Council staff briefed
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry Kissinger</persName> for his
                            breakfast meeting the next day with Senator Jacob Javits, co-sponsor of
                            the war powers bill introduced in the Senate on December 6 and
                            unanimously voted out of the Senate Committee on Foreign Relations
                            Committee on <ref target="#d7">December 7</ref>. After noting that
                            Javits had gained Senator John Stennis’ co-sponsorship “for the small
                            price of including a phrase permitting action to forestall imminent
                            attack,” <persName corresp="#p_LJFJ1">Lehman</persName> commented that
                            the bill was “wholly unacceptable” and was “almost identical to one
                            which passed the Senate in 1956, but died in the House. We intend to
                            fight and lose in the Senate, and kill it in the House or in extremis
                            veto it.” (National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Subject Files, Box 315,
                            Congressional, Vol. 3.) For text of the Javits–Stennis bill (S. 2956) as
                            reported with amendments by the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, see
                            Senate Committee on Foreign Relations, <hi rend="italic">War Powers
                                Legislation</hi>, pages iii–v.</p>
                        <p>The Javits–Stennis bill was a topic of discussion at a meeting on January
                            24, 1972, of the Legislative Interdepartmental Group, held at the White
                            House and chaired by <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Alexander
                                Haig</persName>. Assistant Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_ADM1">Abshire</persName> stated that “Zablocki thinks he
                            can block this bill in the House and that we should work on the House
                            Foreign Affairs Committee. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJFJ1">Lehman</persName> added that the strategy is to block it in the
                            Zablocki Subcommittee.” (Summary of conclusions, January 24; Library of
                            Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box <gloss target="#t_CL1">CL</gloss>
                            302, Legislative Interdepartmental Group)</p>
                        <p>The Legislative Interdepartmental Group again took up the Javits–Stennis
                            bill at its meeting held at the White House on March 10, 1972. Charles
                            Brower, Deputy Legal Adviser to the Department of State, “reported the
                            outlook is grim. Senators Roth, Bennett, Childs and Ribicoff are
                            prepared to co-sponsor and the bill is becoming a motherhood <pb facs="0876" n="845" xml:id="pg_845"/> issue. It may come to the
                            floor within ten days. The leadership of the American Bar is opposed to
                            it and Clark MacGregor has suggested trying to get it referred to the
                            Judiciary Committee. The main problem is that no one wants to lead the
                            fight against it. Scott won’t do it and Allott won’t lead the fight
                            either. Goldwater and Tower are against it, but would not be helpful as
                            leaders of the opposition.” (Summary of conclusions, March 10;
                            ibid.)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>