<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-12-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="89" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d89">
                        <head>89. Memorandum From Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_LMR2" type="from">Laird</persName> to the President’s Assistant for
                            National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d89fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Agency Files, Box 223,
                                Department of Defense—01 Dec–31 Jan 70, Vol. V. Secret.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1969-12-01">December 1, 1969</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Attached is the letter from Bob <persName corresp="#p_MRP1">Mayo</persName>, providing his views to me on the pending
                            completion of the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1971 budget
                            preparation and the initial stages of the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1972 planning cycle.<note n="2" xml:id="d89fn2">Dated
                                November 19; not printed.</note> I concur in his views that (a) an
                            issue identification process for the Department of Defense, as outlined
                            in the Budget Bureau Bulletin 68–9, is appropriate, and (b) it is
                            premature to deal with the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1972
                            cycle.</p>
                        <p>Much of Bob’s letter bothers me, however. The tone of the letter is
                            strongly aimed at further Defense cuts. The basis for such a
                            predilection is not well-founded, in my judgment. It may be that for any
                            number of reasons such a course will be prudent. But if we do choose
                            that course, it should be on the basis of sound and reasoned analysis,
                            not on the rudimentary analyses which have typified budget and national
                            security resource availability in the past. I believe we have an
                            opportunity to make a quantum jump in our decision-making process at the
                            national level in striving for an optimum resource allocation among our
                            national goals. Pursuing Bob <persName corresp="#p_MRP1">Mayo</persName>’s course would miss that opportunity.</p>
                        <pb facs="0227" n="196" xml:id="pg_196"/>
                        <p>Bob highlights, for example, “… the worsening fiscal picture for 1971….”
                            He concludes, without providing the analysis, that we cannot meet our
                            fiscal goals (unspecified) without a lower Defense target. It is not
                            clear that if employment levels and national production rates slacken,
                            thereby impinging on the revenue flow, the best—much less the
                            only—course is to cut federal outlays. Economic analysis might show that
                            employment levels, production rates, and therefore federal revenues
                            would be enhanced by continuing, or even increased, federal outlays. I
                            do not know. I am simply suggesting the case is not clear based on Bob’s
                            statements.</p>
                        <p>For projecting security outlays in 1972, Bob suggests we wait until the
                            middle of next year to have our discussions, i.e., until <hi rend="italic">Bureau of the Budget</hi> has had the opportunity to
                            reexamine economic projections, the revenue picture, the
                            Administration’s other critical programs, and our progress in Vietnam. I
                            agree on the timing. But it would be far better in my judgment to have a
                            broader look than the Bureau of the Budget can provide by itself. To do
                            the analytical job properly, we need to study: <list>
                                <item>—<hi rend="italic">The overall economic picture</hi>,
                                    including the GNP projections; the resources which will likely
                                    be available for federal programs; the impact of various
                                    spending levels on national goals such as defense, full
                                    employment, economic growth, price stability, and balance of
                                    payments equilibrium.</item>
                                <item>—<hi rend="italic">The sensitivity</hi> of higher and lower
                                    federal spending increments on our key national goals, i.e.,
                                    what price do we pay in inflation, if any, for more national
                                    security.</item>
                                <item>—<hi rend="italic">The allocation of the resources within the
                                        Federal sector for optimum distribution.</hi>
                                </item>
                                <item>—<hi rend="italic">The relation between the supply side of the
                                        national security equation and the demand side, i.e., our
                                        basic national security commitments.</hi>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>We now have an institutional arrangement in the Defense Program Review
                            Committee (<gloss target="#t_DPRC1">DPRC</gloss>) to consider such
                            issues. We should use the <gloss target="#t_DPRC1">DPRC</gloss> for just
                            these purposes. To do so will in my judgment constitute a major
                            accomplishment for this Administration.</p>
                        <p>At the same time, if we use the <gloss target="#t_DPRC1">DPRC</gloss> for
                            lesser tasks, such as assessing the program of individual weapons
                            systems or alternative regional force levels, we shall risk the loss in
                            utility of the Review Committee. Maybe at some later time the <gloss target="#t_DPRC1">DPRC</gloss> can assimilate such important, but
                            lesser, tasks. But at the start—or at least for the ensuing budget
                            cycles—we should reserve to the <gloss target="#t_DPRC1">DPRC</gloss>
                            <hi rend="italic">only</hi> those major aggregate resource allocation
                            issues ancillary to our top-most national goals.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_LMR2">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Mel Laird</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>