<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-12-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="111" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d111">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/26657</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. L. Randolph Higgs
                                of the Division of European Affairs</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-12-04">December 4, 1942</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Mr. Boheman<note n="69" xml:id="d111fn69">Erik Boheman, Secretary General
                                of the Swedish Foreign Ministry.</note> dropped in late this
                            afternoon to say goodbye before his departure for New York to-night. I
                            was reading at the time Stockholm’s telegram no. 3341 [<hi rend="italic">3441</hi>] of December 3,<note n="70" xml:id="d111fn70">Not
                                printed.</note> a white of which is attached,<note n="71" xml:id="d111fn71">A circulation copy on white paper of a telegram
                                received in the Department; not attached to file copy of this
                                memorandum.</note> reporting Swedish press comment on Finland.</p>
                        <p>I showed this telegram to Mr. Boheman and asked him whether he thought it
                            represented the true Swedish opinion on this matter, particularly the
                            statement, <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“If Finland were again face Russia alone, it would be Sweden’s
                                    duty interest aid Finland greater extent than hitherto.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Mr. Boheman after commenting that the <hi rend="italic">Svensha
                                Dagbladet</hi> had always taken a very strong stand in support of
                            Finland, said that under no circumstances which he could now foresee
                            would Sweden give armed assistance to Finland against Russia. I replied
                            that that had been my understanding but that in all of our conversations
                            with the Finns, they showed great confidence that if Germany should be
                            defeated and Finland were faced with the threat of imminent invasion by
                            the Soviet Union, Sweden would give Finland full military support
                            against Russia. I went on to say that if the situation was indeed as he
                            described it, I thought it unfortunate that the Finns were allowed by
                            the Swedes to continue under this misapprehension; as they might, if
                            clearly informed of the Swedish position find it necessary to pursue a
                            different policy. Mr. Boheman agreed fully that this should be done and
                            said that he would discuss the matter with the Swedish cabinet upon his
                            return to Stockholm, especially as regards the Swedish press and their
                            misleading statements.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Boheman … said that rudimentary caution should have prevented the
                            Finns from making any claim to Soviet Karelia when they did. He thought
                            Finland should have announced that it intended only to regain its 1939
                            frontiers and to stop there. He said that such an announcement would
                            have maintained Finland’s moral position in the eyes of world opinion
                            and would not have prevented Finland from taking a “little Russian
                            territory” later if indeed Russia were completely smashed by the
                            Germans. I recalled to him that the Secretary, <pb facs="0109" n="103" xml:id="pg_103"/> as had been made public by the Department, had
                            urged in the strongest terms upon Minister Procopé that Finland declare
                            that it intended only to regain its lost territory and stop there, but
                            without avail.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Boheman said that it had been practically impossible for the Swedish
                            Government to give the Finnish Government any advice about keeping its
                            collaboration with the Germans to a minimum and making peace with the
                            Soviet Union. He said that any such intimations were immediately
                            reported by Finnish Foreign Minister Witting to the Germans who “took
                            the matter up with the Swedish Government.” Mr. Boheman said that as
                            long as Mr. Witting remained Foreign Minister, it was practically
                            impossible for the Swedish Government to offer any suggestions along
                            these lines to Finland.</p>
                        <p>I gave Mr. Boheman our views on Witting and told him that we had already
                            authorized our Chargé d’Affaires in Sweden to pass them on to Mr.
                            Soderbolen [<hi rend="italic">Söderblom</hi>] in the Swedish Foreign
                            Office.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Boheman gave me the impression of being completely in sympathy with
                            our policy toward Finland. He said that he would be very glad to give
                            Mr. Herschel Johnson,<note n="72" xml:id="d111fn72">The American
                                Minister in Sweden.</note> from time to time, any views which the
                            Swedish Government might have on Finland and he would be happy if we
                            would transmit our views on the subject to him through Mr. Johnson
                            whenever we thought appropriate. I thanked him for his offer of
                            cooperation and said that we undoubtedly would avail ourselves of it
                            whenever it seemed feasible to do so.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>