<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador to the Belgian Government in Exile (
                    (Biddle), ), at London</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-08-12T18:25:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-08-12T18:25:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-08-12T18:25:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-08-12T18:25:00-05:00" n="15"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d15">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">855A.24/50: Airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador to the Belgian Government in Exile</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Biddle</hi>
                    </persName>), <hi rend="italic">at London</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-08-12T19:25:00-04:00"
                            >August 12, 1942—7:25 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>A–17. Your despatch no. 36, July 14. Department desires to make following
                    comments upon matters discussed your meeting July 14.</p>
                <p>There is no objection to clause in tripartite agreement permitting revision of
                    agreement before December 31, 1943 if Belgian territory should meanwhile be
                    liberated.</p>
                <p>Department desires a list of those prices which have been agreed upon between the
                    Belgian and British Governments in their agreement <pb facs="0023" n="17"
                        xml:id="pg_17"/> of June 4th, as a basis for considering the prices to be
                    established in the pending tripartite agreement.</p>
                <p>The United Kingdom-Belgian Finance and Purchase Agreement of January 21, 1941
                    would appear to take care of the question of foreign exchange. In considering
                    this question, however, care should be taken that adequate incentive is offered
                    to secure maximum production. With respect to Article IV, it seems doubtful
                    whether we should pay for and take title to unshipped balance of commodities
                    where they lie in the Congo in December, 1943. It would seem more reasonable to
                    pay for and take title to such commodities at least against warehouse receipts,
                    if possible, at the respective export points for each commodity.</p>
                <p>It is out of the question that there be an article in the agreement specifically
                    assuring Belgian Government of necessary shipping. Mr. Makins’ remark that since
                    all shipping is pooled, including that of the United States, there would seem no
                    reason to transfer this question from the authorities which should deal with it,
                    is approved.</p>
                <p>Department has no objection in principle to the lapsing of any uncompleted
                    transactions in the old agreement and their assimilation to the provisions of
                    the new agreement. Specific information desired, however, as to these
                    transactions.</p>
                <p>In addition to above comments with regard to discussion at your meeting,
                    Department desires to advance following suggestions.</p>
                <p>Articles I and II of proposed agreement should state not only that Congo products
                    should be made available according to the quantities enumerated in the first
                    schedule of the agreement, but that United Kingdom and United States should have
                    an option on entire output of all products enumerated.</p>
                <p>Effort should be made to secure inclusion of a further article providing for
                    development work in the Congo. A report, for example, from our Consul at
                    Leopoldville dated April 23, 1942<note n="18" xml:id="d15fn18">Not
                        printed.</note> stated that pyrethrum, for which we have urgent need, will
                    be produced in 1942 in the maximum amount of 539 long tons. The Consul further
                    reports, however, that the maximum possible production in 1943 is 1470 tons. The
                    proposed article might be drafted along the following lines: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“It is recognized by the contracting parties that it may become desirable
                            to undertake active development work for the purpose of increasing
                            supplies of Congo products. Such development work might involve the
                            sending of governmental organizations to the Congo, or perhaps
                            encouraging private firms to engage in procurement of materials or
                            cultivation of forest projects. It is agreed that the Belgium Government
                            will facilitate such activity if it should become desirable and will
                            place no restrictions upon such activity.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="18" xml:id="pg_18"/>
                <p>Have received following telegram from Day:<note n="19" xml:id="d15fn19">Samuel H.
                        Day, Chairman of American Economic Mission in the Belgian Congo.</note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Expect to forward by August 10 complete list of commodities including
                            manufactured goods agreed to by local government as suitable basis for
                            negotiations contemplated agreement covering Belgian Congo civilian
                            consumption requirements. Complete survey of annual quantities and our
                            final will require an additional 6 weeks. Will cable next few days
                            preliminary report on automotive requirements. Gray’s section of report
                            expected by August 15 and Frasché’s by end of August.”<note n="20"
                                xml:id="d15fn20">Anton Gray and Dean Frasché, members of American
                                Economic Mission in the Belgian Congo.</note>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
