<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-07-02T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-07-02T08:00:00-05:00" n="312" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d312">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112 European War 1939/5922:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in France (<persName type="from">Tuck</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Vichy</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-07-02T15:00:00+02:00">July
                                        2, 1942—3 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received July 3—1:22 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>959. The purport of the first two paragraphs of the Department’s 397,
                                June 27, 5 p.m. was communicated confidentially to the official
                                referred to in my 897, June 20, 1 p.m.</p>
                            <p>Today he requested me to convey to the Department his regret that the
                                unofficial undertaking of the French Government that no <pb facs="0335" n="329" xml:id="pg_329"/> further shipments of
                                cobalt would be made could not include the projected shipment from
                                Nemours. He explained that this cobalt had been sold to the Germans
                                and that it was consequently impossible to repudiate the contract.
                                He agreed however to keep us closely informed as to the status of
                                the shipment, its proposed date of departure and the course it would
                                follow. He felt that Murphy’s control officers could play a useful
                                role in this connection and he promised at the same time immediately
                                to convey to me whatever information he received with regard to the
                                vessel’s movements. He added that the ship in question had not as
                                yet reached Nemours.</p>
                            <p>As regards the assurance requested in the second paragraph of the
                                Department’s telegram under acknowledgment he requested our
                                Government to address an official note in this sense to the French
                                Government stating specifically that if this assurance were given we
                                would in return be willing to permit a French tanker to furnish a
                                cargo of kerosene to North Africa.</p>
                            <p>I confidently believe that this official is anxious and willing to
                                keep us informed with regard to the attempted passage of this cobalt
                                and that while it may not be possible for the authorities to arrange
                                to delay the loading and sailing of the vessel he will do his best
                                to keep us posted as to the status of the shipment.</p>
                            <p>The same official informed me that the Germans are now insisting on
                                the continuance of their control at Casablanca for the duration of
                                the armistice period even if United States shipments to North Africa
                                were to be suspended in the future.</p>
                            <p>Repeated to Murphy.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tuck</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>