<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-12T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-12T10:00:00-05:00" n="390" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d390">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/24800:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in France (<persName type="from">Tuck</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Vichy</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-10-12T17:00:00+02:00">October 12, 1942—5 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received October 13—2:49 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1517. Our 1513, October 11, 1 p.m. Another straw indicating that
                                something may be in the wind insofar as French Africa is concerned
                                is a statement made yesterday at Paris by Marion<note n="78" xml:id="d390fn78">Paul Marion, French Secretary of State for
                                    information.</note> to representatives of the North African
                                press (which all Free Zone papers are obliged to carry on the front
                                page today). While Marion opened his conference by extolling the
                                virtues of the French press and radio as compared with the lying
                                insinuations and false information disseminated by “Anglo-Saxon
                                agents and foreign radios” he concluded with the following
                                significant words, which while not pressing openly like the Paris
                                press for a defensive pact with Germany covering French Africa,
                                imply much the same thing: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“You should tell them that our defeat had at least one
                                        advantage, that of leaving us our Empire, and that today,
                                        making use of these psychological factors of which I was
                                        talking a moment ago, others are going to use their power
                                        not against those nations which are too strong to yield
                                        before their attacks, but against ourselves.</p>
                                    <p>We can defend our Empire only if we get Europe’s support; and
                                        refusal on our part to integrate ourselves into Europe, if
                                        continued, would result for our people in the worst of
                                        disasters because in the long run this refusal to
                                        collaborate with Europe would simply become a refusal to
                                        live.</p>
                                    <p>This is the truth for tomorrow, which is that already
                                        proclaimed today, and which you should proclaim unceasingly
                                        with growing energy. This is our duty as it is that of the
                                        Government.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <pb facs="0397" n="391" xml:id="pg_391"/>
                            <p>Laval, in a statement to leaders of the French youth movement
                                yesterday in the following words also stressed the necessity of
                                saving the French Empire— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The goal I set myself is to save our territory and our
                                        Empire. Trust in me. I shall go through with my duty to the
                                        very end. As long as the Marshal gives me his confidence I
                                        shall never desert my post no matter what happens.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>While we have as yet been unable to obtain reliable information as to
                                exactly what may be in the wind, reliable friendly officials believe
                                the Germans are urging the French to come to an agreement calling
                                for joint cooperation which will prohibit the possibility of a
                                successful Anglo-Saxon disembarkation and they express the belief
                                that the opening wedge in endeavoring to obtain some measure of
                                control in Morocco may be a further attempt to liquidate Noguès of
                                whom the Germans are not sure and who in their eyes is now the
                                successor to Weygand<note n="79" xml:id="d390fn79">Gen. Maxime
                                    Weygand, former Delegate General of the French Government in
                                    North Africa.</note> as French public enemy No. 1 in North
                                Africa.</p>
                            <p>Repeated to London and Casablanca.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tuck</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>