<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Algiers (Cole) to the War Department</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d393</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">393</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-10-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-10-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec2p8MfOFI4NR3V8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="393"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d393">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 (E. W.)/11–742: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Algiers (<persName type="from"
                            >Cole</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">War Department</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="85" xml:id="d393fn85">Copy supplied by the Office of the Secretary of
                        Defense under cover of letter of September 7, 1960.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Algiers</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-10-15">October 15 (<hi
                                rend="italic">14</hi>?), 1942</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[No. 670?] From Murphy. For Leahy. In accordance with the President’s directive
                    of September 22 I conveyed the message to General Mast.<note n="86"
                        xml:id="d393fn86">Ma;}. Gen. Charles E. Mast, Commander of French Algiers
                        Division and representative of General Giraud in French Northwest
                        Africa.</note> I inquired whether he would be willing to transmit at once
                    the information to General Giraud and also whether he would comment personally.
                    His reaction was more favorable than I dared hope for the reasons that (1) he
                    expressed genuine alarm over imminent Axis intentions to invade this area and
                    (2) regarding the fragile political situation in France. Mast also told me
                    bluntly that Giraud contemplates that we deal with him and not with Darlan. Mast
                    has learned that Darlan is seeking to climb on the band wagon but in his opinion
                    Darlan could not be trusted. I replied that we hoped that the French would
                    demonstrate some unity, that Darlan is Commander-in-Chief of French armed
                    forces, that French Fleet has its importance and that the Admiralty commands the
                    ports and coastal batteries in French North Africa. Mast retorted that Giraud
                    will command the Army which is loyal to him and not to Darlan and that the Navy
                    in French North Africa would fall in line with the Army. I urged that success of
                    the operation is the cardinal point and that we want the French to consolidate
                    with us.</p>
                <p>Mast’s principal concern is whether we are able to undertake a large scale
                    operation now. I assured him that we are. He then inquired if the Axis attacks
                    in advance of our plans whether we would react immediately and I said I felt
                    confident we would by air but the rest is a technical problem for which I am not
                    competent.</p>
                <p>Mast then insisted that we despatch immediately, because time presses, 5 American
                    officers from Eisenhower’s staff including a general officer to meet equivalent
                    French officers at a point on the Algerian coast 150 kilometers west of Algiers
                    on October 21. Full details regarding reception, hour and facilities will be
                    telegraphed but he urges <pb facs="0401" n="395" xml:id="pg_395"/> that men be
                    selected immediately and be sent to Gibraltar. Officers should include
                    following: one officer competent for operations, one for material, one for
                    debarkation, and one Naval officer. They should arrive by submarine at night and
                    will be received and housed in a private property. A stay of 48 hours is
                    contemplated.</p>
                <p>Mast also stated that urgent need of small arms especially submachine guns and
                    grenades. This has been also subject of discussion with his subordinate group
                    leaders. I informed them with emphasis that we have been waiting for days for
                    their indication of places and time and that time is limited because of moon.
                    They explained that they were awaiting my return from the United States. They
                    promised to supply data for first deliveries by tonight late.</p>
                <p>Mast stated gravest concern over Algiers situation which is menaced by early Axis
                    action. He said there is evidence of arrival of German SS operatives bearing
                    French passports and according to one reliable report Germans were recently
                    given 500 blank French passports intended for use in this area. Mast warned me
                    that American representatives in this area should be prepared to protect
                    themselves against physical attack by Axis agents. I am also requested by Mast,
                    whose representatives returned yesterday from visit to Giraud, to suggest to you
                    the possibility that in the <hi rend="smallcaps">Torch</hi>
                    <note n="87" xml:id="d393fn87">Code name for Allied invasion of Northwest
                        Africa.</note> operation some part of unoccupied France might be held by
                    French Army if latter could be supplied by U. S. Mast said this idea is dear to
                    Giraud’s heart and that latter has worked hard during past 4 months on a plan
                    for combined action next spring in Europe and Africa. He appreciates the
                    compelling reasons for earlier action but urges that you consider the
                    possibility of including in <hi rend="smallcaps">Torch</hi> a plan of
                    establishing a bridgehead in southern France before the Axis has the chance of
                    organizing that area.</p>
                <p>Then question which Mast raised is that of the command of <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Torch</hi>. This is question I have dreaded because of French
                    susceptibilities. After long discussion he proposed the formula of a unified
                    command under which Eisenhower would retain complete command of American forces.
                    In this connection Mast emphasized that French command knowing all details of
                    terrain would be necessary to enable our forces quickly to move through French
                    North Africa to contact the enemy. Mast also referred to the massing of Axis
                    forces on the Tunisian frontier and added that 250,000 Italian troops are lined
                    up on the Italo-French frontier. I suggested this was a technical rather than a
                    political matter but Mast stoutly insisted that it is a political point which
                    must be settled in advance. Are you able to suggest a happy formula for this
                    delicate point which would leave the command effectively with Eisenhower but
                    permit the French to regard the operation as theirs and require them to lend us
                    their maximum aid? Mast <pb facs="0402" n="396" xml:id="pg_396"/> asserts that
                    Giraud’s command will give us entry practically without firing a shot.</p>
                <p>Also Mast states Giraud insists that Embassy at Vichy, Legation in Bern and other
                    possible contacts be instructed that negotiations with Giraud are being
                    channelized elsewhere. Giraud wishes to continue contact with U. S. via Mast in
                    Algiers for reasons of safety.</p>
                <p>Giraud’s departure from France was also discussed. Mast and his advisers believe
                    that we should provide an American submarine to pick up Giraud and his party at
                    night at a point on the French Mediterranean coast. Detailed information on this
                    point will be supplied. They prefer to regard departure by plane only as a last
                    resort. May I say that this is possible. Please inform Eisenhower. [Murphy.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cole</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
