<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="403" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d403">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112 European War
                                1939/7582</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Chief
                                    of the Division of Near Eastern Affairs (Villard)</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-10-21">October 21,
                                        1942</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>I told Mr. de Panafieu that the appropriate authorities of this
                                Government had now approved a restricted program of petroleum
                                shipments to French North Africa on the following quarterly basis:
                                    <table cols="3" rend="width: 70%" rendition="#center-block" rows="5">
                                    <row>
                                        <cell rendition="#hanging">A. Kerosene</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">15,000</cell>
                                        <cell>Tons</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell rendition="#hanging">B. Low grade gasoline</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">10,000</cell>
                                        <cell>Tons</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell rendition="#hanging">C. Gas oil and diesel oil</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">10,000</cell>
                                        <cell>Tons</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell rendition="#hanging">D. Heavy Fuels</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#underline" role="num"> 5,000</cell>
                                        <cell>Tons</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell rendition="#right">Total</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">40,000</cell>
                                        <cell>Tons</cell>
                                    </row>
                                </table>
                            </p>
                            <p>I said it was stipulated that items C. and D. must definitely be of
                                the lower grades, and that any given quota would be subject to
                                change. I added that fuel oil for the Coastwise Service between
                                Casablanca and Algiers would have to come out of the amounts
                                mentioned above.</p>
                            <p>Mr. de Panafieu expressed himself as very greatly pleased with this
                                development. He said that news of the proposed petroleum program
                                would have a most favorable effect in French North Africa and that
                                it would assist materially in producing a friendly attitude on the
                                part of the officials of that territory towards the objectives of
                                the American supply program.</p>
                            <p>I also told Mr. de Panafieu that in connection with this petroleum
                                program we would desire to station at the Consulate General at
                                Casablanca an officer who would be charged with the supervision and
                                control of the supplies. We had selected for this position Mr.
                                Arthur G. Reed, former representative of the Socony-Vacuum Company
                                at Casablanca, who was thoroughly familiar with the French North
                                African territory and well known to the officials in that area. It
                                would be desirable to have Mr. Reed leave at an early date in order
                                to make preliminary arrangements for the arrival of the supplies. I
                                asked Mr. de Panafieu if a visa could be obtained for him. Mr. de
                                Panafieu stated that he would be very pleased to telegraph
                                immediately for Mr. Reed’s visa and that he anticipated no
                                difficulty in this matter. I said that we would like to give him
                                some such <pb facs="0408" n="402" xml:id="pg_402"/> title as Special
                                Assistant or Petroleum Adviser to the Consulate General, and that he
                                would thus operate separately from the Vice Consuls who were serving
                                as control officers. Mr. de Panafieu said he thought there would be
                                no objection whatever to this arrangement.</p>
                            <p>Before talking with Mr. de Panafieu I read to Commander Freseman,
                                aide to Admiral Leahy, the contents of the letter of October 20,
                                1942 from the Secretary of the Navy<note n="1" xml:id="d403fn1">Not
                                    printed.</note> setting forth the joint views of the War and
                                Navy Departments in the matter of petroleum. Commander Freseman
                                stated that the proposed program was “perfectly satisfactory” to
                                Admiral Leahy. I then informed Mr. Cass Canfield of the Board of
                                Economic Warfare, who expressed his concurrence.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>