<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-22T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-22T04:00:00-05:00" n="404" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d404">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/25013:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in France (<persName type="from">Tuck</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Vichy</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-10-22T11:00:00+02:00">October 22, 1942—11 a.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received 10:42 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1571. For Admiral Leahy. Admiral Auphan, Minister of Marine, sent me
                                a verbal message yesterday by Captain Sanson, head of the Deuxième
                                Bureau of that Ministry.</p>
                            <p>Auphan is apparently worried by the recent intensive British press
                                campaign regarding Dakar which he likens to the British press
                                attitude which immediately preceded military intervention in
                                Madagascar. He hopes that our Government would be willing to bring
                                influence to bear on the British to avoid an attack on Dakar which
                                according to Auphan is now strongly defended by mechanized troops
                                and by fairly adequate aviation. Auphan considers that the
                                Madagascan affair and our attitude in the Antilles did not really
                                strike deeply home in France but that an attack on Dakar would
                                provoke a “national reaction” and would arouse deep-rooted animosity
                                against us throughout the whole of France. If Dakar were attacked,
                                he wished me to know that it would be defended to the last ditch and
                                that the garrison would fight to the end rather than surrender.
                                Auphan particularly desired that you should be acquainted with his
                                opinions as he feels certain that you will view them
                                objectively.</p>
                            <p>Quite apart from any legitimate preoccupations as regards the
                                preservation of the French Empire which he may have, I believe that
                                we have a useful friend in Auphan whose influence on Laval has so
                                far been in the right direction.</p>
                            <pb facs="0409" n="403" xml:id="pg_403"/>
                            <p>To my knowledge, Auphan has on two occasions taken a strong stand
                                against the Germans which was illustrated by his attitude towards a
                                proposed joint defense agreement for French Africa and his
                                opposition to turning over French merchant shipping to Germany. (Our
                                telegrams 1284, August 31, 8 p.m.,<note n="2" xml:id="d404fn2">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_194">p.
                                    194</ref>.</note> and 1416, September 24, 5 p.m.<note n="3" xml:id="d404fn3">Not printed.</note>)</p>
                            <p>Certain of our reliable contacts have expressed the opinion that an
                                isolated occupation of Dakar without a successful landing in North
                                Africa would serve no useful purpose and would only arouse the
                                French population against us including many of our well wishers.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tuck</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>