<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chief of Staff, War Department (Marshall), to the Consul General at
                    Algiers (Cole)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d410</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">410</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-10-27T09:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-10-27T09:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2p8MfOFI4NR3V8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-27T09:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-27T09:30:00-05:00" n="410"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d410">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 (E. W.)/11–742: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chief of Staff, War Department (<persName type="from"
                            >Marshall</persName>), to the Consul General at Algiers (<persName
                            type="to">Cole</persName>)</hi>
                    <note n="10" xml:id="d410fn10">Copy supplied by the Office of the Secretary of
                        Defense under cover of letter of September 7, 1960.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-10-27T10:30:00-04:00"
                            >October 27, 1942—10:30 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>No. M–20. This message for Murphy. Herewith is relay of message from Eisenhower.
                    Message begins: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Commander-in-Chief has approved your draft letter to Kingpin subject
                            to change in last paragraph. Second sentence which starts with “However,
                            during the initial phases” and ends with “while the operation is in
                            progress” has been deleted and the following substituted therefor:
                            “However, during those phases of the operation that involve the landing,
                            establishing the security of French North Africa, and providing the
                            necessary bases, it is considered essential that the American Command
                            and organization which has been set up with so much effort and
                            difficulty for this special operation, should remain unchanged. By the
                            time this has been accomplished it is to be assumed that the French
                            Forces, reinforced by the matériel support provided by the Allied
                            Nations will be sufficiently strong to insure the complete security of
                            French territory. Thereafter the primary interest of the American
                            Commander lies in the use of the area as a base of further operations
                            against the Axis, and the defense of French North Africa will be turned
                            over to French Command.” The rest of the letter remains
                            unchanged.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>I request urgently that you expedite news of Kingpin’s decision. If
                            favorable, furnish complete details for his evacuation. This evacuation
                            must occur very soon. It is impossible for American submarine to arrive
                            in time. I have therefore arranged for British submarine, under American
                            command, to stand by at Gibraltar and proceed on short notice when
                            orders are received from me.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Assuming that agreements reached at our conference are confirmed and
                            that you remain convinced of integrity of individuals, you are
                            authorized to notify Kingpin or Flagpole on November 4 of the assault
                            date and of the name of the Commander-in-Chief. Flagpole is acceptable
                            as a Deputy to Commander-in-Chief, whether or not Kingpin accepts
                            invitation.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>In event of postponement of assault date, plans are being prepared to
                            insure that you will be notified.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Message ends here.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
