<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-11-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-11-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="434" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d434">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">851R.24/7</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Lend-Lease Administrator (<persName type="from">Stettinius</persName>) to the Assistant
                                    Secretary of State (<persName type="to">Acheson</persName>)</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-11-13">November 13,
                                        1942</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Dean</hi>: Attached hereto is a proposed
                                draft of a letter on the extension of Lend-Lease aid to the French
                                in North Africa. I would greatly appreciate your comments on it.</p>
                            <p>After getting your comments, I would like to transmit it to the
                                President through Mr. Hopkins.<note n="63" xml:id="d434fn63">Harry
                                    L. Hopkins, Special Assistant to President Roosevelt.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>As you will recall, the President, in a letter to me dated November
                                11, 1941, stated that, “in order to enable you to arrange for
                                Lend-Lease aid to the French Volunteer forces (Free French), by way
                                of retransfer from His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom or
                                their allies, I hereby find that the defense of any French territory
                                under the control of the French Volunteer forces (Free French) is
                                vital to the defense of the United States.”</p>
                            <pb facs="0442" n="436" xml:id="pg_436"/>
                            <p>Subsequently, under date of October 6, 1942, the President sent the
                                following letter to me: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“In order that Lend-Lease aid to the French National
                                        Committee (now Fighting France) may be more effectively
                                        rendered, my letter to you of November 11, 1941, is hereby
                                        amended to remove the provision that such aid be arranged
                                        for ‘by way of retransfer from His Majesty’s Government in
                                        the United Kingdom or their allies’, and you are hereby
                                        authorized to arrange for Lend-Lease aid directly to the
                                        authorities of the French National Committee (Fighting
                                        France).”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>The proposed directive authorizing the extension of Lend-Lease aid to
                                “any French province, colony, protectorate, mandated area or other
                                territory” is intended to leave the whole situation fluid and
                                flexible, so that General Eisenhower, for example, can make the
                                distribution directly to the persons who are going to use the
                                Lend-Lease goods, whether they be representatives of the Fighting
                                French or not. It is, of course, conceivable that the Fighting
                                French may have no part in the Government of some of the newly
                                occupied North African territory for a time at least.</p>
                            <p>One of the principal questions I have is whether or not the language
                                selected in extending Lend-Lease aid to “any French province,
                                colony, protectorate, mandated area or other territory” is broad and
                                flexible enough to cover all the situations that are likely to arise
                                in French North and West Africa, as well as in other parts of the
                                world.</p>
                            <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>E. R. <hi rend="smallcaps">Stettinius, Jr.</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Annex]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Draft Letter From President <persName type="from">Roosevelt</persName> to the Lend-Lease
                                        Administrator (<persName type="to">Stettinius</persName>)</hi><note n="64" xml:id="d434fn64">Marginal note indicates that the Office of Lend-Lease
                                        Administration was informed of Mr. Acheson’s approval. The
                                        President accepted and used this draft in his letter to Mr.
                                        Stettinius dated November 13, 1942.</note>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-11-13">
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">November</hi> 13,
                                        1942</date>.]</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Stettinius</hi>: For purposes
                                    of implementing the authority conferred upon you as Lend-Lease
                                    Administrator by Executive Order No. 8926, dated October 28,
                                    1941, and to enable you to render more effective Lend-Lease aid
                                    to the French people, I wish to supplement the authority
                                    conferred on you in my letters dated November 11, 1941 and
                                    October 6, 1942. Accordingly, I hereby find that the defense of
                                    any French province, colony, protectorate, mandated area or
                                    other territory, not under the control of the Axis, is vital to
                                    the defense of the United States.</p>
                                <pb facs="0443" n="437" xml:id="pg_437"/>
                                <p>The manner in which such aid shall be rendered and recorded
                                    should be determined by you from time to time, after
                                    consultation with the Secretary of State.</p>
                                <p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>F[<hi rend="smallcaps">ranklin</hi>] D. R[<hi rend="smallcaps">oosevelt</hi>]</signed>
                                </closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>