<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Agreement Between General Mark Clark and Admiral François Darlan, Signed at
                    Algiers, November 22, 1942</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d454</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">454</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recb140a4efc2e771d" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general">Warships</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recmU3mkCMXw0nKe9" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Foreign nationals</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recsJ9GxScV9mRtjF" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recR6pcxcU9pXbBvw" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002427"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Agricultural production</term>
                    <term ref="recsTmAcLGbo1pCoe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic stability</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="454"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d454">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851R.01/51</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Agreement Between General Mark Clark and Admiral François
                        Darlan, Signed at Algiers, November 22, 1942</hi>
                    <note n="78" xml:id="d454fn78">
                        <p>Copy transmitted to the Department of State by Mr. Murphy under covering
                            letter of December 5; received December 28. A draft of the agreement,
                            then titled “Protocol Number One,” was circulated in the Combined Chiefs
                            of Staff on November 20, 1942, and on the same day the Combined Chiefs
                            of Staff informed General Eisenhower that the President had approved the
                            draft but had added a condition regarding the avoidance, if possible, of
                            the formal diplomatic term “Protocol” as the title of the agreement. The
                            signed version varies slightly from the approved text. In C. C. S.
                            103/17, General Eisenhower’s comments precede Article I. In his
                            statement, the Supreme Allied Commander set forth his views as follows:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Clear distinction must be drawn between the preamble to the
                                    agreement and the agreement itself. The first two paragraphs of
                                    the preamble merely recite facts that have led up to the present
                                    situation. The mention of Darlan’s name therein does not imply
                                    any obligations on the part of the Allied CINC to perpetuate
                                    Darlan in any position or to support him therein. Paragraph
                                    three of preamble is a recitation of the purposes commonly
                                    agreed upon between the Commander in Chief and the North African
                                    Commission, for which the subsequent agreement is made. Purposes
                                    recited extend beyond the immediate responsibility, mission,
                                    (and) Territory of the Allied Commander in Chief, but they are
                                    taken almost verbatim from letters written by Murphy to various
                                    French officers in this region prior to November 8, when he was
                                    acting as the personal representative here of the President of
                                    the United States.</p>
                                <p>Attention is invited, also, to the fact that this agreement is
                                    merely one between a Commander in the field and a Commission
                                    which is exercising ordinary civil and military functions in the
                                    theater in which he is operating. Its terms are intended only to
                                    facilitate the operations of the Allied Forces brought here,
                                    although, naturally, accomplishment of this purpose involves
                                    certain economic and transportation features. Moreover, it
                                    should be pointed out that the Allied Commander in Chief, as the
                                    signatory authority on one side, is also the interpreter for his
                                    own force of the terms and language employed. In addition, the
                                    effort to gain the cooperation needed by the Allied force is not
                                    going to be the product of exact terminology and language. It is
                                    going to be represented in the success of the Allied Commander
                                    in Chief in galvanizing the local population and local military
                                    forces into action along the general lines indicated in this
                                    draft.” (851R.00/108½).</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Algiers</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1942-11-22">November 22, 1942</date>
                </dateline>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Preamble</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The forces of the United States and their Supporting Allies have landed in French
                    North Africa for the purpose of preventing the domination of this territory by
                    German and Italian forces and their Allies and for carrying on the war for the
                    defeat of the Axis powers.</p>
                <p>By a common agreement among leading French officials in French North Africa, a
                    High Commissioner in French Africa has been established in the person of Admiral
                    of the Fleet François Darlan.</p>
                <p>It has been agreed by all French elements concerned and United States military
                    authorities that French forces will aid and support the forces of the United
                    States and their allies to expel from the soil of Africa the common enemy, to
                    liberate France and to restore integrally the French Empire. In order that this
                    high purpose <pb facs="0460" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/> may be accomplished, and
                    to make appropriate arrangements for the presence in North Africa of large
                    forces of the United States and its allies, the following agreement is entered
                    into at Algiers this 22nd day of November 1942.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>I</label>
                    <item>—There shall be the closest cooperation between the Commander-in-Chief of
                        the French Land, Sea and Air forces and the Commanding General United States
                        Army and supporting forces to accomplish the purpose set forth above.</item>
                    <label>II</label>
                    <item>—The status, command, functions, employment, rights and privileges of
                        French land, sea and air forces will remain under French direction. Such
                        forces will continue in the service of internal security and will be
                        employed, in cooperation with the forces of the United States and its
                        allies, in driving Axis forces from French African territory and in
                        protecting it from further violation by them. All movements of French
                        military, naval or air forces from their normal stations will be notified to
                        the Commanding General of the United States Army by the French
                        command.</item>
                    <label>III</label>
                    <item>—French governmental personnel will continue in the performance of their
                        functions with loyalty to the purpose of the forces under the command of the
                        Commanding General, United States Army and supporting forces. Such
                        government personnel will take such measures as are necessary for the
                        maintenance of order and public administrative services throughout the
                        territory in consultation with the Commanding General of the United States
                        Army.</item>
                    <label>IV</label>
                    <item>—The control and command of all landing and other facilities for aircraft,
                        harbor and port facilities, defenses, fortifications and arsenals will be
                        available to the Commanding General of the United States Army, and
                        supporting forces, for the purpose set forth in the preamble hereof. The
                        control of these facilities will not involve the use of French personnel
                        without the consent of the French authorities.</item>
                    <label>V</label>
                    <item>—Full information will be given as to the location of all facilities,
                        installations, equipment and devices (such as airfields, antiaircraft
                        batteries, observation posts, radio-location and other technical observing
                        stations, minefields, tank traps, military, naval and air force stores,
                        fuel, supplies and equipment, etc.) which may be a hindrance or useful to
                        the purpose of the forces under the command of the Commanding General,
                        United States Army and supporting forces.</item>
                    <label>VI</label>
                    <item>—All telecommunication services will be operated and maintained normally
                        by the French authorities. The United States military forces and supporting
                        Allies will have the unrestricted use of the telecommunication services
                        insofar as may be required for military purpose.</item>
                    <pb facs="0461" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/>
                    <label>VII</label>
                    <item>—French warships shall operate in close cooperation with the Commanding
                        General, United States Army or allied representatives acting with his
                        approval for the accomplishment of the purpose set forth in the preamble
                        hereof. Such warships will continue to fly the French flag and be placed
                        under French command, and will retain such personnel and equipment, and will
                        be provided with fuel and all necessary supplies to enable them to become
                        effective fighting units.</item>
                    <label>VIII</label>
                    <item>—All French merchant vessels in the harbors of French North Africa or
                        those which in the future may enter those harbors will be operated by crews,
                        preferably French, under the French flag in cooperation with the Commanding
                        General, United States Army or allied representatives acting with his
                        approval. Such operations shall be by charter with the public or private
                        owners. Such chartered vessels will be employed in the service of the United
                        Nations to take part in the war effort against the Axis.</item>
                    <label>IX</label>
                    <item>—All port facilities, harbor and naval installations and establishments in
                        French North Africa, together with their records, will be placed intact at
                        the disposal of the Commanding General, United States Army or allied
                        representatives acting with his approval, all remaining under French
                        Command, subject to the provisions of Par. IV above, and such assistance as
                        he may require will be rendered to allow proper maintenance and operation of
                        all machinery and fittings.</item>
                    <label>X</label>
                    <item>—In North Africa, requisitioning of billets, supplies, lands, buildings,
                        transportation and services for the military needs of the forces under
                        command of the Commanding General, United States Army is authorized, if not
                        procurable by agreement promptly, in sufficient quantities and fair prices.
                        Requisitions will be made only by authorization of the Commanding Officer of
                        the troops in the locality and upon the Mayor or other appropriate civil
                        authorities, but may be upon individuals in cases of necessity. Payment will
                        be made at once in cash or in voucher payable in cash by the disbursing
                        Officer of the Army to which the officer belongs and upon whose authority
                        the requisition is issued. Prices will be the fair market value to be fixed
                        by agreement if possible, otherwise by the requisitioning military
                        authority.</item>
                    <label>XI</label>
                    <item>—The authorities in French North Africa will furnish the Commanding
                        General, United States Army with a list of all persons of whatsoever
                        nationality who have been placed under restriction, detention or sentence
                        (including persons sentenced <hi rend="italic">in absentia</hi>) on account
                        of their dealings or sympathies with the United Nations. Those still under
                        restriction or detention will be released when the Commanding General,
                        United States Army, so directs.</item>
                    <pb facs="0462" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/>
                    <label>XII</label>
                    <item>—All service personnel and merchant seamen of any of the United Nations
                        who are interned in French North Africa will be released forthwith and
                        transferred as the Commanding General, United States Army may direct.</item>
                    <label>XIII</label>
                    <item>—The authorities in French North Africa will take such measures as the
                        Commanding General, United States Army, may deem appropriate with regard to
                        the control of foreign property and of the persons and property of foreign
                        nationals, neutral consular officers and such other persons as the
                        Commanding General, United States Army, may direct.</item>
                    <label>XIV</label>
                    <item>—In North Africa no tax, direct or indirect, will be collected upon the
                        property of the United States, the Allied Governments, their representatives
                        and civilian employees, governmental agencies or authorized welfare
                        organizations; nor will any tax be collected upon any purchase from, sale
                        to, or any transaction of any kind with the United States Government, its
                        Allied Governments, their representatives, civilian employees, agencies or
                        organizations.</item>
                    <label>XV</label>
                    <item>—The Commanding General, United States Army, the forces under his command
                        and supporting forces and their legal Governments, the representatives of
                        their governments and civilian employees of these governments shall enjoy
                        extraterritorial privileges and be exempt from the jurisdiction and immune
                        to the process of the courts, civil and criminal, of the territory.</item>
                    <label>XVI</label>
                    <item>—In North Africa areas deemed by the Commanding General, United States
                        Army, to be of importance or useful to the purpose set forth in the preamble
                        hereof, from time to time, may be declared by him to be military areas under
                        his control whereupon the maintenance of order and administrative and public
                        services in such areas shall come under the direct control of such
                        Commanding General. The French authorities will be promptly notified in the
                        event that such a step becomes necessary.</item>
                    <label>XVII</label>
                    <item>—If the internal situation at any time be such as in his opinion to
                        endanger his lines of communication or threaten disorder the Commanding
                        General, United States Army will inform the French authorities of such
                        danger and the French authorities will undertake, in concert with him, such
                        administrative and other measures as may be necessary for the protection of
                        the military interests of the forces under his command and supporting
                        forces.</item>
                    <label>XVIII</label>
                    <item>—The Commanding General, United States Army, will appoint such military,
                        naval, air and economic and branch Missions as he may deem requisite to
                        regulate, in liaison with such agency or agencies, as the local authorities
                        will institute for this purpose, the application of the present
                        accord.</item>
                    <pb facs="0463" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/>
                    <label>XIX</label>
                    <item>—There shall be immediately appointed a Joint Economic Commission which
                        will be charged with the study of the economic needs of French North Africa.
                        The Commission will suggest such measures as may seem appropriate to it
                        regarding exportation and importation, as well as for the increase of
                        agricultural production, as well as for the establishment of economic
                        stability, and the creation of prosperity in French North African
                        territories.</item>
                    <label>XX</label>
                    <item>—A Joint censorship commission shall be established. It will extend its
                        action to the press, radio broadcasts, telecommunications, postal services
                        and all public means for the dissemination of information and shall operate
                        in full conformity with the common purpose set forth in the preamble hereof.
                        The French members of the Commission will be appointed by the High
                        Commissioner.</item>
                    <label>XXI</label>
                    <item>—The foregoing arrangements will be drawn up in the English and French
                        languages. The English text is authoritative.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
