<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-12-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="464" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d464">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112 European War
                                1939/7362</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Commanding General, Services of Supply (<persName type="to">Somervell</persName>)</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-12-01">December 1,
                                        1942</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear General Somervell</hi>: Following the
                                receipt of your letter of November 26 to Mr. Atherton in regard to
                                the staff which is to proceed to North Africa to assist Mr. Murphy
                                in civil affairs, I have discussed the matter further with the other
                                interested agencies, i.e. the Treasury Department, the Board of
                                Economic Warfare, the Lend Lease Administration, and the Department
                                of Agriculture. With the exception of Agriculture, these agencies
                                feel that it would be most desirable if the initial mission could
                                include two representatives rather than one from each agency, since
                                the problems to be surveyed are so various in character that they
                                are beyond the competency of a single individual.</p>
                            <p>I am inclined to concur in the recommendation of the other agencies.
                                Under these conditions the mission would include Mr. Paul Culbertson
                                and Mr. Donald Hiss of the State Department, Mr. Lloyd Cutler and
                                Mr. John Orchard of the Lend Lease Administration, Mr. Morris
                                Rosenthal and Mr. Harold Starr of the Board of Economic Warfare, Mr.
                                Garthoff of the Department of Agriculture and two representatives,
                                as yet unnamed, of the Treasury Department. Three of these desire to
                                proceed to North Africa via London; the others will follow whatever
                                route you designate.</p>
                            <p>It is hoped that it may prove possible to make arrangements for the
                                departure of this group early next week. I may add that I attach
                                greatest importance to the work of this mission and believe that it
                                will contribute materially to the long term success of our
                                operations in North Africa.</p>
                            <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Cordell Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>