<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-12-09T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-12-09T21:00:00-05:00" n="475" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d475">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">851R.50/23: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom (<persName type="to">Winant</persName>)</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-12-09T22:00:00-04:00">December 9, 1942—10 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>6236. Your 6763, November 30. We welcome the concurrence of the
                                British Government in the arrangements envisaged by this Government
                                and the British offer of cooperation. We feel that the interest of
                                both Governments can be most expeditiously handled by the joint
                                procedure envisaged in this and previous telegrams.</p>
                            <p>It is expected that the civilian mission composed of two
                                representatives of State, BEW, and Lend-Lease, one Treasury and one
                                Agriculture representative will proceed to North Africa within the
                                next few days. Until they have had an opportunity, after
                                consultation with General Eisenhower and his Civil Affairs staff, to
                                submit recommendations, it is not our intention to formalize any
                                specific procedure to deal with the non-military operations in North
                                Africa. We have not been informed regarding the organization of the
                                two boards mentioned in your telegram and believe that details of
                                the organization should be left to the Civil Affairs staff under the
                                direction of the Civil Affairs officer. The four following
                                paragraphs represent the Department’s views in this respect which
                                are being communicated to Murphy:</p>
                            <p>During the period of actual military operations and until General
                                Eisenhower has decided that full responsibility for civil affairs
                                can be transferred to civil departments and agencies, non-military
                                operations shall be carried on under the general supervision of the
                                military commander and shall be subject to the exigencies of the
                                military situation. The primary objective of all civilian officials
                                in North Africa during this period shall be to contribute to the
                                success of our military operations and particularly to assist in the
                                supply of materials which are recommended by the Army as
                                contributing to these operations.</p>
                            <p>It is anticipated that following this period of active military
                                operations there will be a transition period during which the
                                military commander will wish to divest himself of certain
                                responsibilities for the conduct of civilian affairs. At that time
                                and in accordance with the judgment of the military commander
                                representatives of the civil departments and agencies, under the
                                leadership of the State Department, will be able to undertake those
                                responsibilities.</p>
                            <p>During the initial period non-military problems in North Africa will
                                be dealt with by the Civil Affairs Staff of the Military Commander,
                                which shall consist of both United States and British members. <pb facs="0484" n="478" xml:id="pg_478"/> All members of the staff
                                shall be responsible to the Civil Affairs Officer of the Allied
                                Forces, Mr. Murphy. Relations with the French authorities shall be
                                conducted exclusively through or with the approval of the Civil
                                Affairs Officer. Operating programs of supply, procurement, finance
                                and other controls, under policies agreed to in Washington, and
                                recommendations for policy consideration in Washington will be
                                worked out in joint terms under Mr. Murphy’s direction by the United
                                States and British members of his staff and with such collaboration
                                with the local authorities as seems desirable.</p>
                            <p>In Washington the formulation and implementation of the economic and
                                social program has been placed under the Office of Foreign
                                Territories in the European Division of the Department. Mr. Paul
                                Appleby, Under Secretary of Agriculture, has been loaned to the
                                Department for the purpose of assuming charge of this Office. The
                                Office will be assisted by a number of advisory and operational
                                committees on which the interested United States and British
                                agencies will be represented. The facilities of these agencies,
                                including the Combined Boards, will of course be used whenever
                                possible. It seems desirable that questions arising under the
                                program be dealt with in the first instance by these groups in
                                Washington, subject of course to the recommendations of General
                                Eisenhower and the Civil Affairs Officer, and to the concurrence in
                                policy matters of the British authorities. The Office of Foreign
                                Territories will of course maintain the closest liaison with the
                                British Embassy on matters affecting the overall program.</p>
                            <p>The Department agrees with the British that the seven economic
                                warfare objectives listed in your telegram are important and must be
                                dealt with as promptly as possible. It is envisaged that the
                                operating Committee and the Civil Affairs Staffs will give early
                                consideration to them. In the meanwhile, we should welcome any
                                further British views on these subjects. We regard, however,
                                censorship and communication in the present stage of operations as
                                military in character to be handled by the military, under whose
                                joint United States and British direction any necessary surveys
                                should be undertaken.</p>
                            <p>As to the dispatch of United States personnel from London to North
                                Africa, the Department is authorizing Gullion to proceed for the
                                specific purpose of surveying under the general direction of the
                                Civil Affairs Staff, the problems of using this area for economic
                                intelligence purposes. In general, however, the Department would
                                prefer that no further United States personnel proceed from London
                                until our mission has had an opportunity to examine the situation
                                and report their personnel needs, as well as their other
                                recommendations. <pb facs="0485" n="479" xml:id="pg_479"/> In view
                                of the novel and complicated problems of organization faced by the
                                Civil Staff in North Africa, it seems desirable that United States
                                Civil personnel be dispatched from Washington after instruction here
                                as to their duties and position in the field.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>