<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Secretary of State (
                    (Berle))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d48</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">48</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-03-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfstIIL5scNKk3A" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-03-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="48"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d48">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">701.60D11/243½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Berle</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-04">March 4,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Finnish Minister came in to see me at his request.</p>
                <p>He brought up again the question of restrictions on Finnish consuls who are by
                    law required not to leave the city in which they work. He said he believed that
                    some of the honorary consuls who were American citizens were not observing this;
                    specifically, there was an honorary consul who worked in New York but lived in
                    Long Island. He likewise asked about restrictions on his own movements, saying
                    that he had to go to New York quite frequently in connection with the
                    liquidation of the Finnish purchasing mission.</p>
                <p>I said the matter was still under consideration and I would try to expedite a
                        solution.<note n="65" xml:id="d48fn65">A notation dated March 12, 1942, to
                        this portion of the memorandum reads: “Mr. Berle says to let Eu [Division of
                        European Affairs] handle this: the Minister should not be able to shop
                        around.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>He then, as usual, tried to draw me into a discussion of the general Finnish
                    position. I avoided this, saying that I thought that the discussions had between
                    himself and Mr. Welles had made the matter perfectly clear.</p>
                <p>He renewed his insistence that they considered it a “Finnish War”, not to be
                    connected with a World War. I confined myself to saying <pb facs="0055" n="49"
                        xml:id="pg_49"/> that unhappily Finland had got herself into the position of
                    fighting on the side of the Germans, with all that implied.</p>
                <p>He asked whether he might personally go over the various possibilities in the
                    situation. I inquired whether he was doing this by instruction of his Government
                    and he said he was not. I said that I likewise had no authority to discuss those
                    matters and that I feared that under all the circumstances, merely personal
                    discussion could be of no useful result.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>A. A. B[<hi rend="smallcaps">erle</hi>], <hi rend="smallcaps">Jr.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
