<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-03-26T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-03-26T17:00:00-05:00" n="506" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d506">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">851.01/390: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom (<persName type="from">Matthews</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-26T23:00:00+01:00">March 26,
                                    1942—11 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received March 26—9:45 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1453. I received a call from Tixier, Chief of the Free French Delegation
                            at Washington, who is shortly returning to the United States. I found
                            him unhappy over the situation he has found here. He feels that neither
                            the British Government nor our own “understands” the situation in France
                            and that General de Gaulle and his entourage at Carlton Gardens are
                            equally devoid of all “sense of realism”. His thesis is briefly this:
                            France must again become a battle field before the end of the war. The
                            seeds of resistance which exist in France should therefore be carefully
                            nurtured. Those seeds of resistance are only to be found in the
                            “people”. De Gaulle and his followers, he says, have no contact with
                            “the people”. Specifically what he wants, apparently, is to have the
                            British through clandestine means bring over a few trusted persons who
                            will subsequently return to France and organize for “the day”. He finds
                            the Free French headquarters here so occupied with “their own petty
                            squabbles” as to be unable to give that leadership “devoid of
                            self-seeking” which the movement requires.</p>
                        <p>While he touched on it only briefly, I gather that his criticism of our
                            Government is not the maintenance of relations with Vichy but alleged
                            efforts to discourage financially generous and well-disposed groups in
                            the United States from giving that material and moral aid that he would
                            like to see.</p>
                        <p>Tixier impressed me, as he apparently has the British, as honest and
                            intelligent. Whether, however, in view of his own long absence from his
                            country, he has a proper evaluation of the situation in France today and
                            of the sentiments of his fellow countrymen I am not sure. I thought the
                            Department might be interested, however, in a brief account of his views
                            and his impressions since arriving here.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Matthews</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>