<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-07-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="558" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d558">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">851U.7962/4</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Assistant Chief of Staff (<persName type="from">Handy</persName>) to the Assistant Secretary of State
                                    (<persName type="to">Berle</persName>)</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-07-01">July 1,
                                1942</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Berle</hi>: In your letter of June
                            24th, you make reference to an agreement reached by the Military
                            Commandant at Pointe Noire concerning the use of the airport at Pointe
                            Noire by the United States. No formal negotiations have been carried on
                            with the Military Commandant of Pointe Noire by representatives of the
                            War Department. However, informal discussions have been carried on with
                            General Sicé and Colonel Carretier at Brazzaville, and with the Military
                            Commandant of Pointe Noire. These discussions concerned only matters of
                            a technical nature and were conducted by U. S. Army Engineer and Air
                            Corps officers in connection with the survey and reconnaissance of the
                            air ferry route through Pointe Noire. The above officers were not
                            authorized to make any formal agreements or commitments involving the
                            United States. Any understandings reached were purely of an unofficial
                            nature.</p>
                        <p>Enclosed are a paraphrase of a cablegram sent by the Army Air Forces
                            Ferrying Command through the State Department to the American Consul at
                            Leopoldville, 15 March 1942, and extracts from a Report on
                            Reconnaissance of Additional Air Routes to Australia, dated April 18,
                                1942.<note n="15" xml:id="d558fn15">Enclosures not attached to file
                                copy of this letter.</note> The above-mentioned papers indicate the
                            nature and substance of all informal discussions which have taken place
                            between Free French authorities and the above mentioned U. S. Army
                            personnel.</p>
                        <p>Early action toward obtaining permission from the Government of French
                            Equatorial Africa for improvement and operation by the U. S. Army of the
                            Airport at Pointe Noire together with such supply <pb facs="0577" n="571" xml:id="pg_571"/> installations as may be required in that
                            connection, will be appreciated.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Thos. T. Handy</hi>
                            </signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Brigadier General</hi>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>