<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Finland ( (Schoenfeld) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-04-27T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-04-27T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec8b79a8b95ce4a65" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="atlantic-charter">Atlantic Charter</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-04-27T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-04-27T11:00:00-05:00" n="56"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d56">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/21256: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Finland</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Schoenfeld</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Helsinki</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-04-27T19:00:00+03:00"
                            >April 27, 1942—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received April 28—5:02 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>309. Upon his return to Helsinki from an absence President Ryti received me today
                    and I spoke to him in sense of your 63, April 23. President expressed confidence
                    that Russian resistance to Germans would be broken this year and countered any
                    intimation of possible further Finnish offensive in Soviet territory by
                    asserting that it was Russians who continued to attack Finnish positions. These
                    attacks in recent past and still going on in some sectors at no time represented
                    serious threat to Finnish positions and in general he gave impression that
                    Finnish military situation remained satisfactory.</p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="54" xml:id="pg_54"/>
                <p>He said he could not know outcome of war against Germany but he remained sure
                    that if Germany were defeated and Russia victorious Bolshevism would sweep
                    Europe, including Britain and even threaten internal stability in United States.
                    President while disclaiming sympathy with Nazism considers Hitler pivot of
                    balance between Nazi Party and German Army which balance might be destroyed by
                    his elimination and deliver Germany to Bolshevism while in Britain and United
                    States the lowering of standard of life, the casualties and other losses
                    incident to war on its present scale would similarly prepare ground for
                    proletarian upheavals at least akin to Bolshevism if in form different from its
                    expression in Russia.</p>
                <p>Ryti expressed doubt that we would be able to restore European position in Far
                    East and said he expected the present would not be the last war between United
                    States and Japan. Ryti said that if Finland and the other northern countries
                    survived present war it would be necessary with Sweden and Norway to form the
                    northern coalition which Finland sought to create in 1940 and which was accepted
                    in principle by Swedes but failed for various reasons.<note n="78"
                        xml:id="d56fn78">See footnote 54, <ref target="#pg_41">p. 41</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In response to inquiry as to effect of continuance of war on Finland’s internal
                    economy President was vague but expressed view that in Finland as well as in
                    other belligerent countries including Britain and United States public debt
                    being piled up would never be repaid.</p>
                <p>So far as Finland’s relation with Russia and Germany was concerned the President
                    said frankly that as a Finn he would prefer the danger attendant upon German
                    domination of the continent to decapitation of the Finnish people which would
                    follow Russian control of this country because the first danger could be met by
                    passive resistance in which Finns were experienced whereas the second danger
                    would mean destruction of nation. He said that during the peace negotiations at
                    Moscow in March 1940 Molotov had frankly admitted to him that purpose of Soviet
                    policy was creation of a new Soviet nationality and elimination of all
                    traditional national groups in the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>My conversation with President which lasted more than 2 hours and covered pretty
                    well entire range of world affairs was first I have had with him since November
                    and I do not think he has changed in slightest his view of what Finnish policy
                    should be. I would describe that policy as designed to make maximum use of
                    Finland’s relation with Germany to prevent Russia from controlling this country
                    but with no inclination specially to facilitate possible German plans for
                    propagation of Nazi ideology here. Policy mentioned undoubtedly includes also
                    hope that territorial gains already achieved can at least be held pending result
                    of European War and perhaps extended if Russian <pb facs="0061" n="55"
                        xml:id="pg_55"/> power is forced back to line of Volga River which the
                    President mentioned. He clings tenaciously to the claim that hostilities last
                    June were initiated by Russians against Finland and said in response to my
                    inquiry as to reason for such action on part of Russians that it was undoubtedly
                    due to Soviet Government’s knowledge of its own military power, which was
                    unknown outside Russia, and to belief that relatively small number (about
                    30,000) of German troops then in this country could be destroyed and Finland
                    taken over because of its supposed exhaustion as a result of Winter War.</p>
                <p>So far as our relations with Finland are concerned, my view is that nothing we
                    can do short of direct military action or a free offer to feed Finland will
                    change Finnish policy. The President said as much when he pointed out that if
                    Russia were on victorious side at end of war she would dispose of this country
                    as she saw fit and we could do nothing about it. Britain, he said, was already
                    committed to Russian domination of this country and President asserted that he
                    knew this to be fact although he admitted that we were still governed in our
                    view of status of Finland and of the small nations in Russian orbit by our
                    interpretation of Atlantic Charter.<note n="79" xml:id="d56fn79">For text of the
                        Atlantic Charter, see <ref target="frus1941v01#pg_367">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1941, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 367</ref>. The Minister in Finland
                        commented in a later telegram, No. 320, April 29, 5 p.m., that the Finns
                        still believed that “despite our displeasure at their collaboration with
                        Germany,” at the end of the general war our sympathy “will at least preserve
                        their independence and lead us to contribute to reconstruction of the
                        country. They are strengthened in this view by fact that, notwithstanding
                        our warnings since last fall, they have been able to keep to their course
                        and at the same time maintain official relations with us.” (740.0011
                        European War 1939/21300)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Summing up—there has been no essential change in Ryti’s view of general European
                    situation. He still expects European War to end in relatively short time, say
                    within a year with defeat of Russia or her withdrawal to Volga and a compromise
                    peace between Germany and the Western powers. He seems still to count on German
                    victory for salvation of Finland but said that he would make peace with Russia
                    the moment he could get “security.” I did not press for any definition of that
                    term in view of your no. 61, April 22.<note n="80" xml:id="d56fn80">See last
                        paragraph of telegram No. 296, April 22, 5 p.m. to the Minister in Sweden,
                            <ref target="#pg_52">p. 52</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Schoenfeld</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
