<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-04-26T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-04-26T17:00:00-05:00" n="57" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d57">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/21251:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Matthews</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-04-27T00:00:00+02:00">April 27,
                                    1942—midnight.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received April 27—11:20 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>2202. The competent official of the Foreign Office mentioned that the
                            various reports which circulate occasionally regarding the possibility
                                <pb facs="0062" n="56" xml:id="pg_56"/> of Finland withdrawing from
                            the Russian war apparently originate in the hopes of certain Social
                            Democrats in Finland and gain currency abroad through Social Democratic
                            circles in Sweden. In this official’s view such reports were exaggerated
                            and premature to say the least and he still believed that Finland would
                            in any event await an indication of the outcome of this summer’s eastern
                            campaigns. According to this official, one of the chief holds which the
                            Germans possess over Finland is the food supply. The Foreign Office had
                            consequently considered suggesting to the Russians that, despite their
                            present food stringency, they might explore the practicability of making
                            food available to the Finns as a possible basis of discussion at some
                            later stage. This suggestion had been telegraphed to the British Embassy
                            at Kuibyshev which was left discretion whether it should be placed
                            before the Russians at this time, particularly from the standpoint of
                            whether the suggestion under the present circumstances might be
                            interpreted by the Russians as part of an independent British initiative
                            to make peace with the Finns, an impression which the Foreign Office
                            wished to avoid. As yet no answer has been received from Kuibyshev.</p>
                        <p>The Foreign Office official referred with appreciation to the cooperation
                            which the Department has extended to the British Embassy in Washington
                            in the consideration and formulation of policy toward Finland.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Matthews</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>