<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-06-10T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-06-10T16:00:00-05:00" n="759" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d759">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">868.48/3145: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Sweden (<persName type="from">Johnson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-06-10T22:00:00+01:00">June 10,
                                    1942—10 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 10:27 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1466. My 1465, today. Boheman told us that he felt Junod had done a good
                            job with the Italians and he urged that both American and British
                            Governments agree to International Red Cross proposals as soon as
                            possible. If we do Swedes will start chartering ships at once and will
                            send Swedish representatives immediately to Athens. They will ask safe
                            conduct for ships and for three to go at once or more if British and
                            American Governments agree in view of long delay. Allard, Swedish Chargé
                            d’Affaires at Sofia, will be one of members and Risberg, a Swedish
                            subject, formerly representative Swedish Bail-Bearing Company in Athens
                            and now Swedish Consul at Athens, another. Boheman knows Risberg
                            personally and says he has highest opinion not only of his honesty but
                            of his intimate knowledge of Greece and conditions in that country.
                            Risberg has already reported to Foreign Office his opinion that it is
                            extremely desirable for neutral commission to get to work at once. He
                            says food now being distributed by International Red Cross is not taken
                            by occupying authorities which on contrary are showing disposition to
                            get it to Greek civilians but due to lack of personnel and proper
                            supervision distribution is bad and some of it is getting to black
                            market. Foreign Office is of opinion that adequate number of neutral
                            personnel to be attached to commission is essential to effective
                            supervision and they think that there should be at least 30 individuals
                            for this purpose of whom presumably half would be Swedes and half Swiss.
                            A careful search is now being made for suitable personnel among Swedish
                            businessmen and in quartermaster service of the army as well as
                            elsewhere.</p>
                        <p>Boheman pointed out that all of original conditions put forward by
                            British Government have been fully covered by assurances given to
                            Swedish Government by Axis Governments and he stated that performance of
                            these conditions will be fully covered in reports which Swedish
                            Government will make to British and American Governments. If any hitch
                            occurs on the ground Swedish delegates will report at once and Allied
                            Governments can take any action they see fit. Boheman thinks essential
                            thing is to get approval and to start organizational ground work at
                            once.</p>
                        <p>He said that there was one point that should be made clear with respect
                            to chartering of ships. The Swedish Red Cross which is nominal charterer
                            and Swedish ship owners are not satisfied to have <pb facs="0770" n="764" xml:id="pg_764"/> only Greek Government as responsible party
                            and desire what is essentially a British-American underwriting guaranty.
                            It is important that Greek Government in London not appear in any open
                            communication in this connection as it would only serve to make trouble
                            with Axis.</p>
                        <p>The Italian Government has given assurances to Junod and reaffirmed these
                            assurances to Swedish Minister at Rome that all food stuffs produced in
                            Greece will be reserved exclusively for civil Greek population and that
                            if there is any surplus which may eventually be exported it will be
                            entirely compensated for by other foodstuffs imported into Greece. This
                            communication was made to Swedish Minister at Rome on June 5.</p>
                        <p>Boheman finally pointed out that both Risberg and Allard have emphasized
                            the necessity for motor transportation and fuel being made available to
                            commission and that without it effective supervision is impossible. Both
                            transportation and fuel would be unprocurable in Greece and should be
                            sent out with grain ships. Swedes will undertake responsibility for
                            vehicles and for their proper use, tagging them with necessary Red Cross
                            and other emblems to insure their identity.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>