<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom (Winant) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d770</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">770</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-09-11T08:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-09-11T08:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-09-11T08:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-09-11T08:30:00-05:00" n="770"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d770">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">868.48/3264: Airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom (<persName type="from"
                            >Winant</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-09-11T14:30:00+01:00"
                            >September 11, 1942—2:30 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received September 15—2 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>A–105. Greek Series from Biddle. With reference to Department’s telegram Greek
                    Series No. 7, September 4, 11 p.m.,<note n="42" xml:id="d770fn42">See footnote
                        41, <ref target="#pg_772">p. 772</ref>.</note> regarding relief food
                    shipments for Greece, Prime Minister Tsouderos, in note of September 8, requests
                    me to convey to you following account of situation: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“As is known, the solution of the problem of supplying the bare
                            necessities in the way of foodstuffs to the starving population of
                            Greece was based on securing the despatch of some elementary foods,
                            indispensable for the maintenance of the people, such as (<hi
                                rend="italic">a</hi>) a certain proportion of the population’s wheat
                            requirements, and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) a small quantity of pulses
                            by means of which the popular feeding-centres prepare a little hot food
                            to accompany the ration of bread. The question of the wheat has entered
                            a favourable phase, thanks to the fact that the scheme for regular
                            shipments in Swedish vessels has begun to be applied. On the other hand,
                            the question of the pulses, which during last winter had been more or
                            less solved by means of shipments from Turkey, has since a few months
                            ago been faced with a fresh and insuperable difficulty in the
                            aggravation of the food situation in Turkey. Exports from Turkey were
                            attended by progressively greater difficulties. The articles of food
                            exported began to be restricted, during the last voyages of the Turkish
                            steamship <hi rend="italic">Dumlupinar</hi> the cargoes consisted mainly
                            of dried fruits, the value of course, far less than that of pulses.
                            Finally, some time ago the Turkish Government, faced by its own
                            difficulties, declared that it would be compelled to discontinue the <hi
                                rend="italic">Dumlupinar’s</hi> voyages. It was only as a result of
                            persistent efforts on the part of the British that permission for these
                            voyages to be <pb facs="0782" n="776" xml:id="pg_776"/> continued was
                            obtained, though no undertaking was given as to the duration of this
                            permission, with the consequence that through the progressive
                            deterioration of the food situation in Turkey we are threatened with the
                            possibility of the suppression of the voyages at any moment.</p>
                        <p>“But a particularly serious aspect of the matter is that the quality even
                            of the small quantities still being despatched from Turkey to Greece has
                            fallen to such a degree that some of these foodstuffs are imperilling
                            the consumers’ health. According to information of an absolutely
                            confidential nature which has reached us from various reliable sources,
                            some of the food carried during the latest voyages of the <hi
                                rend="italic">Dumlupinar</hi> was in a state of utter decomposition.
                            Naturally responsibility for this can in no way be laid either to the
                            Turkish or the Allied competent authorities, to whom we are ever
                            grateful for their truly indefatigable endeavours. It is clear that it
                            is due to the prevailing condition of the market and its restricted
                            resources. Nevertheless it would be a tragic matter if these damaged
                            foodstuffs, so far from bringing relief, were to aggravate the health of
                            the Greek population, whose systems are already enduring such a
                            strain.</p>
                        <p>“It should be noted that our requests for foodstuffs other than wheat are
                            extremely modest. We have given express instructions to our Embassy at
                            Washington to concentrate all their efforts on securing the despatch of
                            pulses and, indeed, that any such despatch should entail a proportionate
                            reduction in the shipments of wheat; in this way additional transport
                            facilities would not be required. It is necessary to stress the fact
                            that the available stocks of pulses in Turkey are exhausted, and that
                            every attempt at obtaining these articles from other countries in the
                            Middle East has met with an absolute refusal on the part of the blockade
                            authorities. Pulses however as well as an adequate quantity of milk or
                            milk products for the salvation of the imperilled children, must be
                            considered, from a purely humanitarian point of view, as indispensable
                            for even an elementary relief of the sufferings of the Greek population.
                            If wheat alone is available without the above vital nourishment, it is
                            to be feared that we shall have to face new tragedies.</p>
                        <p>“We address to you, Mr. Ambassador, a fervent request that you be so good
                            as to communicate the above facts to your Government at your earliest
                            convenience. We are making a similar request to the British Government
                            since, as you state in your letter No. 67, the latter is in touch with
                            the Department of State, respecting this matter.</p>
                        <p>“It is our firm conviction that the American Government which has always
                            shown so lively and deep a concern for the suffering population of
                            Greece, will on this occasion also take the necessary steps to ensure a
                            regular and unhampered shipment to Greece of a minimum quantity of the
                            foodstuffs necessary for the bare maintenance of life among the
                            population.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Not repeated to Ankara. [Biddle.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
