<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Notes of a Meeting Held at President Wilson’s House in the Place des
                    Etats-Unis, Paris, on Friday, June 6, 1919, at 11 a.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-06-06T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-06-06T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85065851"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Industrial development</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-06-06T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-06-06T05:00:00-05:00" n="27"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d27">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 180.03401/49½</note>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">CF–49A</note>
                <head>Notes of a Meeting Held at President Wilson’s House in the Place des
                    Etats-Unis, Paris, on Friday, June 6, 1919, at 11 a.m.</head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1919-06-06T11:00:00+01:00">June 6, 1919, 11 a.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Present</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States of America</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>President Wilson.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">British Empire</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>The Rt. Hon. D. Lloyd George, M. P.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">France</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>M. Clemenceau.</item>
                                    <item>Sir Maurice Hankey, K. C. B., <hi rend="italic"
                                            >Secretary</hi>.</item>
                                    <item>Prof. P. J. Mantoux, <hi rend="italic">Interpreter.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>1. <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> said he had arranged to send General
                    Hallier to Carinthia. He asked what his mission would be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> said merely to be present when the
                    Armistice was patched up between the Austrians and the Jugoslavs. <seg
                        type="margin">Carinthia: Armistice</seg>
                </p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> handed to Sir Maurice Hankey the first
                    part of a reply from Admiral Koltchak, to be translated and circulated. <seg
                        type="margin">Russian Policy: Koltchak’s Answer</seg>
                </p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> said he had received a letter from
                    M. Orlando, in the sense that, in the course of his conversation with the
                    President, M. Orlando had assumed that M. Tardieu’s proposal did not exclude
                    Italy from advising what frontiers it considered to be advisable and fair for
                    the new State of Fiume to have. This, of course, was an impossible proposal. He
                    himself had understood M. Orlando to say that he assumed that the map did not
                    show the final drawing of the frontier in detail and had thought he only
                    referred to the establishment of the details of the boundaries by the Boundary
                    Commission, or some body of that kind. He had never thought he had alluded to
                    serious changes in the boundaries. This showed the inconvenience of having to
                    work through an interpreter. Earlier in the discussions when his colleagues of
                    the American Delegation had met the Jugo-Slavs to put the Tardieu proposal to
                    them, M. Orlando had come and said that it would ease the situation if Fiume
                    were made an independent city. President Wilson had replied that in that case
                    there was no object in having a Free State. M. Orlando’s only argument had been
                    that it would make it easier with public opinion in Italy. He only mentioned
                    this to show that at <pb facs="0223" n="211" xml:id="pg_211"/> present there was
                    apparently nothing fixed in M. Orlando’s mind, which was quite fluid on the
                    subject. <seg type="margin">Italian Claims</seg>
                </p>
                <p>President Wilson then produced a map<note n="1" xml:id="d27fn1">No map
                        accompanies the minutes.</note> showing the Jugo-Slav counter-proposals to
                    the Tardieu scheme, which are described in the attached memorandum (Appendix
                    I).</p>
                <p>He said that this proposal by the Jugo-Slavs was in line with the other
                    settlements made in the Treaty of Peace, whereas the Italian proposals were not.
                    M. Orlando, he continued, in the course of subsequent conversation, insisted
                    that the junction of Assling must go to Italy. He then produced an Italian
                    ethnographical map prepared by the Italian expert Marinelli(?) before the war.
                    According to this map the Southern portion of Cherso and one spot on the island
                    of Veglia were Italian. The island of Lussin was entirely Italian. This was a
                    non-partisan map, prepared before the present war. He personally was of opinion
                    that the Jugo-Slav proposal seemed fair. He had been much impressed on the
                    previous day of a Slovene Delegation that had come to see him on the subject of
                    Klagenfurt. They had pointed out that in former days, in spite of the oppression
                    of Austrian rule, nevertheless the Slovene population had succeeded in
                    maintaining itself as a unit. Now it was to be divided relatively into small
                    pieces. Those Slovenes who lived on the western side of the Italian Alps were
                    coming under Italian rule. This they had realised was unavoidable. Then an
                    additional number in the Tarvis region were placed under Italian rule. Further
                    to the north a pocket of Slovenes was placed under Austrian rule. And now they
                    said it was to be debated as to whether Klagenfurt was to be under Austrian
                    rule. He had explained what was proposed about Klagenfurt, and thought they were
                    satisfied on that point. Nevertheless, he had been touched by their humility.
                    Their attitude made him feel that the liberation of the Jugo-Slavs must be a
                    real liberation. What Italy really cared for was not the islands but only
                    Fiume.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> thought that the Adriatic coast was
                    of real military importance to Italy. During the war they had only been able to
                    run the railway along the eastern coast of Italy for military purposes, and with
                    the risks that soldiers always had to run. Civilian traffic had practically been
                    brought to a standstill, because the Austrian Navy, though inferior to the
                    Italian, was able to send fast vessels across to make raids on the coast.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> said the Italians were not afraid of
                    the Jugo-Slav fleet. What they were afraid of was that Jugo-Slavia might form an
                    alliance with a Naval Power. The only possible Naval Powers were France and
                    Great Britain.</p>
                <pb facs="0224" n="212" xml:id="pg_212"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> said there was one Power which was
                    constantly overlooked in this Conference, namely, Russia. At the moment it had
                    gone to pieces but in five years who could tell what it would be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> suggested that Russia would be
                    bottled up, owing to the fact that some other Power would hold the straits of
                    the Bosphorus and the Dardanelles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> said that France was most afraid of
                    the Teuton, but his view was that the Teuton was largely done for. The nation he
                    feared was the Slav, which was an incalculable factor, capable of following the
                    instructions of a dictator or becoming Bolshevik. If some powerful, capable,
                    ambitious man arose in Russia the Slav race might become a great danger.
                    Moreover, there was a very close feeling between Russia and the Southern Slavs.
                    Serbia had always been treated as a younger brother by Russia. If he were
                    Italian he would feel much happier if the islands in the Adriatic were not Slav.
                    He thought this was a factor that ought to be taken into account.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> agreed that all arguments ought to be
                    taken into account. The Slavs, however, had nowhere shown the organisation that
                    made the Teuton so dangerous. The German had been the best trained instrument
                    that the world had ever seen for carrying out German policy. Behind it all was a
                    full generation of thorough education. Russia could not get that for years and
                    years. He himself had been trained with people who had had their training in
                    Germany. They had re-visited Germany and had been horrified. They had found that
                    the old intellectual freedom of the German University was gone. There had been a
                    systematic direction of the whole education of the country, down to the primary
                    schools always inculcating and promoting the policy which was aimed at. They had
                    even gone to the length of teaching false facts in the schools. If Russia were
                    ever to get an educational system comparable to that of Germany and should
                    impregnate the whole country as Germany had done with Slav ambitions, she might
                    become very dangerous. At present, however, Russia was entirely illiterate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> pointed out that Napoleon, with an
                    illiterate population had marched to every capital in Europe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> said also that a great industrial
                    development was necessary for the creation of a native-built fleet. We knew that
                    Russia could not place orders for any great naval development in Western
                    countries. The United States had had a great development of mercantile
                    ship-building during the war, and was full up with orders for years to come.
                    Russia was not developed as a shipbuilding country, and the development could
                    not take place within a generation. The central fact was that the population of
                    mujiks was so <pb facs="0225" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/> ignorant that
                    communications to it could only be made by word of mouth. The United States had
                    sent out Y. M. C. A. men as propagandists, the only effective means of
                    propaganda being pictures and conversations through interpreters. He thought it
                    would be necessary to watch the development of the Russian people very
                    carefully. But it would be a mistake to assume this possible development as the
                    basis of the present treaty, and this would only cause exasperation with the
                    Slavs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> said he was satisfied that the
                    transfer of the islands contemplated in the Treaty of London to Italy would not
                    involve the transfer of any large population. The only danger to Italy was that
                    these islands and ports might become nests for submarines. Russia was not in the
                    League of Nations, and there was no control over her. He recalled that twice
                    within modern times Great Britain had been in danger of war with Russia, first
                    in Lord Beaconsfield’s time—but, of course, he was very Turcophile—and later
                    when Gladstone was Prime Minister. In spite of the fact that Mr. Gladstone was
                    very pro-Russian, the Penjdeh incident had almost brought on war, and Mr.
                    Gladstone had had to go to the House of Commons for a vote of credit. This
                    showed the danger of Russia, when in the hands of dangerous bureaucrats. Now new
                    great Slav States were being created, and Russia might eventually dominate 160
                    millions of people. If Koltchak got to Moscow this year, the situation might
                    even begin to develop. The Teutons had at best 70,000,000. He hoped that the
                    danger which M. Clemenceau had mentioned on the previous day would not be
                    under-estimated, namely that the organising ability of the Teutons would be
                    brought to re-organise Russia. Nothing in the Treaty could stop this. In Germany
                    there were hundreds of thousands of men trained for war and nothing else, for
                    whom in the collapse of German industry it would be difficult to find anything
                    to do. These people would seek employment in Russia and with the Teutonic gift
                    of organisation behind her Russia might become very formidable. This was why
                    Italy had reason to apprehend the proximity of great Slav States. Bigger things
                    than these Islands were being given away.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> said not for strategic reasons. Even
                    in the case of the Alps the reason was not strategic. A great barrier like the
                    Alps forced a certain economic unity. He recalled that the Council had spent
                    hours in arguments in favour of giving the Rhine as a frontier of France, and
                    from the strategic point of view the various arguments of Marshal Foch were
                    unanswerable, but at one time he recalled that M. Clemenceau had wanted to
                    create a buffer state for strategic reasons between Germany and France. But when
                    he came to view the whole situation after talking it over with <pb facs="0226"
                        n="214" xml:id="pg_214"/> his colleagues M. Clemenceau had agreed that this
                    would not be consistent with the principles on which peace was being made. When
                    in this much more important case to France, strategic principles had been cast
                    aside, how could the principles be applied in a different way now?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> said that it only involved a very
                    small transfer of population. In reply to M. Clemenceau he said he was in favour
                    of the Tardieu proposal. This got over a difficulty in which France and Great
                    Britain were as regards the Treaty of London.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> said that the moment M. Orlando
                    refused to give Fiume to the Jugo-Slavs, they were free of the Treaty of London.
                    He said that the Jugo-Slavs urged that if strategical considerations applied for
                    Italy, they applied equally for Jugo-Slavia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> pointed out that they did not apply
                    to the same extent. In the present war a possibility had been carefully studied
                    of entering Austria from the Adriatic, but it had not been found possible to do
                    so, even from Ragusa where there was some sort of a railway. The country was too
                    steep and difficult.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> pointed out that if the Italians were
                    given the Island of Cherso, the Jugo-Slavs contended that it would bottle up
                    Fiume. The Italian commercial interests of Trieste were determined to stifle
                    Fiume and that was the basis of the argument for the Assling Junction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> urged the importance of a settlement,
                    as M. Orlando had to go back to Italy next week. If some settlement could not be
                    reached it was doubtful if he could remain in office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> asked if any figures were available as
                    to the population of the Islands.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> produced a map which gave the
                    population of Cherso as, Italian 2,200; Jugo-Slav 5816. As regards Sebenico the
                    town contained 858 Italians and 9031 Jugo-Slavs, while the judicial district
                    contained 873 Italians and 36,177 Jugo-Slavs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> said he was willing to give Zara to the
                    Islands [<hi rend="italic">Italians</hi>], but he would object to Sebenico. He
                    thought if this plan were adopted both sides would be satisfied. Sebenico
                    should, of course, go to the Slavs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> suggested that Sebenico should be
                    Slav and that Zara should be a free city represented in its foreign relations by
                    Italy. The Italians spoke vaguely of a hinterland for Zara.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> said he would not give any
                    hinterland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> said he would not either.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> urged the importance of insisting on
                    free and un discriminating access by railway to the port of Fiume on the same
                    terms for all the countries concerned. He was afraid attempts might be made to
                    colonise the state of Fiume with other nations.</p>
                <pb facs="0227" n="215" xml:id="pg_215"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> said that the Jugo-Slav population
                    said that this would be impossible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> said that the Italians were insisting
                    on what was called the <hi rend="italic">corpus separatum</hi> for the town of
                    Fiume. As far as he could learn the Italian majority in Fiume was not an
                    influencial majority. The Italians consisted of small shopkeepers, and the rank
                    and file of the population, whilst the big interests, including the bank and
                    shipping interests were Jugo-Slav. M. Trumbitch had given him information to
                    this effect, which was confirmed from independent sources.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> urged that it was important not to
                    cripple the development of the new state. If the result of the creation of the
                    new state was a great increase in business, the Italians might refuse to carry
                    out the necessary technical works, such as the provision of wharfs and
                    cranes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> said the most important thing was to
                    lengthen the existing mole. It already ran out into 100 feet of water, and
                    consequently it was a big work to extend it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> said this showed Fiume was a bad
                    port. Buccari seemed more promising, and he thought the Jugo-Slavs could
                    probably make a port there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> said the difficulty there was that
                    the mountains were so steep that the terminus of the railway would actually have
                    to be hewn out of the rock. It was a choice between the construction of the very
                    difficult breakwaters of Fiume and elaborate tunnels and railway works at
                    Buccari.</p>
                <p>(President Wilson undertook to draft iu general terms proposals based on the
                    discussion of that morning which he would communicate to Experts to formulate in
                    more precise terms. His proposals would include the creation of a free state in
                    Fiume commencing in the north from the point where the line of the Treaty of
                    London joined the American line, and extending the Tardieu line so as to include
                    the islands of Cherso as well as Veglia.)</p>
                <p>[4.] <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> read a telegram from the British
                    High Commissioner at Constantinople, of which a paraphrase is attached (Appendix
                    II). This telegram pointed out that the French High Commissioner when
                    communicating, as instructed by M. Clemenceau, on behalf of the Council of the
                    Principal Allied and Associated Powers, their acceptance of the Grand Vizier’s
                    proposal to come to Paris, conveyed the impression that this was done as a
                    result of his own representations and those of the French Government. And
                    further, that it had been followed up by a special message from the President of
                    the Republic to the Crown Prince of Turkey forwarded by M. Pichon conveying the
                    same impression. <seg type="margin">Turkey: Visit of the Grand Vizier</seg>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0228" n="216" xml:id="pg_216"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> recalled his own share in the
                    transaction. He was first told that the Turks wished to come to Paris. He had
                    given instructions that the French High Commissioner was to be instructed not to
                    discourage them. Then he brought the Despatch to the Council and Mr. Lloyd
                    George had drafted an answer which had been agreed to.</p>
                <p>M. Pichon had sounded him as to whether he should take the attitude that the
                    French were in favour of it. He had told M. Pichon that no special advantage was
                    to be taken of this by France. He asked Sir Maurice Hankey to give him a
                    paraphrase of the telegram, and he undertook to enquire into the matter.</p>
                <p>(The Meeting then adjourned.)</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Villa Majestic</hi>, <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-06-06">6 June,
                            1919</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Appendix I to CF–49A</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Mission to Negotiate Peace</hi>,<lb/>
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-06-04">4 June,
                                1919</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">To: The President.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">From: Douglas Johnson.<note n="2" xml:id="d27fn2">Maj.
                            Douglas W. Johnson, specialist on boundary geography, Division of
                            Territorial, Economic, and Political Intelligence, American Commission
                            to Negotiate Peace.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">re:</hi> Adriatic problem.</p>
                    <p>In a conversation held Monday afternoon, June 2nd, Mr. Trumbic<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d27fn3">Ante Trumbic, Jugoslav Minister for Foreign Affairs;
                            plenipotentiary to the Peace Conference.</note> informed me:</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>That he would renounce his claim to have portions of central Istria,
                            and part of the Pola-Trieste railway, included in the proposed free
                            state, and would accept the “American line” as the western boundary of
                            that state. Under no condition would he consent to having the island of
                            Cherso and the districts of Volosca and Albona, east of that line,
                            excluded from the free state.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>That he would insist on having Susak excluded from the free state; and
                            that only in the last extremity, in case it alone formed a stumbling
                            block to a solution, could he recede from his position that Veglia
                            should be excluded from the free state. This for the reason that in the
                            possible event that the free state voted for annexation to Italy,
                            Jugo-Slavia must have at least the remnant of a port at Susak and
                            protection in Veglia for an exit from that port for coastwise
                            trade.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>That Zara and Sebenico would be given the fullest measure of autonomy
                            desired, under Jugo-Slav sovereignty. But under no condition could he
                            admit Italian sovereignty over either state.</item>
                        <pb facs="0229" n="217" xml:id="pg_217"/>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>That he would accept either of the following solutions for the
                            islands: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Place all the islands claimed by Italy in the last compromise
                                    proposition (i. e. those marked pink)<note n="4" xml:id="d27fn4"
                                        >No map accompanies the minutes.</note> excepting Cherso,
                                    under the League of Nations, with provision for a plebiscite at
                                    the expiration of a reasonable period,—preferably three years,
                                    and not over five years,—the group to vote as a whole and not by
                                    islands separately.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Place the Lussin group and the Lissa group under the League of
                                    Nations without reserve, to be disposed of by the League of
                                    Nations when and how it deems wise and just.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Appendix II to CF–49A</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-06-04">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 4, 1919</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Telegram From the British High Commissioner at
                            Constantinople to His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign
                            Affairs</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>I only received on June 3rd in the evening your telegram of the previous day,
                        whereas my French colleague appears to have received the corresponding
                        telegram addressed to him as early as June 1st.</p>
                    <p>As I have already reported, he communicated its contents at once. This he did
                        personally and alone to the Grand Vizier. Later on, he published in the
                        Press a statement to the effect that the steps which he had taken had been
                        the cause of permission being granted. He insisted on doing this in spite of
                        my protests. His organ in the Press, commenting on his communication to the
                        Grand Vizier, expressed pride that, at the time of Turkey’s greatest
                        misfortune, it should be France who had extended a helping hand towards her.
                        The Paper observed that it had often emphasised the community of interests
                        between Turkey and France and their ancient relations of friendship, and
                        affirmed that France had never failed to manifest generous sentiments
                        towards Turkey. It bade Turkey to be of good cheer, since France was
                        incapable of betraying her high traditions.</p>
                    <p>The newspapers this morning, moreover, publish the reply of the French
                        Minister of Foreign Affairs to a telegram addressed by the Turkish Crown
                        Prince to the President of the French Republic, in which Turkey’s friendship
                        for France is asserted. In his message Mr. Pichon instructs my colleague to
                        thank the Crown Prince for his telegram and to assure His Imperial Highness
                        that France will neglect nothing which can further Turkey’s interests and
                        that she will be true to her traditions.</p>
                    <p>This message shows that the French Government itself, and not merely its
                        representatives here, has left its place on the united front <pb facs="0230"
                            n="218" xml:id="pg_218"/> which the Powers have hitherto presented to
                        Turkey, and has inaugurated a return to the old system of frantic
                        competition for Turkish favours, whereas, till the Supreme Allied Council at
                        Paris has pronounced its verdict, that front should undoubtedly be
                        maintained intact. I therefore regard Mr. Pichon’s message as a step of
                        utmost gravity and one profoundly regrettable from every point of view.</p>
                    <p>My French colleague has, moreover, mobilised all the agents, and is employing
                        all the means, at his disposal to start on these lines a campaign of
                        propaganda which he is no longer at any pains to conceal.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
