<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1986-01-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1986-01-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="125" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d125">
                        <head>125. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs (Poindexter) to President Reagan<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d125fn1">Source: National Security Council, National
                                Security Council Institutional Files, Box SR 092, NSDD 206. Secret.
                                Sent for action. Prepared by Wright. Reagan wrote his initials in
                                the upper right-hand corner of the memorandum.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1986-01-13">January 13, 1986</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Instructions for Round IV—Nuclear and Space Talks (<gloss target="#t_NST_1">NST</gloss>)</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Our negotiators will be returning to Geneva this weekend to begin Round
                            IV of the talks on January 16 covering <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> and Defense and
                            Space. Recall that just before your summit and at the end of Round III,
                            the U.S. provided a detailed counter-proposal involving the principle of
                            50 percent reductions. The Soviet delegation has not had the chance to
                            really address our proposals yet. Our task during this upcoming round
                            will be to focus on the areas where we have the most common ground
                                (<gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> reductions) and press the Soviets for
                            an early, constructive response to our new proposals.</p>
                        <p>With regard to Defense and Space we will concentrate on the
                            offense/defense relationship and explain the nature of <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> and your open laboratories initiative.
                            The instructions to this delegation contain the main points which you
                            have used personally with General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MSGorbachev_1">Gorbachev</persName> on <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss>. These have been drawn from both the
                            dialogue in Geneva and your subsequent letters and are provided for the
                            delegations’ information at <hi rend="italic">Tab E</hi>.<note n="2" xml:id="d125fn2">Attached but not printed, at Tab E, are the draft
                                    <gloss target="#t_DST_1">DST</gloss> Instructions.</note></p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_SACG_1">SACG</gloss> has met on the individual
                            instruction cables at <hi rend="italic">Tabs B through E</hi>,<note n="3" xml:id="d125fn3">Attached but not printed, at Tabs B, C, and
                                D, are draft <gloss target="#t_NST_1">NST</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> Instructions.</note> and there are no outstanding
                            issues. I believe it is appropriate for you to issue an NSDD (<hi rend="italic">Tab A</hi>)<note n="4" xml:id="d125fn4">Printed below
                                as <ref target="#d126">Document 126</ref>.</note> to further
                            emphasize your involvement and desires for Round IV of the
                            negotiations.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendation</p>
                        <table cols="3">
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">OK</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">No</hi></cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>That you sign the draft NSDD at <hi rend="italic">Tab A</hi>
                                    approving the instructions for Round IV of the Nuclear and Space
                                        Talks.<note n="5" xml:id="d125fn5">Reagan initialed his
                                        approval.</note></cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>