<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1986-08-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1986-08-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="145" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d145">
                        <head>145. Memorandum From the Special Advisor to the President and
                            Secretary of State on Arms Control Matters (Nitze) to Secretary of State
                                Shultz<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d145fn1">Source: Department
                                of State, Lot 90D397, Ambassador Nitze’s Personal Files 1953,
                                1972–1989, Box 4, 1986 July–Aug. Secret.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1986-08-13">August 13, 1986</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Meeting with Secretary of Defense Weinberger On the Moscow Trip,
                                August 13, 1986</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I had an hour-long meeting with Secretary Weinberger. He was assisted by
                            Ikle, Gaffney and Hanmer.</p>
                        <p>Two principal issues in the discussion related to his interpretation of
                            the President’s letter<note n="2" xml:id="d145fn2">See <ref target="#d139fn2">footnote 2, Document 139</ref>.</note> versus
                            my reading of what the letter, in fact, says.</p>
                        <p>Weinberger envisages that the offer immediately to conclude an agreement
                            implies that that agreement will set up a regime beginning immediately
                            which would differ radically from the regime provided for by the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty; he thinks, this would promptly
                            open the door to testing and development going beyond that permitted by
                            the current <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty. I said that, as
                            I read that portion of the President’s letter, the contemplated
                            agreement including “a treaty now” was to deal with the situation which
                            would arise in the event the research program of either side reached a
                            point (after a minimum of five years) at which that side had come to the
                            conclusion that it wished to deploy an advanced <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> system; the contemplated treaty would obligate it to
                            initiate negotiations for an agreement covering such deployment
                            concurrent with an agreed program for the total elimination of ballistic
                            missiles.</p>
                        <p>I further pointed out that the U.S. space/defense proposal in the letter
                            was made contingent upon a concurrent agreement to begin radical and
                            stabilizing reductions immediately and was not contingent upon either
                            side’s <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> research program being
                            successful; it was for that reason I thought it essential that we
                            concentrate promptly on our preparatory work concerning the agreement on
                            the immediate reductions of offensive missiles and warheads.</p>
                        <p>There was a similar dispute between the two of us as to what was implied
                            by the President’s letter concerning “interim approach” to <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>. He asserted that any such interim
                            approach must include agreement <pb facs="0627" n="600" xml:id="pg_600"/> on an end point of zero/zero globally and a step-by-step program to
                            attain that end point; in that context Cap claimed that “interim <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> approach” referred to the initial
                            steps of a program, all steps of which would have been agreed upon. I
                            said I interpreted the word “interim” to imply that both sides would
                            have stated an end objective of total elimination of <gloss target="#t_LRINF_1">LRINF</gloss> missiles, but that the “interim
                            approach” would deal only with the initial one or a few stages of
                            reductions without requiring agreement on the specifics of the final
                            step or steps to zero.</p>
                        <p>Otherwise our meeting was warm and friendly. Weinberger said that he had
                            received a very favorable report from Perle<note n="3" xml:id="d145fn3">Not found.</note> on the conduct of the Moscow meeting.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>