<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1986-12-05T11:08:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1986-12-05T11:08:00-05:00" n="175" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d175">
                        <head>175. Telegram From the Delegation to the Nuclear and Space Talks in
                            Geneva to the Department of State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d175fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Foreign Policy
                                File, N860011–0350. Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_NODIS_1">Nodis</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1986-12-05T16:08:00+00:00">December 5, 1986, 1608<gloss target="#t_Z_1">Z</gloss></date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>11159. Subject: Need for <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> and
                                <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> draft treaties</p>
                        <p>1. Secret—Entire text.</p>
                        <p>2. We strongly recommend that Washington complete work on a draft <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> treaty for tabling during the next
                                <gloss target="#t_NST_1">NST</gloss> round in Geneva and a draft
                                <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> treaty.</p>
                        <p>3. There are several reasons for this recommendation. First, tabling
                            these treaties would give the U.S. the high ground in the Geneva talks.
                            As the Soviets have revealed again, in their approach to the special
                                <gloss target="#t_NST_1">NST</gloss> meeting this week and in their
                            high-level barnstorming around Europe, their primary objective is to
                            portray <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> as the sole obstacle to
                            nuclear arms reductions and the U.S. as retreating from the results of
                            Reykjavik. Tabling draft <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> treaties in Geneva would provide
                            convincing evidence that it is the U.S., not the Soviet Union, which is
                            attempting to translate the results of Reykjavik into actual <pb facs="0804" n="777" xml:id="pg_777"/> accords. Washington should
                            also bear in mind that the Soviets may try to preempt us by early
                            tabling of their own draft, perhaps a single document covering all three
                            areas designed to tighten linkage.</p>
                        <p>4. Second, as administration spokesmen have now said publicly, we are
                            running out of time. These treaties, if they are to be sound, durable
                            and ratifiable—and effective in helping to avoid future disputes over
                            compliance—must be carefully negotiated in Geneva. This will take time,
                            especially to work out the modalities for effective verification. It is
                            hard to imagine, for example, that the draft <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> treaty under preparation, especially given its multiple
                            verification annexes, could take any less than a year to negotiate in
                            Geneva even if the Soviets engaged actively. The longer we wait to table
                            our verification proposals, the more we will play into the customary
                            Soviet tactic of trying to delay discussion of verification until the
                            end and dealing with verification measures only in vague generalities.
                            The longer we wait to table our treaties, given the new public
                            commentary on the timing question, the less we will be seen as
                            negotiating credibly.</p>
                        <p>5. Finally, we need to pin the Soviets down. Since the opening of <gloss target="#t_NST_1">NST</gloss> in March 1985, the Soviets have zigged
                            and zagged and, as the December 2–5 meeting just illustrated, may now be
                            trying either to slip away from some of their Reykjavik commitments or
                            to sell them twice. A draft treaty would be a highly useful negotiating
                            tool in explaining precisely what the U.S. envisages in an agreement and
                            in pressuring the Soviets to move from abstract principles to concrete
                            provisions.</p>
                        <p>6. The Soviets are the demandeur in the <gloss target="#t_DS_1">D&amp;S</gloss> area, and only if they move toward accepting the
                            framework proposed by the President at Reykjavik do we see any value in
                            tabling a <gloss target="#t_DS_1">D&amp;S</gloss> treaty. It will,
                            however, be useful to table a draft <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> treaty before a draft <gloss target="#t_DS_1">D&amp;S</gloss> treaty, thus, reinforcing the U.S. position that a
                                <gloss target="#t_DS_1">D&amp;S</gloss> agreement shall not enter
                            into force before the entry into force of a <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> agreement. By this same logic, if there is to be any
                            hope of achieving a <gloss target="#t_DS_1">D&amp;S</gloss> agreement by
                            1988 reflecting the President’s concept of the offense-defense
                            relationship, the U.S. needs to get a draft <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> agreement on the table by the spring of 1987.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_MMKampelman_1"><hi rend="strong">Kampelman</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>