<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1987-06-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1987-06-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="198" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d198">
                        <head>198. Memorandum From the Special Advisor to the President and
                            Secretary of State on Arms Control Matters (Nitze) and the Special
                            Assistant to the Deputy Secretary of State (Timbie) to Secretary of
                            State Shultz<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d198fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Bureau of Arms Control and Disarmament, Lot
                                01D127, 1969–1990 Subject Records of James P. Timbie, Box 1, <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> 1987. Secret. Drafted by Timbie; cleared by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HAHolmes_1">Holmes</persName> and Burton.
                                Timbie initialed the memorandum on Nitze’s behalf. A stamped
                                notation indicates that Shultz saw the memorandum.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rend="right" rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1987-06-27">June 27, 1987</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> in Your Meeting with
                                    Shevardnadze<note n="2" xml:id="d198fn2">Shevardnadze visited
                                    Washington for talks with Reagan, Shultz, and other U.S.
                                    officials from September 15–17. See <ref target="#d210">Document
                                        210</ref>. The memoranda of conversation are printed in <ref target="frus1981-88v06#d66"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. VI, Soviet Union,
                                        October 1986–January 1989, Documents 66</ref>–<ref target="frus1981-88v06#d74">72</ref>, <ref target="frus1981-88v06#d74">74</ref>–<ref target="frus1981-88v06#d76">76</ref>.</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Having made considerable progress in <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>, it is worth a serious effort at the Foreign Ministers
                            meeting to revive <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>, both because
                            this is indeed the “root problem” and because it will be much easier to
                            make the case for <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> if there is an
                            agreement or a reasonable prospect for agreement in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>. Our leverage is not likely to be
                            greater in the future than it is today.</p>
                        <p>We had a similar objective for the April meeting, but accomplished very
                            little. At that time, we made the best arguments for our current
                            position. To be more successful now, we will need a different
                            approach.</p>
                        <pb facs="0896" n="869" xml:id="pg_869"/>
                        <p>Our suggestion is to try to engage on some of the issues of interest to
                            the Soviets that we have been saving for the endgame, if the Soviets are
                            prepared to engage on issues of interest to us. Specifically, you could
                            tell Shevardnadze early in the meeting that you are prepared to discuss
                            and resolve issues they have raised—<gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCMs</gloss> and mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBMs</gloss>—if
                            they are prepared to discuss and resolve issues of interest to
                            us—sublimits and throw weight. If Shevardnadze is interested, discussion
                            of their subjects and our subjects could proceed in parallel.</p>
                        <p>If we could get such a negotiation going, we would push for an outcome
                            along the following lines:</p>
                        <quote><p>—4800 ballistic missile warheads</p>
                            <p>—3600 <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> warheads<note n="3" xml:id="d198fn3">Shultz drew a horizontal line from this point
                                    to the right-hand margin and wrote: “could we live w/o this
                                    sublimit so we don’t get into the <gloss target="#t_SLBM_1">SLBM</gloss> question?” A typed note on the memorandum
                                    dates Shultz’s comment as June 29.</note></p>
                            <p>—1500 heavy <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> warheads</p>
                            <p>—Missile throw weight 50% below the current Soviet level</p>
                            <p>—Mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBMs</gloss> (and other survivable
                                    <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> basing modes) permitted
                                subject to numerical and verification constraints</p>
                            <p>—Declarations by both sides of their deployment plans for long-range
                                nuclear-armed <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCMs</gloss></p>
                            <p>—All of this to be implemented over seven years (e.g., by
                            1995).</p></quote>
                        <p>If the Soviets have not given up on <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> or closed their minds to sublimits, an outcome along
                            these lines may be possible. There would appear to be little to lose in
                            trying.</p>
                        <p>While such an outcome would receive broad support as achieving our
                            primary objectives at little cost, there will be opposition on both
                            substance and timing. We would need authority to permit mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBMs</gloss>, settle the <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss> question on the basis of
                            declarations, and drop the 1650 sublimit in favor of the Soviet proposal
                            to cut heavy <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBMs</gloss> by 50%.</p>
                        <p>We can anticipate that Shevardnadze will probably counter by proposing to
                            expand the discussion to include a sublimit on <gloss target="#t_SLBM_1">SLBM</gloss> warheads and to include linkage to defense and space.
                            The package could be expanded to deal with these issues in ways that
                            serve our interests, and this would also require new authority. Applying
                            a 3600 sublimit to <gloss target="#t_SLBM_1">SLBM</gloss> warheads as
                            well as to <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> warheads would permit
                                <gloss target="#t_SLBM_1">SLBM</gloss> warheads to comprise ¾ of our
                            ballistic missile force, a slightly larger fraction than in our present
                            force. Such a limit should be acceptable to the United States, but we
                            know from experience that the <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss>
                            opposes such a sublimit on grounds that we should keep open the option
                            to deploy most of our warheads in a survivable sea-based mode as a hedge
                            against inability to deploy survivable <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBMs</gloss>. With regard <pb facs="0897" n="870" xml:id="pg_870"/> to linkage to defense and space, Shevardnadze will probably want to
                            add a provision in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> permitting a
                            side to terminate the reductions agreement if the other side breaks out
                            of the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty.<note n="4" xml:id="d198fn4">Shultz underlined “a provision in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> permitting a side to terminate
                                the reductions agreement if the other side breaks out of the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty” and wrote in the
                                right-hand margin: “elaborate as in your other memos.” A typed note
                                on the memorandum dates Shultz’s comment as June 29. The reference
                                to Nitze’s and Timbie’s other memoranda is not further
                                identified.</note> Since in this situation a party could invoke the
                            supreme interest withdrawal clause in any event, such an explicit
                            provision would actually add little. However, we can anticipate
                            opposition on this point as well.</p>
                        <p>We and Max and Ron tried to get comparable ideas approved for use with
                            Shevardnadze in April, with very modest success. This implies we should
                            try a different approach now. One idea would be to put our
                            recommendations together as a package, and try to get the President to
                            make an up or down decision on the package. If you concur, we can work
                            with <gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_PM_1">PM</gloss> to assemble a package which you could brief to the
                            President and Max and Paul could brief to Howard Baker and <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Frank Carlucci</persName>. The White
                            House needs to appreciate the advantages of a <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> agreement to accompany or closely follow <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>, so they are prepared to make a
                            serious effort to get one.</p>
                        <p>There is no need for detailed interagency staffing of these ideas; none
                            of them is novel. Ideally, the President could call a meeting on our
                            package with you, Cap, <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>, and perhaps Webster and then give you
                            guidance. We can exploit our home court advantage, and not try to
                            anticipate every move with contingency guidance. You can report as the
                            talks progress, and get further guidance as necessary.</p>
                        <p>We would like to meet with you, Max, Roz, and Allen to discuss these
                            ideas further.<note n="5" xml:id="d198fn5">In a June 29 note affixed to
                                the memorandum, Shultz wrote: “I favor trying to get ourselves in a
                                position to do this.” (Department of State, Bureau of Arms Control
                                and Disarmament, Lot 01D127, 1969–1990 Subject Records of James P.
                                Timbie, Box 1, <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> 1987)</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>