<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1987-12-04T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1987-12-04T14:00:00-05:00" n="239" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d239">
                        <head>239. Minutes of a National Security Planning Group Meeting<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d239fn1">Source: Reagan Library, Executive
                                Secretariat: National Security Planning Group (NSPG) Records, NSPG
                                171 12/24/1987. Secret. The meeting took place in the Situation
                                Room. All brackets are in the original.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1987-12-04T14:00:00-05:00" to="1987-12-04T15:00:00-05:00">December 4, 1987, 2–3 p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Arms Control Preparations for the Summit (U)</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">The President</hi></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">State</hi></head>
                                    <item>Secretary George Shultz</item>
                                    <item>Ambassador Paul Nitze</item>
                                    <item>Ambassador Edward Rowny</item>
                                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MMKampelman_1">Max
                                            Kampelman</persName></item>
                                    <item>Ms. Rozanne Ridgeway</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Treasury</hi></head>
                                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_JABaker3_1">James
                                            Baker</persName></item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Defense</hi></head>
                                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Frank
                                            Carlucci</persName></item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RLehman_1">Ron
                                        Lehman</persName></item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Energy</hi></head>
                                    <item>Mr William Martin</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss></hi></head>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RMGates_1">Robert
                                            Gates</persName></item>
                                    <item>Dr. Jay Castillo</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss></hi></head>
                                    <item>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">William
                                            Crowe</persName></item>
                                    <item><gloss target="#t_VADM_1">VADM</gloss>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_JTHowe_1">Jonathan
                                        Howe</persName></item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_ACDA_1">ACDA</gloss></hi></head>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KAdelman_1">Kenneth
                                            Adelman</persName></item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Vice President’s Office</hi></head>
                                    <item>Mr. Craig Fuller</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss></hi></head>
                                    <item>Mr. James Miller</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">OSTP</hi></head>
                                    <item>Dr. William Graham</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">White House</hi></head>
                                    <item>Mr. Howard Baker</item>
                                    <item>Mr. Ken Duberstein</item>
                                    <item>Mr. Marlin Fitzwater</item>
                                    <item>General Colin Powell</item>
                                    <item>Mr. John Negroponte</item>
                                    <item>Colonel <persName corresp="#p_RLinhard_1">Robert
                                            Linhard</persName></item>
                                    <item>Captain Linton Brooks</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="1067" n="1040" xml:id="pg_1040"/>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi></p>
                        <p>The NSPG meeting, December 4, opened at 2:00 p.m. <hi rend="italic">General Powell</hi> opened the meeting: We are here for a final
                            review of some aspects of our arms reductions positions before the
                            summit. Mr. President, would you care to make any initial remarks before
                            we begin?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">The President:</hi> Used his Talking Points (attached
                            at <hi rend="italic">Tab A</hi>),<note n="2" xml:id="d239fn2">Attached
                                but not printed. See Tab C, <ref target="#d238">Document
                                238</ref>.</note> interrupting them to say: Our people will learn
                            from the summit. In a Wirthlin poll only 50% supported <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss>. Once they heard him [<persName corresp="#p_MSGorbachev_1">Gorbachev</persName>] on air, then 70%
                            say we ought to have <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss>.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell</hi> [Using his talking points at <hi rend="italic">Tab B</hi>]:<note n="3" xml:id="d239fn3">Attached but
                                not printed. See Tab II, <ref target="#d237">Document
                                237</ref>.</note> Thank you sir. We have a compartmented paper
                            you’ve all been provided to help structure the discussion. Lets first
                            turn to <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>. I want to walk through
                            the approach as I understand it. First we all need to be clear that this
                            is intended as a package. I know it’s important to the <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss> and others to view it that way; some
                            moves are only acceptable in the context of things like counting rules.
                            What we’ve done is set forth a paper that describes how <hi rend="italic">we</hi> want the joint statement at the end of the
                            summit to come out. Near the end of the meeting we’ll talk about tactics
                            to do this. (S)</p>
                        <p>We have general agreement on several points. If you look at the top of
                            the paper [NOTE: refers to <hi rend="italic">Tab C</hi>,<note n="4" xml:id="d239fn4">Attached but not printed. See Tab D, <ref target="#d238">Document 238</ref>.</note> distributed to each
                            participant] you will see an agreed a chapeau that makes it clear the
                            Joint Draft Treaty Text is agreed by both sides. We then agree and will
                            document in the Joint Statement:</p>
                        <quote><p>—1600 Strategic Nuclear Delivery Vehicles (Bombers, <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBMs</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SLBM_1">SLBMs</gloss>);</p>
                            <p>—6000 total “warheads” on these <gloss target="#t_SNDV_1">SNDVs</gloss></p>
                            <p>—Within the 6000, 1540 warheads on Soviet heavy <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBMs</gloss> (a 50% cut from current
                                levels); and</p>
                            <p>—A 50% cut in total Soviet ballistic missile throwweight.</p></quote>
                        <p>The introduction would reflect agreement . . . . (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> Where is the bomber counting
                            rule?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RLehman_1">Lehman</persName>:</hi> In the Joint Draft Text.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> It should go here. That rule is
                            very, very important to the Chiefs, and it needed to be added. We really
                            ought to deal with counting rules first in the order that we deal with
                            the Soviets. Ever since <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Bill
                                Crowe</persName> told me he’d kill for that rule, I want to add it
                            every chance I get. (S)</p>
                        <pb facs="1068" n="1041" xml:id="pg_1041"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi> [continuing]: Then we’d have
                            sections on the 4800 ballistic missile sublimit and our current position
                            of 3300 sublimit on <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBMs</gloss>. We’d have
                            an <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> counting rules (attribute 6
                                <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCMs</gloss> to each <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> carrying heavy bomber). It wouldn’t
                            be a limit on each bomber but a number we’d use to get an aggregate
                            limit. We’d have ballistic missile warhead counting rules for existing
                            missiles. We would agree on a number for each type, for example 8 for
                            the D–5. They could come to a submarine, pick a missile at random and
                            we’d lift the nose cone and show them the number. If it was more than 8
                            it would be a violation. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> We would declare a number, they would do
                            likewise. (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi> Would Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName> explain to the President
                            why this is important? (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> Yes, but first, I don’t see a discussion
                            of <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> range and <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> definitions in the presentation of
                            the counting rules. That’s important and needs to be added. (S)</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss> have looked at this and our
                            highest priority is counting rules. Predictability is important. The
                            Soviets want mobiles, Backfire, and <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>, but before we can deal with those, we need to focus
                            on the counting rules now including the <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> range and definition as the highest priority. If we
                            see that they will accept our position there, we can then move on
                            mobile, Backfire, and <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>, and other
                            items; but we need the counting rules first. The military sufficiency of
                            an agreement at 50% is very very close. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> This would be a good subject,
                            Mr. President, for you to raise with <persName corresp="#p_MSGorbachev_1">Gorbachev</persName> as an opening, but
                            for any detailed conversation, we ought to shift it to the Working
                            Groups under Ahkromeyev. (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> This may be a very difficult area for
                            the Soviets to agree. There will be a lot of give and take. (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_KAdelman_1">Ken
                                    Adelman</persName>:</hi> But we also have to recognize that it
                            will be more difficult to get counting rules for future systems. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> The Chiefs have done a lot of thinking
                            on verification which will help. The Air Force is ready to have the
                            Soviets look at <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCMs</gloss> to see if
                            they’re nuclear or non-nuclear. The Navy is ready to go as Colin Powell
                            described with respect to warhead numbers. These were painful decisions
                            for the services. The Chief of Staff of the Air Force said it wasn’t the
                            Soviets he knew were wandering around his bases he was worried about, it
                            was the ones he didn’t know about. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi> (Returned to his Talking Points,
                            and ran down through the verification items that were agreed, working
                            his way to the subject of mobiles and verification. After describing the
                            varying positions on mobiles and verification he asked for comments.)
                            (S)</p>
                        <pb facs="1069" n="1042" xml:id="pg_1042"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> We have to be very, very careful. If
                            we move now, we are going to undercut our own position because we have
                            insisted that the Soviets describe for us how they would verify mobiles;
                            the Soviets have not given anything on verification. In addition, if we
                            move now, we’re just not going to get anything for it. So it’s
                            premature. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> I’m inclined to agree with
                            Frank, but we could ask creative questions about verification. For
                            example, do you have in mind that we have a limited area? How would we
                            deploy? What are your views on verification? The Air Force Chief of
                            Staff, General Welch, scoffs at the idea of differentiating between
                            rail- and road-mobile missiles. He thinks that there is no significant
                            difference in distinguishing between road- and rail-mobile systems,
                            we’ve just had more experience with the road-mobile version. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> That’s exactly right; he believes that
                            you can verify rail as well as you can road. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> Therefore, maybe we could put
                            some ideas forward. We never get anything from the Soviets on any of
                            these technical areas; it’s always us who have to put the ideas forward.
                            (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> We are not opposed to that; the
                            question is what ideas. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RLehman_1">Lehman</persName>:</hi> We’ve asked them for ideas and just get
                            generalities. What we should do is ask them in Geneva for specific
                            Protocols on verification. We should ask them to give us draft
                            Protocols, and then if we can find something acceptable, we would be
                            willing to consider mobiles. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KAdelman_1">Adelman</persName>:</hi> I see rail- and road-mobiles as
                            different. My problem is we currently have a package on how we verify
                            road mobile missiles; we have no package for rail mobiles, and that’s
                            one big difference. And secondly, a little cheating goes an awful long
                            way when you’re talking about rail-mobiles, because if you’re a little
                            wrong with a missile that has 10 <gloss target="#t_RV_1">RVs</gloss>,
                            it’s a lot different than being a little wrong about a missile that has
                            only one <gloss target="#t_RV_1">RV</gloss>. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> You’re not claiming that road-mobiles
                            can be verified? (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KAdelman_1">Adelman</persName>:</hi> It was good enough for 100 SS–20s, but
                            of course, the rail situation is worse. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> We’ve always offered to discuss
                            verification, but once again, the Soviets never seem to offer technical
                            details; perhaps, we should move forward. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KAdelman_1">Adelman</persName>:</hi> Verification is our problem; the
                            Soviets can read about it in the Congressional Record. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> The Joint Chiefs have some suggestions.
                            We’re ready to suggest the rail garrison scheme. We could make some very
                                <pb facs="1070" n="1043" xml:id="pg_1043"/> constructive suggestions
                            here. Of course we don’t know if they’d accept. Our own rail scheme is
                            the <hi rend="italic">best</hi> of the two options in terms of mobility
                            in a fiscally constrained future. If we face fiscal constraints, there’s
                            more deterrence per pound per dollar in the <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss> than there is in the small mobile. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_JABaker3_1">James
                                    Baker</persName>:</hi> There’s no “if” about fiscal constraints;
                            they’re here. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> (Quietly) The small missile is dying
                            anyway. (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RMGates_1">Bob [Gates]</persName> what about
                            verification? That seems to be the issue. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RMGates_1">Gates</persName>:</hi> The hardest thing you can ask us to monitor
                            would be a limit on mobiles, but we can offer suggestions on things that
                            could help us quite a bit. For example, it would be interesting to know
                            how they would distinguish the SS–24’s that are rail mobile missiles
                            rather than those being produced with silos. In general, there are some
                            good things that could be done, and we need to explore this. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">The President:</hi> Well, tell me, suppose we had a
                            ban—our position—what if there were no mobile missiles? Could we <hi rend="italic">know</hi> that there really were not? I just keep
                            thinking what a vast country that is. (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> It would be easier to monitor if they
                            were banned, because if we found one, it would be a violation. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> Besides that, Mr. President, they just
                            can’t roam around out there forever; they need to bring them in sometime
                            for maintenance and for training, and the like. It would be very hard
                            for them to just hold them out in the field for all that time. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi> They also need to train and to
                            test and that we would be able to observe. (S)</p>
                        <p>I’d like to summarize up to this point. It seems like people are saying
                            that we should remain on our position, but in the Working Group, we
                            should be ready to explore verification options. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> A caveat; I don’t want to go off our
                            current position <hi rend="italic">unless</hi> we get something. (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Senator Baker</hi> (Chief of Staff): Well, what do you
                            have in mind, Frank? (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> I think we ought to get something in
                            the <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> area, and I’ll come back to
                            that later. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> We’re ready to move on mobiles, but <hi rend="italic">only</hi> if we get the items above the line; that
                            means agreement on counting rules and the like. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi> [Turning to “heavies,” read his
                            talking points on the “heavy” issue through the point where he asked for
                            agency views.]</p>
                        <pb facs="1071" n="1044" xml:id="pg_1044"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> It’s okay by us; we’re prepared to
                            make heavy modernization, provided we get the proper trade and don’t
                            just give them away. (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi> We can be sure the Soviets will
                            raise <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCMs</gloss> and Backfire. As I
                            understand it we all agree that we could offer an exchange of
                            declarations of nuclear <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss> forces.
                            At our last meeting in Geneva, Ahkromeyev laid down a marker that <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCMs</gloss> may be a show stopper for the
                            Soviets. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Ambassador Rowny:</hi> I think we ought to note that
                            Ahkromeyev said he has some new ideas on how to verify <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCMs</gloss>. Before we get involved in
                            unilateral declarations of our force structure, why don’t we call his
                            bluff and hear him out. I’m alone in this room; I think that <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss> limits can be verified. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> I agree; I think we ought to hear what
                            he has to say. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi> With respect to Backfire, if the
                            Soviets accept our position, some would exclude Backfire from the treaty
                            if there was no increase in numbers, it could not be refueled, and was
                            not equipped to carry <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCMs</gloss>. Opinions?
                            (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> Mr. President, what we’re talking
                            about is moving towards the Soviets in a number of areas. Once again, I
                            want to make sure if we do so, that we don’t do so and not get anything
                            for it. We need to get <hi rend="italic">some</hi> handle on the
                            Backfire issue and some handle on this motion, and I believe that there
                            needs to be a substantive linkage here—some trade for what we want in
                                <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss>. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KAdelman_1">Adelman</persName>:</hi> Mr. President, two points on the issue
                            of Backfire. First, this can really rattle the conservatives. (During an
                            earlier campaign, I wrote some language for you as then a candidate that
                            argued very strongly against <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II
                            based specifically on the Backfire issue). Ahkromeyev wants <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCMs</gloss>. Maybe the best thing we could do
                            is to wait and see if we can get something on <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss> and Backfire at the eleventh hour—push them both off
                            and handle it, perhaps, that way. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> We agree [to pushing both Backfire and
                                <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss> until the eleventh hour and
                            working something then]. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Senator Baker</hi> (Chief of Staff): Isn’t there a
                            verification problem here? (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KAdelman_1">Adelman</persName>:</hi> The Intelligence Community said
                            Backfire was strategic; now all agree it is not. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Senator Baker:</hi> It says that you’re not supposed to
                            have a refueling or <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>-carriage on
                            Backfires. Can we really verify <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>-carriage? (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Colonel <persName corresp="#p_RLinhard_1">Linhard</persName>:</hi> One point is that we have yet to see
                            an <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> tested from a Backfire.
                            (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. Castillo:</hi> Yes, we haven’t seen <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> testing. We believe that we would be
                            able to do so if they are tested. (S)</p>
                        <pb facs="1072" n="1045" xml:id="pg_1045"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Dr. Graham:</hi> Well, that’s one thing, but we can’t
                            really verify the refueling. They have the internal piping already, and
                            all they’ve done is to cover the refueling probes with a plate. They can
                            refuel in radio silence in the middle of the country, just like we do,
                            and we wouldn’t detect it. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> We don’t just refuel in the middle of
                            the country; we do it worldwide. But I do agree that it would be a
                            simple change for them to have refueling capability. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi> (Summarizing by making the
                            following points) I think I hear that we agree that the Chapeau is fine;
                            that Items “A” through “D”—that’s the sublimit issue, the <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> counting rules, ballistic counting
                            rules, and verification package—are okay, and that the additional
                            items—mobiles, <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss> forces, Backfire,
                            and heavy modernization—we have some reservations on until we see
                            whether we see Soviet movement described above. And Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName> has laid down a
                            marker on <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss>. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Ambassador Rowny:</hi> Before we leave <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>, I want to make sure that we agree
                            that we’re not going to give up on the 3300 sublimit on <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBMs</gloss> without getting something for it.
                            (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KAdelman_1">Adelman</persName>:</hi> Yes, yes, we are agreed that we’re
                            going to start with the counting rules, and that we won’t move beyond
                            our current position on sublimits unless we get some motion on counting
                            rules. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> Well, let’s keep Item A, which is the
                            sublimits item, out of the basic package. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Colonel <persName corresp="#p_RLinhard_1">Linhard</persName>:</hi> “A” is our current position. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> OK. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi> We push for that; we work the
                            counting rule problem; and only <hi rend="italic">after</hi> we have
                            ascertained whether we successfully have the counting rules, would we
                            come back to revisit the numbers of 4800 and 3300. [All agree on that
                            summary.] (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> The counting rules affect our
                            attitude toward the 3300 number. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi> Lets move to Defense and Space.
                            Here we have agreement on a chapeau paragraph that is consistent with
                            our current position. Our Defense and Space Negotiator, Hank <persName corresp="#p_HFCooper_1">Cooper</persName>, and Ed Rowny would make
                            no move beyond that paragraph lengthening the non-withdrawal period,
                            unless the Soviets concede to us a clear right to deploy after the
                            period. Other agencies believe that we need to make some concessions.
                            These are spelled out in the first two options. The first option would
                            extend the non-withdrawal period through 1996, return us to the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty after the period, and commit us
                            to negotiate on the distinction between permitted testing and prohibited
                            deployment. The second option would entail a non-<hi rend="italic">deployment</hi> commitment <pb facs="1073" n="1046" xml:id="pg_1046"/> through 1996, with a right to deploy thereafter,
                            and an agreed understanding of what constitutes prohibited deployment,
                            coupled with clear acknowledgement of our right to test under the broad
                            interpretation. There are some things common to both options; rather
                            than talk about them I want to talk about a third option which weaves
                            together elements of the first two. [refers to second page of handout at
                                <hi rend="italic">Tab C</hi>]. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> We ought to start with the idea
                            that we have agreement on some period of time, whatever that period is,
                            as a concept. I mean we agreed that there would be some period of time
                            where something will happen as a concept. The <hi rend="italic">big</hi>
                            question really is what can you do during that period of time. If you
                            have no one standing with the Soviets, you fall into the hands of the
                            Congress, and that’s a trap in which we give the Soviets the 50%
                            reductions, and then we are inhibited from doing what we want to do by
                            the Congress. So it’s important to get an understanding. The only thing
                            we’re interested in is testing. . . . (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> [Interrupts] And the right to deploy.
                            (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> Right. So what we want is an
                            agreement that tests aren’t deployment. A change from our earlier
                            position of an unstructured attempt to kick the can down the road. We
                            need to make it clear exactly what testing means and what deployment
                            means. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> I agree, an unstructured approach is
                            a very, very dangerous problem for us, but the third bullet on the third
                            option protects us. We can support this without any further discussion
                            of what’s broad and what’s narrow. We need a clean right to deploy after
                            the regime, and I have reservations on any idea of negotiating a
                            definition of testing and deployment. I prefer to just unilaterally tell
                            them what we mean by deployment. We need to work on that. If we got
                            Option 2 in the paper, I’d be ready to give an awful lot in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">The President:</hi> Well, okay, when might we be able
                            to deploy? I can’t remember how many times I’ve stood up and said “When
                            it’s ready we will deploy.” 1996 sounds like a long time. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> In all candor 10 years isn’t very
                            long for a major weapons program. When you were told 1994, that assumed
                            a crash program and that <persName corresp="#p_JABaker3_1">Jim
                                Baker</persName> and Jim Miller would get us all the money we
                            needed. That hasn’t happened. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_JABaker3_1">Baker</persName>:</hi> Well <hi rend="italic">excuse</hi> me!
                            (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> We asked for 5.8 [billion dollars] in
                            FY 1988 and we got 3.9. These are complex developments. You can’t
                            predict how it will go. The issue isn’t 7 years versus 10. We need the
                            right to test; that’s the issue. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> I agree. Testing impacts the schedule.
                            (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">The President:</hi> Well, I’ve got to tell you that
                            I’ve seen the monkey; therefore, I’m ready to run the circus. I’ve been
                            to Denver, and it’s <pb facs="1074" n="1047" xml:id="pg_1047"/> amazing
                            what they’re doing out there, and we ought to send out a lot of doubting
                            Thomases in Congress out to Denver and get the spirit of the thing.
                            (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> It’s impressive. We agree, Sir, but
                            1992 is the earliest we could go into full-scale engineering
                            development, and, quite honestly, it’s going to be a while before we
                            actually get to the point where we can make progress. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Senator Baker</hi> (Chief of Staff): Well, the
                            President’s been clear on this for a long, long time, and our intent is
                            to research, develop, and deploy as soon as we can. All right, if you
                            guys are suggesting 1996, is that consistent with what the President has
                            said in the past? (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> The 1996 year would not be
                            constraining on the US program. We would be ready to move to 1996 as our
                            position if we could get together the items involved and, especially, if
                            we are sure we understood what we are getting on testing. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Senator Baker:</hi> I don’t want to be at variance with
                            what the President has said before; he has said he wants to deploy at
                            the earliest. Once again, are you sure of this? (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> 1996 is not unreasonable. We’ve been
                            working on the D–5 [Trident II missile] for 9 years. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> Yes, Sir, that’s exactly right. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">The President:</hi> Well, I thought that we might be
                            able to have something a lot sooner based on what I’ve seen. (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> Well, what Abe [refers SDIO head
                            General Abrahamson] will tell you, given the budgets and everything that
                            we have, Sir, the window for potential deployment, as we told you in the
                            past, begins in 1994, but that was assuming full budget. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Dr. Graham:</hi> Mr. President, you’ve got to remember
                            that the D–5 program was eight to nine years, but the Minuteman program,
                            the Polaris program, and the Manhattan project were all done in four.
                            The real issue is concurrency. Technologically, if we had the full
                            support we asked for, we could begin phased deployment in 1994. It
                            wouldn’t be a full-scale deployment, but it would be a real deterrent,
                            and we could do it. We shouldn’t fall off just because we don’t have
                            Congressional funding now, because it would become a self-fulfilling
                            prophecy. If we fall off, it is certain that it will happen. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> But Bill, it has happened; we moved
                            from 5.8 to 3.9 this year. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Dr. Graham:</hi> We shouldn’t encourage Congress.
                            (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_JABaker3_1">Baker</persName>:</hi> We don’t have to. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KAdelman_1">Adelman</persName>:</hi> I agree with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>; we do need the right
                            to deploy. We want the broad interpretation, but the Soviets will not
                                <pb facs="1075" n="1048" xml:id="pg_1048"/> sign on to the broad
                            interpretation, and we ought to recognize that. So you have to ask
                            yourself, Mr. President, what do you do if they just say no. One option
                            would be for us to agree to the narrow interpretation, and there’s no
                            one in the room who would accept that. Another option is to agree to
                            disagree. Now I agree that if we simply agree to disagree, there’s a
                            danger that we would fall into the hands of the Congress, but I think
                            I’d rather trust the Congress than the Soviets. . . . [At this point,
                            the whole room broke up with a number of side comments suggesting that
                            many rejected this hypothesis.] (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> If the Soviets would accept the broad
                            interpretation, I think the Congress would go along. The key issue,
                            though, is that we have to remember that if the Soviets go with killing
                                <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss>, then I think all of this is a
                            waste of effort. But I think they are pressing for their own program,
                            and if that’s the case, and they are ready for a <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> deal under those terms, then it
                            would be okay. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">The President:</hi> Well, we saw <persName corresp="#p_MSGorbachev_1">Gorbachev</persName> on TV the other
                            night, and he admitted they’re working on their own program. I think we
                            might be in that condition, and they may be just worried that we’re
                            going to get there first, and they need time to make their program match
                            up and get ahead of us perhaps. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> Well, under that context, a
                            commitment not to deploy for some time is very useful for us; we ought
                            to understand that too. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> Well, let me summarize. I see a
                            shift here in view. The view that we’ve had in the past is that we deal
                            with predictability by offering a period of non-deployment or
                            non-withdrawal and then we finesse what goes on during the period. Now,
                            what I’ve said here is that if they agree to simply accept the period of
                            non-withdrawal from the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty—and
                            they have, providing we comply with the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty as negotiated and ratified as they have
                            offered—that would take us in a situation where if we go that route and
                            try to test under the broad interpretation, the Soviets would come up on
                            the net and say if you go broad, we stop the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> reductions. (S)</p>
                        <p>What Frank and I are saying is not to give them that hammer. It isn’t the
                            number of years, it’s what you can do. If you can do the tests you need,
                            you can make the program go. That’s the issue. (S)</p>
                        <p>We should stop talking about broad/narrow <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> definitions. What we want is the tests we need for our
                            program. You do the tests you need for your program. Now deployment
                            becomes crucial. You put something up today, something more tomorrow,
                            something more the next day. Logical question: is this deployment?
                            (S)</p>
                        <p>They say they want confidence thru the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> period. We have confidence building measures, open
                            labs and the like. We could build <pb facs="1076" n="1049" xml:id="pg_1049"/> a package of ways of distinguishing tests from
                            deployment. It would be something to talk about. I agree with Ken that
                            it is very unlikely that they will agree, but it’s more likely than that
                            they would agree to the broad interpretation of the Treaty. In any case,
                            this would be a good package to stand on before the American people.
                            (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> It will help institutionalize <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss>. That should be a key goal of the rest
                            of your Administration. We could stop fighting with the legislators.
                            (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Senator Baker:</hi> Would you really list what you can
                            do, or would you simply identify a criterion of what is not deployment?
                            (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> Well, others know more about the
                            program than I do. What I wanted to say is that the US can do the tests
                            it needs for its program, and the Soviets can do the tests that they
                            need for their program. We would have a right of observation of tests.
                            Now a lot of development is needed on this idea, but it is more in line
                            with our real objectives. (S).</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> I agree that we can develop some kind
                            of confidence-building measures in this area. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Dr. Graham:</hi> Confidence-building measures are okay,
                            and we need safeguards too, but we can’t commit to negotiate what is
                            deployment because it would move us down the road to what is permitted
                            and prohibited. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> George didn’t say to negotiate.
                            (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Senator Baker:</hi> That was my point. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> It would be unilateral, not
                            negotiated. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> Well, I really think we need to
                            begin . . . (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Senator Baker:</hi> [Interrupted] If we could let it
                            evolve over time, we could simply get into this and develop an
                            understanding of what is deployment over time. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> Look, my position is that we don’t
                            negotiate on this; we declare what we mean by deployment; and we avoid
                            slipping that way into permitted and prohibited. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Dr. Graham:</hi> That’s absolutely right, Mr.
                            President. We can’t afford a structure of agreement that involves what’s
                            permitted and what’s prohibited. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_JABaker3_1">Baker</persName>:</hi> Once again, I thought you told us the
                            last time that we don’t know what the technology might be; so how are we
                            going to do that? (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi> All right then, how do we engage
                            the Soviets on this? (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Dr. Graham:</hi> We just tell them we do what we want
                            to do for testing and they do what they want to do, and then we describe
                            what we are <pb facs="1077" n="1050" xml:id="pg_1050"/> going to do. And
                            if there’s an issue with respect to whether that’s deployment or not,
                            we’ll talk about it. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Ambassador Rowny:</hi> That’s right, and we’ve got to
                            make sure we don’t give them a veto on testing or what we test. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Senator Baker:</hi> They can’t stop, they can just
                            look. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> It may be easier to distinguish
                            deployment versus testing than permitted and prohibited. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Ambassador Rowny:</hi> I asked Ahkromeyev if they were
                            interested in blocking testing for <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss>,
                            and his answer was “yes,” they were. So we must not accept some of the
                            words of the Soviets until we get that cleared up. [Several participants
                            say “yes, that’s their goal.”] (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi> Well, let me summarize then. For
                            the Chapeau in Defense and Space, everybody is okay. As far as it goes,
                            as I understand this conversation, it’s okay to go to 1996 if we need
                            to, based on what happens in the Working Groups. We have to reaffirm our
                            right to deploy; we’ll add a six-months’ notification, but we have the
                            right to deploy after the period. It’s better not to determine what is
                            broad and narrow and what’s permitted and prohibited, and we probably
                            have to engage in a discussion on what is testing vice deployment.
                            (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> No, I don’t agree with that; just
                            make a unilateral statement about what deployment means for us. “Here is
                            our understanding of what we’re going to do.” (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> I’m not as hung up on our right
                            to deploy as distinct from the 6 month <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> non-withdrawal. We can give six-months’ notice to
                            withdraw from the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty, and that
                            will allow us to deploy. We shouldn’t get all hung up on the idea that
                            this extra withdrawal from the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss>
                            Treaty is significant, because the act of deployment will be significant
                            enough. Someone will have to make the decision to deploy; it will
                            involve a lot of people and dollars, so it won’t go unnoticed. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> Let me read you Article 15 of the
                            Treaty. It says I have the right to deploy, but only if I can declare
                            that the situation jeopardizes my supreme national interest. That’s a
                            real high criterion; there’s no reason for us to have that. What we
                            ought to be doing is to get away from that and bring it down; I have no
                            doubt that it’s going to be a hard choice. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Senator Baker:</hi> Am I correct that we don’t need the
                            Congress to withdraw from the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss>
                            Treaty; we don’t need consent? [All noted that while that’s legally
                            true, Congress will be involved in any case.] (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> Look, I’m trying to lower the
                            threshold here. I want to go with the direct right to deploy after the
                            period. I’m prepared to give them six-months’ notice. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Senator Baker:</hi> The threshold is what we say it is.
                            (C)</p>
                        <pb facs="1078" n="1051" xml:id="pg_1051"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>:</hi> But we should shift what we say it
                            is. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> I’m willing to settle for
                            Frank’s position. But if the Soviets say “OK, except it has to be
                            non-withdrawal,” I bet you’ll all buy it. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi> Okay, six-months’ notice and the
                            right to deploy. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>:</hi> I want to emphasize once again that what
                            we’ve done and what we need to do is to reverse the emphasis so that we
                            don’t focus so much on a time-frame and time period, but more on
                            understanding that we get what we need in the period, i.e., the ability
                            to test and the like. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz:</hi> I agree; it’s important that we
                            reverse. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General Powell:</hi> Fine, <persName corresp="#p_RLinhard_1">Bob Linhard</persName> and the
                            compartmentalized group will write this all up, and we’ll get these
                            decisions reported. We have a lot of consensus. It’s been a useful
                            conversation. Please, gentlemen, no press; don’t debrief your staffs.
                            We’ll get decisions out through the group. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Ambassador Rowny:</hi> Mr. President, before you go,
                                <persName corresp="#p_MSGorbachev_1">Gorbachev</persName> wants you
                            to go to Moscow. The pressure is on him. We can draw a lot out of him if
                            we just recognize that. We have a lot of leverage here. It’s all lost on
                            the press, but the leverage is really yours. We’ve had our deadlines;
                            now let him have his deadlines and put his prestige on the line as to
                            whether you are going to be there in ’88 or not. So you’ve got a lot
                            that you can do there. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">The President:</hi> That will be easy for me; from
                            everything I hear about the Soviet Union, I don’t think I want to go
                            there. (C)</p>
                        <p>The meeting then ended at 3:05 p.m.</p>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline">
                                <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                            </note>
                            <head><hi rend="strong">Paper Prepared in the National Security
                                    Council</hi><note n="5" xml:id="d239fn5">Secret; Sensitive. All
                                    brackets are in the original.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" when="1987-12-04">undated</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss></hi></p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">Agreed chapeau:</p>
                            <p>—1600 Strategic Nuclear Delivery Vehicles (Bombers, <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBMs</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SLBM_1">SLBMs</gloss>)</p>
                            <p>—6000 total “warheads”</p>
                            <pb facs="1079" n="1052" xml:id="pg_1052"/>
                            <p>—1540 warheads on Soviet heavy <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBMs</gloss> (a 50% cut from current levels)</p>
                            <p>—a 50% cut in total Soviet ballistic missile throwweight</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">Additional items:</p>
                            <p>a. 4800 ballistic missile sublimit and 3300 sublimit on <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBMs</gloss></p>
                            <p>b. <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> counting rules (attribute 6
                                    <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCMs</gloss> to each <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> carrying heavy bomber)</p>
                            <p>c. Ballistic missile warhead counting rules for existing missiles</p>
                            <p>d. Verification package:</p>
                            <quote><p>1. Data exchange</p>
                                <p>2. Baseline inspections</p>
                                <p>3. On-site observance of elimination</p>
                                <p>4. Continuous monitoring of portals of productions facilities</p>
                                <p>5. Short-notice inspections of declared facilities</p>
                                <p>6. Short-notice inspections of suspect sites</p>
                                <p>7. No concealment or interference with NTN</p>
                                <p>8. <persName corresp="#p_HFCooper_1">Cooper</persName>ative
                                    measures to enhance NTM</p></quote>
                            <p>[<hi rend="italic">Added items if Soviets accept the above</hi>]</p>
                            <p>e. Provisions for verification of a limited mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> deployment</p>
                            <p>f. Allow heavy <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>
                                modernization</p>
                            <p>g. Unilateral declarations of nuclear <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss> forces</p>
                            <p>h. Permit BACKFIRE if not refueled, numbers not increased, and not
                                equipped to carry <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCMs</gloss></p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">DEFENSE AND SPACE</hi></p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">Agreed chapeau:</p>
                            <p>—Instruct negotiators to develop Joint Draft Treaty Text</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Additional items:</hi> take the form of three
                                options</p>
                            <p>Option I:</p>
                            <p>—Non-withdrawal through October 11, 1996</p>
                            <p>—After 1996, return to <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty
                                regime</p>
                            <p>—Negotiate distinction between testing and deployment</p>
                            <p>—Confidence building package</p>
                            <p>Option 2:</p>
                            <p>—Non-deployment through October 11, 1996</p>
                            <p>—After 1996, free to deploy</p>
                            <p>—Negotiate understanding on what constitute deployment</p>
                            <p>—Make it clear that testing is permitted</p>
                            <p>—Confidence building package</p>
                            <p>Merge of two options is attached.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <pb facs="1080" n="1053" xml:id="pg_1053"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline">
                                <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                            </note>
                            <head><hi rend="strong">Paper Prepared in the National Security
                                    Council</hi><note n="6" xml:id="d239fn6">Secret;
                                    Sensitive.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1987-12-03">December 3, 1987</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">DEFENSE AND SPACE “MERGE”
                                OPTION</hi></p>
                            <p>—A 10 year period of [<hi rend="italic">A: non-withdrawal</hi>] [<hi rend="italic">B: non-deployment</hi>] through the tenth
                                anniversary of the Reykjavik meeting (October 11, 1996).</p>
                            <p>—After that time (October 11, 1996), the sides are free to [<hi rend="italic">A: exercise their right to withdraw from the
                                        <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty</hi>] [<hi rend="italic">B: deploy defenses not currently permitted by the
                                    Treaty</hi>] after having given 6 months notice.</p>
                            <p>—It would be clearly understood that during the 10 year period, both
                                sides have the right to conduct research, development and testing,
                                including testing in space, which are permitted by the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty, and that the United States
                                intends to fully exercise those rights.</p>
                            <p>—With respect to conduct during the 10 year period, the sides will
                                negotiate an agreed understanding as to [<hi rend="italic">A: the
                                    distinction between testing (which is permitted) and deployment
                                    (which is not</hi>)] [<hi rend="italic">B: what constitutes
                                    prohibited deployment</hi>]. [<hi rend="italic">C: Do not
                                    negotiate anything in this area, simply agree to
                                disagree</hi>.]</p>
                            <p>—To enhance strategic stability, provide predictability, and ensure
                                confidence that prohibited deployments were not being undertaken
                                during the 10 year period, the sides meet regularly to exchange
                                briefings on each side’s strategic defense programs and to
                                facilitate mutual observation of strategic defense tests and visits
                                to strategic defense research facilities.</p>
                            <p>—[If at any time after the eighth anniversary of the Reykjavik
                                meeting (i.e. October 11, 1994), should a side wish to deploy
                                strategic defenses not permitted by the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty, it shall initiate a two year period of
                                discussions to ensure a stable transition. At the end of this two
                                year discussion period, unless agreed otherwise, either side will be
                                free to [<hi rend="italic">A: exercise their right to withdraw from
                                    the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty</hi>] [<hi rend="italic">B: deploy defenses not currently permitted by the
                                    Treaty</hi>] after having given 6 months notice.]</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>