<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1988-03-23T14:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1988-03-23T11:45:00-05:00" n="285" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d285">
                        <head>285. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d285fn1">Source: Department of State, Executive Secretariat,
                                S/S-IRM Records, Memoranda of Conversations Pertaining the United
                                States and <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> Relations,
                                1981–1990, Lot 93D188, 3/88 Washington/Shultz—Shevardnadze. Secret;
                                Sensitive. The meeting took place in the Oval Office, the Cabinet
                                Room, and the Roosevelt Room. The complete memorandum of
                                conversation is printed in <ref target="frus1981-88v06#d138"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. VI,
                                    Soviet Union, October 1986–January 1989, Document
                                138</ref>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1988-03-23T11:45:00-05:00" to="1988-03-23T14:35:00-05:00">March 23, 1988, 11:45 a.m.–2:35 p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Meeting with Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> (U)</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">US</hi></head>
                                    <item>The President</item>
                                    <item>The Vice President</item>
                                    <item>Secretary of State George Shultz</item>
                                    <item>Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Frank Carlucci</persName></item>
                                    <item>Chief of Staff Howard Baker</item>
                                    <item>Deputy Chief of Staff Kenneth Duberstein</item>
                                    <item>Colin L. Powell, Assistant to the President for National
                                        Security Affairs</item>
                                    <item>Under Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_MHArmacost_1">Michael
                                        Armacost</persName></item>
                                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JFMatlock_1">Jack
                                            Matlock</persName></item>
                                    <item>Counselor <persName corresp="#p_MMKampelman_1">Max
                                            Kampelman</persName></item>
                                    <item>Ambassador Paul Nitze</item>
                                    <item>Ambassador Edward Rowny</item>
                                    <item>Assistant Secretary of State Rozanne Ridgway</item>
                                    <item><persName corresp="#p_RLinhard_1">Robert E.
                                            Linhard</persName>, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss></item>
                                    <item>Thomas Simons (State, Notetaker)</item>
                                    <item>Fritz W. Ermarth, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>
                                        (Notetaker)</item>
                                    <item>Dimitry Zarechnak (Interpreter)</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss></hi></head>
                                    <item>Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze</item>
                                    <item>Deputy Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_ABessmertnykh_1">Aleksander
                                            Bessmertnykh</persName></item>
                                    <item>Deputy Foreign Minister Adamishin</item>
                                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YDubinin_1">Yuriy
                                            Dubinin</persName></item>
                                    <item>General Nikolay Chervov</item>
                                    <item>Ambassador Victor Karpov</item>
                                    <item>Ambassador Aleksey Obukhov</item>
                                    <item>Foreign Ministry Deputy Director Georgiy Mamedov</item>
                                    <item>Foreign Ministry Official Teymuraz Stepanov</item>
                                    <item>Foreign Ministry Official Sergey Tarasenko</item>
                                    <item>Pavel R. Palazhchenko (Interpreter)</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Soviets arrived at 1135 in the Oval Office. Following initial
                            pleasantries and a multiwave photo-op, <hi rend="italic">the
                                President</hi> opened the meet<pb facs="1306" n="1279" xml:id="pg_1279"/>ing by saying that he wished to raise a few
                            personal thoughts before convening the larger plenary session.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here are discussions not related to <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>.]</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">PLENARY MEETING IN CABINET ROOM</p>
                        <p>When the plenary session convened in the Cabinet Room at 1200, <hi rend="italic">the President</hi> noted that the discussion had
                            already begun and invited Secretary Shultz to start this round. (U)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz</hi> said that the now regular pattern
                            of small meetings with principals, including Colin Powell and Roz
                            Ridgway on the US side, had been applied during this ministerial. He
                            noted that working groups on all the arms control issues and on regional
                            conflicts had met, that ambassadors had met on bilateral matters, and
                            that working-group talks on human rights would be underway during the
                            day. He said that all areas of concern were in play and that reports
                            would be heard about them. But, first, he asked whether the Soviet
                            visitor would like to comment on the overall ministerial. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Shevardnadze</hi> began by conveying to the President
                            the personal regards of Mr. and Mrs. Gorbachev who, he said, warmly
                            remembered their visit to Washington and their talks with the President
                            and with the American people. They believed that this was a truly
                            historic occasion. In the dynamic of US-Soviet relations, especially
                            regarding security issues, Shevardnadze continued, the first
                            constructive phase of the relationship starting with Geneva in 1985
                            could now be said to be over, and we were moving into a new phase. There
                            was no need, he said, to elaborate on the importance of the <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> agreement signed in Washington. The
                            General Secretary had recently received the President’s message conveyed
                            through Secretary Shultz saying that the US side was willing to move
                            forward on security issues, especially to accomplish a 50% reduction of
                            strategic forces within the context of compliance with the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty and the parameters of the Joint
                            Statement agreed to in Washington. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Shevardnadze</hi> observed that he had had 23 meetings
                            with Secretary Shultz, and could report that the dialogue was
                            constructive and businesslike. Good experience had been gained in using
                            a unique mechanism involving summits—an unprecedented fourth summit now
                            impending—and the continuing dialogue of foreign ministers and experts.
                            Now the state of US-Soviet relations was focused particularly on the
                            task of completing a 50% <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>
                            agreement. The President and the General Secretary had instructed the
                            ministers and, in turn, the Geneva delegations to accelerate their work.
                            The latter had prepared very substantial documents—on inspection,
                            elimination and conversion, and an MOU on data exchange—which provided a
                            basis for progress. Informed by the <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>
                            experience, these were important for<pb facs="1307" n="1280" xml:id="pg_1280"/>ward steps, in Shevardnadze’s view. Despite many
                            areas of disagreement and little time to resolve them, Shevardnadze said
                            there was a good basis for a joint effort to reach a 50% <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> agreement by the Moscow Summit.
                            The Soviet leadership believed, he said, that, while difficult, this
                            goal could be achieved. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Shevardnadze</hi> observed that this ministerial would
                            lay a good basis for the Moscow summit if there was agreement on the
                            basic question of compliance with the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty. The General Secretary had said and the
                            President had agreed that there would be no 50% reductions agreement if
                            there were no agreement on the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss>
                            Treaty, according to Shevardnadze, and it was important to be guided by
                            this in preparing for the summit. Additional requirements existed to
                            amplify on certain aspects of verification so as to assure against
                            circumvention. Shevardnadze said that he had shared new suggestions with
                            the Secretary. Another very complex issue, he continued, concerned
                                <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>. As discussed since
                            Reykjavik, without a solution to the <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss> problem no <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>
                            agreement could be hoped for, but a basis for proceeding had been
                            achieved. First, it had been agreed that there would be a limit on
                                <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCMs</gloss>. The Soviets had proposed a
                            ceiling which, whether accepted now or not, provided a basis for
                            discussion. Both sides agreed that the verification problem, secondly,
                            was very difficult, but susceptible to solution through hard work by the
                            experts. The Soviet side had presented to Secretary Shultz a
                            comprehensive concept for <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>
                            verification. It had not yet heard a response, but understood that this
                            might take time to study. Shevardnadze said this concept deserved
                            serious study, and expressed the conviction of the Soviet side the
                                <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss> limits could be verified.
                            Another issue, he said, concerned <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>
                            counting rules. Both sides had proposed counting rules, and now the
                            effort to reach agreement must be intensified. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Shevardnadze</hi> said it was realistic to work for
                            documents on nuclear testing for signature in Moscow. There were two
                            aspects that needed to proceed in parallel, the preparation of protocols
                            and the preparation of joint verification experiments. If willingness to
                            accelerate both processes existed, a basis for agreement existed. The
                            Soviet side had accepted the US technical approach and the US side did
                            not object to the Soviet seismic approach. Moving to chemical weapons,
                            Shevardnadze said that, since a completed convention banning chemical
                            weapons was not realistic by the time of the Moscow summit, then a
                            statement on accelerating the effort to complete a convention should be
                            sought, a worthwhile draft of which had been submitted by the Soviet
                            side. (S)</p>
                        <p>Regarding conventional arms, specifically in Europe, <hi rend="italic">Shevardnadze</hi> said there was every reason to accelerate work on
                            defining the mandate and substance of talks. Good progress was being
                            made and acceptable <pb facs="1308" n="1281" xml:id="pg_1281"/> language
                            was attainable. <persName corresp="#p_MSGorbachev_1">Gorbachev</persName>, Shevardnadze recalled, had said the Soviet
                            side was ready to put all its cards on the table, all its forces data.
                            It was ready to begin negotiating on all asymmetries regarding
                            conventional arms. Even before negotiations, it was ready to publish
                            jointly all data about weapons pertinent to the goal of limiting
                            conventional forces from the Atlantic to the Urals, data covering Warsaw
                            Pact and <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> countries. The Soviet
                            side was ready to publish data by region, including central, southern,
                            and northern Europe. (S)</p>
                        <p>This in broad outline, <hi rend="italic">Shevardnadze</hi> said, was the
                            state of his dialogue with the Secretary. As to regional matters, he
                            said he could not yet report conclusions. Agreed language regarding
                            Afghanistan had not yet been reached, but he was hopeful it could be
                            reached based on the Soviet decision to withdraw its forces. There had
                            been discussion of Iran-Iraq and the Middle East, but no agreement yet;
                            there would be discussion of Central America and Kampuchea, and some on
                            southern Africa. (S)</p>
                        <p>This was the agenda, the mosaic of the ministerial, <hi rend="italic">Shevardnadze</hi> said, and the ministers would work in a
                            businesslike manner to build a good basis for the Moscow summit. After
                            this ministerial in Washington, Shevardnadze proposed another
                            ministerial in Moscow, suggesting a date somewhere in mid-May, to assure
                            that the Moscow Summit was as productive as possible, something the
                            Soviet Union and its people keenly desired. (S)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">LUNCH DISCUSSION</p>
                        <p>Repairing for lunch in the Roosevelt Room at 1315, the party sat down at
                            1325 for a discussion that ranged over many topics.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here are discussions not related to <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>.]</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz</hi> turned to arms control topics
                            noting the importance of coming to grips with chemical weapons. The US
                            side, he said, wanted to see results in the effort to get a ban on
                            chemical weapons. Toward this objective he said that maybe a suitable
                            statement for issuance at the Moscow summit could be constructed. He
                            then asked Ambassador Nitze for a run-down on arms control. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Ambassador Nitze</hi> reported that one large working
                            group on arms control had subdivided into several separate groups on
                            nuclear testing, conventional arms, <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>, Defense and Space. Verification problems generally,
                                <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCMs</gloss>, mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBMs</gloss> and their verification, heavy
                                <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBMs</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCMs</gloss> had been addressed. The two
                            protocols on elimination and inspection and the MOU on data tabled in
                            Geneva had been examined and some progress made on eliminating
                            differences. Nitze observed that it would be important and feasible to
                            exchange data called for by the MOU even before completing the full
                            outline of the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> agreement
                            because the first informed the second action. The US side moved <pb facs="1309" n="1282" xml:id="pg_1282"/> from 6 to 10 as an <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> counting rule in response to Soviet
                            concerns, but the Soviet side still had problems with the US position.
                            (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Shevardnadze</hi> charged that the US was understating
                            the <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> carrying capability of its
                            very good bombers. <hi rend="italic">Nitze</hi> responded that the
                            counting rule of 10 was fair for the force as a whole. He went on to say
                            that mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> verification had seen
                            hard work and some progress. On heavy <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>, the sides’ positions were clear and disagreed. There
                            remained problems on sublimits, but progress was being made. The main
                            problem remain <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCMs</gloss>, where the Soviet
                            side, Nitze reported, had made substantive proposals which the US side
                            was examining. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Shevardnadze</hi> agreed that the MOU on data was
                            important; categories needed to be defined; it would provide the basis
                            for speeding up exchange of data. But, he said, it remained unacceptable
                            that <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCMs</gloss> were not included. <hi rend="italic">Nitze</hi> said that the sides should start exchanging
                            data as soon as possible. He then broached Defense and Space. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Shevardnadze</hi> interjected by proposing to the
                            President that the language of the December Joint Statement simply be
                            used as the text of a document to be signed in Moscow. Not only had the
                            two top leaders already accepted it, others present had worked on it,
                            including Shultz, <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>, Baker, and Powell. If the Washington language
                            on the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty was still in effect,
                            then things could move boldly ahead. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary Shultz</hi> responded that this matter was
                            actively being discussed; the Washington language was valid. But, he
                            said, it contained areas of ambiguity which even the Soviets could see.
                            This had to be cleared up. (S)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Shevardnadze</hi> said that efforts were being made to
                            go beyond the Washington language; these might lead in a negative
                            direction which would be unfortunate. (S)</p>
                        <p>The luncheon broke up at 1435. Departing, <hi rend="italic">Shevardnadze</hi> asked the President to consider the proposal of
                            spending more time and doing more travel in the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> than currently planned. (C)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>