<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1988-07-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1988-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="317" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d317">
                        <head>317. National Security Decision Directive 310<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d317fn1">Source: National Security Council, National
                                Security Council Institutional Files, Box SR 097, NSDD 310 [<gloss target="#t_NST_1">NST</gloss> Negotiations Round X]. Secret.
                                Negroponte distributed the decision directive to <persName corresp="#p_GHWBush_1">Bush</persName>, Shultz, <persName corresp="#p_FCCarlucci3_1">Carlucci</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_JHerrington_1">Herrington</persName>, Webster,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_WJCrowe2_1">Crowe</persName>, and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_WFBurns_1">Burns</persName> under cover of
                                a July 18 memorandum that reads in part: “Agency proposals to limit
                                the scope of technical data exchanged, to specify treaty duration
                                and to define space launch vehicles were deleted from the
                                instructions without prejudice and will be reconsidered as part of
                                the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> work program.”
                                (Ibid.)</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1988-07-18">July 18, 1988</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">INSTRUCTIONS FOR THE TENTH <gloss target="#t_NST_1">NST</gloss> NEGOTIATING ROUND</hi> (C)</p>
                        <p>The attached instructions provide guidance for the tenth round of the
                            Nuclear and Space Talks (<gloss target="#t_NST_1">NST</gloss>), which
                            begins on July 12, 1988, in Geneva. They include the agreements reached
                            during my June 1988 meeting with General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MSGorbachev_1">Gorbachev</persName> in Moscow. (S)</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Ronald
                                Reagan</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                        <pb facs="1487" n="1460" xml:id="pg_1460"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline">
                                <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                            </note>
                            <head><hi rend="strong">Draft Telegram</hi><note n="2" xml:id="d317fn2">Secret. The Department transmitted the overall instructions to
                                    the Delegation to the Nuclear and Space Talks in telegram 22382,
                                    July 12. (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                    D880591-0430)</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-editorial-annotation" calendar="gregorian" when="1988-07-12">undated</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Subject: Overall instructions for Round X of the U.S.-Soviet Nuclear
                                and Space Arms Talks (U)</p>
                            <p>Ref: (A) Round X <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>
                                    Instructions<note n="3" xml:id="d317fn3">Attached but not
                                    printed. The Department transmitted Round X <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> Instructions to the
                                    Delegation to the Nuclear and Space Talks in telegram 222516,
                                    July 12. (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                    P880088-1905)</note></p>
                            <p>(B) Round X <gloss target="#t_DST_1">DST</gloss> Instructions<note n="4" xml:id="d317fn4">Attached but not printed. The Department
                                    transmitted Round X <gloss target="#t_DST_1">DST</gloss>
                                    Instructions to the Delegation to the Nuclear and Space Talks in
                                    telegram 222515, July 12. (Department of State, Central Foreign
                                    Policy File, N/A)</note></p>
                            <p>1. Secret—entire text.</p>
                            <p>2. The following is overall guidance for the U.S. <gloss target="#t_NST_1">NST</gloss> delegation for Round X, which
                                begins on July 12, 1988. Guidance from previous rounds remains in
                                effect except as modified below. Specific guidance for the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> and the Defense and Space
                                Negotiating Groups is provided in reftels.</p>
                            <p>3. Principal objectives for Round X include:</p>
                            <p>—To build on the progress achieved during the May 29–June 1, 1988
                                summit in Moscow.</p>
                            <p>—To conclude by the earliest possible date the Treaty on Reduction
                                and Limitation of Strategic Offensive Arms consistent with U.S.
                                principles that we seek only effectively verifiable and stabilizing
                                reductions.</p>
                            <p>—To prepare the joint draft text of a separate agreement concerning
                                the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty building on the
                                language of the Washington summit joint statement dated December 10,
                                1987 and to continue work on its associated protocol.</p>
                            <p>—To continue to resist Soviet attempts to produce a key provisions or
                                framework agreement for either <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_DST_1">DST</gloss>.</p>
                            <p>—To continue to counter Soviet efforts to hold <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> negotiations hostage to
                                progress in Defense and Space.</p>
                            <p>—To reaffirm our longstanding concern with Soviet failure to comply
                                with and to correct Soviet violations of the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty.</p>
                            <pb facs="1488" n="1461" xml:id="pg_1461"/>
                            <p>—To make it clear that we will not conclude any strategic ARMS
                                agreements, either in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> or
                                Defense and Space, while the issue of the illegal Soviet Krasnoyarsk
                                radar remains unresolved, and that we consider the only appropriate
                                resolution to be dismantlement of the radar.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>