<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-12-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-12-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="44" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d44">
                        <head>44. Memorandum From the Special Representative for Arms Control and
                            Disarmament (Rowny) to Acting Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KWDam_1">Dam</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d44fn1">Source: Reagan Library, Executive Secretariat,
                                National Security Council: Country File, <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> (12/08/1982–12/13/1982). Secret. From December
                                7–19, Shultz traveled to the Federal Republic of Germany, Belgium,
                                the Netherlands, Italy, France, Spain, and the United
                                Kingdom.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-12-13">December 13, 1982</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Short-Run Tactics and Long-Range Strategy on <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">What is the situation in Geneva?</hi> We finished
                            the second round of <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> on December
                            2 and resume the third round on February 2. During the second round the
                            United States laid out most of the remaining details of President
                            Reagan’s Eureka proposal. The Soviets proposed little new and
                            essentially stalled.</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">What is the situation in Moscow?</hi>
                            <persName corresp="#p_YAndropov_1">Andropov</persName> has moved in
                                rapidly,<note n="2" xml:id="d44fn2">On November 12, 1982, two days
                                after <persName corresp="#p_LBrezhnev_1">Brezhnev</persName>’s
                                death, the Communist Party’s Central Committee selected <persName corresp="#p_YAndropov_1">Andropov</persName> to succeed
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LBrezhnev_1">Brezhnev</persName> as
                                General Secretary. (John F. Burn, “Ex-Chief of K.G.B: New Communist
                                Leader Emphasizes ‘Invincible Might’ of Military,” <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, November 13, 1982, p. 1)</note> is in
                            complete charge, and is putting younger protegés into key positions. He
                            apparently struck a deal with the military and will not reduce the
                            momentum of buildup in strategic arms. <persName corresp="#p_YAndropov_1">Andropov</persName> has shown he is well
                            aware of the Soviets’ serious economic and foreign policy situations and
                            will tackle them energetically. In arms control he will be more
                            sophisticated and clever than <persName corresp="#p_LBrezhnev_1">Brezhnev</persName>. He will seek to appear flexible and reasonable
                            while in actuality he will be tougher than <persName corresp="#p_LBrezhnev_1">Brezhnev</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_YAndropov_1">Andropov</persName> will exploit public
                            opinion sentiment in the West, giving priority to Europe.</p>
                        <p>3. <hi rend="italic">What is the situation in Washington?</hi> President
                            Reagan achieved a victory in the November elections by keeping intact
                            the Senate majority but suffered a defeat by losing 26 Republican seats
                            in the House. Since the economy has yet to show a conclusive
                            turn-around, defense cuts are the prime objective of an increasing
                            number of legislators. The deletion of funds for <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss> on December 7 by a substantial majority (and the less
                            publicized deletion of funds for the Pershing II) are severe blows to
                            our defense programs and will have grave implications for <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>. Meanwhile, the freeze movement and highly publicized
                            Catholic Bishops’ activities, although cooled off somewhat, are still
                            very much alive and need to be actively countered by prominent
                            Administration officials.</p>
                        <pb facs="0168" n="139" xml:id="pg_139"/>
                        <p>4. <hi rend="italic">What is the situation in Western Europe?</hi> We
                            are, unfortunately, faced with a tired and weary Europe, reluctant to
                            face up to the threat and the needs of their own security. Europeans are
                            increasingly skeptical about the direction of US foreign policy and
                            about US sincerity in arms control. They show increasing resentment over
                            US role in Europe but at the same time are unwilling to take care of
                            their own needs. The Soviets have skillfully exploited this European
                            malaise and <persName corresp="#p_YAndropov_1">Andropov</persName> can
                            be expected to work harder to split us from Europe.</p>
                        <p>5. <hi rend="italic">What will be the Soviets’ strategy and tactics for
                                    <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>?</hi> The Soviet
                            strategy and long-term goals will <hi rend="italic">not</hi> undergo any
                            major change. <persName corresp="#p_YAndropov_1">Andropov</persName>,
                            while seeking to improve the internal economic and social situation and
                            the external international situation, will continue to rely heavily upon
                            military power to back up Soviet foreign policy objectives. Tactically,
                            he will make arms control proposals and foreign policy moves which will
                            make him appear moderate, flexible, and reasonable. In Geneva the
                            Soviets have linked any reductions in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> to no deployments of <gloss target="#t_GLCM_1">GLCMs</gloss> and P–II’s in Europe. While Moscow will probably not
                            make such linkage public, it will undoubtedly publicly accuse the United
                            States of lack of flexibility in <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>,
                            and of stalling in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_ADobrynin_1">Dobrynin</persName> will attempt to
                            establish the back-channel as a way of exploiting US internal
                            differences and influencing US arms control policies.</p>
                        <p>6. <hi rend="italic">What should be our long-term strategy and short-term
                                tactics?</hi> Our long-term strategy should be to continue the
                            two-track approach of modernization of US programs and arms control.
                            Without a strong defense posture US foreign policy goals will not be
                            achieved. At the same time, only an improved military posture will
                            provide the Soviets incentives for entering into arms control
                            agreements. Most importantly, we need a strong and steady public
                            relations campaign. The President, although the most important player,
                            cannot carry this program alone. Other officials should carry the main
                            burden of the stepped-up public relations program. I would suggest that
                            the President shift his rhetorical style and let others point out that
                            the Soviets lie and cheat. <persName corresp="#p_YAndropov_1">Andropov</persName> wants, more than anything, respect; he will
                            react sharply to being humiliated.</p>
                        <p>As for <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>, we should do the work
                            now in Washington which will allow us to lay out the full scope of our
                            proposed agreement in Geneva early in round three. This will do much to
                            blunt Soviet criticism that we expect them to “disarm unilaterally”
                            without the US accepting constraints on cruise missile and other
                            modernization programs. Beyond this we need to “show progress” on arms
                            control by pursuing a separate and early agreement on
                            confidence-building measures.</p>
                        <pb facs="0169" n="140" xml:id="pg_140"/>
                        <p>7. <hi rend="italic">What should be our course of action in 1983?</hi>
                            1983 will be a critical year for arms control. Since <persName corresp="#p_YAndropov_1">Andropov</persName> will engage in a more
                            dynamic Soviet diplomacy, we should be in a position to initiate action
                            in US-Soviet relations, not just react. Otherwise, the Soviets will be
                            perceived as setting the East-West agenda, not us, and scoring
                            diplomatic gains at our expense. The last full year before the election
                            year of 1984 affords us opportunities to get beyond the stage of
                            tactical skirmishing in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> before
                            domestic pressures and Soviet hedging of bets begins to set in. The next
                            year may also be the last chance to achieve a truly effective deep-cuts
                            agreement since the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is on the
                            threshold of production and deployment decisions. Allowing <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> negotiations to stall could mean
                            lost opportunities. From many vantage points, therefore, 1983 could be
                            an excellent time to draw the Soviets into a real bargaining
                            situation.</p>
                        <p>As for timing, it is too early to make any shifts or take any major
                            initiatives. We should stick to our basic position and extol its
                            virtues. We should see how <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss>/CSB
                            Peacekeeper fares in Congress, and see how our defense authorizations
                            stand up. We should also wait to see what the Soviet leadership does
                            during the next several months. In April, at the end of round three of
                                <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>, we will be in a position
                            to evaluate whether it would be in our national interest to move to get
                            an agreement by the end of 1983. This decision should not be tied to
                            domestic politics. Nevertheless, it should be obvious that if we take no
                            initiative by the summer of 1983 nothing will happen until after the
                            elections in 1984. On the other hand, if we decide next spring, after
                            careful evaluation, to move to get an agreement by the end of 1983, it
                            will take us at least six months in Geneva to work out the details. Such
                            an agreement would probably have to settle for:</p>
                        <quote><p>—Reductions in warheads and deployed missiles to figures higher
                                than our proposed levels of 5000/2500/850.</p>
                            <p>—Reductions in throw-weight less than could be achieved through
                                reductions to the Eureka levels.</p>
                            <p>—Limits on the number of <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>-carrying bombers. We should explicitly link any
                                willingness to constrain cruise missiles to Soviet willingness to
                                agree to substantially lower levels of ballistic missile
                                throw-weight.</p></quote>
                        <p>Thus, while some current US goals, such as equal throw-weight, reductions
                            to low levels of missiles and warheads, and limits on the number of
                            non-deployed missiles, might not appear achievable the <hi rend="italic">near-term</hi>, we would want to retain them as <hi rend="italic">long-term</hi> objectives and continue negotiations toward these
                            ends. We would need to retain sufficient leverage with which to achieve
                            our long-term goals.</p>
                        <p>However, these are not decisions we need to make now. By round three we
                            need only be prepared to table our Basic Elements and certain
                            definitions.</p>
                        <pb facs="0170" n="141" xml:id="pg_141"/>
                        <p>8. <hi rend="italic">Relationship of <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>
                                and <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss></hi>. As the time for
                                <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> deployments draws nearer,
                            Soviet agitation will act on Allied nervousness to make our political
                            position in these negotiations less secure. The Soviets can be expected
                            to make their major propaganda efforts in Europe. They will contrast
                            their supposed flexibility with our unwillingness to consider any
                            possibility other than zero-zero. They may also indicate a willingness
                            to move ahead in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> if we show
                            “reasonable” in <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>. In my view this is
                            the time to be firm and patient. The United States should adhere to
                            zero-zero and not reevaluate it until after the German elections in
                            March.</p>
                        <p>9. <hi rend="italic">What surprises might we expect and how should we
                                react?</hi> As indicated above, <persName corresp="#p_YAndropov_1">Andropov</persName> will be energetic and clever; he can be
                            expected to deal us some surprises. We should anticipate these and make
                            preparations now to head them off or turn them to our advantage. These
                            surprises can be grouped under three clusters: (a) The Soviets may try
                            to appear more reasonable and forthcoming; (b) The Soviets may opt to
                            play hard-ball; and (c) The Soviets may seek interaction between <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>a. <hi rend="italic">The Soviets may try to appear more reasonable and
                                forthcoming</hi>. Soviet leaders and negotiators in Geneva may make
                            new proposals, such as offering to include missile throw-weight if we
                            include bomber “throw-weight,” may make new proposals on warhead and
                            cruise missile limitations, or may try to show that the 1800 proposal is
                            a good “way station” on the way to further cuts. <hi rend="italic">Counter:</hi> We should be prepared to table our Basic Elements, to
                            demonstrate that bomber throw-weight is not the same as missile
                            throw-weight, and that the 1800 proposal (in the absence of limitations
                            on missile warheads) could lead to little or no reduction in Soviet
                            strategic capability.</p>
                        <p>b. <hi rend="italic">The Soviets may opt to play hard-ball</hi>. This
                            could cover a number of actions. They might charge that since we are
                            deploying <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss>/CSB, the Soviets need not
                            be limited by <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>. This could be
                            followed by decisions to build new systems and to cease to dismantle
                            older systems, for example, Yankee submarines, as newer systems are
                            deployed. The Soviets could stop their current “moratorium” and begin
                            deploying additional SS–20s or <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCMs</gloss>
                            against Europe. They could also announce a decision to deploy Soviet
                                <gloss target="#t_GLCM_1">GLCMs</gloss> against Europe and offer to
                            trade them for US <gloss target="#t_GLCM_1">GLCMs</gloss>. They could
                            carry out <persName corresp="#p_LBrezhnev_1">Brezhnev</persName>’s
                            threat to place the US in an “analogous” position should <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> deployment proceed by deploying SS–20s
                            or cruise missiles in Cuba or by stationing <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>-carrying submarines off the US coasts. <hi rend="italic">Counter:</hi> We should make the necessary
                            preparations now so that we can play hardball in return.</p>
                        <p>c. <hi rend="italic">The Soviets may seek interaction between <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss></hi>. They could play this card in a number of
                            ways. For example, they could <pb facs="0171" n="142" xml:id="pg_142"/>
                            offer us concessions in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> if we
                            offer them concessions in <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>, walk out
                            of <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> because we are not being
                            “flexible and reasonable,” and offer to fold <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> into <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>. <hi rend="italic">Counter:</hi> We should insist that intermediate and
                            strategic systems are separate, that no concessions can be made for
                            so-called “<gloss target="#t_FBS_1">FBS</gloss>,” and that no
                            compensation can be made for <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> and
                            French systems. We should fold <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> into
                                <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> only when it is in our
                            interest to do so.</p>
                        <p>Whatever happens, the Soviets can be expected to intensify their
                            propaganda efforts that the US is stalling while they are moving ahead.
                            This could take the form of renewed calls for a freeze, saying we are
                            fueling the arms race, exploiting the Bishops’ movement, etc. We must
                            start now to devote the time and effort to our public affairs planning
                            and implementation. The effort at the negotiating table could be won or
                            lost depending on whether we succumb to public pressures or turn public
                            opinion around.</p>
                        <p>10. <hi rend="italic">Back-channel</hi>. The use of the back-channel by
                                <persName corresp="#p_ADobrynin_1">Dobrynin</persName> or others in
                            Washington should be discouraged. It can only lead to a repetition of
                            past exploitation of US internal differences and cause confusion and
                            erosion in our negotiations in Geneva.</p>
                        <p>11. <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi>. The above is a realistic approach
                            to continuing the bold initiative in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> announced at Eureka. Now is not the time to
                            compromise on <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>. Now <hi rend="italic">is</hi> the time to get <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss>/CSB and defense expenditures approved. It is also the
                            time to step up the public affairs effort and prepare to react to
                            surprises. Now is the time to invigorate the Washington bureaucracy.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>