<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1989-01-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1981-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="79" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d79">
                        <head>79. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>On September 10, 1983, President Ronald Reagan convened a meeting of the
                            National Security Council in the Cabinet Room of the White House. The
                            meeting lasted from 11:02 a.m. to 12:03 p.m. (Reagan Library,
                            President’s Daily Diary). No formal minutes were found. National
                            Security Council staff member <persName corresp="#p_RLehman_1">Ronald
                                Lehman</persName> sent President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs <persName corresp="#p_WPClark2_1">William Clark</persName> a
                            briefing package for the meeting under cover of a September 9
                            memorandum; <persName corresp="#p_WPClark2_1">Clark</persName> made a
                            number of handwritten notes on the talking points provided for his use.
                            (National Security Council, Box SR–103, <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>/LEBANON 10 Sept 83) Participants spent most of the
                            meeting discussing Lebanon: a transcription based on handwritten notes
                            of Howard Teicher of the National Security Council staff is scheduled
                            for publication in <ref target="frus1981-88v18p2"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, volume XVIII Part 2,
                                Lebanon, September 1982–March 1984</ref>. In his handwritten notes
                            of the meeting, which otherwise describe the discussion of Lebanon,
                            Admiral John Poindexter of the National Security Council staff wrote:
                            “Brent feels that builddown should not be handled separately from other
                            possible changes to <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>.” (National
                            Security Council, Box SR 084, NSDD 0098) The reference is to Brent
                            Scowcroft.</p>
                        <p>On September 19, Deputy Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KWDam_1">Kenneth Dam</persName> dictated a personal note that read in part:
                            “I had lunch with <persName corresp="#p_LSEagleburger_1">Eagleburger</persName> and Scowcroft today to discuss the general
                            situation on the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> negotiations
                            and the build-down. Then at 5 o’clock in the afternoon I went to a
                            meeting of the <persName corresp="#p_WPClark2_1">Clark</persName> group
                            to discuss our position on <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> and
                            the build-down, looking to a meeting with six key Congressmen, three
                            Senators (<persName corresp="#p_WCohen_1">Cohen</persName>, Nunn, and
                            Percy) and three Representatives (<persName corresp="#p_LAspin_1">Aspin</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_NDicks_1">Dicks</persName>,
                            and <persName corresp="#p_ASGore2_1">Gore</persName>) on Wednesday. The
                            idea is to come to some sort of a bipartisan consensus on the arms
                            control position.” The meeting took place on Wednesday, September 21.
                            After discussing the Intermediate-Range Nuclear Forces negotiations,
                                <persName corresp="#p_KWDam_1">Dam</persName> continued: “The
                                <persName corresp="#p_WPClark2_1">Clark</persName> group is clearly
                            becoming a decision-making group, and in fact things are moving very
                            rapidly now. Unfortunately, the <persName corresp="#p_WPClark2_1">Clark</persName> group does not always meet as a group, and too
                            much is left to <persName corresp="#p_RLehman_1">Ron Lehman</persName>,
                            Judge <persName corresp="#p_WPClark2_1">Clark</persName>’s defense
                            programs assistant, who really does not have the stature that <persName corresp="#p_RCMcFarlane_1">Bud McFarlane</persName> had. He is quite
                            substantive, but he is young and has not got the clout that Bud had.
                            Clearly the use of Bud as a negotiator in the Middle East has been a big
                            loss for the coherence of our arms control position.” (Department of
                            State, Executive Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_SSI_1">S/S–I</gloss>
                            Records: Deputy Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KWDam_1">Dam</persName>’s Official Files, Lot 85D308, Personal Notes of Deputy
                                Secretary—<persName corresp="#p_KWDam_1">Kenneth W.
                            Dam</persName>—Oct. 1982–Sept. 1983)</p>
                        <p>The next day, <persName corresp="#p_KWDam_1">Dam</persName> dictated
                            another personal note that read in part: “The most important meeting of
                            the day was the <persName corresp="#p_WPClark2_1">Clark</persName>
                            group, <pb facs="0314" n="285" xml:id="pg_285"/> which met on arms
                            control at 5:30. We went through our position on <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> and on build-down with a view to
                            meeting with the so-called Gang of Six, three Senators and three
                            Representatives, of whom the most important are Senators Nunn and
                                <persName corresp="#p_WCohen_1">Cohen</persName> for these
                            particular purposes. We essentially agreed on our position by the end of
                            the meeting, and there will be a meeting tomorrow with the six Members
                            of Congress.” (Department of State, Executive Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_SSI_1">S/S–I</gloss> Records: Deputy Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KWDam_1">Dam</persName>’s Official Files, Lot 85D308,
                            Personal Notes of Deputy Secretary—<persName corresp="#p_KWDam_1">Kenneth W. Dam</persName>—Oct. 1982–Sept. 1983)</p>
                        <p>On September 23, <persName corresp="#p_KWDam_1">Dam</persName> dictated a
                            personal note that read in part: “I spent much of the afternoon on arms
                            control. I received a briefing from the Rand Corporation on the new
                            double build-down idea, where the briefing was given by its creator,
                            General <persName corresp="#p_GKent_1">Kent</persName>, and on the Rand
                            summer study on defense against ballistic missiles. The latter project
                            grew out of the star wars speech of the President last March.
                            Thereafter, I went to the Situation Room for still another meeting of
                            the <persName corresp="#p_WPClark2_1">Clark</persName> group. This was
                            strictly procedural. <persName corresp="#p_WPClark2_1">Clark</persName>
                            gave a briefing on his meeting with the Group of Six on Wednesday and
                            showed us the letter that had been sent back on Thursday promising a
                            position on build-down within a week. We then agreed that it was
                            necessary to come up with a formula for how we were going to respond. We
                            did arrive at the heads of agreement, so to speak, and an agreement that
                            we would work on it over the week. We will have four parts to our
                            response, <persName corresp="#p_WPClark2_1">Clark</persName> decided,
                            based upon a suggestion by <persName corresp="#p_RRBurt_1">Rick
                                Burt</persName>. First, we will get a resolution next week through
                            an <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> meeting of the outstanding
                                <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> issues. Second, we will
                            have a build-down proposal of some kind. Third, we will work on the
                            build-down within <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> through a
                            special working group, which we will propose to the Soviets, as well as
                            a proposed build-down annex. And finally, we will expand the membership
                            of the General Advisory Committee (frankly, to bring in some members
                            more agreeable to the Hill and, from my point of view, additional
                            members of greater stature) and announce that there will be a public
                            member of the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> delegation (who,
                            it is already decided, will be Jim Woolsey, who is a Democratic member
                            of the Scowcroft Commission).” (Department of State, Executive
                            Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_SSI_1">S/S–I</gloss> Records: Deputy
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KWDam_1">Dam</persName>’s Official
                            Files, Lot 85D308, Personal Notes of Deputy Secretary—<persName corresp="#p_KWDam_1">Kenneth W. Dam</persName>—Oct. 1982–Sept.
                            1983)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>