<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1983-10-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1983-10-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="82" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d82">
                        <head>82. National Security Decision Directive 106<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d82fn1">Source: National Security Council, National Security
                                Council Institutional Files, Box SR 0106 [<gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>]. Secret. <persName corresp="#p_WPClark2_1">Clark</persName> distributed the decision directive to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GHWBush_1">Bush</persName>, Shultz,
                                Weinberger, Stockman, <persName corresp="#p_WJCasey_1">Casey</persName>, Vessey, <persName corresp="#p_KAdelman_1">Adelman</persName>, and Rowny under cover of an October 5
                                memorandum: “The President has decided upon additional guidance on
                                the U.S. approach to the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>
                                negotiations as incorporated in the attached National Security
                                Decision Directive (NSDD–106). In view of the special sensitivity of
                                the details of the negotiating approach, it is directed that the
                                NSDD–106 document be held by addressees. It is further directed that
                                no copies are to be made, and that a record of authorized personnel
                                who are provided access to the document be maintained by the office
                                of each addressee.” (Ibid.)</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1983-10-04">October 4,
                                1983</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">U.S. APPROACH TO <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> NEGOTIATIONS—VII</hi> (U)</p>
                        <p>We are about to enter the fifth round of <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> negotiations with the Soviet Union. During the last
                            round, while remaining firmly focused <pb facs="0320" n="291" xml:id="pg_291"/> upon our principal objective, a stable nuclear
                            balance at reduced levels of forces, the United States made a number of
                            important initiatives designed to increase the flexibility concerning
                            the details of the U.S. negotiating position and to incorporate the
                            major recommendations of the Report of the President’s Commission on
                            Strategic Modernization. As a result, Round IV was, by far, the most
                            useful to date. (U)</p>
                        <p>Even so, in the face of Soviet rigidity, we still have not yet made
                            meaningful progress on the central issues involved in this critical
                            negotiation. The Soviet Union has not yet shown any significant movement
                            in response to the considerable flexibility displayed by the United
                            States in Round IV. In addition, as we approach the period in which
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> will likely have to implement
                            the deployment track of the 1979 <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>
                            dual-track decision, Soviet tactics in opposing the implementation of
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>’s decision will likely cause
                            the climate of the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> negotiations
                            during the upcoming round, Round V, to deteriorate. (U)</p>
                        <p>Despite these facts, however, I remain fully determined to take whatever
                            steps are necessary to increase the likelihood of real, substantive
                            progress towards an agreement which involves significant reductions in
                            U.S. and Soviet strategic nuclear arsenals, which increases stability,
                            and which, as a result, promotes the national security interests of both
                            sides. Therefore, during Round V, the United States will continue to
                            press for progress and build upon the positive elements noted during the
                            last negotiating round. (U)</p>
                        <p>In Round V, the U.S. Delegation will attempt to extract a more positive
                            response to the flexibility demonstrated by the United States in the
                            last round and will propose a number of additional initiatives,
                            including additional initiatives concerning the limitation of <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCMs</gloss>, and a proposal for a mutual,
                            guaranteed build-down. (U)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Additional Limits on <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCMs</gloss>
                            <hi rend="roman">(U)</hi></p>
                        <p>During Round V, the U.S. delegation will be instructed to: (U)</p>
                        <p>a. Inform the Soviets that the United States is prepared to explore ways
                            to further limit the size of <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>
                            forces in the context of reciprocal Soviet flexibility on items of
                            concern to the U.S. The intent is to make it clear that the U.S. is
                            willing to discuss <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> limits which
                            are more in line with U.S. programs and that the U.S. <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> proposal is not aimed at
                            protecting some 8,000 <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCMs</gloss> as
                            asserted by the Soviets. (U)</p>
                        <p>b. Propose a ban on <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCMs</gloss> with multiple
                            nuclear warheads. (U)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Build-Down Initiative <hi rend="roman">(U)</hi></p>
                        <p>The United States will introduce into the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> negotiations in Round V a proposal for a mutual,
                            guaranteed build-down designed to encourage stabilizing systems using
                            variable ratios linked to modernization and a guaranteed annual
                            percentage build-down (approxi<pb facs="0321" n="292" xml:id="pg_292"/>mately 5% mandatory build-down). Build-down will be paced by that rule
                            which produces the greatest reductions on a yearly basis. At the
                            appropriate time during the round, the U.S. delegation will also propose
                            a concurrent, parallel build-down on bombers from agreed <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II levels and will negotiate
                            limitations on the destructive capability of bombers in frameworks that
                            also address the destructive capacity of missiles and which relate the
                            two in an appropriate manner. Finally, during Round V, the U.S.
                            delegation will propose the establishment of a working group to discuss
                            the U.S. build-down initiative. (U)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">The Elements of the U.S. Initiative <hi rend="roman">(U)</hi></p>
                        <p>The following elements will compose the U.S. build-down initiative:
                            (U)</p>
                        <p>a. The U.S. delegation will propose 5% annual reduction in the total
                            number of ballistic missile warheads from existing levels to an equal
                            level of 5,000 ballistic missile warheads on each side. (C)</p>
                        <p>b. The U.S. delegation will initiate discussion of additional build-down
                            provisions which are designed to encourage movement to more stabilizing
                            systems and which are tied to the modernization of the ballistic missile
                            forces of each side using variable ratios. Discussion can begin on a
                            concept involving a network of variable build-down ratios, with 2
                            existing warheads reduced for each new <gloss target="#t_MIRV_1">MIRVed</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> warhead introduced and 3 existing
                            warheads reduced for each 2 new <gloss target="#t_SLBM_1">SLBM</gloss>
                            warheads introduced. (C)</p>
                        <p>c. Definitions and verification rules will have to be developed and
                            finalized before a specific, detailed build-down provision tied to the
                            modernization of ballistic missile forces is added to the U.S. position.
                            Work on developing such definitions and verification rules should
                            continue on a priority basis so that the United States is in a position
                            to offer such a provision before the end of Round V. (C)</p>
                        <p>d. The U.S. delegation will propose that when the additional build-down
                            provision tied to ballistic missile modernization is agreed, if such a
                            provision would result in a greater reduction in a specific year than
                            the 5% annual reduction, then the additional provision would set the
                            level of required reduction that year for the side involved in the
                            modernization activity. (C)</p>
                        <p>e. At the appropriate time, but during Round V, the U.S. delegation will
                            propose a concurrent, parallel build-down provision based upon the
                            number of bombers (not the number of bomber weapons) as a mechanism for
                            reducing that number from existing agreed (<gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>) levels down to the limits on bomber numbers proposed
                            by the U.S. in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>. (C)</p>
                        <p>f. The specific details of the bomber provision need not be immediately
                            placed on the table in Geneva. However, we must expect that <pb facs="0322" n="293" xml:id="pg_293"/> the Soviets will ask how we
                            would apply the U.S. build-down concept to bombers. In response to this
                            Soviet action, the U.S. delegation must be prepared to offer a specific
                            provision. To ensure this is the case, work will continue on a priority
                            basis to finalize the details of such a provision so that it is
                            available for use before the end of Round V. (C)</p>
                        <p>g. The U.S. delegation will initiate discussion/negotiation of an
                            appropriate parallel build-down provision which addresses the
                            destructive capacity of ballistic missiles. The U.S. delegation will
                            also initiate discussion/negotiation of appropriate ways for addressing
                            the destructive capacity of bombers in frameworks that also address the
                            destructive capacity of missiles and which relate the two in an
                            appropriate manner. (C)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Trading Areas of Advantage to Reach Agreement <hi rend="roman">(U)</hi></p>
                        <p>Reaching an agreement in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>
                            ultimately will involve trade-offs between areas of U.S. interest or
                            advantage and areas of Soviet interest or advantage. Such trade-offs can
                            be accomplished by a number of approaches, but any such approach must be
                            made in a way which enhances and maintains stability and protects the
                            vital interests of the United States and its allies. The United States
                            will continue to explore the asymmetries that exist between U.S. and
                            Soviet forces to look for appropriate ways to trade our advantages and
                            interests for Soviet advantages or interests, providing each side
                            maximum flexibility consistent with movement towards a more stable
                            balance of forces. (U)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Additional Guidance on the Treatment of Bombers
                                <hi rend="roman">(U)</hi></p>
                        <p>Bomber delivered weapons are clearly retaliatory weapons and inherently
                            more stabilizing than rapidly arriving, non-recallable ballistic missile
                            warheads. Encouraging a greater dependence on more stable systems is a
                            basic U.S. objective and an essential element in the basic U.S.
                            position. (U)</p>
                        <p>The U.S. has placed both bombers and <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> limits on the table in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> as a part of the basic U.S. package in a manner fully
                            consistent with the basic U.S. objective of encouraging stability.
                            Within the context of the build-down initiative outlined above, the
                            approach to bombers directed also supports that objective. However, the
                            U.S. remains firm on the point that we will not treat the weapons
                            carried by our slow-flying bombers which have to penetrate extensive
                            Soviet defenses, defenses which are not being negotiated on the table in
                            Geneva, in the same way that we treat more destabilizing ballistic
                            missile warheads. (C)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Importance of Verification <hi rend="roman">(U)</hi></p>
                        <p>Current issues of non-compliance reinforce the requirement that effective
                            verification is an essential part of <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> and the build-down <pb facs="0323" n="294" xml:id="pg_294"/> initiative incorporated into the U.S. <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> position during Round V. (C)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Previous Directives on <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>
                            <hi rend="roman">(U)</hi></p>
                        <p>This Decision Directive supplements NSDD–33,<note n="2" xml:id="d82fn2">See <ref target="#d19">Document 19</ref>.</note> NSDD–36,<note n="3" xml:id="d82fn3">See <ref target="#d24">Document
                                24</ref>.</note> NSDD–44,<note n="4" xml:id="d82fn4">See <ref target="#d29">Document 29</ref>.</note> NSDD–53,<note n="5" xml:id="d82fn5">See <ref target="#d36">Document 36</ref>.</note>
                                NSDD–78,<note n="6" xml:id="d82fn6">See <ref target="#d53">Document
                                    53</ref>.</note> and NSDD–98.<note n="7" xml:id="d82fn7">See
                                    <ref target="#d71">Document 71</ref>.</note> (U)</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Ronald
                                Reagan</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>