<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1984-03-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1984-03-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="91" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d91">
                        <head>91. Personal Note Prepared by the Deputy Secretary of State (Dam)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d91fn1">Source: Department of State,
                                Executive Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_SSI_1">S/S–I</gloss>
                                Records: Deputy Secretary Dam’s Official Files, Lot 85D308, Personal
                                Notes of Deputy Secretary—Kenneth W. Dam—Oct. 1983–Sept. 1984.
                                Secret. Dictated on March 30.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1984-03-30">March 30, 1984</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I attended a meeting of the Senior Arms Control Policy Group this
                            afternoon at 4:30.<note n="2" xml:id="d91fn2">No formal minutes were
                                found.</note> The subject was continued work on <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>. The way we are putting this is that we want to have
                            our options clearly delineated so that we will be in a position to
                            negotiate in the event that the Soviets express an interest in returning
                            to either talks. There seems no possibility that they will be prepared
                            to return to the <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> talks as such, but
                            it does seem that they have dug themselves something of a hole by saying
                            they won’t return to the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> talks
                            until we withdraw the <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> missiles from
                            Europe. The President has authorized some probing of the Soviets on
                                <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>, including the possibility
                            of being able to lay out to them what we have in mind when we say we
                            would be prepared to discuss trading off areas of advantage to us for
                            areas of advantage to them.<note n="3" xml:id="d91fn3">See <ref target="#d90">Document 90</ref>.</note> Thus we now have a green
                            light to do additional work in both areas, but the work on <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> is what is particularly important.
                            In addition, we are looking at ways in which <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> might be brought into the <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> negotiations in some fashion, <pb facs="0367" n="338" xml:id="pg_338"/> not necessarily by means of the so-called “merger”
                            about which there has been so much public discussion.</p>
                        <p>I attended a meeting in the Secretary’s office at the end of the day in
                            preparation for his meeting with <persName corresp="#p_ADobrynin_1">Dobrynin</persName> next week. We now have had an exchange of
                            letters between the President and <persName corresp="#p_KChernenko_1">Chernenko</persName>,<note n="4" xml:id="d91fn4">Scheduled for
                                publication in <ref target="frus1981-88v04#d190"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. IV, Soviet Union,
                                    January 1983–March 1985, Documents 190</ref> and <ref target="frus1981-88v04#d197">197</ref>.</note> and that leaves
                            the possibility of some progress in discussions between the U.S. and the
                            Soviet Union, and the purpose of the discussion with <persName corresp="#p_ADobrynin_1">Dobrynin</persName> next week will be to
                            explore how our talks can be moved ahead. One can say that outside of
                            the nuclear area, there is a good deal going on, including <gloss target="#t_CDE_1">CDE</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> and chemical weapons, as well as boundary talks in the
                            Bering Sea, upgrade of the hot line, consulates, exchanges (which was
                            previously called “cultural agreement”), and other related areas.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here are discussions not related to <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>