<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-03-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-03-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="43" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d43">
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Romero</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-03-09"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 9, 1866.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>My <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir:</hi> I have the honor to remit to you
                            copy, so far as touches the matter, of a letter which I have received
                            to-day from Paris, dated 19th of February last past, in which important
                            advices are given to me respecting the policy which the French
                            government proposes to follow in the affairs of Mexico. The person who
                            writes the letter is worthy in all respects of confidence, and the
                            sources from which his knowledge is derived are also authentic.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>M. ROMERO.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi> H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Seward, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c.,
                                &amp;c</hi></hi>.</p>
                        </postscript>
                        <pb facs="0157" n="99" xml:id="pg_99"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>[Translation.—Extract.]</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-02-19"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 19, 1866.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Esteemed Friend:</hi> Still in bed and without
                                strength, I nevertheless take up the pen to communicate to you some
                                information I have derived from a person connected with a high
                                functionary of the empire. He assures me that at the last two
                                conferences of the council of ministers it was resolved to try a
                                middle course on the Mexican question, which gives those ministers
                                disquiet who have been for the simple withdrawal of the army. It
                                seems that this middle course consists in forming in Mexico a
                                Franco-Mexican party, which is to hoist as a new standard the
                                departure of Maximilian, and the re-establishment of the republic
                                with Bazaine as president <hi rend="italic">ad interim.</hi> Thus it
                                is thought to tie the hands and stop the mouths of the United
                                States. Absurd as this project may appear, there is no room to doubt
                                fully of its existence. The news comes borne out by various
                                antecedents—the invincible repugnance which Napoleon feels to
                                withdraw his forces, without concealing that he was mistaken, that
                                Bazaine is working for himself in Mexico, and the project being the
                                theme of all the French employés and functionaries, who for some
                                time have been informing Napoleon that the French army is looked on
                                favorably by the Mexicans, and that what they dislike is the
                                monarchy and the incompetency of Maximilian. So I have read for some
                                time in the private letters from the Abbé——. I am assured that this
                                was the idea that Barrés tried to inculcate in the interviews which
                                he had with Napoleon; and of myself many times questions have been
                                asked in this sense. By the last packet a chief of staff and an
                                employe of the finance department have gone out, and perhaps they go
                                to modify, in accordance with this idea, the instructions of
                                Saillard, for the packet was even delayed to wait for them. * *
                                *</p>
                            <p>It is stated that the minister of that republic here is condescending
                                to this government even to weakness. He is flattered and praised
                                incessantly with real recklessness. * * *</p>
                            <p>Your friend,</p>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>Señor M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Romero, <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>,</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>