<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1912-04-26T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1912-04-26T14:00:00-05:00" n="1089" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1089">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 312.11/288a.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">American Ambassador</gloss></hi>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram.—Paraphrase.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1912-04-26T14:00:00-05:00">
                                    <hi rend="italic">April 26, 1912—2 p.m.</hi>
                                </date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The transport <hi rend="italic">Buford</hi>, accommodations about 1,000
                            persons, ordered to Mexico for the purpose of getting in touch with
                            conditions on the west coast as they affect Americans and their
                            interests and to provide transportation for such Americans as can reach
                            the ports of Topolobampo, Altata, Mazatlan, San Bias, Manzanillo,
                            Acapulco, and Salina Cruz. At San Diego the <hi rend="italic">Buford</hi> will take Guyant on board. The Department desires that
                            the Embassy endeavor to have all Americans who may want to come away
                            adequately informed. You may inform the Minister for Foreign Affairs of
                            the foregoing and say in addition that the newspaper reports relative to
                            orders to the <hi rend="italic">Maryland</hi> are untrue and that it is
                            hoped the Mexican authorities will do whatever they properly can to aid
                            the <hi rend="italic">Buford</hi> on its mission, and to have
                            appropriate orders issued to the various officials concerned at the
                            ports en route, and that no misconstruction will be placed upon its
                            movements</p>
                        <p>On the afternoon of the 24th the gunboat <hi rend="italic">Yorktown</hi>,
                            accompanied by the collier <hi rend="italic">Prometheus</hi>, sailed
                            from San José de Guatemala in pursuance of orders issued to her prior to
                            the receipt of your April 23, 2 p.m. It was thought that her small size
                            and the fact that she was near by would keep her mission, which is to
                            get in touch with the situation and to report, from seeming to have any
                            offensive character. Out of deference to the Mexican Government and
                            after a full and satisfactory report from you as to the advisability of
                            such or any other action involving warships, the Department is prepared
                            to have the <hi rend="italic">Yorktown</hi> instructed not proceed to
                            Topolobampo, but to continue to San Diego.</p>
                        <p>It seems likely that the French cruiser <hi rend="italic">Descartes</hi>
                            will arrive at some port on the east coast within the next few days. It
                            is hoped that its arrival will break the shock to the Mexican mind of
                            sending even a warship in case of necessity to the west coast.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Knox.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>