<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1911-06-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1911-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="1327" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1327">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 412.00.</note>
                        <head ana="#head_untitled-inferred-from-preceding-sibling-head">[Untitled]</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">Serial 634.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1911-06-07">
                                    <hi rend="italic">June 7, 1911</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the matter of the
                            settlement of claims growing out of the damages to lives and property
                            during the recent revolution, I have the honor to advise the Department
                            of the existence of a strong desire on the part of all the diplomatic
                            representatives accredited to this Government to take accordant action
                            in bringing the claims of their respective nationals to the attention of
                            the Mexican authorities. It is the general opinion that such procedure
                            will cause prompt action and that all claims will then be settled upon
                            the same basis, thus obviating any complaints of favoritism or special
                            consideration on the part of those claimants who may think that they
                            have not been adequately indemnified. It is also thought that such a
                            method will be more acceptable to the Mexican Government, and will avoid
                            any feelings of resentment which the urging of one nation or another on
                            account of especially large losses might bring about. In this connection
                            I beg to enclose to the Department, in translation, a copy of a letter
                            from the Spanish Minister at this capital, in which it <pb facs="1046" n="930" xml:id="pg_930"/> is suggested that identic action would be
                            the best procedure in dealing with the adjustment of claims. The day
                            after writing me this letter the Spanish Minister sent me a short
                            informal note to indicate that he had trustworthy information to the
                            effect that the Mexican Government has already come to some decision,
                            which it is believed will satisfactorily dispose of this question.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry Lane Wilson.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Spanish Minister</gloss> to
                                    the <gloss type="to">American Ambassador</gloss></hi>.</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Spanish Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1911-06-02">
                                        <hi rend="italic">June 2, 1911</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Ambassador</hi>: As agreed in our
                                conversation of this morning, I have the honor to address this
                                letter to your excellency.</p>
                            <p>I have considered it my duty to lay before your excellency the fact
                                that from the moment that certain foreign representatives had
                                addressed themselves to the Ministry of Foreign Relations in the
                                matter of the sufferings and losses of their countrymen during the
                                recent troubles and had received replies thereto more or less
                                similar, it might be of advantage to us to study in common, as
                                occasion arises, the principles to be defined. These could not but
                                be harmonious and in agreement with one another, and likewise the
                                solution and procedure to be followed would be in accord with the
                                sincerely amicable sentiments and relations which we all endeavour
                                to cultivate with the Government of the Republic.</p>
                            <p>In the observance, therefore, of the development of this important
                                question, so intimately connected with the definite realization of
                                peace which is so much to be desired both by Mexico and ourselves, I
                                have been of the opinion that we might be disposed and ready to
                                enter upon an exchange of views if the circumstances should indicate
                                the advisability of so doing, and it is with this in mind that I
                                have had the honor of opening the subject with your excellency.</p>
                            <p>Thanking your excellency for the kind reception given to my
                                suggestion.</p>
                            <p>I beg [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">B. J. dé Cologán.</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>