<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Resolution of Congress to investigate American claims against
                    Mexico..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1912</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1386</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1386</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1912-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1912-08-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1912-08-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1912-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="1386"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1386">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolution of Congress to investigate American claims against
                        Mexico</hi>.</head>
                <p rend="center">[Public Resolution No. 48—S. J. Res. 103.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Joint Resolution Directing the Secretary of War to investigate
                    the claims of American citizens for damages suffered within American territory
                    and growing out of the late insurrection in Mexico.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolved by the Senate and House of Representatives of the
                        United States of America in Congress assembled</hi>, That the Secretary of
                    War be, and he is hereby, authorized and directed to make, or cause to be made
                    under his direction, a full and thorough investigation of each and all claims of
                    American citizens and of persons domiciled in the United States which may be
                    called to his attention by claimants or their attorneys for damages for injuries
                    to their persons or property, received by them or by those of whom claimants may
                    be the legal representatives, within the boundaries of the United States, by
                    means of gunshot wounds or otherwise inflicted by Mexican Federal or insurgent
                    troops during the late insurrection in Mexico in the year nineteen hundred and
                    eleven.</p>
                <p>For the purpose of such investigation the Secretary of War is authorized to
                    appoint a commission of three officers of the Army, <pb facs="1083" n="967"
                        xml:id="pg_967"/> one of whom shall be an inspector general. Such commission
                    shall have authority to subpoena witnesses, administer oaths, and to take
                    evidence on oath relating to any such claim and to compel the attendance of
                    witnesses and the production of books and papers in any such proceeding by
                    application to the district court of the United States for the district within
                    which any session of the commission is held, which court is hereby empowered and
                    directed to make all orders and issue all processes necessary for that purpose,
                    and said commission shall have all the powers conferred by law upon inspectors
                    general of the United States Army in the performance of their duties. Such
                    commission shall report to Congress, through the Secretary of War, as soon as
                    practicable, its findings of fact upon each and all the claims presented to it
                    and its conclusion as to the justice and equity thereof and as to the proper
                    amount of compensation or indemnity thereupon.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">Approved, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1912-08-09">August 9, 1912</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
