<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The American Chargé d’Affaires to the Secretary of State..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1912</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1393</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1393</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1912-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1912-11-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1912-11-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1912-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="1393"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1393">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 412.11 H141/5.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Chargé d’Affaires</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1793.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1912-11-30">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 30, 1912</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to this Embassy’s despatch of August
                    30th last. No. 1625,<note n="1" xml:id="d1393fn1">Not printed.</note> regarding
                    the claim of Mr. Herbert L. Hall, I have the honor to transmit herewith a copy
                    in translation of a recent note from the Minister for Foreign Affairs in reply
                    to the Embassy’s representations in this matter.</p>
                <pb facs="1098" n="982" xml:id="pg_982"/>
                <p>It will be observed that in this note the Mexican Government takes a positive
                    attitude towards such claims for losses suffered by foreigners by revolutions
                    and one which, if concurred in by the Department, will render useless any
                    further steps towards the collection of damages for losses suffered by American
                    interests in Mexico arising from the revolutionary movements of the past two
                    years.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Montgomery Schuyler.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Minister for Foreign
                                Affairs</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">American Chargé
                                d’Affaires</gloss>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 3203.]</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Relations</hi>, <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1912-11-23">
                                <hi rend="italic">November 23, 1912</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Chargé d’Affaires</hi>: After the examination of
                        the claim which, through the Embassy, Mr. Herbert L. Hall has formulated
                        against the Mexican Government for the sum of $40,000 United States
                        currency—this being the value of property belonging to him which he says was
                        destroyed by Federal forces—it is to be observed first of all that the
                        allegations made by Mr. Hall are not justified, in evidence of which it is
                        sufficient to say that only one of the witnesses states that he has seen
                        what Mr. Hall refers to. But it seems unnecessary to insist on this point in
                        view of the fact that, although the allegations might be proved, it is a
                        principle of international law that when a government finds itself
                        temporarily unable to repress within its territory all the punishable acts
                        resulting from insurrection or civil war it is not responsible for the
                        damages which foreigners may suffer in person or property during the course
                        of the campaign as a consequence of the measures that the government may
                        find it necessary to take in order to recover its dominion.</p>
                    <p>This principle has been recognized in favor of your excellency’s Government
                        by the Government of Great Britain when the latter refused to make claim
                        against the former for its subjects for any compensation for the damages
                        which they had suffered during the Civil War, taking the position in that
                        case that foreigners are subject to the same consideration as nationals; and
                        even your excellency’s own Government has acknowledged this principle in a
                        most ample manner when it refused to make claim against Brazil for
                        compensation for the damages which an American citizen had suffered during
                        the civil war of 1893, in spite of the fact that his business, having been
                        in the line of fire, had been destroyed by the forces of the Government and
                        by the revolutionists, considering with all justice that a person domiciled
                        in a foreign country is exposed equally with the nationals of that country
                        to the results of the state of affairs, and therefore if his property is
                        destroyed by revolutionary forces or by those of the Government the latter
                        is not legally responsible therefore.</p>
                    <p>Therefore, upon the basis of these principles of strict justice, the
                        Government of Mexico declines all responsibility, and in consequence does
                        not accept the claim of Mr. Herbert L. Hall.</p>
                    <p>I avail [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Pedro Lascurain.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
