<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Secretary of the Treasury.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1912</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1723</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1723</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1912-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1912-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1912-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1912-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="1723"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1723">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 823.124/4.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of the Treasury</gloss>.</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d1723fn1">Mutatis mutandis, to the Secretary of War.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1912-04-24">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 24, 1912</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Government of Peru has been authorized by the
                    Congress of that country to contract a loan of 200,000 pounds for the sanitation
                    of Iquitos. The Department is now informed by the American Minister at Lima that
                    the President of Peru requests this Government to recommend a sanitation expert
                    for the carrying out of this work. In reply to an inquiry as to the authority
                    which will be given to such an expert the Minister telegraphs that the President
                    of Peru will invest the expert with as full authority as the law authorizing
                    this work will permit him to confer, and that the services of the expert will be
                    contracted for until the completion of the work.</p>
                <p>I therefore have the honor to request that you will be so good as to recommend,
                    at your earliest convenience, with the advice of the Surgeon General of the
                    Public Health and Marine Hospital Service, one or more men whom you believe to
                    be well fitted for this important position. It is presumed that a knowledge of
                    Spanish on the part of the person finally recommended will be required.</p>
                <p>With the view to learning from the War Department of a possible candidate for
                    this position, a similar letter is being sent to the Secretary of War.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">P. C. Knox.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
