<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1912-05-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1912-05-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="1785" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1785">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 701.1611/28.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Remarks of the Minister of Salvador, on Special
                                Mission, when received by the President in Special Audience, May 10,
                                1912</hi>.</head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1912-05-10">May 10, 1912</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. President</hi>: I have been honored by my
                            Government with the high office of Envoy Extraordinary on Special
                            Mission to express to you in its name and that of the Salvadoran people,
                            and especially that of the President of the Republic, their profoundly
                            grateful acknowledgement of the cordial visit with which they have been
                            honored in your name by the Honorable Secretary of State, Philander C.
                            Knox.</p>
                        <p>I am now discharging that pleasant duty, Sir, and in so doing I cherish
                            the hope that you will see therein a sincere token of the high regard in
                            which we hold you and our ardent desire that the good and cordial
                            relations happily existing between Salvador and this great Republic may
                            continue unalterable.</p>
                        <p>The Honorable Secretary of State’s visit to my country, Sir, has been
                            appreciated to its full value by my Government, and there is no doubt
                            that its beneficent results will be felt. The noble mission that took
                            him thither, his frank declarations and disinterested views, in
                            conjunction with the eminent personal gifts of so distinguished and high
                            a personage could not but produce a pleasing impression and excite our
                            sympathy with your enlightened Government.</p>
                        <pb facs="1453" n="1337" xml:id="pg_1337"/>
                        <p>I conclude, Mr. President, in placing in your hands the autograph letter
                            of President Araujo and I express in his name, in that of the Salvadoran
                            people, and in my own, wishes for your personal happiness and the
                            prosperity of this great people.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>