<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1912-03-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1912-03-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="406" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d406">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 437.00/32.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Minister</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 138.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1912-03-05">
                                    <hi rend="italic">March 5, 1912</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to previous correspondence in
                            regard to the so-called “insurrectionary claims” against Cuba, and
                            particularly to <pb facs="0398" n="282" xml:id="pg_282"/> my despatch
                            No. 104 of the 12th ultimo, I have the honor to transmit herewith
                            enclosed copy and translation of a personal note and enclosure received
                            from Sr. Sanguily, wherein he informs me as to the more recent
                            developments in his negotiations with the representatives of the three
                            interested powers.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">A. M. Beaupré</hi>.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Cuban Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">American
                                        Minister</gloss></hi>.</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1912-03-04">
                                        <hi rend="italic">March 4, 1912</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Minister</hi>: As it seems to me
                                but natural and appropriate, after my letter of February 9, that I
                                should not leave you in ignorance of the course of the
                                insurrectionary claims, and especially what has transpired since
                                then, I beg to advise you that on the 22d ultimo, as published in
                                the newspapers, the Ministers of Germany, England and France came to
                                the Department to ask me for the reply of the Cuban Government to
                                the proposal contained in the memorandum which they handed me on
                                November 7, 1911, in which they submitted that the matter of the
                                claims of their subjects should be settled by arbitration.</p>
                            <p>Animated by the same purpose of putting off a definite reply that I
                                have heretofore had to pursue for reasons explained to you in my
                                former letter, I offered certain arguments and exceptions, and as
                                they asked me to reduce them to writing in the form of a memorandum
                                which I had written the day before and now have the honor to
                                transmit to you, confidentially, so that you may be acquainted as to
                                what point we have arrived in this difficult situation.</p>
                            <p>With assurances [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Manuel Sanguily</hi>.</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Sub-inclosure.—Memorandum.—Translation.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Cuban Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Ministers of France,
                                        Germany and Great Britain</gloss></hi>.</head>
                            <p>The Secretary of State of the Republic of Cuba has the honor to
                                submit to the consideration of T. E. the Ministers of Germany,
                                France and England a few remarks in respect to the memorandum that
                                they handed to him on November 7, 1911, which embodies the point of
                                view of the Cuban Government upon the subject of the claims filed by
                                citizens of those nations for damages which they allege to have
                                suffered in their interests or property during the war for
                                independence of 1895–98.</p>
                            <p>The Government of the Republic does not reject <hi rend="italic">in
                                    principle</hi> now, as it has not previously rejected, the
                                appeal to arbitration; but it reiterates, on the contrary, its
                                adherence to the principle of settling international disputes by
                                that means. Unequivocal proofs of this are to be found in the Hague
                                Convention of October 18, 1907, signed by Cuba’s delegates and
                                approved by the Senate on March 10, 1909, and in the Convention of
                                Rio Janeiro of August 13, 1906, approved and ratified during a
                                recess of the Senate by the Provisional Governor on March 17, 1908.
                                And the Secretary of State, speaking in its name, and for the very
                                reason that an attempt has been made to make it appear to the
                                contrary to the damage and discredit of Cuba, hastens to declare
                                that the Republic stands ready now and always to pay what it
                                legitimately owes and is proved to owe beyond any shadow of
                                doubt.</p>
                            <p>From data communicated to the Department of State it would appear
                                that the claims—which, though improperly, have also been called
                                “debts”—are of three classes, to wit: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Those alleged to be obligations based on documents signed
                                        by corps commanders and by the General-in-Chief of the Army
                                        of Liberation, for sums received on various grounds for the
                                        Revolution.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0399" n="283" xml:id="pg_283"/>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Damage caused to the property of French, English and
                                        German subjects, attributed to revolutionary forces, which
                                        must surely be supported also by documentary
                                        evidence.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Robberies</hi>—so they are called in some
                                        of the claims—for which it is sought to attach
                                        responsibility to the revolutionary forces and consequently
                                        to the Government of the Republic.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>With respect to the first two classes of claims the Secretary of
                                State, voicing not only his personal conviction and the contention
                                repeatedly maintained by the Government of the Republic but the
                                general public opinion of Cuba as well, begs to invite the
                                Ministers’ attention to the following points: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>That claims supported by documents signed by generals and
                                        corps commanders of the Army of Liberation, or arising from
                                        proved obligations contracted by the Revolutionary
                                        Government or lawfully in its name, ought not and can not be
                                        submitted to arbitration; because, coming as they do within
                                        the terms of the First Transient Provision of the
                                        Constitution, they must as therein prescribed be passed upon
                                        by the Cuban Congress, which, if it finds them correct and
                                        legitimate, will order their payment; and as the
                                        Constitution provides a simple and easy procedure for the
                                        purpose it would be inappropriate to resort to arbitration,
                                        which in any ease is a costly expedient and in this case is
                                        wholly unnecessary, for it would be sufficient for each
                                        claimant personally or each legation in the name of its
                                        nationals to apply to Congress through the Executive by
                                        petition for the consideration of the claims by that body
                                        and payment in a proper case, transmitting with their claims
                                        the documentary evidence upon which they are based.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>That in respect of claims for damages caused to property
                                        by military necessity, inasmuch as there is a radical
                                        discrepancy of opinion between the Governments of Germany,
                                        England and France on one side and the Cuban Government on
                                        the other, the proposal to submit them to arbitration would,
                                        in the absence of any other means of settling them
                                        diplomatically, be considered by the Cuban Government. But
                                        it must be borne in mind that in order to resort to this
                                        means of settlement it would first be necessary to apply to
                                        Congress for authorization in such form as it might deem
                                        appropriate, in accordance with the said First Transient
                                        Provision of the Constitution, which limits the powers of
                                        the Executive in respect to obligations contracted by
                                        authorities and agents of the Revolution in the
                                        circumstances and under the conditions prescribed by that
                                        provision; and because Congress alone can, if the
                                        application is approved, make the necessary appropriation
                                        for the expenses of the arbitration.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>In respect of the other claims, included in the third class under the
                                head of “robberies,” the Secretary of State considers them
                                inadmissible because the present Republic of Cuba having become,
                                according to the reasoning of the claimant powers, identified with
                                the Revolution of 1895, if for no other reason than the respect
                                which the Revolution inspires in the Cuban Government, and its own
                                decorum, it cannot possibly accept on any ground the name of thieves
                                for the soldiers of the Army of Liberation, nor responsibility for
                                deeds which, if committed, were isolated and individual and
                                imputable solely to malefactors.</p>
                            <p>The Secretary of State has stipulated that these remarks shall not be
                                regarded as counterpropositions but merely as observations and
                                points of view, although they might be reduced to
                                counterpropositions later if accepted as the bases for an agreement
                                by the claimant powers, as the Secretary hoped; for what to him was
                                most important was to arrive promptly at some practicable and easy
                                solution or arrangement in harmony with the good relations which
                                happily exist between the several Governments concerned and that of
                                the Republic of Cuba.</p>
                            <closer><dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <placeName><hi rend="italic">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1912-02-28"><hi rend="italic">February 28, 1912</hi></date>.</dateline></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>