<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1912-03-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1912-03-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="553" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d553">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 738.3915/98a.]</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">American Minister to
                                    Haiti</gloss></hi>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram.—Paraphrase.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1912-03-18">
                                    <hi rend="italic">March 18, 1912</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>State the following to the Minister for Foreign Affairs: Reports have
                            reached this Department that the Haitian authorities on the <pb facs="0498" n="382" xml:id="pg_382"/> frontier are giving active
                            support to the revolution led by Arias; that arms are being sent to
                            Haitian ports for reshipment to Dominican territory for the use of the
                            revolutionists; that Hiatian troops are advancing southward beyond the
                            zone in dispute; and that the Government of the United States can not
                            remain indifferent to such information, but must take a special interest
                            in maintaining the status quo on the Haitian-Dominican frontier because
                            of the position it holds as mediator in the question which both
                            Governments have wisely resolved to submit to arbitration according to
                            the terms of a compromise to be arranged at Washington through the good
                            offices of this Government. If the Haitian Government should not take
                            immediate vigorous steps to refute the above-mentioned rumors, this
                            Government will regretfully have to conclude that the Haitian Government
                            has modified its attitude in favor of the settlement of the boundary
                            dispute by immediate arbitration, a conclusion which will appear the
                            more unavoidable because of the apparently inexplicable failure of the
                            Haitian Government to furnish the Haitian Minister here with unlimited
                            full powers similar to those with which the Dominican Minister is
                            provided, signed on January 18 by the Dominican Government, as follows:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>We have resolved to appoint and constitute him, and we do hereby
                                    appoint and constitute him, a plenipotentiary of the Dominican
                                    Republic for the purpose of negotiating, concluding and signing,
                                    with whatever person or persons may hold similar full powers
                                    from the Republic of Haiti, any treaty, convention, act, or
                                    arrangement that may be deemed necessary for the submission to
                                    arbitration of the boundary question pending between the two
                                    Republics.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilson.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>