<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1911-12-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1911-12-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="56" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d56">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.00/807.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Ambassador to Great
                                    Britain</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegrams.—Paraphrases.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1911-12-23">
                                    <hi rend="italic">December 23, 1911</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Langley, has just sent
                            me the following note: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>About a fortnight go Sir John Jordan suggested that the Japanese
                                    Government should be invited to cooperate with us in assisting
                                    the negotiations between Yuan Shih Kai and the revolutionaries.
                                    He pointed out that it would strengthen our hands if we were in
                                    a position to let it be known that the other powers were with
                                    us.</p>
                                <p>We agreed with this view, communicated on the subject with Tokyo,
                                    and when we replied to Sir John Jordan informing him of our
                                    concurrence, we told him of Mr. Knox’s general wish, expressed
                                    some days before, that the United States Government and His
                                    Majesty’s Government should be and act in perfect accord on the
                                    Chinese question.</p>
                                <p>That there is no change in the policy of joint action hitherto
                                    pursued is quite clear from the telegrams subsequently received
                                    from Sir John Jordan, showing that he is in constant
                                    communication with his American colleague as well as with the
                                    Japanese minister; and as late as the 20th instant the American,
                                    British, French, German, Japanese and Russian representatives at
                                    Peking made a joint communication to the Commissioners of the
                                    Peace Conference at Shanghai, which shows conclusively that
                                    there is no change of policy.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Reid.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>