<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1912-04-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1912-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="671" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d671">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 841.857 T53/50.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Consul General at
                                    Halifax</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 139.</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Consulate General</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Halifax, Nova Scotia</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1912-04-30">
                                    <hi rend="italic">April 30, 1912</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to confirm my telegram
                            of April 29th and the Department’s reply of same date. In this
                            connection I may say that I made no demand on the authorities here that
                            the effects found on the bodies of American citizens should be turned
                            over to me. Up to the 27th instant it was understood that the parties
                            representing the White Star Company would forward all such effects to
                            their New York office, where the same could be had on proper
                            application, and against this proposition the Provincial authorities
                            offered no remonstrance so far as I have been able to learn, but
                            emphatic protest against this method was offered by numerous relatives
                            and friends. <pb facs="0612" n="496" xml:id="pg_496"/> Finally the
                            matter was taken up by the Provincial authorities and both the
                            Lieutenant Governor and the Premier called and offered to take any
                            action that might result in peace and harmony. A meeting of the
                            authorities was called at the Attorney General’s office on Monday to
                            consider the matter, and I was advised to be present. After mature
                            deliberation the Premier advised that the statutes of the Province be
                            complied with by having the Provincial Secretary receive all the
                            effects, inventory the same, and after their use as means of
                            identification by the Coroner they should be turned over to the American
                            Consul General for such disposition as the law might require.</p>
                        <p>This arrangement, it seemed to me, would be in accordance with section
                            392 of the regulations and would not conflict with section 389 inasmuch
                            as the authorities were willing to waive all formalities and have it
                            that way.</p>
                        <p>In the meantime I cabled the Department for instructions. On receipt of
                            reply I advised the authorities here and have taken no further part in
                            the matter.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">James W. Ragsdale.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Note.</hi>—At the time of the disaster the
                                Cunarder <hi rend="italic">Carpathia</hi> was 58 miles distant, the
                                Leyland liner <hi rend="italic">Californian</hi> 5 to 10 miles
                                (various estimates), the Canadian Pacific’s <hi rend="italic">Mount
                                    Temple</hi> 49 miles; others at greater distances. The <hi rend="italic">Carpathia</hi> was east bound, the two others
                                named west bound. The Senate committee’s conclusion, and that of the
                                British court of inquiry, was that the <hi rend="italic">Californian</hi>, which made no attempt to give aid, could have
                                rescued those aboard the <hi rend="italic">Titanic</hi> (probably
                                all of them, according to the British findings) had it promptly
                                offered such assistance as came, at the earliest possible moment,
                                from the <hi rend="italic">Carpathia</hi>, commanded by Captain
                                Arthur Henry Rostron, who saved thirty-three per cent of those on
                                board.</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>