<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The American Minister to the Secretary of State..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1912</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d703</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">703</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1912-07-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1912-07-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1912-07-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1912-07-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="703"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d703">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 838.032/8.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Minister</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1093.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Port au Prince</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1912-07-05">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 5, 1912</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I have the honor to enclose herewith copy of the reports of the different
                    departments of the Haitian Government submitted to Congress upon the opening of
                    that body of April last.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">H. W. Furniss</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.—Extract.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Message of the <gloss type="from">President</gloss> to
                                <gloss type="to">Congress</gloss>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen</hi>. I have the honor, by this message, to
                        hand to you the General Statement of the condition of the Republic. * *
                        *</p>
                    <p>In reporting thereupon the Ministers have at the same time placed before you
                        the efforts of the Government to ameliorate the conditions bequeathed to us
                        by former administrations.</p>
                    <p>In the first place, I am glad to inform you that in the midst of this effort
                        to better conditions the Republic is maintaining the most cordial relations
                        with friendly powers. In proof thereof I need but cite the very courteous
                        visit, at the beginning of this month, of the distinguished representative
                        of the greatest Republic of the New World.<note n="1" xml:id="d703fn1">See
                            infra “Visit of the Secretary of State to Haiti.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>In regard to the nation that is our nearest neighbor, the Republic is doing
                        all that it can to strengthen more and more the friendship that unites us,
                        which will always be the principal guaranty of our territorial
                        integrity.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.—Extract.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Report of the Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen</hi>: The examination of the numerous claims
                        which we have found pending has absorbed and continues to absorb precious
                        time. France had 38 of which 16 were for Syrians; Germany 14; American
                        citizens 10; Great Britain 6; Italy 4; Denmark 1; Holland 1; Spain 1;
                        Belgium 1; Dominican Republic 2. It was necessary to attend to them
                        immediately, for certain foreign Powers had come to an understanding for the
                        purpose of forming an international commission with a view of obtaining or
                        imposing settlement.</p>
                    <p>In fact by a collective note dated December 22, 1910, which, nevertheless,
                        was not signed by the American Minister, the Governments of Great Britain,
                        France, Germany, United States and Italy proposed the formation of that
                        commission, in which each one of them would have a representative. Haiti
                        would have only one vote, since they gave her only one member. On July 4,
                        1911, a new collective note, bearing this time the signature of the Minister
                        of the United States, was addressed to the Department of Foreign Relations
                        by the representatives <pb facs="0638" n="522" xml:id="pg_522"/> of the same
                        Governments to announce their intention of organizing the commission if
                        within a period of three months the difficulties pending had not been
                        decided. It was a critical moment for the country. The new Government had
                        scarcely been established when the Consulate General of Great Britain
                        returned to the question. The Department hastened to state its intentions,
                        and since then in interviews with the several signers of the collective note
                        we have not failed by formal assurances to show our great desire to reach a
                        prompt settlement. At the same time we refused even to admit the principle
                        of an international commission.</p>
                    <p>Faithful to its promises, the Government did not delay in giving proofs of
                        its good faith. In fact, on October 14 last it granted, through the
                        intermediation of the Legation of France, an indemnity of $8,000 to Mr.
                        Prosperi, the father of that unfortunate young man who disappeared under the
                        painful circumstances which are known.</p>
                    <p>On the request of the German Legation on October 20th we cleared the title to
                        the bonds in the case of Mr. Samietz and likewise put an end to the dispute
                        relative to the bonds of the Public Debt belonging to Mr. Ahrendts and to
                        other German subjects.</p>
                    <p>On November 15th following, the American Legation collected at the Banque
                        Nationale de la République d’Haiti the equivalent in principal and interest
                        of the bonds delivered in the past in payment of the Heuvelman, Haven, Tecla
                        Arci and Oaksmith claims.</p>
                    <p>Contrary to all expectation, the Department of Foreign Relations received
                        December 8, 1911, a new collective note almost identical with the one of
                        July 4. The period of three months was prolonged to April 4th. In a note as
                        firm as it was courteous the Haitian Government protested against all
                        attempt at forming an international commission, declaring ourselves willing,
                        however, to refer to arbitration in the usual form all differences that it
                        had not been able to settle otherwise.</p>
                    <p>This incident did not prevent us from continuing the examination of the
                        claims presented by the citizens of the different foreign Powers. And on
                        January 30 last the Department of Foreign Relations liquidated with the
                        Consul General of Great Britain all the disputes pending up to that date.
                        Hence it is that the Consulate General of H. B. M. took upon itself to
                        indemnify Messrs. Julius Schama, Aaron Macnally, Samuel Lewison and Misses
                        Idelie Angus, Elmiro Peters and Ellen Coban.</p>
                    <p>In the course of the same month of January, Doctor Terres, United States
                        Consul, who had been previously chosen as umpire in the case of Mr. Ciplon,
                        a Frenchman, rendered a decision in favor of Haiti. The claimant alleged
                        that he had been the victim of a denial of justice. On the other hand, in
                        carrying out two arbitration decisions against us by the same umpire, it was
                        necessary to pay the sum of $7,000 to Messrs. Cauro and Massoni, French
                        citizens.</p>
                    <p>In February our differences with Italy were ended by general settlement
                        accepted by the Consul of that country. And the amounts granted by the
                        Haitian Government were by its intermediary divided between Messrs.
                        Francesco Paolo, Michel Senisse, Giuseppe Casale and Madam Gaetano
                        Guadagnole.</p>
                    <p>We have, therefore, no differences with Great Britain and Italy. And if it is
                        not possible to say as much of France and Germany, it is because the claims
                        presented by the citizens of those Powers are more numerous or that they
                        require a more careful examination. They will soon be settled, as well as
                        those submitted directly to my Department by some citizens of the United
                        States.</p>
                    <p>In the meantime the Syrian question presented itself. You know how much it
                        has agitated public opinion.</p>
                    <p>On all sides, they called out energetically for the carrying out of the law
                        of August 10, 1903. It was necessary to protect the nationals against the
                        dishonest competition of the Levantines often of uncertain nationality; it
                        was also necessary to protect the public health.</p>
                    <p>The Government, therefore, decided to act and refused licenses to a certain
                        number of Syrians. At once the representatives of France, the United States,
                        Dominican Republic, Great Britain, Cuba and Italy addressed to us identic
                        notes tending to ask us to repeal the measure. Our reply was a precise
                        statement of the question and an affirmation of our right to issue laws for
                        the national protection. And we added that Haiti only followed the example
                        of the United States, whose measures of exclusion against the Chinese are
                        known to all. The Department maintained its views. However, the Haitian
                        Government <pb facs="0639" n="523" xml:id="pg_523"/> decided to grant
                        licenses to persons of Syrian origin who, residing in Haiti, had obtained
                        another nationality before the law of 1903.</p>
                    <p>While we were occupying ourselves with the Syrian incident, the question of
                        our frontier limits absorbed the attention of the Department. Desirous above
                        all of establishing on a solid basis the relations between the two peoples
                        that divided the sovereignty of the island, the present Government
                        manifested from the outset the intention of again taking up the negotiations
                        which were going on at Washington, and that had been interrupted by
                        circumstances. Therefore, it hastened to furnish our new representative in
                        the United States, Mr. Solon Ménos, whom it would be superfluous here to
                        praise, full special powers, and to confer on him the mission of bringing to
                        a good ending the negotiations which had already lasted too long.</p>
                    <p>The tragical death of President Cáceres happened to further delay the
                        solution. As soon as this terrible news was confirmed, the President of the
                        Republic hastened to cable his condolences to the Dominican people and to
                        the widow of the unfortunate President. The election of Senator Eladio
                        Victoria to the Presidency of the Dominican Republic and the sending to
                        Washington of Mr. Peynado, the new Minister Plenipotentiary, permits us to
                        hope that the examination of the frontier question will be immediately
                        resumed.</p>
                    <p>In the meanwhile, it is our duty not to allow any attack on our rights.
                        Therefore, we have occupied ourselves about reestablishing the statu quo
                        before the Pedernales incident. And the Republic of Haiti has restricted
                        itself to reorganizing the Posts at Bois-Tombé, Tête-à-l’Eau, Bois d’Ormes
                        which have never ceased to form a part of its territory.</p>
                    <p>While deploring the civil war which is flooding with blood the neighboring
                        Republic, we must not hide from you the sacrifices which we are obliged to
                        impose upon ourselves with a view of preventing any hostile act being
                        committed on our territory against a friendly Government. And we hope that
                        the Dominican Government will finally be convinced that we have neglected
                        nothing to that end.</p>
                    <p>Besides, the Blue Book, which my Department will publish soon, will give an
                        idea of what we have done to defend our rights as well as to preserve and
                        strengthen the good relations with all the friendly Powers.</p>
                    <p>These relations we can give you the assurance have remained the most cordial.
                        And it is with pleasure that we particularly thank the President of the
                        United States for having, on the 1st of January last, kindly shown his
                        sympathy for the Haitian people by the telegram that he sent on that day to
                        the President of the Republic. There is in that a delicate attention which
                        the recent visit of Mr. Knox renders still dearer. That visit, of which the
                        country preserves the best remembrance, cannot fail in strengthening the
                        friendly bonds which unite us to the great Northern Republic.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
