<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1912-09-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1912-09-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="882" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d882">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 882.51/439.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">American Ambassador to
                                    France</gloss></hi>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 54.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1912-09-11">
                                    <hi rend="italic">September 11, 1912</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to previous correspondence
                            relative to the negotiations entered into by the Governments of France,
                            Germany, Great Britain and the United States for the rehabilitation of
                            the finances of Liberia, I transmit herewith for the information of your
                            Embassy copy of a note<note n="1" xml:id="d882fn1">The note of July 19,
                                ante.</note> which has been received from the Chargé d’Affaires of
                            the French Republic at Washington, asking in the way of compensation for
                            his Government’s assent to the appointment of a German receiver of
                            customs of the Republic of Liberia at Monrovia, that the Government of
                            the United States grant to the French Republic such facilities for a
                            rectification of the Franco-Liberian boundary as may be deemed requisite
                            by the Government of France. The Department’s attitude on this
                            proposition is made known to you through the enclosed copy of the
                            Department’s reply to Mr. de Peretti’s note.<note n="2" xml:id="d882fn2">Dated September 11, ante.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>A note has also been received from the German Chargé d’Affaires in
                            Washington asking that this Government exert its good offices in
                            approving the plans of the Imperial German Government to the end that
                            the German Vice Consul at Monrovia continue for a time in that capacity
                            should the customs receivership go into operation before the appointment
                            of a new German consular officer at Monrovia. A copy of this note is
                            also enclosed.<note n="3" xml:id="d882fn3">Dated August 23, ante.</note>
                            The Department’s views, expressed from time to time to the effect that
                            the refusal of the Liberian Government to recognize Mr. Lange in a dual
                            capacity meets with the moral support of the Government of the United
                            States, is set forth in the Department’s reply,<note n="4" xml:id="d882fn4">Dated September 11, ante.</note> a copy of which is
                            appended herewith.</p>
                        <p>It is expected that the receivership of customs of Liberia will go into
                            active operation at an early date and the Department would be glad if,
                            at the opportune time, you would express this Government’s confidence in
                            the continued support and cooperation on the part of the Government of
                            France in arriving at a satisfactory conclusion of the loan
                            arrangements.</p>
                        <p>I am [etc.],</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Huntington Wilson.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>