<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Agreement of January 11, 1915, between Governor Maytorena and General
                    Calles..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1915</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1043</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1043</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1915-01-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1915-01-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-01-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-01-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="1043"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1043">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 812.00/14612.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Agreement of January 11, 1915, between Governor Maytorena and
                        General Calles</hi>.</head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1915-01-11">January 11, 1915</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>Agreement celebrated between the Constitutional Governor and Military Commandant
                    of the State of Sonora, and General P. Elias Calles, Commandant of the
                    Constitutionalist forces in Naco and Agua Prieta, Sonora.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1st.</label>
                    <item>That the Port of Naco, Sonora, will be evacuated by the Constitutionalist
                        forces under the command of General P. Elias Calles.</item>
                    <label>2d.</label>
                    <item>That Governor Maytorena and General P. Elias Calles solemnly promise that
                        they will not occupy in any way the Port of Naco, Sonora.</item>
                    <label>3d.</label>
                    <item>In order to carry the foregoing articles into effect, the Port of Naco,
                        Sonora, will remain neutral and closed to traffic and commerce as to its
                        custom house until the constituted government of Mexico, recognized by the
                        United States, shall take possession, or that<note n="58" xml:id="d1043fn58"
                            >The accompanying Spanish copy reads: “quedará neutral y cerrado al
                            tráfico y al comercio <hi rend="italic">asi como</hi> su aduana hasta
                            que pueda tomar posesión de él. <hi rend="italic">un Gobierno
                                Constituido en Mexico y reconocido al menos por los Estudos Unidos o
                                que</hi> una de las facciones contendientes, etc.” (“will remain
                            neutral and closed to traffic and commerce <hi rend="italic">as well
                                as</hi> its custom house until <hi rend="italic">a constituted
                                government in Mexico and recognized at least by the United
                                States</hi> can take possession thereof, <hi rend="italic">or
                                until</hi> one of the contending factions, etc.”).</note> one of the
                        contending factions in the State dominates completely and substantially the
                        other.</item>
                    <label>4th.</label>
                    <item>It is agreed also that during the military operations the contending
                        factions will respect, respectively, the ports of Nogales, in the power of
                        the Conventional [sic] forces under the command of Señor Maytorena, and of
                        Agua Prieta, under the command of Señor P. Elias Calles, chief of the
                        Constitutionalist troops in the State, that is, that the said places will
                        not be attacked for any reason in order to avoid a struggle at any frontier
                        occupied place<note n="59" xml:id="d1043fn59">The Spanish copy reads “esto
                            es que dichas plazas no seran atacadas por ningún motivo <hi
                                rend="italic">ast también como se evitará la lucha</hi> en cualquier
                            población fronteriza, etc.” (“that is, that said places will not be
                            attacked for any reason, <hi rend="italic">just as fighting will also be
                                avoided</hi> at any frontier town, etc.”.</note> which corresponds
                        to an American occupied place, with the object of avoiding damage on
                        American territory, and thus expose the friendly relations with the United
                        States.</item>
                    <label>5th.</label>
                    <item>It is agreed, in order to conclude and put in practice the agreement in
                        the foregoing articles, that all the troops under the command of Senor
                        Maytorena, actually operating in the neighborhood <pb facs="0906" n="790"
                            xml:id="pg_790"/> of Naco, will retire to Cananea or Nogales, Sonora, at
                        their choice, and they will not molest in the least the troops of Señor P.
                        Elias Calles during the evacuation of Naco and march toward Agua Prieta. It
                        is agreed also that during the aforesaid operations that the troops of
                        General P. Elias Calles will not molest those of Señor Maytorena.</item>
                    <label>6th.</label>
                    <item>The troops under the command of Señor Maytorena, actually in the
                        neighborhood of Agua Prieta will retire to Fronteras, south of said place,
                        leaving free the western side of the same, until the moment in which the
                        troops under the command of Señor General P. Elias Calles occupy the said
                        place of Agua Prieta.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>(Sgd) <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">General P. Elias Calles</hi>
                    </signed>, <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Naco, Arizona, January 11, 1915</hi>. <lb/> (Sgd) <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">José M. Maytorena</hi>
                    </signed>.</closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Naco</hi>, A., <hi rend="italic">January 11,
                        1915</hi>.</p>
                    <p>A true copy. <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">H. L. Scott</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Brig. Gen. U. S. A., Chief of Staff.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
