<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ambassador Guthrie to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1915</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d109</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">109</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1915-03-20T22:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1915-03-20T22:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recKrzVuLHn3WbqNd" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85105939"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Poverty</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-03-20T22:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-03-20T22:00:00-05:00" n="109"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d109">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 793.94/258.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">Guthrie</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-03-21T12:00:00+09:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 21, 1915—noon</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Yesterday afternoon I had a very full and frank interview with Japanese Minister
                    for Foreign Affairs. He read to me a telegram which he stated he had sent to
                    Chinda in regard to Mr. Bryan’s note, only an abstract of which he said he had
                    as yet received. He dwelt especially on Fukien saying that Japan was very
                    sensitive about it because of its proximity to Formosa, and that she had been
                    made uneasy some years ago by Secretary Hay’s suggestion that the United States
                    desired to improve a harbor there for a naval coaling station,<note n="42"
                        xml:id="d109fn42">
                        <p>The text refers to the following:</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of State to Minister Buck</hi>.</p>
                        <p rend="center">[Telegram.]</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington, December 7, 1900</hi>.</p>
                        <p>The Navy greatly desires a coaling station at Samsah Inlet north of
                            Fuchow. Ascertain informally and discreetly whether Japanese Government
                            would see any objection to our negotiating for this with China.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hay.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister Buck to the Secretary of State.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">[Telegram.]</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Tokyo, December 10, 1900.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Japanese Government declines to accede to the proposal for coaling
                            station for the United States Navy at Samsah Inlet. Today Minister of
                            Japan at Washington has been instructed by telegraph upon the subject
                            fully. He will communicate particular reasons.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Buck.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister Buck to the Secretary of State.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">No. 524.]</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Tokyo, December 11, 1900.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to confirm your
                            telegraphic instruction of the 7th instant, received on the 9th, and my
                            reply by telegraph yesterday, the 10th, concerning the matter of
                            obtaining for our Navy a coaling station at Samsah Inlet, north of
                            Foochow.</p>
                        <p>In an interview with the Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs yesterday
                            he said that he had received on the 7th instant a telegram from the
                            Japanese Minister in Washington giving an account of a conversation with
                            you upon this subject; that he had consulted the Emperor and the Acting
                            Minister President of State, and had been to Oiso to confer with Marquis
                            Ito (still absent sick), and on that day (yesterday) had already
                            telegraphed at length to his Minister in Washington the conclusion
                            reached. He then kindly read me a copy of the telegram sent, which gave
                            particularly and in full the reasons why the Japanese Government were
                            unwilling to accede to the proposal, and said that because of the very
                            friendly relations of the two countries it was with regret that
                            circumstances were such as, in the opinion of his Government, made it
                            necessary to decline to give a favorable response which otherwise would
                            be given with pleasure. He having said that his Minister in Washington
                            would communicate to the State Department fully the views of the
                            Japanese Government, I deem it unnecessary to enter into particulars in
                            this despatch.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">A. E. Buck.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="italic">The Japanese Foreign Office to the Japanese
                                Minister</hi>.*</p>
                        <p>Regarding the proposed acquisition by the United States of a coaling
                            station in Samsah Bay, the Imperial Government would not, were it
                            possible to be guided only by sentiments of good will, experience any
                            difficulty in meeting the wishes of the United States; but there being
                            many reasons of a commanding nature which make undesirable the
                            realization of the project of the United States Government, the Imperial
                            Government cannot but take these reasons into serious consideration, and
                            they confidently believe that the United States Government will not,
                            upon a careful review of the entire situation, fail to perceive that it
                            would be impossible for the Imperial Government to view with
                            indifference the consummation of the proposed step.</p>
                        <p>In the first place, in view of the fact that the Chinese Government have
                            given to the Imperial Government a self-denying engagement on the
                            non-alienation of any portion of Fuhkien Province, such an acquisition
                            as is proposed by the United States Government would practically be an
                            abrogation of that engagement, to which, for geographical and other
                            reasons, the Imperial Government attach the highest importance; for
                            should the door be once opened to enable one Power to secure territorial
                            advantages in that Province, it would be impossible to prevent others
                            from acquiring similar concessions.</p>
                        <p>* Copy handed to the Secretary of State by the Japanese Minister,
                            December 11, 1900.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, having in view Article II of the Anglo-German Agreement@@†, to
                            which both the United States and Japan have declared their adhesion, the
                            Imperial Government fear that the acquirement by the United States
                            Government of such territorial advantage as is desired would at once
                            bring into force Article III of the same agreement, which is a
                            contingency that cannot be viewed without the gravest apprehensions.</p>
                        <p>† <ref target="frus1900#pg_354">For. Rel. 1900, pp. 354</ref>, <ref
                                target="frus1900#pg_355">355</ref>.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, not less serious would be the effect of the proposed step upon
                            the situation at Peking, which is already at the present moment
                            sufficiently delicate.</p>
                        <p>The Imperial Government harbor no territorial designs upon China; their
                            policy, on the contrary, is directed to the maintenance of her
                            territorial integrity; and they have noted with entire satisfaction the
                            declaration made on several occasions by the Secretary of State that the
                            United States were also anxious to preserve the territorial entity of
                            that Empire. That desired end may be, in the opinion of the Imperial
                            Government, best attained by those Powers which entertain similar views
                            refraining from accepting any advantages which might give other Powers a
                            pretext for territorial demands.</p>
                        <p>For these reasons, which are suggested with the frankness and sincerity
                            fully justified by the good relations subsisting between the two
                            Governments, the Imperial Government confidently hope that the United
                            States Government will definitely abandon their above-mentioned
                            project.</p>
                        <p>You are hereby instructed to present to the Secretary of State an answer
                            in the above sense.</p>
                    </note> and that this uneasiness had been recently revived <pb facs="0230"
                        n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/> by published reports that the Bethlehem Steel
                    Company was negotiating with China a contract for that harbor’s improvement. He
                    said that the purpose of Japan’s request on this point was to guarantee her
                    against any action by any power which would give the latter a foothold in that
                    province, as any attempt by any power to gain a foothold there would be regarded
                    as unfriendly and inimical to Japan. He said that his only desire was to prevent
                    this, not to secure for Japan any exclusive commercial advantages, his
                    information being that the district is poor, that there are no indications of
                    valuable mineral resources and that the hilly character and poverty of the
                    country would make railroad building expensive and unprofitable. He expressed
                    the belief that if Japan, at the suggestion of the United States, withdrew the
                    request concerning Fukien and the fact became known in Japan it would create a
                    suspicion and resentment and impair the growing cordiality between the two
                    peoples. In conclusion he said that before the United States approve the
                    withdrawal of this request he would suggest that the United States and Japan
                    should agree upon a frank and friendly statement concerning this province by
                    which all possibility of future uneasiness might be eliminated. He expressed his
                    belief that if some such mutual understanding could be reached the friendship
                    between our two countries would be put upon a more solid basis than it had <pb
                        facs="0231" n="115" xml:id="pg_115"/> ever known. He again pointed out the
                    distinction between Japan’s “demands” and “requests” saying that while it was
                    Japan’s wish to gain the latter and while she would continue to press them she
                    did not expect to compel compliance by force. He expressed regret at the
                    published report that information as to our objections had been given out at
                    Washington by authority saying that public belief on this point would seriously
                    embarrass the administration here and that for this reason although he had
                    instructed the censors to permit publication of telegrams received by papers
                    here he had authorized the statement that the United States had not fully
                    understood all the propositions submitted to China, had asked for further
                    explanations which had been given and which he expected would be satisfactory,
                    and that no protest against any of Japan’s “demands” had been made. Newspapers
                    of last night and this morning contained inspired paragraphs stating that some
                    time ago Washington asked Japan for explanation on a certain ambiguous point but
                    that this was not to be construed as a warning much less a protest and that
                    there is not the slightest truth in the report that the United States has
                    demanded of Japan that she modify her demands. All vernacular newspapers this
                    morning discuss the question on the basis of this inspired statement.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Guthrie.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
