<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Price to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1915</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1739</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1739</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1915-06-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1915-06-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-06-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-06-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="1739"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1739">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 718.1915/237.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Price</persName> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 521.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Panama</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-06-03">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 3, 1915</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit a copy of my note
                    sent to the Foreign Office of Panama in compliance with the Department’s
                    instruction No. 137 of the date of April 28 last, relating to matter of the
                    acceptance by Panama of the award rendered by Chief Justice White in the
                    boundary dispute between Costa Rica and Panama.</p>
                <p>Some weeks ago Panama reestablished its Legation in Costa Rica, which had been
                    abandoned several years ago, and appointed Señor Santiago de la Guardia as Envoy
                    Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to the Republic. The new Minister is
                    an able man; has affiliations in Costa Rica; in fact, I understand that some
                    years since, when he lived there, he occupied high official positions, including
                    that of a cabinet portfolio at one time. He has been a leader in law and
                    politics in Panama since the establishment of the Republic, having at one time
                    been Secretary of Foreign Affairs. Señor de la Guardia is and has been
                    affiliated with the Conservative party in Panama and an opponent of the present
                    administration.</p>
                <p>The Panaman Foreign Office admit that his appointment was for the purpose of
                    attempting to further a compromise settlement with Costa Rica following the
                    rendition of the award of Chief Justice White.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wm. Jennings Price.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Price</persName> to the
                                <gloss type="to">Minister for Foreign Affairs</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 184.]</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Panama</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-05-31">
                                <hi rend="italic">May 31, 1915</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to inform your
                        excellency that I am in receipt of a communication from the Secretary of
                        State of the United States of America, in which I am informed that both
                        Panama and Costa Rica have presented to the Department of State their views
                        in regard to the award made by Chief Justice White of the United States
                        Supreme Court, fixing the boundary line between Panama and Costa Rica.</p>
                    <p>After examination of the papers the Department of State is convinced that no
                        exception can be taken to the procedure followed, or to the findings of the
                        Arbitrator, and that, therefore, there should be prompt and complete
                        acquiescence in the award made.</p>
                    <p>The Department calls attention to the fact that this is an old dispute and is
                        impelled to believe that the value of the territory involved is
                        insignificant compared with the annoyance and ill-feeling that it has
                        aroused. It is, of course, taken for granted that no action of either
                        interested party with reference to said award could be of a character which
                        either of them would be willing to have susceptible of the construction of
                        casting discredit upon the Arbitrator, who is the presiding officer of the
                        highest court in our land. Neither could my Government view with
                        indifference, I am instructed to say, the baneful influence which a
                        rejection of this award by either party would have upon arbitration as a
                        means of adjusting disputes between nations. And, owing to the intimate
                        relationship existing between the United States and Panama, it would be a
                        matter of deep regret if Panama should take any steps which would indicate a
                        lack of respect either for the principle of arbitration or for the high
                        tribunal to which this dispute was submitted.</p>
                    <pb facs="1266" n="1150" xml:id="pg_1150"/>
                    <p>If any hardship is caused by the award, my Government will be pleased to use
                        its good offices to bring the parties together upon some plan which will
                        afford an adequate remedy; but this cannot be taken up, of course, until
                        after Panama indicates a willingness to accept the award.</p>
                    <p>In the fixing of boundaries it sometimes happens that citizens of one country
                        find their possessions included within the boundary of another country, and
                        it is possible that the boundary line as now drawn may leave Panamans in
                        Costa Rica, and Costa Ricans in Panama. In such case it might be possible to
                        effect an agreement by which Costa Rica would purchase at its market value
                        the real estate of any such Panaman who does not desire to become a citizen
                        of Costa Rica; and, in like manner, Panama might agree to purchase at its
                        market value all real estate of any Costa Rican who does not desire to
                        become a citizen of Panama.</p>
                    <p>This, however, is only made as a suggestion, to indicate my Government’s
                        desire to go as far as it can in aiding the two countries to reach a final
                        and satisfactory settlement of all differences connected with the boundary
                        dispute.</p>
                    <p>In presenting the foregoing views of the United States of America to the
                        Foreign Office of the Republic of Panama, over which your excellency so
                        worthily presides, I am instructed to express assurances of the good will of
                        my Government and, also, of its earnest desire to be helpful in every
                        legitimate way to all of its neighbors.</p>
                    <p>I avail [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Wm. Jennings Price.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
