<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-10-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-10-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="1820" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1820">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 319.1123 L25/19.</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Price</persName> to
                                    the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 634.]</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Panama</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-10-04">
                                        <hi rend="italic">October 4, 1915</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my despatches Nos. 599,
                                607, and 614 of the respective dates of August 30, September 8 and
                                September 14 last, relating to my efforts to procure prosecution by
                                Panama on account of the events connected with the Colon riot of
                                April 2, 1915, I have the honor to report that on Saturday I
                                received the first response <pb facs="1331" n="1215" xml:id="pg_1215"/> herein from the Secretary of Foreign Affairs
                                of Panama of a character at all satisfactory. I enclose a copy of
                                same and its translation.</p>
                            <p>The comparatively small number of witnesses thus far examined by the
                                Panaman authorities in the matter is noticeable. With reference to
                                my request regarding the police force the response is most meager,
                                and I shall again request the full list.</p>
                            <p>Señor Lefevre has stated to me that he was arranging so that a
                                representative of our Government chosen from the military
                                authorities may be present at the further investigations and any
                                prosecutions which may follow, with right to take part therein. He
                                requested me to have General Edwards, Military Commander of the
                                Canal Zone, designate some one, and stated that within a few days he
                                expected to have the Attorney General of Panama go over with us the
                                proceedings thus far followed and submit their plans as to the
                                future. Upon the return of General Edwards this week from Costa Rica
                                I shall submit Señor Lefevre’s proposition to him for his decision
                                as to whether the military cares to share the responsibility with
                                Panama in the matter of the prosecutions in order to obtain more
                                definite assurance by representation therein of the good faith of
                                the efforts of the Panaman officials.</p>
                            <p>I should be glad to have expression of the opinion of the Department
                                upon the policy involved in the matter.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Wm. Jennings Price.</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure—Translation.]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary for Foreign
                                            Affairs</gloss> to Minister <persName type="to">Price</persName>.</hi>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">S–8057.]</seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>, <lb/>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Panama</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-09-30">
                                            <hi rend="italic">September 30,
                                        1915</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>: I have the honor to refer
                                    to the courteous note No. 217 from your excellency, of the 4th
                                    instant, bearing on the events which took place in Colon last
                                    April 2.</p>
                                <p>Although, as I told your excellency in my former note, according
                                    to our judicial code the report ordered by the judicial
                                    authorities is of a private character, nevertheless the Superior
                                    Judge of the Republic has told me that, as a courtesy to your
                                    excellency’s Government, he will submit to you all the
                                    information possible, and we are trying to find the way within
                                    our laws for the Government of the United States to have
                                    representation in those judicial matters in which her citizens
                                    play a part.</p>
                                <p>I have been able to obtain almost all the information necessary
                                    to reply to the questions of the last two notes of your
                                    excellency, which I now proceed to answer in the following
                                    statements:</p>
                                <p>1. No writ of procedure against any person has as yet been
                                    issued, due to the fact that this affair is in the stage of
                                    investigation; when this is concluded the Superior Judge will
                                    issue his writ of procedure, if there is occasion for it. As
                                    regards the tardiness of the whole case, it is right to take
                                    into consideration that it deals with fixing the
                                    responsibilities for various crimes; that is, not only for the
                                    death of Corporal Langdon of the American patrol, and for wounds
                                    to different soldiers, among them James Deloughery, but also for
                                    the wounds suffered by various Panamans and some foreigners, and
                                    other crimes in connection with these, such as the damage caused
                                    to the property of Benigno Palma. This circumstance, together
                                    with the delays required by our codes, justifies in part the
                                    delay.</p>
                                <p>2. The policeman is provisonally detained on account of the
                                    complaints against him made in declarations taken before the
                                    American military authorities. It is for the Superior Judge to
                                    decide about his detention.</p>
                                <p>3. As stated above, before the Superior Judge decides on a writ
                                    of procedure against any person, it is necessary that the
                                    investigation be concluded. The <pb facs="1332" n="1216" xml:id="pg_1216"/> Attorney General has promised that this
                                    shall occur with the least possible delay.</p>
                                <p>4. I enclose a list of the witnesses up to date who have given
                                    testimony in the case<note n="10" xml:id="d1820fn10">Not
                                        printed.</note> and I shall be glad if your excellency will
                                    send me the names of the witnesses which the American military
                                    authorities have ready to testify before our judicial
                                    authorities, as you told me, in order that the prosecuting
                                    attorney may present them to the superior judge and they may be
                                    able to testify.</p>
                                <p>5. I also enclose a list of the members of the police force who
                                    served in the streets of Colon where the disturbances took place
                                    on April 2.<note n="10" xml:id="d1820fn11">Not printed.</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>6. The Mayor of Colon who held the first investigations is Manuel
                                    de J. Grimaldo; he was appointed to this position by the
                                    Governor of Colon, Ruben Arcia.</p>
                                <p>7. Miguel A. Grimaldo, as Judge No. 1 of the Colon Circuit, at
                                    the designation of the Superior Judge of the Republic, conducted
                                    the investigation at the start; but when he became Judge No. 3
                                    of the Panama Circuit, the new judge of the Colon Circuit,
                                    Gerardo Abrahams, also designated by the Superior Judge,
                                    continued it. The Superior Judge is J. Demosthenes Arosemena;
                                    the Attorney General, Chief of the Department of Prosecution, is
                                    Alfonso Fabrega.</p>
                                <p>Under the terms of the Panaman Constitution, all the judges are
                                    named by the Supreme Court; the prosecuting attorneys by the
                                    President.</p>
                                <p>8. The judge of the case, as has been stated, is the Superior
                                    Judge of the Republic and, for the second instance, for appeal
                                    or consultation, the Supreme Court.</p>
                                <p>I shall not close without telling your excellency that when it
                                    has been settled in what manner the United States Government
                                    will have representation in the case, you will be convinced that
                                    everything is being carried on with all possible fullness and
                                    justice, and the prosecuting attorney, who not only has the duty
                                    to prosecute but also to show up the truth whatever it may be,
                                    has genuine interest to see justice given in this case, which my
                                    Government is the first to deplore; and we are all anxious to
                                    cooperate so as to avoid a repetition of such events.</p>
                                <p>I take [etc.]</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">E. T. Lefevre.</hi>
                                    </signed>
                                </closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>