<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Reinsch to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1915</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d196</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">196</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1915-09-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1915-09-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-09-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-09-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="196"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d196">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.543 C 42/6.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Reinsch</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 770.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-09-30">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 30, 1915</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In continuation of dispatch No. 761, of the 22d
                    instant, I have the honor to submit for the information of the Department a
                    translation of the note<note n="17" xml:id="d196fn17">Not printed.</note> in
                    which the Foreign Office, replying under date of the 22d instant to the
                    Legation’s note of August 30, communicated to the Legation the text of that
                    judgment with the comment that it had been discussed with and approved by both
                    the American and Japanese assessors. There is also enclosed a copy of the
                        note<note n="17" xml:id="d196fn18">Not printed.</note> by which the Legation
                    on the following day pointed out that the case was one between Americans and
                    Chinese, in which no other nationality was involved, and requesting for its
                    files another statement of the settlement which should not confuse the question
                    at issue by irrelevant references to third parties.</p>
                <p>Lest any misunderstanding should arise out of the ambiguous phraseology of the
                    note from the Foreign Office, which seems to imply that the final judgment was
                    signed by the Japanese assessor, I have to report that the Legation has
                    communicated with the Consulate General at Shanghai and has ascertained that
                    such is not the case.</p>
                <p>When calling on the Minister for Foreign Affairs yesterday afternoon I took
                    occasion to express to him the unwillingness of the Legation to accept the note
                    of the 22d instant as concluding the matter, in view of its gratuitously
                    confusing the question of jurisdiction involved by setting forth the concurrence
                    of the Japanese assessor—in <pb facs="0370" n="254" xml:id="pg_254"/> entire
                    disregard of the contention upon which the Legation has rested the case, and
                    which the Minister for Foreign Affairs, in conversations with me and with the
                    Chargé d’Affaires during my absence, has accepted as being the sole contention
                    compatible with Chinese sovereignty under the existing treaties. In reply, the
                    Minister consented that the Foreign Office note of September 22 and the
                    Legation’s reply of the 23d should both be returned, and that this exchange of
                    correspondence should be considered as non avenu.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Paul S. Reinsch.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
