<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-10-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-10-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="197" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d197">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.54/322.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                Minister <persName type="to">Reinsch</persName>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 347.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-10-26">
                                    <hi rend="italic">October 26, 1915</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Receipt is acknowledged of the Legation’s
                            despatch No. 695 of July 20, 1915, with its enclosures, relative to the
                            Vaseline and Eagle Brand milk trade-mark cases.</p>
                        <p>The Department understands that the Chesebrough Manufacturing Company, an
                            American corporation, had registered at the appropriate office at
                            Shanghai in pursuance of the provisions of Article 9 of the Treaty of
                            October 8, 1903, the company’s trade-mark Vaseline; that imitations, of
                            Japanese manufacture, bearing the company’s trade-mark were sold in
                            China by certain Chinese; that criminal proceedings were brought in the
                            Mixed Court at Shanghai against one Kuang Sung Chiang [Yung Kee Chiang?]
                            for the purpose of having him penalized for infringement and enjoined
                            from further dealing in imitation goods bearing the company’s trademark;
                            and that the Chinese magistrate withheld judgment of conviction on
                            account of representations made by the Japanese Consulate General at
                            Shanghai to the local Chinese authorities, and later declared that the
                            case should be dismissed on the ground that the fact of infringement
                            should first be established in a Japanese court.</p>
                        <p>It is the opinion of the Department that the Chinese magistrate’s view of
                            this case is wholly unwarranted and that if judgment be withheld or the
                            case dismissed in accordance with this view there would be a violation
                            of the treaty obligation of the Chinese Government fully “to protect any
                            citizen, firm or corporation of the United States in the exclusive use
                            “in the Republic of China “of any lawful trademark which they have
                            adopted and used or intend to adopt and use, as soon as registered”
                            (Art. IX, Treaty of October 8, 1903), and the company would be deprived
                            of the judicial remedies provided by Article IV of the Treaty of
                            November 17, 1880.</p>
                        <p>Mr. MacMurray’s proposal to protest to the Chinese Government in the
                            event that the magistrate fails to render judgment on the merits of the
                            case is approved, and in communicating the protest to the Foreign Office
                            you are authorized to say that this Government reserves the right to
                            present, in behalf of American citizens or corporations, claims for
                            damages resulting from such denials of justice. It is deemed
                            inadvisable, however, to propose arbitration of such claims at the
                            present time.</p>
                        <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>