<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-01-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-01-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="280" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d280">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 839.51/1474</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Dominican Minister</gloss>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-01-09">
                                    <hi rend="italic">January 9, 1915</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Minister</hi>: I have the honor to
                            transmit herewith for your consideration a memorandum in which attention
                            is most respectfully called to certain political and financial
                            conditions now existing in the Dominican Republic and suggesting the
                            adoption of some reforms which, if put into operation, will aid
                            materially in securing permanent peace and prosperity in that
                            country.</p>
                        <p>It is earnestly hoped that you may find it convenient to call at the
                            Department at an early date in order that this important matter may be
                            discussed with you personally. An expression from you as to the date
                            when a conference with you can be arranged will be appreciated.</p>
                        <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">W. J. Bryan.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Dominican Legation</gloss>.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">memorandum</hi>.</p>
                            <p>The United States desires to assist the Dominican Republic in putting
                                certain needed reforms into operation to insure the peace and
                                prosperity of that country.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">First</hi>. A decree placing the collection of the
                                internal revenues under the receivership. At the present time the
                                internal revenue is hypothecated for many years in advance, and
                                brings in no revenue to the Dominican Government. It is estimated
                                that from this source the Government should receive approximately
                                two thousand dollars daily, whereas at the present time it is
                                receiving nothing. This Department is informed that revenue stamps
                                can be redeemed at the present time for about ten cents on the
                                dollar, and it is strongly recommended that all hypothecated stamps
                                should be immediately redeemed at the best rate possible.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Second</hi>. Official recognition of Charles M.
                                Johnson [Johnston] as comptroller of finances for the Dominican
                                Republic, whose duties shall be: (a) to prepare a budget for the
                                Dominican Republic based upon his knowledge of income and probable
                                expenditures; this budget to be rigidly adhered to; (b) to approve
                                and countersign all payments made by the Dominican Government, it
                                being understood that no payment shall be valid unless countersigned
                                by the comptroller. This reform is really essential if the finances
                                of the Dominican Republic <pb facs="0414" n="298" xml:id="pg_298"/>
                                are to be rescued from the deplorable condition in which they are at
                                present. It is estimated that under the present administration of
                                Dominican finances the debt of the country is increasing not less
                                than one thousand dollars daily. It may be of interest in this
                                connection to state that the Chief of the Bureau of Insular Affairs
                                of the War Department, in a communication bearing date of January 4,
                                1915, reports that, carrying out instructions of this Department of
                                September 15, 1914, October 23, 1914, and December 14, 1914,
                                directing that the general receiver of Dominican customs pay to the
                                Dominican Government the sum of five thousand dollars daily from and
                                including September 1, 1914, and an additional sum of two thousand
                                dollars daily for the period of October 23–31, 1914, inclusive,
                                there have been paid to the Dominican Government sums in excess of
                                the customs revenues properly accruing to that Government as
                                follows: <table cols="2" rows="5">
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For September, 1914</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">$114,194.17</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For October, 1914</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">97,267.98</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For November, 1914 (estimated)</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">58.147.19</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For December, 1914 (estimated)</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">75,000.00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>Total (estimated)</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">344,609.34</cell>
                                    </row>
                                </table>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Bureau of Insular Affairs further states that to reimburse the
                                general receiver of Dominican Customs for the excess amounts paid by
                                him to the Dominican Government as aforesaid it was necessary, or it
                                will be necessary, to draw upon the convention fund with the
                                Guaranty Trust Company of New York, and such withdrawals from the
                                convention fund, amounting to $344,609.34, are treated “as advances
                                to the Dominican Government to be paid at a future date.” He further
                                suggests the advisability of asking for a ratification by the
                                Dominican Congress of the advances from the convention fund that
                                have been made solely upon Executive request.</p>
                            <p>Unless Mr. Johnson [Johnston], the recently appointed comptroller of
                                finance, is given such authority as he must have in order to
                                successfully carry on the work for which he has been selected, it
                                will be useless to continue him in the service, and without the
                                supervision of such an officer it is very evident that the finances
                                of the Dominican Republic will continue to drift into an even more
                                deplorable condition.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Third</hi>. As the Dominican Government is
                                threatened by no external enemies, the presence of a Dominican army
                                (which is always in an inefficient state of discipline) is regarded
                                as an incentive to disaffected political leaders to start internal
                                resolutions. <hi rend="italic">As the expenditures of the military
                                    establishment amount to nearly fifty per cent. of the total
                                    budget</hi>, it is most desirable that President Jiménes issue a
                                decree largely reducing the expense of the army, so that education
                                and public works may receive their just proportion of the public
                                revenues. The United States will be pleased to give President
                                Jiménes any assistance he may desire in reorganizing the police
                                force of the Republic, or in the creation of a constabulary, to take
                                the place of the an and rural guard as now constituted.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Fourth</hi>. Amending the contract of Mr. A. J.
                                Collett. It is necessary that clauses III and V of the present
                                contract be amended in order that this official may have proper
                                authority to render the most efficient service to the Dominican
                                Government.</p>
                            <p>Proposed amendment to Clause III: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>The Director General of Public Works shall be removed only
                                        for cause, satisfactory proof of which shall be first
                                        submitted by the Dominican Government to the Department of
                                        State at Washington.</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>Proposed amendment to Clause V: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>The Director shall be given authority to employ and discharge
                                        his subordinates, it being understood that in recommending
                                        appointees to the Dominican Government preference shall be
                                        given to citizens of the Dominican Republic who may be
                                        qualified and competent in every way to properly discharge
                                        the duties which may be assigned them by the Director
                                        General of Public Works.</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Fifth</hi>. Wireless and land telegraph and
                                telephone systems. It is earnestly recommended that these systems be
                                placed under the control of the Director General of Public Works.
                                This change is recommended in order that the three services may be
                                under one head, which means their most economical
                                administration.</p>
                            <p>Superintendent of the wireless and land telegraph and telephone
                                systems. The United States Navy Department recommends that these
                                systems be placed <pb facs="0415" n="299" xml:id="pg_299"/> under
                                the direction of an American manager. Mr. Roscoe Kent, an
                                experienced operator, has been selected for this work, and is ready
                                to enter upon his duties when a suitable contract can be agreed
                                upon. The compensation of this officer is to be three hundred
                                dollars, gold, a month, and two hundred dollars traveling expenses,
                                each way, from his home in the United States to Santo Domingo. He is
                                to be allowed thirty days’ leave of absence each year, exclusive of
                                the time occupied in traveling from Santo Domingo to New York City
                                and return.</p>
                            <p>In order to insure an efficient service, it is necessary that the
                                superintendent of the wireless and land telegraph and telephone
                                systems shall be free to employ and discharge all subordinates; and
                                that he shall be removed from office by the Dominican Government
                                before the expiration of his contract only for proven incompetency
                                or for malfeasance in office, and it is extremely desirable that in
                                the event of his discharge written charges should be filed at the
                                American Legation for transmission to the Department of State for
                                its consideration, it being understood that the appointee shall not
                                be removed by the Dominican Government without the approval of the
                                Department of State.</p>
                            <p>This contract, as well as the one with Mr. Collett, the Director
                                General of Public Works, should be for three years, renewable,
                                however, with the consent of both parties.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>