<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-01-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-01-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="32" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d32">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Treaty Series No. 606.]</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">By the President of the United States of
                                America.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p rend="center">A PROCLAMATION.</p>
                        <p>Whereas, a Treaty between the United States of America and the Republic
                            of Bolivia looking to the advancement of the cause of general peace was
                            concluded and signed by their respective Plenipotentiaries at
                            Washington, on the twenty-second day of January, one thousand nine
                            hundred and fourteen, the original of which Treaty, being in the English
                            and Spanish languages, is word for word as follows:</p>
                        <p>The United States of America and the Republic of Bolivia, being desirous
                            to strengthen the bonds of amity that bind them together and also to
                            advance the cause of general peace, have resolved to enter into a treaty
                            for that purpose, and to that end have appointed as their
                            plenipotentiaries: <list>
                                <item>The President of the United States, the Honorable William
                                    Jennings Bryan, Secretary of State; and</item>
                                <item>The President of Bolivia, Senor Don Ignacio Calderon, Envoy
                                    Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of Bolivia to the
                                    United States;</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Who, after having communicated to each other their respective full
                            powers, found to be in proper form, have agreed upon and concluded the
                            following articles:</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Article I</hi>.</p>
                        <p>The High Contracting Parties agree that all disputes between them, of
                            every nature whatsoever, to the settlement of which previous arbitration
                            treaties or agreements do not apply in their terms or are not applied in
                            fact, shall, when diplomatic methods of adjustment have failed, be
                            referred for investigation and report to a permanent International
                            Commission, to be constituted in the manner prescribed in the next
                            succeeding article; and they agree not to declare war or begin
                            hostilities during such investigation and before the report is
                            submitted.</p>
                        <pb facs="0147" n="31" xml:id="pg_31"/>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Article II</hi>.</p>
                        <p>The International Commission shall be composed of five members, to be
                            appointed as follows: One member shall be chosen from each country, by
                            the Government thereof; one member shall be chosen by each Government
                            from some third country; the fifth member shall be chosen by common
                            agreement between the two Governments, it being understood that he shall
                            not be a citizen of either country. Each of the High Contracting Parties
                            shall have the right to remove, at any time before investigation begins,
                            any Commissioner selected by it and to name his successor, and under the
                            same conditions shall also have the right to withdraw its approval of
                            the fifth Commissioner selected jointly; in which case a new
                            Commissioner shall be selected jointly as in the original selection. The
                            Commissioners shall, when actually employed in the investigation of a
                            dispute, receive such compensation as shall be agreed upon by the High
                            Contracting Parties. The expenses of the Commission shall be paid by the
                            two Governments in equal proportion.</p>
                        <p>The International Commission shall be appointed as soon as possible after
                            the exchange of the ratifications of this treaty; and vacancies shall be
                            filled according to the manner of the original appointment.</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Article III</hi>.</p>
                        <p>In case the High Contracting Parties shall have failed to adjust a
                            dispute by diplomatic methods, they shall at once refer it to the
                            International Commission for investigation and report. The International
                            Commission may, however, by unanimous agreement spontaneously offer its
                            services to that effect, and in such case it shall notify both
                            Governments and request their cooperation in the investigation.</p>
                        <p>The High Contracting Parties agree to furnish the Permanent International
                            Commission with all the means and facilities required for its
                            investigation and report.</p>
                        <p>The report of the International Commission shall be completed within one
                            year after the date on which it shall declare its investigation to have
                            begun, unless the High Contracting Parties shall limit or extend the
                            time by mutual agreement. The report shall be prepared in triplicate;
                            one copy shall be presented to each Government, and the third retained
                            by the Commission for its files.</p>
                        <p>The High Contracting Parties reserve the right to act independently on
                            the subject matter of the dispute after the report of the Commission
                            shall have been submitted.</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Article IV</hi>.</p>
                        <p>The present treaty shall be ratified by the President of the United
                            States of America, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate
                            thereof; and by the President of Bolivia, with the approval of the
                            Congress thereof; and the ratifications shall be exchanged as soon as
                            possible. It shall take effect immediately after the exchange of
                            ratifications, and shall continue in force for a period of five years;
                            and it shall thereafter remain in force until twelve months after one
                                <pb facs="0148" n="32" xml:id="pg_32"/> of the High Contracting
                            Parties have given notice to the other of an intention to terminate
                            it.</p>
                        <p>In witness whereof the respective plenipotentiaries have signed the
                            present treaty and have affixed thereunto their seals.</p>
                        <p>Done in Washington on the 22d day of January, in the year of our Lord
                            nineteen hundred and fourteen.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">William Jennings Bryan</hi> [<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>]</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ignacio Calderon</hi> [<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>]</p>
                        <p>And whereas, the said Treaty has been duly ratified on both parts and the
                            ratifications of the two Governments were exchanged in the City of
                            Washington on the eighth day of January, one thousand nine hundred and
                            fifteen;</p>
                        <p>Now, therefore, be it known that I, Woodrow Wilson, President of the
                            United States of America, have caused the said Treaty to be made public
                            to the end that the same and every article and clause thereof may be
                            observed and fulfilled with good faith by the United States and the
                            citizens thereof.</p>
                        <p>In testimony whereof, I have hereunto set my hand and caused the seal of
                            the United States to be affixed.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <seg type="margin">[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal</hi>.]</seg> Done at
                                the City of <placeName>Washington</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian us-republic" when="1915-01-09">this ninth
                                    day of January in the year of our Lord one thousand nine hundred
                                    and fifteen, and of the Independence of the United States of
                                    America the one hundred and thirty-ninth</date>.</dateline>
                            <lb/>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Woodrow Wilson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>By the President: <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">W. J. Bryan</hi>: <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State.</hi>
                            </p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>