<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Chargé Summerlin to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1915</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d35</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">35</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1915-06-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1915-06-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-06-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-06-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="35"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d35">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 825.02/9.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Chargé <persName type="from">Summerlin</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 642.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Santiago</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-06-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 15, 1915</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that the President of
                    the Republic opened the ordinary sessions of the Congress on the first instant *
                    * * at which the President’s Message was read. Copies of the Message, with
                    translations of the most important passages, are enclosed herewith. * * *</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">George T. Summerlin.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure—Translation—Extract.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-inferred-from-preceding-sibling-head"
                        >[Untitled]</head>
                    <p>The friendly mediation of the Argentine, Brazilian and Chilean Governments in
                        the conflict stirred up between the United States of America and the
                        Government of General Huerta in the Republic of Mexico, which was so
                        successful at the Niagara Falls conferences, has been an eloquent testimony
                        of the solidarity spirit which governs the relations of the American
                        peoples.</p>
                    <p>Inspired by the same sentiment of Pan-Americanism which led them to tender
                        their good offices on that occasion, the Governments of these three
                        Republics agreed upon an interchange of visits between their Ministers for
                        Foreign Affairs in order to contribute by a public act of cordiality to the
                        drawing closer of their relations.</p>
                    <p>In fulfilling this agreement the capital of the Republic has had the honor of
                        receiving the Ministers for Foreign Affairs of Brazil and Argentina, Messrs.
                        Lauro Müller and José Luis Murature; and the Minister for Foreign Affairs,
                        Mr. Alejandro Lira, has visited Buenos Aires.</p>
                    <p>The enthusiastic and warm welcome which these three representatives met in
                        Santiago and Buenos Aires is a frank manifestation that the diplomatic
                        action of the Governments has faithfully interpreted the sentiment of the
                        people, and that the policy of approximation so happily initiated is a solid
                        guaranty of peace for the American Republics and of respect for their
                        rights, the most vital of which is the integrity of the Continent.</p>
                    <p>As a practical result of this international act, a treaty between the three
                        Republics was signed in Buenos Aires on the 25th of May last, destined to
                        strengthen the cordial understanding which unites them and which establishes
                        a formula, inspired by the Bryan Peace Treaty, for the solution of questions
                        which might arise among them.</p>
                    <p>Upon the initiative of the Government of the United States, our Government
                        raised its diplomatic representation in that country to the rank of Embassy,
                        and we continue to cultivate a constantly closer friendship with that
                        country.</p>
                    <p>In order to increase the means of solving through juridical channels the
                        differences that might arise between the nations, the Secretary of State of
                            <pb facs="0152" n="36" xml:id="pg_36"/> the American Government, Mr.
                        Bryan, submitted to the diplomatic representatives accredited in Washington
                        a proposed treaty which was given the frankest acceptance by the
                        Governments. Our Government, simultaneously with those of Argentina and
                        Brazil, signed a treaty of this nature with the Government of the United
                        States, which desired to invest this act with special solemnity.</p>
                    <p>We have signed a similar treaty with the Government of Uruguay.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
