<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Hartman to the Secretary of State..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1915</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d356</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">356</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1915-10-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1915-10-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-10-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-10-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="356"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d356">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 422.11G93/824.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Hartman</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 145.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Quito</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-10-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 19, 1915</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the Department’s telegram of October
                    11, 1915, 6 p.m., and to my telegram of October 13, 3 p.m., I have the honor to
                    make the following report.</p>
                <p>The first information this Legation received that the Congress of Ecuador was
                    even considering such a resolution was furnished it on the evening of October 6,
                    when a translation of the resolution, and of the report of the mixed committee
                    reporting the same was delivered to the Legation. At the same time the Legation
                    was informed that the resolutions had been considered in secret joint session of
                    the Congress, but that they would probably be considered in open session before
                    the close of Congress, which was to, and did, close on October 8. Accordingly,
                    on October 7 I personally called upon President Plaza, brought the matter to his
                    attention and requested him to use his good offices to prevent the passage of
                    the resolutions. His answer to that request was that he would speak to Dr.
                    Baquerizo Moreno, the President of the Senate, leaving the <pb facs="0478"
                        n="362" xml:id="pg_362"/> implication that his remarks to Dr. Baquerizo
                    Moreno would be in harmony with my request.</p>
                <p>The next information I received on the subject was that the resolutions had
                    passed Congress at 11 o’clock on the morning of October 8.</p>
                <p>Immediately upon receipt of the Department’s telegram of October 11, I prepared
                    and delivered to the Minister for Foreign Affairs my note No. 154 of October 13,
                    1915, of which copies are herewith enclosed. To this note no answer has yet been
                    received.</p>
                <p>I also enclose herewith for the information of the Department Spanish copies of
                    the resolutions and the committee report thereon, with translation.</p>
                <p>I respectfully point out to the Department that the first paragraph of its
                    telegram above mentioned is not entirely sustained by the resolutions in this,
                    that the resolutions do not instruct the Defensor Fiscal to embargo the
                    properties of the Railway Company in order to obtain immediate possession
                    thereof. But the statement is sufficiently accurate, and certainly all the facts
                    make a case which justify the protest made. Indeed, I should have felt entirely
                    warranted in filing a note of protest even in the absence of any instruction
                    from the Department.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Chas. S. Hartman</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Hartman</persName> to the
                                <gloss type="to">Minister of Foreign Affairs</gloss>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 154.]</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Quito</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-10-13">
                                <hi rend="italic">October 13, 1915</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: In compliance with telegraphic
                        instructions from my Government, I have the honor respectfully to invite
                        your excellency’s attention to the following important subject, and to
                        submit some views of my Government in relation thereto.</p>
                    <p>The fact of the passage by the Ecuadorian Congress of a resolution declaring
                        that arbitration of differences between the Government of Ecuador and the
                        Guayaquil &amp; Quito Railway Company under the arbitration agreement
                        stipulated for previously has lapsed, and instructing the Fiscal Attorney,
                        in agreement with the Minister of Public Works, to bring and prosecute suit
                        against the Railway Company in the courts of Ecuador, has been brought to
                        the knowledge of the Department of State at Washington.</p>
                    <p>That action of this nature should have been taken by the Congress of Ecuador
                        is a matter of great surprise to the Government of the United States; and in
                        pursuance of my instructions it becomes my duty to make formal and earnest
                        protest to your excellency’s Government against such action, which, if
                        persisted in, would make it necessary for my Government to consider the
                        adoption of such measures as will give adequate protection to this American
                        corporation in its just rights.</p>
                    <p>That the Government of Ecuador should entertain or consider taking such a
                        step is all the more surprising to the Department of State of my Government
                        at this time when the exercise of its good offices has been requested to
                        assist Ecuador in securing a loan in the United States, where the obvious
                        effect of the reported proceedings against the Railway Company will be
                        highly detrimental.</p>
                    <p>Your excellency’s well known high sense of just, equitable, and fair dealing
                        induces me to believe, with great confidence that your excellency will after
                        due deliberation agree with me, that the action of the Ecuadorian Congress
                        above mentioned was unwarranted and unjustified and not in harmony with the
                        customary friendly relations which, I am glad to say, have existed for so
                        long a time between our respective Governments.</p>
                    <p>I avail [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chas. S. Hartman</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0479" n="363" xml:id="pg_363"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolution passed by Congress October 8, 1915</hi>.</head>
                    <p>Whereas the legal term of six months having expired within which the
                        Arbitrators Alfredo Baquerizo Moreno and A. L. Miller should have pronounced
                        on the controversy between the Government of Ecuador and the Guayaquil &amp;
                        Quito Railway Company respecting said railway, the arbitration agreement has
                        lapsed; and</p>
                    <p>Whereas the arbitration agreement having lapsed, legal jurisdiction is
                        restored, according to Article 77 and Clause 2 of Article 82 of the Organic
                        Law of the Judicial Power. Therefore be it</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolved by the Congress of the Republic of Ecuador:</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Article 1. The Fiscal Attorney, in agreement with the Minister of
                                Public Works, shall bring suit to compel the said Company to fulfill
                                its obligations to Ecuador; without prejudice, however, to the
                                negotiation of bases for an extrajudicial settlement or of bases for
                                a new arbitration not open to the objections made to the previous
                                one, said bases to be submitted to the Congress for its
                                approval.</item>
                            <item>Article 2. With due reserve of rights and until final judgment is
                                rendered, the Executive may provisionally agree with the Railway
                                Company upon a friendly and equitable administration and operation
                                of the railway, disbursement of the proceeds thereof, and
                                application of contract provisions not in conflict with said
                                agreement.</item>
                            <item>Article 3. The Executive shall publish in the national and foreign
                                press the facts giving rise to the said controversy and the history
                                thereof, and shall disburse for the purpose, out of the
                                extraordinary expense fund, the amount necessary.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
