<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-04-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-04-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="408" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d408">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 702.6211/218.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Governor <persName type="from">Lister</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Olympia, Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-04-12">
                                    <hi rend="italic">April 12, 1915</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Replying to your telegram of April 5, in
                            relation to the arrest by local authorities, of the German Consul and
                            his secretary at Seattle, Washington, I beg to say that on April 6, I
                            wrote the Prosecuting Attorney of King County, in which county the city
                            of Seattle is located, and enclosed to him a copy of your telegram
                            requesting that he make reply to same. Under date of April 8, I received
                            a letter from the Prosecuting Attorney of King County, a copy of which I
                            herewith enclose, feeling that this letter is probably a clearer
                            explanation of the” situation than I would make if I endeavored to cover
                            it in my letter.</p>
                        <p>I am sure that no further action will be taken by the Prosecuting
                            Attorney until we have again had opportunity to hear from you. I shall
                            be pleased indeed to hear from you further regarding the situation and
                            you can be assured will do what I can to assist in avoiding any
                            embarrassment of an international character.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ernest Lister</hi>.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Prosecuting Attorney <persName type="from">Lundin</persName> to Governor <persName type="to">Lister</persName></hi>.</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Seattle, Wash.</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-04-08">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Apr. 8, 1915</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">My dear Sir</hi>: Your letter of April 6,
                                enclosing copy of a telegram dated April 5, from W. J. Bryan,
                                Secretary of State, received.</p>
                            <p>The German Consul Müller, his Secretary Schulz, and one Tarnasky, are
                                charged by information in the superior court of this county with the
                                crime of conspiracy, the charge being that they conspired together
                                to corrupt John Murdock, the agent of the Seattle Dry Dock &amp;
                                Construction Co. This is a gross misdemeanor under our law. Tarnasky
                                made a complete confession of the conspiracy. The agent Murdock was
                                to receive $1,000 or $1,500 which the German Consul told him had
                                been telegraphed for. The agent had taken from the Construction
                                Company’s files and had concealed in his home copies of way bills.
                                Some five conferences were had between the agent and the Consul’s
                                representative, the last of which was with the German Consul
                                himself.</p>
                            <p>The agent of the Construction Company was a clear cut, reliable young
                                man of twenty-one years, and his reputation and standing have been
                                ruined by virtue of this conspiracy to bribe him.</p>
                            <p>My investigation shows that this is not the only instance in which
                                the German Consul has attempted bribery of this nature.</p>
                            <p>This office has given much consideration to the provisions of the
                                judiciary act referred to, and we admit that jurisdiction of the
                                State’s courts in this matter <pb facs="0524" n="408" xml:id="pg_408"/> is not clear. However, the matter has not been
                                settled, and it was our intention to submit the question of
                                jurisdiction to the court.</p>
                            <p>It is not my desire to cause any embarrassment to the Government of
                                the United States, nor would I, as Prosecuting Attorney of this
                                county, assume to interfere with diplomatic relations between the
                                United States and another country. If, therefore, the State
                                Department feels, after being fully acquainted with all the facts,
                                that the prosecution of the German Consul and his secretary will
                                embarrass the United States in the diplomatic relations with Germany
                                and accordingly requests me to discontinue the prosecution of this
                                case, I will consider it my duty to be governed by such request. If
                                this is done, however, and the Consul is allowed to continue in his
                                official capacity in Seattle, it would seem to me that this State
                                ought to have some positive assurance that his future conduct would
                                be in accordance with the laws of the State.</p>
                            <p>This information was filed March 17; The Consul put up a bond for his
                                appearance, and nothing further has been done in the case. Our laws
                                provide the trial must be had in sixty days after the filing of the
                                information, and it is necessary that the preliminary steps be taken
                                at once. Therefore, whatever action is taken in this matter, must be
                                in the very near future.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Alfred H. Lundin</hi>.</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>