<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-09-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="47" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d47">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.01/35.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Chargé <persName type="from">MacMurray</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 747.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-09-07">
                                    <hi rend="italic">September 7, 1915</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my telegrams of August 25,
                            September 2 and September 4, on the subject of the agitation in favor of
                            a restoration of the monarchical form of government in China, I have the
                            honor to report as follows:</p>
                        <p>For some months past there have been rumors, vague at first, but becoming
                            gradually more definite, that President Yuan Shih-k’ai was maturing a
                            plan for the transformation of the Republic into a monarchy, and taking
                            the throne as the founder of a new dynasty. From several usually
                            trustworthy sources I received, as early as mid-June, information to the
                            effect that the Committee of Ten, entrusted with the drafting of the
                            permanent Constitution, was being carefully “handpicked” with a view to
                            its embodying in the Constitution provisions for the reestablishment of
                            a monarchy, and then demanding that the Legislature, which would in due
                            course have been selected with like care, should be convened in order
                            that it might in the name of the people of China decide whether or not
                            the proposed change in the form of government should be made—the
                            President meanwhile deprecating, with the appropriate degree of
                            earnestness, any action tending to force on him responsibilities more
                            lofty than he had assumed as President of the Republic. Despite the
                            character of the sources from which this information reached me, I
                            attached slight importance to it at the time, believing that while
                            certain influences might be intriguing to that end, it was scarcely
                            credible that so shrewd a politician as the President should choose for
                            such a purpose (even if he entertained it) a time when the personnel of
                            the Government was engaged in bitter factional strife, when the finances
                            of the country were being carried on in hand-to-mouth fashion, when the
                            balance of power in China was destroyed by the European War, when new
                            revolutionary movements were believed to be forming, and when the
                            prestige of his administration was suffering from the yielding of the
                            concessions which the Japanese Government had demanded and enforced by
                            its ultimatum of May 7. Such plans as were being made were in fact
                            worked out with a degree of secrecy altogether unusual in this country;
                            and for some weeks there appeared to be no concrete indications tending
                            to confirm the reports referred to above.</p>
                        <p>The first tangible evidence of anything stirring beneath the., surface
                            was an interview (of which the account given in the Peking Gazette of
                            July 7 is enclosed herewith)<note n="17" xml:id="d47fn17">Not
                                printed.</note> in which the President rebuked General Feng
                            Kuo-chang, military governor of Kiangsu Province, for urging upon him
                            the suggestion that he assume the throne. This abjuration said so much
                            more than would have been necessary to a staged disclaimer of any
                            monarchical aspirations, that it had all the appearance of
                            genuineness.</p>
                        <p>The next development in the movement was associated with the coming of
                            the American Constitutional Adviser, Dr. Frank J. Goodnow, <pb facs="0165" n="49" xml:id="pg_49"/> who had returned to Peking in
                            the middle of July for a short visit. Shortly after his arrival, Dr.
                            Goodnow was asked by the President to prepare for his own information a
                            memorandum on the respective merits of the republican and monarchical
                            forms of government, with particular reference to conditions in China.
                            In entire good faith, though, as the event has proved, with perhaps too
                            little wariness as to the use which might be made of it, Dr. Goodnow, in
                            response to this request, prepared a memorandum (of which a copy, as
                            printed in the <hi rend="italic">Peking Daily News</hi> of August 20 is
                            enclosed herewith<note n="a" xml:id="d47fn1">Inclosure 1.</note>) in
                            which he outspokenly set forth the view that theoretically and in the
                            abstract the monarchical form is the better suited to the genius and
                            traditions and present political development of the Chinese, but
                            expressly disclaimed any judgment on the question whether the conditions
                            actually existing would render feasible or expedient a change from the
                            republican to the monarchical system. I understand that he also
                            discussed the matter with the President in the same sense, making it
                            clear that as a question of practical politics the matter involved
                            considerations of fact as to which no foreigner is competent to form a
                            judgment, and which must be decided by those responsible for the
                            destinies of the country.</p>
                        <p>At the end of the second week of August, a monarchical propaganda,
                            professedly based upon Dr. Goodnow’s advice, was begun with an amazing
                            suddenness that appears to indicate careful preparation in advance. In
                            spite of the reservations with which Dr. Goodnow had qualified his
                            memorandum for the President, it began to be quoted in the Chinese press
                            (as cited in the enclosed clipping from the <hi rend="italic">Peking
                                Gazette</hi> of August 14)<note n="17" xml:id="d47fn18">Not
                                printed.</note> as maintaining categorically the bald thesis that “a
                            monarchical system of government is better than a republican system”;
                            and he was thenceforward referred to as supporting or even as having
                            inspired the monarchical movement. On August 16 there appeared in the
                            press the manifesto of an organization calling itself the Ch’ou An Hui
                            or Peace Planning Society, newly formed for the purpose of “devising
                            means for keeping peace in this country” and for expounding “views
                            concerning the future of our country and the advantages and
                            disadvantages accruing from the republican form of government,” which
                            was based upon the declaration that “Dr. Goodnow has stated that a
                            monarchy is a better form of government than republicanism, and
                            according to his opinion a monarchical form of government is most
                            indispensable at present for China”. (For translation see enclosed
                            clipping from the <hi rend="italic">Peking Gazette</hi> of August
                                16).<note n="b" xml:id="d47fn2">Inclosure 2.</note> Dr. Goodnow
                            found it necessary to repudiate the views thus attributed to him, in an
                            interview which appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Peking Gazette</hi> of
                            August 18 (of which a copy is enclosed herewith);<note n="c" xml:id="d47fn3">Inclosure 3.</note> and with the permission of the
                            President he also caused the full text of his memorandum to be published
                            in the <hi rend="italic">Peking Daily News</hi> of August 20. Even the
                            publication of his memorandum, however, did not put an end to the
                            misquotation of his views by the adherents of the Ch’ou An Hui, who
                            continued to refer to his advice in support of their propaganda; and <pb facs="0166" n="50" xml:id="pg_50"/> as late as August 24, in the
                            society’s circular telegram to which reference is made hereafter, Dr.
                            Goodnow’s views were cited in a passage of which the following is a
                            translation made by the Chinese Secretary of the Legation: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>The United States is the foremost Republic in the world. Dr.
                                    Goodnow, the great American scholar in the science of
                                    government, says that a monarchy is really better than a
                                    republic, and that China especially cannot do without the
                                    monarchical form of government. This opinion is held not only by
                                    Dr. Goodnow, but by many other well-known scholars. As Dr.
                                    Goodnow is a citizen of a republic, he is very familiar with
                                    both the advantages and failures of the republican form of
                                    government. Moreover, he says that conditions in America and
                                    China are different, and that the institutions of the one
                                    country cannot be forcibly transplanted to the other.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Dr. Goodnow consequently found himself placed in a false light, and in
                            order to clear up his position he brought pressure to bear upon certain
                            of his official associates who were in a position to influence the
                            leaders of the Ch’ou An Hui, with the result that a notice to the
                            following effect was published in the Chinese press on August 28: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>With reference to the discussion of the question “Monarchy or
                                    Republic”, Dr. Goodnow has made no statement other than that
                                    contained in the memorandum which he presented to the President.
                                    Lest there should be any apprehension on the subject, we hereby
                                    specially issue this notice.</p>
                                <p rend="right">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Ch’ou An Hui.</hi>
                                </p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>In the earliest days of its formation, the Ch’ou An Hui was scarcely
                            taken seriously by outside observers. Even when there was published an
                            interview (of which the translation appearing in the <hi rend="italic">Peking Gazette of</hi> August 17 is enclosed herewith)<note n="17" xml:id="d47fn19">Not printed.</note> in which the President,
                            referring to the activities of that society, said <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>As to the people of the country * * * it is quite reasonable for
                                    them to discuss the best method which will ensure them permanent
                                    peace and happiness. * * * How can I interfere with such a
                                    movement, merely for the reason that such a movement would tend
                                    to misrepresent me to the public as a person who entertains some
                                    doubtful and suspicious ambition? * * * If it does not tend to
                                    disturb the order of the country, there is no necessity for the
                                    Government to take measures to interfere with it—</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">even then, the apparent inopportuneness of the times,
                            the comparative obscurity of those who were known as its adherents, and
                            the shallowness and obvious insincerity of its propaganda, all tended to
                            induce the belief that the movement was no more than a <hi rend="italic">ballon d’essai</hi>—an activity which the President countenanced,
                            perhaps with a view to its revealing whether or not the temper of the
                            country would admit of such a possibility now or at some later occasion,
                            but which he in all probability regarded as a means of quieting the
                            enthusiasts and the sycophants by letting them batter their heads
                            against an impossibility.</p>
                        <p>But meanwhile the Ch’ou An Hui throve immensely. In addition to the
                            original manifesto (quoted in the enclosure from the <hi rend="italic">Peking Gazette of</hi> the 16th ultimo), it issued a prospectus and
                            notifications (which are enclosed herewith in translation from the <hi rend="italic">Peking Gazette</hi> of August 21)<note n="17" xml:id="d47fn20">Not printed.</note> and a circular telegram to the
                            civil and military governors of the provinces, to the lieutenant
                            generals, and to the chambers of commerce and popular bodies of the
                            provinces, expressing the belief that the republican form of government
                            is not <pb facs="0167" n="51" xml:id="pg_51"/> suitable to China (of
                            which a translation, as printed in the <hi rend="italic">Peking Daily
                                News</hi> of the 25th ultimo is enclosed herewith);<note n="17" xml:id="d47fn21">Not printed.</note> and its chief promoter, Mr.
                            Young Tu, published an elaborate “Defense of the Monarchical Movement”
                            (of which I enclose a translation as printed in the <hi rend="italic">Peking Daily News</hi>, of August 26, 27 and 28);<note n="17" xml:id="d47fn22">Not printed.</note> it attained the distinction of
                            having its leaders interviewed by Mr. B. L. Simpson (Putnam Weale); it
                            acquired the rather more substantial dignity of having its views and
                            purposes contested with eloquent and apparently sincerely patriotic
                            earnestness by Mr. Liang Ch’i-ch’iao, recently Minister of Justice, in
                            an interview printed in the <hi rend="italic">Peking Gazette</hi> of the
                            31st ultimo (of which a copy is enclosed),<note n="17" xml:id="d47fn23">Not printed.</note> and in an article (of which a translation, as
                            printed in the <hi rend="italic">Gazette</hi> of September 4 and 6, is
                                enclosed);<note n="17" xml:id="d47fn24">Not printed.</note> and,
                            most important of all, it contrived to receive from the civil and
                            military governors and others, to whom its circular was addressed, most
                            encouragingly acquiescent replies—which, for the most part, embody the
                            ideas and the terms which the society professed to quote from the
                            memorandum which Dr. Goodnow had submitted for the information of
                            President Yuan. There were obstacles to the progress of the society;
                            according to a report quoted in the <hi rend="italic">Peking
                                Gazette</hi> of August 23 (of which a copy is enclosed),<note n="17" xml:id="d47fn25">Not printed.</note> the President in conversation
                            with the Secretary of State, on August 19, discreetly discountenanced
                            the movement by declaring, <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>If a few shortsighted people attempt to compel me to adopt an
                                    unrighteous course I shall have no alternative but to take
                                    refuge in a foreign land, as I cannot break my solemn oath;</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">and about the same time there was talk of an impeachment
                            to be lodged against its members by the censorate, on the ground of
                            their indulging in a movement subversive of the existing Government; but
                            the chief censor had found it expedient to get to one of the foreign
                            concessions in Tientsin before it was even known to the general public
                            that this suggestion had originated with him.</p>
                        <p>It has now appeared that, back of all this rather puerile agitation on
                            the part of the Ch’ou An Hui, there has been the substantial fact that
                            the President himself, his eldest son, Yuan K’o-ting, and the most
                            powerful civil official in China, Liang Shih-yi, and the most
                            influential military leader, Feng Kuo-chang, have planned and worked for
                            the reinstitution of a monarchical régime with President Yuan as
                            emperor. That is a fact which, for my own part, I must acknowledge
                            having doubted perhaps longer than the evidence warranted; it has now
                            been made indubitable, not only by the indirect testimony of colleagues
                            and of press correspondents and other unofficial sources of information,
                            but also by the direct statements of certain Cabinet Ministers, who have
                            discussed the matter with the President and learned his views
                            authoritatively and at first-hand. As I reported in my telegram of
                            September 4, the majority of the Cabinet and of the other officials of
                            greatest influence are (or have been) in favor of the movement.</p>
                        <p>On the evening of Saturday, the 4th instant, one of the Cabinet Ministers
                            who called to see Dr. Tenney and myself on another matter took occasion
                            to say that he had that morning conferred with <pb facs="0168" n="52" xml:id="pg_52"/> the President in reference to the plans for the
                            reestablishment of a monarchy; and that, whereas President Yuan had up
                            to a few days previously been whole-heartedly in favor of forcing the
                            movement through without delay, he was now “much less enthusiastic”, and
                            determined to proceed, if at all, with the utmost circumspection. My
                            informant went on to say that the reason for this change was doubtless
                            the apprehension that the foreign Powers might withhold their
                            recognition of the new Government, and that Japan, particularly, might
                            exact terms in consideration of its recognition of the new order. He
                            then offered the naive surmise that perhaps this difficulty might be
                            avoided by simply announcing that the appropriate lawmaking body of
                            China had determined to confer upon the President the title of Emperor,
                            and that at some convenient time thereafter the Constitution might, as a
                            matter of purely domestic concern, be so amended as to make the
                            presidency hereditary.</p>
                        <p>Fantastic as these suggestions sound, they seem to accord with the
                            present attitude of those in authority. It appears that the Chinese
                            official mind accepts, without any sense of anomaly, the idea of a
                            hereditary presidency as forming the happiest possible solution of the
                            problem of the succession, which has been brought so persistently to
                            public notice by the propaganda of the Ch’ou An Hui.</p>
                        <p>It would seem that by the mere fact of having created a general
                            impression that something in the present system of government requires
                            modification, that society has now exhausted its usefulness to the
                            purpose in view, and its activities will probably be allowed to dwindle.
                            So nearly as can be judged from the reports as to the present mood of
                            the President, and from the message which was communicated by him
                            yesterday to the Council of State (Tsan Cheng Yuan), sitting as a
                            legislative body pending the establishment of the Li Fa Yuan,<note n="18" xml:id="d47fn27">See infra.</note> the present intention is
                            not to establish the new régime by a <hi rend="italic">coup d’état</hi>,
                            as a few days ago seemed likely, but to leave the matter for decision
                            and adjustment by processes at least superficially constitutional.</p>
                        <p>Concerning the attitude of the Chinese people towards the contemplated
                            change, it is still too early to generalize with assurance. It would be
                            naïve to take without discount the expressions of approval which have
                            been telegraphed, in really considerable volume, by the provincial
                            authorities and by popular bodies of all sorts in the provinces, in
                            reply to the circular of the Ch’ou An Hui; their spontaneity is more
                            than questionable; and in the great majority of cases they must be
                            assumed to represent not a conviction that the monarchical system is the
                            best for the country, but a calculation that that system is the more
                            likely to prevail. It should be noted, however, that among the younger
                            officials—the foreign-educated class, which has hitherto been more or
                            less directly associated with the republican movement,—there has been
                            observable an unmistakable tendency to regard with sympathy, if not with
                            active approval, the idea of reversion to a monarchy. On the other hand,
                            such opposition as has thus far appeared has seemed to be wholly
                            academic and forensic, giving no evidence of any likelihood of serious
                            resistance. There is of course a considerable revolutionary <pb facs="0169" n="53" xml:id="pg_53"/> element which may be expected to
                            take what advantage it can of the discontent which such action would
                            cause; but among both foreign and Chinese observers it seems generally
                            to be believed that the Government has the situation well enough in hand
                            to assure that no revolutionary movement is likely to gain headway or to
                            pass beyond the stage of mere local disturbances—unless abetted and
                            assisted by Japan. The great bulk of the people may, I believe, be
                            assumed to be indifferent to the question of the form of government so
                            long as it does not undertake to govern them too rigorously or tax them
                            too much.</p>
                        <p>With a view to learning the character and effects of the monarchical
                            movement in the provinces, the Legation on August 25 despatched to the
                            consuls a circular directing them to report on the subject. Replies have
                            thus far been received, as follows: Antung, Hankow, Mukden, Nanking and
                            Shanghai. In order to put the Department in possession of all available
                            information at as early a date as possible, I forward copies of these
                                reports<note n="17" xml:id="d47fn26">Not printed.</note> without
                            waiting to coordinate them with those which are still to be
                            received.</p>
                        <p>It has proved difficult to learn with accuracy the views of the several
                            other Legations here. In general, I think it may be said that they
                            regard the contemplated change in the form of government without
                            particular concern, feeling their policies wholly unaffected by it
                            unless in the event that it should lead to disorders detrimental to
                            trade and jeopardizing foreign interests; for the rest, the general
                            feeling is that if the Chinese find it possible to reinstitute their
                            traditional form of government, without bringing on revolution or
                            bankruptcy or foreign intervention, so much the better. But opinions
                            differ as to the feasibility of bringing about the change without those
                            consequences. * * *</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">J. V. A. MacMurray.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName type="from">Goodnow</persName>’s
                                    Memorandum to the <gloss type="to">President</gloss></hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#center">[From the <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Peking</placeName> Daily News</hi> of <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-08-20">August 20,
                                        1915</date>.]</dateline></opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">monarchies originate with one man.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The determination in a given country of the form of government
                                established therein has seldom if ever been the result of the
                                conscious choice of the people of that country or even of the choice
                                of its most intelligent classes. The establishment on the one hand
                                of a monarchy or on the other hand of a republic has in almost all
                                instances been due to influences almost beyond human control. The
                                former history of the country, its traditions, its social and
                                economic conditions all have either favored the form of government
                                which has been adopted or, in case the form of government at first
                                adopted has not been in harmony therewith, have soon brought it
                                about that that form is replaced by one which is better suited to
                                the country’s needs.</p>
                            <p>In other words, the form of government which a country usually
                                possesses is for the most part determined by the necessities of
                                practical life. Among the contributing causes which fix forms of
                                government, one of the most important is force. Almost all
                                monarchies thus owe their origin in last analysis to the exertions
                                of some one man who has been able to organize the material power of
                                the country in such a way as to overcome all competitors. If he has
                                able sons or male relatives, if he has ruled wisely and if the
                                conditions of the <pb facs="0170" n="54" xml:id="pg_54"/> country
                                have been such as to favor monarchical rule, he may be able to
                                establish a dynasty which will during a long period successfully
                                govern the country.</p>
                            <p>Under such conditions one of the most perplexing problems of
                                government is probably more satisfactorily solved than has usually
                                been the case in republics. For on the death of the monarch there is
                                no question as to the succession to the executive power. No election
                                or other method of choosing a successor is necessary. As the English
                                law expresses it: “The King is dead, Long live the King.” In order,
                                however, that the desired result may be attained, it is absolutely
                                necessary that the law of succession be clearly determined and
                                practically universally accepted. Else the death of the monarch will
                                bring into being numerous aspirants for the throne whose conflicting
                                claims can be adjudicated only by resort to civil war.</p>
                            <p>History would seem to prove, furthermore, that the only permanently
                                satisfactory solution of the question of succession in monarchical
                                states is that which has been reached by the States of Europe. This
                                consists in fixing the succession to the throne upon the eldest son
                                of the monarch or in default of sons, upon the nearest eldest male
                                relative. Under this method he who is by the law of succession
                                entitled to the throne is permitted to waive his rights, in which
                                case, if it is the eldest son who has so waived his rights, the next
                                eldest son takes his place.</p>
                            <p>If some such method of fixing the succession is not adopted, if for
                                example the succession to the throne is left to the determination of
                                the monarch, who may choose as his successor a son not the eldest,
                                or some other relative not the nearest eldest male relative the
                                uncertainty as to the succession is almost certain to produce
                                trouble. Palace intrigues in favor of the various claimants to the
                                throne are sure to develop which both embitter the closing days of
                                the monarch’s life and often lead to confusion if not civil war
                                after his death.</p>
                            <p>The advantages which history would seem to show are attendant upon a
                                monarchy as compared with a republic, so far as concerns this
                                important question of succession to the executive power, are thus,
                                it would seem, conditioned very largely upon the adoption of that
                                law of succession which experience has shown to be the best, that
                                is, succession in the eldest nearest male line.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">european republics.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Until recently the accepted form of government both in Asia and
                                Europe was monarchical. It is true that in Europe, contrary to the
                                usual rule there were a few republics such as Venice and
                                Switzerland. But the States possessing a republican government were
                                few in number and small in size. In almost all the important States
                                of the world the government was monarchical in character.</p>
                            <p>Within the last hundred and fifty years, however, there is noticeable
                                among European peoples a distinct movement away from monarchical and
                                in favor of republican government. The first attempt to establish
                                republican government in any of the large European States was made
                                in England in the 17th century. After a successful revolution
                                Charles I, the English King, was tried by Parliament, convicted of
                                treason and executed. A republic, the so-called “Commonwealth” was
                                established with Oliver Cromwell as “Protector” or President.
                                Cromwell obtained his power as a result of his control of the
                                revolutionary army which had defeated the forces of the crown.</p>
                            <p>This early English Republic lasted only a few years and fell as a
                                result of the difficulties attendant upon the question of the
                                succession to the Protectorate which arose on Cromwell’s death.
                                Cromwell had attempted to place his son Richard in the position left
                                vacant by his death. But either because the English people were not
                                suited to a republic or because Richard Cromwell did not have the
                                characteristics required of the possessor of executive power, this
                                attempt to continue the English Republic was a failure, and England
                                abandoned the republican and re-established the monarchical form of
                                government. Charles II, the son of the executed Charles I, was put
                                upon the throne, largely as the result of the support of the army
                                but with the almost universal approval of the English people.</p>
                            <p>The next attempt to form a republic among European peoples was made
                                after the American revolution at the end of the 18th century when
                                the United States of America was formed. The American revolution was
                                due not so much to an attempt to overthrow monarchical government as
                                to a desire upon the part of the English colonies in America to
                                obtain their independence of England. The success of this revolution
                                brought, however, in its train, <pb facs="0171" n="55" xml:id="pg_55"/> almost necessarily, the establishment of
                                republican government. There was no royal family left in the country
                                to which its government might be entrusted. There was, furthermore,
                                in the country a distinct sentiment in favor of a republic due in
                                large measure to the fact that quite a large number of those who had
                                participated in the establishment of the ill-fated English Republic
                                in the preceding century had come to America and had exerted even
                                after their death an influence in favor of republican
                                institutions.</p>
                            <p>It is, however, possible that George Washington, who had led the
                                American armies during the revolution, might have if he had been so
                                inclined, established himself as king. He was, however, in principle
                                a republican rather than a monarchist. He furthermore had no son
                                who, had he been crowned king, could have succeeded him.</p>
                            <p>The result was that, when the United States obtained its
                                independence, it definitely adopted the republican form of
                                government which has lasted during a century and a quarter. The
                                unquestioned success which has attended the United States during
                                most of its existence has done much to give to the republican form
                                of government the prestige which it now possesses. It is well,
                                however, to remember that the United States inherited from England
                                the principles of constitutional and parliamentary government and
                                that these principles had been applied in America for a century or
                                more before the republic was established. The change from the form
                                of government which was in force during the colonial period to the
                                republic adopted in 1789 was not therefore anything in the nature of
                                a change from autocracy to a republic. Such a change as was made had
                                been preceded by a long period of preparation and discipline in
                                self-government. Furthermore, the American people even of that day
                                possessed a high grade of general intelligence, owing to the
                                attention which had from the very beginning of American history been
                                given to the common schools where almost every child could learn at
                                any time to read and write.</p>
                            <p>The establishment of the American Republic was followed almost
                                immediately by the formation of the French Republic. The Government
                                of France prior to the declaration of the republic had been
                                autocratic. Almost all public powers were centered in the crown and
                                the people participated hardly at all in the administration. The
                                French people had thus had little experience in self-government and
                                were therefore unable to carry on successfully the republic which
                                they endeavored to establish. Periods of disorder followed by
                                military dictatorships followed in rapid succession. The monarchy
                                was restored after the fall of Napoleon largely as the result of
                                foreign intervention. A revolution in 1830 brought into being a more
                                liberal monarchy. This was overthrown by a revolution in 1848, when
                                a republic was again established. The President of this Republic,
                                the nephew of the great Napoleon, overthrew it and declared himself
                                Emperor. After the Franco-Prussian war in 1870 he was deposed and
                                the present French Republic came into being. This republic has now
                                lasted nearly half a century and gives every evidence of
                                permanence.</p>
                            <p>It is well to remember, however, that the present permanence of
                                republican institutions in France was secured only after nearly a
                                century of political change, if not disorder, and that during that
                                century serious attempts had been made both to give the people
                                generally that education upon which intelligent political action
                                must be based and to accustom them by participation public affairs
                                to the exercise of powers of self government.</p>
                            <p>The French, like the Americans, would appear to have solved
                                successfully the most difficult problems in republican government,
                                that is the succession to the executive power. In France the
                                President is elected by the Legislature. In the United States he is
                                elected by the people. In both France and the United States the
                                people have long had experience in self government through
                                participation in public affairs, while in both countries, during the
                                past half century particularly, great attention has been paid to
                                their general education through schools in many cases supported by
                                the Government. The result is that the grade of intelligence of the
                                people in both America and France, is comparatively speaking,
                                high.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">the latin republics.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The examples given in the latter part of the 19th century by the
                                United States and France were very largely followed in South and
                                Central America at the time the former Spanish colonies in this part
                                of the world achieved their independence. As was the case in the
                                United States when it became independent a republic seemed the only
                                practicable form of government which <pb facs="0172" n="56" xml:id="pg_56"/> could be adopted. There was no royal family to
                                which the people might look for guidance.</p>
                            <p>The success which had been attendant upon the establishment of a
                                republic in North America had caused the belief to be entertained by
                                many thinkers, both that a republic was the best form of government
                                and that its establishment and maintenance were possible under all
                                conditions and among all peoples. Republics were therefore
                                established almost everywhere throughout South and Central America.
                                But, either because of the disorders which were incident to the long
                                struggle for independence or because of the difficulties inherent in
                                a republican form of government among a low grade of intelligence,
                                due to the lack of general education, and accustomed only to
                                autocratic rule, the South and Central American Republics have not
                                been generally successful. For years after the independence of the
                                Spanish colonies was achieved South and Central America was the
                                scene of continual disorder, incident for the most part to the
                                struggles of military leaders for political power. At times there
                                were periods of comparative peace due to the success of some
                                extraordinarily strong man who was able to seize and keep in his
                                hands political power. Little if any attempt was for a long time
                                made by any of those who obtained political power to educate the
                                people generally through the establishment of schools or to aid them
                                in the acquisition of political experience by according them
                                participation in the government. The result was that when the strong
                                hand which controlled the country was relaxed, owing either to the
                                increasing age or death of him who possessed political power,
                                disorder again appeared due to the struggles of the claimants for
                                the political succession—since no satisfactory solution of the
                                question of succession was reached. Whatever progress the country
                                had been able to make during its period of peace was arrested and
                                not infrequently the anarchy and chaos which followed caused a
                                serious deterioration in the economic and social conditions of the
                                country.</p>
                            <p>What has happened in Mexico recently has too often been the lot of
                                the Central and South American States under a republican form of
                                government not suited to their stage of economic and political
                                development. Under the Government of Diaz, who acquired political
                                power through his control of the army, it seemed as if Mexico had
                                successfully solved the problem of government. Diaz, however, did
                                little for the education of the people and discouraged rather than
                                encouraged their participation in the government. When increasing
                                age caused him to relax his control revolution broke out again and
                                he fell from power. Since his loss of power the country has been
                                devastated by the contending armies of rival leaders, and at present
                                it would seem that its salvation is possible only as the result of
                                foreign intervention.</p>
                            <p>It is of course true that in some of the South American countries
                                progress is apparently being made in solving the problems of
                                republican government. Such countries are particularly Argentine,
                                Chile and Brazil. In both Argentina and Chile a long period of
                                disorder and disturbance has been followed by a comparatively long
                                period of peace. In Brazil the establishment of the republic about
                                twenty-five years ago, was accompanied by little trouble and the
                                subsequent life of the republic has been a peaceful one. In all
                                three countries considerable progress has been made in the
                                establishment of constitutional government, in Argentine and Chile
                                as one of the results of the struggles of the early part of the
                                nineteenth century, in Brazil, partly at any rate, during the empire
                                which preceded the present republic, and which encouraged the
                                participation of the people in the government of the country.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">lessons from republican experience.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The experience in the South and Central American countries would seem
                                to inculcate the same lessons which may be derived from the
                                experience of the United States and France. These are <list>
                                    <label>1st.</label>
                                    <item>That the difficult problem of the succession to executive
                                        power in a republic may be solved by a people which has a
                                        high general intelligence due to the existence of schools
                                        where general education may be obtained and which has
                                        learned to exercise political power through participation in
                                        the affairs of government; and</item>
                                    <label>2d.</label>
                                    <item>That little hope may be entertained of the successful
                                        solution of the question of presidential succession in a
                                        country where the intelligence of the people is not high and
                                        where the people do not acquire political wisdom by sharing
                                        in the exercise of political power under some form of
                                        constitutional <pb facs="0173" n="57" xml:id="pg_57"/>
                                        government. Where such conditions do not exist a republican
                                        form of government—that is a government in which the
                                        executive is not hereditary—generally leads to the worst
                                        possible form of government, namely, that of the military
                                        dictator. The best that can be hoped for under such a system
                                        is periods of peace alternating with periods of disorder
                                        during which the rival claimants for political power are
                                        striving among themselves for the control of the
                                        government.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">great powers will not permit disorder.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>At the present time, it may further be remarked, it is very doubtful
                                whether the great Powers of the European world will permit the
                                government of the military dictator permanently to exist, if it
                                continues to be accompanied by the disorder which has been its
                                incident in the past. The economic interests of the European world
                                would have grown to be so comprehensive, European capital and
                                European commercial and industrial enterprises have become so wide
                                in their ramifications that the governments of the foreign countries
                                interested, although caring little what may be the form of
                                government adopted by the nations with which they deal, are more and
                                more inclined to insist, where they have the power, that conditions
                                of peace shall be maintained in order that they may receive what
                                they consider to be the proper returns on their investments. This
                                insistence they are more and more liable to carry to the point of
                                actual destruction of the political independence of offending
                                nations and of direct administration of their government if this is
                                necessary to the attainment of the ends desired.</p>
                            <p>It is therefore becoming less and less likely that countries will be
                                permitted in the future to work out their own salvation through
                                disorder and revolution, as may have been the case during the past
                                century with some of the South American countries. Under modern
                                conditions countries must devise some method of government under
                                which peace will be maintained or they will have to submit to
                                foreign control.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">china’s needs considered.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The question naturally presents itself: How do these considerations
                                affect the present political situation of China?</p>
                            <p>China is a country which has for centuries been accustomed to
                                autocratic rule. The intelligence of the great mass of its people is
                                not high owing to the lack of schools. The Chinese have never been
                                accorded much participation in the work of government. The result is
                                that the political capacity of the Chinese people is not large. The
                                change from autocratic to republican government made four years ago
                                was too violent to permit the entertainment of any very strong hopes
                                for its immediate success. Had the Tsing dynasty not been an alien
                                rule which it had long been the wish of the Chinese people to
                                overthrow, there can be little doubt that it would have been better
                                to retain the dynasty in power and gradually to introduce
                                constitutional government in accordance with the plans outlined by
                                the commission appointed for this purpose. But the hatred of alien
                                rule made this impossible and the establishment of a republic seemed
                                at the time of the overthrow of the Manchus to be the only
                                alternative available.</p>
                            <p>It cannot, therefore, be doubted that China has during the last few
                                years been attempting to introduce constitutional government under
                                less favorable auspices than would have been the case had there been
                                a royal family present which the people regarded with respect and to
                                which they were loyal. The great problem of the presidential
                                succession would seem still to be unsolved. The present arrangement
                                cannot be regarded as satisfactory. When the present President lays
                                down the cares of office there is great danger that the difficulties
                                which are usually incident to the succession in countries
                                conditioned as is China will present themselves. The attempt to
                                solve these difficulties may lead to disorders which if long
                                continued may seriously imperil the independence of the country.</p>
                            <p>What under these conditions should be the attitude of those who have
                                the welfare of China at heart? Should they advocate the continuance
                                of the republic or should they propose the establishment of a
                                monarchy?</p>
                            <p>These are difficult questions to answer. It is of course not
                                susceptible of doubt that a monarchy is better suited than a
                                republic to China. China’s history and traditions, her social and
                                economic conditions, her relations with <pb facs="0174" n="58" xml:id="pg_58"/> foreign powers all make it probable that the
                                country would develop that constitutional government which it must
                                develop if it is to preserve its independence as a State, more
                                easily as a monarchy than as a republic.</p>
                            <p>But it is to be remembered that the change from a republic to a
                                monarchy can be successfully made only on the conditions <list>
                                    <label>1st.</label>
                                    <item>That the change does not meet with such opposition either
                                        on the part of the Chinese people or of foreign Powers as
                                        will lead to the recurrence of the disorders which the
                                        present republican government has successfully put down. The
                                        present peaceful conditions of the country should on no
                                        account be imperiled.</item>
                                    <label>2d.</label>
                                    <item>The change from republic to monarchy would be of little
                                        avail if the law of succession is not so fixed that there
                                        will be no doubt as to the successor. The succession should
                                        not be left to the crown to determine for the reasons which
                                        have already been set forth at length. It is probably of
                                        course true that the authority of an emperor would be more
                                        respected than the authority of a president. The people have
                                        been accustomed to an emperor. They hardly know what a
                                        president is. At the same time it would seem doubtful if the
                                        increase of authority resulting from the change from
                                        president to emperor would be sufficient to justify the
                                        change, if the question of the succession were not so
                                        securely fixed as to permit of no doubt. For this is the one
                                        greatest advantage of the monarchy over the republic.</item>
                                    <label>3rd.</label>
                                    <item>In the third place it is very doubtful whether the change
                                        from republic to monarchy would be of any lasting benefit to
                                        China, if provision is not made for the development under
                                        the monarchy of the form of constitutional government. If
                                        China is to take her proper place among nations greater
                                        patriotism must be developed among the people and the
                                        government must increase in strength in order to resist
                                        foreign aggression. Her people will never develop the
                                        necessary patriotism unless they are given greater
                                        participation in the government than they have had in the
                                        past. The government never will acquire the necessary
                                        strength unless it has the cordial support of the people.
                                        This it will not have unless again the people feel that they
                                        have a part in the government. They must in some way be
                                        brought to think of the government as an organization which
                                        is trying to benefit them and over whose actions they
                                        exercise some control.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Whether the conditions which have been set forth as necessary for
                                such a change from republic to monarchy as has been suggested are
                                present, must of course be determined by those who both know the
                                country and are responsible for its future development. These
                                conditions are present if there can be little doubt that the change
                                would be of benefit to the country.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Frank J. Goodnow.</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Society for Peace. Chou An Hui.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <p rend="center">[From the <hi rend="italic">Peking Gazette</hi>, August
                                16, 1915.]</p>
                            <p>A number of prominent officials, including Messrs. Yang Tu, Sun
                                Yu-yun, Yen Fu, General Li Shi-ho and others have promoted a society
                                under the name Chou An Hui, or the Society for Peace. The following
                                is a translation of the manifesto:—</p>
                            <p>During the revolution of 1911 the racial prejudices of our people
                                were so aroused that their attention was entirely concentrated on
                                the removal of a certain section of the population and they did not
                                give the least consideration to the future political affairs of the
                                country. They hastily adopted the republican form of government
                                without weighing carefully its suitability for this country. When a
                                proposal to this effect was made by a few people, others followed
                                blindly without further questioning its advisability. The farsighted
                                people at that time foresaw the danger and trouble to the future of
                                the country, but to prevent dissension and other troubles, which
                                would have further endangered the existence of the country, were
                                compelled to accept this proposal though reluctantly. Since the
                                abdication of the Tsing Imperial House, followed by a period of
                                anarchy, the régime of the Provisional Government and finally the
                                establishment of the present Government, there have been numerous
                                crises in the Government and many unspeakable sufferings of the
                                people which are still fresh in the memory of every class of our
                                people. If a proper measure is not devised to remedy the situation,
                                there will be endless trouble in this country.</p>
                            <pb facs="0175" n="59" xml:id="pg_59"/>
                            <p>In such countries as Argentine, Peru, Chile and other Republics in
                                South and Central America, party feuds have been the order of the
                                day, and such quarrels frequently culminated in civil war. In
                                Portugal the recent change of Government from a monarchy to a
                                republic has been immediately followed by deadly internecine strife
                                and the worst case of all is in Mexico. Since the abdication of
                                Diaz, that country has been seething with civil strife till the
                                present day. Their party leaders have struggled for supremacy with
                                one another with military force. When they win they occupy the land
                                and when they are defeated they never scruple to commit looting,
                                incendiarism and massacre. Finally the whole nation is divided into
                                five camps with as many presidents, and the country is practically
                                in a state of anarchy. As we are a newly established republic, we
                                should take Mexico as our object lesson.</p>
                            <p>The United States of America is the senior republic of the world and
                                her great student of politics, Dr. Goodnow, has stated that a
                                monarchy is a better form of government than republicanism and
                                according to his opinion, a monarchical form of government is most
                                indispensable for China at present. This view has been shared by not
                                a few notable scholars of other countries. As Dr. Goodnow is a
                                citizen of a republic, he is more competent to make such a statement
                                than others. His words are, <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p rend="flushleft">the conditions are different in China and
                                        America and it is impossible to transplant one system from
                                        one country to another.</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>If foreigners who are in sympathy with China have so openly and
                                loudly laid before us their unprejudiced views, can we people of
                                China leave everything to fate, raising not a hand to find a
                                fundamental solution for this important problem? Where is your
                                patriotism? Where is your duty as a citizen to the country, if you,
                                for fear of adverse criticism or other dangers, remain silent and
                                indecisive?</p>
                            <p>As we are the people of this country, the prosperity or decline of
                                this country is nothing less than the prosperity or decline of
                                ourselves. Therefore we cannot bear to sit silent and see the
                                country being obliterated out of existence without making any
                                attempt to save it. We have therefore gathered a number of our
                                sympathizers and started this society with a view to devising means
                                for keeping peace in this country. We shall each give our views
                                concerning the future of our country and the advantages and
                                disadvantages accruing from the republican form of government for
                                general discussion. There are not a few wise and farsighted people
                                in this country, and if they are kind enough to condescend to join
                                us in the discussion of these points, we shall extend them our
                                heartiest welcome.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Yang Tu</hi>,</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sun Yu-yun</hi>,</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Yen Fuh</hi>,</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Liu Shih-pei</hi>,</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Li Hsi-Ho</hi>,</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hu Ying. <lb/>
                                                <hi rend="italic">Promoters.</hi>
                                            </hi>
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">A statement by Dr. Goodnow</hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#center">[From the <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Peking</placeName> Gazette</hi> of <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-08-18">August 18,
                                        1915</date>.]</dateline></opener>
                            <p>The following statement of views expressed by Dr. Goodnow in an
                                interview which we had with him yesterday, defines his attitude on
                                the subject of a monarchical restoration in China in terms which
                                forbid the further citation of his name in support of the thesis
                                that “a monarchical system of government is better than a republican
                                system.” It is also clear that Dr. Goodnow cannot be cited as an
                                authority for the proposition that a monarchical form of government
                                is most indispensable at present in China in the sense suggested by
                                the Chou An Hui in the manifesto published in our issue last Monday.
                                In the interests of clear thinking and of the national welfare, it
                                is to be hoped that this exceedingly grave and anxious question will
                                be discussed with care and with exact knowledge of the principles
                                and all the facts involved, bearing in mind the possibility—if not
                                the probability—of the proposed change reacting with disastrous
                                effect on the foundations of the State.</p>
                            <p>Referring to the leading article which appeared in these columns on
                                Monday, Dr. Goodnow stated that the statement attributed to him to
                                the effect that “a monarchical system of government is better than a
                                republican system,” <pb facs="0176" n="60" xml:id="pg_60"/> which we
                                had quoted from the manifesto of the newly formed Chou An Hui or
                                Society for Peace was not a correct statement either of anything
                                that he has said or of his views. Dr. Goodnow declared that he not
                                only had never made such a statement, but, on the contrary, he was
                                of the opinion that no form of government could be said to be
                                superior under all conditions to other forms of government. He
                                believed that for some countries—where the conditions were
                                favorable—a republican form of government was the best form of
                                government. This was true of the United States and France. In these
                                countries the grade of intelligence of the people was high, owing to
                                the long continued existence of schools, and the people themselves
                                had for many years participated in the work of government and,
                                through this participation, they had learned the lesson of
                                self-government. On the other hand it was just as true, he thought,
                                that a monarchy was often better suited for countries where the
                                conditions were different from those obtaining in the United States
                                and France.</p>
                            <p>Dr. Goodnow also expressed it as his opinion that conditions in China
                                made difficult the orderly development of republican government;
                                because, among other things, of the general lack of knowledge of the
                                people and their long subjection to autocratic rule, tie said that
                                from some points of view it had been unfortunate that China could
                                not have carried further the experiment—begun by the Manchus—of
                                developing gradually constitutional government under a monarchy, but
                                that probably under the conditions existing after the revolution,
                                the establishment of a republic was unavoidable.</p>
                            <p>When asked his opinion as to the expediency of re-establishing a
                                monarchy in China in the near future, he said that the change could
                                be justified only because under a monarchy the question of the
                                succession to the executive power, the most dangerous question in
                                republics, might possibly be more satisfactorily solved than was
                                probable under any sort of republican government which was likely to
                                be established in this country. The settlement of this question had
                                often, particularly in some of the South and Central America States,
                                led to civil war which had as its result the worst form of
                                government known, viz, that of the military dictator. Chinese could
                                not afford to permit civil war or great disorder, as this would
                                almost certainly lead to foreign intervention with the probable loss
                                of political independence.</p>
                            <p>And, speaking slowly and with care, he added that because of these
                                considerations, a monarchical restoration in China would be
                                justified, in his opinion, only on condition <list>
                                    <label>(a)</label>
                                    <item>That the change be acceptable both to the thinking people
                                        of China and to the foreign Powers in order that it might
                                        not meet with such opposition as would lead to
                                        disorder;</item>
                                    <label>(b)</label>
                                    <item>That the succession to the throne be so fixed that no
                                        doubt could arise on the death of the monarch as to who
                                        would succeed. If we might judge from European experience,
                                        the only proper method of fixing the succession was to give
                                        it to the eldest son of the monarch or in default of sons to
                                        the eldest nearest male relative;</item>
                                    <label>(c)</label>
                                    <item>That the monarchy established be a limited constitutional
                                        monarchy, which, while for the moment vesting large powers
                                        in the Crown, would permit of the gradual development of
                                        greater popular government. The re-establishment of the
                                        former autocratic monarchy in China could not be regarded as
                                        promising any improvement over present conditions.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>When asked whether these conditions could be met at present in China,
                                Dr. Goodnow said that he did not know enough about the country or of
                                Chinese opinion to be able to express an opinion of any value and
                                must therefore leave that question to be answered by those who did
                                know China’s conditions and were responsible for her destinies.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>