<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-01-04T09:49:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-01-04T09:49:00-05:00" n="585" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d585">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 838.516/42.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Blanchard</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Port au Prince</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-01-04T10:00:00-04:49">
                                    <hi rend="italic">January 4, 1915—10 a.m.</hi>
                                </date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Department of Foreign Relations has asked, by note received last
                            night, the good offices of the Legation for transmission to Mr. Wehrhane
                            of the following reply to his telegram<note n="14" xml:id="d585fn14">
                                <ref target="frus1914#pg_379">For. Rel. 1914, pp. 379</ref>–<ref target="frus1914#pg_380">380</ref>.</note> addressed to the
                            President of Haiti, which was forwarded through the Department and this
                            Legation: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p rend="center">[Translation.]</p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry H. Wehrhane</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Vice President National Bank of the Republic
                                        of Haiti, New York:</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>In answer to your telegram the President of Haiti charges me to
                                    express his satisfaction at seeing the Bank, actuated by
                                    condition of the country, disposed to propose arbitration for
                                    the settlement of the difficulties pending and at last decided
                                    to an understanding with reference to this matter to be adopted
                                    to improve the financial and economic situation of the
                                    country.</p>
                                <p>He regrets, however, not to be able to consent to send to the
                                    United States Doctor Heraux, Minister of Finance, accompanied by
                                    one or more colleagues, to the end of negotiating agreements and
                                    to lay, should there be occasion, the basis of a new budgetary
                                    convention. He thinks preferable that the Bank enter into
                                    relations with the Haitian Minister at Washington, who will
                                    receive full powers to that effect. In the meantime the
                                    President thinks that the Bank, previous to any negotiation,
                                    would give indisputable proof of the sincerity of its sentiments
                                    by consenting to execute without delay the two laws recently
                                    voted by the Legislative Body which place at the disposal of the
                                    Government certain credit balances of which the payment is
                                    imperatively claimed for the urgent necessities of public
                                    service.</p>
                                <p rend="right">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. Edmond Heraux</hi>.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Blanchard</hi>.</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>