<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Consul Pontius to the Secretary of State..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1915</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d729</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">729</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1914-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1914-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="729"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d729">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.773/12.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Consul <persName type="from">Pontius</persName> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Consulate</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Newchwang</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-06-30">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 30, 1914</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit herewith copy of my
                    No. 5, with enclosures, reporting to the Legation at Peking concerning the
                    reduction in railway freights instituted by the South Manchuria Railway on
                    importations from Japan through the port of Dairen.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Albert W. Pontius.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Consul <persName type="from">Pontius</persName> to
                            Minister <persName type="to">Reinsch</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">American Consulate</hi>, <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Newchwang, China</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-06-30">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 30, 1914</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: For the information of the Legation, I have
                        the honor to report that the South Manchuria Railway announced in a recent
                        issue of its official gazette published in Dairen, that a reduction would be
                        made on specific through shipments from Japan over its railway to interior
                        points in Manchuria. The new rates are to take effect on the first proximo,
                        and in a recent issue of a Dairen newspaper direct mention is made of the
                        fact that the reduction in railway freights does not apply to Newchwang, the
                        import route via that port being <pb facs="0712" n="596" xml:id="pg_596"/>
                        entirely left out of account. The article also mentioned that the new rates
                        were limited to the Mukden-Antung line and the import route through Dairen.
                        The schedule of the new rates is quoted herewith as table No. 1, and the
                        rates previously existing as table No. 2.</p>
                    <p>A careful examination of the two tables<note n="1" xml:id="d729fn1">Not
                            printed.</note> will show that the reduction applies chiefly to cotton
                        goods, the decrease in freight rates to distributing points such as Mukden,
                        Tiehling and Changchun amounting to about 30%. Cotton goods is one of the
                        chief staple articles of Japanese importation into Manchuria, and this new
                        move on the part of the Japanese concerned appears a clever device to
                        discriminate against shipments of foreign manufactured piece goods into
                        Manchuria from Shanghai, through either the port of Dairen or Newchwang.
                        This fact seems self-evident when it is realized that large quantities of
                        American and European manufactured piece goods are continually imported by
                        Japanese firms from Japan through the ports of Dairen and Antung.</p>
                    <p>What with the favorable treatment now accorded importations of foreign goods
                        from Japan through the port of Antung in the shape of import tariff
                        reduction of one-third duty, and the present preferential freight rates
                        extended to goods shipped to interior points in Manchuria through Dairen,
                        foreign firms interested in the import trade in Manchuria apparently have
                        every reason to complain at the discrimination it is proposed to exercise
                        against them. The purpose of the South Manchuria Railway is seemingly to
                        hamper and obstruct further importations from Shanghai through Dairen, and
                        confine the commercial possibilities of Newchwang to a still narrower sphere
                        of activity.</p>
                    <p>In spite of the many efforts in the past to cripple the future trade
                        possibilities of Newchwang by those interested in the diverting of commerce
                        to Dairen, the former port has so far succeeded in holding a fair share of
                        the trade of this region, and the renewed activity of those at present
                        concerned in the additional tactics of discrimination make it imperative
                        that the Liao River conservancy project, when means so much for the future
                        welfare of the port, be instituted without unnecessary delay.</p>
                    <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Albert Pontius.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
