<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1907-01-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1907-01-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="180" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d180">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 167/90–91.</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Rockhill</persName>
                                to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>,<date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-01-07"><hi rend="italic">January 7,
                                1907</hi>.</date></dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 499.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In further acknowledgment of your cabled
                            instruction of December 11 [13]<note n="a" xml:id="d180fna">See <ref target="frus1906p1#pg_324">Foreign Relations, 1906, p.
                                324</ref>.</note> informing me that you had reached an agreement
                            with the Chinese minister in Washington in the matter of the indemnity
                            for the Lienchou massacre, and instructing me to conclude the
                            arrangement of the whole affair in the manner indicated in my dispatch
                            No. 381 of August 28, 1906,<note n="b" xml:id="d180fnb">See <ref target="frus1906p1#pg_321">Foreign Relations, 1906, p.
                                321</ref>.</note> I have the honor to inform you that on December
                            111 called at the Wai-wu Pu and handed His Excellency T’ang Shao-i a
                            copy of your cablegram. He said that the foreign office had already
                            telegraphed to the viceroy at Canton to pay to the American
                            consul-general the indemnity agreed upon by you and Sir Chentung Liang
                            Cheng, and that this would probably be done in a few days. He added that
                            the delay in settling this question had been occasioned by a
                            misunderstanding, that while the foreign office had been all the time
                            desirous of indemnifying the families of the Lienchou victims, as
                            ordered by the imperial edict of October 28, 1905, the Chinese minister
                            at Washington and the Canton viceroy, misunderstanding the general
                            statement of the missionary board that it would not receive
                            indemnification for the killing of any of its members, had insisted that
                            in the present case no indemnity was to be paid; hence the delay.</p>
                        <p>I then told his excellency that, with the indemnity paid, all the
                            conditions of the settlement agreed to by the American consul-general at
                            Canton and the viceroy would have been complied with, except the
                            publication of the proclamation to be issued by the provincial
                            authorities of Kuang-tung stating the settlement, and which was to be
                            submitted to this legation as provided for in the draft agreement I had
                            handed to the Wai-wu Pu in August, 1906. (See my No. 381 of August 28,
                            1906.) We could then sign the final protocol of settlement, or
                            agreement, and the whole matter would be finally disposed of.</p>
                        <p>He at first raised some slight objections to the signing by the Wai-wu Pu
                            of a general agreement on the subject, contending that the local
                            settlement by the viceroy and the consul-general was sufficient. To this
                            I replied that the mode of settlement you had approved and authorized me
                            to make was in strict accordance with that followed a few months ago by
                            the Wai-wu Pu in the settlement made with the British and French
                            ministers for the Nanch’ang Fu riots, and that he had raised no
                            objection to it when I had previously submitted it to him. He then said
                            that he thought the matter could be arranged as you desired, and that he
                            would take the orders of the Prince of Ch’ing.</p>
                        <p>On the 18th of December I telegraphed our consul-general at Canton as
                            follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="smallcaps">American Consul</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Canton:</hi></p>
                                <p>Foreign office has informed me have directed Canton viceroy pay
                                    you $25,000 in gold to indemnify Americans killed Lienchou.
                                    Secretary of State has informed me has agreed to accept. You
                                    will receive it, therefore, at the rate of <pb facs="0325" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/> exchange on New York on the date
                                    of payment. Advise me when paid, for further instructions. Final
                                    agreement covering the settlement will be signed here.</p>
                                <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rockhill.</hi></p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>On the 31st ultimo I received a dispatch from the consul-general
                            informing me that the missionaries were now anxious to return to
                            Lienchou to resume their work there, and asking me to telegraph him
                            whether I thought they could be authorized to do so—all proper
                            precautions being taken for their safety on the journey and after
                            arrival at their destination. My telegraphic reply to him and the
                            reasons for sending it appear in my dispatch to Mr. Bergholz of the 3d
                            instant, copy of which I inclose.</p>
                        <p>On the 5th instant I received a telegram from Mr. Bergholz advising me
                            that the indemnity had been paid to him. I at once instructed him to
                            remit the amount directly to you, and at the same time I telegraphed of
                            the payment having been made and that I expected shortly to sign the
                            protocol of settlement with the Wai-wu Pu. This I have not yet done.</p>
                        <p>I confirm as follows my telegram to you of the 5th instant<note n="a" xml:id="d180fnc">Supra.</note> referred to above.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">W. W. Rockhill.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Rockhill</persName> to Consul-General <persName type="to">Bergholz</persName></hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>,<date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-01-03"><hi rend="italic">January 3,
                                        1907</hi>.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to acknowledge the receipt of
                                your dispatches Nos. 32 of December 12, 36 of December 18, and 37 of
                                December 19, dealing with the question of the settlement of the
                                Lienchou affair.</p>
                            <p>In your No. 32 you inclose copies of the texts engraved upon the two
                                tablets erected by the local authorities of Lienchou in compliance
                                with the arrangement reached by your predecessor with the Viceroy
                                Ch’en, the one being the imperial edict of October 28, 1905, the
                                other, placed in front of the cave temple in which the victims of
                                the massacre were found by the mob, a memorial of the event, and a
                                statement of the punishment of those guilty of the murders. You also
                                inclose a copy of a letter from Henry V. Noyes, chairman of the
                                executive committee of the American Presbyterian Mission, Canton, in
                                which he says in the name of his mission that they “think the
                                officials have faithfully carried out their agreement in regard to
                                the Lienchou affair so far as concerns the payment for losses
                                incurred there, and the erection of the tablets.”</p>
                            <p>In his note to you of December 2 last (inclosure 3 in your No. 32)
                                the viceroy informs you that he has ordered higher rewards than
                                those previously offered to be made for the arrest of the culprits
                                still at large; that the acting subprefect of Lienchou has reported
                                his readiness to use every possible means for protecting the
                                missionaries on their return to that place, and that on their
                                arrival he will again post the imperial edict of October 28, 1905,
                                in conspicuous and public places in the city and district of
                                Lienchou.</p>
                            <p>As regards the conversion into a schoolhouse of the small temple used
                                for <hi rend="italic">ta tsui</hi> celebrations, the viceroy in the
                                same note states that he has ordered the acting subprefect to devise
                                proper means for so doing. In your dispatch No. 37 you say, in view
                                of the subprefect’s statement that he has been unable <pb facs="0326" n="214" xml:id="pg_214"/> to raise the funds
                                necessary to convert the temple into a schoolhouse, that the viceroy
                                may be induced to order the razing of the temple or its removal to
                                some other part of the city. “The latter course,” you remark, “would
                                be as satisfactory as transforming it into a school.” I had
                                originally suggested to Mr. Lay that he should ask the razing of the
                                temple in question, but on his stating that he thought this might be
                                strongly objected to I agreed to only ask its conversion into a
                                schoolhouse. I would be much pleased to see my original suggestion
                                carried out.</p>
                            <p>It appears from the above and from previous correspondence that the
                                Chinese authorities have now complied—so far as can be done at the
                                present time—with the demands which your predecessor made of them,
                                with the exception of the razing of the temple, which you believe
                                will shortly be done. Such being the case, I see no reason why the
                                Lienchou missionaries, who, you say in your No. 36, are “fearful of
                                the influence their continued absence may have upon the minds of
                                their converts and are desirous of getting speedily to work to
                                regain the ground they may have lost and to begin the erection of
                                their mission property,” should not return to Lienchou as soon as
                                they are ready to do so, the viceroy again undertaking to protect
                                them adequately on the journey and after their arrival at their
                                place of destination.</p>
                            <p>The payment by the viceroy to you of $25,000 United States gold for
                                the surviving members of the families of those killed in October,
                                1905, not being an essential feature of the settlement so far as
                                punishment of culprits, reparation for losses, guaranteeing of
                                future protection, etc., are concerned, this payment not having yet
                                been made, though it certainly will within a very short period, the
                                amount having been agreed to by both Governments, need not delay the
                                return of the missionaries to Lienchou.</p>
                            <p>The above being the present status of the settlement of this affair,
                                I telegraphed you on the 2d instant, in reply to the request in your
                                No. 36, as follows:</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">“<hi rend="smallcaps">American Consul</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Canton:</hi></p>
                            <p>“If all conditions are complied with about Lienchou except payment of
                                the indemnity, missionaries may return. Razing of temple is very
                                satisfactory arrangement.</p>
                            <p rend="right">“Rockhill.”</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">W. W.
                                Rockhill.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>