<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1907-07-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1907-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="364" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d364">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 5727/83.</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British
                                        Ambassador</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">British Embassy</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Intervale,
                                            N. H.</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-07-18"><hi rend="italic">July 18,
                                        1907</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 168.]</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                receipt of your note No. 108 of the 10th instant, informing me that
                                in view of the facts set forth as to the status of British chambers
                                of commerce, they will in future be recognized as qualified to issue
                                certificates of value on the same terms as are accorded German
                                chambers of commerce under paragraph F of the recent agreement
                                between the United States and Germany.</p>
                            <p>I desire to express my recognition of the liberal spirit in which the
                                United States Government have acted in this matter, and of the
                                readiness shown in removing a difficulty which might have proved
                                detrimental to important mutual commercial interests.</p>
                            <p>I am now instructed by His Majesty’s Government to make certain
                                inquiries for the elucidation of minor points connected with the
                                exercise of these powers by British chambers of commerce. I should
                                therefore be greatly obliged if I might be informed, for telegraphic
                                communication to the competent authorities, whether the certificates
                                of the British chambers of commerce will supersede the other
                                documents relative to value required by the customs administration,
                                particularly the declarations required to be indorsed on the back of
                                the invoice under section 3 of the customs administrative act. Also,
                                whether the value to be stated in the guarantee certificate is to
                                include packing and other charges incidental to shipment.</p>
                            <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">James Bryce.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>