<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1907-01-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1907-01-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="439" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d439">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 4001/95–98.</note>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Rear-Admiral <persName type="from">Davis</persName>
                                to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of the Navy</gloss></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Flagship Alabama</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Guantanamo
                                        Bay, Cuba</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-01-30"><hi rend="italic">January 30,
                                1907</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 149–D.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have this day received a letter from the
                            governor of Jamaica under date of January 19, the day of my departure
                            from Kingston, a copy of which, together with a copy of my reply, I
                            transmit herewith. I request that these documents may be made an
                            appendix of my report of the operations of the squadron under my command
                            at Kingston.</p>
                        <p>Very respectfully,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">C. H. Davis.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.].</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Governor of
                                        Jamaica</gloss> to Rear-Admiral <persName type="to">Davis</persName></hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Kings House</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Jamaica</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-01-19"><hi rend="italic">January 19,
                                        1907</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: It is both a duty and a pleasure to me
                                to express to you on your departture from this port the profound
                                gratitude of the colony to you and to the officers and men of the
                                United States detached squadron for the services you have rendered,
                                and also for those tendered to this colony at a time when it was
                                suffering from the effect of a sudden calamity; the promptitude with
                                which you dispatched the surgical appliances which we needed, and
                                the rapidity with which you followed them and devoted the services
                                of the officers and men of your squadron to aiding suffering
                                humanity, to guarding your consular archives and the penitentiary,
                                to assisting in clearing the streets and pulling down walls, as well
                                as numerous acts of assistance generously rendered to citizens,
                                deserve my fullest recognition and gratitude, which I heartily
                                tender to you on behalf of the government and people of this
                                island.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>I also desire to express my most sincere thanks for the desire
                                    you expressed to have done more if my scruples had permitted my
                                    acceptance of your squadron’s services so generously
                                    rendered.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>I trust that we may meet again under circumstances which will
                                    permit my testifying more formally than the present turmoil
                                    permitted my personal desire to do you the honor prescribed for
                                    your rank in the King’s Regulations.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">J. A. Swettenham</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Governor.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Rear-Admiral <persName type="from">Davis</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Governor of
                                        Jamaica</gloss></hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Flagship Alabama</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Guantanamo
                                            Bay, Cuba</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-01-30"><hi rend="italic">January 30,
                                        1907</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: It gives me great pleasure to
                                acknowledge your excellency’s letter of the 19th instant, and to
                                assure you of my deep appreciation of the sentiments which it
                                expresses.</p>
                            <pb facs="0679" n="567" xml:id="pg_567"/>
                            <p>I may add without impropriety, I believe, the earnest wish that your
                                own efforts in behalf of your city will be crowned with success and
                                that the work of restoration and rebuilding will progress with
                                rapidity.</p>
                            <p>I beg to assure your excellency of the high consideration with which
                                I have the honor to be,</p>
                            <p>Your excellency’s obedient servant,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">C. H. Davis.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>