<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the British Ambassador..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1907p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d440</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">440</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1907-05-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1907-05-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1907-05-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1907-05-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="440"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d440">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 4001/122–123.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">British Ambassador</gloss>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-05-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 1, 1907</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 50.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herewith
                    copies of certain correspondence received from the Secretary of the Navy
                    regarding the request of His Majesty’s legation at Habana for a statement of the
                    amount owed to the United States by the government of Jamaica on account of
                    stores sent to Kingston by the American Atlantic Fleet at the time of the
                    earthquake.</p>
                <p>I should be very much obliged if you would be so good as to advise the Jamaican
                    government, in accordance with the request of the Navy Department, that no
                    charges lie against that government for the stores in question.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Elihu Root.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of the
                                Navy</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Navy Department</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-04-25">
                                <hi rend="italic">April 25, 1907</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The honorable Secretary of War has referred
                        to this department a communication addressed to him by the provisional
                        governor of Cuba, dated March 2, 1907, inclosing one addressed to Governor
                        Magoon by the chargé d’affaires of the British legation, Habana, requesting,
                        on behalf of the governor of Jamaica, a statement of the amount for which
                        the government of Jamaica is responsible on account of the stores which were
                        sent to Kingston by the U. S. Atlantic Fleet, in compliance with the request
                        contained in the governor’s telegram of January 16 last, which read:</p>
                    <p>“Kindly send immediately bandages, lint, and wool for those injured by the
                        earthquake, at cost of colony.”</p>
                    <p>In this connection I have the honor to inclose herewith, for your
                        information, a copy of the department’s letter of the 23d instant to the
                        President, recommending that in pursuance of the act of Congress approved
                        January 18, 1907, entitled “An act for the relief of citizens of the island
                        of Jamaica,” the issuance of the stores in question by the U. S. Atlantic
                        Fleet be approved and that no charges therefor shall lie against the
                        Jamaican government, which recommendation has been approved by the
                        President.</p>
                    <p>It is requested that the British Government be advised accordingly.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Truman H. Newberry.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of the Navy</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">President</gloss>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Navy Department</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-04-23">
                                <hi rend="italic">April 23, 1907</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On January 16 last, on the occasion of the
                        earthquake and attending conflagration on the island of Jamaica, the
                        governor of that island telegraphed the provincial governor of Cuba as
                        follows:</p>
                    <p>“Kindly send immediately bandages, lint, and wool for those injured by the
                        earthquake, at cost of colony.”</p>
                    <pb facs="0680" n="568" xml:id="pg_568"/>
                    <p>A copy of this telegram was sent by Governor Magoon to the commander in chief
                        U. S. Atlantic Fleet, asking him at the same time to respond, if possible,
                        to the call of the governor of Jamaica.</p>
                    <p>The department cabled the commander in chief U. S. Atlantic Fleet on January
                        17, 1907, as follows:</p>
                    <p>“If in your judgment conditions require issuing stores to Kingston earthquake
                        sufferers, you are authorized to do so.”</p>
                    <p>In compliance with the foregoing it appears that stores were furnished from
                        the medical department of the several ships of the fleet, consisting of
                        medicines, dressing materials, etc., at an approximate cost of $186.48.</p>
                    <p>The act of Congress approved January 18, 1907, entitled “An act for the
                        relief of the citizens of the island of Jamaica,” authorized the President
                        of the United States—</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">“to use and distribute among the suffering and destitute
                        people of the island of Jamaica, such provisions, clothing, medicines, and
                        other necessary articles belonging to the subsistence and other stores of
                        the naval establishment as may be necessary for the purpose of succoring the
                        people who are in peril and threatened with starvation on said island in
                        consequence of the recent earthquake and attending conflagration.”</p>
                    <p>In pursuance of the foregoing act of Congress I have the honor to request
                        that the issuance of the stores in question by the U. S. Atlantic Fleet be
                        approved, and that no charges therefor shall lie against the Jamaican
                        government.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">V. H. Metcalf.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">President.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The White House</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-04-23">
                                    <hi rend="italic">April 23, 1907</hi>
                                </date>.</dateline>
                            <lb/> Approved.<lb/>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">T. Roosevelt.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
