<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ambassador Francis to the Secretary of State..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1907p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d60</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">60</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1907-06-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1907-06-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85108801"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public schools</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1907-06-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1907-06-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="60"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d60">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">Francis</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-06-22">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 22, 1907</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 257.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that the new Austrian
                    Parliament was opened by Emperor Francis Joseph in the hall of ceremonies in the
                    imperial palace on the 19th instant. Every political party was represented in
                    the assembled delegates of both houses of this National Legislature; even the
                    socialist members were present—the first time they had been permitted to attend
                    such a function in the Hofburg.</p>
                <p>His Majesty’s address, read from the throne, to the recently elected Parliament
                    touches upon all prominent subjects affecting the country, such as the language
                    question, reforms in official administration, the economic condition of the
                    state, agriculture, railways, public schools, education, state finance, legal
                    reforms, etc., but the topics alluded to by the Emperor that commanded the most
                    attention were His Majesty’s allusions to the preservation of the Pragmatic
                    Sanction and the union with Hungary, to the preservation of peace with all
                    nations, and to the love and devotion that had been shown him by his subjects
                    during his long reign.</p>
                <p>The speech was a strong appeal to the new Parliament to ever keep in mind the
                    higher interests of the country and to seek in all things peace, concord, and
                    the common good.</p>
                <p>“It is my most lively desire,” said the Emperor, “to leave when the time shall
                    come, as a precious inheritance to my peoples the <pb facs="0173" n="61"
                        xml:id="pg_61"/> assured existence of their national possessions, and
                    thereby to guarantee to all a national peace that may become a joint treasure of
                    all lovers of the fatherland. Upon my Government I have urged the duty of
                    turning to this end its whole strength, and to all who hold dear their popular
                    characteristics and the weal of the state I address the plea that they will
                    cooperate with entire devotion in the attainment of this goal.”</p>
                <p>In treating the subject of universal suffrage His Majesty said the reform is
                    “based on my trust in the loyalty of my peoples to the state. It will be the
                    especial task of the newly elected chamber to justify my confidence and to prove
                    that a comprehensive widening of the juridical foundations of political life may
                    go hand in hand with a concentration and increase of the state’s political
                    power. For the right to participate in decisions creates coresponsibility for
                    the fate of the whole body politic. I expect, therefore, that the popular
                    representation yielded by universal suffrage will be penetrated by the
                    consciousness of its duties toward the state, and will, together with my
                    Government, provide for state needs and be fertile in work for the welfare of
                    our country.”</p>
                <p>In referring to the relations between the countries of the dual monarchy the
                    Emperor declared their political unity must exist under all conditions,
                    unchanged by future generations, and it would be of the greatest value if this
                    relationship could be placed on a firm basis while adhering to, so far as
                    possible, its traditional forms. He added: “In all circumstances the leading
                    idea must be that the political tie between the two states, a tie hallowed by
                    centuries of common history and firmly knit and preserved by the Pragmatic
                    Sanction, shall be conserved unimpaired for future generations. Therefore while
                    duly respecting the autonomous rights of both parties, all loosening of
                    relationship, economic as well as political, must be avoided, were the loosening
                    such as to involve peril for the future of the Pragmatic Communion.”</p>
                <p>The Emperor declared that armed strength is the strongest protection for economic
                    activity and the best guardian of peace, and concluded his half-hour address by
                    saying, with much feeling: “Through the grace of Providence it has been
                    vouchsafed to me to lead two generations of my peoples. I have seen the toils of
                    my princely office rewarded by a love and loyalty tried in all the vicissitudes
                    of destiny and by my peoples’ progress in well-being and civilization. To
                    further this progress and well and truly to administer the inheritance of the
                    glorious history of our fathers is the task to which I have dedicated my whole
                    life. With this same goal before your eyes you will find the way to concord and
                    internal peace, which to see assured I should esteem the highest favor of fate.
                    May the reconciling spirit of love of the common fatherland brood over your
                    work, and may the blessing of the Almighty accompany you therein.”</p>
                <p>The impression produced on the public is that His Majesty felt compelled to
                    deliver this address, generally considered to have been the most impressive
                    appeal ever made by the Emperor to his people, and that this last “speech from
                    the throne “marks an important event in the history of the House of
                    Hapsburg.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles S. Francis.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
