<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1907-01-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1907-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="82" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d82">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 4878/2–3.</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Beaupré</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Buenos
                                        Aires</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-01-16"><hi rend="italic">January 16,
                                1907</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 476.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose an article cut
                            from La Presna of the 13th instant, which gives, I believe, accurately
                            the story and results <pb facs="0198" n="86" xml:id="pg_86"/> of efforts
                            that are being made to settle the pending boundary dispute between the
                            neighboring Republics of Bolivia and Paraguay, the outcome of which is
                            that the offer of the President of this Republic to act as arbiter in
                            the matter has been accepted, subject to the approval of the Congresses
                            of the two countries.</p>
                        <p>The dispute in question is, as will be seen, one of long standing,
                            repeated efforts having been made to reach an amicable solution of it. A
                            renewed and serious effort was made by the two countries during the past
                            year to reach a friendly settlement, in that the Government of Bolivia
                            accredited to that of Paraguay one of the most able diplomats, Dr.
                            Emeterio Cano, at one time Bolivian minister for foreign affairs, with
                            special instruction in the matter in question. The Government of
                            Paraguay responded to the cordial act of Bolivia and appointed special
                            plenipotentiary to treat with Doctor Cano an ex-vice-president of
                            Paraguay, Dr. Manuel Dominguez. These two representatives of their
                            respective countries, in spite of diligent endeavors, were unable to
                            find common ground on which to agree.</p>
                        <p>Such was the state of affairs when Doctor Zeballos, on November 26 last,
                            accepted the portfolio of minister of foreign affairs of this
                            Government. Doctor Zeballos took advantage of the presence in this
                            country some weeks ago, en route for Europe, of the minister for foreign
                            affairs of Bolivia, Dr. Caludio Pinilla, through the Argentine minister
                            in Asuncion to offer to the Government of Paraguay the mediation of this
                            Government in the pending question on the following conditions: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Meeting in Buenos Aires of the ministers for foreign affairs of
                                    the two countries in order to discuss the respective claims of
                                    the same, and to endeavor to reach a direct arrangement between
                                    them. In case of disagreement the matter to be submitted to
                                    arbitration before the President of this Republic.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>This offer of intervention was accepted, and Dr. Adolfo L. Soler, at
                            present minister of finance but recently minister for foreign affairs of
                            Paraguay, was at once sent to Buenos Aires to represent that country in
                            the matter. Doctor Dominguez, the special plenipotentiary of Paraguay
                            appointed last year to treat with Doctor Cano, of Bolivia, accompanied
                            him to advise with Doctor Soler.</p>
                        <p>These plenipotentiaries of the two countries met in this city with Doctor
                            Zeballos. In spite, however, of repeated endeavors the matter proved
                            difficult of solution, and it was decided to avail themselves of the
                            alternative condition contained in Doctor Zeballo’s offer of mediation
                            and to submit the question to the arbitral decision of the President of
                            this Republic. Accordingly, on the 12th instant, a protocol to that
                            effect was signed by the authorized parties. The protocol, in accordance
                            with one of its terms, will be submitted to the congresses of Bolivia
                            and Paraguay, and, if approved, the matter will be taken up in regular
                            form, and the decision of the President of this country will be final in
                            the matter.</p>
                        <p>It will be observed from the map which <hi rend="italic">La Prensa</hi>
                            prints to accompany the inclosed article that the territory in question
                            lies between the rivers Paraguay and Pilcomayo, and between the
                            parallels of latitude 19½ and 23 south and between the meridians of
                            longitude 58 and 63 west.</p>
                        <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">A. M. Beaupré.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>