<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Spanish Ambassador.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1173</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1173</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1914-07-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1914-07-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec6SOt1hMx6m4tne" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085495"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-07-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-07-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="1173"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1173">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 812.63/12a.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Spanish Ambassador</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-07-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 2, 1914</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to propose that this
                    Government and the Spanish Government agree that they will withhold all
                    diplomatic support from their respective citizens or subjects, who claim
                    directly or indirectly, title or interest in mines or mining rights in Mexico,
                    which they have acquired since January 1, 1913, or may hereafter acquire,
                    directly or indirectly, by reason of the cancellation of contracts, leases or
                    other forms of conveyance or by reason of the confiscation or taking by de facto
                    authorities of mines or mining rights, in which American citizens or Spanish
                    subjects are interested, on the ground of default in contractual obligations or
                    noncompliance with legal requirements, provided such default or noncompliance
                    was unavoidable because of military operations or political disturbances in
                    Mexico.</p>
                <p>It should however, be distinctly understood that this agreement will not apply to
                    any case in which the failure of the American or Spanish owner of an interest in
                    mines or mining rights in Mexico to perform his contractual obligations or to
                    comply with a legal requirement was not the direct result of the political
                    unrest prevailing in Mexico at the time of default, or to any case of bona fide
                    transfer.</p>
                <p>If the proposed agreement relative to mines and mining rights in Mexico is
                    acceptable to your Government, a note stating its acceptance will be considered
                    by this Government as putting the agreement into effect.</p>
                <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. J. Bryan</hi>
                    </signed>.</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
