<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-10-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-10-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="118" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d118">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.811/166.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Reinsch</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 424.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-10-28">
                                    <hi rend="italic">October 28, 1914</hi>
                                </date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit the
                            translation of a letter dated the 18th instant, directed to the American
                            Minister by his excellency Mr. Chang Chien, Minister of Agriculture and
                            Commerce, and Mr. Hsu Tung-lin, in which they set forth the extent of
                            the calamity brought upon the Provinces of Kiangsu and Anhui through the
                            unusual floods of this autumn, and request that an advance be made on
                            the Huai River loan account so that the conservancy work may be begun
                            find employment given to the starving people. I also enclose a copy of
                            my answer to the above.</p>
                        <p>In my answer to Mr. Chang and Mr. Hsu I endeavored to make clear to them
                            the difficulties which, under present general conditions, stand in the
                            way of affording immediate relief in this matter. The terrible calamity
                            which has again come over the Huai River region, however, emphasizes the
                            necessity of carrying through the engineering work, which will not only
                            afford permanent relief but will turn a region now so desolate into one
                            of the richest garden spots in China. The report of the Engineers’
                            Commission upon this work is so favorable that all doubts with regard to
                            the undertaking, both as to its economic soundness and as to the lasting
                            benefits to be secured, have been dispelled. Should it be possible for
                            the Red Cross Society to prevail upon the bankers in the United States
                            to undertake the furnishing of this loan immediately, so that the work
                            could be commenced, a vast additional benefit would be gained by
                            affording work and relief to the million or more of people who would
                            otherwise be exposed to suffering and death. In thus combining in one
                            enterprise immediate and permanent relief, the purposes of the American
                            Red Cross Society would be achieved in a most striking manner.</p>
                        <p>I therefore have the honor to request that this matter be communicated to
                            the American Red Cross Society, in order that if possible means may be
                            devised for beginning the work of the Huai River improvement at this
                            time when such enormous benefits would be gained by prompt action. As
                            the work itself has now been shown to be both practicable and beneficial
                            and its ultimate execution would seem to be assured, it would be a
                            matter highly to be regretted if the opportunity to save these people
                            from untold sufferings through a prompt beginning of the work would have
                            to be passed by. Both as a sound business venture and as philanthropy in
                            the best sense of the <pb facs="0228" n="112" xml:id="pg_112"/> word,
                            this enterprise is sure to appeal to American men of means and to the
                            American public in general. I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Paul S. Reinsch</hi></signed>.</closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1—Translation.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Messrs. <persName type="from">Chang Chien and Hsu
                                        Tung-lin</persName> to Minister <persName type="to">Reinsch</persName>.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" when="1914-10-18"><hi rend="italic">Undated</hi></date><hi rend="italic">; received October
                                        18, 1914</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In the spring and summer of this year
                                northern Kiangsu and Anhui suffered from drought and the people were
                                reduced to extremities. In the autumn the rain fell continuously day
                                and night for ten days so that water stood over the level ground to
                                a depth of twenty feet. Houses were washed away and innumerable
                                people were drowned. Such a calamity has not occurred for several
                                decades. Husbands and wives have hanged themselves. Nine members of
                                one family hanged themselves. Parents, knowing that they themselves
                                had to die, have tied their children on to wooden doors and let them
                                float off in hope that they might be rescued by someone, and the
                                children have starved to death after floating so for many days. Many
                                such incidents reported wound one’s heart.</p>
                            <p>Formerly benevolent men of your honorable country helped the people
                                in the stricken regions of Kiangsu and Anhui, and now the American
                                Red Cross Society is contemplating a loan for the conservancy of the
                                Huai River in order to prevent floods. The Chinese people are very
                                grateful for their earnest efforts. But the mere confining of the
                                waters of the Huai River to a deepened channel without improving the
                                channels of the branch streams entering the Huai will not of itself
                                prevent floods. We have already asked you to explain to the American
                                Government the gravity of the present flood in Kiangsu and Anhui,
                                and to ask it to consult with the managers of the Red Cross Society,
                                in view of the extraordinary sufferings of the people, with
                                reference to an advance on the Huai River loan account of $5,000,000
                                gold to be used in deepening at once the channels of the tributaries
                                of the Huai and I rivers. In this way wages would take the place of
                                alms, the wages paid to one supporting two, so that the afflicted
                                people to the number of over a million might be kept alive. We shall
                                be deeply grateful if this request can be granted. We now enclose a
                                list of the districts affected and a chart of the streams to be
                                deepened, which we ask you to forward to the American Government, so
                                that negotiations may be carried on at once with the directors of
                                the Red Cross Society and the starving people may be saved by giving
                                them work. The merit so acquired would be boundless.</p>
                            <p>With compliments.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chang Chien</hi>.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hsu Tung-lin</hi>.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Reinsch</persName>
                                    to Messrs. <persName type="to">Chang Chien and Hsu
                                        Tung-lin</persName>.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-10-28">
                                        <hi rend="italic">October 28, 1914</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sirs</hi>: I desire to acknowledge the receipt
                                of your letter of the 18th instant, in which you describe the flood
                                and famine conditions in the Provinces of Kiangsu and Anhui. You
                                also ask me to explain to the American Government the gravity of the
                                present situation and to request it to consult with the managers of
                                the Red Cross Society with reference to an advance on the Huai River
                                loan account.</p>
                            <p>The condition which you describe is indeed so serious and threatens
                                such terrible calamity that I should only consider it my duty to
                                make the utmost efforts in aiding you to devise means for relief.
                                The past interest of the American people and of the American Red
                                Cross Society in the region which is again visited by so severe a
                                misfortune makes it certain that great sympathy will be felt for the
                                sufferers in my country, and that its people will be predisposed to
                                lend their assistance as far as possible.</p>
                            <pb facs="0229" n="113" xml:id="pg_113"/>
                            <p>As you know the American Red Cross Society aims to relieve suffering
                                in all parts of the world. The terrible war which is now devastating
                                Europe has engaged the energies of the Red Cross Society in an
                                effort to relieve the suffering incident thereto; this is a
                                difficult undertaking which is taxing the energies and resources of
                                the American Red Cross Society, and the financial disturbances which
                                accompany the war make it more difficult than ever to get funds even
                                for the most important and worthy objects. All this renders the work
                                of the Society especially difficult at the present time.</p>
                            <p>I feel every assurance that the American Red Cross Society is
                                continuing to feel a deep interest in the conditions of northern
                                Kiangsu and Anhui. As I have often expressed to you, however, the
                                Society in acting in the matter of the Huai River loan is only
                                exercising its good offices to bring the Chinese Government in touch
                                with the bankers and contractors, whose cooperation is necessary to
                                carry out the great work of the Huai River Conservancy. The American
                                Red Cross Society itself can not raise any money for loans; it can
                                only extend its good offices.</p>
                            <p>I shall be glad to submit this matter to the American Department of
                                State, asking that the Red Cross Society be informed. However,
                                whether it will be possible to get a large advance on the loan at
                                this time, upon this I can not give you any assurance. The report of
                                the engineers is indeed favorable, and we have every reason to hope
                                for the ultimate success of this great enterprise. But it is almost
                                impossible to get large sums of money for any purpose at the present
                                time; and the bankers may not desire to take up any part of this
                                loan before the entire contract has been definitely settled so that
                                they may be assured that the work will be completely carried out so
                                that the object of this undertaking may be achieved and permanent
                                relief afforded to the entire region.</p>
                            <p>I have felt it necessary to call your attention to the above
                                difficulties. I shall, however, report the whole situation to my
                                Government and I may assure you that every consideration will be
                                given to this matter both by the American Government and by the
                                American Red Cross Society, so that, if at all possible, a certain
                                amount of relief at least may be afforded in so far as is possible
                                in view of the distress in other parts of the world and of the
                                abnormal financial conditions now prevailing. I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Paul S. Reinsch</hi></signed>.</closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>