<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-10-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="1325" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1325">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 312.115/99.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">
                                <gloss type="from">Vice and Deputy Consul Germon</gloss> to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Consulate</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Progreso</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-10-01">
                                    <hi rend="italic">October 1, 1914</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to advise that the local
                            State Government has issued a decree declaring a forced loan amounting
                            to 8,000,000 <pb facs="0895" n="779" xml:id="pg_779"/> pesos, to be
                            contributed by all having a capital of real estate valued at more than
                            100,000 pesos.</p>
                        <p>The various allotments thus far run from 10,000 to 500,000 and the time
                            allowed to contribute same was fixed at 5 days after date of said
                            decree, namely, September 28th.</p>
                        <p>No definite conditions have been made upon which the loan is to be
                            effected, that is to say, the contributors are expected to pay over this
                            money” without a guarantee as to when same will be returned, nor for any
                            specified length of time. These conditions are to be determined by the
                            Government later on, as stated in the decree.</p>
                        <p>I have been approached by several Americans inquiring as to whether there
                            existed a treaty exempting American citizens from such forced payment,
                            and I have been unable to find anything in the Consulate upon a subject
                            of this sort. I would appreciate advice from the Department upon this
                            point, both where the American citizen owns property here, as well as
                            when he does not.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">J. W. Germon</hi></signed>.</closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>