<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-07-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-07-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="1545" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1545">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 812.404/3.</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Vice Consul <persName type="from">Silliman</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss>.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">American Consulate</hi>, <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Tampico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-07-27">
                                        <hi rend="italic">July 27, 1914</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to quote herewith a
                                translation made by myself of the decree of the Governor of the
                                State of Nuevo Leon, Gov. Villareal, regarding the Catholic clergy
                                and the Roman Catholic Church in that State: <pb facs="0991" n="875" xml:id="pg_875"/>
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>Decree of the Governor of the State of Nuevo Leon, Antonio I.
                                        Villareal, Governor and Military Commander of the State of
                                        Nuevo Leon, to the inhabitants thereof, Greeting:</p>
                                    <p>For reasons of public welfare, and complying with the
                                        unavoidable dictates of justice and morality, this
                                        Government has decided to suppress and punish within the
                                        limits of the State of Nuevo Leon the Roman Catholic clergy,
                                        taking into account the following considerations: <list>
                                            <label>1.</label>
                                            <item>During our whole National life, the clerics of
                                                Mexico, have been a pernicious factor of
                                                disorganization and discord; for, in forgetfulness
                                                of their spiritual mission, the only reason they
                                                have for existence under the tolerant spirit of
                                                modern society, they have devoted themselves mainly
                                                to controlling the direction of public affairs and
                                                to the complete domination of the politics of the
                                                country. To obtain this object, they have ever
                                                sought an alliance with our reactionary and despotic
                                                governments and even with foreigners, and when they
                                                could not be helping a Bustamente or a Santa Ana,
                                                they have called from Europe a Maximilian; on the
                                                other hand they have shown themselves the implacable
                                                enemy of every liberal and progressive movement from
                                                that of our National independence and the Revolution
                                                of Ayutla, until the present revolution, and they
                                                have fulminated their ridiculous excommunications
                                                against the greatest and grandest benefactors of the
                                                country: Hidalgo, Juarez, and Lerdo de
                                                Tejada.</item>
                                            <label>2.</label>
                                            <item>The forceful and clerical dictatorship of Porfirio
                                                Diaz and Victoriano Huerta against which the people,
                                                in these later years have heroically fought, have
                                                had all the sympathy and aid of the Mexican Church
                                                which has ever striven that light should not shine
                                                upon the darkness of the oppressed, and which has
                                                loved to weld the chains of those who suffer. The
                                                clergy has had blessings for the crimes and the
                                                repugnant corruptions of Huerta and has worked,
                                                fortunately without success, to induce the credulous
                                                proletariat to rise against the Constitutionalist
                                                movement which has come for their redemption.</item>
                                            <label>3.</label>
                                            <item>The clergy, on account of its very character and
                                                its way of living, in open contradiction with
                                                nature, whose laws can not be violated with
                                                impunity, tends to corruption, carries in itself the
                                                germs of corruption which reaches excess, when, as
                                                has happened among us, its power and its privileges
                                                are unrestrained. Clerical corruption has come to be
                                                a threat against morality in Mexico. The
                                                Confessional and the Sacristy are to be feared as
                                                anterooms of prostitution. To suppress them is a
                                                holy and regenerative work, as is also the closing
                                                of Catholic schools and the expulsion of Jesuits and
                                                teaching brothers (friars) foreign and Mexican,
                                                which this Government will do, excepting only those
                                                who can prove that they have not been allied with
                                                the men of the uprising at Mexico against Madero. In
                                                the Catholic schools the truth is perverted; the
                                                pure white soul of childhood, the idealistic burning
                                                spirit of youth is deformed, and as an instrument
                                                for the ambitions of the clericals there are chosen
                                                young spirits which in an environment more honorable
                                                and free might have come to be apostles of liberty
                                                and progress.</item>
                                            <label>4.</label>
                                            <item>It is a supreme national necessity and an
                                                obligation which can not be avoided by the
                                                Constitutional revolution, to take energetic and
                                                effective measures to dig up from the root, and once
                                                for all, put an end to the abominable abuses of the
                                                Catholic clergy and terminate the grave danger which
                                                this institution, more political than religious, has
                                                for the future tranquillity and progress of the
                                                fatherland.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>It is not the intention of this Government to ignore the
                                        liberty of conscience or to persecute what is really worship
                                        among Catholics while other religionists enjoy guarantees,
                                        and for this reason it is agreed that five of the Catholic
                                        churches of Monterey may be reopened for public worship, but
                                        it being necessary, and this Government being firm in its
                                        determination to maintain the Catholic clergy and the
                                        Catholic worship within the limit of its spiritual mission,
                                        without allowing it any influence, politically,
                                        economically, or educationally, has resolved to impose the
                                        following orders for the Catholic schools and worship.</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>The decree consists of eight articles which were wired to the
                                Department in a radiogram yesterday.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">John E. Silliman</hi></signed>.</closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>