<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Thomson to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d154</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">154</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1914-03-11T21:56:00-05:00" notAfter="1914-03-11T21:56:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-03-11T21:56:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-03-11T21:56:00-05:00" n="154"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d154">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 711.21/235.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Thomson</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Bogotá</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-03-11T22:00:00-04:56">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 11, 1914, 10 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Your March 10, 8 p.m. In the Colombian counter-proposition of February 5, 5 p.m.,
                    to that of your December 19, 6 p.m., there was inserted a new clause in Article
                    IV whereby it was understood that, in recognizing the independence of Panama,
                    Colombia renounced liability for all claims of whatsoever nature whether of
                    governments or individuals for acts or events which may have taken place at any
                    time in the territory of Panama.</p>
                <p>By your telegraphic instruction of February 28, 11 p.m., I was directed to say,
                    and so informed the Colombian Government, that you did not consider this
                    provision to be germane to the present treaty and that it was a proper subject
                    for discussion between Colombia and Panama at the time of negotiating the treaty
                    of peace and friendship for which Article IV provides.</p>
                <p>As I have already had the honor of informing the Department in my telegram of
                    March 7, 9 p.m., Colombia has insisted upon retaining this provision in the face
                    of your opinion that it was not germane to the present treaty. Although my
                    understanding had been, when leaving Washington, that the instructions [to] be
                    sent me on my arrival at Bogota would be final, I wished to leave nothing undone
                    in my power if possible to satisfy legitimate Colombian aspirations, and
                    therefore ventured to inquire whether you would be willing to retain this
                    provision proposed by Colombia if a <pb facs="0267" n="151" xml:id="pg_151"/>
                    further provision were added releasing Panama from all obligation to pay her
                    share of the external and internal debt of Colombia existing on November 3,
                    1903.</p>
                <p>Although the suggestion to insert such a provision releasing Panama from all
                    Colombian claims has not been proposed by the Minister for Foreign Affairs, I
                    learn on reliable authority that if presented by me it would be accepted by the
                    Minister and the Commission of the Foreign Office.</p>
                <p>If, therefore, the Department should see fit to instruct me to accept Paragraph 2
                    of Article IV of the Colombian counterproposition of March 5, 5 p.m., with a
                    proper proviso similarly releasing Panama from all claims Colombia might have
                    against her, I have no doubt but that with this modification, and with the
                    acceptance of the two modifications in Article II submitted to your
                    consideration in my telegram of March 7, 9 p.m., a speedy settlement will be
                    reached.</p>
                <p>If, however, you maintain your former opinion that this proposal is not germane
                    to the present treaty, or if the mutual release of obligations is unacceptable
                    to Panama, I feel confident that I shall nevertheless be able to settle on the
                    terms of your telegram of February 28, 11 p.m.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomson</hi>
                    </signed>.</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
