<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-07-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-07-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="1547" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1547">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 312.51/76.</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">French Chargé
                                        d’Affaires</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss>.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">French Embassy</hi>, <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Manchester</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-07-27">
                                        <hi rend="italic">July 27, 1914</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: The attention of
                                the Government of the Republic has been drawn to the trying
                                circumstances which in May last, attended the arrest at and
                                expulsion from Monterey, by the Constitutionalist authorities, of 14
                                French citizens, of the Christian Brothers, teachers at the
                                “Instituto del Sagrado Corazon de Jesus” with 300 pupils, and the
                                “Colegio Guadalupano.”</p>
                            <p>Arrested on May 12, asked to pay 500,000 pesos for the
                                Constitutionalist cause, they were ordered to leave the next day by
                                the very first train. With great difficulty and after repeated
                                calls, the Consular Agent of the Republic, Mr. Pierre Lambreton with
                                the assistance of the American, Italian and Spanish Consuls, finally
                                secured the release of the prisoners and permission for them to
                                leave in three groups on the 14th, 15th and 16th of May.</p>
                            <p>My Government directs me to bring the occurrence to your excellency’s
                                knowledge and to ask, on this occasion, that the Federal Government
                                will intervene to protect French interests in North Mexico.</p>
                            <p>By order of my Government I also have the honor to call your
                                excellency’s attention to the fact that the Government of the
                                Republic reserves to itself the right to claim hereafter such
                                indemnity as it may deem commensurate to the wrong done to French
                                interests by the Constitutionalist authorities.</p>
                            <p>Be pleased to accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Clausse</hi></signed>.</closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>