<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Gonzales to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d211</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">211</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1914-06-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1914-06-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-06-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-06-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="211"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d211">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 837.911/31.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Gonzales</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 116.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Habana</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-06-16">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 16, 1914</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to request authority to ask
                    President Menocal for the pardon of Enrique Maza.</p>
                <p>On August 27, 1912, Maza, a young Cuban, was a reporter on the Cuban newspaper La
                    Noche. That day, after much public agitation, Mr. H. S. Gibson, then Charge,
                    went to the Cuban State Department with the Second Secretary of Legation and
                    with the American contractor, and collected the Keilly claim amounting to more
                    than $500,000. The Government’s check was declined, and the Cuban authorities
                    were required to bring the currency and deliver it to Mr. Gibson in the State
                    Department.</p>
                <p>That evening Enrique Maza assaulted Mr. Gibson in the lobby of the Miramar Hotel,
                    striking him from behind with his fists and knocking him down. Mr. Bell, the
                    Second Secretary, interposed and knocked down Maza.</p>
                <p>The following day Maza was indicted and placed in jail. On October 7, 1912, he
                    was sentenced to two years and six months imprisonment. He has served more than
                    twenty months of the sentence and has been in prison for nearly twenty-two
                    months.</p>
                <pb facs="0306" n="190" xml:id="pg_190"/>
                <p>The Cuban administration at that time was pronouncedly anti-American and in
                    speaking to reporters Secretary of State Sanguily unquestionably incited them to
                    attacks upon the American attitude. I believe from information received here
                    that Maza, having received a distorted idea of his country’s wrongs and having a
                    temperament that lent itself to a morbid patriotism, imagined that he was
                    striking a blow for his country’s honor when he assaulted Mr. Gibson. He was in
                    reality an irresponsible instrument through which the antagonism of high Cuban
                    officials was expressed.</p>
                <p>The only formal appeal made to me in behalf of Maza has come from an association
                    of working women of Cuba. President Menocal has ignored all pleas for pardon
                    made by the Cuban press association.</p>
                <p>I think the punishment already suffered by Maza is sufficient and the dignity of
                    the United States fully sustained. Should Maza be permitted to serve the
                    remaining nine months of his sentence he would emerge from prison a popular
                    idol, hailed as a martyr for his country. On the other hand, his pardon, secured
                    on the initiative of the United States, would not only prevent any recurrence of
                    anti-American sentiment but would increase friendly feeling. An opportunity
                    would be offered, also, for a statement of the true obligations of a worthy
                    press of any country, and such an understanding is greatly needed in Cuba.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William E. Gonzales</hi>
                    </signed>.</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
