<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-07-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-07-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="213" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d213">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 837. 911/32.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Gonzales</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 123.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-07-11">
                                    <hi rend="italic">July 11, 1914</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the recent correspondence in
                            regard to the case of Enrique Maza, the Cuban newspaper reporter who was
                            serving a jail sentence in Habana for an assault upon Mr. Gibson, then
                            American Charge d’Affaires, in 1912, I have the honor to inclose
                            herewith a copy of a letter which I addressed to President Menocal on
                            the 2d instant, stating that the time already served by Maza <pb facs="0307" n="191" xml:id="pg_191"/> might well be considered by
                            the Cuban Government as sufficient satisfaction of his sentence, and
                            that the United States had no desire for his further confinement.</p>
                        <p>In consequence of this letter the President has pardoned Maza. The press
                            has expressed much satisfaction over our action in this matter. While
                            profusely welcoming Maza’s release, I have noticed no attempt to
                            exculpate his act or revive the feeling against our Government to which
                            the assault upon Mr. Gibson was attributed.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">William E. Gonzales</hi></signed>.</closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Gonzales</persName>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">President of Cuba</gloss>.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-07-02">
                                        <hi rend="italic">July 2, 1914</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: With an
                                understanding of that courtesy between nations that precludes the
                                Government of one country from extending clemency to one of its
                                nationals for an offense committed against another country without
                                the consent of the offended country, representatives of the
                                Asociacion de la Prensa de Cuba and the Sociedad de Bobineras have
                                sought my intercession in behalf of Enrique Maza, who, on October 7,
                                1912, began serving a prison sentence of 2½ years as punishment for
                                an assault upon Mr. Gibson, then Chargé d’Affaires of the United
                                States in Cuba.</p>
                            <p>I am authorized to say to Your Excellency on behalf of my Government
                                that the time already served by Maza might well be considered by the
                                Cuban Government as sufficient satisfaction of his sentence, and
                                that the United States has no desire for his further
                                confinement.</p>
                            <p>This attitude of my Government must not be taken as indicating that
                                the offense of an attack upon the person of the representative of
                                the United States, in resentment of his official acts, is viewed in
                                other than the most serious light.</p>
                            <p>I wish to take this opportunity to deny the assumption that because
                                Maza had a journalistic connection his act represents the press. It
                                is futile, as it is unreasoning and narrow, to expect that the
                                customs and standards of one people should take the mold of another
                                people, but the spirit of a free press is universal. It knows the
                                boundaries of no countries. Liberty, when first given the press by
                                the people, was for service performed and expected for the people. A
                                free press is unknown except among self-governing people, and for
                                such people respect for the law of the land is the surest guaranty
                                of justice and safety for the masses.</p>
                            <p>If the press has a mission, it is to stand unfalteringly for good
                                government, and therefore to contend always for those prime
                                essentials of good government, honesty in the affairs of government,
                                and obedience to the law by all classes. The true patriot is not one
                                who loudly proclaims his patriotism and makes protest against
                                alleged wrongs to his country by violating law and bringing reproach
                                upon that country; it is the one who practices and preaches good
                                citizenship.</p>
                            <p>The journalist who indulges in lawless acts debars himself from
                                defending the law and places himself in antagonism to the spirit of
                                that press which is worthy its constitutional liberty. Such a
                                journalist may no more become the champion of law and order and
                                defender of the people’s rights than the newspaper that prostitutes
                                itself, by secretly selling its influence against public welfare,
                                may assail dishonesty and immorality. The spirit of the press that
                                earned a right to free speech, because its voice was raised against
                                dishonesty, injustice and crime, and which is unbought and
                                unpurchasable, stands unfalteringly for law and order, equality
                                before the law and responsibility for infraction of the law.</p>
                            <p>The spirit of the press is the spirit of patriotism; it has nothing
                                in common with unbridled passions or lawlessness—those are bred of
                                the spirit of anarchy.</p>
                            <p>With renewed assurance [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">William E. Gonzales</hi></signed>.</closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>