<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Remarks made by the Bulgarian Minister on his reception by the President,
                    December 22, 1914.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d50</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">50</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1914-12-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1914-12-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-12-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-12-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="50"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d50">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 701.7411/12.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Remarks made by the Bulgarian Minister on his reception by the
                        President, December 22, 1914.</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1914-12-22">December 22, 1914</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. President</hi>: In his great desire to maintain and
                    draw closer the ties of friendship happily existing between the United States
                    and Bulgaria, His Majesty the King of the Bulgarians has deigned to appoint me
                    his representative near the Government of the United <pb facs="0151" n="35"
                        xml:id="pg_35"/> States. In the performance of the duties incumbent upon me
                    for the carrying out of this desire of His Majesty, I shall endeavor to acquit
                    myself of my mission in such a way as to win your confidence and merit His
                    Majesty’s approbation. With this end in view, I shall highly prize the valuable
                    aid and good will of Your Excellency and your Government, which will facilitate
                    my task and help to make my mission a success.</p>
                <p>In handing you, Mr. President, the credentials whereby His Majesty accredits me
                    to you, I have been bidden to express on his behalf and in behalf of his
                    Government the deep sorrow and sincere sympathy they feel for you in the sad
                    bereavement that has lately befallen you, to assure you of the high esteem His
                    Majesty entertains for your person and the ardent wishes he cherishes for the
                    progress and prosperity of your great country, as well as for the wellbeing and
                    happiness of its people.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
