<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to Ambassador O’Brien.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d611</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">611</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1913-07-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1913-07-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1913-07-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1913-07-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="611"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d611">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 365.117/9.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        Ambassador <persName type="to">O’Brien</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 143.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1913-07-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 15, 1913</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department has received your despatch No. 254
                    of June 11, 1913, in reply to its instruction No. 139, of May 26 last,
                    concerning the age limit for military service in Italy.</p>
                <p>In the Department’s printed circular entitled “Notice to American Citizens
                    Formerly Subjects of Italy Who Contemplate Returning to that Country,” dated
                    March 18, 1901, a copy of which was enclosed with the instruction mentioned
                    above,’ appears the following statement: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>A former Italian subject may visit Italy without fear of molestation when
                            he is under the age of 20 years; but between the ages of 20 and 39 he is
                            liable to arrest and forced military service, if he has not previously
                            reported for such service. After the age of 39 he may be arrested and
                            imprisoned (but will not be compelled to do military duty) unless he has
                            been pardoned. He may petition the Italian Government for pardon, but
                            this Department will not act as the intermediary in presenting his
                            petition.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>You will please inform the Department, after such further inquiry as may be
                    necessary, whether the paragraph just quoted is correct or should be amended.
                    This paragraph does not appear to agree with the following statement in your
                    despatch of June 11:</p>
                <p>After the age of 32, while a subject is still liable for military service in the
                    territorial reserves, he is not punishable for past failure to appear for
                    service.</p>
                <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">J. B. Moore</hi>
                    </signed>.</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
