<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to Ambassador Page.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d615</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">615</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1914-06-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1914-06-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-06-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-06-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="615"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d615">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 711.654/7.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        Ambassador <persName type="to">Page</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 65.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department Of State</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-06-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 19, 1914</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the last paragraph of your
                    despatch No. 52, of January 5, 1914, concerning the Department’s “Notice to
                    American Citizens Formerly Subjects of Italy who Contemplate Returning to that
                    Country,” 1 send you herewith a copy of a letter of June 5, 1914, from the
                    Honorable Charles B. Smith, a Representative in Congress from the State of New
                    York, concerning the introduction in Congress of a proposed resolution asking
                    the Department to negotiate for a treaty of naturalization with Italy. I also
                    enclose a copy of the Department’s reply of this day, calling your special
                    attention to the references therein to previous correspondence with your office
                    concerning the negotiation of a naturalization treaty between this country and
                    Italy.</p>
                <p>As a step preliminary to the formal opening of further negotiations with the
                    Italian Government, looking to the conclusion of a treaty of naturalization, the
                    Department desires to be informed as to what changes, if any, have been made in
                    the Italian laws since <pb facs="0519" n="403" xml:id="pg_403"/> the
                    correspondence with your office in the year 1911, which would seem to make the
                    conclusion of a naturalization treaty more feasible than before.</p>
                <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing</hi>
                    </signed>.</closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Honorable <persName type="from">Charles B.
                                Smith</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">House of Representatives</hi>, <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-06-05">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 5, 1914</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: I have had under
                        consideration the introduction of a resolution asking the State Department
                        to negotiate for a further treaty with Italy. The purpose I have in mind is
                        to obtain from the Italian Government a concession which will permit
                        Italians who have become American citizens to return to their homes in Italy
                        to make a visit without being in danger of arrest for violating the laws in
                        regard to military duty. One of my friends, a professional man, who was two
                        years old when he left Italy, would like to visit his old home in his native
                        country. He is a citizen of the United States and a most estimable young
                        man. But he does not dare to visit his relatives in Italy owing to the fear
                        of the conscription regulations of the Italian Government.</p>
                    <p>I have a population of more than thirty thousand Italian-Americans in my
                        Congressional District. Those who are affected in this particular have been
                        persistent in their desire that something be done to make it possible for
                        them to visit Italy. I will be glad to have your views on this subject.</p>
                    <p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles B. Smith</hi>
                        </signed>.</closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            Honorable <persName type="to">Chas. B. Smith</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-06-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 19, 1914</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department has received your letter of
                        June 5, 1914, concerning the proposed introduction in Congress of a
                        resolution asking the Department to negotiate for a treaty of naturalization
                        with Italy, for the purpose of obtaining from the Italian Government “a
                        concession which will permit Italians who have become American citizens to
                        return to their homes in Italy to make a visit without being in danger of
                        arrest for violating the laws in regard to military duty.”</p>
                    <p>This Government has repeatedly approached the Government of Italy for the
                        purpose of obtaining a naturalization treaty, the last time in the year
                        1911. I enclose, for your information, copies of the Department’s
                        instructions to the Embassy at Rome, Nos. 173, of February 11, 1907, and 185
                        of April 6, 1911, directing the Embassy to negotiate for the conclusion of a
                        treaty of naturalization, and stating the reasons therefor; and copies of
                        despatches from the Embassy, Nos. 389, of June 19, 1908, and 446, of
                        September 15, 1911, giving the grounds upon which the Italian Government
                        declined to conclude such a treaty. You are also referred to Moore’s
                        International Law Digest, Volume 3, page 614, and the volume of <ref
                            target="frus1896#pg_422">Foreign Relations of the United States for
                            1896, pages 422</ref> et seq.</p>
                    <p>In view of the repeated attempts of this Government to obtain a treaty of
                        naturalization with Italy, through the Embassy at Rome, it may reasonably be
                        presumed that the Italian Government is aware of the desire of this
                        Government to conclude such a treaty. Perhaps a joint resolution of Congress
                        asking the Department to open further negotiations for a naturalization
                        treaty would impress the Government of Italy with the importance which is
                        attached to this matter by the people of the United States, I may add that
                        the Department has recently had under consideration the question of
                        instructing the Embassy at Rome to approach the Italian Government again
                        with regard to the conclusion <pb facs="0520" n="404" xml:id="pg_404"/> of
                        the desired treaty. It is the understanding of the Department that the
                        principal obstacle to the conclusion of a naturalization treaty is found in
                        Article 12 of the Italian Civil Code, which provides that the law of Italian
                        citizenship through the naturalization of an Italian as a citizen of another
                        country “does not work exemption from the obligations of the military
                        service, nor from the penalties imposed on those who bear arms against their
                        country.” The Department, as a step preliminary to the formal opening of
                        further negotiations for a naturalization treaty with the Italian
                        Government, has this day forwarded to the Ambassador at Rome a copy of your
                        letter under acknowledgment, with instructions to ascertain and inform the
                        Department as to what changes, if any, have been made in the laws of Italy
                        since the correspondence in the year 1911, mentioned above, which would seem
                        to make the conclusion of a naturalization treaty more feasible than before.
                        I shall be glad to inform you of the Ambassador’s reply, and would like to
                        be informed of your final decision as to the introduction of the proposed
                        resolution.</p>
                    <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing</hi>
                        </signed>.</closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
