<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Chargé MacMurray to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d92</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">92</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1914-09-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1914-09-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-09-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-09-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="92"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d92">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 493.11/529.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Chargé <persName type="from">MacMurray</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 367.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-09-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 12, 1914</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to previous correspondence in regard to
                    the payment of interest by the Chinese Government on claims arising out of the
                    Revolution of 1911–1912, I have the honor to enclose herewith copies of
                    diplomatic circulars embodying recent communications which have passed between
                    the Foreign Office and the Dean of the Diplomatic Body on this subject.</p>
                <p>It will be seen therein that the Chinese Government has finally acquiesced in the
                    demands of the Diplomatic Body that interest should be allowed, and has notified
                    it that interest at the rate of 5 per cent will be paid on liquidated claims,
                    calculated from April 26, 1913, until the date of actual payment; and that this
                    offer has been accepted.* * *</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">J. V. A. MacMurray</hi>
                    </signed>.</closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1—Summary.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-inferred-from-preceding-sibling-head"
                        >[Untitled]</head>
                    <p>Report, dated July 10, of the Dean to the Diplomatic Body that he had made a
                        verbal demand upon the Wai Chiao Fu for interest on settled claims at 5%
                        from January 1, 1913; and that the Minister for Foreign Affairs had refused
                        to consider this request. Request of the Dean for the Diplomatic Body’s
                        authorization to convey formally its decision that interest should be so
                        paid.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2—Summary.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-inferred-from-preceding-sibling-head"
                        >[Untitled]</head>
                    <p>Incloses, July 25, a note addressed on July 22 by the Dean to the Wai Chiao
                        Pu formally conveying the Diplomatic Body’s demand for interest on all
                        settled claims at 5% from January 1, 1913.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0211" n="95" xml:id="pg_95"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3—Extract.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-inferred-from-preceding-sibling-head"
                        >[Untitled]</head>
                    <p>Incloses, August 26, the following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p rend="right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi>, <hi rend="italic">August 25,
                                    1914</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>To the Dean of the Diplomatic Body:</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge
                                receipt of your excellency’s note of July 22 on the subject of the
                                payment of interest on Revolution indemnity claims.</p>
                            <p>After the Revolution of 1911 the Government, out of compassion for
                                foreign merchants, set apart a portion of the loan in order to
                                compensate them for their losses, and appointed a committee of
                                investigation. All cases of claims on account of direct losses have
                                since been impartially considered in conjunction with the foreign
                                commissioners, and successive payments have been made. The Chinese
                                Government may be said to have been most generous in its
                                consideration for foreign merchants. If in addition payment of
                                interest be demanded, the amounts individually received by foreign
                                merchants will be small while the burden falling on the Chinese
                                Government will be very heavy. In view, however, of the repeated
                                requests made by your excellency in your capacity as Dean, this
                                Ministry will give consideration to your views and those of your
                                honorable colleagues and will, as an exceptional proceeding, admit
                                the payment of 5 per cent interest in addition to the payment of
                                indemnities; such interest to be calculated from April 26, 1913,
                                being the date of signature of the Reorganization Loan wherein China
                                admitted the payment of compensation to foreigners for losses
                                suffered during the 1911 revolution, until the date on which such
                                payment was made.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Seal of the</hi>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps"> Wai Chiao Pu</hi>
                        </signed>.</closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4—Extract.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-inferred-from-preceding-sibling-head"
                        >[Untitled]</head>
                    <p>Incloses, September 9, the following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p rend="right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">British Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Peking, September 9, 1914</hi>.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">His Excellency Sun Pao-ch’i</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to your excellency’s
                                note of August 25, I have the honour to inform you that the members
                                of the Diplomatic Body authorize me to accept the proposal made by
                                your excellency’s Government that interest should be paid by your
                                Government on indemnities admitted on revolution claims, such
                                interest to be at the rate of 5 per cent per annum and to run from
                                26th April, 1913, the date of the signature of the Reorganization
                                Loan, to the date on which payment of the claim was made.</p>
                            <p>I avail [etc.]</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">J. N. Jordan</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Dean of the Diplomatic Body</hi>
                        </signed>.</closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
