<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-03-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-03-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="103" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d103">
                        <head>103. Memorandum From the Naval Aide to the Presidentʼs Military
                            Representative (<persName corresp="#p_BWH1" type="from">Bagley</persName>) to the Presidentʼs Military Representative
                                (<persName corresp="#p_TMD1" type="to">Taylor</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d103fn1">Source: National Defense University,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName> Papers, T-133-69.
                                Secret.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-03-10"><hi rend="italic">March 10,
                                1962</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Operation Sunrise</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The attached plan<note n="2" xml:id="d103fn2">Not found.</note> provides
                            for the pacification of Binh Duong province (southern edge of which is
                            12 miles north of Saigon).</p>
                        <p>Essentials of plan are as follows:</p>
                        <pb facs="0233" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Enemy:</hi> 1800 regular and provincial troops plus
                            sympathizers; in strong control of northern half of province.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Friendly:</hi> In addition to unspecified number of
                                <gloss target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss> in the province now, allocate five <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> infantry battalions to clear northern
                            part of province; two civil guard battalions for local security; four
                            ranger companies; one river forces group; VNAF and US Army helo company.
                            There are nine civic action teams (16 men per team) operating now in
                            southern part of Binh Duong province; five additional teams (32 men per
                            team) will be added for the operation.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mission:</hi> The Government of the Republic of South
                            Vietnam conducts combined civil-military operations in the province of
                            Binh Duong to eliminate Viet Cong control over the people; provide for
                            the selective relocation and physical security of the population;
                            enforce law and order; assist in rehabilitating village administration,
                            economy and security; and assist in consolidating national control
                            within the area of operations by enhancing popular support for the
                            counterinsurgency effort.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Concept:</hi> Three phases of operations are planned: <list>
                                <label>I.</label>
                                <item>Preparatory (prior to D-Day). Reconnaissance and planning;
                                    determine requirements for village relocation and civic action;
                                    determine requirements for additional para-military personnel;
                                    train paramilitary and civic action personnel; command and
                                    logistic planning in detail; psywar and civic action planning;
                                    military planning.</item>
                                <label>II.</label>
                                <item>Military (D-Day to D+30). Regular forces gain control of
                                    northern areas in which population resettlement is to be
                                    undertaken; psywar campaign to explain to population the reasons
                                    for movement of their homes; Army engs and civic action teams
                                    move to new village sites (population of 15 villages will be
                                    moved to 5 new defended villages) for clearing ground and
                                    constructing defenses; <gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss> provide
                                    village security; regular forces maintain secure <gloss target="#t_LOC1">LOC</gloss>ʼs; villagers moved to new sites
                                    (priority to 3 villages because of limited resources; complete
                                    other 2 villages when forces are released) and given
                                    funds/material/help in reconstructing their homes; concurrently,
                                    clear western part of province and resettle on more limited
                                    basis.</item>
                                <label>III.</label>
                                <item>Consolidation (D+30 to D+120 approximately). Phase out of
                                    regular forces as <gloss target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss> are able to provide security;
                                    defensive village system and population controls continued and
                                    refined; village alarm system established; security patrols
                                    instituted; civic action pursued on urgent basis to regain
                                    normal living conditions; information program and facilities
                                    established; civic action teams (after 2-4 months) train local
                                    replacements and prepare to move to a new location.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Command:</hi> The Province Chief is responsible for
                            Phases I and III; the Commander. <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss>
                            5th Inf Div for Phase II.</p>
                        <pb facs="0234" n="214" xml:id="pg_214"/>
                        <p>Specific parts of this plan which you may wish to scan are clipped as
                            follows: <list>
                                <item><gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> organization</item>
                                <item><gloss target="#t_LOC1">LOC</gloss> overlay</item>
                                <item>Village overlay</item>
                                <item>Secure Village Concept</item>
                                <item>Emergency Assistance and Support</item>
                                <item>Material requirements—village security</item>
                                <item>Psywar Plan</item>
                                <item>Civil Affairs Plan</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Some questions which the Plan raises: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Date Phase II will commence (will rainy season delay until
                                    Oct/Nov)?</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Extent of population indoctrination prior to Phase II.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>What the US is doing now to expedite Phase I (which is in
                                    progress to some unknown extent)?</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>What the US is doing to provide resources for Phase
                                    III.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>What role US advisors will have at command levels during Phase
                                    II to assure effective direction as the operation
                                    unfolds.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Possibility of success in view of strong <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> position in north part of
                                    province and zone D to the east (it is of interest that in past
                                    10 days, <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> have increased scope
                                    of operations in Tay Ninh Province to the west).</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>Nature of follow-on operations in other provinces and extent
                                    of concurrent planning.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>Supporting operations planned to divert <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> reinforcements from Binh Duong as the operation
                                    gets underway.</item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item>Extent of reserves to be earmarked for the operation.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_COMUSMACV1">COMUSMACV</gloss> are working with the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> on details of this plan; detailed
                            information on status is almost nonexistent. While not expressed, I
                            think this operation will not be ready until the fall of this year. This
                            is why it is vital there be more intensive attention to preparatory and
                            supplemental actions (country-wide civic action; border patrols) to
                            prevent further deterioration of the security situation while we prepare
                            for offensive operations.<note n="3" xml:id="d103fn3">Phase I of
                                Operation “Sunrise” got underway on March 22. According to the
                                minutes of the meeting of the Committee on Province Rehabilitation
                                for April 20, Phase 1I began on April 17. (Department of State,
                                Vietnam Task Force Files: Lot 66 D 193, 6.1-C, <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> 1962, Agrovilles &amp; Land
                                Devmt)</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_BWH1"><hi rend="strong">W.H.B.</hi></persName><note n="4" xml:id="d103fn4">Printed from
                                    a copy that bears these typed initials.</note></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>