<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>150. Telegram From the Embassy in Vietnam to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d150</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">150</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-04-07T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-04-07T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-04-07T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-04-07T07:00:00-05:00" n="150"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d150">
                <head>150. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d150fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 951K.6211/4-1762. Secret Priority. Repeated to <gloss
                            target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_Polad1"
                            >Polad</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-04-07T20:00:00+08:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 7, 1962—8 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1277. For Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HWA2">Harriman</persName>
                    from <persName corresp="#p_NFEJ1">Nolting</persName>. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1"
                        >Deptel</gloss> 1173.<note n="2" xml:id="d150fn2">
                        <ref target="#d145">Document 145</ref>.</note> Your message has been read by
                    all principal officers Task Force Saigon and its importance stressed. We have
                    all been striving for many weeks to prevent and correct the kind of reporting to
                    which you refer, for the reasons given your tel. Will continue do everything
                    possible to keep reporting in perspective, stressing, as we have been doing,
                    fact that US role here is advisory and supporting, and does not involve US
                    direction, control, leadership, or responsibility for Vietnamese struggle. Since
                    receipt <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1006,<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d150fn3">
                        <ref target="#d75">Document 75</ref>.</note> I think we have made headway in
                    enlisting cooperation of majority US press corps here, but there are still
                    certain exceptions. Davis has been working constantly and effectively on this
                    and related problems. Given scope and magnitude US assistance, however,
                    attainment our objectives will require self-discipline on part of press and
                    interest in more accurate and balanced reporting.</p>
                <p>Vietnamese themselves invented code word “Binh Minh” (translate “Sunrise”). We
                    taking steps to assure that shorthand names for other <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                        >GVN</gloss> operations have indigenous character.</p>
                <p>Bigartʼs reference to “large group Americans” inspecting stockade apparently
                    confuses military operation with dedication ceremony of Cu Chi strategic
                    village. No large group Americans involved in either, but about a dozen
                    Americans, representatives of civilian agencies as well as military, attended
                    dedication ceremony Cu Chi March 28 on invitation <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                        >GVN</gloss>. Numbers were deliberately held down below those invited.</p>
                <p>All members team Saigon will continue do their utmost on this problem.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NFEJ1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Nolting</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
