<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>197. Memorandum From the Public Affairs Officer at the Embassy in Vietnam
                    (Mecklin) to the Deputy Public Affairs Officer () to the Deputy Public Affairs
                    Officer (Baumgartner))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d197</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">197</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-05-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recHrSmzhfG78SwqX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="recpqcSvEFyuxPc7E" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134146"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Testing</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-05-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="197"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d197">
                <head>197. Memorandum From the Public Affairs Officer at the Embassy in Vietnam
                        (<persName corresp="#p_MJ10" type="from">Mecklin</persName>) to the Deputy
                    Public Affairs Officer (<persName type="to">Baumgartner</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d197fn1">Source: Washington National Records Center,
                        RG 84, Saigon Embassy Files: FRC 67 A 677. <gloss target="#t_USIS1"
                            >USIS</gloss> 1962. Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-05-17">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 17, 1962</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>PsyOps Committee Meeting of May 18</item>
                </list>
                <p>As you know, I had planned to propose to the Committee at tomorrowʼs meeting that
                    we react to the coming on stream of the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>ʼs
                    new radio transmitters with a hard look at the content of counter-insurgency
                    information activities. Since I cannot attend the meeting, perhaps you could
                    propose the idea and see what happens? If there is adequate encouragement, my
                    thought is that perhaps each agency could put together a report within, say, a
                    week which you and I would undertake to wrap up in a sort of working paper for
                    discussion at the next meeting. I realize, of course, that this is something
                    less than a new idea, and that a good many people have already sweated at length
                    over this problem. But Iʼm told that there has not been an effort to look at it
                    collectively in this fashion.</p>
                <p>In any case, it seems to me we should try to sort out four questions: <list>
                        <label>1)</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>How effective, vis-à-vis the insurgency problem, is the propaganda
                                now being directed at the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> and the
                                Vietnamese people?</p>
                            <p>Replies to my superficial enquiries have been unanimous that the
                                content of <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> propaganda is poor.
                                The most common complaint was that it is too negative, with
                                heavy-handed emphasis on what the regime is against, instead of what
                                itʼs for. At yesterdayʼs ceremonies <pb facs="0426" n="406"
                                    xml:id="pg_406"/> opening the new Saigon transmitter, for
                                example, Minister Hieu talked first about the sins of the <gloss
                                    target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> and then about “the three enemies”:
                                Communism, disunity, and backwardness. The sense of his remarks was
                                that the new radio facilities would be devoted more or less
                                exclusively to the battle against those things. Just about the only
                                positive thought in his speech was a relatively secondary reference
                                to personalism, which he elaborated in only one or two
                                sentences.</p>
                            <p>One of the most helpful errors of Communist propaganda worldwide is
                                that it is monumentally long-winded and boring. Is the <gloss
                                    target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> pitch committing the same mistake?
                                Minister Hieu remarked to me the other night that <gloss
                                    target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> propaganda at the boondocks level
                                was now avoiding all mention of President <persName
                                    corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> and talking instead about
                                specific boondocks problems. Apart from the controversy about the
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> regime, can you
                                reach the Vietnamese peasant without offering him a leader? Is the
                                suppression of <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName>ʼs name a
                                surrender to <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> propaganda, or to
                                stateside press criticism, or perhaps inescapable in the present
                                circumstances? Is it true that <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                                propaganda (as well as our own supporting efforts) uniformly depicts
                                the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> as baby-murdering, arsonist
                                monsters? Is this a true picture of the <gloss target="#t_VC1"
                                    >VC</gloss> as it is known to the majority of the peasants in
                                the red and pink areas whom we are trying to reach? In short is the
                                present pitch credible?</p>
                            <p>Does anyone have a really hard reading on how well <gloss
                                    target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> propaganda is working in the rural
                                areas? Among town dwellers who probably have not had first-hand
                                contact with the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>? Is adequate
                                consideration being given to the probability that the pitch to town
                                dwellers should be different from the pitch to peasants?</p>
                            <p>(Of course there is also the equally basic question of whether
                                existing propaganda programs are really arriving in the target
                                areas, regardless of the quality of the content. Should the heavy
                                emphasis be on radio, or village newspapers, or airdropped leaflets,
                                or what? But this perhaps should be the subject of a separate
                                study.)</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>2)</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>Is it possible to establish broad guidelines on ways to improve
                                    <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> propaganda?</p>
                            <p>Is it possible, for example, to laugh at the <gloss target="#t_VC1"
                                    >VC</gloss>, to make them look ridiculous and thus lose face?
                                For village level consumption, can a more subtle approach be used,
                                with less emphasis on terror and more on Communist techniques for
                                capturing and destroying a manʼs mind? How should the American
                                presence be treated? Ignored on the theory that the villagers
                                dislike foreigners? Or perhaps brought out in carefully controlled
                                ways to show the presence of American power to help defend the
                                people against the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>? How about more
                                emphasis on economic improvements bestowed by the Saigon Government,
                                along lines of <persName corresp="#p_WCB1">Ben Wood</persName>ʼs
                                paper on <gloss target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss>ʼs achievements?<note
                                    n="2" xml:id="d197fn2">Not found.</note> In any case, <pb
                                    facs="0427" n="407" xml:id="pg_407"/> can policy lines be
                                established to put more emphasis on the positive, in the sense
                                perhaps of a sort of frame of reference for testing new
                                projects?</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>3)</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>To what extent do the various U.S. agencies now influence the content
                                of <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> propaganda and in what
                                specific ways is this done?</p>
                            <p>In the case of <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss>, there is close
                                to total U.S. control (except for a <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                                    >GVN</gloss> veto) in such operations as the weekly newsreel,
                                some 50 hours of weekly radio programming, the Operation Sunrise
                                newspaper, plus various other areas which you can elaborate. My idea
                                is that it would be useful for the Committee to collect specifics on
                                what all the U.S. agencies in Vietnam are doing along these lines,
                                and then to try to assess effectiveness and target areas that are
                                not being adequately covered.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>4)</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>Finally, where and how can the U.S. increase its influence over the
                                content of <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> propaganda, assuming
                                this is desirable?</p>
                            <p>As I see it, this would be a study primarily concerned with specific
                                situations and personalities within the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                                    >GVN</gloss> and with specific U.S. <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                                    >GVN</gloss> relationships where there are possibilities for
                                negotiating a greater U.S. voice, e.g. the proposed <gloss
                                    target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss> effort to get the <gloss
                                    target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> to accept a stateside task force to
                                advise on a program of rural education (the
                                    <persName>Winfield</persName> fetter),<note n="3"
                                    xml:id="d197fn3">Not further identified.</note> or your
                                suggestion for a VOA advisor. My thought is that this kind of a
                                go-round should ultimately produce agreement on which agency should
                                try to promote what specific objectives vis-à-vis improvement of the
                                    <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> propaganda effort.</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
