<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-07-20T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-07-20T06:00:00-05:00" n="245" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d245">
                        <head>245. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d245fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 751K.5/7-2062. Confidential; Priority. Repeated to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_Polad1">Polad</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Saigon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-07-20T19:00:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">July 20,
                                        1962—7 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>84. For Viet Nam Working Group. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss>
                                61.<note n="2" xml:id="d245fn2"><ref target="#d242">Document
                                    242</ref>.</note> Although Task Force Saigon fully appreciates
                            importance establishment geographical priorities for Strategic Hamlet
                            Program, we favor somewhat different approach from that suggested <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>. As Dept aware, Task Force some
                            time ago agreed on geographically phased counterinsurgency program
                            including priorities (Emb despatch 429).<note n="3" xml:id="d245fn3">See
                                    <ref target="#d11fn1">footnote 1, Document 11</ref>.</note> This
                            program has served as basis US advice to <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> on Strategic Hamlet Program and in deciding allocation
                            of US resources to specific clear and hold operations. Believe we now
                            have more effective means of applying these priorities de facto to
                            ongoing Strategic Hamlet Program. With establishment US owned piaster
                            fund and <gloss target="#t_PAPR1">PA/PR</gloss> for dollar procurement,
                            we should have carrot with which to induce <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> to come up with coordinated clear and hold operations
                            in those areas which we regard as having highest priority. If this
                            approach works, effect will be to apply bulk of resources and effort in
                            highest priority areas. Through experience we should also be able to
                            develop more accurate programming justifications.</p>
                        <p>This approach will not result in slowing down or stopping Strategic
                            Hamlet Program in non-priority areas. <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> is firmly and publicly committed to pushing program on
                            nation-wide basis. While this is bound to result in some failures, we do
                            not think that there is any substantial risk that these will be “fatal
                            to <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>”. Our impression is that even
                            where program appears to be spread quite “thin”, it is <pb facs="0560" n="540" xml:id="pg_540"/> causing <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                            trouble. Moreover, <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>, specifically
                                <persName corresp="#p_NDN1">Nhu</persName> and MinInterior, are
                            aware of risks and are now insisting that hamlets be established in most
                            secure areas first.</p>
                        <p>In sum, Task Force Saigon believes should welcome undeniable momentum
                            behind Strategic Hamlet Program, seek to impose priorities on it by
                            device of concentrating resources under US control on areas considered
                            most important, and accept as divided any benefits which flow from
                            operations of program in other areas.</p>
                        <p>We are in regular touch with <persName corresp="#p_TRGK1">Thompson</persName> and believe above is in accord with his own
                            thinking. Will discuss further with him prior Honolulu meeting if
                            possible.</p>
                        <p>Re earth moving equipment, there are indications President <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> is prepared to cut back on
                            Presidential Road Program and this may release some equipment for hamlet
                            construction. We are also studying other possibilities.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> In discussion with Pres <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> July 19, he raised question
                            priorities in Strategic Hamlet Program, saying he understood our desire
                            to gear our aid programs to the Strategic Hamlet Program, and need for
                            priorities. He said that general priorities are: (a) in white areas
                            extending into blue and eventually red; (b) in the richest and most
                            heavily populated parts of the Delta, roughly the ten provinces of the
                            Delta Plan; (c) in areas, especially coastal plains of central
                            provinces, where Viet Cong pressure greatest and danger of cutting the
                            country greatest. He said that the establishment of fixed priorities in
                            building strategic hamlets is not simple. In some areas, the districts,
                            villages and hamlets themselves are sufficiently rich and enthusiastic
                            to carry out program largely under their own steam. In poorer areas, or
                            in areas where the people are less ready to take sides, govt resources
                            would be concentrated. Thus there would continue to develop Strategic
                            Hamlets beyond the first priority areas indicated above, but govt help
                            would be applied on a priority basis as indicated in (a), (b), and (c)
                            above. In short the substance of this conversation, I believe,
                            reinforces the rationale of this telegram.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_NFEJ1"><hi rend="strong">Nolting</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>