<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-10-29T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-10-29T04:00:00-05:00" n="310" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d310">
                        <head>310. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d310fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 951K.50/10-2962. Confidential; Priority. Repeated to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_Polad1">Polad</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Saigon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-10-29T17:00:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">October 29,
                                        1962—5 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>466. <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 464.<note n="2" xml:id="d310fn2">Telegram 464, October 28, reported that <persName corresp="#p_NFEJ1">Nolting</persName> had talked repeatedly to
                                no avail with <persName corresp="#p_NDT2">Thuan</persName> about the
                                expulsion of <persName corresp="#p_RJ14">James
                                    Robinson</persName>,<gloss target="#t_NBC1">NBC</gloss>
                                Southeast Asia correspondent. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.,
                                951K.50/10-2862) Despite <persName corresp="#p_NFEJ1">Nolting</persName>ʼs appeal directly to <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RJ14">Robinson</persName> was expelled on November 5. For another
                                account of the expulsion, see <persName corresp="#p_MJ10">Mecklin</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Mission in Torment</hi>,
                                pp. 136-138.</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_TWC2">Trueheart</persName> and I spent hour and a
                            half with President <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> this
                            morning seeking persuade him change his position on expulsion of
                                <persName corresp="#p_RJ14">Robinson</persName> (<gloss target="#t_NBC1">NBC</gloss>). Regret to report that <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> proved quite impervious to my
                            arguments. He did agree, at my request, to allow <persName corresp="#p_RJ14">Robinson</persName> to remain in Vietnam three
                            more days but he gave us no reason to believe that he would use this
                            period to reconsider the matter, still less to change his position.</p>
                        <p>In approach to <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName>, I made it
                            clear that I considered decision to expel <persName corresp="#p_RJ14">Robinson</persName> was matter of utmost gravity which could only
                            have highly adverse effects on our joint effort here—particularly coming
                            after expulsion <persName corresp="#p_SF3">Sully</persName> and
                            continued banning of <hi rend="italic">Newsweek</hi>. Reminding him that
                            what I was telling him was in large part repetition of what President
                            and Secretary had told <persName corresp="#p_NDT2">Thuan</persName> in
                                Washington,<note n="3" xml:id="d310fn3">For memoranda of <persName corresp="#p_NDT2">Thuan</persName>ʼs conversations with
                                President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> and
                                Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>, see <ref target="#d285">Documents 285</ref> and <ref target="#d292">292</ref>.</note> I stressed that it was essential that
                            American public, Congress and government not gain impression that <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> was seeking to conceal what was going
                            on in Vietnam. I pointed out that press reporting on Vietnam had
                            improved markedly in recent weeks and that this favorable development
                            would be undermined by expulsion <persName corresp="#p_RJ14">Robinson</persName>. I urged him to accept fact that press problem
                            would cure itself, and could only be curbed, by manifest success in
                            defeating Viet Cong. Finally, I told him calmly that his rationale for
                            action against <persName corresp="#p_RJ14">Robinson</persName> would not
                            be understood or accepted by US Government or people.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_TWC2">Trueheart</persName> and I repeated these and
                            other arguments many times in course of meeting without apparent effect.
                                <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> acknowledged that visa
                            question was technicality and that action was directed against <persName corresp="#p_RJ14">Robinson</persName> personally. He had with him a
                            dossier of <persName corresp="#p_RJ14">Robinson</persName>ʼs past
                            broadcasts and showed me one of about six months ago which was highly
                            critical of President and his family. He characterized <persName corresp="#p_RJ14">Robinson</persName>ʼs attitude as “intolerable”,
                            lacking in elementary respect for chief of state, referring specifically
                            to <persName corresp="#p_RJ14">Robinson</persName>ʼs alleged remark to
                                <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> press <pb facs="0742" n="722" xml:id="pg_722"/> officer, after long interview with <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> some months ago, that president
                            had “taken a great deal of time saying nothing”. He referred to
                            sacrifices which he and his family have made for Vietnam over many years
                            and said that for these past actions he and his family were widely
                            respected in Vietnam. It was his duty not to permit this respect to be
                            undermined by insulting press reporting. He said several times that it
                            was also his duty to other chiefs of state not to tolerate attitude of
                            reporters like <persName corresp="#p_RJ14">Robinson</persName>. (It was
                            made clear that American political leaders do not expect immunity from
                            personal press attacks for themselves or their families.)</p>
                        <p>This is essence of lengthy discussion in which I believe all available
                            arguments were brought to bear with great earnestness and in which basic
                            difference in points of view was clearly isolated. Fundamentally, this
                            difference is that <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> is
                            unwilling or unable to subordinate to other considerations, however
                            important, his canons of correct behavior, and what he regards as his
                            primordial obligations to his family. Accordingly, I frankly have little
                            or no hope that <persName corresp="#p_RJ14">Robinson</persName>ʼs
                            expulsion can be averted.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_RJ14">Robinson</persName> has been advised of
                            three-day reprieve and gist of above.<note n="4" xml:id="d310fn4">At 7
                                p.m. on October 29, the Embassy in Saigon transmitted <persName corresp="#p_RJ14">Robinson</persName>ʼs message to <gloss target="#t_NBC1">NBC</gloss> in Washington summarizing the
                                events of October 28-29 and stating that American correspondents
                                were alarmed that <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> might
                                get away with the expulsion without a vigorous protest from
                                Washington. (Telegram 467; Department of State, Central Files,
                                951K.6211/10-2962)</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_NFEJ1"><hi rend="strong">Nolting</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>