<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-02-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="69" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d69">
                        <head>69. Letter From <persName type="from">Wesley R. Fishel</persName> of
                            the Michigan State University Group in Vietnam to President <persName type="to">John A. Hannah</persName> of Michigan State
                                University<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d69fn1">Source:
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> Library, National
                                Security Files, Vietnam Country Series. Personal and Confidential. A
                                date stamp on the source text indicates that President Hannah
                                received it on February 23. Hanna forwarded it under a covering
                                letter to President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName>
                                on February 26, noting that the contract with the MSU Group had been
                                terminated by President <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName>
                                and expressing misgivings about ever having gotten involved in
                                Vietnam in the first place. Also attached to the source text was a
                                copy of a letter from <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">McGeorge
                                    Bundy</persName> to President Hannah of March 26 resuming the
                                original, thanking him on President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName>ʼs behalf, and informing him that copies of
                                the <persName>Fishel</persName> letter had been distributed to
                                members of the Presidentʼs staff concerned with
                            Vietnam.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Rangoon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-02-17"><hi rend="italic">February 17,
                                    1962</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear President Hannah</hi>: I have recently left
                            Saigon after spending four weeks there, and given the developments there
                            during that time it occurred to me that you might be interested in my
                            personal report on the situation which prevails there.</p>
                        <p>Since I left Saigon I have had no word from the MSU people there, and can
                            only assume that the President has not reversed his decision to
                            terminate the Universityʼs contract program in Vietnam. (If he has, of
                            course, you will read the following remarks with a different perspective
                            than otherwise.) As you can easily imagine, the interview at which the
                            President informed me that he had decided against renewing the MSU
                            contract was a difficult one.<note n="2" xml:id="d69fn2">The interview
                                between <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> and
                                    <persName>Fishel</persName> took place on January 24. An account
                                of it is in a memorandum of January 25 from Guy Fox of the MSU Group
                                to <persName>James Hendry</persName>, Assistant Dean of the College
                                of Business and Public Service. (Michigan State University, Hannah
                                Papers, H, Vietnam, 1962)</note> He was obviously ill at ease and
                            made it plain that he hoped the program termination would not affect our
                            personal relationship. At the same time it was clear that he held me at
                            least partially responsible for the fact that MSU people had published
                            what he called “untrue, unfair, and tendentious” criticisms of his
                            government. He tried to depersonalize his decision by telling me that
                            the members of his Cabinet had recommended against our continuation. But
                            since I had already learned that he had consulted only two advisers: his
                            brother, <persName corresp="#p_NDN1">Ngo Dinh Nhu</persName>, and the
                            Secretary of State at the Presidency, <persName corresp="#p_NDT2">Nguyen
                                Dinh Thuan</persName>, I called him on this, whereupon he repeated
                            earlier accusations that MSU personnel had been “disloyal.” Both the
                            President and his brother individually voiced implicit accusations in
                            talking with me, to the effect that our professors had used their
                            “privileged position”, which gave them access to government offices,
                            personnel, and files, to engage in intelligence <pb facs="0169" n="149" xml:id="pg_149"/> activities in the guise of “research”; and had
                            then used the information they had secured to the detriment of the
                            Vietnamese Government.</p>
                        <p>I tried to reason with <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> on
                            this, though I recognized from his manner that argument was probably
                            futile. The voice was that of the President, but the reasoning was that
                            of his brother, <persName corresp="#p_NDN1">Nhu</persName>. I am sorry
                            to say that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NDN1">Nhu</persName> apparently
                            actually believes his own arguments and persuaded <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> of them. It is also a fact,
                            however, that other members of the government, headed by the Vice
                            President, while sharply critical of the publications in question, were
                            fully convinced of the value of MSUʼs work and wanted very much for our
                            group to continue its programs.</p>
                        <p>As much as I regret the termination at this time, when all of us should
                            be making a maximum effort to keep the Vietnamese Government afloat, I
                            am relieved that the issue was resolved enough in advance of the
                            termination date to permit an orderly phasing out. And given also the
                            situation which I shall outline in the following paragraphs, it is
                            probably just as well that our work is being brought to a close, at
                            least for the present time.</p>
                        <p>For the first time in seven and one-half years I have become a pessimist
                            about the fate of South Vietnam. In the two and one-half years since my
                            last visit to that country there has been a most profound and
                            distressing deterioration there, politically, socially, and
                            psychologically. Economically, though some progress is still being made,
                            the gains of the past few years are in many cases being reversed, by a
                            combination of factors of which the major ones have been very serious
                            floods along the Mekong last fall, and sharply intensified Viet Cong
                            activity. As you may know, Vietnam is not exporting rice this year; it
                            will in fact import some. Again, there has been just enough interference
                            in normal business and investment activity on the part of the
                            government-supporting political party of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NDN1">Nhu</persName> to have a monkey-wrench kind of effect on economic
                            operations. Militarily, the recent influx of thousands of American
                            officers and men, and dozens of helicopters, etc., is starting to make a
                            distinct change in the situation already, turning what was a minus into
                            a plus. I would hesitate to predict, however, that the plus will remain
                            that for long, for I find it hard to believe that the Chinese and Viet
                            Cong will allow this challenge to go unmet. Indeed, my travels to the
                            high plateau, the center, and the Mekong delta last month have left me
                            with the impression that a Viet Cong offensive is very likely in the
                            next few weeks. By that I donʼt mean a major invasion out of the north,
                            but rather a heavily intensified terrorization program that may spread
                            even to the cities, with the intent of panicking the population and
                            weakening the <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> governmentʼs
                            hold still more.</p>
                        <pb facs="0170" n="150" xml:id="pg_150"/>
                        <p>Politically and psychologically things are at a low ebb. The commendable
                            programs which were begun a few years ago have been allowed in many
                            instances to lose their momentum by reason largely of a failure on the
                            part of the Central Government to follow through on initial decisions
                            and acts. The hopes and aspirations of 1954 and 1955 have been allowed
                            to die, and a miasma of apathy pervades the atmosphere. I talked more
                            than casually with 118 people during my four weeks in Vietnam. Almost
                            all are people I have known for many years. None of them is politically
                            part of the “opposition.” At least two thirds of them were still
                                <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName>ʼs strong adherents in
                            1959. Yet today, only three or four of these men and women support the
                            government with discernible enthusiasm. Then too, there is much popular
                            fear: fear that “the Viet Cong are coming,” and that the government is
                            not going to be able to move to meet the Communist threat swiftly enough
                            to save many people from being hurt or killed. Of course, this is the
                            kind of fear which is surreptitiously encouraged by Communist agents, of
                            whom there are many in Saigon.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> himself is linked more and
                            more often with those around him—the “evil influences,” as some call
                            them. After all, he is the Chief of State and must take responsibility
                            for the acts of his entourage, whether he knows of them or not: if he
                            knows of them, he is at fault because they are “evil”; if he doesn’t
                            know of them, he should by now. No one yet accuses him of wrongdoing,
                            and in fact he could recoup his former stature and support easily with
                            just a minimum of effort. But he does not see the necessity or
                            desirability of such steps, and no one who does has the courage to tell
                            him. This applies even to those few still with him who are basically
                            courageous, men of integrity and ability who despise the craven
                            flatterers who surround him and insulate him from the realities of his
                            situation. They are reluctant to tell him unpleasant truths because he
                            may dismiss them, and they know that in that case “the evil ones” would
                            put their own men into the vacancies and then even this tiny opening to
                            the outside would be closed off.</p>
                        <p>Who are these “evil influences?” As always, <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName>ʼs brother, <persName corresp="#p_NDN1">Nhu</persName>, heads the list, but shares his position with his
                            wife. <persName corresp="#p_NDN1">Nhu</persName>ʼs policies have formed
                            the philosophical basis of the regimeʼs activity for the past six years,
                            and they have failed miserably to win the people to the side of the
                            government. But he doesn’t realize this, and one cannot convince him (or
                                <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName>) of this. His wife is as
                            brilliant, vivacious, bitchy, and brutal in her Borgia-like fashion as
                            ever—and with (charitably) the purest of intentions she is succeeding in
                            alienating substantial segments of the population from her
                            brother-in-lawʼs regime at a time when it needs the enthusiastic support
                            of everyone. She is the sponsor, for example, of an asinine bill that
                            passed the National Assembly by a questionably secured majority: the
                            “Social Purification Law.” <pb facs="0171" n="151" xml:id="pg_151"/>
                            This silly legislation, rammed through the Assembly in the name of
                            “austerity” and “mobilizing the population”, prohibits dancing or the
                            teaching of dancing, even in private homes, bans dissemination of birth
                            control information, devices, or medications, and would regulate all
                            sorts of other activities and practices including public displays of
                            affection, certain kinds of dress, etc.<note n="3" xml:id="d69fn3">In
                                the margin next to this sentence is written in an unidentifiable
                                hand: “<persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName> has returned this
                                bill to the assembly for reworking.”</note> Coming from a Catholic
                            it is interpreted to mean that Catholic dogma is being forced on the
                            people, which means that it is creating inter-religious frictions where
                            few have existed previously. Then there is the Secretary of State at the
                            Presidency, <persName corresp="#p_NDT2">Nguyen Dinh Thuan</persName>, a
                            shifty, ambitious, clever, and unscrupulous-but able-administrator, who
                            has his eye on even higher position, and some American friends who think
                            he would be easier to handle than <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Diem</persName>. Much as I do not wish to see the influence of the
                            Nhus continue, the elevation of <persName corresp="#p_NDT2">Thuan</persName> is not to me the answer either. For this man is as
                            well hated as the Nhus (who put him into his job, incidentally) and a
                            likely candidate for assassination, either by the Communists or by many
                            others who detest him as a man who has tasted power and likes it too
                            well, and who climbed to his present position on the backs of those who
                            were his friends and benefactors.</p>
                        <p>The US role in all this is, as ever, of mixed quality. The determined
                            military effort we are now making is likely to help a good deal; our
                            economic measures will also help. But these steps are helping only to
                            warm the fingers and the toes; the body itself needs badly to be warmed
                            too if it is to be kept alive. Unless Vietnam experiences a major and
                            favorable psychological shock within the next few months, I doubt
                            seriously whether it will survive, notwithstanding our efforts and our
                            money and our men. The bright spots which were so clearly visible two
                            and even one year ago are now fading into insignificance because the
                            regime still has failed to mobilize the hearts and loyalties of the
                            people. This is ironical, for this is a regime which has based its
                            system of appointment to office on “loyalty.” And ironical too is the
                            fact that this regime, which has a philosophical base (synthetic and
                            unloved) of “personalism,” which teaches that every man has the right to
                            the fullest development of his personality, has failed miserably to
                            enable men to do just that. (I am not speaking of civil liberties
                            here—they are still a side issue, by and large—I speak of the freedom of
                            men to rise in their chosen professions to positions of responsibility,
                            to improve their status by their own efforts, by demonstrating their
                            capacities and their talents.) I think here of all the young men I have
                            known and worked with in Vietnam (including Nguyen Thai, who is once
                            more back at MSU, and Vu Van Thai, who reportedly is now at Harvard),
                            who have the qualities of leadership which Vietnam will <pb facs="0172" n="152" xml:id="pg_152"/> need in the years ahead, but who have been
                            alienated and their development stifled and smothered by the heavy hand
                            of their government. (But I must clarify one point here: the Vietnamese
                            Government is not malicious or predatory or vicious or particularly
                            oppressive, especially if it is compared with the regimes of neighboring
                            countries. Rather it is a clumsy and bumbling government which has
                            failed to take advantage of one opportunity after another, and which has
                            not dared to take the risks involved in implementing its avowed ideas,
                            and which has not carried successful programs to their successful
                            conclusion.)</p>
                        <p>Perhaps my rhetoric has left you with the impression that I have written
                            my friend off. I have not. However, I am firmly of the opinion that
                            unless what I have termed the “evil influences” are removed from the
                            scene in one way or another, <persName corresp="#p_NDD2">Ngo Dinh
                                Diem</persName>ʼs government is not going to make the grade. Support
                            for the government is dwindling, and one finds evidences of a growing
                            feeling of desperation among the able and hitherto loyal men and women
                            who have supported it. Unless the situation can be changed for the
                            better, we are in for a very bad period in Vietnam.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Wesley
                                Fishel</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>