<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1861-05-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1861-05-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="123" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Dayton</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Seward</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">[Extracts.]</note>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 5.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1861-05-22"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 22, 1861</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the pleasure to announce to you my
                            arrival in this city on Saturday, May 11. On Monday, application was
                            made through our legation for an audience with Mr. Thouvenel, minister
                            of foreign affairs, which was granted for the 16th instant, on which day
                            I was duly presented to him by Mr. Walsh, of the American legation.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Thouvenel, in the course of the conversation, took occasion to say
                            that he deeply regretted the condition of things in the United States,
                            and that in this expression of feeling he represented the views and
                            feelings of the Emperor; that so deeply concerned was the Emperor that
                            he had felt disposed to offer his good offices, but had been deterred
                            from the fear that his offer might not be well received; but should
                            occasion for this arise, he would always be ready and happy to be of
                            use. He made special inquiry as to the policy of our government in
                            regard to neutral rights, particularly in reference to neutral property
                            found in southern ships. He went into considerable detail to show that
                            historical precedents were in favor of treating southern vessels as
                            those of a regular belligerent, and applying the same doctrine to them
                            as had always been upheld by the United States. He dwelt particularly
                            upon the fact that Great Britain, during our revolutionary war, had not
                            considered our privateers as pirates. I understood him to say that, as
                            respects an effective blockade, it would be fully recognized and
                            respected; but he seemed much impressed with the importance of
                            understanding clearly the intentions of our government in reference to
                            these matters as respects the foreign world.</p>
                        <p>As respects a tender of the kind offices of the Emperor I could only
                            thank him for the interest in our country which the suggestion
                            manifested, but gave him no reason to suppose such offer at this time
                            would be accepted. As to the doctrines which our government would apply
                            in reference to the blockade of southern ports and neutral rights, I
                            told him I had no specific instructions at present, and could only refer
                            him to the proclamation of the President and the general principles of
                            international law which might bear on the case. I further informed him
                            that immediately after my reception by the Emperor I would apprise my
                            government of the anxiety of the French government to learn the views of
                            our government more definitively upon these questions. You will not fail
                            to have observed that the action of France and England upon this
                            question of belligerent rights has been upon a mutual understanding and
                            agreement.</p>
                        <pb facs="0209" n="209" xml:id="pg_209"/>
                        <p>Throughout the conversation he seemed anxious to impress upon me the
                            great interest which France took in our condition, and their desire for
                            the perpetuation of the Union of the States. He referred to the fact
                            that France had aided in its formation, and did not desire to witness
                            its dissolution. The recognition of the southern confederates as
                            possessing belligerent rights he did not consider at all as recognizing
                            them as independent States.</p>
                        <p>After the conversation had closed, to save time I at once presented a
                            copy of my letters of credence, and requested an audience of the
                            Emperor, &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>On the next day I was informed by a note from the minister that I would
                            be received at the palace on the 19th instant, at which time I was
                            presented in due form to the Emperor, in the presence of certain
                            officers of the court.</p>
                        <p>A copy of my remarks to the Emperor will be found enclosed, (letter A.)
                            In reply, the Emperor, after a courteous welcome, and one or two remarks
                            of a character personally complimentary, said, in substance, that he
                            felt great interest in the condition of things in our country; that he
                            was very anxious our difficulties should be settled amicably; that he
                            had been and yet was ready to offer his kind offices, if such offer
                            would be mutually agreeable to the contending parties; that whatever
                            tended to affect injuriously our interests was detrimental to the
                            interests of France, and that he desired a perpetuation of the Union of
                            the States, with some additional remarks of like tenor and character.
                            His observations were in the same vein as those of the minister of
                            foreign affairs, and I doubt not were the frank expressions of his views
                            on this subject.</p>
                        <p>Immediately after the formal part of my presentation had closed, and my
                            letters of credence been delivered, he entered for a short time into
                            general conversation. Upon taking my leave of the Emperor I was
                            conducted by the grand chamberlain to the apartments of the Empress, and
                            there presented to her. She repeated to some extent the same views
                            already presented by the Emperor. My reception at the palace was in
                            every respect agreeable. On Monday, the 20th instant, I called again on
                            Mr. Thouvenel, in company with Mr. Sanford, (our minister to Belgium,)
                            for the purpose of obtaining, if possible, a little more distinct
                            information as to what France meant by the terms “neutral rights” and
                            “belligerent” rights; how far he considered such rights as extending to
                            the capture and condemnation of prizes in the ports of France, &amp;c.
                            He said in reply, in substance, that they held that the flag covers the
                            cargo; and that if a southern ship carrying neutral property was
                            captured, the property would not be condemned, &amp;c. He hoped our
                            government would recognize principles for which it had always contended.
                            I told him it would certainly do so, but the question here was, whether
                            there <hi rend="italic">was a flag;</hi> that our government insisted
                            that the confederates, being merely in rebellion, had no flag, and I
                            could not exactly understand how a foreign government which had not
                            recognized them as an independent power could recognize them as having a
                            flag. He said, furthermore, that the French government had given no
                            warning to their citizens, &amp;c., (as the English government had,) by
                            proclamation, because it was unnecessary; that the statute law of France
                            (of 1825, April 10, I think) declared that any French citizen taking
                            service under a foreign power lost all claim to protection as a citizen;
                            that if a subject of France should take service on board of a letter of
                            marque licensed by the Confederate States, it would be, as I understood
                            him, piratical on the part of such subject. He said, furthermore, that
                            no letters of marque could be fitted out in their ports, or <hi rend="italic">even sheltered</hi> there, unless they came in from
                            necessity, (as stress of weather, &amp;c.,) and then could remain, I
                            think, but twenty-four hours; that Consequently there could be no
                            bringing of prizes into French ports, and while there a condemnation of
                            them in the courts of the southern States. His conversation on this part
                            of the case was very satisfactory, and he <pb facs="0210" n="210" xml:id="pg_210"/> promised me a reference in writing to the French
                            statutes bearing on the question. He added that the French government
                            had addressed certain interrogatories to our government, and would await
                            their answer. The disposition of this government to keep on friendly
                            relations with us is, I think, manifest, and it will not, I judge, be
                            diminished by the obvious fact that certain portions of the public men
                            and the press of England are felicitating themselves on the condition of
                            things in America. The policy of having a heavy commercial power in the
                            west, as some counterpoise to the marine power of England, is too
                            manifest to escape a mind so sagacious as that of the present Emperor of
                            the French. I had taken the liberty before the reception of your last
                            despatch, dated 4th instant, of assuring all persons, official and
                            otherwise, with whom I came in contact, that the most effective measures
                            were being taken by our government to crush out this causeless and
                            wicked rebellion, and that I believed such efforts would be continued to
                            the end; that the fears (which existed in some quarters) that the
                            government would again temporize, and lose the advantage which the
                            present determined enthusiasm of the people gave to it, were groundless.
                            I find very strong feelings existing here in behalf of the Union among
                            the American citizens from the northern States, and a determination to
                            support the government with men and money.</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>I have had many applications, since here by foreigners for service as
                            officers in the army of the United States, and I understand from one of
                            the former secretaries of the legation that many applications were made
                            at the office of the legation before I came. There was one case only, as
                            the secretary says, of an application at the office of the legation for
                            service in the army of the south, and this was from an anonymous
                            correspondent, the note seeking service being unsigned. To these
                            applications I have said that our service was open to volunteers, but I
                            had no authority to commit the government to appointments; that, in
                            fact, we needed arms rather than men. * * *</p>
                        <p>No formal notice of the blockade of southern ports has been given to the
                            government here, unless through the agency of the French minister at
                            Washington. Indeed, I think I understood Mr. Thouvenel to say that they
                            had received no such formal notice at all. I shall call the attention of
                            Mr. Thouvenel to the original proclamation when I communicate to him (as
                            I shall at once do) the additional proclamation (just received) of the
                            blockade of the ports of Virginia and North Carolina.</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>I have opened, since here, (directed to my predecessor,) a copy of the
                            President’s proclamation as to the blockade of the ports of Virginia and
                            North Carolina, dated 27th April, 1861. I received likewise despatch No.
                            4 last night, containing views of the government at Washington as to the
                            abolition of privateering, and enclosing to me a commission to effect
                            with the French government a treaty for that purpose, with the form of
                            such treaty. This is of great importance, and will affect in a material
                            degree the means of defence on the part of our country in time of war. I
                            shall proceed in conformity, however, with these instructions to
                            communicate with the minister of foreign affairs on the subject. But I
                            cannot help feeling, in view of what the French law is, as heretofore
                            stated, and the little danger to our commerce which can soon arise from
                            any action of this government or of its subjects from privateers, that I
                            had better attempt again to obtain a provision exempting from seizure
                                <hi rend="italic">private</hi> property afloat (unless contraband)
                            the same as private property is now exempt on land. I should very much
                            regret an opportunity lost to obtain such a treaty provision, if
                            possible, before we give up that species of volunteer marine by which we
                            are enabled in some degree to affect the commerce of other nations,
                            having <pb facs="0211" n="211" xml:id="pg_211"/> a heavier naval marine,
                            while they are destroying our own. The Emperor is about to leave Paris
                            for the country, and it is doubtful if great expedition can be had in
                            this matter; but, acting under the direct instructions of the government
                            at home, I shall incur no unnecessary delay in carrying those
                            instructions (if I can procure no better terms) into effect.</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>I have received your despatch (No. 7) containing instructions as to
                            matters to be communicated to Mr. Thouvenel in reference to the unity of
                            the cabinet at Washington and the intentions of the government to
                            prosecute the war with the utmost effect.</p>
                        <p>I will, at the earliest moment, so state to Mr. Thouvenel, though it will
                            be to some extent a restatement of what has already been said. There
                            has, I fear, been some misapprehension upon the minds of the authorities
                            here upon this subject.</p>
                        <p>Since my arrival here my engagements, personal and official, have been
                            constant; so much so that it has not been in my power to communicate as
                            promptly with your department as I would have desired.</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>Your very obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer><signed>WM. L. DAYTON.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Secretary of State</hi>.</p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>A.</head>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Your Majesty</hi>: I have the honor to present
                                to your Imperial Majesty these, my letters of credence from the
                                President of the United States of America, accrediting me as envoy
                                extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary near to your Majesty.</p>
                            <p>By these letters it is made my especial duty, as it will certainly be
                                my pleasure, with the assent of your Majesty, to cultivate and
                                strengthen the friendship and good correspondence which has
                                heretofore existed between France and the United States, and as far
                                as possible to preserve and advance the interest and happiness of
                                both nations. The people of the United States have not forgotten,
                                nor can they ever forget, that France was their first ally, and
                                throughout the whole period of their national existence has been
                                (with a passing cloud only) their constant friend. An unbroken
                                intercourse of good offices and kind feelings between two great
                                nations for so long a period affords just cause of pride and
                                congratulation to both. Each year has continued to enlarge those
                                business interests which bind us together, and I am happy to know
                                that at no period in our past history have those interests been more
                                prosperous than under the wise, liberal, and enlightened policy of
                                your Imperial Majesty. All our recollections of the past, all our
                                interests of the present, and all our hopes for the future, prompt
                                the United States to cultivate with sedulous care those friendly
                                relations with the government of France which have existed so long
                                and been productive to each nation of results so auspicious.</p>
                            <p>I have it specially in charge from the president of the United States
                                to give assurance to your Imperial Majesty of his disposition to
                                cultivate such friendly relations; to assure your Majesty personally
                                of his high respect and appreciation; to tender to you, to the
                                Empress, your imperial consort, and to each of the members of the
                                imperial family, his best wishes for their <pb facs="0212" n="212" xml:id="pg_212"/> health, prosperity, and happiness. Permit me
                                only to add that the mission near to your Imperial Majesty, with
                                which I have been honored, is one most grateful to my feelings, and
                                without neglecting the interests of my own government, I shall
                                endeavor so to discharge its duties as to make my residence here
                                entirely agreeable to your Majesty.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>