<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Pike to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1861</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d258</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">258</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1861-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1861-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1861-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1861-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="258"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d258">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Pike</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Seward</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 20.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Hague</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1861-10-09">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 9, 1861</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Since my last (under date of October 2) I have
                    received a letter from the United States consul at Paramaribo, of which the
                    following is a copy:</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">“<hi rend="smallcaps">United States
                                Consulate</hi>,<lb/>“<placeName>
                                <hi rend="italic">Port of Paramaribo</hi>,</placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1861-09-04">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 4, 1861</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor (but with chagrin) to inform
                        you that the rebel steamer Sumter arrived at this port on the 19th of
                        August, and left on the 31st, having been allowed to coal and refit. I used
                        my best endeavors to prevent it without avail.</p>
                    <p>“I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>“HENRY SAWYER.”</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Immediately on the receipt of it I addressed the following note to the
                            minister of foreign affairs.</p>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume"
                                >[Untitled]</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">“<placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The Hague</hi>,</placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1861-10-08">
                                        <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 8, 1861</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have just received a communication
                                from the American consul at Paramaribo under date of the 4th of
                                September last, which I lose no time in laying before your
                                excellency.</p>
                            <p>“The consul states.”</p>
                            <p rend="center">[See above.]</p>
                            <p>“The reappearance of the Sumter in a port of the Netherlands, after
                                so brief an interval, seems to disclose a deliberate purpose on the
                                part of the persons engaged in rebellion against the United States
                                government to practice upon the presumed indifference, the expected
                                favor, or the fancied weakness of the Dutch government.</p>
                            <p>“During a period of forty-six days, during which we have heard of
                                this piratical vessel in the West Indies, it would appear that she
                                had been twice entertained and supplied at Dutch ports, and spent
                                eighteen days under their shelter.</p>
                            <p>“This can be no accidental circumstance.</p>
                            <p>“In the multitude of harbors with which the West India seas abound,
                                the Sumter has had no occasion to confine her visits so entirely to
                                the ports of one nation, especially one so scantily supplied with
                                them as Holland. And the fact that she does so is, in my judgment,
                                not fairly susceptible of any other interpretation than the one I
                                have given.</p>
                            <p>“I feel convinced that the government of the Netherlands will see in
                                this repeated visit of the Sumter (this time, it appears, without
                                any pretext) a distinct violation of its neutrality according to its
                                own views, as laid down <pb facs="0376" n="376" xml:id="pg_376"/> in
                                your excellency’s communication to me of the 17th of September last,
                                and a case which will call for the energetic assertion of its
                                purpose expressed in the paper referred to, namely, not to allow its
                                ports to be made the base of hostile operations against the United
                                States. For that the Sumter is clearly making such use of the Dutch
                                ports would seem to admit of no controversy.</p>
                            <p>“In view of the existing state of the correspondence between the
                                United States and the Netherlands on the general subject to which
                                this case belongs, and of the questions and relations involved
                                therein, I shall be excused for the brevity of this communication
                                upon a topic of so much importance and so provocative of
                                comment.</p>
                            <p>“The undersigned avails himself,” &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
                            <p>I called to-day upon Baron Von Zuylen, but he was absent, and I shall
                                not therefore be able to see him again before the close of the mail
                                which takes this. And I do not know that an interview would in any
                                way affect the existing state of things or give me any new
                                information. This government’s intentions are good; and it desires
                                to avoid all difficulty with the United States, and with everybody
                                else.</p>
                            <p>As I stated in my despatch of the 25th September, I have confidence
                                that orders have been given that will impede the operations of these
                                vessels in Dutch ports hereafter, and probably drive them
                                elsewhere.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to be, with great respect, your most obedient
                                servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>JAMES S. PIKE.</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington</hi>.</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
