<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1861-06-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1861-06-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="56" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d56">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Adams</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Seward</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">[Extracts.]</note>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 9.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United
                                    States</hi>,<lb/><placeName><hi rend="italic">London</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1861-06-21"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 21, 1861</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: * * * * * * * * *</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>I have not deemed it necessary to ask a special interview to communicate
                            to Lord John Russell the sense entertained by the President of the
                            manner of my reception here, as directed in yours of the 3d of June.
                            Presuming it to be altogether likely that another despatch, prepared
                            after the reception of my No. 2, is now near at hand, I have preferred
                            to wait and see if that may not give me other matter to submit at the
                            same time.</p>
                        <p>The intelligence received from the United States of the effect produced
                            by the reception of the Queen’s proclamation has not been without its
                            influence upon opinion here. Whilst people of all classes unite in
                            declaring that such a measure was unavoidable, they are equally earnest
                            in disavowing any inferences of want of good will which may have been
                            drawn from it. They affect to consider our complaints as very
                            unreasonable, and are profuse in their professions of sympathy with the
                            government in its present struggle. This is, certainly, a very great
                            change from the tone prevailing when I first arrived. It is partly to be
                            ascribed to the accounts of the progress of the war, but still more to
                            the publications in the London <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> of the
                            letters of its special correspondent. There is no longer any floating
                            doubt of the capacity of the government to sustain itself, or any belief
                            that the insurgents will make their own terms of accommodation. The idea
                            still remains quite general that there will never be any actual
                            conflict, and it is connected in many cases with an apprehension that
                            the reunion may be cemented upon the basis of hostile measures against
                            Great Britain. Indeed, such has been the motive hinted at by more than
                            one person of influence as guiding the policy of the President himself.
                            Whenever such a suggestion has been <pb facs="0110" n="110" xml:id="pg_110"/> made to me, I have been careful to discountenance
                            it altogether, and to affirm that the struggle was carried on in good
                            faith, and from motives not subject to be affected by mere
                            considerations of policy, or by temporary emotions. More especially have
                            I endeavored to disavow any “arrière pensée” which has the effect to
                            confirm the suspicion of our sincerity, I regret to say, by far too much
                            disseminated. * * * * *</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>I am now earnestly assured on all sides that the sympathy with the
                            government of the United States is general; that the indignation felt in
                            America is not founded in reason; that the British desire only to be
                            perfectly neutral, giving no aid nor comfort to the insurgents. I
                            believe that this sentiment is now growing to be universal. It inspires
                            her Majesty’s ministers, and is not without its effect on the
                            opposition. Neither party would be so bold as to declare its sympathy
                            with a cause based upon the extension of slavery, for that would at once
                            draw upon itself the indignation of the great body of the people. But
                            the development of a positive spirit in the opposite direction will
                            depend far more upon the degree in which the arm of the government
                            enforces obedience than upon any absolute affinity in sentiments. Our
                            brethren in this country, after all, are much disposed to fall in with
                            the opinion of Voltaire, that “Dieu est toujours sur le coté des gros
                            canons.” General Scott and an effective blockading squardron will be the
                            true agents to keep the peace abroad, as well as to conquer one at home.
                            In the meanwhile the self-styled commissioners of the insurgents have
                            transferred their labors to Paris, where, I am told, they give out what
                            they could not venture publicly to say here, that this government will
                            recognize them as a State. The prediction may be verified, it is true;
                            but it is not now likely to happen, under any other condition than the
                            preceding assent of the United States.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer><signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Secretary of State</hi>.</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>