<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-10-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-10-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="255" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d255">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">838.00/2159</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The High Commissioner in Haiti</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Russell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Port au
                                        Prince</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-10-10"><hi rend="italic">October 10,
                                1925</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received October 17.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 632</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose herewith, for
                            the Department’s information, a copy of the <hi rend="italic">Moniteur</hi> of August [<hi rend="italic">October</hi>] 8, 1925,
                            containing a circular letter addressed by the President to the Prefects
                            of Arrondissements, concerning the question of national elections.</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>I had suggested to President Borno that he express the hope that national
                            elections might, with the continued improvement of conditions throughout
                            the country, be held in 1928. It will be noted that his remarks are not
                            quite as strong as the above.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">John H. Russell</hi></signed></closer>
                        <pb facs="0387" n="305" xml:id="pg_305"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Circular Letter of President <persName type="from">Borno</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Prefects of the Haitian Arrondissements</gloss></hi></head>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Prefect</hi>: The policy of the Government,
                                as you know, is governed entirely by a sentiment of absolute
                                sincerity. Having decided to spare no effort in organizing our
                                democracy, firm and prosperous, in order and in liberty, the
                                Government has for its first duty to consider the country as it is,
                                to place itself resolutely before the reality of facts, and not to
                                permit itself to be led astray by any empty declamations, by any
                                lie.</p>
                            <p>What spectacle did we offer to the world when the intervention of the
                                United States occurred, and what was the work of this intervention?
                                Herewith is the official statement by President Dartiguenave in his
                                proclamation of the 29th of August, 1916: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The country was the prey to the most terrible anarchy. The
                                        cities and fields of the departments of the North,
                                        Northwest, Artibonite, and a large part of the West had been
                                        ravaged and stained with blood by an almost uninterrupted
                                        series of civil wars; anguish, desolation, and misery were
                                        everywhere. In less than four years, seven chiefs of state
                                        succeeded each other! The last, Vilbrun Guillaume, had just
                                        been violently torn from the French Legation, and sacrificed
                                        in the street by the blind and barbarous anger of a mob
                                        which had been exasperated by the unattoneable slaughter at
                                        the prison of Port-au-Prince.</p>
                                    <p>The American Intervention put an end to this scandal, and the
                                        same National Assembly which, under the pressure of a
                                        victorious force, had ratified three “coups d’Etat” by
                                        electing successively three revolutionary chiefs, this same
                                        National Assembly, acting for the first time in its full and
                                        complete freedom, called to the first magistracy, Senator
                                        Dartiguenave. It was necessary henceforth, to secure in the
                                        ruined and blood-stained Republic, order and peace,
                                        security, a stable government, every condition in a word
                                        indispensable to work, to normal living, indispensable to
                                        the well being and the prosperity of the citizens. And the
                                        proof was given, definitely given, of the complete impotence
                                        of the leading nationals, too divided among themselves, to
                                        procure for this country these basic conditions.</p>
                                    <p>The convention was then signed consecrating to the profit of
                                        the Republic of Haiti the powerful aid of the American
                                        Government.</p>
                                    <p>That was certainly a sacrifice to national self-respect. But,
                                        between this sacrifice and the life of shame, misery, and
                                        ignominy from which it had rescued us, no citizen, having a
                                        true sense of national honor, could hesitate.</p>
                                    <p>And since then what have we seen? Peace, inestimable benefit,
                                        has been reestablished. The laboring people have been able
                                        to devote themselves to their work; thanks to the order
                                        maintained everywhere, they have been able to realize from
                                        our agricultural potentialities the greatest advantages. The
                                        work of rehabilitation and sanitation, undertaken by degrees
                                        everywhere, has facilitated communications, benefited <pb facs="0388" n="306" xml:id="pg_306"/> public health, and
                                        procured at the same time means of sustenance for thousands
                                        of our citizens; for the first time in years, families have
                                        known the joys of security and exercised the prerogatives of
                                        true social liberty.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>And I add to-day:</p>
                            <p>More than twelve hundred kilometers of roads have been constructed;
                                new roads are still being opened; numerous bridges have been thrown
                                across the water courses; important irrigation works have been
                                undertaken; a technical service has been instituted to give us at
                                last an organized agricultural system, demanded for over a hundred
                                years; city and rural schools have already been built and a
                                progressive program of school work is in operation; new laws have
                                put into the hands of the authorities means of protecting the
                                peasants against the despoiling methods of a certain class of rotten
                                and heartless lawyers; the fine results of the public health
                                service, in the towns and in the country, have procured, and are
                                procuring each day, invaluable aid to citizens in every walk of
                                life; the national magistracy, so long neglected, has, at last,
                                initiated in its favor, better conditions which will develop in
                                proportion; and the financial credit of the country is so high in
                                foreign markets that it could be said “that it is virtually on the
                                same plane as such conservative states as Holland, Sweden, and
                                Switzerland.”</p>
                            <p>And, nevertheless, if the general situation offers so much
                                satisfaction, how can it be denied that the work accomplished until
                                now is but a beginning, when one considers all that still is left to
                                be done to assure the continued development of agriculture,
                                commerce, public education, health, seriously to guarantee public
                                peace, public and private property, the home, and the security of
                                all, against any possible return to our bad past, our past of bloody
                                and destructive revolutions, scandalous pillage, and by the
                                persecution of exploitations of the peasants by military satrapes,
                                masters of life and property.</p>
                            <p>And before this immense task which solicits, urges, and demands an
                                active coalition of all good wills, what do we see today? Groups of
                                politicians at bay, scattered through different parts of the
                                country, who pretend to oppose the civilizing progress of the
                                government by exerting themselves to create and to develop an
                                agitation purely political under the lying pretext of “restoring
                                democratic institutions”, that is to say, to be exact, to replace
                                the present legislative Council of State by a Chamber and a
                                Senate!</p>
                            <p>You are not ignorant of the fact, Mr. Prefect, that it is the firm
                                design of the present government to realize fully the constitutional
                                provision for the election of the two Legislative Chambers. But at
                                what moment ought this election be brought about, which the
                                constitution itself, in an evident view to prudence and wisdom, has
                                made <pb facs="0389" n="307" xml:id="pg_307"/> dependent upon a
                                special convocation by the President of the Republic? That is the
                                whole question between the Government and its adversaries. These
                                latter say: “Immediately”, that is to say, “on January 10, next.”
                                But the Government, which has no thought of deceiving itself or of
                                deceiving anyone else, replies: No, the Haitien people are not
                                ready. Democracy is the government of the people by conscious,
                                popular suffrage, practiced with the greatest possible liberty. We
                                have that liberty. Never in any period of our country, for more than
                                a century, has there been in Haiti as much liberty as at the present
                                moment. The liberty of circulation is absolute; without any
                                passport, one crosses the country in every sense. The freedom of
                                holding meetings is subject only to a previous notification to the
                                local police. The freedom of the press which is, when summed up, the
                                expression of all the others, is absolute; the law which governs it
                                is made only to suppress abuses, defamation, outrage, provocation to
                                crime, all those intolerable excesses by which the old revolutionary
                                demon, impatient to break his chains, manifests himself from time to
                                time.</p>
                            <p>We have liberty. But where then is our popular conscious
                                suffrage?</p>
                            <p>Our rural population, which represents nine-tenths of the Haitien
                                people, is almost totally illiterate, ignorant and poor; although
                                its material and moral situation has been appreciably bettered in
                                these last few years, it is still incapable of exercising the right
                                of vote, and would be the easy prey of those bold speculators whose
                                conscience hesitates at no lie.</p>
                            <p>As for the town population, one-tenth of the total population, those
                                of its members who are capable of expressing an intelligent vote,—a
                                little progressive minority formed of peaceful men, business men,
                                artisans, citizens of different professions, belonging to different
                                social classes,—have for a long time, for the most part, renounced
                                their electoral right, disgusted by the immoral maneuvers and the
                                insolent frauds which render, and would still render illusory their
                                efforts as intelligent electors. The remainder is the small group of
                                professional politicians, with their followers of every sort, who
                                are mainly illiterate.</p>
                            <p>That is the present electoral body! It is characterized by an
                                absolute lack of organization as to the little number of its useful
                                elements, and, for the rest, by a flagrant inability to assume, in
                                the decisive period through which we are passing, the heavy
                                responsibilities of a political action.</p>
                            <p>Popular suffrage has not its <hi rend="italic">raison d’etre</hi>, if
                                it can only serve to elect individuals and nothing else. True
                                democratic suffrage should serve, primarily, to elect in individuals
                                definite principles, programs of action, and methods of
                                government.</p>
                            <pb facs="0390" n="308" xml:id="pg_308"/>
                            <p>All this amounts to saying, that the rational and necessary
                                foundation of democratic suffrage is, in a conscious electoral body,
                                the organization of parties with platforms.</p>
                            <p>Our national history has only presented up to now two real parties,
                                the National party which extols the principle of a strong executive
                                authority, and the Liberal party, enthused by parliamentarism. Both
                                have disappeared from the political scene through lack of interior
                                discipline and of support by a real public opinion.</p>
                            <p>The Government is working to prepare the way to the intelligent and
                                disciplined democracy, to the solid organization thereof. The
                                present electoral law is recognized by all as incompatible with the
                                sincere expression of popular will. A new law, now in the course of
                                preparation, will be presented at the next Ordinary Session; it will
                                offer all the possibilities for the full functioning of political
                                parties, and for the constitution of an intelligent electoral body,
                                capable of exercising, without danger to the Republic, the sovereign
                                attributes of universal suffrage.</p>
                            <p>And when the hour shall have struck, an hour which will be hastened,
                                let us hope, by the wisdom of our citizens, the President of the
                                Republic will be proud to put into operation the solemn prerogative
                                which the constitution has consigned to his patriotism, his
                                judgement, and his conscience, to fix the date of the legislative
                                elections.</p>
                            <p>Until that time, I advise you, Mr. Prefect, the Council of State will
                                continue to follow the formal provision which, in this same
                                constitution, has delegated to it the functions of the legislative
                                power.</p>
                            <p>And you will take care that the approaching elections of January 10,
                                1926, shall be exclusively communal.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Borno</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>