<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-10-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-10-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="37" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d37">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">860f.51/450</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Spencer Phenix, of the Office of
                                the Economic Adviser</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-10-14"><hi rend="italic">October 14,
                                1925</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Mr. Ralph Crews, Counsel for the National City Company, telephoned this
                            afternoon to say that representatives of the Czechoslovak Government
                            desired to negotiate with the National City Company in connection with
                            certain loans desired by them. Mr. Crews stated that the Czechoslovak
                            representatives informed him that they had signed an agreement for the
                            funding of the indebtedness of Czechoslovakia to the United States, but
                            in view of the Department’s correspondence last summer with the National
                            City Company, he desired to have definite advice as to the Department’s
                            position with respect to such negotiations. I told Mr. Crews that I
                            would endeavor to telephone him an answer to his inquiry during the
                            afternoon.</p>
                        <p>I spoke with the Secretary about this matter and was informed by him that
                            he had discussed the general question with Mr. Mellon and Mr. Hoover and
                            that all three had agreed that no objection would be offered by this
                            Government to negotiations looking to Czechoslovak financing in this
                            country. Accordingly I telephoned Mr. Crews that the Department had no
                            objection to negotiations between the National City Company and the
                            Czechoslovak Government.</p>
                        <closer><signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">pencer</hi>] P[<hi rend="smallcaps">henix</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>