<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chargé in Mexico ( (Schoenfeld))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1925v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d410</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">410</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1925-06-15T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1925-06-15T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-06-15T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-06-15T17:00:00-05:00" n="410"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d410">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.12/548: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chargé in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Schoenfeld</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-06-15T18:00:00-04:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 15, 1925—6 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>133. The following is for your information and guidance: The Secretary’s
                    statement will be allowed to stand. The Department will make no supplementary
                    comment for publication. It does not consider making a retort to the reply of
                    President Calles.</p>
                <p>When Ambassador Téllez called at the Department this morning it was pointed out
                    to him that the Secretary’s statement should tend to augment the position of
                    President Calles. It was also stated that although President Calles’
                    interpretation of the Secretary’s statement and his retort were matters of
                    surprise and regret to the Department, nevertheless, the Secretary would not
                    recede from his position. Ambassador Téllez expressed his belief that the
                    Secretary’s statement need not be regarded as antagonistic to President Calles
                    personally, and he said he would inform his Government in that sense.</p>
                <pb facs="0603" n="521" xml:id="pg_521"/>
                <p>The attention of the Ambassador was invited in a cursory way to the large number
                    of vexatious and longstanding cases still awaiting satisfactory disposition, and
                    to other features of the Mexican situation, and the impression was conveyed to
                    him that the attitude of this Government towards his Government was no different
                    from the one which we would assume toward any Government which might treat
                    American interests with contumely. It was intended that the conversation should
                    contain the implication that unless the Government of Mexico saw to it that a
                    fair deal was given to Americans and American interests it could hardly expect
                    continued encouragement by our Government and without a logical <hi
                        rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> of satisfactory treatment it could not
                    reasonably look for countenance and support.</p>
                <p>The Department hopes that after the initial excitement has subsided and that
                    after the rallying of dissenting groups around President Calles, in view of the
                    fancied threat of foreign interference, has ceased, the point of the statement
                    of June 12 will make an impression, and that the better and more conservative
                    elements of the Government will endeavor to support President Calles in carrying
                    out a program which was so auspiciously inaugurated but which unfortunately has
                    been deviated from.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kellogg</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
