<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-10-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-10-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="411" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d411">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">812.5200/1</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Schoenfeld</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-10-02"><hi rend="italic">October 2,
                                1925</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received October 9.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1178</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to recent correspondence<note n="18" xml:id="d411fn18">Not printed.</note> regarding the
                            announcement made by the President of the Republic in his message to
                            Congress on September 1, last, of the forthcoming introduction of a bill
                            regulating the ownership of property in this country by foreigners, I
                            have the honor now to enclose a clipping from today’s edition of the
                            newspaper <hi rend="italic">Excelsior</hi> containing the full text of
                            the President’s message to Congress under date of September 30, last,
                            covering the proposed bill, together with a translation thereof.<note n="19" xml:id="d411fn19">Only the text of the bill which accompanied
                                the President’s message is printed <hi rend="italic">infra.</hi></note></p>
                        <p rend="center"> . . . . . . .</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">H. F. Arthur
                            Schoenfeld</hi></signed></closer>
                        <pb facs="0604" n="522" xml:id="pg_522"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation<note n="20" xml:id="d411fn20">File translation
                                revised.</note>]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Proposed Alien Land Bill to Regulate Section 1
                                    of Article 27 of the Mexican Constitution</hi><note n="21" xml:id="d411fn21">For text of the Mexican Constitution, see <ref target="frus1917#pg_951"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, 1917, p. 951</ref>.</note></head>
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1. In order that a foreigner
                                    may form part of a Mexican corporation which has acquired, or
                                    may acquire, lands or rights to waters and their accessions in
                                    the territory of the Republic, outside the prohibited zone, as
                                    stipulated in the final part of section 1 of article 27 of the
                                    Constitution, he must comply with the provisions of section 1,
                                    to wit: To agree before the Department of Foreign Affairs to be
                                    considered a national in respect to the part of the property
                                    which is his share in the corporation, and not to invoke in
                                    respect to the same the protection of his Government under
                                    penalty, in case of breach, of forfeiture to the Nation of the
                                    properties which he has acquired, or may acquire, as a
                                    shareholder in the corporation of which he may form a
                                    part.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 2. This provision must be
                                    complied with by any foreigner who wishes to acquire shares or
                                    participation of any kind in a Mexican corporation which
                                    possesses, or may possess, real estate, rights to waters and
                                    their accessions within national territory.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 3. No foreigner may form
                                    part of a Mexican corporation which possesses, or may possess,
                                    real property, rights to waters and their accessions in a zone
                                    of 100 kilometers along the frontiers and 50 kilometers along
                                    the seacoast.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 4. Agreements and contracts
                                    entered into in violation of the provisions of the three
                                    articles just preceding, shall be null and void. No agreement
                                    for the alienation of property may be considered retroactively
                                    perfect until the renouncement stipulated in article 1 of this
                                    law shall have been made.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 5. Any corporation in which
                                    one or more foreigners may have, in any form, an interest
                                    greater than 50 percent of the total shares of the corporation,
                                    will not enjoy the privileges which the law grants to Mexican
                                    corporations.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 6. Those foreigners who may
                                    have acquired, in the prohibited zones, any kind of real
                                    property, rights to waters and their accessions, as shareholders
                                    in a Mexican corporation, before this law came into force, must
                                    divest themselves thereof within 3 years from the time this law
                                    came into force, unless they acquire Mexican nationality in
                                    accordance with the existing legal provisions. Foreigners
                                    holding any shares in corporations possessing real property,
                                    rights to waters and their accessions, outside of the prohibited
                                    zone, must make a declaration before the Department of Foreign
                                    Affairs <pb facs="0605" n="523" xml:id="pg_523"/> within 6
                                    months after the date of the promulgation of this law, in regard
                                    to their participation in such corporation, with the
                                    understanding, that if they do not do so, the acquisition will
                                    be considered as made subsequent to the promulgation of this
                                    law.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 7. The Executive is
                                    empowered to regulate the provisions of this law.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 8. The present law shall
                                    take effect from the date of its promulgation.</item>
                            </list>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>