<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-12-12T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-12-12T19:00:00-05:00" n="422" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d422">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">812.6363/1592: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Sheffield</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-12-12T19:00:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">December 12,
                                        1925—7 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>274. Below is the substance of my conversation today with the Mexican
                            Ambassador. Unless you believe it to be inadvisable you are authorized
                            to use it as a basis of a conversation with the Mexican Minister for
                            Foreign Affairs:<note n="45" xml:id="d422fn45">Quotation which follows
                                not paraphrased.</note></p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“The Secretary referred to a memorandum of the Mexican Minister for
                                Foreign Affairs<note n="46" xml:id="d422fn46"><hi rend="italic">Supra.</hi></note> in answer to a memorandum left with
                                Señor Sáenz on November 27,<note n="47" xml:id="d422fn47">See
                                    telegram No. 264, Nov. 25, to the Ambassador in Mexico, <ref target="#pg_529">p. 529</ref>.</note> in which certain
                                observations were made concerning the bill proposed to ‘regulate’
                                Article 27 of the Mexican Constitution. Señor Téllez stated that he
                                had not yet received a copy of this memorandum, but that he had had
                                a telegram from his Government stating that it was on the way.</p>
                            <pb facs="0630" n="548" xml:id="pg_548"/>
                            <p>The Secretary then read to Señor Téllez from Page 2 of the
                                    memorandum,<note n="48" xml:id="d422fn48">Reference is to the
                                    text as telegraphed by the Ambassador in his No. 269, Dee. 8, 10
                                    a.m.; not printed.</note> and remarked, in connection with the
                                implied criticism of the Secretary’s action in commenting upon
                                pending legislation in Mexico, that we had received at different
                                times representations from foreign governments in respect to pending
                                legislation in the United States, and that it seemed to him that the
                                time to make these comments was before the legislation should be
                                enacted, with a view to avoiding future friction. The Secretary
                                explained very fully to Señor Téllez that this Government had made
                                it most clear at all times that it did not wish to make any
                                observations on legislation in Mexico aimed solely at the future,
                                and had carefully restricted the scope of the observations made to
                                the features in the pending bills which seemed to have retroactive
                                effect and to affect vested rights duly acquired under previously
                                existing Mexican laws. He added that the letter and spirit of the
                                minutes of the discussions between the Mexican Commissioners and
                                Messrs. Warren and Payne should also always be borne in mind in this
                                connection.</p>
                            <p>Alluding to the implication in the reply from the Mexican Minister
                                for Foreign Affairs that these observations were preceded by press
                                publications which, although he was sure did not emanate officially
                                from the respective offices, certainly originated therein, the
                                Secretary stated that this was not true; that he had in accordance
                                with his own views and the agreement reached with the Minister for
                                Foreign Affairs, carefully refrained from any allusion to the matter
                                during his conversations with the press, and that no information had
                                been given out either by the members of the American Embassy in
                                Mexico or by the Department. Señor Téllez observed that some of the
                                American correspondents in Mexico City had sent despatches
                                concerning the bill, and it was intimated subsequently to Señor
                                Téllez that these correspondents had many sources of information in
                                Mexico and that the text of the bill was not difficult for them to
                                obtain.</p>
                            <p>The Secretary stated to the Ambassador that he did not desire to go
                                into a detailed discussion of the provisions of the Alien Land and
                                Petroleum laws; that he had examined with care the reply of the
                                Mexican Government and had examined the Petroleum Bill<note n="49" xml:id="d422fn49"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_531">p. 531</ref>.</note> and it seemed to him,
                                and it was the unanimous opinion of all American interests which had
                                made representations to the State Department, that these bills, if
                                they become laws, would divest vested rights legally acquired under
                                Mexican laws and he deplored the construction evidently placed upon
                                his recommendations, which were made only in a friendly spirit and
                                in consonance with his desire to protect duly vested American rights
                                and to avoid misunderstanding between the two countries. The
                                Secretary pointed out to the Ambassador that the two laws referred
                                to, the one of Arizona and the one of Illinois, were not retroactive
                                and did not divest previously vested rights of foreign citizens. The
                                Arizona law specifically provides that no person other than a
                                citizen of the United States, or who has declared his intention to
                                become such, and no corporation more than 30 percent of whose stock
                                is owned by persons other than citizens of the United States or who
                                have declared their intention to become <pb facs="0631" n="549" xml:id="pg_549"/> such, shall hereafter acquire any land or
                                title thereto or interest therein other than mineral lands or such
                                as may be necessary for the actual working of mines and the products
                                thereof. The Arizona law also has a proviso that it shall not be
                                construed in any way to prevent or interfere with the ownership of
                                mining lands. The Illinois Statute does not in terms apply to lands
                                acquired previous to the passage of the law and has been so
                                construed by the Supreme Court of Illinois as not applying to
                                previously vested rights of aliens. This construction is binding
                                upon every court in the United States.</p>
                            <p>The Secretary went on to say that we have given many evidences of our
                                friendship to the present Government of Mexico; that the restriction
                                on the sale of arms have been removed from all Central American
                                countries except in one or two instances where we have treaty
                                requirements, but we continued to police the international border at
                                our expense and to maintain the embargo on arms to Mexico; that no
                                shipments of arms or explosives have been made to Mexico since the
                                embargo except upon express permit given by the Department of State
                                and with the approval of the Mexican Embassy in this capital; that
                                we had on several occasions attempted to restrict the activities of
                                persons in this country supposed to be furthering revolutionary or
                                subversive movements; that we have always refused, to receive
                                representatives of any Mexican revolutionary groups; that he has
                                purposely refused to receive any Mexican in order to avoid the risk
                                of finding himself confronted with some one representing a
                                revolutionary movement unless that Mexican were duly presented by
                                the Mexican Ambassador. The Secretary referred to … whom he had
                                refused to receive because he was informed that he was in league
                                with Mexicans in this country desiring to stir up a revolution.</p>
                            <p>The Secretary alluded to the growing impression among Americans
                                interested in Mexico that there was a general campaign of
                                legislation designed to deprive them of their rights, and concluded
                                by saying that he hoped that this was not true but that he desired
                                to have a frank talk with Señor Téllez on the subject.</p>
                            <p>The Secretary alluded to the labor bill pending in Mexico, but
                                observed that of course it was a matter of domestic policy, and that
                                we did not wish to make any official representations thereon, but
                                that American interests were very much concerned over its
                                possibilities.”</p>
                        </quote>
                        <p>Department is of the opinion that some provisions of the petroleum bill
                            are retroactive and destructive of the vested rights of Americans. After
                            reading reply of Foreign Minister I am convinced that criticisms of land
                            bill were justified. If you are of the opinion, after you have had
                            further conversations with the Foreign Minister, that the Department
                            should file a formal protest against the petroleum bill and should make
                            a further reply to Foreign Office note in answer to your November 27th,
                            I shall do so. Do not leave with Foreign Office a memorandum of my above
                            conversation since the Ambassador took no notes and his report may
                            differ from mine in detail. Reply at once as to whether Department
                            should make representations.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Kellogg</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>