<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in Nicaragua ( (Ramer))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1925v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d474</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">474</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1925-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1925-02-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-02-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="474"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d474">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">817.1051/50</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in Nicaragua</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ramer</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-02-17">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 17, 1925</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 204</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the Department’s telegram No.
                    26, February 10, 3 p.m., regarding the plan for the establishment of a
                    Constabulary in Nicaragua, there is transmitted herewith a copy of the plan as
                    outlined in the telegram.<note n="7" xml:id="d474fn7">Telegram not printed. This
                        copy of the plan incorporates the Department’s amendments to an earlier
                        draft transmitted by the Legation.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It is assumed that you will transmit to the Department a copy of the plan as
                    presented to the Nicaraguan Government, together with your note presenting the
                    plan and any other correspondence regarding it.</p>
                <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph C. Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Plan for the Establishment of a Constabulary in
                            Nicaragua</hi>
                    </head>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The Nicaraguan Government will establish a civil police force which
                            shall be referred to hereinafter as the “Constabulary.”</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The strength of the constabulary, exclusive of the American personnel,
                            shall be 23 officers and 392 enlisted men, but this force will be
                            increased should such increase appear advisable.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The Constabulary is to be armed, equipped and trained as a military
                            police force with the object of entirely replacing the existing national
                            police, navy and army of Nicaragua. This force is to be trained free
                            from political influence as a national institution and used only to
                            maintain peace, law and order.</item>
                        <pb facs="0707" n="625" xml:id="pg_625"/>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>To provide efficient organization and training the Constabulary will
                            have a division known as the “Nicaraguan National Constabulary Training
                            Branch.” The numerical strength of this force will vary in size as the
                            state of the organization and training of the Constabulary dictates.
                            This force will be hereinafter referred to as the “Training Branch” and,
                            in counter-distinction to this branch, the remainder of the Constabulary
                            will be termed the “Constabulary proper.”</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>In view of the desire of Nicaraguan Government that the United States
                            lend its friendly cooperation in the formation of the Constabulary it is
                            agreed that the officers and enlisted men of the Legation Guard, now
                            stationed at Managua, will, until their withdrawal, voluntarily lend
                            their service in its formation and training.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>To this end it is agreed that these officers and enlisted men, whose
                            voluntary service the Nicaraguan Government has accepted, shall within
                            the training branch but not within the Constabulary proper, have full
                            and complete authority. It is further agreed that upon the withdrawal of
                            the Legation Guard detailed and more permanent arrangements for the
                            development of the Constabulary will be made. In accordance with the
                            request of the Government of Nicaragua the Government of the United
                            States will suggest the names of qualified persons who may be employed
                            under contract by the Nicaraguan Government to take over the management
                            of the training branch after the withdrawal of the Legation Guard. The
                            Nicaraguan Government will make every effort to obtain the services of
                            these instructors a sufficient time in advance of the withdrawal of the
                            Legation Guard to assure the uninterrupted functioning of the training
                            branch.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>The training branch, and all the Nicaraguan officers and enlisted men
                            who may from time to time compose it, is not to come under the authority
                            of the Ministry of War or the Commander of the Constabulary proper but
                            be subject directly and solely to the command and authority of the
                            senior American Marine Officer who is subordinate only to the President
                            of the Republic in all matters pertaining thereto.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>The commander of the training branch will prepare such rules and
                            regulations as may be necessary for the proper administration,
                            discipline and control of the Constabulary and these rules and
                            regulations, when approved by the President of Nicaragua, will be
                            binding on all persons who are or who may become members of the
                            Constabulary. Such persons will not be subject to Civil Law
                            process.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>All officers and enlisted men of the Constabulary must first pass
                            through the training branch and qualify by such physical, mental, moral
                            and professional standards as the training branch commander may
                            prescribe.</item>
                        <pb facs="0708" n="626" xml:id="pg_626"/>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>All replacements of either officers or enlisted men must come from the
                            training branch.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>Whenever the Commander of the training branch deems it necessary all
                            officers and enlisted men of the Constabulary proper, either as
                            individuals or as entire organizations, may be returned to the training
                            branch and their places taken by individuals or organizations of the
                            training branch.</item>
                        <label>12.</label>
                        <item>The American Officers who have volunteered their services with the
                            training branch will have the authority to make such inspections of the
                            Constabulary proper as the Commander of the training branch deems
                            desirable and necessary.</item>
                        <label>13.</label>
                        <item>The procurement of all supplies for the Constabulary will be made by
                            the Supply Officer of the training branch who will honor all reasonable
                            and necessary requisitions from the supply officers of the Constabulary
                            proper.</item>
                        <label>14.</label>
                        <item>Such existing army supplies, buildings, grounds and other army
                            utilities as may be considered by the Commander of the training branch
                            necessary for the establishment and maintenance of the Constabulary are
                            to be placed at his disposal by the Nicaraguan Government.</item>
                        <label>15.</label>
                        <item>The Nicaraguan Government will appropriate in its annual budget the
                            funds necessary for the execution of this plan, as set forth in the
                            appendix hereof. Checks drawn against this appropriation must in each
                            case be approved by the supply officer of the training branch.</item>
                        <label>16.</label>
                        <item>All disbursements for the Constabulary accounts will be made by the
                            supply officer of the training branch. Officers accounts may be audited
                            not to exceed twice in one year by a competent auditing commission
                            (which is to be selected by the American Minister to Nicaragua and the
                            Nicaraguan Minister of Finance.) Unless the question of the correctness
                            of the auditing of the accounts be presented within thirty days after
                            the auditing of the accounts, no question concerning the correctness of
                            such auditing shall thereafter be raised. If the correctness or legality
                            of any payment cannot be satisfactorily determined by conference between
                            the auditing commission and the Supply Officer, the matter shall be
                            referred to the American Minister to Nicaragua and the Nicaraguan
                            Minister of Finance, whose decision is to be final. If any account is
                            paid in good faith and with honest intention no disallowance of such
                            account shall be made.</item>
                        <label>17.</label>
                        <item>American officers and enlisted men who are being utilized in the
                            training branch of the Constabulary shall enjoy the privileges of free
                            entry into Nicaragua of their personal and household effects and other
                            supplies needed for their personal and family use.</item>
                        <pb facs="0709" n="627" xml:id="pg_627"/>
                        <label>18.</label>
                        <item>Such changes in the present arrangement as may seem necessary on
                            account of the withdrawal of the Legation Guard, or at any future time,
                            will be made by the Nicaraguan Government in consultation with the
                            Government of the United States.</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
