<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-04-17T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-04-17T11:00:00-05:00" n="574" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d574">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.5231/406: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Spain</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Moore</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-04-17T16:00:00+00:00"><hi rend="italic">April 17,
                                        1925—4 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received 6:40
                            p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>13. After numerous conferences I have received the following proposition
                            from Admiral Magaz, Acting President Military Directorate: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“In an interview recently held with the Assistant Secretary of
                                    State, Your Excellency referred to a note of your Government
                                    dated December 5, 1924, in which the proposition was made to His
                                    Majesty’s Government that a commercial agreement of temporary
                                    nature be negotiated between the United States and Spain pending
                                    the arrangement of a new commercial treaty between the two
                                    countries, a temporary agreement based on unconditional
                                    reciprocal favored-nation treatment. The Assistant Secretary
                                    having explained to Your Excellency the reasons of a legal
                                    nature that prevent the Government of His Majesty from agreeing
                                    to negotiate on that basis, which the Ambassador of His Catholic
                                    Majesty at Washington has been instructed to communicate to the
                                    North American Government, Your Excellency suggested to the
                                    Acting Foreign Minister as a subsidiary solution that the
                                    commercial regime in effect, which will terminate May 5th next,
                                    be extended.</p>
                                <p>The Government of His Majesty after careful consideration given
                                    to the suggestion of Your Excellency in this respect agrees to
                                    accept in principle that solution; but at the same time, in view
                                    of the great injury to so important a factor of Spanish
                                    production as the grapes of Almeria that has been and continues
                                    to be occasioned by the policy of the American Government<note n="4" xml:id="d574fn4">An embargo on the importation of
                                        grapes and other fruits from regions where the Mediterranean
                                        fruit fly was present (including the Spanish province of
                                        Almeria), was laid by the Federal Horticultural Board in its
                                        Plant Quarantine No. 56.</note> which in the opinion of the
                                    Government of His Majesty is unjustified for the reasons
                                    communicated to that Government, in requesting derogation [<hi rend="italic">modification</hi>] of the same the Spanish
                                    Government would regard with pleasure and would appreciate as an
                                    evidence of the good will animating the Washington Government
                                    for the development of commercial relations between the two
                                    countries without limitation or restrictions, should the latter
                                    be willing to examine this matter anew with the purpose of
                                    seeing if it would be possible to conform to its<note n="5" xml:id="d574fn5">i. e., the Spanish Government’s.</note>
                                    expressed desire.</p>
                                <p>I have then the honor to inform Your Excellency that the
                                    Government of His Majesty would agree to extend the period of
                                    the present commercial regime whose effects should terminate on
                                    May 5th next <pb facs="0791" n="709" xml:id="pg_709"/> for a
                                    period which, in order to be agreeable to the Washington
                                    Government, it would be willing to fix as one year more, or
                                    until May 5th, 1926, if the latter in exchange would be
                                    favorably inclined to reexamine the matter in reference,
                                    animated by a standard of benevolence for the benefit of a
                                    normal development of the commercial relations between our two
                                    countries.[”]</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Will the Department kindly instruct me what answer to make to the
                            above?</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Moore</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>