<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-06-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-06-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="592" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d592">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">703.5867/85</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Chargé in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Magruder</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-06-24"><hi rend="italic">June 24,
                                1925</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 134</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department’s No. 102 of January 31,
                                1925,<note n="5" xml:id="d592fn5">Not printed.</note> informed you
                            of the desire of the Swedish Government, as made known by the American
                            High Commissioner at Constantinople, to discontinue the protection it
                            has been affording to American interests in Turkey. It is now desired
                            that you address the Minister of Foreign Affairs in the following sense:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>At the request of the Government of the United States the
                                    Government of Sweden kindly consented to permit its officers in
                                    Turkey to act in representation of American interests in that
                                    country. In the view of the Government of the United States the
                                    need for such representation no longer exists. I am therefore
                                    directed by my Government to request that instructions may be
                                    issued to the Minister of Sweden at Constantinople to
                                    discontinue such representation and to turn over to the American
                                    High Commissioner any records or other property of the United
                                    States that may be in his charge.</p>
                                <p>At the same time it is desired that I convey to you, as I do with
                                    much pleasure, the expression of the profound thanks of the
                                    Government of the United States and of its very high
                                    appreciation for the friendly courtesy of the Government of
                                    Sweden.</p>
                                <p>The Government of the United States has been impressed with the
                                    intelligence, efficiency and faithful care with which American
                                    interests have been looked after by Swedish officials at
                                    Constantinople, and <pb facs="0811" n="729" xml:id="pg_729"/>
                                    would be obliged if, through your intermediacy, there could be
                                    made known to all such, and especially to Mr. d’Anckersvard, Mr.
                                    G. O. Wallenberg, Colonel G. Ahlgren, Dr. Kolmodin, and Mr. Karl
                                    Mohn, its sense of obligation to them and its high appreciation
                                    of their whole hearted service in its behalf.<note n="6" xml:id="d592fn6">Mr. d’Anckersvärd and Mr. Wallenberg were
                                        successively the Swedish Ministers in Turkey; Col. Ahlgren,
                                        Counselor of Legation; Dr. Kolmodin, Secretary; and Mr.
                                        Mohn, Clerk.</note></p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Frank B. Kellogg</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>