<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in France ( (Herrick))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1925v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d84</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">84</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1925-10-24T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1925-10-24T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-10-24T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-10-24T19:00:00-05:00" n="84"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d84">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">890d.00/228: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Herrick</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-10-24T19:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 24, 1925—7 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>391. I desire you to make immediate and vigorous representations to Minister for
                    Foreign Affairs that this Government expects that all possible steps will be
                    taken for the protection of American lives and property in Syria. In your
                    representations you may make discreet use of information contained in paragraphs
                    1, 2 and 3 of Department’s 390<note n="6" xml:id="d84fn6">Not printed.</note>
                    which tends to indicate failure on part of French authorities to extend adequate
                    protection to American citizens in Damascus as well as a failure to give
                    reasonable warning of impending danger to American Consul and our nationals from
                    French bombardment and evacuation of their troops.</p>
                <p>Further you may indicate that this Government reserves the right to demand
                    settlement for any injury to American citizens and property and to make such
                    further representations as the facts of the case may warrant in the event that
                    it should appear that injury to American citizens or destruction of American
                    property had resulted from unjustifiable action of the French Military forces.
                    In this connection note what Keeley says with reference to French
                    bombardment.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kellogg</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
