<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memoramdum of Conversation, by Mr. Albert H. Gerberich of the
                        Division of North and West Coast Affairs</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d134</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">134</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-03-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-03-13T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-03-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-03-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="134" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d134">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">561.333D3/3–1347</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memoramdum of Conversation, by Mr. Albert H. Gerberich of the
                        Division of North and West Coast Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-03-13">March 13,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_IR1">IR</gloss>—Mr. Edward G. Cale<note n="2" xml:id="d134fn1">Associate Chief of the International Resources
                                Division, and Chairman of the Inter-American Coffee Board.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. William H. Bray</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_CPA1">CPA</gloss>—Mr. Fred G. Heins</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_BA2">BA</gloss>—Mr. Harold N. Midkiff</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_NWC1">NWC</gloss>—Mr. Albert H. Gerberich</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Summary</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Cale gave a review of the coffee situation since 1939 and explained that the
                    Inter-American Coffee Agreement (of Nov. 28, 1940)<note n="3" xml:id="d134fn2">For text, see Department of State Treaty Series No. 970, or 55 Stat. (pt.
                        2) 1143. For documentation on the Third Pan American Coffee Conference, see
                            <ref target="frus1940v05#pg_380">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1940, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 380</ref> ff.</note> will come up for
                    renewal again on Sept. 30, 1947, and he wanted to hear what the feeling is
                    regarding it.</p>
                <p>After Mr. Cale’s introductory remarks, Mr. Midkiff stated that he could see
                    little purpose in continuing the agreement, as there are no serious problems
                    affecting coffee at the moment.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cale said that this is correct, that prices are now extremely high (26¢ per
                    lb. for Santos as compared with 6.38¢ in 1940, for example), and there seems to
                    be no likelihood of a coffee surplus for some time to come, especially since
                    Brazilian exports are down from 22 million bags per year to between 12 and 14
                    million. Furthermore, there are no quotas to be adjusted, since all <gloss target="#t_OPA1">OPA</gloss> controls are off.</p>
                <p>He added confidentially that Paul Daniels<note n="4" xml:id="d134fn3">Counselor
                        of Embassy in Brazil and former Chairman of the Inter-American Coffee
                        Board.</note> favors permitting the Agreement to lapse, but Mr. Cale fears
                    that there will be some objection to this from the smaller producing countries,
                    especially Guatemala. Mr. Daniels will be in the Department toward the end of
                    March. The Inter-American Coffee Board will meet again in April, <pb facs="0172" n="156" xml:id="pg_156"/> and perhaps Mr. Daniels can be present for another
                    discussion before then.</p>
                <p>The report on the world coffee situation called for under Article 3 of the
                    Extension of the Agreement (of Jan. 6, 1947), has been completed, but Mr. Cale
                    expressed himself as somewhat disappointed with it despite its length and
                    detail.</p>
                <p>(With regard to the improved conditions in the Colombian coffee industry this
                    recent statement of Roberto Marulanda, Minister of National Economy, is of
                    interest: “In 1946 the <hi rend="italic">campesinos</hi> had to pay 4 arrobas of
                    coffee for one machete; today they can get four machetes for one arroba.”)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
