<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Brazil (
                        Pawley
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d343</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">343</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-05-16T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-05-16T20:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-05-16T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-05-16T20:00:00-05:00" n="343" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d343">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">832.00/5–1647: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pawley</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de Janeiro</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-05-16T22:00:00-03:00">May 16, 1947—10 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>596. <hi rend="italic">Tribuna Popular</hi> published on May 15 facsimile of
                    memorandum dated May 7 issued by General Saville’s<note n="7" xml:id="d343fn1">Brig. Gen. Gordon P. Saville, United States Army member, Joint
                        Brazil-United States Military Commission.</note> executive officer to
                    personnel, US Army section air, <gloss target="#t_JBUSMC1">JBUSMC</gloss>,
                    stating that it was contemplated <pb facs="0409" n="393" xml:id="pg_393"/> that
                    an important political decision would be rendered by Brazilian Govt on following
                    day, May 8, and that it was possible that there might be public demonstrations
                    during next few days.</p>
                <p>Memo cautioned personnel to avoid public gatherings, stay off streets as much as
                    possible and wear civilian clothes after working hours.</p>
                <p>In reproducing Saville’s memo, <hi rend="italic">Tribuna Popular</hi> alleged
                    that Truman was responsible for closing Communist Party and that American
                    “imperialists” knew what vote of the electoral tribunal would be day before it
                    took place. <hi rend="italic">Tribuna Popular</hi> today points out that
                    Saville’s memo referred to important “political” decision of “government” not
                    merely “tribunal”. Although Saville has made no mention to anyone of fact, it is
                    known to Embassy that he was not in town on day on which this memo was
                    issued.</p>
                <p>Saville yesterday gave statement to <hi rend="italic">O Globo</hi> stating in
                    substance that on his honor as a soldier he had no knowledge that Supreme
                    Electoral Tribunal would cancel Communist Party registration when he issued his
                    instruction preceding day; that this instruction was issued as matter of routine
                    to reiterate our traditional position that Brazilian domestic affairs are
                    reserved exclusively to Brazilians; that like other newspaper readers he learned
                    from published accounts that the tribunal was about to render judgment;
                    consequently cautioned personnel to be alert in avoiding any act which might
                    even inadvertently be interpreted as indication of participation in domestic
                    affairs of Brazil. Other papers have not featured story although several have
                    carried Saville’s statement.</p>
                <p>I called Saville’s attention to fact that it was unwise to have issued statement
                    in effort to justify his instruction and that had I been consulted such
                    statement would not have been made. I also cautioned Saville and other members
                    of <gloss target="#t_JBUSMC1">JBUSMC</gloss> to make no written instructions of
                    this nature in future.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Pawley</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
