<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                            Embassy in Brazil</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d364</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">364</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-07-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="364" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d364">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">832.34/7–2947: Airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in Brazil</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-07-29">July 29,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>A–454. There are now in the possession of the Brazilian government a number of US
                    naval vessels leased to Brazil during the war under a charter party agreement
                    between the two governments. By the terms of this agreement, the US retains
                    title to the vessels and Brazil is required to return each vessel, unless lost,
                    to this Government at a place and time to be specified by the US. This procedure
                    was used because <pb facs="0426" n="410" xml:id="pg_410"/> under the Lend Lease
                        Act<note n="48" xml:id="d364fn1">Act of March 11, 1941; 55 Stat. 31.</note>
                    it was not permitted to transfer title to these vessels.</p>
                <p>As the Navy Department now considers the ships leased to Brazil to be surplus to
                    its needs, it is planned to offer all of them, with the exception of 8 destroyer
                    escorts, for sale to Brazil as surplus property at a low price. There is no
                    legislative authority whereby destroyer escorts may be sold to foreign
                    governments. If Brazil should agree to purchase, it is planned not to require
                    Brazil to return the ships to a US port for actual repossession by the US, but
                    to ask that they be returned to an appropriate US official in Brazil until a
                    contract of sale is finalized. Failure to purchase the ships will necessitate
                    that they be returned by Brazil to a US port for actual repossession by the US
                    and subsequent disposal. Although the agreement states that “hire” (charge for
                    use) of the vessels during the war shall be determined by subsequent agreement
                    between the two governments, it is not planned to charge for use of the ships,
                    since they were employed in the common defense effort.</p>
                <p>Without approaching Brazilians, please report your comments regarding plan by
                    cable and any objections you may perceive. US ships covered by agreement with
                    Brazil are: 8 subchasers (PC); 8 subchasers (SC); 1 transport (<gloss target="#t_AP1">AP</gloss>); 1 repair barge (YR); 5 launches (<gloss target="#t_ML1">ML</gloss>); 1 gate vessel (<gloss target="#t_YNG1">YNg</gloss>); 1 barge (YS); 1 floating drydock (YFD); 11 plane personnel
                    craft; 19 plane rearming craft; 1 landing boat. In addition, Brazil has 8
                    destroyer escorts (<gloss target="#t_DE1">DE</gloss>) covered by the agreement,
                    but, as indicated above, there is no legislative authority whereby these may be
                    sold to Brazil.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
