<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Chairman of the United States Delegation (
                        Marshall
                    ) to the Acting Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d49</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">49</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-08-21T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-08-21T23:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-08-21T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-08-21T23:00:00-05:00" n="49" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d49">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">710 Consultation 4/8–2247: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chairman of the United States Delegation</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Marshall</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Petrópolis</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-08-22T01:00:00-03:00">August 22, 1947—1 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>51. Daily Conference summary 6. Central Committee approved plan work Conference
                    and fixed August 28 termination work committees. Brazil proposed September 5
                    closing session but Committee decided leave open, in view possibility earlier
                    termination.</p>
                <p>Committee I established two subcommittees begin substantive work. Discussion and
                    proposals. Committee II show considerable support inclusion comprehensive
                    definition aggression. Subcommittee Committee III decided organ consultation
                    under treaty should be meetings Foreign Ministers but that <gloss target="#t_PAU1">PAU</gloss> governing board could act on interim basis.
                    Possibility left open use other methods by agreement parties.</p>
                <p>Following Mexican proposal economic cooperation now supported fourteen other
                    countries, including US, Brazil, Argentina:</p>
                <p>That inter-American <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss> prepare draft
                    agreement economic cooperation submission Bogotá; that staffs members be
                    augmented for purpose; and that special economic conference be called second
                    half next year, time to be set by Bogotá Conference, to study-procedures carry
                    out agreement and make economic cooperation more effective.</p>
                <p>Prearranged plan, which called for presentation above resolution Central
                    Committee today, stalled because Belt (Cuba), pretending cooperation, said he
                    wanted obtain approval government drop Cuban economic resolution in favor
                    Mexican proposal.</p>
                <p>Now learn Belt will insist presentation tomorrow proposal economic aggression,
                    notwithstanding pledge cooperation to members US delegation. Therefore present
                    plan is that Mexican proposal will be presented tomorrow and US will second.</p>
                <p>Plenary session speeches Trujillo (Ecuador) and Zuleta Angel (Colombia). Trujillo
                    stated hemisphere must close ranks and prepare eventualities in view two
                    opposing forces world today. Stated that after individualistic fight last
                    century for separate sovereignties and period romantic Pan-Americanism, American
                    representatives now see necessary articulate individual sovereignties giving up
                    part in interest sovereignty hemisphere. In discussing Ecuadorian proposals, he
                    stated principle inviolability treaties must be modified prevent perpetuation
                    injustice, insisted must define aggression in treaty; and supported Mexican
                    proposal basic charter Bogotá.</p>
                <p>Zuleta placed great emphasis Latin American unity although giving US high praise,
                    and referred brave fight Latin American delegations <pb facs="0070" n="54" xml:id="pg_54"/> San Francisco for autonomy inter-American system. Insisted
                    system should have complete liberty in pacific settlement, full right
                    self-defense and full choice of taking necessary preventive steps in event
                    aggression, limiting rigor of principle of article 53, <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> charter by distinguishing between coercive and preventive
                    measures, latter not requiring S[ecurity] C[ouncil] authorization.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
