<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Chargé in Colombia (
                        Warner
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d526</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">526</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-08-15T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-08-15T11:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-08-15T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-08-15T11:00:00-05:00" n="526" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d526">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">821.51 Bondholders/8–1547: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Colombia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Warner</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bogotá</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-08-15T11:00:00-05:00">August 15, 1947—11 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>537. <gloss target="#t_reEmbtel1">ReEmbtel</gloss> 536, August 14. President
                    Ospina called me to Palace last evening to stress how serious he considered
                    reopening of the proposed foreign debt settlement would be. He reviewed history
                    of negotiations starting with his discussion as to debt settlement with
                    Assistant Secretary Braden, US bankers, and others when he visited US last year.
                    He noted that he was able to obtain agreement to Rogers proposals from the
                    departmental governors, and municipality representatives. He repeated arguments
                    set forth in Lleras letter to Rogers. The President believes that a reopening of
                    negotiations or failure to carry through Rogers plan would cause him
                    considerable political embarrassment, would be basis for new attacks by
                    Communists and other extremists against so-called US imperialism, and would in
                    general be contrary to US interests.</p>
                <p>The President regrets such possibility especially at this time when he is highly
                    satisfied with relations with US. He attributes good relations to oil companies’
                    present policy of publicity and to rise in coffee prices which not only benefits
                    economy of country, but especially permits the buying of machinery et cetera to
                    improve lot of workers. He called Welsh’s attitude unfortunate and expressed
                    fervent hope that it would not delay final settlement on basis of Rogers
                    agreement especially since proposal was sponsored by Department and Ambassador
                    Wiley. I told him that his views would be conveyed to the Department.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Warner</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
