<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Costa Rica (
                        Donnelly
                    
                    The nomination of Walter J. Donnelly as Ambassador
                        in Costa Rica was confirmed by the United States Senate on April 9,
                        1947.) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d530</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">530</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-07-25T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-07-25T15:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-07-25T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-07-25T15:00:00-05:00" n="530" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d530">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">818.00/7–2547: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Costa Rica</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Donnelly</hi>
                    </persName>
                    <note n="4" xml:id="d530fn1">The nomination of Walter J. Donnelly as Ambassador
                        in Costa Rica was confirmed by the United States Senate on April 9,
                        1947.</note>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">San José</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-07-25T14:00:00-06:00">July 25, 1947—2 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>345. Dr. Alberto Oreamuno, Dr. Antonio Peña Chavarría and Dr. Francisco Jiménez
                    Rodriguez, prominent pro-Ulatistas, called on me last night at their own
                    request. They said they wished explain the facts of the present crisis as they
                    saw it. I observed that while I would be pleased to receive their views, I
                    wanted to make it perfectly clear to them that this Embassy was wholly neutral
                    and that I was confident they would understand our position. I asked them if
                    they were representing Ulate and they replied they came of their own accord;
                    they were not to be considered as officially representing Ulatista Party.</p>
                <p>They said they considered our Government partially responsible for events of
                    yesterday which according to them resulted in 10 persons killed and 20 wounded
                        (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embstel</gloss> 341, July 24<note n="5" xml:id="d530fn2">Not printed.</note>) by reason of fact our Government had
                    sent arms and ammunition to Picado administration and that our military mission
                    here had trained the men who had “murdered these unarmed innocent by-standers”.
                    They said they understood the justification for the military mission during war
                    but that they could not understand reason for keeping the mission in Costa Rica
                    since termination of war.<note n="6" xml:id="d530fn3">For the United
                        States-Costa Rican agreement relating to a military mission, signed at
                        Washington December 10, 1945, see Department of State Executive Agreement
                        Series No. 486, or 59 Stat. (pt. 2) 1682.</note> I interjected with
                    statement to the best of my knowledge my Government had not authorized shipments
                    arms to Costa Rica since end of war with the exception of some ammunition and
                    with respect to their statement that military mission has trained 300 or more
                    men that this figure was considerably exaggerated.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Donnelly</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
