<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Chief of the
                        Division, of Caribbean Affairs (Walker)</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d553</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">553</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-05-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-05-29T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-05-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-05-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="553" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d553">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">837.61351/5–2947</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Chief of the
                        Division, of Caribbean Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Walker</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-05-29">May 29,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>Señor Guillermo Belt, Ambassador of Cuba</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_ABr1">A–Br</gloss>—Mr. Braden</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>—Mr. Briggs</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_CRB1">CRB</gloss>—Mr. Walker</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Ambassador Belt stated that during his recent visit to Cuba he had discussed with
                    President Grau and with several members of the American Chamber of Commerce of
                    Cuba the question of a larger and more equitable share of the U.S. market for
                    Cuban sugar. The Chamber of Commerce members, he added, were concerned over some
                    of the difficulties confronting American businessmen in Cuba and felt that a
                    treaty of commerce was absolutely essential.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador said that he had spoken with President Grau regarding the
                    desirability of satisfactorily resolving the problems (including a larger sugar
                    quota for Cuba) between the United States and Cuba. The President, he stated,
                    agreed that it would be advisable to settle these problems and instructed him to
                    open discussions with this. Government in an effort to reach a basis for
                    satisfactory settlement. <pb facs="0630" n="614" xml:id="pg_614"/> The
                    Ambassador then presented a note to Mr. Braden<note n="21" xml:id="d553fn1">Not
                        printed.</note> setting forth his Government’s suggestion that this was the
                    opportune moment to settle outstanding problems between the two countries and
                    that discussions be undertaken as early as possible.</p>
                <p>Mr. Braden stated that the matter raised in the Ambassador’s note would be
                    studied by the Department and other interested government agencies. He added
                    that upon the completion of these studies the Department would of course
                    communicate with the Ambassador.</p>
                <p>Mr. Braden handed Ambassador Belt the Department’s preliminary reply to the
                    Ambassador’s note of May 20,<note n="21" xml:id="d553fn2">Not printed.</note>
                    expressing the Cuban Government’s preoccupation over efforts being made in
                    Congress to have the Sugar Act of 1937 extended for a period of one year.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
