<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                            Embassy in Mexico</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d658</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">658</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-11-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-11-19T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec9429801e8b840d1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="lend-lease">Lend-Lease</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-11-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-11-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="658" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d658">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">812.24/11–1947</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in Mexico</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        <lb/> No. 1585</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-11-19">November 19,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I refer to the Department’s airgram no. A–305
                    dated April 10, 1947,<note n="12" xml:id="d658fn1">Not printed; the Department
                        indicated that it was then giving further serious consideration to revision
                        of the terms of lend-lease payment to permit part payment in real estate or
                        local currency for the Division of Foreign Buildings Operations program
                        (812.24/3–1147).</note> concerning modification of the terms of repayment to
                    the United States Government by the Government of the United Mexican States of
                    obligations incurred under the Lend-Lease Agreement of March 18, 1943, and to
                    conversations of recent date between officers of the Department and yourself on
                    the same subject.</p>
                <p>It was agreed in the discussions referred to that conversations leading to the
                    revision of the payment in terms embodied in the exchange of notes accompanying
                    that agreement could best be held in Mexico. Accordingly, you are requested to
                    approach the Mexican Government <pb facs="0765" n="749" xml:id="pg_749"/> and
                    proceed with revision of the payment terms through an exchange of notes on the
                    basis outlined in the attached draft note to the Mexican Ministry of Foreign
                        Affairs.<note n="13" xml:id="d658fn2">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>For your information, the sum now due from the Mexican Government under the
                    present terms of the above-mentioned exchange of notes is $8,800,000. An
                    additional sum is scheduled to become due January 1, 1948. According to the
                    latest reports of the lend-lease fiscal authorities (Statement <gloss target="#t_LL1">LL</gloss>–12), this will be $957,000, making a grand total
                    of $9,757,000. This sum represents 33 per cent of lend-lease charges reported
                    through December 31, 1946 of $29,566,805.27. It is not final since reporting and
                    auditing of lend-lease accounts has not yet been completed.</p>
                <p>The Mexican Embassy in Washington was informed of the sum now due in a note dated
                    March 24, 1947, a copy of which was transmitted to the Embassy under cover of
                    instruction no. 971 dated March 28, 1947.<note n="14" xml:id="d658fn3">Neither
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The undetermined amount of the final payments specified in paragraph B of the
                    draft note is due to the fact that reports of lend-lease charges are not yet
                    final. Charges and credits in connection with lend-lease transfers effected
                    during the past several years are still being reported to the Treasury
                    Department fiscal authorities by the United States procuring agencies.
                    Consequently the net bill is likely to be somewhat higher than the total of
                    $9,757,000 mentioned above, or it may possibly be somewhat lower. This point
                    should be made clear to the Mexican Government. In the event that the
                    indeterminate amount of the final payments should prove an obstacle to the
                    success of your negotiations, however, the Department would consider an agreed
                    total, if it should be proposed by the Mexicans.</p>
                <p>The draft note attached of course is not intended to be absolutely final in
                    respect to specific language. Any substantial revision of the proposed terms,
                    however, except the substitution of alternate paragraph C concerning interest
                    charges, should be referred to the Department for clearance. There is no chance
                    that a proposal for reduction of the 33 percent payment originally specified
                    would be accepted.</p>
                <p>The proposed exchange of notes should be <hi rend="italic">Confidential</hi>, as
                    it is felt that publicity regarding this matter might seriously jeopardize
                    prompt collections of sums due from other countries. You may inform the Mexicans
                    accordingly at your discretion.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>[For the Secretary of State] <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Norman</hi> T. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ness</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Director, Office of Financial and Development Policy</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
