<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Secretary of State to
                        the Embassy in Mexico</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d692</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">692</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-12-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-12-16T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-12-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-12-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="692" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d692">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">812.628/12–947: Airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Mexico</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-12-16">December 16,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>A–923. Reference Embassy’s telegram 1406 December 9, 1947.<note n="15" xml:id="d692fn1">Not printed; it concerned the undesirability of any
                        additional publicity at that time regarding the fisheries treaty
                        (812.628/12–947).</note> Department concurs Embassy’s recommendation.</p>
                <p>Department would appreciate receiving promptly Embassy’s evaluation past
                    publicity regarding proposed United States-Mexican fisheries treaty in Mexican
                    publications and probable effect these newspaper accounts on opinions of
                    government officials or public; also recommendations with reference desirability
                    of later release in Mexico of U.S. 1945 draft. In view Lindner’s<note n="16" xml:id="d692fn2">Milton J. Lindner, Chief of the United States Fisheries
                        Mission to Mexico.</note> statement that additional publicity at this time
                    will stimulate opposition to treaty, Embassy is instructed not approach Mexican
                    Government to request permission release in this country or give permission
                    release U.S. 1945 draft in Mexico until further instructed by Department.</p>
                <p>Department being criticized for failure inform and consult with fishing industry
                    and Congress on international problems of concern, to fishing industry. Believe
                    essential, if proposed treaty is to receive support in this country, that all
                    important segments industry affected must be consulted on all phases before
                    commencement Mexican treaty negotiations. For this reason public release in this
                    country of substance U.S. 1945 draft and Mexican memorandum thereon is
                    considered highly desirable. If, however, a simultaneous release substance these
                    documents in Mexico would have repercussions inimical to welfare treaty
                    negotiations, some other course of action must be considered. Industry
                    consultation in this country might be achieved by informing interested persons
                    on confidential basis of all pertinent points for their consideration and
                    advice, without releasing contents U.S. or Mexican documents to newspapers or
                    periodicals. Department would like Embassy’s views in order to help determine
                    desirable course of action.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
