<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Embassy in Mexico</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d699</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">699</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-08-15T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-08-15T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-08-15T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-08-15T17:00:00-05:00" n="699"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d699">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.1256/8–647: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Mexico</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-08-15T18:00:00-04:00"
                            >August 15, 1947—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>772. Meeting August 12 Agriculture of representatives Agriculture including Under
                        Secretary,<note n="42" xml:id="d699fn1">N. E. Dodd.</note> Bureau Animal
                    Industry, representative Dr. Steelman’s office<note n="43" xml:id="d699fn2">John
                        R. Steelman, Assistant to the President; Merle E. Colby, representative of
                        Mr. Steelman’s office.</note> and Dept for purpose determining policy
                    current aphthous problems <gloss target="#t_reurtel1">reurtel</gloss>s 853, 858,
                    859, August 4 and 869, August 6.<note n="44" xml:id="d699fn3">Telegrams 859,
                        August 4, and 869, August 6, not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Agreed with MexGovt US appraisers and paymasters should not occupy prominent
                    position beyond necessary assure just appraisals and disbursements US funds
                    consistent responsibility American Section. Correction present situation
                    requires employment additional <gloss target="#t_Mex1">Mex</gloss> personnel.
                    Agriculture agrees to appraisals group basis whenever practical. US Govt cannot
                    agree to simultaneous vaccination program because inadequate but will consider
                    holding conference Mexican, American and European scientists preferably in
                    Washington lay groundwork further research England where large staff trained and
                    experienced personnel available. Proposes adequate publicity showing that both
                        <gloss target="#t_Mex1">Mex</gloss> and US actively pursuing research all
                    phases disease.</p>
                <p>Concerning broad control this Govt cannot agree designation special Presidential
                    representative. Secretary Agriculture responsible to President and Congress
                    operations American Section and disbursement American funds, and Ambassador is
                    personal representative President Truman in <gloss target="#t_Mex1">Mex</gloss>.
                    Designation of another person to make political decisions would create confusion
                    and hamper campaign.</p>
                <p>US Govt holds agreement immediate future re financial participation essential
                    future effectiveness joint campaign. Would accept plan whereby MexGovt maintains
                    army units and <gloss target="#t_Mex1">Mex</gloss> personnel in field and pays 6
                    million pesos monthly into Joint Commission toward <hi rend="italic">all</hi>
                    other expenses, US to supply all additional funds needed estimated at $5,000,000
                    US. Arrangement would permit coordinated field operation including immediate
                    indemnities <hi rend="italic">all</hi> domestic animals slaughtered, purchase
                    and delivery costs of mules, harnesses and plows, and salaries <pb facs="0836"
                        n="820" xml:id="pg_820"/> of American personnel. Whereas <gloss
                        target="#t_Mex1">Mex</gloss> contribution would remain fixed our
                    contribution would increase with tempo of campaign. <gloss target="#t_Mex1"
                        >Mex</gloss> financial participation therefore on basis of not more than one
                    peso for each US Govt dollar. Proportionately greater American participation
                    could not be justified before Congress.</p>
                <p>Airmail instruction follows with request that Embassy prepare detailed analysis
                    those aspects of campaign having political and economic significance in <gloss
                        target="#t_Mex1">Mex</gloss> and probable effects of continuance of present
                        program.<note n="45" xml:id="d699fn4">
                        <p>In instruction 1422, August 16, the Acting Secretary of State transmitted
                            a copy of the memorandum prepared by the Division of Mexican Affairs at
                            the conclusion of the August 12 meeting; also, a copy of a memorandum by
                            Dr. M. R. Clarkson of the Bureau of Animal Industry, Department of
                            Agriculture, to Dr. B. T. Simms, Chief of that Bureau. He also informed
                            Ambassador Thurston that President Truman had approved the general
                            policy decisions agreed to by the representatives of the Departments of
                            State and of Agriculture at the meeting of August 12, and continued as
                            follows:</p>
                        <p>“The Department desires that you convey the substance of the policy
                            decisions contained in Dr. Clarkson’s memorandum of August 12 orally to
                            President Alemán and that you endeavor to convince him of the desire of
                            this Government to continue its participation in the joint campaign to
                            the fullest possible extent consistent with the obligations of this
                            Government to Congress for the most efficacious expenditure of United
                            States public funds in the conduct of the campaign. You may inform him
                            that the President has and is according full and sympathetic
                            consideration to the serious political and economic problems confronting
                            President Alemán and his administration because of the eradication
                            program, and that the United States Government desires to assist in
                            every practical way in reaching solutions to these problems concurrently
                            with the energetic and efficient conduct of the campaign.”</p>
                        <p>In despatch 4477, August 25, from Mexico, Ambassador Thurston reported on
                            an interview with President Alemen on August 22 at which time he had
                            conveyed to the President the substance of the Department’s telegram 772
                            of August 15.</p>
                        <p>For text of an exchange of notes of September 26 and October 3, 1947,
                            making effective an agreement between the United States and Mexico,
                            namely, a joint agreement of the Mexican-United States Commission, see
                            TIAS No. 2404.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
