<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Nicaragua ( (Warren) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d724</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">724</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-04-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-04-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="recMHJD4XLL5GtXeu" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general">Emissary</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="reclX4mzFRYzavuL4" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections">Free elections</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-04-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-04-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="724"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d724">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">817.00/4–2347</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Nicaragua</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Warren</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                        <lb/> No. 1560</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Managua</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-04-23">April 23,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that the now generally
                    conceded failure of Dr. Enoc Aguado’s trip to Washington has led to increased
                    anti-American feeling in opposition circles and to a marked sense of relief in
                    Government quarters.</p>
                <p>As reported in the Embassy’s despatch no. 1412 of February 15, 1947,<note n="18"
                        xml:id="d724fn1">Not printed.</note> the Embassy’s frequent reiteration to
                    Dr. Aguado and other opposition leaders of the United States’ non-intervention
                    policy had <pb facs="0863" n="847" xml:id="pg_847"/> apparently dispelled their
                    previous hopes of unilateral United States action on their behalf. However,
                    whether through a willful policy of deceit on the part of opposition leaders, or
                    whether through a genuine hope of a sudden reversal in United States policy,
                    Aguado’s trip and subsequent conversations in Washington was allowed to lead to
                    a growing hope amongst the rank and file that the United States Government might
                    refuse to recognize the Argüello regime after all. When these hopes were dashed
                    by the designation of a special American emissary to the inauguration,
                    speculation centered around the possibility that the United States might accord
                    only conditional recognition, based on the condition that General Somoza
                    relinquish his position as Jefe-Director of the Guardia Nacional. Most recently
                    even this hope has faded and it is now generally acknowledged that Aguado failed
                    completely in obtaining United States aid. With this realization has come a
                    marked increase in the already present anti-American feeling in Opposition ranks
                    and a tendency to accuse the United States of hypocrisy, selfishness and
                    insincerity. Typical Opposition feeling is displayed in the enclosed
                        translation<note n="19" xml:id="d724fn2">Not printed.</note> of an editorial
                    which recently appeared on the front page of the Conservative <hi rend="italic"
                        >El Heraldo.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>While the opposition has thus come to condemn the United States for the failure
                    of Aguado’s trip, the Government has loudly applauded the United States’
                    steadfast refusal to intervene in Nicaraguan affairs. Although at first a
                    certain nervousness was displayed lest Dr. Aguado discredit the Government and
                    perhaps even secure outside assistance, confidence returned with the
                    announcement that the United States would be represented at the inauguration on
                    May 1. Current Government attitude was summarized by President Somoza in his
                    last press interview, copies of which are enclosed,<note n="19" xml:id="d724fn3"
                        >Not printed.</note> in which he comments extensively on Dr. Aguado’s trip.
                    In answer to certain statements allegedly made by Aguado in the United States
                    and in reply to local Opposition speculation growing from the trip, President
                    Somoza bluntly and emphatically made the following points: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>He never had pictures of Hitler and Mussolini in his office, as Dr.
                            Aguado has reportedly asserted in the United States.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>His relations with the notorious Nazi, Wilhelm von Brayman, were
                            exclusively of a commercial nature.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>He has fulfilled his promises of not seeking reelection and of giving
                            free elections “to the extent humanly possible”.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>“With respect to (retiring from) the Command of the Army, I have never
                            made any promise to anybody nor to the Department of State, for I could
                            not make such a promise as long as I was not asked, and the Department
                            of State has been very far from asking such a <pb facs="0864" n="848"
                                xml:id="pg_848"/> question, conduct which truly brings honor to that
                            Government, not asking of me what is a matter only for the future
                            government of Dr. Argüello”.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>“If (the United States) refused to intervene in the most important
                            question of electing a President, how much less would it be disposed to
                            intervene in the appointment of an official, which, as I have said
                            before, is a matter for the President of the Republic”.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Dr. Aguado has gotten nowhere in the United States and “I hope that
                            this defeat will teach Dr. Aguado a lesson and that he will return to
                            this country with more disposition to work for the prestige and
                            advancement of his native country”.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Fletcher Warren</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
