<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-07-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-07-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="867" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d867">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.23/7–947</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. James Espy of the
                                Division of North and West Coast Affairs</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-07-09">July 9, 1947</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Participants:</cell>
                                <cell>Dr. Enrique García Sayán, Minister of Foreign Affairs,
                                    Peru</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Señor Jorge Prado, Peruvian Ambassador to the U.S.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Señor Juan Chavez, former Peruvian Commercial Counselor</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Señor Carlos Alzamora, Peruvian Commercial Counselor</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Willard L. Thorp, Assistant Secretary</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Norman T. Ness, Director <gloss target="#t_OFD1">OFD</gloss>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. James H. Wright, Acting Director, <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>The Honorable Prentice Cooper, U.S. Ambassador to Peru</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. James Espy, <gloss target="#t_NWC1">NWC</gloss>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>A meeting was held this afternoon at 3:30 p.m. in Assistant Secretary
                            Thorp’s office for the purpose of discussing the economic and financial
                            problems of Peru which the Foreign Minister had indicated he desired to
                            take up with the Department.</p>
                        <p>The Minister presented briefly the present financial and economic <pb facs="1028" n="1012" xml:id="pg_1012"/> situation in Peru stressing
                            the current difficult foreign exchange position. In remedy he said Peru
                            was in need of loans from the U.S. He explained that what would be
                            particularly helpful would be dollar credits to help finance a number of
                            industries in the country.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Thorp asked the Minister what projects the Peruvian Government had in
                            mind. In reply the Minister said that he had not brought with him to the
                            meeting all the material that had been prepared on the subject but that
                            offhand he could mention such enterprises as irrigation, railroads,
                            petroleum and coal. He then went on to say that the Banco Industrial of
                            Peru had applications for loans aggregating an amount of some $30
                            million dollars which had been received from small enterprises in the
                            country. He inquired whether an open credit could be granted by the
                            Export-Import Bank to the Banco Industrial in approximately this amount
                            for re-loaning, by the latter Institution, to the enterprises.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Ness informed the Minister there would be no possibility of such a
                            credit from the Export-Import Bank for the reason that it was against
                            the Bank’s policy to make available such open credits. He explained that
                            the Bank only made loans for specific projects.</p>
                        <p>The discussion then turned to the $30 million dollar line of credit which
                            had been previously established for Peru by the Export-Import Bank but
                            which the Peruvian Government had been informed could not be drawn upon
                            until a satisfactory settlement had been made of the Peruvian Foreign
                            Debt in this country. The Minister asked whether this credit which had
                            lapsed as of December 31, 1946 could be re-established and used by Peru.
                            In reply he was informed that such was not feasible.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Thorp then said that the Department had consulted the Export-Import
                            Bank during the past few days and that it had been decided that the Bank
                            would now be prepared to give appropriate consideration, on their
                            economic merits, to applications for loans made by the Peruvian
                            Government. Mr. Thorp added that this was, of course, no assurance of
                            the granting of loans by the Export-Import Bank to Peru but that, in
                            effect, it lifted the previous ban and that Peru was to be considered as
                            one of the countries whose loan applications could now be presented to
                            the Bank. The Minister expressed his gratification on hearing this
                            announcement.</p>
                        <p>The question then arose whether some sort of formal communication should
                            be addressed to the Peruvian Government to this effect. It was suggested
                            that possibly the Export-Import Bank could send a letter to the Peruvian
                            Ambassador. Mr. Thorp and Mr. Ness expressed doubt as to the
                            appropriateness of such action but it was agreed <pb facs="1029" n="1013" xml:id="pg_1013"/> that the matter would be broached, later
                            in the day, to Mr. Martin<note n="26" xml:id="d867fn1">William McChesney
                                Martin, President of the Export-Import Bank.</note> of the Bank.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador Cooper then said that speaking on behalf of Peru he believed
                            the question of timing was of great importance. He pointed out that the
                            Peruvian Congress would meet on July 28th and that, naturally, the
                            Peruvian Government would want to go before it with something concrete
                            in the way of evidences of a financial character. This point was left
                            with the understanding that the door had now opened for the application
                            for credits by the Peruvian Government to the Export-Import Bank and
                            that the next step would be for the Peruvian Government, if it so
                            wished, to submit sound project applications.</p>
                        <p>Following the discussions on this subject, Mr. Thorp referred to the
                            recent import restrictions imposed by the Peruvian Government and
                            inquired whether the Peruvian Government proposed to initiate further
                            restrictions. Mr. Thorp explained that this question did not imply
                            criticism or representations in the matter but that we hoped, as
                            provided by the United States-Peruvian Trade Agreement, consultations
                            would first be held between the two Governments before any further
                            restrictions would be placed on imports from the U.S. The Minister said
                            that he could give no assurances that there would be no further
                            restrictions but upon his return to Peru, he would immediately get in
                            touch with the Ministers of Finance and National Economy and bring this
                            to their attention.</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>