<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Chargé in Peru (
                        Ackerman
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d875</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">875</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-05-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-05-02T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-05-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-05-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="875" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d875">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.2331/5–247</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Peru</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ackerman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                        <lb/> No. 1510</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lima</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-05-02">May 2,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report the promulgation of
                    Law No. 10880 dated April 1, 1947 (see clipping enclosed)<note n="48" xml:id="d875fn1">Not reprinted.</note> paragraphs (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>), (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>), (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) and (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) of Article I of which contain provision for taxation
                    of imported commodities when consumed in the Province of Jauja at rates in
                    excess of taxes applied to similar commodities of national origin. In the event
                    the higher charges were to be applied to goods of United States manufacture,
                    this would appear clearly to contravene Article II of our trade agreement with
                    Peru.</p>
                <p>This matter was discussed by the Commercial Attaché with the Minister of
                        Finance<note n="49" xml:id="d875fn2">Luis Echecopar Garcia.</note> on April
                    25. It was the Minister’s contention that although Law No. 10880 does not in
                    itself contain provision for any exceptions in the application of the taxes
                    under reference, the appropriate authorities of the Peruvian Government would
                    naturally take into account any agreements or treaties having the effect of law
                    and providing for exemption from internal charges at rates in excess of those
                    applicable to national products.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, the Minister agreed that for the purpose of avoiding possible
                    errors in the application of the law his Ministry would perceive no objection to
                    the issuance at the Embassy’s request of a letter <pb facs="1042" n="1026" xml:id="pg_1026"/> to the appropriate Peruvian Government authorities
                    calling to their attention the existence of Article II of the United
                    States-Peruvian trade agreement. There is accordingly enclosed a copy of the
                    Embassy’s communication of April 29<note n="50" xml:id="d875fn3">Not
                        printed.</note> on this subject to the Minister of Finance. A copy of the
                    Minister’s reply, when received, will be forwarded promptly to the
                    Department.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Chargé d’Affaires, <gloss target="#t_ai1">a. i.</gloss>
                    <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi> S. <hi rend="smallcaps">Campen</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Commercial Attaché</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
