<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul at Geneva ( (Gilbert) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d111</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">111</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-02-08T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-02-08T08:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recVCENpezMj2XgOU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions">Oil embargo</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-02-08T08:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-02-08T08:00:00-05:00" n="111"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d111">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">765.84/3658: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Geneva</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gilbert</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-02-08T14:00:00+01:00"
                            >February 8, 1936—2 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received February 8—10:40 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>58. Consulate’s 52, February 6, 10 a.m.</p>
                <p>1. The data thus far studied by the Petroleum Subcommittee indicates the
                    following: total annual requirement of Italy at present rate of consumption is
                    from two to two and a half million tons; Italian transport facilities will care
                    for 75 per cent of this requirement; substitutes are not an important factor, a
                    perfected economical product being a matter for the future; equivalent stocks in
                    Italy and Italian colonies total 500,000 tons which is regarded as limit of
                    present storage facilities including ships in ports.</p>
                <p>Consulate’s 54, February 6, 8 p.m.</p>
                <p>2. The relative size of stocks in Italy in proportion to purchases in Rumania is
                    regarded as indicating large quantities of “Italian oil” at present in
                    Rumania.</p>
                <p>3. I am informed of the foregoing through Gomez, the Mexican Chairman of the
                    Subcommittee.</p>
                <p>Respecting the position of the United States in this matter he felt that the
                    Latin-American delegates who were so concerned over the question did not take
                    into sufficient account the factor of stocks in storage now in the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>4. The Mexican representative has been most active in advocating the adoption and
                    application of an oil embargo against Italy. He now states that he was urged to
                    this course by the British who also suggested his chairmanship of the
                    subcommittee. He says that the British took the same line with other
                    Latin-American states both here <pb facs="0174" n="109" xml:id="pg_109"/> and
                    through diplomatic channels as suggested in paragraph 2 of my telegram No. 54.
                    The attitude now adopted here by the British that the figures indicate that a
                    petroleum embargo is not practicable is causing him extreme annoyance declaring
                    that he has been “let down”.</p>
                <p>A number of Latin-American delegates have for some time been intimating to me
                    that the British were urging them that they should support the League in the
                    cause of peace their remarks carrying more or less the implication that the
                    United States was outside the peace circle. The British were taking the
                    opportunity, according to these Latin Americans, to weaken the new relationship
                    which we have built up in Latin America. I naturally discount such views knowing
                    the great extent to which they are influenced by the tendency here for Latin
                    Americans to assume a role beyond their instructions and the personal equations
                    which enter the picture; the possibilities discussed in paragraph 1 of my
                    telegram last referred to precipitated, however, the excited state of mind here
                    which I reported.</p>
                <p>5. The press has for some days been drawing inferences deduced from leaks in the
                    studies of the Petroleum Subcommittee respecting the positions of various
                    states, both League and non-League as nullifying any embargo measure. This has
                    evoked repercussions in various capitals and the Committee is now endeavoring to
                    keep their deliberations more secret and in particular is eliminating substance
                    from its communiqués.</p>
                <p>6. As having something to do with the situation just described the present
                    program is that the report of the Subcommittee will be transmitted privately to
                    the governments for their consideration before any further action is taken. This
                    is viewed as confirming that a meeting of the Committee of Eighteen will
                    probably not take place until March as reported in the final paragraph of my No.
                    52.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gilbert</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
