<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul at Geneva ( (Gilbert) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d123</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">123</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-04-08T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-04-08T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recXuFW8WO1tqBrVK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-04-08T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-04-08T06:00:00-05:00" n="123"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">765.84/4051: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Geneva</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gilbert</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-04-08T12:00:00+01:00"
                            >April 8, 1936—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received April 8—11:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>101. Latin American representatives inform me in confidence as follows: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The Ecuadorean Government has presented a note to the Italian
                            Government, a copy of which it is understood will be officially
                            transmitted to Secretary General, to the effect that Ecuador’s position
                            is that in view of Italy’s offer of conciliation (Consulate’s 81, March
                            9, 9 a.m.) sanctions against Italy should be immediately lifted. This is
                            construed in Latin American circles here as meaning at the least that
                            Ecuador in fact is canceling such sanction measures as she has adopted
                            against Italy.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The Mexican Government is understood to be addressing a communication
                            to Vasconcellos<note n="9" xml:id="d123fn9">Augusto Vasconcellos,
                                Portuguese delegate to the League and Chairman of the Committee on
                                Coordination.</note> urging a reenforcement of sanctions against
                            Italy. I am told that the implications lying back of this Mexican
                            position are that if the League fails to pursue a policy of sanctions
                            against an aggressor Mexico will consider her membership in the League
                            without value and may take a public position to this effect.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The Chilean Government is believed to be preparing to express a
                            position in some form in the presumably immediate future that the
                            constitution or the procedures of the League must be shortly revised so
                            as to exclude the participation of Latin American League members in
                            non-American questions and of non-American League members in American
                            questions and that failing such action Chile will consider withdrawing
                            from active participation in the League.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The foregoing is derived from entirely reliable sources and I believe
                            that it represents at least tentative developments along the lines
                            indicated. While certain of these matters will I believe shortly come
                            into the open I must regard them all at this moment as
                            confidential.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>I understand that the Italian representative here has called on a
                            number of Latin American delegations among them the Argentine suggesting
                            that the Latin American League states adopt a common front in Geneva
                            advocating the lifting of sanctions against Italy. The Argentines made
                            no reply to this Italian <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi>. They inform me
                            that they are acting under their standing instructions respecting
                            sanctions which I have previously reported to the Department and that on
                            their more general relationship to the League their position remains
                            that of supporting the Covenant in line with their obligations <pb
                                facs="0183" n="118" xml:id="pg_118"/> while at the same time they
                            are enjoined by Buenos Aires strictly to avoid taking a partisan
                            position in European political contentions.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>These developments are creating a violent stir among such Latin
                            American representatives here as are aware of them and thus in my
                            estimate of them I allow for probable exaggeration. I learn however that
                            the more important of the delegations including Argentina have urgently
                            requested instructions from their governments. The private conversations
                            among the Latin Americans take particular note of the positions adopted
                            by the Latin American Council powers at the recent Council sessions in
                            London of which the Department is doubtless cognizant which have been
                            felt here as probably foreshadowing an issue on some basis between the
                            Latin American states and the League. I have reported what I could learn
                            of the background of these London developments in my No. 1650,
                                political,<note n="11" xml:id="d123fn11">Not printed.</note> mailed
                            today.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gilbert</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
