<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-02-14T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-02-14T07:00:00-05:00" n="186" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d186">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">765.84/3717: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Italy</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Long</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-02-14T13:00:00+01:00">February 14, 1936—1
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received February 14—10:13 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>54. My 843, November 18, noon, paragraph 3.<note n="19" xml:id="d186fn19"><ref target="frus1935v01#pg_820"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1935, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 820</ref>.</note> From a
                                well-informed confidential unofficial source I learn that the
                                Italian Government is undertaking to transfer from France, England,
                                Switzerland and other countries in Europe to the United States money
                                and securities which were appropriated by the Italian Government
                                from its citizens. I am informed a small part is also being sent to
                                the Argentine. The movement is alleged to be for the purpose of
                                removing the physical control of the securities from the
                                jurisdiction of sanctionist countries. Furthermore, there is no need
                                in those countries of balances for trade purposes which precludes
                                the idea of selling them there to establish credits.</p>
                            <p>As approximately 70 per cent of these securities owned abroad were
                                physically within the United States at the time of appropriation,
                                and I am recently informed that very few of these securities have
                                been liquidated, I invite your attention to the large increase in
                                the market <pb facs="0254" n="189" xml:id="pg_189"/> value of the
                                American securities listed on the New York Exchange. I still feel as
                                expressed in my telegram under reference that some attention should
                                be given to the possibility of their being dumped on the market in
                                case the market should break but not for retaliatory reasons. Some
                                months ago there was an alleged agreement between the Governments of
                                France and Italy to the end that Italy would not dump on the French
                                market French Government bonds but that liquidation if needed would
                                take place gradually so as not to disturb the market. We have not
                                been able to verify this agreement with France but we have sound
                                reason to believe it is correct. I call it to your attention for
                                possible guidance but I cannot recommend that we be supplicants to
                                that extent.</p>
                            <p>However, there is the real danger that the Italian Government would
                                attempt to dispose of its securities at the highest price obtainable
                                if the market gave the appearance of breaking. And in addition to
                                the potential danger which existed as of the time of my telegram
                                under reference which contemplated only 70 per cent of Italian
                                holdings abroad there is now the danger involved in the increased
                                amount which will run probably as high as 90 per cent in the United
                                States of securities held abroad by the Italian Government and all
                                valued at a higher level.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Long</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>