<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far Eastern Affairs (
                    (Hornbeck))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d196</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">196</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-05-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-05-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="196"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d196">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.00111 Armament Control/888</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far Eastern
                        Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-05-18">May 18,
                            1936</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>In the light of developments of last week, and especially of information given in
                    telegrams from Engert and Kirk and Gilbert<note n="45" xml:id="d196fn45"
                        >Prentiss B. Gilbert, Consul at Geneva.</note> over the week-end, it is
                    believed that this Government should persevere in its attitude of “watchful
                    waiting” and should continue to take no action toward proclaiming, as for this
                    country, that the “state of war” between Italy and Ethiopia is at an end.</p>
                <p>Unquestionably the course pursued by this country, as indicated in and followed
                    under the so-called “neutrality” acts, has made more difficult for the countries
                    members of the League the effort which they have made, under the Covenant, in
                    their handling of the Italy-Ethiopia question. The merits of our attitude and
                    course of action from point of view of interests other than those of this
                    country need not in this connection be discussed. The fact that a number of
                    countries are doing what they can to make the collective system a reality and
                    that this country does not see fit to participate in that effort needs, however,
                    always to be kept in mind. Accepting the fact that we will not participate,
                    there still remains as a practical question for us this question: May not and
                    should not this Government be liberally and sympathetically disposed toward the
                    efforts of those who seek to make the collective system effective to deal with
                    the questions which are of more immediate and direct concern to them than to us;
                    should we not refrain wherever possible from taking action not urgently needing
                    to be taken by us, which action, if taken, will make more difficult the efforts
                    of the others?</p>
                <p>In considering the question of any proposal for action by us in reference to the
                    Ethiopia situation, ought we not ask ourselves both of two questions, (1) what
                    real advantage will that action, if taken, be to us; and (2) will that action,
                    if taken, be to the advantage or to the disadvantage of efforts which are being
                    made by other nations in connection with problems in regard to which we have
                    along with them a common interest (such as the problems of peace, of respect for
                    treaties, etc.)?</p>
                <p>With regard to the question of our possibly proclaiming the “war” at an end and
                    lifting our embargoes,—would this action, if taken at this moment, be of any
                    real advantage to us? Is our trade or are our interests in general with Italy
                    and/or Ethiopia now suffering losses or impairment because of continuance in
                    existence of the embargoes? <pb facs="0263" n="198" xml:id="pg_198"/> Insofar as
                    export trade in arms is concerned, would our trade be measurably increased if
                    the embargo were lifted; and, are we eagerly solicitous for increase in that
                    trade? In the matter of travel, and in that of their business and their
                    relations in general with Italy, are our nationals now suffering any substantial
                    inconvenience or losses or hardship in consequence of the continuance in
                    existence of the embargo?</p>
                <p>Would not any action in this connection by us at this time add to the confusion
                    which exists at Geneva and make more difficult the effort which the British
                    Government is making on behalf of the principle of peace and toward preventing
                    new eruptions in Europe?</p>
                <p>Insofar as public opinion in this country is concerned, is there any extensive or
                    highly influential demand that the Government lift the embargoes? Is there not a
                    latent interest in the efforts of the League and of the British Government,
                    which, if action were taken by this Government tending to contribute toward
                    further frustration of those efforts, would elicit an outburst of adverse
                    criticism?</p>
                <p>It is believed that it would be advisable for this Government to continue to
                    “proceed slowly” in regard to this whole question.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">tanley</hi>] K. H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ornbeck</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
