<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-06-05T01:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-06-05T01:00:00-05:00" n="204" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d204">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">765.84/4600: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister Resident in Ethiopia</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Engert</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Addis
                                            Ababa</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-06-05T09:00:00+03:00">June 5, 1936—9
                                    a.m.</date><lb/>[Received June 7—6:30 p.m.<note n="54" xml:id="d204fn54">Telegram in two
                                    sections.</note>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>395. Department’s 266, June 4. There is really very little to add to
                                my telegrams in the latter part of May as the situation has remained
                                practically unchanged. But I should like to correct certain
                                erroneous statements in telegrams the Department has been good
                                enough to repeat to me.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Department’s 242, May 20.<note n="55" xml:id="d204fn55">See
                                        footnote 49, <ref target="#pg_200">p. 200</ref>.</note> It
                                    is untrue that Italian airmen are maintaining surveillance
                                    “throughout the entire country”. They may do so in the north and
                                    southeast but no attempt at surveillance has so far been made in
                                    the south and southwest.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Department’s 265, June 4.<note n="56" xml:id="d204fn56">See
                                        footnote 53, <ref target="#pg_204">p. 204</ref>.</note> …
                                    Italian forces cannot yet be said to be “in complete control”
                                    anywhere south of the ninth parallel and west of the fortieth
                                    meridian except along the railway. There seems to be no Italian
                                    troops south of the Blue Nile and the westernmost point in
                                    central Ethiopia so far occupied is Ambo about 55 miles from
                                    Addis Ababa. To say that contact with the inhabitants is
                                    maintained “almost entirely by civil officials” is entirely
                                    untrue even in Addis Ababa although it may be applicable to the
                                    extreme north.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>No attempt has been made by the Italians to penetrate into the
                                    vast areas comprising such provinces as Jimma, Wollega, Kaffa,
                                    Bakema, Walamo, Sidamo, Arussi. For example, there are eight
                                    Europeans on the ninety-fourth [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>]
                                    coffee plantations in Arussi who sent message to the Belgian
                                    Minister here that their homes had been sacked and they were in
                                    danger of their lives. Although they are <pb facs="0271" n="206" xml:id="pg_206"/> only 14 hours by road from Arba railway
                                    station, the Italians have so far been unable to send any forces
                                    for their evacuation.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Similarly my repeated inquiries concerning welfare of
                                    Americans in the south and southwest have always received the
                                    reply that the Italian authorities have no information whatever
                                    regarding the situation in those provinces and were not yet
                                    prepared to send any troops there. When I suggested patrolling
                                    by planes I was told it was too risky because of impossibility
                                    of landing in an emergency.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Ras Seyum the Italians claim to have captured; also Dejazmatch
                                    Wandwossen, Ras Kassa’s eldest son. Ras Imru still has a force
                                    somewhere west of Ambo and Ras Desta is believed to be in
                                    Sidamo. In Lekempti, the province due west of Addis Ababa,
                                    Dejazmatch Gabre Mariam, a Galla who is the hereditary ruler
                                    there, has set up a government of his own and is reported to
                                    keep good order. Jimma, which like Lekempti is a Galla province,
                                    is being held by Kantiba Tanna an ex-mayor of Addis Ababa. He
                                    too is said to have the situation fairly well in hand. In
                                    Wallega a certain Fitoraori Johannes, another Galla and son of a
                                    former chief there, appears to have assumed control but with
                                    what success is unknown here.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>The Italians themselves admit that the disarming of the
                                    natives has been very slow and unsatisfactory. For example,
                                    Badoglio told me that in Addis Ababa only 400 rifles had been
                                    collected which is a ludicrous figure considering that nearly
                                    every Abyssinian habitually carried a rifle of some sort. In the
                                    provinces the proportion is doubtless even smaller and convoys
                                    between here and Dessie continue to be attacked.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>The above is not intended to convey the impression that
                                    properly constituted political entities exist which govern
                                    portions of the country in the name of the Emperor or that any
                                    large organized forces are in the field even in those areas
                                    where no Italian soldiers have so far been seen. I merely wish
                                    to point out that certain obvious difficulties are only just
                                    beginning for the Italians and that even if they are left in
                                    undisturbed possession by the other powers it may be 6 months or
                                    more before the whole country can be properly garrisoned.</item>
                            </list>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Engert</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>