<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister Resident in Ethiopia ( (Engert) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d332</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">332</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-05-06T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-05-06T03:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-05-06T03:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-05-06T03:00:00-05:00" n="332"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d332">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">765.84/4301: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister Resident in Ethiopia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Engert</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Addis Ababa</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-05-06T11:00:00+03:00"
                            >May 6, 1936—11 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 2:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>298. Have just received call from member of Marshal Badoglio’s staff who handed
                    me a <hi rend="italic">note verbale</hi> in Italian dated today of which
                    substance is as follows:</p>
                <p>High Commissioner and Commander in Chief has in name of King of Italy assumed all
                    military and civil powers and has appointed a military and a civil government
                    for the city of Addis Ababa which, under his orders, will be governed in
                    accordance with the laws and military ordinances of Italy.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“Based on these laws and ordinances and pending further disposition regarding
                        the cessation of hostilities and the new status of the country the Chief of
                        Mission and the members of the Legation of the United States of America will
                        enjoy the prerogatives accorded to them for the representation of the
                        interests of the countries represented by them and for the protection of
                        their respective nations [<hi rend="italic">subjects</hi>]”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>(Italian text of above paragraph reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“In base a tali leggi ed a tali ordinamenti fino alle future
                            determinazione relativo al cessazione delle ostilita ed al nuevo
                            assestamento del paese il capo missione ed i membri della legazione
                            degli S. U. d’America godranno delle prerogative loro riconosciute per
                            la rappresentazione degli interessi dei paesi da essi rappresentati e
                            per la tutela dei respettivi loro sudditi.”)</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Note then states that for these purposes they may address themselves to cabinet
                    of High Commissioner who will insure protection of persons of Chief of Mission
                    and members of American Legation and persons in their service as well as
                    personal or real property belonging to them.</p>
                <p>High Commissioner requests American Legation observe laws and military ordinances
                    of Italy and hopes it will assist in maintaining good relations between High
                    Commissioner and Legation.</p>
                <p>Any official relations between the Legation and authorities other than Italian,
                    or acts contrary to laws and ordinances published by High Commissioner, will not
                    be recognized by the latter.</p>
                <p>High Commissioner hopes that Legations realizing special circumstances and
                    necessity of assuring, in the interests of the public, order discipline and
                    justice, will also in their own interest and that of the occupied country lend
                    cooperation for which High Commissioner would be grateful.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Engert</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
