<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Italy (
                    (Phillips))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d394</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">394</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-12-10T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-12-10T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-12-10T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-12-10T20:00:00-05:00" n="394"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d394">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">365D.1163/13: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in Italy</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phillips</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-12-10T20:00:00-05:00"
                            >December 10, 1936—8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>178. By unpublished decree dated November 27 Italian authorities requisitioned
                    entire property of the Sudan Interior Mission including all buildings,
                    residences of staff and mission headquarters at Akaki and Furi near Addis Ababa,
                    together with entire contents except personal belongings of missionaries. Decree
                    provided for a commission <pb facs="0391" n="326" xml:id="pg_326"/> to make list
                    of properties and in consultation with mission to estimate a fair value. Copy of
                    decree was handed mission only on December 2. Italian authorities refused
                    request of mission for postponement of action to permit consultation with
                    mission headquarters and apparently Italian commission is to proceed with
                    appraisal of properties without cooperation of missionaries.</p>
                <p>Sudan Interior Mission appears to be partly American and partly Canadian and
                    British. The Department is now endeavoring to ascertain the extent of the
                    American interest. Meanwhile Engert has been instructed to avoid taking any
                    position which will raise question as to status or recognition of Italian
                    Government in Ethiopia and to confine his efforts to having American interests
                    given ample opportunity to present evidence of value of property and to prevent
                    any undue delay in payment of compensation.</p>
                <p>Engert reports it would be helpful if postponement of requisition proceedings
                    could be suggested at Rome. He has made a similar request of Graziani who
                    probably referred question to Ministry of Colonies.</p>
                <p>Unless you perceive some objection please take this matter up with appropriate
                    authorities and, after pointing out the haste with which the requisition was
                    made, request postponement of proceedings so that American interests involved
                    may have sufficient opportunity to give consideration to a matter of importance
                    to them.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Moore</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
