<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in Iran ( (Hornibrook))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d430</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">430</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-01-07T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-01-07T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recqhvaPBazS2SPQl" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051711"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Freedom of the press</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-01-07T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-01-07T19:00:00-05:00" n="430"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d430">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">701.9111/469: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in Iran</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hornibrook</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-01-07T19:00:00-05:00"
                            >January 7, 1936—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1. Your 2, January 7, 11 a.m. Full details and documents regarding Djalal’s
                    arrest and subsequent action by this Government were transmitted in Department’s
                    instruction No. 167 of December 12 forwarded via Cairo and Baghdad pouch on
                    Steamship <hi rend="italic">Excalibur</hi> due at Alexandria Janury 9. Pouch
                    should reach Baghdad within the next few days and presumably will be forwarded
                    via British courier.</p>
                <p>In case the Iranian Government approaches you officially in the matter before you
                    are in possession of full details, you should explain that fact. You should
                    however state that as soon as this Government was informed of the incident the
                    Secretary of State expressed his personal regrets to the Minister and urged the
                    Governor of Maryland <pb facs="0412" n="347" xml:id="pg_347"/> to take immediate
                    steps to bring about the dismissal and punishment of the offending police
                    officers. This action was taken without delay. In a letter received at the same
                    time from the Governor he requested the Secretary to convey to the Iranian
                    Minister an expression of his sincere apologies. In communicating these
                    sentiments to the Minister the Secretary added his formal regrets on behalf of
                    this Government.</p>
                <p>The Department considers that the amends made for this unfortunate occurrence
                    were adequate in every respect and that they in fact exceed the action that
                    might have been considered necessary under the circumstances.</p>
                <p>In view of the fact that the Minister has been instructed to state that his
                    Government considers the incident closed, the Department approves of your having
                    ignored the press tirade on this subject and wishes you to continue to assume an
                    attitude of reserve unless the Iranian Government takes the matter up with you
                    officially.</p>
                <p>With reference to this Government “obtaining public retraction from certain
                    American newpapers” you should of course, if the need arises, point out that
                    freedom of the press is guaranteed in this country by the Constitution.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
