<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-05-09T08:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-05-09T08:35:00-05:00" n="450" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d450">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">701.9111/552: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Iran</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Merriam</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Teheran</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-05-09T17:00:00+03:25">May 9, 1936—5
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received May 10—6 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>33. On May 6 I called on Soheily since previous discussions regarding
                            special mission had been with him. I left two <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoires</hi> the drafting of which was extremely delicate,
                            one containing merely the substance of the Department’s No. 22 April 30,
                            7 p.m., the other adding a quotation of the pertinent portion of the
                            Constitution, explaining that it had been in force for nearly 150 years,
                            the indispensable role played by a free press under our system, the
                            procedure of amendment and that an amendment restricting freedom of the
                            press was not a practical possibility. It went on to describe
                            Department’s hard work in securing correction as evidence both of its
                            good will and as further proof that our Government had no control over
                            the press adding that its action could not be considered a precedent.
                            Both documents asked him to bring contents to the attention of his
                            Minister. I explained that the first covered my instructions but that I
                            would leave the second, if he thought it preferable, for presentation to
                            higher authority.</p>
                        <p>Soheily was deeply disappointed that the mission would not be sent and
                            vented his feeling on Kazemi whose suggestion to Hornibrook he thought
                            was an unwarranted interference in the internal affairs <pb facs="0427" n="362" xml:id="pg_362"/> of another country. He himself would have
                            refused to discuss such a request had it been made of him and for this
                            reason he believed there must have been a misunderstanding. He asked
                            whether this consideration was the real reason for the Department’s
                            decision or a pretext.</p>
                        <p>I replied that I did not think the Department had been particularly
                            disturbed by that phase of it. I thought the Department argued that if
                            Kazemi who had some years in the United States knew so little of our
                            Government and institutions, it would be a hopeless task for a special
                            envoy, who would be regarded as a special pleader, to convince the
                            Iranian Government of the facts. As to a pretext I said the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> contained the sole reason given by
                            the Department for rejecting the idea of a special mission and it was
                            impossible to say whether, independently of Kazemi’s remark, the
                            Department would have arrived at the same decision or not.</p>
                        <p>The Under Secretary was extremely loath to accept any <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> on the ground that the suggestion had come from
                            us and not from the Iranian Foreign Office. On my explaining that I was
                            carrying out instructions and that I thought the Secretary wished to
                            show that he had given the idea of a special mission serious and careful
                            consideration and desired a written record of the fact in the Iranian
                            archives he consented to keep them for further study. He seemed
                            painfully afraid that the rejection of the idea of a mission might be
                            thought a rebuff to Iran and I had to emphasize that it was solely the
                            Legation’s idea that was being turned down and that the <hi rend="italic">aide-Mémoire</hi> so stated.</p>
                        <p>He asked to see the interpreter this afternoon and returned both
                            documents saying that the Foreign Minister agreed that as the special
                            envoy had not been solicited by Iran there was no occasion to have
                            anything in writing. He said he had found a note of Kazemi that the
                            United States Government should take steps to protect foreign sovereigns
                            from the press and he felt sure Kazemi had gone no further than that. He
                            seemed very discouraged that the idea of the mission had been
                            rejected.</p>
                        <p>In my opinion the plan was attractive to the Foreign Office, which has
                            not been in the good graces of the Shah recently, because it could say
                            to His Majesty that it had arranged for a great power like ourselves to
                            go to this length to request the restoration of Iranian representation.
                            The Foreign Office would therefore tend to encourage the sending of a
                            mission whatever the chances of success. Nevertheless I believe Soheily
                            is sincere in expressing the informal opinion that a special mission
                            offers the best method of righting the present situation.</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>I believe it would be both wise and useful to explain the Department’s
                            rejection of a special mission on the basis of a partial
                            misunderstanding <pb facs="0428" n="363" xml:id="pg_363"/> of Kazemi’s
                            suggestion and to keep the question open with the idea that an envoy
                            will be sent if and when we have reasonable assurance that he can
                            succeed.</p>
                        <p>Copies of <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoires</hi> are being forwarded.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Merriam</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>