<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-05-06T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-05-06T12:00:00-05:00" n="76" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d76">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">765.84/4300: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Italy</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-05-06T18:00:00+01:00">May 6, 1936—6
                                    p.m.</date><lb/>[Received May 6—2:05 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>133. Foreign Office officials inform me that order has been
                                established in Addis Ababa and that all measures for the protection
                                of foreigners have been taken. They state that the details of the
                                provisional administration of the recently occupied territory have
                                not yet been determined but it is understood that all military
                                powers are vested in Badoglio and that Bottai, Governor of Rome, who
                                is with the Italian forces, has been named a frontier governor to
                                administer the city of Addis Ababa.</p>
                            <p>In the course of conversations with Foreign Office officials the
                                information was volunteered that although the chiefs of mission at
                                Addis Ababa could not be recognized as accredited representatives
                                they and the members of their legations would be given diplomatic
                                privileges as a matter of courtesy and such facilities as are usual
                                in the case of a military occupation. The officials added that as a
                                matter of practice the diplomatic representatives there would have
                                the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> status of consuls and that the
                                situation was simplified by the fact that many of the diplomatic
                                officers in Addis Ababa had consular rank also.</p>
                            <p>Repeated nowhere.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Kirk</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>