<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by the Counselor of the Department of State
                        (
                        Bohlen
                    ) to the Under Secretary of State (
                        Lovett
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d108</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">108</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-10-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-10-27T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-10-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-10-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="108" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d108">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.<gloss target="#t_BC1">BC</gloss>/10–2747</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Counselor of the Department of State</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bohlen</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lovett</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-10-27">October 27,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lovett</hi>: I find here particularly in Washington and
                    even in the Department considerable lack of understanding of the situation with
                    regard to the election in the Security Council and the Ukrainian and Indian
                    deadlock.</p>
                <p>The whole criticism that has appeared publicly and even the doubts expressed in
                    the Department appear to be based on a number of complete <pb facs="0193" n="163" xml:id="pg_163"/> misconceptions. In New York, I was unfortunately
                    absent when the first deadlock occurred and general distorted versions as to our
                    position and the causes of the deadlock were spread in the papers. The following
                    are the misconceptions:</p>
                <p>First, that the United States is blocking the election of the Ukraine. This is
                    completely untrue. The United States has not campaigned against the Ukraine in
                    the slightest degree. The countries, namely, the Latin Americans, on which the
                    United States would have maximum influence are with possibly three or four
                    exceptions voting solidly for the Ukraine. Of the 25 votes received by India,
                    according to our information all but two or three are voting their conviction
                    and preference for India. These votes are composed of the British Commonwealth,
                    5; the Arab States, 7; the other Mohammedan countries—Turkey, Iran and Pakistan,
                    3; three Far Eastern countries, China, Siam and the Philippines. Thus, had the
                    United States initially voted for the Ukraine, the Ukraine would not be elected
                    and it is very doubtful that should we switch our vote to the Ukraine that she
                    would be elected.</p>
                <p>It might also be pointed out that two of the permanent members of the Security
                    Council, Great Britain and China, are voting against the Ukraine and for India.
                    It is therefore surprising in the circumstances that the United States should be
                    tagged as responsible for the deadlock or working against the Ukraine. The real
                    cause of the deadlock is a deal made behind our backs by the Latin American
                    countries with the Soviet Union—in my opinion an added reason, in addition to
                    those of substance, why the United States should not support the Ukraine whose
                    only chance of election is based on the kind of deal of which we generally
                    disapprove.</p>
                <p>The second false assumption is that in voting to admit the Ukraine and White
                    Russia we were confirming their status as “independent states”. This again is
                    not true since at the time of the adoption of the Charter two other nations not
                    enjoying independence, namely, India and the Philippines, were entered as
                    regular members. There is nothing in the Charter which says that membership is
                    the equivalent of a recognition of full independence. Article 23 of the Charter
                    lays down specific qualifications for membership on the Security Council of
                    which the geographic principle is the <hi rend="italic">secondary</hi>.<note n="1" xml:id="d108fn1">Mr. Bohlen attached the text of this article, not
                        printed.</note> Language in Article 23 was the subject of much debate in San
                    Francisco and an amendment that membership alone in the United Nations was the
                    sole qualification for membership in the Security Council was overwhelmingly
                    voted down in the Commission.</p>
                <p>The Ukraine is by the constitution of the USSR bound by the decisions of the
                    central government, and thus to vote for the Ukraine would be to support one
                    nation having by its own constitution two <pb facs="0194" n="164" xml:id="pg_164"/> votes in the Security Council. This is quite a different
                    principle from the practical question that any eastern European state would vote
                    along with Russia. I fully agree that this issue has been magnified far out of
                    its proportion, but I do not think the impression should be allowed to circulate
                    in Washington that this was caused by the United States. It was caused by some
                    twenty nations voting their conviction on India and the majority of the Latin
                    American countries for voting for the Ukraine because of a deal they made with
                    the Soviet Delegation.</p>
                <p>I am giving you this spiel simply because I think at least if we are going to be
                    criticized for our position, it should not be on a thoroughly false basis. In
                    fact our position is: (1) we do not question the eligibility of the Ukraine; (2)
                    having voted in the first instance in accordance with the geographic principle
                    for Czechoslovakia, we then voted our preference for India over the Ukraine
                    whose qualifications under Article 23 we doubted.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles E. Bohlen</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
