<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-10-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="128" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d128">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">
                            <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Files: US/A/C.1/401</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Eric Stein of the United States
                                Delegation Staff of Advisers</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                        York</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-10-21">October 21, 1947</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                                <cell>Mr. Dulles</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Rusk</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Miss Fosdick</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Marcy</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Notter</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Popper</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Stein</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Taylor</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Thompson</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Wainhouse</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum of Meeting Held on October</hi> 20 <hi rend="smallcaps">on the Interim Committee</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Mr. Dulles asked whether the proposed Interim Committee was contemplated
                            as a technical study group or whether it should function for the purpose
                            of crystallizing world opinion through discussion like the <pb facs="0243" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/> General Assembly itself. If
                            the second alternative is adopted, he anticipated objections both from
                            legal and policy standpoint. The political objections arise primarily
                            out of fear that the discussions in the Committee will accentuate the
                            U.S.-U.S.S.R. conflict and perpetuate the wrangling and name-calling. He
                            suggested a test which the Interim Committee might follow in selecting
                            matters for its agenda: The Committee should consider only major matters
                            with which the General Assembly could not adequately deal without prior
                            preparation through study and investigation, such as the Korean and
                            Palestinian question.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Dulles said that the Committee’s decision whether it should take up a
                            matter should be made by a simple majority since a requirement of a
                            two-thirds majority might lead to the formation of a bloc within the
                            Committee which could exercise a type of a veto; however, if there is a
                            strong pressure for a two-thirds majority requirement, Mr. Dulles was
                            inclined not to make it a fighting issue.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Dulles also pointed to the opposition among our friends to the
                            jurisdiction of the Committee under Articles 11(1) and 13(1<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) and raised the question whether and to what
                            extent we should be ready to abandon this function of the Committee. Mr.
                            Wainhouse suggested that we should do all in our power to retain the
                            jurisdiction both under Articles 11(1) and 13(1<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                            and, if pressed, we might abandon the reference to Article 13(1<hi rend="italic">a</hi>). Mr. Dulles then inquired what specific
                            studies are envisaged under the two provisions. Mr. Rusk mentioned the
                            possible activities of the Comintern, and Mr. Notter referred to Soviet
                            pressure on Turkey and certain forms of Soviet economic penetration in
                            the Balkans. He also mentioned that in the exercise of its jurisdiction
                            in this field, the Committee could evolve more detailed principles with
                            a view to improving the techniques for pacific settlement of disputes
                            through the means indicated in Article 33(1). Mr. Dulles mentioned also
                            the development of the provisions of Article 36(3), and indirect
                            aggression. Mr. Stein recalled that Sir Hartley referred in this
                            connection to indirect aggression, “general principles governing the
                            summoning of international conferences” and the principles of
                            nonintervention. Mr. Dulles thought that at least some of these topics
                            might fall in the field of development of international law. Some
                            discussion ensued as to which of these topics could be dealt with under
                            other Articles within the proposed jurisdiction of the Committee. Mr.
                            Notter emphasized that if we should agree to dropping the study
                            functions of the Committee, it could be argued that its character as a
                            competitor of the Security Council would become more pronounced. Mr.
                            Dulles suggested that the Interim Committee could be entrusted with the
                            task to prepare a working plan for the studies under Articles 11(1) and
                                13(1<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) rather than to undertake the studies
                            themselves. Mr. Rusk agreed with this suggestion and said that an
                            appropriate <pb facs="0244" n="214" xml:id="pg_214"/> provision could be
                            added to the clause requiring the Committee to report on the
                            desirability of the establishment of a permanent Interim Committee.</p>
                        <p>It was agreed that we will oppose the Canadian proposal to extend the
                            Committee’s preparatory functions to items other than those relating to
                            international peace and friendly relations. Mr. Rusk emphasized that one
                            of the dangers of such extension would be that the Committee might turn
                            into a permanent organ investigating the activities of the
                            Secretary-General and other organs of the United Nations. However, we
                            might accept the Canadian suggestion that the Committee should consider
                            and report to the General Assembly on the implementation of resolutions
                            referred to it by the General Assembly. Mr. Dulles suggested that this
                            provision could be spelled out in paragraph 2(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)
                            of the United States resolution although this paragraph in its present
                            form appears to cover the Canadian suggestion.</p>
                        <p>Referring to the United Kingdom draft resolution, Mr. Wainhouse said that
                            this resolution fails to provide for recommendations or for reports by
                            the Committee to the General Assembly in connection with the Committee’s
                            preparatory function. It was agreed that the Committee must be given
                            express authority to “report” or make “proposals” to the General
                            Assembly; however, we will not insist on the use of the word
                            “recommendations”.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Eric Stein</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>