<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-10-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-10-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="129" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d129">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">
                            <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Files: US/A/C.1/481</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">Elwood N.
                                    Thompson</persName> of the United States Delegation Staff of
                                Advisers to <gloss type="to">All Political Officers</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                        York</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-10-30">October 30, 1947</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>It is suggested that conversations with other delegations concerning the
                            United States position on the “veto” should begin at once. In these
                            conversations you may find useful the general guide lines set forth
                            below.</p>
                        <p>The United States believes that liberalization of the voting procedure
                            would make the Security Council more effective. As stated by the
                            Secretary in his opening speech to the General Assembly, the abuse of
                            the veto in the Security Council has made such liberalization essential.
                            Therefore, the United States would be willing to agree to the
                            elimination by whatever means may be appropriate of the veto under
                            Chapter VI of the Charter (pacific settlement), and in voting on
                            applications for membership. The United States however is opposed to any
                            alteration of the veto under Chapter VII, or in the process of amending
                            the Charter. Concerning other decisions to which the veto may now be <pb facs="0245" n="215" xml:id="pg_215"/> applicable, the United States
                            will indicate its position as occasion may require in the course of the
                            study proposed below.</p>
                        <p>As to the means of securing liberalization of the voting procedure, the
                            United States wishes to go as far as possible through the development of
                            practices and procedures in the Security Council agreed to by all its
                            members.</p>
                        <p>However we recognize that such changes will probably not go far enough to
                            solve the problem. It will be necessary for the General Assembly to
                            study what can be accomplished through Charter interpretation and by
                            changes that may require Charter amendment. The issues arising out of
                            substantial changes in the voting procedure of the Security Council are
                            so complex and so important to the future of the United Nations, and
                            there is such a divergence among the members, that a year’s study is
                            essential prior to decisions on the issues involved. Moreover the United
                            States hopes that the General Assembly study will stimulate the efforts
                            of the Security Council itself to improve its voting practices.</p>
                        <p>Our position on the veto in this Assembly constitutes an important step
                            forward in the direction of liberalizing the veto from the basic
                            position which we took last year. Last year we were unwilling to support
                            steps looking toward the amendment of the Charter although we expressed
                            hope that in the future the permanent members might agree among
                            themselves and with other members to modify the veto under Chapter VI.
                            This year, the United States continues to stand by its conviction
                            concerning the necessity of agreement among the major powers in taking
                            decisions under Chapter VII and with respect to amendement of the
                            Charter; however the United States is prepared to support, after careful
                                study,<note n="1" xml:id="d129fn1">A “Comment Paper” of some length
                                with four annexes setting forth the United States position on
                                General Assembly items dealing with voting in the Security Council
                                had been prepared for the information and guidance of the Delegation
                                    (<gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Files, Doc. US/A/C.1/228/Rev.
                                1, October 21, 1947). The main paper describes the need for a
                                basically new U.S. position for liberalization of the voting
                                procedure in the Security Council in terms of “… experience to date,
                                that the abuse of the rule requiring unanimity of the permanent
                                members of the Security Council in non-procedural decisions is
                                preventing the Council from meeting its responsibilities under the
                                Charter for the maintenance of international peace and security.”
                                Specific remedies enumerated in the document to which this footnote
                                is appended are described in detail in the comment paper, along with
                                careful consideration of how to implement the new U.S. position both
                                in the Security Council and in the current session of the General
                                Assembly. The annexes contain <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi> an
                                historical account of the former U.S. position on the voting problem
                                and new draft rules recently proposed by the United States in the
                                Security Council’s Committee of Experts.</note> the liberalization
                            of the veto under Chapter VI and on membership questions by any
                            appropriate means including modification in the attitude expressed in
                            the Four-Power Statement and amendment of the Charter.</p>
                        <p>The United States will make every effort to find a common ground among
                            the permanent members of the Security Council so that any <pb facs="0246" n="216" xml:id="pg_216"/> recommendations resulting from
                            the General Assembly’s study will have their approval as well as the
                            overwhelming support of the members of the United Nations. The
                            acceptance and support by the United States of such recommendations,
                            however, will not necessarily depend upon their approval by all the
                            permanent members.</p>
                        <p>The United States believes that the General Assembly should include in
                            its study both a survey of the changes that should be made and the
                            methods of their accomplishment. Accordingly we shall suggest that
                            proposals submitted by members concerning the “veto” be referred to a
                            special committee (presumably the Interim Committee would be
                            appropriate), which would make the necessary study and report to the
                            next session of the General Assembly.</p>
                        <p>The United States is not at this time abandoning the Four-Power Statement
                            of June 7, 1945. However, the United States believes the General
                            Assembly’s study should not be limited by the Statement; in the event of
                            a conflict between the recommendations resulting from the study and
                            interpretations of Article 27 contained in the Four-Power Statement, the
                            United States would be willing to consider changes from the attitude
                            expressed on that Statement.</p>
                        <p>The United States would agree to a resolution limiting the terms of
                            reference of the Committee, so as to exclude recommendations eliminating
                            or limiting the requirement of unanimity under Chapter VII and in
                            amending the Charter.</p>
                        <p>The United States considers a study by a committee preferable to a
                            general conference under Article 109 as requested by Argentina. The
                            study by a committee offers a possibility of attaining the desired
                            result without the disturbance to the basic fabric of the Charter
                            inherent in the calling of a general conference at this time, where the
                            range of proposals for change in the Charter would be virtually
                            unlimited.</p>
                        <p>Pending study by a committee, the United States does not plan to urge the
                            adoption by the current session of the General Assembly of specific
                            proposals either for interpreting or amending the Charter. The United
                            States delegation hopes other delegations will share its belief that the
                            debate in Committee I will be most useful if directed to establishing
                            the proposed committee study rather than to determining, in advance of
                            the study, the merits of the specific proposals. The United States also
                            hopes that other delegations, aware that Committee I will begin its
                            discussion of the veto near the end of its long and difficult agenda,
                            will likewise prefer to refer for study substantive proposals on voting
                            in the Security Council.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>