<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-11-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-11-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="143" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d143">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">
                            <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Files: US/A/954</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Delegation Position Paper</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                        York</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-11-20">November 20, 1947</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Report of the First Committee on the Convocation of
                                a General Conference Under Article</hi> 109 <hi rend="smallcaps">of
                                the Charter To Amend the Privilege of the Veto</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d143fn1">The First Committee report is printed as U.N. Doc.
                                A/501, found in United Nations depository libraries. The report was
                                read <hi rend="italic">in toto</hi> to the General Assembly by the
                                rapporteur of the First Committee on November 21; see <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> (II), <hi rend="italic">Plenary</hi>,
                                vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 1218–1220.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Resolution of the Second Part of the First Session
                                of the General Assembly in Relation to the Exercising of the Veto in
                                the Security Council and the Extent to Which the Recommendations
                                Contained in That Resolution Have Been Carried Out</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">A. United States Position</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The United States should vote in favor of the Committee
                                Resolution, which requests the Interim Committee of the General
                                Assembly: to (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) consider the problem of
                                voting in the Security Council; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) consult
                                with any committee which the Security Council may designate to
                                cooperate with the Interim Committee in the study of the problem;
                                and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) report with its conclusions to the
                                Third Session of the General Assembly; and which further requests
                                the permanent members of the Security Council to consult with one
                                another on this problem.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Since the United States introduced the Resolution, it would be
                                appropriate for the United States Representative to make a brief
                                statement in support thereof in the plenary if it appears, as seems
                                likely, that speeches will be made against it. Since the resolution
                                does not contain substantive recommendations, but merely requests
                                further study, if possible, debate should be reduced to a minimum.
                                The United States should not initiate nor participate in a debate on
                                the substantive issues.</item>
                            <pb facs="0262" n="232" xml:id="pg_232"/>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The question should be deemed an “important” one within the
                                meaning of Article 18 and the adoption of the Resolution should
                                therefore require a two-thirds majority. This point will probably
                                not arise since in Committee 1 only the States of Eastern Europe
                                voted against the Resolution.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">B. History in Committee</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The United States Representative in Committee 1 emphasized that the
                            Resolution was a moderate one intended to ensure that “the next Assembly
                            would approach the problem with better understanding and less antagonism
                            toward a coordinate body”. The Eastern European States bitterly opposed
                            the Resolution, taking the extreme position that the only acceptable
                            action of the General Assembly would be to drop the matter from the
                            Agenda.</p>
                        <p>The USSR, while supporting the general principle of consultation among
                            the permanent Members of the Security Council, rejected that principle
                            in connection with this subject on the ground that no changes in the
                            voting formula of any nature would be acceptable to it. Despite such
                            statements in the debates, none of the Eastern European States,
                            excepting Yugoslavia, voted against the last paragraph of the Resolution
                            which requested the permanent Members of the Security Council to consult
                            with one another on the problem of voting.</p>
                        <p>Since the United States Resolution provided for further study of the
                            problem, the representative of Argentina did not submit a resolution to
                            give effect to his request for convocation of a general conference under
                            Article 109. Likewise, the representative of China decided not to ask
                            for a vote in Committee 1 on a substantive proposal which had previously
                            been submitted, it being understood that the Chinese proposal would be
                            referred to the Interim Committee.</p>
                        <p>Because a number of States were unable to support the first paragraph
                            after the preamble of the United States Resolution, while favoring the
                            second paragraph, the representative of Egypt requested that paragraphs
                            be voted separately.</p>
                        <p>The preamble received 44 affirmative votes and 6 negative votes (the
                            Eastern European States) with no abstentions. The first paragraph after
                            the preamble received 30 affirmative votes and 7 negative votes (Eastern
                            European States and Chile) with 11 abstentions. The second paragraph
                            received 43 affirmative votes and 1 negative vote (Yugoslavia) with 8
                            abstentions. (Eastern European States and three Arab States). The
                            Resolution as a whole received 36 affirmative votes and 6 negative votes
                            (Eastern European States) with 11 abstentions. (Five Arab States, India,
                            Yemen, Ethiopia, Guatemala, Sweden, Iceland), 4 absent including the
                            Philippines.</p>
                        <pb facs="0263" n="233" xml:id="pg_233"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">C. Possible Developments in Plenary Session</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It seems probable that a request will be made that the paragraphs of the
                            resolution be voted on separately.</p>
                        <p>It is possible, but unlikely that the United Kingdom may seek to secure
                            unanimous agreement on a resolution which omits the second paragraph
                            after the preamble of the Committee Resolution. The United States must
                            oppose any such effort not only because of its position in support of a
                            study by the Interim Committee but also because Argentina and other
                            States desiring changes in the present voting formula withheld their
                            more drastic proposals on the understanding that the study would take
                            place in the Interim Committee.</p>
                        <p>In all probability the Eastern European States will continue to oppose
                            the resolution in the plenary debates and will raise in their speeches
                            all the substantive issues. The United States should avoid!
                            participating in the discussion of the substantive issues.</p>
                        <p>It is possible that some of the States which abstained would vote
                            affirmatively in the Plenary Sessions if the United States position were
                            further explained to them.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>