<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Chief of the
                        Division of Northeast Asian Affairs (Allison)</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d172</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">172</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-03-19T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                    <term ref="recd38b75873bd4a33" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="far-eastern-commission" subject="far-eastern-commission">Far Eastern Commission</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-03-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="172" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d172">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">890.0146/3–1947</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Chief of the
                        Division of Northeast Asian Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Allison</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-03-19">March 19,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>Mr. Alfred Stirling, Minister, Australian Embassy</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. John M. Allison, Acting Chief of NA</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Arthur Richards, Assistant Chief, British Commonwealth
                            Division</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>As a result of discussion among <gloss target="#t_DA1">DA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>, it was
                    decided to request Mr. Stirling of the Australian Embassy to come in and discuss
                    the whole question of the Australian attitude toward the U.S. Draft Trusteeship
                    Agreement for the Japanese Mandated Islands.<note n="1" xml:id="d172fn1">
                        <p>The text of a draft telegram to New York dated March 19, which was never
                            sent, throws light on Department thinking prior to the conversation
                            recorded here.</p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <list>
                                <item>“1. While Australia proposed new Article 17 to US draft
                                    trusteeship agreement as revised at <gloss target="#t_SC2">SC</gloss> meeting Monday is totally unacceptable as you so
                                    effectively made clear we are concerned over embarrassing
                                    necessity of publicly defeating Australia and UK. We would like,
                                    if possible, to persuade Hasluck [Australian Representative at
                                    the United Nations] to withdraw amendment or give him
                                    opportunity to save his face in final showdown.</item>
                                <item>“2. Please remind Hasluck that US has consistently informed
                                    Australian Government on several occasions that it recognizes
                                    Australian position and interests in Pacific and will assist
                                    Australia to become a principal participant in the peace
                                    settlement with Japan. While we cannot publicly confirm this
                                    policy at this time we are happy to do so privately.</item>
                                <item>“3. You may tell Hasluck that if he is unwilling to withdraw
                                    his amendment you will state before final vote that US, of
                                    course, recognizes Australia’s natural interest in all problems
                                    relating to Pacific and the valiant part played by Australia in
                                    Pacific War and that US equally recognizes the great
                                    contribution made by Australia to the trusteeship principles of
                                    the Charter and in implementation of these principles in New
                                    Guinea trusteeship agreement. Furthermore, you may inform him
                                    that US will gladly agree at peace conference to proposals or
                                    support a treaty article to following effect: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) that treaty extinguishes any rights and interests
                                    which Japan may have in mandates system as one of the Principal
                                    Allied and Associated Powers in First World War and in former
                                    Japanese Mandated Islands as a former mandatory power, and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) that treaty takes note that by
                                    instrument of surrender that Japan has lost all rights, titles
                                    and control in former Japanese Mandated Islands and in any
                                    Japanese islands which may be detached.”
                                    (890.0146/3–1947)</item>
                            </list>
                        </quote>
                    </note> Mr. Stirling came in at 4:30 this afternoon. He stated that he was not
                    entirely familiar with the problem but did have a general knowledge of the
                    question.</p>
                <p>It was explained to Mr. Stirling that Australia’s insistence on her proposed
                    amendment to the effect that the agreement would not enter into force until the
                    date on which the interim or final peace treaty became binding on Japan was a
                    real source of concern to the Department. Reference was made to the statement of
                    the Australian representative on the Security Council that the sole purpose of
                    this amendment was the support of the principle that belligerents against <pb facs="0301" n="271" xml:id="pg_271"/> Japan were entitled to participate in
                    the peace settlement and that the disposition of these islands was part of such
                    a settlement. It was emphasized that in view of the fact that representatives of
                    all members of the Far Eastern Commission had been invited to the Council table
                    it would seem that at least all the active belligerents against Japan were
                    taking part in the proceedings.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stirling was told it did not therefore seem to the Department that any
                    legitimately interested parties were being ignored and that it was felt an
                    outsider listening to the Australian statement might very well come to the
                    conclusion that Australia had some ulterior reason for wishing to delay
                    consideration of the agreement. In view of official Australian statements that
                    it did not have any objection to the U.S. occupying the Mandated Islands as
                    administering power, the Department naturally had no doubts itself of the
                    Australian position but wanted to point out how the present Australian action
                    might be misconstrued by unfriendly persons. It was further emphasized that the
                    Department had no desire or intention of bypassing any of the powers properly
                    concerned in the final settlement with Japan. Reference was made to previous
                    confidential assurances that the U.S. Government would support the full and
                    equal participation of Australia in any consideration of a peace treaty with
                    Japan and this assurance was reiterated.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stirling was told that it was evident from expressions of opinion at the
                    Security Council Meeting on March 17 that if a vote were to be taken the
                    Australian proposal would be defeated but that the Department hoped it would not
                    be necessary to press the matter that far. The hope was expressed that the
                    Australian Government might see fit to reconsider its action and might desire to
                    instruct its representative on the Security Council not to press for adoption of
                    the proposed amendment or even to withdraw it.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stirling was informed that the Department was distressed that in this matter
                    it was necessary to oppose Australia and the United Kingdom, two of its best
                    friends, but that the Department was firmly convinced of the rightness of its
                    position and that it would continue to press for approval by the Security
                    Council of the Trusteeship Agreement without the Australian Amendment.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
