<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Minutes of the Seventh Meeting of the United States
                        Delegation, New York, September 15, 1947, 3 p.m.For information regarding the composition and organization
                        of the United States Delegation to the second regular session of the General
                        Assembly of the United Nations, see pp. 3–13 ff. The General Assembly convened at New York
                        on September 16, 1947.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d179</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">179</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-09-15T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-09-15T14:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="jurisdiction" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="propaganda" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443" lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="sovereignty" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696" lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-09-15T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-09-15T14:00:00-05:00" n="179" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d179">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Flies: US/A/M(Chr)/51<note n="1" xml:id="d179fn1">Short title for the Master Files of the Reference and
                        Documents Section of the Bureau of International Organization Affairs,
                        Department of State.</note>
                </note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Seventh Meeting of the United States
                        Delegation, New York, September 15, 1947, 3 p.m</hi>.<note n="2" xml:id="d179fn2">For information regarding the composition and organization
                        of the United States Delegation to the second regular session of the General
                        Assembly of the United Nations, see <ref target="#pg_3">pp. 3</ref>–<ref target="#pg_13">13</ref> ff. The General Assembly convened at New York
                        on September 16, 1947.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1947-09-15T15:00:00-04:00">September 15, 1947, 3 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follow the list of persons (31) present and a discussion of preceding items
                    on the agenda of the meeting.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Information From Non-Self-Governing Territories</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Green<note n="3" xml:id="d179fn3">James F. Green, Associate Chief of the
                        Division of Dependent Area Affairs, and Adviser, U.S. Delegation Advisory
                        Staff.</note> reported that there had been a sharp cleavage between the
                    colonial and anti-colonial powers in the recent meeting of the <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi>
                    <pb facs="0318" n="288" xml:id="pg_288"/> Committee on the Transmission of
                    Information under Article 73<hi rend="italic">e</hi>.<note n="4" xml:id="d179fn4">The <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee met at Lake
                        Success August 28–September 12, 1947. The Committee was composed of 16
                        members, eight representing governments transmitting information under
                        Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)—Australia, Belgium, Denmark, France,
                        the Netherlands, New Zealand, the United Kingdom, and the United States, and
                        eight representing Member Governments elected by the General
                        Assembly—Brazil, China, Cuba, Egypt, India, the Philippines, the Soviet
                        Union, and Uruguay. For text of the report of the <hi rend="italic">Ad
                            Hoc</hi> Committee, see United Nations, <hi rend="italic">Official
                            Records of the General Assembly, Second Session, Fourth Committee</hi>
                        (hereafter cited as <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> (II), <hi rend="italic">Fourth Committee</hi>), annex 4<hi rend="italic">a</hi>,
                        pp. 202 ff.</note> The delegates of the U.S.S.R., China, Philippines, India
                    and sometimes the Arab States took the position that Chapter XI implied that the
                    United Nations should have broad supervisory powers with respect to
                    non-self-governing territories. The U.S.S.R. has argued quite frequently for
                    immediate independence. Of the administering powers, the French, Dutch and
                    Belgians had taken the most recalcitrant attitude, while the British,
                    Australians, New Zealanders and Danes had been willing to accept a broad
                    interpretation of Chapter XI, subject to the maintenance of their sovereign
                    position. The United States, he continued, had tried to provide constructive
                    leadership and to rally the moderate states by stressing the need for concrete
                    proposals. Such proposals had in the past won a large measure of support. He
                    explained that the position paper (US/A/C.4/34)<note n="5" xml:id="d179fn5">
                        <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note> had been based on the first draft of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee report supplemented by a
                    conversation with Mr. Gerig, who sat for the United States. He said the paper
                    was very preliminary and subject to clearance by the Navy and Interior
                    departments.</p>
                <p>There were three issues involved, he explained: (1) the kind of information that
                    should be transmitted; (2) what the Secretary-General should do with the
                    information; and (3) what the General Assembly should do with it. The Charter
                    was very precise on the first issue. Despite the fact that political information
                    had been deliberately left out of Article 73<hi rend="italic">e</hi>, there had
                    been a concerted effort to include political information. Mr. Gerig had agreed
                    to include political information in the United States reports but only as a
                    voluntary transaction. This stand was endorsed by the other administering
                    powers. The United States had submitted a draft outline including an optional
                    section on general information. This had been unanimously accepted. The second
                    issue was more difficult since the Charter left this open. Article 73<hi rend="italic">e</hi> was stretched somewhat at London when the
                    Secretary-General was requested to prepare summaries and analyses. The United
                    States had insisted that the Secretary-General’s use of supplemental documents
                    be subject to the approval of the administering power concerned, and that the
                    Secretary-General should not analyze political information. Use by the
                    Secretary-General, for the purposes of comparison, of data on independent states
                    had been approved by the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee, <pb facs="0319" n="289" xml:id="pg_289"/> but had not been very popular with
                    non-reporting states, who saw dangerous implication for themselves. It was
                    generally agreed by the United States that the General Assembly could discuss
                    any matter relating to dependent countries. The United States position papers
                    for the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee stated that the General Assembly
                    should also have power to make recommendations of a functional character but not
                    to individual states. The <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee had also
                    recommended the establishment by the General Assembly Committee 4 of a Special
                    Committee, but left to the Assembly whether it should meet during or before the
                    next General Assembly.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dulles called attention to the difficulty of deciding, in the light of United
                    States foreign policy as a whole, the extent to which the United States should
                    work along with the Western European colonial powers and the extent to which it
                    should come out for dependent peoples. The U.S.S.R., he noted, had refused
                    membership on the Trusteeship Council, but was striving to develop the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee, which exercised jurisdiction over a
                    wider group of territories, into a serious competitor of the Trusteeship
                    Council. This would make it possible for the U.S.S.R. to stir up more trouble.
                    The U.S.S.R., he recalled, had usually been able to muster a substantial
                    majority against the United States position in such matters. United States
                    Committee IV delegates ought to have a general indication of the United States
                    policy on the fundamental problem.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Sayre noted that Mr. Gerig had done an excellent job in the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee in protecting the interests of the
                    United States. He felt that the position paper went about as far as the United
                    States could go at the moment. He had no doubt that the Soviets intended to make
                    the best of the propaganda potentialities of this issue. Mr. Dulles agreed that
                    Mr. Gerig had done an excellent job in thwarting the extreme tactics of the
                    anti-colonial bloc and at the same time in avoiding identification with the
                    colonial powers. This, said Mr. Dulles, should continue to be the United States
                    policy in the future. He added that it was generally possible for the Russians
                    and Indians to rally Committee 4 against the United States.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Sayre pointed out that the great difference between the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee and the Trusteeship Council lay in the
                    matter of sovereignty. Chapter XI entailed no surrender of sovereignty. Mr.
                    Green replied affirmatively when asked by Ambassador Austin if reports had been
                    received on seventy-four territories. Mr. Fahy held that the United States
                    position was legally sound, but that it would be risky to go further. The United
                    States could not take the position that the information submitted could not be
                    discussed by the General Assembly. Functional recommendations were also proper.
                    Citing Article II(7), he added that the United States was also right in
                    resisting any <pb facs="0320" n="290" xml:id="pg_290"/> effort to have the
                    General Assembly make recommendations to Members with respect to their
                    non-self-governing territories. This position should not be abandoned unless the
                    International Court of Justice decided otherwise. It could not be fairly
                    criticized as a conservative interpretation of the Charter.</p>
                <p>The meeting adjourned at 5:30 p.m.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Roger Mann</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
