<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d184</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">184</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-10-14T16:54:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-10-14T16:54:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec1Gk59BaIROJJML" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85116922"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Salvage</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-10-14T16:54:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-10-14T16:54:00-05:00" n="184"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d184">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB/10–1447: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-10-14T16:54:00-05:00"
                            >October 14, 1947—4:54 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 31. Special for Gerig from Green.<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d184fn1">Seen in draft by Mr. Dulles and Ambassador
                        Sayre.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Recent decisions taken in Comm 4 on resolutions proposed by <hi
                            rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee raise serious question as to
                        position which <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss> should take in
                        plenary meeting.<note n="2" xml:id="d184fn2">For the summary record of the
                            deliberations of the Fourth Committee in respect to the five
                            resolutions, see <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> (II), <hi
                                rend="italic">Fourth Committee</hi>, pp. 66 ff. For the <hi
                                rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee text for which the United States
                            voted affirmatively, see <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., pp. 212 and 213;
                            for text of the resolutions adopted by the Fourth Committee on October
                            10 and which the United States voted against, see <gloss target="#t_GA1"
                                >GA</gloss> (II), <hi rend="italic">Plenary</hi>, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 1547 (Report of the Fourth
                            Committee).</note> Resolutions 2, 3, and 5 were drastically amended, to
                        disadvantage of Members administering non-self-governing territories, by
                        votes of 22–18, 20–19, and 23–19 respectively. Effect of amendments is as
                        follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>Resolution 2, para 6, now provides that the <gloss target="#t_SYG1"
                                    >SYG</gloss> may, for purposes of comparison between data
                                relating to the various non-self-governing territories and their
                                metropolitan areas (rather than relating to the territories and <hi
                                    rend="italic">all</hi> independent states), use official
                                statistical material as is available in the statistical services of
                                Secretariat and as may be agreed upon between <gloss
                                    target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> and Member concerned.</p>
                            <pb facs="0329" n="299" xml:id="pg_299"/>
                            <p>Resolution 3, after referring to Article 73(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                                of Charter, states transmission of info re results achieved in
                                matter of participation of local populations in work of local organs
                                of adm is entirely within spirit of Article 73 and recommends
                                administering states to transmit such info.<note n="3"
                                    xml:id="d184fn3">For the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee
                                    text on which the United States voted affirmatively, see <hi
                                        rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., p. 213; for text of the resolution
                                    adopted by the Fourth Committee, against which the United States
                                    voted, see <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> (II), <hi
                                        rend="italic">Plenary</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                        >ii</hi>, pp. 1547 and 1548. The amended resolution was
                                    moved by the Soviet Union in the Fourth Committee on October 11
                                    and adopted by a vote of 20–19 (<gloss target="#t_GA1"
                                        >GA</gloss> (II), <hi rend="italic">Fourth Committee</hi>,
                                    pp. 72, 76); see also <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., p. 217,
                                    annex 4<hi rend="italic">h</hi>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Under Resolution 5 proposed Special Comm is created by, and its
                                non-administering Members elected by, <gloss target="#t_GA1"
                                    >GA</gloss> rather than Comm 4; its tenure is 2 years rather
                                than unspecified; its recommendations are not limited to procedural
                                matters and functional fields; and its time of meeting is specified
                                as some weeks before <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>.<note n="4"
                                    xml:id="d184fn4">
                                    <p>The <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee text of
                                        Resolution 5 is found in <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>
                                        (II), <hi rend="italic">Fourth Committee</hi>, p. 214; the
                                        United States supported this draft. This text was amended by
                                        the Fourth Committee on October 11 on the motion of the
                                        Indian delegate (<gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>. (II),
                                            <hi rend="italic">Plenary</hi>, vol. <hi
                                            rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 1548); the U.S. voted
                                        against the amended resolution. For discussion in the Fourth
                                        Committee, see <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> (II), <hi
                                            rend="italic">Fourth Committee</hi>, pp. 76 ff.; see
                                        also <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., pp. 215 and 216, annex
                                            <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</p>
                                    <p>For statements by the United States delegate, Ambassador
                                        Sayre, see <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., pp. 69, 70, 75, 76,
                                        and 77.</p>
                                </note>
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                    </item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>These decisions were taken only after prolonged debate in which US, UK,
                        and other Delegations presented in clearest and strongest manner possible
                        their interpretation of character and purposes of Chapter XI of Charter, and
                        emphasized limitations of Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>). It is clear
                        that Soviet bloc, Arab States, India, Pakistan, Philippines, and many Latin
                        American countries are determined to continue embarrassing administering
                        Members by misinterpreting Chapter XL</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Amended Resolutions 3 and 5, taken together, have far-reaching
                        implications for US and other administering Members. On one hand, an
                        administering Member which does not transmit information on participation of
                        local populations in local organs of government will be censured next year
                        for disregarding a recommendation of the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>.
                        On other hand, any such information transmitted will be subject to censure
                        in recommendations of Special Comm.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>As Dept is aware, functions of UN under Chapter XI have been steadily
                        expanded from first part of first session of <gloss target="#t_GA1"
                            >GA</gloss> through second part and <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Comm
                        to present session. End of this process is not yet in sight. Fact that
                        Soviet <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> did not submit, contrary to its
                        original announcement in Comm 4, proposal that UN should provide for visits
                        to non-self-governing territories and examination of petitions relating to
                        them suggests that this further extension of UN supervision is being
                        postponed until next year.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss> would appreciate Dept’s
                        recommendations as to tactics to be employed in plenary meeting. Possible
                        courses, together with preliminary observations, are outlined in paras 5 and
                        6 below. Dept will <pb facs="0330" n="300" xml:id="pg_300"/> wish to
                        consider whether it desires a real showdown over Chapter XI this year or
                        would prefer wait until next session when pressure against administering
                        Members will be even heavier. Question also arises as to whether <gloss
                            target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss> should seek to have the five
                        resolutions considered “important matters” under Article 18 of Charter
                        requiring adoption by two-thirds vote. This involves larger issue as to
                        whether it is in long-term US interest to enlarge list of these “important
                        matters”. In any event it might be difficult to argue for two-thirds vote,
                        since resolution constituting <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Comm was adopted
                        last year by majority vote.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Two possible courses which seem feasible are as follows: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss> could submit amendments, for
                                consideration at a plenary meeting, with a view to restoring
                                original wording of Resolutions 2, 3, and 5. This procedure would
                                indicate US willingness to cooperate in implementing Article 73 (<hi
                                    rend="italic">e</hi>) so long as implementation follows
                                moderate, compromise resolutions agreed upon by <hi rend="italic">Ad
                                    Hoc</hi> Comm. It would involve, however, long debates on
                                technical points and perhaps a complicated series of votes.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss> could vote in favor of
                                Resolutions 1 and 4 and against Resolutions 2, 3, and 5. We
                                tentatively favor this procedure as it would enable <gloss
                                    target="#t_Gadel1">Gadel</gloss> to salvage two most useful
                                resolutions and probably to eliminate two—Resolutions 3 and 5—which
                                were not wholly satisfactory even in original form. It would involve
                                long debates but these debates could be focused on resolutions
                                rather than amendments.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>A third course, which seems less desirable, is the following: <quote
                            rend="blockquote">
                            <p>
                                <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss> could oppose all five
                                resolutions on ground that balance attained in <hi rend="italic">Ad
                                    Hoc</hi> Comm has been completely upset by actions of Comm 4.
                                This procedure would enable <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss>
                                to argue case on general principles and to focus debate on
                                interpretation of Chapter XI. It would have disadvantage, however,
                                of making <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss> appear to take a
                                recalcitrant “all or nothing” attitude.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>If resolutions were adopted in present amended form, <gloss
                            target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss> could take one or more of following
                        positions, each of which deserves careful consideration in terms of
                        long-range US interests: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss>, perhaps invoking Article
                                2(7) of the Charter, could state reservations as to legality of
                                recommendation contained in Resolution 2 and of any recommendations
                                made by proposed Special Comm under amended Resolution 5, and could
                                state tha such recommendations cannot be legally and morally binding
                                on administering Members.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss> could warn that, because of
                                misinterpretation of Chapter XI underlying amended Resolutions 2, 3,
                                and 5, US cannot state at this time that it will be willing to
                                transmit any information on Govt (Section I, D of Standard
                                Provisional Form annexed to Resolution 1) with respect to
                                territories it administers.<note n="5" xml:id="d184fn5">The United
                                    States had approved the text of Resolution 1 as voted both in
                                    the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee and in the Fourth
                                    Committee.</note>
                            </item>
                            <pb facs="0331" n="301" xml:id="pg_301"/>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss> could propose that <gloss
                                    target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> seek an advisory opinion of <gloss
                                    target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss> as to proper interpretation of
                                Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) of Charter especially with
                                respect to interpretation of “for information purposes” and
                                transmission of information on political conditions.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Whatever course it is determined that <gloss target="#t_Gadel1"
                            >GADel</gloss> should pursue in plenary meeting, it will be necessary
                            (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) to explain this course with great care in
                        background conferences with press, and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) to bring
                        some pressure to bear on Latin American and other Delegations to support US
                        position. (Because many other items on the agenda, especially those before
                        Comm 1, have been more urgent, political officers have not sought support of
                        other Delegations on Comm 4 matters.) If two-thirds vote is required in
                        plenary meeting, support of only half the Latin American Delegations would
                        almost be sufficient to enable <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss> to
                        defeat any or all of the five resolutions. If only majority vote is
                        required, much wider support would be needed. In order that future <gloss
                            target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss> course may be explained to press and to
                        other Delegations, Dept’s recommendations should be received if possible by
                        end of week. [Green.]</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
