<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Joint Chiefs of Staff to the
                        United States Representatives on the United Nations
                            Military Staff Committee
                    
                    Sent to the United States Representatives on the
                        United Nations Military Staff Committee as SM–7382, January 10; circulated
                        in the State–War–Navy Coordinating Committee for information as SWNCC 240/2, January 13.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d208</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">208</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-01-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-01-13T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-01-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-01-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="208" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d208">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss> Files<note n="1" xml:id="d208fn1">Lot
                        52M45, the files of the State–War–Navy Coordinating Committee which are
                        located in the National Archives under the administration of the Department
                        of State. For information regarding the organization and functions of <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss>, see <ref target="frus1946v01#pg_1112">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1946, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, footnote 3, p. 1112</ref>. Regarding the
                            <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee to Effect Collaboration on
                        Security Functions of the United Nations, the principal <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss> subcommittee charged with consideration
                        of matters relating to the regulation of armaments and collective security
                        at the UN, see <ref target="frus1946v01#pg_754">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., footnote 73, p. 754</ref>.</note>
                </note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Joint Chiefs of Staff</gloss> to the
                        United States Representatives on the <gloss type="to">United Nations
                            Military Staff Committee</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d208fn2">Sent to the United States Representatives on the
                        United Nations Military Staff Committee as SM–7382, January 10; circulated
                        in the State–War–Navy Coordinating Committee for information as <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss> 240/2, January 13.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss> 240/2</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-01-13">January 13,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Guidance as to Information Which States Members of the
                        United Nations Should Furnish in Regard to Their Armed Forces</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The Joint Chiefs of Staff desire that you take the following position
                        should your advice be sought with respect to the scope and character of the
                        information member nations of the United Nations should be called upon to
                        furnish in order to give effect to the United Nations resolution of 14
                        December 1946 on the Principles Governing the Regulation and Reduction of
                        Armaments.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>You should inform the U.S. Representatives that the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                        are of the opinion that no information concerning existing military
                        establishments is essential for the implementation of the general
                        resolution. However, in accordance with the policy which was in effect
                        established for the United States by the speech of the Secretary of State
                        before the General Assembly of the United Nations on 13 December 1946<note n="3" xml:id="d208fn3">For text, see <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>(I/2), <hi rend="italic">Plenary</hi>, pp. 1289–1296.</note>
                        and by formal statements of members of the United States Delegation to the
                        General Assembly, United Nations, you should indicate that the Joint Chiefs
                        of Staff perceive no objection to disclosing the numbers and locations of
                        the total armed forces of the United States provided such a resolution is
                        not based upon the specific resolution contained in paragraph 7 of the
                        United Nations Document <pb facs="0387" n="357" xml:id="pg_357"/> A/269 [<hi rend="italic">A/267</hi>].<note n="4" xml:id="d208fn4">
                            <p>Reference is to paragraph 7 of the General Assembly resolution on the
                                regulation of armaments of December 14, 1946, A/267; for full text,
                                see <ref target="frus1946v01#pg_1101">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1946, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 1101</ref>. Paragraph 7 read as
                                follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">There shall be established</hi>,</p>
                                    <p>within the framework of the Security Council, which bears the
                                        primary responsibility for the maintenance of international
                                        peace and security, an international system, as mentioned in
                                        paragraph 4, operating through special organs, which organs
                                        shall derive their powers and status from the convention or
                                        conventions under which they are established.</p>
                                    <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The General Assembly</hi>,</p>
                                    <p>regarding the problem of security as closely connected with
                                        that of disarmament,</p>
                                    <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Recommends</hi> the Security Council to
                                        accelerate as much as possible the placing at its disposal
                                        of the armed forces mentioned in Article 43 of the
                                        Charter;</p>
                                    <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">It recommends</hi> the Members to
                                        undertake the progressive and balanced withdrawal, taking
                                        account of the needs of occupation, of their armed forces
                                        stationed in ex-enemy territories, and the withdrawal
                                        without delay of armed forces stationed in the territories
                                        of Members without their consent freely and publicly
                                        expressed in treaties or agreements consistent with the
                                        Charter and not contradicting international agreements;</p>
                                    <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">It further recommends</hi> a
                                        corresponding reduction of national armed forces, and a
                                        general progressive and balanced reduction of national armed
                                        forces.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">The resolution contained in Doc. A/269, also adopted
                                by the General Assembly on December 14, 1946, read as follows:
                                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">The General Assembly</hi>,</p>
                                    <p>Desirous of implementing, as soon as possible, the resolution
                                        of 14 December 1946 on the principles governing the
                                        regulation and reduction of armaments,</p>
                                    <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Calls</hi> upon the Security Council to
                                        determine, as soon as possible, the information which the
                                        States Members of the United Nations should be called upon
                                        to furnish, in order to give effect to this resolution.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                        </note> If you are requested to furnish this information to the United
                        States Representatives on the Security Council you should forward such a
                        request to the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>You should inform the U.S. Representative that no information concerning
                        the types and numbers of arms or armaments possessed by the United States
                        should be disclosed at this time since the Joint Chiefs of Staff are unable
                        to perceive that supplying such information would facilitate the development
                        of an effective system for regulation and reduction of armaments. For your
                        information the Joint Chiefs of Staff are informed that if it should become
                        apparent that the United States would be placed in an untenable position by
                        resisting a resolution calling for such disclosures, the United States will
                        insist that the following conditions be satisfied before such disclosures
                        are actually made: <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>It must be demonstrated that such disclosures will be helpful in
                                working out the practical measures for general regulation and
                                reduction of armaments.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Adequate safeguards must be provided to insure that all nations
                                conform to the same standards with respect to information
                                disclosed.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Adequate safeguards must be provided to insure that no nation’s
                                security is endangered by such disclosures.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The Joint Chiefs of Staff recognize that implementation of paragraph 7 of
                        the general resolution will require member states to make <pb facs="0388" n="358" xml:id="pg_358"/> known in due course the character and size of
                        the armed forces they are willing to make available to the Security Council
                        in accordance with Article 43 of the Charter. Guidance in this respect was
                        furnished you by memorandum dated 11 March 1946.<note n="5" xml:id="d208fn5">The document under reference, approved by the State–War–Navy
                            Coordinating Committee as <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss> 219/8,
                            is summarized in footnote 2 in <ref target="frus1946v01#pg_769">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1946, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 769</ref>.</note> It is conceivable,
                        but not now probable, that the figures furnished you as to the size of the
                        forces the United States is willing to make available to the Security
                        Council will require revision due to the length of elapsed time between the
                        original establishment of the figures and their formal presentation.
                        Therefore, these figures should be considered as tentative only and should
                        not be formally presented until they have been reaffirmed or changed by the
                        Joint Chiefs of Staff. You should request such reaffirmation or change when
                        you have learned that the time for formal disclosure of the figures is at
                        hand.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The views of the Joint Chiefs of Staff on the general subject of
                        disarmament and regulation of arms and armaments as stated in their
                        memorandum dated 6 December 1946,<note n="6" xml:id="d208fn6">
                            <ref target="frus1946v01#pg_1091">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1946, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 1091</ref>.</note> and their
                        memorandum dated 31 December 1946,<note n="7" xml:id="d208fn7">
                            <ref target="frus1946v01#pg_1107">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., p. 1107</ref>.</note> remain
                        unchanged.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>For the Joint Chiefs of Staff: <lb/>
                    <signed>A. J. <hi rend="smallcaps">McFarland</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Colonel, Infantry Secretary</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
