<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Telephone Conversation, by the Chief of the
                        Division of International Security Affairs (Johnson)</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d283</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">283</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-06-13T08:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-06-13T08:30:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-06-13T08:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-06-13T08:30:00-05:00" n="283" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d283">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.<gloss target="#t_BC1">BC</gloss>
                    Atomic/6–1347</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Telephone Conversation, by the Chief of the
                        Division of International Security Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-06-13T09:30:00-04:00">June 13, 1947—9:30 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Osborn called to pose two questions which are now in the minds of himself and
                    his colleagues regarding the report which the United Nations Atomic Energy
                    Commission is to submit in the Fall, and which he would like to have interested
                    persons in Washington thinking about.</p>
                <p>1. What form should the second report of the <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>
                    take?</p>
                <p>This question arises as a result of the present efforts of the Soviet Union to
                    have the proposals recently put forward by Mr. Gromyko in the Commission<note n="1" xml:id="d283fn1">For the text of the proposals, see Gromyko’s speech
                        at the 12th Meeting of the Atomic Energy Commission, June 11, <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>, <hi rend="italic">2nd yr., Plenary</hi>,
                        pp. 20–24.</note> referred to Committee 2. Mr. Osborn says that the Soviet
                    Union is endeavoring to have this referral made for the purpose of mixing these
                    proposals with the papers now being developed by Committee 2. (This appears to
                    be consistent with Gromyko’s statement reported in today’s <hi rend="italic">New
                        York Times</hi> to the effect that there is a possibility of agreement on
                    the basis of the divergent Soviet and United States proposals.) The United
                    States view, shared by a number of others including particularly the French and
                    Canadians, is that if the Soviet proposals are submitted to Committee 2, there
                    will be real danger of confusion and of possible compromising attitudes on the
                    part of certain delegations.</p>
                <p>Mr. Osborn indicated that he personally sees certain advantage in the Atomic
                    Energy Commission submitting two proposals in its next report,—that being
                    developed in Committee 2 along the lines of the First Report of the Commission,
                    and one based upon the Soviet proposals. While he did not say so specifically, I
                    gathered that his expectation was that the submission of two plans might result
                    from keeping consideration of the recent Soviet proposal and of the development
                    of the First Report separate. Specifically, therefore, Mr. Osborn’s question is
                    whether it would be wise to consider making a report which would include the
                    submission of two plans.</p>
                <p>2. Would it be advisable for the United States to consider permitting a report to
                    go forward containing some proposals on which we have reservations?</p>
                <p>Mr. Osborn explained that it might be possible by “politicking,” negotiation and
                    heavy pressure to get the same kind of agreement on a plan acceptable to us as
                    was obtained last December. On the other hand, it is conceivable that we might
                    accede to the watering down of the plan on certain points, with the United
                    States entering a reservation on all points that we considered important.</p>
                <pb facs="0538" n="508" xml:id="pg_508"/>
                <p>Mr. Osborn pointed out that certain countries will definitely make reservations
                    on specific points. Brazil, for example, will undoubtedly continue to make a
                    reservation with respect to international control of her monozite sand deposits.
                    Australia also will probably insist that ownership and management of refineries
                    and concentration plants by the international control agency should be
                    permissive rather than mandatory. (On this last point Mr. Osborn commented that
                    he finds it difficult to fight too hard on this point, provided it is definitely
                    clear that the agency may in its discretion own such plants.)</p>
                <p>Mr. Osborn commented that Mr. Baruch would undoubtedly disapprove any open
                    willingness on the part of the United States to permit a plan to go forward on
                    which we have reservations. Mr. Osborn’s own preliminary thought, however, is
                    that since all our reservations would be in favor of stronger security
                    provisions than the actual draft, it might not be too dangerous to consider this
                    tactic.</p>
                <p>When Mr. Osborn indicated that he was merely telephoning in advance of a letter,
                    I suggested that, rather than send a letter to me, he prepare a formal dispatch
                    to the Secretary of State (either telegraphic or by courier) raising the
                    questions. He gave me the impression that he would do so, but made it clear that
                    his formal message would only raise the questions and would not indicate his
                    preliminary attitude on them as outlined above.</p>
                <p>In further discussion Mr. Osborn indicated that he thinks it will be possible to
                    defeat the Soviet effort to have their recent proposals referred to Committee
                    2.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph E. Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
