<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Embassy in tJie United Kingdom</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d288</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">288</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-06-17T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-06-17T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-06-17T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-06-17T20:00:00-05:00" n="288"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d288">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.<gloss target="#t_BC1">BC</gloss>
                    Atomic/6–1147: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in tJie United Kingdom</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-06-17T21:00:00-04:00"
                            >June 17, 1947—9 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2603. For Chargé d’Affaires eyes only from the Secretary. <gloss
                        target="#t_reurtel1">Reurtel</gloss> 3183, June ll.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d288fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_502">p. 502</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Bevin’s reference to Hyde Park and Quebec agreements<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d288fn2">See footnote 5, <ref target="#pg_781">p. 781</ref>, and
                            footnote 4, <ref target="#pg_787">p. 787</ref>.</note> and to technical
                        assistance available to him in London seemed to indicate intention to link
                        question of British request for supply of information for use in developing
                        atomic energy plants with question of independent British line in <gloss
                            target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss> as discussed in my 2486.<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d288fn3">Dated June 10, <ref target="#pg_490">p.
                            490</ref>.</note> However, British Embassy now volunteers information
                        that Foreign Office officials discussed with Bevin his conversation with you
                        and that, as a result, the British do not plan to try to tie the two
                        questions together.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Dept strongly of opinion that they are separate and distinct problems and
                        hopes that discussion of British request for information can be avoided.
                        Your conversations should bear on international control proposals but we do
                        not wish to conduct definitive negotiations in London on either the proposed
                        new British UN plan or British request for information. Our thought is that
                        your talks would be exploratory and chiefly directed, until further
                        instructions are received, toward gathering information about British plan
                        and explaining to British why they should not put it forward in light of
                        considerations in my telegram in reference and New York background which
                        Arneson can supply.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>For your own strictly confidential information, and with reference British
                        request for industrial atomic energy information, Dept is at present engaged
                        with US Atomic Energy Commission in studying whether provisions of McMahon
                        Act will allow us, in view of primary objective which is to assure common
                        defense and security, to use information as a counter in dealings necessary
                        to assure adequate supply raw materials for development atomic energy in
                        this country. We are trying establish whether this proposition, which
                        applies not only to our relations with UK, is correct and, if so, what our
                        course should be. In any case we shall try to hasten decision.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Also for your own strictly confidential information, it is possible, <pb
                            facs="0548" n="518" xml:id="pg_518"/> but not likely, that we may come
                        to some conclusion before <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAE Commission</gloss>
                        presents its report to Security Council in late summer or early autumn. We
                        still hold strongly to view that original Dec 31 proposals present best
                        scheme for international control and that abandonment of concept of full
                        international control in favor of less complete control means endangering
                        world security, rather than merely settling for something less than
                        hypothetical “total” security of the earlier proposals.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>If therefore Bevin in his further talks with you tries to condition UK
                        support of our UN position upon our supplying information to them, or if he
                        should press you for action on their request, you should tell him that we do
                        not see how one relates to the other; that you are not in position to go
                        into latter question extensively. We are trying as best we can to find
                        solution to problem posed by McMahon Act and will investigate every
                        possibility of extending basis of cooperation with Brit within provisions of
                        law. Some time may yet elapse before we can come to conclusion since we are
                        still in stage of basic studies within some of the Executive Departments.
                        Some progress toward solution has been made by getting over one of the
                        collateral obstacles in the way. Action on Brit request seemed to us
                        necessarily to involve disclosure to the Joint Congressional Committee on
                        Atomic Energy of wartime agreements, such as Quebec and Hyde Park
                        arrangements. As Brit are aware, on May 12, 1947, I told Congressional
                        Committee about these arrangements in strictest secrecy. There appear to
                        have been no leaks and no complications. I believe our future handling of
                        this problem has been facilitated by this session.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>If Bevin renews his comment about a US proposal which might have effect of
                        denying to his government use of atomic energy for industrial purposes, you
                        may say that we do not understand this reference since we know of no such
                        proposal. It is true that we believe that all important atomic facilities
                        should be closely controlled by an international authority but this we
                        conceived to be in interest of world security and not solely in US interest
                        and most certainly not US policy aimed at Brit. When such an authority is
                        set up, US and UK would be in same position in respect to whatever abatement
                        of sovereignty an international authority would involve. We had thought UK
                        in agreement with this position, when it supported Dec 31 report of <gloss
                            target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss> to Security Council.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Perhaps Bevin believes McMahon Act would prevent our turning over to an
                        International Atomic Authority information it needs to develop plants in
                        areas where they do not now exist. You may assure him that we do not see any
                        obstacle there; in fact setting up of authority would presumably constitute
                        kind of safeguard which the Act contemplates as existing before exchange of
                        information on use of <pb facs="0549" n="519" xml:id="pg_519"/> atomic
                        energy for industrial purposes is permitted. In sum, we do not see how Brit
                        position with respect development atomic energy for industrial purposes
                        would be affected one way or another by proposed modification Dec 31 <gloss
                            target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss> proposals.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Re last paragraph your 3183, Dept presently sees no necessity Amb to forego
                    planned short visit with General Clay but if at any time you and Arneson believe
                    his immediate return necessary, Dept would concur in your decision.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
