<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Under Secretary of State (
                        Acheson
                    ) to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                        (
                        Douglas
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d298</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">298</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-06-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-06-27T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons" subject="nuclear-weapons" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic weapons</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="propaganda" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443" lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-06-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-06-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="298" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d298">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Policy Planning Staff Files<note n="1" xml:id="d298fn1">Lot 64D563, files of the Policy Planning Staff, Department
                        of State, 1947–1953.</note>
                </note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Acheson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-06-27">June 27,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Lew</hi>: Your cable 3353 of June 19 states precisely
                    what we expect from your conversations with the British in regard to their
                    intention to introduce a new plan for international control of atomic energy
                    into the United Nations discussions. I hope that you personally make clear to
                    Bevin, informally, that our strong reluctance to see any such diversionary
                    proposals presented is tied up with our apprehensions about Russian foreign
                    policy and tactics in <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>It is difficult, if not impossible, at this stage to synthesize all the
                    impressions of the Russians held by various persons who deal with them or work
                    on the Soviet Union problem in the Department, UN, the War and Navy Departments,
                    and in our Missions abroad, and to peg that composite as an official government
                    estimate of Russian policy. I should think that the British would understand
                    this difficulty.</p>
                <p>What I am about to describe is merely the climate of opinion here, more or less
                    reflected in official thinking, as in the so-called “Ridgway” memorandum (<gloss target="#t_SC2">SC</gloss> 210—“Objectives of USSR atomic energy &amp;
                    disarmament policies”, April 7, 1947<note n="2" xml:id="d298fn2">A revision of
                        General Ridgway’s memorandum of February 3, <ref target="#pg_402">p.
                            402</ref>.</note>) which Mr. Joseph Johnson discussed with you in
                    Washington, and of which you have a copy. Although we have not lost hope of
                    achieving an international control regime and intend to continue the effort in
                    the <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> as long as we can, I, personally, and
                    most other observers are much discouraged about <pb facs="0568" n="538" xml:id="pg_538"/> present prospects and fear that the Russians’ present line
                    is to filibuster in the United Nations, while at the same time they try: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>To attract support from anxious minority opinion in other United
                            Nations atomic energy commission countries;</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>To break down existing US–UK arrangements for procurement of raw
                            materials by tactics such as they are pursuing in Belgium;<note n="3" xml:id="d298fn3">For documentation on this subject, see pp. 781 ff.
                                    <hi rend="italic">passim.</hi>
                            </note>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>To infiltrate research and control programs in any or all other
                            countries;</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>To hasten their own development of atomic weapons; and</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                        <item>To extend their area of effective political domination, as in
                            Hungary.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The longer the filibuster can be prolonged, the more they can hope to play upon
                    the fears and idealism of that part of the population of interested countries
                    which is desperately anxious to preserve peace and which is receptive to Soviet
                    professions and propaganda.</p>
                <p>In the early fall the United Nations Atomic Energy Commission is to make its
                    second report to the Security Council; we had planned and hoped that by that
                    time the essential points of difference between the Soviet Union and the
                    countries supporting the original December 31 proposals would have been
                    isolated, and that it would be clear just what, if any, possibility existed of
                    agreement on these points, so that if negotiations were to fail or to drift into
                    nothingness, it would be clear to the world where the responsibility lay.</p>
                <p>Since we have been pursuing that policy it has been difficult to bring the
                    Russians down to brass tacks or to prevent them from taking refuge in
                    discussions of comparatively minor phases of an international convention. It is
                    my own strong feeling that they are not really ready to adopt any international
                    control scheme, either the Baruch proposals, the new British plan, or any other.
                    They have recently given some details as to how they would expect inspection
                    systems to function, but it is clear that they do not intend to abandon their
                    insistence on the destruction of atomic bomb stocks before adoption of an
                    international control convention. I am confident that the United States would
                    never agree to this. Furthermore, the Soviet Union is just as adamant as ever
                    about not accepting international ownership or genuine control of important
                    facilities. Compared to these two major points of disagreement, the questions of
                    the veto and of the mechanics of inspection seem less important.</p>
                <p>In view of all the above, I think it would be a grave error for the British to
                    introduce new proposals at this time. It would merely give the Soviet Union a
                    new set of points to discuss, new papers to prepare, and new ammunition for the
                    filibuster.</p>
                <pb facs="0569" n="539" xml:id="pg_539"/>
                <p>I should like you, if possible, to convey to Bevin some sense of this climate of
                    opinion here, without giving him the impression that you are presenting a
                    crystallized hard-and-fast policy on Russia. Also, both we and the British must
                    avoid giving the Russians the opportunity of accusing us of bad faith or of
                    selling the UN negotiations short.</p>
                <p>It would be very useful to have from the British at the close of your talks a
                    clear indication as to whether they intend to put forward their proposal or to
                    support one on similar lines. They might not be willing to tie their hands now
                    but I think you should ask them anyway for any forecast they are prepared to
                    give of their future course, at least through September.</p>
                <p>The conversations have been most helpful and we are very grateful to you and
                    Arneson.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>[File copy not signed]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
