<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-07-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-07-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="322" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d322">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of State Disarmament Files</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Executive Committee on Regulation of
                            Armaments</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d322fn1">This document was approved by
                            the Executive Committee on July 23 and was transmitted to the United
                            States Mission at the United Nations with instruction No. 181, July 29
                            (Department of State Disarmament Files).</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <gloss target="#t_RAC1">RAC</gloss> D–18/2a</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-07-25">July 25, 1947</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Basic Principles Which Should Be Incorporated in an
                            International Supervisory System for the Regulation and Reduction of
                            Armaments</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">preamble</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The principle has been established by the General Assembly of December 13
                            [<hi rend="italic">14</hi>], 1946, “that essential to the general
                        regulation and reduction of armaments and armed forces is the provision of
                        practical and effective safeguards by way of inspection and other means to
                        protect complying states against the hazards of violations and
                        evasions”.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>An international agency should be established within the framework of
                            the Security Council, deriving its powers and status from the treaty or
                            treaties under which it is established, to supervise and administer a
                            system of regulation and reduction of conventional armaments.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The international agency should be broadly representative of the
                            states participating in the system, but limited in size in the interest
                            of efficient operations. It should be composed of a representative from
                            each of the states which are members of the Security Council, the
                            non-permanent membership changing in conformity with elections to and
                            retirement from the Security Council.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The inspectorate should be recruited on the basis of character and
                            competence from all participating states and should have international
                            status similar to that provided for the International
                            Secretariat.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>There should be routine inspections which should be automatic, and
                            such other inspections as the agency may decide upon. The inspectorate
                            will include nationals of member states other than the nation being
                            inspected.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>The international agency and its representatives should have no
                            authority to issue directions to contracting states, except as may be
                            provided in the treaty or treaties under which it is established.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>The size and composition of the inspectorate for any nation should be
                            determined by the international supervisory agency.</item>
                        <pb facs="0605" n="575" xml:id="pg_575"/>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>Individual members of the inspectorate should be rotated periodically
                            by nationality and geographic location.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>There should be no requirement of unanimity within the agency with
                            respect to its decisions within its defined functions.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>The system of safeguards, basically, should be composed of three
                            parts: <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>An accurate reporting by each nation of all essential elements
                                    of its military potential, and</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Accurate verification of reports by an international
                                    supervisory agency.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Effective inspection by an international supervisory
                                    agency.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>The system of international safeguards should be so devised that its
                            operations will be effective, technically feasible, and practicable, and
                            will: <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Detect promptly the occurrence of violations;</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Minimize interference with and impose minimum burdens on the
                                    economic and industrial life of the inspected nation.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>Each participating state should afford duly accredited representatives
                            of the agency unimpeded rights of ingress to and egress from, and
                            movement within its territories; should aid and assist them in the
                            performance of their duties, should provide access to the activities
                            subject to inspection, and should arrange for the full cooperation of
                            national or local authorities or private individuals.</item>
                        <label>12.</label>
                        <item>The agency will be responsible for immediate certification to the
                            Security Council and to all participating states, for appropriate
                            action, of serious or willful violations of a treaty or treaties
                            providing for the regulation and reduction of armaments.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>[Here follows Appendix “A,” “Discussion.”]</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>