<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-10-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-10-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="431" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d431">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of State Atomic Energy Files</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. <persName type="from">Theodore C. Achilles</persName> of the Division of <gloss type="to">Western European Affairs</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                            </placeName>], <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-10-03">October 3,
                                1947</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Belgian Participation in Industrial Application of
                        Atomic Energy</p>
                    <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">The Belgian Prime Minister</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">The Secretary (Ambassadors Silvercruys<note n="1" xml:id="d431fn1">Baron Silvercruys, Belgian Ambassador in
                                    the United States.</note> and van Langenhove<note n="2" xml:id="d431fn2">Fernand van Langenhove, Permanent Belgian
                                    Representative at the United Nations.</note> and Mr. Achilles
                                were present.)</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>M. Spaak stated that the continuing secrecy of the Belgian-United States
                        agreement on uranium was causing him increasing difficulties. Communist
                        insistence for disclosure of its terms had led many prominent non-Communists
                        to request information, but he had not yet felt at liberty to take even his
                        cabinet into his confidence. He said that the only real secret in the
                        agreement was its duration, and that he, for his part, saw no objection to
                        making the whole agreement public.</p>
                    <p>M. Spaak said that the pressure to which he was subjected had been
                        intensified by press reports that the atomic pile now being built in England
                        would be providing industrial power in a year or two. He thought that the
                        time had come to begin giving effect to the clause in the agreement
                        providing for Belgian participation on equitable terms in the benefits of
                        industrial utilization of atomic energy derived from Congo uranium.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary stated that he was not in the position to give a definite reply
                        at the moment, but that he would take up both points with his associates in
                        order that a definite answer might be given the Prime Minister without
                        delay.</p>
                    <p>M. Spaak stated that he would not press unduly his point on making the
                        agreement public. He would like, however, if pressed hard, to be able to say
                        that Belgian interests were fully safeguarded by provision in the agreement
                        for Belgium to share equitably in the benefits of industrial utilization.
                        That was the basic point. If a pile could be built in England to supply
                        electricity for the use of England, could not a second pile be built, and,
                        possibly at Belgium’s expense, to supply electricity to Belgium? The
                        scientists assured him transmission of the power from England to Belgium
                        would be practicable. He had not discussed this matter in any way with the
                        British.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary said that both psychological and technical problems were
                        involved. He understood the difficulties caused M. Spaak by Communist <pb facs="0872" n="842" xml:id="pg_842"/> propaganda. The United States was
                        facing similar problems in its efforts to secure international control of
                        atomic energy. Any public statement on the agreement would have to be very
                        carefully framed to minimize the propaganda advantages which might be taken
                        of any loopholes. As to the construction of atomic piles, he had had heavy
                        personal responsibilities in this field during the war. The width of the
                        Atlantic Ocean provided invaluable protection, and he had not been happy
                        over the decision to build a pile in England. However, M. Spaak’s suggestion
                        of a second pile in England to provide power for Belgium offered an
                        interesting possibility. He reiterated that a definite reply would be given
                        on the points M. Spaak had raised.</p>
                    <p>While leaving the building, van Langenhove asked Achilles if his
                        understanding was correct that our major worry was the construction of a
                        pile in Europe. He was advised that this was certainly one of our principal
                        worries.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>