<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Minutes of a Meeting of the Combined Policy Committee at the
                        Department of State, December 15, 1947, 3 p.m.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d449</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">449</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-12-15T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-12-15T15:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-12-15T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-12-15T15:00:00-05:00" n="449" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d449">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of State Atomic Energy Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of a Meeting of the Combined Policy Committee at the
                        Department of State, December 15, 1947, 3 p.m.</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1947-12-15T15:00:00-05:00">December 15, 1947, 3 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Present:</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">Members</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>The Acting Secretary of State (in the Chair) as alternate for the
                            Secretary of State</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>The Secretary of Defense</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>The Chairman of the United States Atomic Energy Commission</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>The British Ambassador, Lord Inverchapel</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Sir Gordon Munro</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>The Canadian Ambassador, Mr. Hume Wrong, as alternate for Mr. C. D.
                            Howe</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">By Invitation</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Dr. Bush</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Kennan</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Wilson</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Volpe</cell>
                    </row>
                    <pb facs="0928" n="898" xml:id="pg_898"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Admiral Sir Henry Moore</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Bateman</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Ignatieff</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Wells</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Dr. Cockroft</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Peirson</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Makins</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretariat</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Gullion</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Maclean</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Stone</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p rend="flushleft">I. <hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It was agreed that the minutes of the previous meeting,<note n="1" xml:id="d449fn1">December 10, <ref target="#pg_889">p. 889</ref>.</note>
                    together with the minutes of the present meeting, should be submitted for
                    approval at the next meeting.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">II. <hi rend="italic">Procedure</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lovett</hi> suggested that the procedure of the present
                    meeting should be to consider the reports of the sub-groups appointed at the
                    meeting on Wednesday, December 10th.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">III. <hi rend="italic">Information</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lovett</hi> said that the committee had before it the
                    report (appended to these minutes as Tab A)<note n="2" xml:id="d449fn2">December
                        12, <ref target="#pg_894">p. 894</ref>.</note> of the sub-group on the
                    exchange of scientific and technical information. He asked Dr. Bush to comment
                    on this report.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. Bush</hi> said that the report indicated nine areas in
                    which the cooperation in scientific and technical fields might appropriately be
                    started at the present time. The sub-group were unanimously agreed that the
                    areas defined represented a good start but that the list was not exclusive. He
                    said that further definition would be necessary.</p>
                <p>It was generally agreed that clear definitions of these areas of cooperation
                    would be developed as discussions went on between the experts concerned and that
                    other areas will be found where interchange of information is desirable. It was
                    emphasized in the discussion that the areas defined by the technical sub-group
                    were the immediately desirable areas of exchange of information and technical
                    cooperation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lovett</hi> observed that the report of the sub-group
                    represented a notable advance in the field of technical cooperation and wished
                    to be sure that all members of the committee agreed that this was not an
                    exclusive list. He suggested that there should be some continuing group of
                    technicians qualified to keep possible fields of exchange under <pb facs="0929" n="899" xml:id="pg_899"/> review. This is the type of thing which does not
                    lend itself to definition or absolute limits. It would be necessary to redefine
                    and establish boundaries as we go along.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lilienthal</hi> emphasized that the exchange of
                    information was a continuing process of interpretation and establishment of new
                    areas from time to time.</p>
                <p>It was generally agreed that this meeting of minds on the desirability of
                    exchanging information should be clearly recorded in these minutes, with a
                    reference to III (A) in the minutes of the <gloss target="#t_CPC1">C.P.C.</gloss> meeting of December 10th.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lovett</hi> desired it to be recorded that the report
                    of the subgroup on information was accepted with thanks and that discussions
                    would continue on a technical level.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">IV. <hi rend="italic">Materials</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lovett</hi> said that the sub-group on materials had
                    submitted factual reports (appended to these minutes as Tab B and Tab C)<note n="3" xml:id="d449fn3">Neither printed.</note> on the supply and
                    requirements situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord Inverchapel</hi> noted that in the United Kingdom view
                    the report of the sub-group reflected a conservative estimate of supplies and
                    that the situation was perhaps not as bad as it appeared.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wilson</hi> drew attention to the fact that the report
                    of the subgroup was in two parts—one on supply, the figures of which were based
                    on the judgment of specialists, and one on requirements, which showed two levels
                    of United States operations and one level of United Kingdom operations and also
                    a note on Canadian needs.</p>
                <p>There was some discussion of the figures as presented by the subgroup from which
                    it developed as follows: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The fall-off in Congo production in 1949 is explained by the fact that
                            the figures given are based upon all of the nigh grade ore in
                            sight—subsequent to 1948 lower grade ores will have to be
                            processed.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>While the table of requirements shows a maximum and minimum level of
                            operation for the United States, it shows only one level of operation
                            for the United Kingdom. Mr. Makins explained this by saying that the
                            United States figures represented the requirements of a continuing
                            operation while the United Kingdom figures represented the requirements
                            of a starting operation. In answer to a question by Mr. Wilson, Mr.
                            Makins said that the United Kingdom figures represented the supplies
                            required for presently authorized plans and did not include additional
                            supplies which would be required for a diffusion plant, the installation
                            of which was presently under consideration.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lovett</hi> observed that it seemed to him that a
                    sub-committee should now be authorized to examine the problem of how to
                    reconcile supply and demand.</p>
                <pb facs="0930" n="900" xml:id="pg_900"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord Inverchapel</hi> again emphasized that the picture as
                    presented was conservative and that in addition to the points which he had
                    previously mentioned (hopes for more ore from the Congo and possibly other
                    sources) there was the possibility of economy in the use of material, especially
                    through the re-working of sludges, a field in which British scientists were
                    conducting promising research.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that a sub-committee should commence its work with all possible
                    speed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wilson</hi> said that in his view the sub-committee in
                    its approach to the problem of supply and demand should bear in mind: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>That while the Congo is the principal source and that while there is
                            always the possibility of developing new strata of high grade ore there,
                            there is always the possibility that the mines may be played out, plus
                            the possibility of technical or political problems arising which might
                            retard or cut off deliveries.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>That while the estimates of South African production represented the
                            best judgement of the experts, uranium will be extracted there by new
                            processes which might be expedited but which might also be delayed by
                            unforeseeable technical difficulties.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>As regards requirements, while one must recognize the efforts being
                            made towards economy in the use of materials and in improved processes,
                            these were not yet sure enough to be guaranteed by anyone.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wilson</hi> affirmed that the statistical picture as
                    presented by the sub-group was the “coldest” estimate of the supply situation
                    over the period under review. He suggested that the sub-group be now given
                    directions as to how to proceed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Peirson</hi> recalled that 12 months ago an almost
                    equally discouraging picture on the Congo situation, as regards high grade ores,
                    had been presented, but at the close of the year it was found that high grade
                    ore was, in fact, available for a further year’s mining.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lovett</hi> observed that this was encouraging but
                    nevertheless the committee must balance supply and consumption. He suggested
                    that the sub-group be reconstituted to include non-technical members. He thought
                    that this reconstituted group might receive further guidance from the <gloss target="#t_CPC1">C.P.C.</gloss> and he asked the Secretary of Defense if he
                    had any observations to make on this point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Forrestal</hi> said that he was encouraged to hear that
                    there were prospects of continuing Congo production. He, however, preferred to
                    proceed on the basis of more pessimistic assumptions. He pointed out that as a
                    result of the military planning of the United States, the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                    have put demands on the Atomic Energy Commission for increased
                    production—demands the importance of which, in his view, has been emphasized by
                    events of the past week. He thought that nations in the East must be impressed
                    with the true facts—policy must never outstrip power, and power must be based on
                    fact. These were the governing considerations in United States planning. He
                    personally <pb facs="0931" n="901" xml:id="pg_901"/> regarded Canada and the
                    United Kingdom as partners in the field. He thought that the joint approach of
                    the three countries to these problems should be in this spirit. He recognized
                    that each of the three countries has domestic problems in this regard but he
                    expressed the hope that the partnership would have a meaning backed up by
                    fact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lovett</hi> thanked the Secretary for his frank
                    statement and suggested the naming of a further sub-group to consider the
                    problem of materials and requirements.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that this group would consist of:</p>
                <table cols="2" rows="3">
                    <row>
                        <cell>For the United States:</cell>
                        <cell>Messrs. Kennan and Wilson</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>For the United Kingdom:</cell>
                        <cell>Messrs. Munro and Makins</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>For Canada:</cell>
                        <cell>Messrs. Wrong and Stone</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p rend="flushleft">V. <hi rend="italic">Other Questions</hi>
                </p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Standards of Security</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lilienthal</hi> drew attention to the need of having
                    common standards of security, especially in relation to the exchange of
                    information. He thought that this was a matter in which there was complete
                    agreement as to intention, that no policy questions were involved and that the
                    problem was, therefore, one of drafting.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Nomenclature</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lilienthal</hi> drew attention to the desirability of
                    changing the name of the Combined Development Trust. It was emphasized that the
                    reasons for this were purely political and related to the Congo contracts.
                    Several suggestions were made, e.g., the CD. Trading Organization, the CD.
                    Traders Ltd. It was agreed that an examination of the legal position should be
                    made, assuming that the name became the CD. Trading Organization. If no legal
                    problems arose the change could be made forthwith.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Basis of Future Cooperation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord Inverchapel</hi> suggested that the drafts of 1946
                    provided starting point for discussion. He said that on the United Kingdom side
                    thinking was in the direction of a minute of the <gloss target="#t_CPC1">C.P.C.</gloss>, which would be confirmed by the three governments.</p>
                <p>It was generally agreed that having a minute of the <gloss target="#t_CPC1">C.P.C.</gloss> was a desirable approach to the problem and that a drafting
                    sub-committee should be set up at once.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lovett</hi> drew attention to the constitutional
                    difficulty in the United States of determining the form of an international
                    understanding in these matters from the point of view of executive-legislative
                    relationships. He pointed out that it would be unfortunate if the present
                    arrangements in respect to the old agreements had to be discussed in detail by
                    Congress. He felt that the present situation was an unhappy one and that we
                    should try to provide clear statements of intentions which would obviate the
                    possibility of old misunderstandings arising again. He thought, therefore, that
                    one paper should be <pb facs="0932" n="902" xml:id="pg_902"/> drafted which
                    would set out intent and purpose and that this paper should be put up to each
                    government as a recommendation and, after approval, be incorporated in the
                    minutes of the <gloss target="#t_CPC1">C.P.C.</gloss>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Forrestal</hi> expressed agreement and said that the
                    language of this paper should express intent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wrong</hi> raised the question of registration under
                    Article 102.<note n="4" xml:id="d449fn4">Reference is to the United Nations
                        Charter.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lovett</hi> agreed that registration would present
                    difficulties from the security point of view. He thought that the solution under
                    discussion was best calculated to meet this problem.</p>
                <p>After further discussion a drafting group was set up to consist of the
                    following:</p>
                <table cols="2" rows="3">
                    <row>
                        <cell>United States:</cell>
                        <cell>Messrs. Gullion and Volpe</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>United Kingdom:</cell>
                        <cell>Messrs. Peirson and Maclean</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Canada:</cell>
                        <cell>Messrs. Ignatieff and Stone</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Requests for Assistance from certain
                        Commonwealth Countries in the field of Technical Information</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord Inverchapel</hi> drew the attention of the committee
                    to requests received by the United Kingdom, particularly from Australia and New
                    Zealand, for information and assistance in the scientific and technical
                    field.</p>
                <p>In reply the United States members pointed out that frank exchanges of views in
                    the <gloss target="#t_CPC1">C.P.C.</gloss> were only possible on the assumption
                    that reports of the discussions were not made available to any non-<gloss target="#t_CPC1">C.P.C.</gloss> country. They emphasized that insofar as the
                    United States was concerned the law by which they were governed precluded such
                    exchanges except where it was clear that they could be regarded as in the
                    interest of the National Security of the United States. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                        Lovett</hi> particularly pointed out that under the Atomic Energy Act
                    consideration of common defense and National Security offered latitude for
                    cooperation with other countries. Insofar as Canada and the United States were
                    concerned the case seemed to be clear considering the importance of each to
                    common defense and National Security. In this connection he referred
                    specifically to joint continental defense planning as between the United States
                    and Canada.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Cockroft</hi> suggested that there would be found
                    certain areas of exchange of information with non-<gloss target="#t_CPC1">C.P.C.</gloss> countries which might be justified within the terms
                    indicated. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lilienthal</hi> cited as an example long
                    range detection.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that such cases should be discussed on their merits by appropriate
                    technical advisers.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Publicity</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord Inverchapel</hi> suggested that the view of the United
                    Kingdom was that there should be no publicity on the current discussions.</p>
                <pb facs="0933" n="903" xml:id="pg_903"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lovett</hi> agreed insofar as any reference to the
                        <gloss target="#t_CPC1">C.P.C.</gloss> was concerned. He thought that some
                    reference might be made to the existing deadlock in the <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">U.N.A.E.C.</gloss>, and possibly to its effect on U.S.
                    foreign policy in the President’s message in January to Congress on the State of
                    the Union. He thought that the present false sense of security on the part of
                    the public required correction. This reference, however, would not include any
                    mention of present discussions in the <gloss target="#t_CPC1">C.P.C.</gloss>
                </p>
                <p>In answer to a question from Mr. Ignatieff, Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                    said that this reference would not raise any question as to the validity of the
                    majority plan—on the contrary, the majority plan would probably be the
                    springboard from which it would take off, placing emphasis on the discouraging
                    attitude of the two minority members of the Commission.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lilienthal</hi> pointed out that present discussions of
                    the <gloss target="#t_CPC1">C.P.C.</gloss> would be reported fully to the Joint
                    Congressional Committee on Atomic Energy.</p>
                <p>As regards any statement to the public, if one should become necessary, he
                    suggested that present discussions of the <gloss target="#t_CPC1">C.P.C.</gloss>
                    should be explained as a continuation of long standing cooperation which is
                    already public knowledge.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that the next meeting of the <gloss target="#t_CPC1">C.P.C.</gloss>
                    would be held on Wednesday, December 17th, at 4:00 p.m.<note n="5" xml:id="d449fn5">The Combined Policy Committee did not meet again in
                        1947.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Edmund A. Gullion</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Donald D. Maclean</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas A. Stone</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
