<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>131. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d131</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">131</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-10-10T11:20:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-10-10T12:05:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-10-10T12:05:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-10-10T11:20:00-05:00" n="131"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d131">
                <head>131. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d131fn1"
                        >Source: <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> Library, National
                        Security Adviser, Memoranda of Conversations, Box 6, <persName
                            corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> Administration. Secret; <gloss
                            target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. The meeting was held in the Oval
                        Office. According to the President’s Daily Diary, the meeting lasted until
                        1:05 p.m. (Ibid., Staff Secretary’s Office) All brackets are in the
                        original.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_imprecise-inferred-from-outside-research"
                            calendar="gregorian" from="1975-10-10T12:20:00-04:00"
                            to="1975-10-10T13:05:00-04:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            >October 10, 1975, 12:15 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>President <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Maj. Gen. <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Ernesto de Melo Antunes</persName>,
                        Minister of Foreign Affairs of Portugal</item>
                    <item>Amb. Joao Hall Themido, Portuguese Ambassador</item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>, Secretary
                        of State and Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                    <item>Lt. Gen. <persName corresp="#p_SBC_1">Brent Scowcroft</persName>, Deputy
                        Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                </list>
                <p>[The press entered for photographs. There was a discussion of the <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName> meeting in Bonn in May and
                        <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName>’ first visit to the United
                    States. The press then left.]</p>
                <p>The President: How long will you be here?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName>: I will be returning right away.
                    There are many things pending in Lisbon. I am staying over a day, though,
                    because you are kind enough to receive me.</p>
                <p>The President: That was good of you. We have a great interest in developments in
                    your country. We are encouraged by what has happened recently. We congratulate
                    you on the strong stand that you and your associates have taken and we think it
                    is very important to the West.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName>: Thank you. I am sure you know
                    there are important things afoot and I am eminently aware of the importance of
                    this to the West and I know you are aware of the role that I and my associates
                    have played in the building of democracy. I want to assure you that we will
                    continue.</p>
                <p>The President: We want to support that in the proper way, and we agree the
                    Portuguese people want to support that democratic development.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName>: Regarding those sentiments of
                    the Portuguese people. I am convinced that the capacity of the Portuguese people
                    is adequate to the task, and I think the sentiments of the people will be
                    correctly confirmed in the coming elections. I think the people will justify the
                    confidence of the West.</p>
                <pb facs="0363" n="324" xml:id="pg_324"/>
                <p>The President: I was pleased by the vote last spring and I was pleased to see
                    that the most recent Cabinet was limited in Communist participation.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> is meeting with you
                    again later today,<note n="2" xml:id="d131fn2">During <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s meeting with <persName
                            corresp="#p_AEM_1">Melo Antunes</persName> at 3 p.m. that afternoon, the
                        two men discussed the issue of military equipment left behind in Angola in
                        some detail. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> said: “Our
                        concern is that the <gloss target="#t_MPLA_1">MPLA</gloss> has received
                        considerable amounts of Soviet equipment. We are very concerned that if the
                        other Africans see that the Soviet Union can be this effective such a long
                        distance away, it will affect the whole African situation, even though
                        Angola may not be directly involved. We therefore hope very much that you
                        will not make available to the <gloss target="#t_MPLA_1">MPLA</gloss> the
                        arms that you leave behind. We are strengthening <persName corresp="#p_SJ_2"
                            >Savimbi</persName> and the <gloss target="#t_FNLA_1">FNLA</gloss> and I
                        agree with what you said to the President this morning about this being a
                        formula for civil war. But at a minimum we do not want the
                        communist-supported side to win, and this has certain parallels with
                        Portugal.” (Library of Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box CL 274, Memoranda of
                        Conversations, Chronological File, August–November 1975)</note> but I want
                    to say now that we are increasing our assistance to you, both for the refugees
                    and to rebuild your economy.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName>: With regard to participation of
                    Communists in the government, the recent prolonged crisis has revealed that the
                    Communist Party does not represent the aspirations of the people. In another
                    vote I am convinced they would get only 6–7%. The minor role they have in the
                    government represents that minor role.</p>
                <p>We appreciate your announcement of economic help. We are very grateful. But you
                    should know that our needs are enormous—both as a result of the past government
                    and the recent revolutionary governments. I will be talking to Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> about this.</p>
                <p>The President: We are pleased to be able to help. We plan to help further with
                    the evacuation of refugees, and I understand that this is on the basis that you
                    will not leave military equipment in Angola, when you leave, for the <gloss
                        target="#t_MPLA_1">MPLA</gloss>.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName>: We are very grateful for the
                    refugee assistance. It has been valuable, and anything you can do will be a
                    vital help in stabilizing the situation in Portugal.</p>
                <p>I already told your Ambassador that we won’t help any of the factions in Angola,
                    so we won’t leave any equipment at all, based on our policy of neutrality among
                    them.</p>
                <p>The President: We deplore the fighting. Is there any prospect of a settlement
                    prior to the independence date of November 11?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName>: As I said to the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>, our position remains in favor of a conference
                    of the three movements, together with us and representatives of Africa chosen by
                    the three, to settle the situation in accordance with this conference. There
                    should be a settlement which would provide national unity and therefore there
                    should be a government <pb facs="0364" n="325" xml:id="pg_325"/> formed which
                    can receive these powers. This is our last effort in Angola, but I am optimistic
                    now, even if a political solution is achieved as a result of this conference. I
                    think civil war will continue.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Do you think <persName
                        corresp="#p_NA_1">Neto</persName> is a Communist?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName>: I think he is pretty close,
                    although it is difficult to classify him as an orthodox Communist. We all are
                    aware of the support he has received from the Soviet Union and other Socialist
                    countries, primarily from the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>The President: What about <persName corresp="#p_RHA_1">Roberto</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_SJ_2">Savimbi</persName>?</p>
                <p>[Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> leaves the meeting
                    at this point.]</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName>: In regard to <persName
                        corresp="#p_RHA_1">Roberto</persName>, he has no solid political background.
                    He is easily corruptible and dependent on <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1"
                        >Mobutu</persName>. Of the three factions I would say <persName
                        corresp="#p_SJ_2">Savimbi</persName> is the most intelligent, the most able
                    and the strongest politically. Some question his political judgment. He has
                    played on all sides and has switched supporters from outside. I think he will
                    end up losing popularity because of these actions. But at the present moment he
                    has considerable support from Zaire and Zambia, while <persName
                        corresp="#p_NA_1">Neto</persName>, because of his bull-headedness, has lost
                    some of that support.</p>
                <p>The President: They have all been involved in decolonization?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName>: Yes, so all of them have been
                    involved in fighting against the Portuguese regime.</p>
                <p>The President: With the refugees leaving, do they have the capability of running
                    the economy?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName>: From what I know of Angola—and
                    I am familiar with it in depth—we will see administrative and economic chaos.
                    They don’t have the numbers needed to maintain it.</p>
                <p>The President: What will happen to Cabinda?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName>: Cabinda is now characterized by
                    a separatist tendency, aided by native Cabindans, supported by Zaire and
                    Congo-Brazzaville. So it will probably be separated, with grave consequences to
                    Angola because of its economic value.</p>
                <p>The President: We are very sympathetic with what you are doing, and I hope you
                    will convey our support for what your group is doing and we will do our best to
                    help. What you are doing is in the best interest of the West, and free societies
                    around the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName>: Thank you for your expression
                    of support. Our struggle is truly a difficult one. We will go the whole route to
                    achieve a free society. We are facing a real struggle against obstructionist
                    groups and we need all your help.</p>
                <p>The President: This meeting with you is much more encouraging than the one I had
                    in Brussels with Goncalves. It appeared then that the <pb facs="0365" n="326"
                        xml:id="pg_326"/> will of the Portuguese people was not being expressed. We
                    will help all we can and I give you my very best wishes and those of the
                    American people.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AEM_1">Antunes</persName>: Thank you, Mr. President. I
                    want to say how much I appreciate your receiving me and your offer of help. This
                    has been a fruitful dialogue which should lead to new cooperation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
