<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-11-01T19:20:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-11-01T19:20:00-05:00" n="133" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d133">
                        <head>133. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Consulate in Luanda</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d133fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy Files.
                                Secret; Niact Immediate. Drafted by Fugit; cleared in AF/EX, OC/T,
                                SY, M, S, and <gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss>; and approved by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MEW_1">Mulcahy</persName>. Repeated
                                Immediate to Lisbon.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-11-02T00:20:00+00:00">November 2, 1975,
                                0020Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>259582. Subject: Angolan Contingency Planning. Ref: Luanda 1720 <gloss target="#t_Notal_1">Notal</gloss>.<note n="2" xml:id="d133fn2">In
                                telegram 1720 from Luanda, November 2, <persName corresp="#p_KT_1">Killoran</persName> reported on the logistical problems
                                associated with closing the Luanda post. (Ibid.)</note> For
                                <persName corresp="#p_KT_1">Killoran</persName> from <persName corresp="#p_MEW_1">Mulcahy</persName>.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Department decided close <gloss target="#t_ConGen_1">ConGen</gloss> prior Nov. 11, on date to be determined. We
                                believe that advantage should be taken of the last scheduled refugee
                                flight on Nov. 3 to reduce personnel and sensitive material to
                                absolute minimum. You are authorized to depart. You should choose
                                either Rodgers or Doubleday to remain and retain one State
                                communicator and comtech. Agency will communicate directly with COS
                                on their per. questions, etc.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In separate message <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> will
                                authorize you to hold last relief flight until all is in readiness
                                to depart. This will provide you with some flexibility for loading
                                    <gloss target="#t_ConGen_1">ConGen</gloss> personnel, equipment
                                and those American, British and Canadian citizens who decide to
                                seize this last opportunity to depart on relief flight. You are
                                authorized to discreetly inform these citizens of our plans to
                                reduce staff to minimum, and you should strongly urge them to
                                depart. <gloss target="#t_ConGen_1">ConGen</gloss> equipment and
                                    <gloss target="#t_HHE_1">HHE</gloss> of staff will be given
                                priority on baggage space ahead of refugee effects.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_ConGen_1">ConGen</gloss> personnel should remain
                                in Lisbon pending further instructions. Orders will be transmitted
                                Lisbon.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>All <gloss target="#t_WATTS_1">WATTS</gloss> equipment should be
                                loaded aboard Nov. 3 flight. Backup <gloss target="#t_RTTY_1">RTTY</gloss> system should be retained.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">For Lisbon and Luanda:</hi> Inform the <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> and the High Commissioner that in
                                view of the sharp deterioration in security conditions in Luanda, we
                                are reducing our official presence to a minimum and may decide to
                                close the Consulate General before Nov. 11.</item>
                            <pb facs="0368" n="329" xml:id="pg_329"/>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">For Luanda:</hi> Request that you ask High
                                Commissioner if we could evacuate few remaining <gloss target="#t_ConGen_1">ConGen</gloss> personnel and small amount
                                of baggage and equipment aboard last Portuguese frigate we
                                understand will depart Nov. 10. We would utilize this only as a
                                contingency if air travel not feasible.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">For Lisbon:</hi> Appreciate your help in assisting
                                three or four <gloss target="#t_ConGen_1">ConGen</gloss> personnel
                                who would have to remain in Lisbon pending Department
                                decision.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>We all are well aware and proud of your efforts and those of the
                                entire staff throughout the last grueling weeks. The reporting,
                                airlift and protection of citizens has been superb.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Kissinger</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>