<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-11-28T17:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-11-28T17:45:00-05:00" n="142" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d142">
                        <head>142. Message From the <gloss type="from">Soviet Government</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">United States Government</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d142fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> Library, National Security Adviser, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_SBC_1">Scowcroft</persName> West Wing Office Files,
                                Box 30, General Subject File, <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>—<persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Exchanges, Items 98–105. No classification
                                marking. <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> sent this
                                message under cover of a November 28 letter to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>. A handwritten notation
                                on the letter reads: “Delivered to State Department at 5:45 p.m.,
                                11/28/75.”</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1975-11-28T17:45:00-05:00">undated</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Assertions made in the approach by the State Department of November
                                22<note n="2" xml:id="d142fn2">
                                <ref target="#d140">Document 140</ref>.</note> concerning the Soviet
                            position with regard to Angola could not be viewed other than as an
                            attempt to divert attention from the real causes underlining the events
                            which are taking place in that country.</p>
                        <p>As has already been stated earlier to the US Government the information
                            disseminated in the USA alleging mass shipments of arms by the Soviet
                            Union to Angola and the presence there of “hundreds” of Soviet military
                            personnel is without foundation. Not a single Soviet man is taking part
                            in the hostilities in Angola. Likewise the Soviet side rejects
                            assertions that it is the support by the Soviet Union of the legitimate
                            Government of the People’s Republic of Angola, which is recognized
                            already by many states in the world, [that] is the cause of what is
                            going on in Angola.</p>
                        <p>The real causes of that are an open secret. It is well known that the
                            foreign monopolies which for scores of years were masters in the land
                                <pb facs="0398" n="359" xml:id="pg_359"/> of Angola were in no way
                            happy by the beginning of the process of decolonization in this country
                            which was bound inevitably to lead and had led to the victory of the
                            national patriotic forces. That was why even prior to the granting of
                            independence certain foreign circles banked on splitting the national
                            liberation movement in the country and encouraged and supported
                            militarily those separatist movements which bound themselves with
                            foreign interests.</p>
                        <p>Now the events have reached the point when a direct intervention of
                            neocolonialist forces has begun in Angola, in the first place, on the
                            part of the Republic of South Africa. Regular units of the <gloss target="#t_SAR_1">SAR</gloss>, detachments of South African and
                            Rhodesian mercenaries are participating in the military actions. It is
                            also known that these groupings receive an extensive aid, including
                            military aid, from the United States. In other words, the original cause
                            of the continuing bloodshed in Angola lies in the interference into the
                            internal affairs of that country by the forces, which do not wish to
                            reconcile themselves to the loss of their position there. And the US
                            Government knows all this.</p>
                        <p>As far as the Soviet Union is concerned, being a consistent supporter of
                            the liquidation of remnants of colonialism, it recognized the People’s
                            Republic of Angola and its Government, formed by the Popular Movement
                            for the Liberation of Angola (<gloss target="#t_MPLA_1">MPLA</gloss>),
                            which enjoys a wide support of the Angolan people as a leading national
                            patriotic organization. It is not by chance that by the present moment
                            the People’s Republic of Angola has been already recognized by nearly 30
                            states of the world, half of which are the African countries—members of
                            the Organization of African Unity (<gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss>). It shows in itself the groundlessness of statements that
                            the Soviet position on this question supposedly contradicts the position
                            of the African states.</p>
                        <p>It is also known that after concluding in January 1975 an agreement among
                            the three Angolan movements on the order of granting independence to
                            Angola and on establishing a transitional Government with the
                            participation in it of representatives of those movements the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> welcomed the creation of such a
                            Government.</p>
                        <p>Yet, shortly after, the <gloss target="#t_FNLA_1">FNLA</gloss> and the
                                <gloss target="#t_UNITA_1">UNITA</gloss> embarked on the path of
                            undermining the transitional Government thus frustrating its normal
                            functioning and eventually starting military actions which were
                            encouraged and supported from outside.</p>
                        <p>The Soviet Union never was and could not be in favour of unleashing a
                            civil war in Angola. It has always supported and is acting in support of
                            the aspirations of the Angolan patriotic forces, as well as of the
                            efforts of the African states designed to ensure national independence
                            and peaceful development of Angola. The Soviet Union would only welcome
                            such mode of action which would be pursuing the goal <pb facs="0399" n="360" xml:id="pg_360"/> of consolidating in Angola all the forces
                            that are striving for a genuine independence and free development of
                            this country.</p>
                        <p>The Soviet Union firmly adheres to the position that armed aggression in
                            Angola be seized and the right of its people be safeguarded to decide by
                            itself how to build the new life under conditions of independence and
                            territorial integrity without any outside interference.</p>
                        <p>The Soviet Union is prepared to state publicly about it. If the USA is
                            also prepared to make a similar statement and act accordingly, we would
                            welcome this.</p>
                        <p>In the light of the above-stated, attempts to lay some sort of blame on
                            the Soviet Union for the present developments in Angola are devoid of
                            any foundation. Equally groundless are the endeavors to present this
                            matter in such a way as if the policy of the Soviet Union toward Angola
                            is not consistent with the Soviet-American documents.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>