<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>195. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d195</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">195</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1976-04-27T02:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1976-04-27T02:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recLEJU0igInf5ESh" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005905"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Apartheid</term>
                    <term ref="recyQwssZrUcxu4Pw" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-04-27T02:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-04-27T02:00:00-05:00" n="195"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d195">
                <head>195. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d195fn1"
                        >Source: Library of Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box CL 99, Geopolitical
                        File, Africa, Trips, 1976, Apr.–May, Resource Book. Secret; <gloss
                            target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. Initialed by <persName
                            corresp="#p_HHE_1">Horan</persName>. The meeting was held at State
                        House. Brackets are in the original.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Lusaka</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1976-04-27T09:00:00+02:00"
                            >April 27, 1976, 9 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kenneth Kaunda</persName>, President of
                        Zambia</item>
                    <item>Elijah Mudenda, Prime Minister</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BR_1">Rupiah Banda</persName>, Minister of Foreign
                        Affairs</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MSG_1">Seteke Mwale</persName>, Zambian Ambassador to
                        the U.S.</item>
                    <item>Grey Zulu, Secretary General, U.N.I.P.</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CM_2">Mark Chona</persName>, Special Assistant to the
                        President for Foreign Affairs</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KP_1">Peter Kasanda</persName>, Deputy to <persName
                            corresp="#p_CM_2">Mark Chona</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ruben Kamanga, Chairman, Sub-Committee on Political, Legal, Constitutional
                        and Foreign Affairs United Nat’l Independence Party Central Committee</item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>, Secretary
                        of State</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Charles W. Robinson</persName>, Deputy
                        Secretary of State</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WJM_1">Jean M. Wilkowski</persName>, U.S. Ambassador
                        to Zambia</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SWE_1">William E. Schaufele, Jr.</persName>, Assistant
                        Secretary for African Affairs</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_LW_1">Winston Lord</persName>, Director, Policy
                        Planning Staff</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HHE_1">Harold E. Horan</persName>, Senior Staff
                        Member, National Security Council (Notetaker)</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName>: I want to welcome you, Mr.
                    Secretary, to Zambia, and I know that my colleagues had the opportunity to
                    extend their welcome yesterday on your arrival. We would like you to know that
                    this is a very welcome visit. You are the second Secretary of State who has
                    visited here, and we also had a visit by Vice President <persName
                        corresp="#p_HHH_1">Humphrey</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: How long did he speak?
                    (Laughter)</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName>: Quite a short time. (Laughter)
                    Mr. Secretary, when I was in Washington last year and met your President,<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d195fn2">See <ref target="#d103">Document 103</ref>.</note> I
                    said that southern Africa was at a turning point and that the situation was very
                    worrisome <pb facs="0534" n="495" xml:id="pg_495"/> indeed. We have been
                    operating as a team cooperating on two common programs, and I will explain in
                    more detail in our enlarged meeting. I will confine myself here to what I see of
                    the solutions your Government might wish to participate in.</p>
                <p>As far as Rhodesia is concerned, we don’t see any solution to the problem as long
                    as Smith is there. His record shows that we have to get <persName
                        corresp="#p_VBJ_1">Vorster</persName> involved because he is Smith’s
                    colonial master in the area, but still the only solution is for Smith to get
                    out. But how do we do this? We don’t know, but we have to work together to find
                    a way. We have to fight and the African countries are backing the liberation
                    groups to the hilt. Smith depends very much on the white settlers, and we would
                    like to believe that the Western Governments can support moves to erode that
                    support. If the British, French, West Germans and others would help to
                    underwrite the certain financial losses that some of the settlers might suffer,
                    this would accomplish an outflow of the settlers if they would then see they
                    could go to places like Australia to begin a new life. We would also like to
                    believe that the United States could pressure <persName corresp="#p_VBJ_1"
                        >Vorster</persName> to be more cooperative now that Mozambique has closed
                    its borders. South Africa is the key to Rhodesia. I know that your Government
                    fears Russian and Cuban interference in Rhodesia, but I also know of no African
                    leader who has spoken of this possibility. We do not want to see outside
                    interference at all, and we would not like to see outside support for factions
                    in Rhodesia. They should be left alone; that is the only way to avoid an Angolan
                    situation in Rhodesia. Once the United States Government understands the problem
                    clearly I see no chance of outside interference.</p>
                <p>On Namibia our stand is clear, and the role the U.S. should play is most
                    important. In defying the United Nations, <persName corresp="#p_VBJ_1"
                        >Vorster</persName> is saying that Namibia is his. We do not want Bantustans
                    in Namibia but one government, nor do we want to see interference from the
                    outside there, but the delays in independence make that possible. The role you
                    can play is to put pressure on South Africa to respect the decision of the
                    United Nations. Your influence on South Africa is important, and you could use
                    it to make <persName corresp="#p_VBJ_1">Vorster</persName> see sense. If he does
                    not, there will be fighting and dying.</p>
                <p>South Africa itself is an independent African state which is not a colonial
                    power, and we accept that fact. We do not, however, accept apartheid, and we
                    support those who are struggling to change apartheid. Once again, the United
                    States has a great deal to do with changing the situation in South Africa. South
                    Africa exists because of western commerce and investment.</p>
                <p>Whether in Rhodesia, Namibia or South Africa, African leaders have never said
                    they were chasing away anybody. We are all Africans, and the whites in South
                    Africa have their own right to live in their own <pb facs="0535" n="496"
                        xml:id="pg_496"/> country. But the issue of southern Africa is a question of
                    life and death. For you, Mr. Secretary, the question for your decision is what
                    you want to do to make life more meaningful for all. Your decision to come here
                    shows that you want to find solutions to the southern African problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Thank you for your kind
                    remarks. The warmth and friendship that you and your delegation have shown me
                    has meant a great deal to me. You are admired in my country for your courage and
                    wisdom. We remember well your remarks in Washington on the principles of
                    equality and your call on us to live up to these principles.</p>
                <p>We have come through a difficult period in the United States, but we have made
                    our decision. I don’t make ceremonial visits, and I am here to develop a
                    program. A few years ago it was said that we have no Middle East program, but
                    events belie that statement. While it is true that within the United States
                    there will be resistance to my speech today, we have made our decision. We are
                    totally behind majority rule, and we will work with the four presidents. You
                    appreciate, of course, that we cannot make public statements calling for armed
                    struggle. In any case, I hope you agree that any struggle must end in
                    negotiation.</p>
                <p>We will use our economic and diplomatic pressures on Rhodesia. My speech<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d195fn3">See <ref target="#d194fn3">footnote 3, Document
                            194</ref>.</note> appeals to <persName corresp="#p_VBJ_1"
                        >Vorster</persName> to bring an end to apartheid and set a timetable for the
                    independence of Namibia. I hope that African leaders will find an opportunity to
                    emphasize the positive in our position so that we will not be caught in a
                    crossfire of criticism.</p>
                <p>As for Zambia, we respect you as one of the intellectual and political leaders,
                    and we appreciate the cooperation we have received in certain matters. We want
                    to assist in your development, and after I return to Washington we will look at
                    new programs of assistance to Zambia.</p>
                <p>If foreign intervention is kept out of southern Africa, the United States can
                    give you its maximum support. I appreciate your idea of the need to help the
                    settlers find new homes, and we are prepared to assist economically in such a
                    program. It is important for the four presidents to refer to minority rights and
                    for any constitution to protect those rights. This will not keep many settlers
                    from leaving, but it is important for us psychologically. We have told the
                    British, by the way, that we will cooperate in any resettlement effort. There is
                    no longer any ambiguity. We support you.</p>
                <p>We see it as a practical matter. The first problem to tackle is Rhodesia, then
                    Namibia and lastly South Africa. We need South Africa’s help in solving the
                    other two problems, although I have stated in <pb facs="0536" n="497"
                        xml:id="pg_497"/> my speech that apartheid must end. Of course, we have no
                    problems with you or your Government, Mr. President.</p>
                <p>We are prepared to have normal relations with Mozambique, and I hope to see a
                    representative of that country in Nairobi. There is no organized hostility
                    against Mozambique in the United States, although some see it as a Soviet
                    satellite.</p>
                <p>Let me thank you once again, Mr. President, for receiving me and my delegation
                    and for your warm hospitality.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
