<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-09-21T02:20:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-09-21T02:20:00-05:00" n="207" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d207">
                        <head>207. Telegram From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1" type="from">Kissinger</persName> to the President’s Assistant for
                            National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SBC_1" type="to">Scowcroft</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d207fn1">Source: Library of Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box CL 266,
                                Cables File, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger,
                                    Henry</persName>, August 7–September 23, 1976. Secret;
                                Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes Only. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> was presumably en route to Dar es
                                Salaam.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-09-21T07:20:00+00:00">September 21, 1976, 0720Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_Hakto_1">Hakto</gloss> 27. 1. Please pass following
                            report to President.</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Begin text:</hi> From Pretoria I flew to Lusaka,
                            Zambia, Monday to report to President <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> what I had obtained from <persName corresp="#p_VBJ_1">Vorster</persName> and Smith.<note n="2" xml:id="d207fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> met with <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> September 20, 1:45–4:43 p.m.
                                at State House in Lusaka. A memorandum of conversation is ibid., CL
                                345, Department of State, Memoranda, Memoranda of Conversations,
                                External, September 20–23, 1976.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>3. I went over with <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> in a
                            three-hour private meeting the Rhodesia program that Smith had
                            accepted—the five points I reported to you yesterday, for majority rule
                            in two years and an immediate provisional government. I told him this is
                            what they had been seeking for eleven years and now was the time to
                            move.</p>
                        <p>4. <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> was speechless, and I
                            think it took him a while to absorb what I was saying. After a long
                            pause, the first question he asked was what guarantee we had that this
                            would be carried out. I told him that Smith could have no illusion about
                            what it would mean to doublecross the U.S. and South Africa. He brought
                            some of his ministerial and party colleagues into the room and I went
                            over it again.</p>
                        <p>5. <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> expressed gratitude. As
                            I expected, he said that of course he would have to consult his fellow
                            presidents. He sent three of his closest advisers to make an immediate
                            tour of neighboring capitals. We agreed that after I saw <persName corresp="#p_NJ_2">Nyerere</persName> on Tuesday, I would come back
                            to either Dar or Lusaka to talk with them again.</p>
                        <p>6. Then I went over the Namibia concessions I had obtained from <persName corresp="#p_VBJ_1">Vorster</persName>—moving the Windhoek conference
                            to Geneva, inviting <gloss target="#t_SWAPO_1">SWAPO</gloss> to
                            participate, allowing <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> involvement,
                            and pledging South Africa to accept the results. On this <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> was even more positive. He
                            expressed satisfaction and believed this procedure would succeed. “We
                            can see light here.” If we could arrange that <persName corresp="#p_WK_1">Waldheim</persName> would simultaneously call a
                            Geneva conference, so the blacks could call it a new conference, <gloss target="#t_SWAPO_1">SWAPO</gloss> would probably go along. <gloss target="#t_SWAPO_1">SWAPO</gloss> is based in Lusaka, so <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> is attuned to <gloss target="#t_SWAPO_1">SWAPO</gloss>’s thinking.</p>
                        <p>7. I came back for a small dinner with the President and <persName corresp="#p_CM_2">Chona</persName>. We went over the Pretoria
                            meetings, the opportunity presented to Africa if Smith indeed announces
                            on Friday his support for the plan, and the <pb facs="0616" n="577" xml:id="pg_577"/> need for strong support from the African
                            presidents for the peace initiative in that event. He gives every
                            appearance of having decided to push it, and is turning his attention
                            most seriously now to lining up his fellow heads of state. Evidently he
                            shares my sense that <persName corresp="#p_NJ_2">Nyerere</persName> is
                            the question mark; if he will go along, the others will, too.</p>
                        <p>8. I will be in Dar es Salaam today, and we will know the answer.<note n="3" xml:id="d207fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> met with <persName corresp="#p_NJ_2">Nyerere</persName> at State House in Dar es
                                Salaam on September 21, 12:20–1:45 p.m. The Secretary briefed the
                                President on negotiations with <persName corresp="#p_VBJ_1">Vorster</persName> and Smith. <persName corresp="#p_NJ_2">Nyerere</persName> expressed concerns with arrangements for
                                both conferences, and argued that (a) the British should convene a
                                constitutional conference for Rhodesia before choosing an interim
                                government and (b) the Namibian constitutional conference could not
                                be an extension of the Windhoek conference. <persName corresp="#p_NJ_2">Nyerere</persName> was adamant that conference
                                participants include South Africa (the de facto power), Namibia
                                (represented by <gloss target="#t_SWAPO_1">SWAPO</gloss>), and the
                                United Nations. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                                suggested <persName corresp="#p_NJ_2">Nyerere</persName> meet with
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> to resolve any
                                issues of concern and clarify their position. A memorandum of
                                conversation is ibid.</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Kissinger</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>