<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>228. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    Zambia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d228</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">228</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1976-12-06T13:19:00-05:00" notAfter="1976-12-06T13:19:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-12-06T13:19:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-12-06T13:19:00-05:00" n="228"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d228">
                <head>228. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in Zambia</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d228fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1"
                            >Ford</persName> Library, National Security Adviser, Presidential
                        Country Files for Africa, Box 8, Zambia—State Department Telegrams, From
                            SecState—<gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss> (2). Confidential;
                        Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> and approved by <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>. A similar letter was sent to
                            <persName corresp="#p_NJ_2">Nyerere</persName> in telegram 296389 to
                        Geneva, December 8. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss>
                        59, Central Foreign Policy Files)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1976-12-06T18:19:00+00:00">December 6, 1976,
                        1819Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>296386. For the Ambassador from the Secretary. Subject: Rhodesia Conference:
                    Message to President <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName>.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Please pass following message to President <persName corresp="#p_KK_1"
                            >Kaunda</persName> from the Secretary.<note n="2" xml:id="d228fn2">In
                            telegram 3259 from Lusaka, December 7, the Embassy reported that
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s message was
                            delivered to <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> at 11:30
                            local time December 7. (Ibid.)</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Dear Mr. President: <list>
                            <item>—I read with considerable interest Ambassador <persName
                                    corresp="#p_RJE_1">Reinhardt</persName>’s report of his meeting
                                with you of a week ago.<note n="3" xml:id="d228fn3">In telegram 3179
                                    from Lusaka, November 27, <persName corresp="#p_RJE_1"
                                        >Reinhardt</persName> reported on his meeting with <persName
                                        corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName>: “Meeting with <persName
                                        corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> marked by very frank,
                                    extended exchanges but with unsatisfactory results from our
                                    point of view. In effect, he is supporting <persName
                                        corresp="#p_CM_2">Chona</persName> position that Smith’s
                                    role in Geneva is to surrender without conditions. US–<gloss
                                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> role is to make certain that
                                    unconditional surrender is expeditious. Lamely argues that any
                                    insistence on negotiating with Smith is a ‘new element.’”
                                        (<persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> Library,
                                    National Security Adviser, Presidential Country Files for
                                    Africa, Box 8, Zambia—State Department Telegrams, To
                                        SecState—<gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>
                                    10/1/76–11/30/76)</note> I always admire your candor and
                                openness, and I greatly value your views. You have given generously
                                of your time in receiving my emissaries.</item>
                            <item>—I must tell you very frankly that I was disturbed by the
                                implication of your remarks to <persName corresp="#p_RJE_1"
                                    >Reinhardt</persName> with regard to the two-tier arrange<pb
                                    facs="0677" n="638" xml:id="pg_638"/>ment for the interim
                                    government.<note n="4" xml:id="d228fn4">Telegram 9102 from
                                    Geneva, November 15, transmitted the text of a British paper
                                    circulated to the conference participants outlining a proposal
                                    for the structure of the transitional government that called for
                                    separating the Council of Ministers from the legislative body,
                                    creating a two-tier system. (National Archives, <gloss
                                        target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy
                                    Files)</note> As you will recall, not only did I discuss this
                                concept with you during my first meetings with you in September, but
                                there were four preceding missions, American and British, which had
                                already discussed with you the basic structure of the proposed
                                interim government. While there may have been some questions
                                concerning the composition of the interim government, especially of
                                the Council of State, the concept of a sharing of power on the basis
                                of a two-tier system was never challenged. In addition, I want to
                                stress that at no time was there any suggestion that there should be
                                an immediate transfer of power to majority rule. This had never been
                                a consideration in our discussions, and it could not have been
                                because it is not workable or acceptable.</item>
                            <item>—It is important to remember what the exercise we are engaged in
                                at Geneva is all about. We are in Geneva to try to reach a
                                settlement that transfers power in Rhodesia from the hands of whites
                                who now hold it to Africans who rightfully deserve it.</item>
                            <item>—We are in Geneva to get a solution that offers the rest assurance
                                of a smooth transition to a moderate and responsible government, one
                                that can bring stability and prosperity to Zimbabwe, and one that
                                would not pose a threat to the stability of its neighbors, most
                                notably Zambia.</item>
                            <item>—We are disturbed by what we perceive to be a growing sense of
                                unreality in Geneva, not only among some of the nationalist
                                delegations, but also among the observers.</item>
                            <item>—Somehow, there appears an increasing tendency to ignore some of
                                the fundamental realities of the Rhodesian situation:</item>
                            <item>—The first of these realities is that <persName corresp="#p_SID_1"
                                    >Ian Smith</persName> and the Rhodesia Front hold de facto power
                                in Rhodesia, not the South Africans, not the British, and certainly
                                not the United States. No matter how much we may dislike that
                                situation, it is not something that can be wished away.</item>
                            <item>—The second, there are limitations on the degree of influence that
                                external powers can effectively exercise, especially for a
                                settlement that does not insure minority rights.</item>
                            <item>—The third point concerns those understandings which persuaded
                                Smith to accept, for the first time in his 12 years in power, the
                                principle of majority rule and the implementation of that principle
                                within a fixed time frame. Whatever one chooses to say about the
                                five points of Smith’s Sept. 24 speech, and particularly point 3,
                                there can be <pb facs="0678" n="639" xml:id="pg_639"/> no
                                disagreement over the fact that they were understood to form the
                                basis for negotiations.<note n="5" xml:id="d228fn5">See <ref
                                        target="#d206">Document 206</ref>.</note> They can be
                                altered in the course of a negotiation but they can not simply be
                                discarded in toto. Nor can there be any argument over the fact that
                                the concept that underlies the five points and that made possible
                                Smith’s acceptance of them—as well as that of his party—is the
                                concept that Rhodesian whites would be assured of a meaningful voice
                                and role in the political decisions in the transition period that
                                will affect their future in Zimbabwe. Moreover, the five points in
                                concept were discussed repeatedly with the front line presidents
                                before they were put forward.</item>
                            <item>—We have heard the view expressed by several persons in Geneva
                                that Smith and the Rhodesia Front may now be ready to abandon the
                                concept of shared power in the interim government in exchange for
                                vague and ambiguous promises or understandings. We have also heard
                                it said that the United States can deliver Smith upon demand and get
                                him to accept any alternative set of proposals that might be put
                                forward at the conference. With regard to the first point, nothing
                                Smith has said or implied since the opening of the conference offers
                                any suggestion that he is prepared to abandon the concept that
                                Rhodesia whites must have effective and clearly defined powers
                                within the interim government. With regard to the second, anyone who
                                thinks that we can persuade or coerce Smith into accepting a
                                settlement on terms that do not even take account of the five points
                                fails to understand the situation.</item>
                            <item>—Our assessment is that Smith and the Rhodesians are fully
                                prepared to fight on and to resist all forms of pressure if they do
                                not get the kind of settlement that they feel meets their minimum
                                requirements. We are especially concerned about the very evident
                                erosion of support in South Africa for a settlement, which could tie
                                    <persName corresp="#p_VBJ_1">Vorster</persName>’s hands and
                                prevent him from continuing his positive contributions not only with
                                respect to Zimbabwe but also Namibia.</item>
                            <item>—If there is no settlement, it is not the United States that will
                                suffer most directly from the consequences of that failure. Those
                                who will suffer most will be the Zimbabweans, who face the prospect
                                of having a whole generation of youth chewed up in needless
                                bloodshed, and whose only reward will be a country ravaged by war
                                and destruction.</item>
                            <item>—Zambia would pay a heavy price if the war is allowed to drag on,
                                and not merely in economic terms. Zambia already knows what it means
                                to have foreign armies living in armed camps on its soil and how
                                difficult it can be to control them. The Lebanese experience stands
                                as an example to all of how disruptive a force these armies can
                                become.</item>
                            <pb facs="0679" n="640" xml:id="pg_640"/>
                            <item>—You must also understand that if continuing violence leads to
                                foreign intervention, the United States cannot ignore it.</item>
                            <item>—We can understand your concern of <gloss target="#t_ZIPA_1"
                                    >ZIPA</gloss> and your desire not to provide those who wish to
                                see the conference fail with the excuse they are looking for. But we
                                fail to comprehend how Zambia’s interests, or Zimbabwe’s either,
                                would be served by a solution that merely places power in the hands
                                of the militants without imposing any discipline or restraint on the
                                exercise of that power.</item>
                            <item>—Nor do we understand the argument for giving in to <gloss
                                    target="#t_ZIPA_1">ZIPA</gloss>’s demand for instant majority
                                rule, which seems to us to be contrary to Zambia’s own interests,
                                and which will also destroy any chance of getting a
                                settlement.</item>
                            <item>—Transition means just that, not an instantaneous and total
                                reversal of existing power relationships but an irreversible
                                movement towards it in a limited span of time. Obviously Smith will
                                have more power at the beginning of the transition than at the
                                end.</item>
                            <item>—The United States is committed to a solution that results in the
                                effective transfer to the African majority by the end of that
                                already agreed interim period. For a solution to be acceptable to
                                us, it must also be a solution that can be supported by the front
                                line presidents and sold to the <gloss target="#t_OAU_1"
                                >OAU</gloss>. In other words, Zimbabwe’s victory is assured, and any
                                talk about a second <gloss target="#t_UDI_1">UDI</gloss> is baseless
                                and absurd. We will oppose any such move sharply and can count on
                                South African support in this regard.</item>
                            <item>—However flawed the institutional arrangements outlined in the
                                five points may appear, we must remember that they were the basis on
                                which Smith was hooked into the process of surrendering his own
                                position and power.</item>
                            <item>—The name of the game is to keep him hooked and not make it
                                possible for him to wiggle off.</item>
                            <item>—There is a lot the British can do to make the structure of the
                                interim government function more smoothly and effectively. We
                                believe they are prepared to play a role, and we are prepared to
                                push them in that direction. But we cannot expect the British to
                                assume responsibilities in Rhodesia that they have never had and for
                                which they lack the authority to back them up. They are willing to
                                bridge the gap, but you must be very precise and very realistic
                                about what you expect of them. They can provide the additional
                                margin of assurance for both sides; but in the final analysis, the
                                British role cannot take the place of a basic agreement among the
                                parties themselves which defines in clear and unambiguous terms the
                                powers that each will exercise in the interim period.</item>
                            <item>—Throughout the course of our common effort to find a settlement,
                                no nation has had clearer vision than Zambia. No nation has a <pb
                                    facs="0680" n="641" xml:id="pg_641"/> greater stake in a
                                successful outcome, one that brings a moderate, pragmatic and
                                responsible government to Zimbabwe. We believe that other nations
                                will recognize and accept the fact that Zambia faces greater risks
                                than anyone else if our efforts fail; and as a result, we believe
                                that your word will be needed and accepted by the other front line
                                presidents and by African leaders generally. It is up to Zambia,
                                being closest to the problem, to remind the others of how dangerous
                                the situation can become if a settlement based on compromise is not
                                achieved.</item>
                            <item>—It is important that the Patriotic Front rethink its position and
                                negotiate proposals which provide for power sharing with Rhodesian
                                Europeans during the period of transition.</item>
                            <item>—The framework which the Patriotic Front appears to be advancing
                                does not meet this criteria and cannot, therefore, enjoy our
                                support.</item>
                            <item>—I apologize for the length of this letter but I consider it
                                important at this delicate phase of the negotiations that we analyze
                                carefully and fully what is involved. I trust that you will use your
                                influence to bring the Patriotic Front around to a more realistic
                                approach. If you succeed, you can count on us to work behind the
                                scenes with the other parties.</item>
                            <item>—I look forward to hearing from you. Warmest regards, <persName
                                    corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Kissinger</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
