<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-03-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-03-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="123" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                        <head>123. Memorandum From the Staff Secretary of the National Security
                            Council (<persName corresp="#p_DJW1" type="from">Davis</persName>) to
                            the Deputy Secretary of Defense (<persName corresp="#p_PDM1" type="to">Packard</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d123fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Institutional Files (H-Files), Box H–053, <gloss target="#t_SRG1">SRG</gloss> Meeting, Pakistan, 3/6/71. Secret;
                                    <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>. Keith Guthrie signed
                                for <persName corresp="#p_DJW1">Davis</persName>. Also sent to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_IJNII1">Irwin</persName>, <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> Chairman <persName corresp="#p_MTH1">Moorer</persName>, and <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> Director <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>. A copy of the contingency study in the
                                Department of State files indicates that it was prepared by the
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Interdepartmental Group for
                                Near East and South Asia and forwarded to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> on March 2 by <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName>, who was serving as chairman
                                of the group. (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                                Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 1 <gloss target="#t_PAK1">PAK</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>)
                                The Senior Review Group meeting scheduled for March 3 was held on
                                March 6.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d123fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_DJW1">Davis</persName> circulated to members
                                of the Senior Review Group the response to <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 118, a contingency study that examined the policy
                                options available to the United States in the event of a move by
                                East Pakistan to secede.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-03-03">March 3, 1971</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                            <item>Response to <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 118 on
                                Pakistan</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Attached is the contingency study on Pakistan which has been prepared in
                            response to <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 118. A preliminary
                            discussion of this paper is planned at the Senior Review Group meeting
                            scheduled for Wednesday, March 3 at 3:00 p.m.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_DJW1">Jeanne W. Davis</persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                        <pb facs="d123-02" n="2" xml:id="d123-02"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">Attachment</note>
                            <head>Paper</head>
                            <dateline><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                <date>undated</date></dateline>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">CONTINGENCY STUDY ON PAKISTAN—EAST PAKISTAN
                                    SECESSION (<gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss>-118)</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Part I of this study traces the immediate background of the current
                                political crisis in Pakistan, discusses U.S. interests in Pakistan’s
                                unity and current limitations on U.S. policy, and assesses the
                                outlook for East and West Pakistan if they become two independent
                                states. Part II considers alternative U.S. postures toward a
                                possible move by East Pakistan to secede. Part III outlines
                                decisions and actions we might have to take in the event such. a
                                separation occurs. Longer range implications of this problem will be
                                considered in <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss>-109, “Policy
                                Study on South Asia”.</p>
                            <p rend="center">PART I </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">THE CURRENT CRISIS: BACKGROUND AND U.S.
                                    INTERESTS</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Background</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The possibility of imminent separation of the two wings of Pakistan
                                stems from the outcome of the December 1970 elections to choose a
                                National Assembly to frame a constitution. The elections resulted in
                                a nearly complete polarization of political forces in Pakistan. In
                                the east wing, the Awami League, campaigning on a Six Point Program
                                calling for full provincial autonomy, won virtually all the seats
                                and secured a small but absolute majority in the National Assembly.
                                The Awami League favors a policy of reconciliation with India. In
                                the west wing, a substantial majority of the seats was won by the
                                leftist People’s Party, which advocates a Central Government with
                                substantial powers and a policy of continuing confrontation toward
                                India. The leaders of the two parties have conferred but have in
                                effect agreed only to oppose each other’s constitutional
                                program.</p>
                            <p>President <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya</persName>, whose power
                                to arbitrate was greatly diminished by the decisive outcome of the
                                elections, had summoned the National Assembly to convene in Dacca on
                                March 3. However, confronted with the political impasse, he
                                announced on March 1 that he was postponing the Assembly
                                indefinitely to give political leaders more time to resolve their
                                differences. Awami League leader <persName corresp="#p_RSM1">Mujibur
                                    Rahman</persName> had asserted that he intended to use his
                                absolute majority to enact a constitution based on his party’s
                                autonomist program. People’s Party leader <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Zulfiqar Ali Bhutto</persName> had declared
                                his intention to absent himself and his party from the session
                                unless Mujib modified his constitutional proposals on at least some
                                of the Awami League’s Six Points. A number of other West Pakistan
                                members from smaller parties joined <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName> in boycotting the Assembly session.</p>
                            <pb facs="d123-03" n="3" xml:id="d123-03"/>
                            <p>Because of his landslide mandate Mujib has little flexibility in
                                modifying his program, although he and his party are believed to
                                prefer to remain in a unified federal state of Pakistan with maximum
                                provincial autonomy rather than secede. <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName> and his followers, on the other hand, may
                                have tacitly concluded that they would be prepared to let the East
                                Pakistanis secede—leaving themselves to govern a residual state in
                                West Pakistan—rather than accept a weak federal system based on the
                                Awami League program.</p>
                            <p>As a result of <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya</persName>’s
                                postponement of the Assembly, the crisis has reached a critical
                                juncture. Unless a compromise formula can be devised, secession by
                                the Bengalis or separation of the two wings of Pakistan by mutual
                                consent have become real possibilities.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">U.S. Interests and U.S. Policy Limitations</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Our consistent position has been that U.S. interests are better
                                served by a unified Pakistan than by its separation into two
                                independent states—West Pakistan with a population of about 61
                                million and East Pakistan with about 76 million. We have concluded
                                that an independent East Pakistan would be more vulnerable to
                                internal instability, economic stagnation and external subversion
                                than an East Pakistan affiliated with West Pakistan. We have also
                                concluded that the East Pakistanis provide a moderating influence
                                over West Pakistani hostility toward India. Finally, we have
                                recognized hostility that we have had no realistic alternative but
                                to support Pakistan’s unity if we were to maintain satisfactory
                                relations with the government in Islamabad.</p>
                            <p>We also recognize that as a practical matter our ability to influence
                                the course of these events is very limited. The special relationship
                                which we maintained with the Government of Pakistan until the late
                                1960’s has ended, and with it the sort of leverage, as well as
                                interest, we might once have had in influencing political
                                developments in Pakistan. In the present circumstances, we could
                                perhaps affect the timetable or modalities of East Pakistani
                                secession through our posture toward Mujib and his followers, or
                                perhaps influence the West Pakistani response to it. However, we
                                could not deter a move for independence if the East Pakistanis
                                should make the ultimate decision to establish their own country.
                                Nor could we dissuade dominant political forces in West Pakistan,
                                notably Bhutto and his followers, from pursuing a course of
                                obstruction which would result in driving East Pakistan into
                                secession if they should choose to do so.</p>
                            <p>All evidence points to the fact that President <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya</persName> is doing his utmost to
                                effect an accommodation between the two contending forces in his <pb facs="d123-04" n="4" xml:id="d123-04"/> country in order to
                                preserve a unified state, and we see little we could effectively do
                                to help him except to maintain our general posture of cooperation
                                with his government and to encourage him in his efforts as long as
                                they stand a reasonable chance of success. The alternative U.S.
                                postures in Part II, below, have been framed in the context of these
                                judgments regarding the limitations on our policy options.</p>
                            <p>We should also recognize that, while we have regarded our interests
                                as better served by a unified Pakistan, we should be able to adjust
                                to the emergence of two separate states and to maintain satisfactory
                                relations with them without serious damage to our interests. It is
                                unlikely that either state will in the foreseeable future
                                significantly change its external orientation from the dominant
                                attitudes toward foreign affairs now prevailing in East and West
                                Pakistan, respectively. Both will want to maintain viable ties with
                                the U.S. as an offset to their relations with other major external
                                powers: India, the U.S.S.R. and Communist China. Both will keenly
                                desire continuation of U.S. economic assistance and will seek our
                                support on various political issues. Both may also desire military
                                and public safety assistance from us, at least in training and the
                                sale of equipment. In short, both states will want friendly and
                                cooperative relations with the U.S.—a desire which it will be in our
                                interest to reciprocate, and to support within the capability of our
                                resource and in the light of our interests in the South Asian region
                                as a whole.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Outlook for Separate States</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>An independent state in East Pakistan would undoubtedly face
                                formidable problems, especially in the economic sphere and
                                eventually in the political. However, these are problems which would
                                inevitably arise whether East Pakistan were independent or merely
                                autonomous within a federated Pakistan. Politically, the Awami
                                League under <persName corresp="#p_RSM1">Mujibur Rahman</persName>
                                would restore democratic government in the new state and enjoy wide
                                popular support from the start, judging from the overwhelming size
                                of its mandate in the recent elections. It would move to establish
                                cooperative relations with its major neighbor, India, for reasons of
                                external security as well as trade. At the same time it would
                                cultivate good relations with many other countries in order to avoid
                                excessive dependence on any one power and to tap the resources of as
                                many aid donors as possible.</p>
                            <p>The Awami League emerged from the recent elections as more of a
                                nationalist mass movement than a tight political organization. As
                                time passes, it will be hard pressed to fulfill its program and
                                satisfy the aspirations of the impoverished masses of East Pakistan.
                                It is likely <pb facs="d123-05" n="5" xml:id="d123-05"/> to face
                                defections from its own ranks and mounting opposition from radical
                                leftist elements outside. The long-term outlook therefore suggests
                                increasing radicalization and political instability in East
                                Pakistan.</p>
                            <p>Economically, an independent East Pakistan might be able to maintain
                                its present low rate of economic growth for some years after
                                separation, assuming improved mobilization of local resources (e.g.,
                                it would enjoy exclusive benefit of the foreign exchange earnings
                                from its jute industry which have been shared in the past with West
                                Pakistan), development of trade with India to supplement or supplant
                                its present inter-wing commerce with West Pakistan, and infusion of
                                substantial levels of foreign aid. Its economy is bound to suffer in
                                the long run, however, as the result of its burdensome population
                                increase—by about 50% in the next 15 years, from the present 76
                                million to around 118 million according to official U.S. estimates.
                                It is difficult to see how the state can in the long run meet its
                                basic needs, let alone improve its economy, even with sizeable
                                external aid.</p>
                            <p>A new state in West Pakistan would most likely be organized around a
                                left-trending populist type of government dominated by <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName> and his People’s Party,
                                supported by the military which will remain an important element in
                                the political equation. An authoritarian regime headed by <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName> and backed by the armed
                                forces, with or without martial law, is a conceivable variant if the
                                disparate and loosely structured People’s Party should disintegrate.
                                Given the influence of the military and the more favorable economic
                                outlook in West Pakistan, the chances for stability would appear
                                somewhat better in the western state than in the eastern one.
                                However, even though the military may provide short-term stability,
                                its ability to exercise power over the long run, either directly or
                                indirectly, may be subject to rising political and public
                                challenges. Externally a new state in West Pakistan would continue a
                                policy of confrontation with India which could spell trouble for its
                                security as well as its economic progress due to excessive defense
                                expenditures. The state might draw closer to China while trying to
                                maintain viable relations with the U.S., correct ones with the
                                U.S.S.R. and close ties with Iran and Turkey.</p>
                            <p>The economic prospects of an independent West Pakistan are brighter
                                than those of East Pakistan. With a larger territory and stronger
                                resource base, lower population and respectable level of economic
                                growth in recent years, the new state should be able with continuing
                                foreign assistance to maintain its forward movement for some years
                                to come, assuming stable and effective government, rational planning
                                and a peaceful environment. But it, too, faces a potentially serious
                                population problem which could badly retard its economic progress in
                                the long run.</p>
                            <pb facs="d123-06" n="6" xml:id="d123-06"/>
                            <p rend="center">PART II </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">ALTERNATE U.S. POSTURES TOWARD POSSIBLE EAST
                                    PAKISTAN SECESSION</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"> A. <hi rend="underline">U.S. Posture Toward
                                    Pakistan Unity While East Pakistan Separation is Uncertain</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>This is essentially the current situation. Awami League leaders have
                                already sounded out American officials on the posture we would take
                                should East Pakistan separate from West Pakistan. Even if separation
                                is not certain, they can be expected to approach us with increasing
                                frequency and directness asking for political support, assistance
                                against possible West Pakistani forceful resistance, and assurances
                                of continued economic assistance if East Pakistan should become
                                independent. At the same time, West Pakistani leaders, including
                                President <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya</persName>, can be
                                expected to continue to probe our position with respect to unity and
                                to watch for any indication of a shift in it toward support for East
                                Pakistan separation. Under these present circumstances, we see three
                                alternative postures:</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Alternative U.S. Postures:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>We can maintain our present official position in response to
                                    Pakistani inquires along the following line: “Our policy has
                                    been and continues to be to support the independence, unity and
                                    integrity of Pakistan. However, this is your country and how you
                                    organize and deal with its problems is your business”.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>We could be more forthcoming toward the Bengalis by indicating
                                    to them that, while the U.S. continues to favor Pakistani unity,
                                    we recognize that there is a rising sense of nationalism in East
                                    Pakistan, and that we would be prepared to adjust our policies
                                    to the evolving situation and to work out a satisfactory modus
                                    vivendi with whatever new governmental arrangements
                                    result.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>We could, while maintaining our present public position,
                                    privately urge President <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya</persName> to make every effort to reach an
                                    accommodation with <persName corresp="#p_RSM1">Mujibur
                                        Rahman</persName> which would enable a single Pakistan to
                                    continue, even though its federal power were limited to defense
                                    and foreign affairs, and even though <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName>’s party refused to cooperate in the
                                    process of government.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Posture:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Unless and until separation is certain, any shift in our <pb facs="d123-07" n="7" xml:id="d123-07"/> position, would be
                                against our continuing interest in seeing Pakistan remain unified.
                                Any softening on our part, as in Alternative Posture 2, would
                                contribute to the process of disintegration. Furthermore, it is
                                likely that any suggestion of U.S. encouragement of East Pakistan
                                separatism would quickly get back to West Pakistan. This would
                                reinforce existing suspicions among some West Pakistanis that the
                                U.S. is working to split the country. It would thereby prejudice our
                                relations with the present West Pakistanis as well as our future
                                relations with a possible independent state in West Pakistan.</p>
                            <p>We therefore prefer at this stage to continue to maintain a balanced
                                posture between West and East Pakistanis along lines of Alternative
                                1. It serves to reassure those with whom we have to continue to deal
                                in West Pakistan while leaving the impression with East Pakistanis
                                that we are not inflexible, although we would prefer (as Mujib
                                presently seems to) a mutually agreeable constitutional system
                                within a unified state.</p>
                            <p>We do not consider Alternative 3 to be necessary or desirable,
                                President <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya</persName> knows well
                                our position favoring unity and is already doing all he can on his
                                own initiative to bring about an acceptable compromise between Mujib
                                and <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName> which is his
                                stated reason for postponing the Assembly session. He does not need
                                any urging from us in this matter and we can realistically offer
                                little or nothing that will materially affect the situation.
                                Moreover, an effort by us to urge compromise could be resented as
                                unwarranted interference in Pakistan’s internal affairs.</p>
                            <p>
                                <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> disagrees with the approach to
                                Alternative Posture 3 in the preceding paragraph and advocates
                                adopting that posture for the following reasons: <list>
                                    <label>(a)</label>
                                    <item>As a consequence of the clear cut election results
                                        Pakistan must move rapidly toward: (i) repressive military
                                        rule, (ii) a split into two nations with the smaller but
                                        stronger dominated by an anti-west demagogue, or (iii) a
                                        constitutional government founded on the Awami League’s
                                        loose confederation platform; the third choice is most
                                        clearly consistent <pb facs="d123-08" n="8" xml:id="d123-08"/> with our interests in South Asia and we should support
                                        it.</item>
                                    <label>(b)</label>
                                    <item>In a confederation reserving foreign policy and defense to
                                        the central government, <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName>’s strongly pro-Chinese and
                                        anti-Indian policies would be checked and he would not
                                        control the Pakistan Army and Air Force as he has an
                                        excellent chance of doing if the country splits.</item>
                                    <label>(c)</label>
                                    <item>There is evidence that some leaders of the Pakistan
                                        military establishment are increasingly apprehensive about
                                        the prospects of left-wing rule in a separate West Pakistan
                                        and see new virtue in a united country, even with maximum
                                        regional autonomy; the Bengali leadership is openly seeking
                                        reassurance from the United States; in this situation our
                                        counsel and assurance can have substantial influence and we
                                        should weigh in on the side of the only possible course
                                        giving some hope of leading to a constitutional government
                                        with a moderate foreign policy.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"> B. <hi rend="underline">U.S. Posture if East
                                    Pakistan Separation Appears Imminent</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The point at which East Pakistan separation seems imminent could
                                rapidly be reached and we should be prepared to adjust our posture
                                quickly to take account of this eventuality. Much will hinge on East
                                Pakistani reactions to <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya</persName>’s decision to postpone the convening of the
                                Assembly.</p>
                            <p>If we judge separation to be imminent, but East Pakistan has not
                                declared its independence, the following U.S. postures could be
                                considered:</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Alternative U.S. Postures:</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>We could continue to adhere to the formulation set forth
                                        in Posture A-1, above, reaffirming that while we support the
                                        independence, unity and integrity of Pakistan, we recognize
                                        that Pakistanis must decide their future for
                                        themselves.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>We could let East Pakistan leaders know that we would be
                                        prepared to recognize an independent state in East Pakistan
                                        and to <pb facs="d123-09" n="9" xml:id="d123-09"/> conduct
                                        normal diplomatic relations with its government. At the same
                                        time, we would keep in close touch with West Pakistani
                                        leaders and, as appropriate, inform them that we were
                                        watching the evolving situation closely and were prepared to
                                        adapt to it.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Depending upon circumstances, we could also acknowledge
                                        that we would consider sympathetically requests for economic
                                        assistance from the new government in East Pakistan.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Posture:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>If separation becomes imminent, but before it is announced, we should
                                adopt Posture 2 and let East Pakistani leaders know privately that,
                                should East Pakistan become independent, we would recognize the new
                                state and be prepared to conduct normal relations with its
                                government. To adhere to Alternative Posture 1 at this stage would
                                unnecessarily alienate Bengali leaders with whom we would want to be
                                on good terms in the future. Adopting Posture 2 should afford us
                                substantial psychological gains with East Pakistanis, with limited
                                risk in West Pakistan if separation were imminent. Posture 3 would
                                be premature until we can better determine the character of the new
                                government and our relationship with it.</p>
                            <p>If East Pakistan leaders, prior to a formal declaration of
                                independence, should request U.S. intercession or intervention to
                                forestall anticipated West Pakistan military action, we should
                                decline on the grounds that we do not consider West Pakistani
                                military intervention likely (assuming this to be the case at the
                                time). We should firmly reject any suggestion of U.S. military
                                involvement.</p>
                            <p>If East Pakistan publicly declares its independence and requests our
                                recognition, we should grant it in the context of the contingencies
                                set forth in Part III-A below.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"> C. <hi rend="italic">U.S. Posture if East Pakistan
                                    Declares Independence and West Pakistan Intervenes
                                    Militarily</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>We think it very unlikely that West Pakistan would intervene
                                militarily to attempt to preserve the unity of Pakistan by force.
                                Given the anticipated vehemence of the Bengali response, the limited
                                strength of West Pakistani forces now in the East (one Army division
                                and a few aircraft), and the <pb facs="d123-10" n="10" xml:id="d123-10"/> difficulties of reinforcement from the West,
                                the risks of military intervention would appear to be excessively
                                high. Moreover, there would probably be a general lack of public and
                                political interest in West Pakistan in preventing Bengali secession.
                                Rather than undertake military action, most of them would prefer to
                                let East Pakistan go its way.</p>
                            <p>The West Pakistanis would also have to weigh the possibility that the
                                Indians would take measures to assist East Pakistan. (We believe
                                India considers that a unified Pakistan is in its interest, but if
                                separation appears imminent, India would prefer an independent state
                                in the East to a united Pakistan dominated by the West Wing.) Should
                                the Pakistanis intervene, India would probably continue the ban on
                                Pakistani overflights or reimpose it if it had been lifted. It might
                                also take steps such as: attempting to interdict West Pakistani
                                supplies and reinforcements coming by sea and air via other routes
                                than over India; providing emergency supplies to East Pakistan; and
                                mounting a psychological diversion, perhaps in Kashmir, against West
                                Pakistan. It is doubtful that India would send troops into East
                                Pakistan since West Pakistan forces there are so weak as to make it
                                unnecessary to take that rather great risk of escalation.</p>
                            <p>Despite the unlikelihood of military intervention, we nonetheless
                                should plan for it on a contingency basis on the theory that an
                                irrational action is always possible. If the West Pakistan military
                                should intervene, the following alternative U.S. postures could be
                                considered:</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Alternative U.S. Postures:</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>We could take no action (other than to protect American
                                        personnel and interests) on the grounds that no U.S.
                                        interest demands our doing so, that we could not
                                        significantly influence the situation, and that our
                                        attempted involvement would only antagonize West
                                        Pakistan.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>We could urge West Pakistani leaders to cease military
                                        action on the grounds that a military solution is futile in
                                        the face of East Pakistan’s determination to go its own way,
                                        that West Pakistani action could provoke Indian intervention
                                        and thus lead to Indo-Pakistan hostilities, and that
                                        needless loss of life should-be avoided.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>We could consult with the Indian Government regarding our
                                        mutual interests concerning the situation in East Pakistan.
                                        We would say that those interests indicate that we should
                                        avoid any sort of military intervention in East Pakistan,
                                        even in response to an East Pakistan request, since it would
                                        be unlikely that West Pakistan’s <pb facs="d123-11" n="11" xml:id="d123-11"/> military forces could prevail in any
                                        case. In the unlikely event that India nonetheless appeared
                                        to be on the point of intervening with ground forces in East
                                        Pakistan, we should urge the Government of India to avoid
                                        such action on the additional grounds that it could provoke
                                        an India-West Pakistan conflict and could be exploited by
                                        the Chinese.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>If West Pakistani—and possibly Indian—military
                                        intervention should occur, we would not make any military
                                        moves ourselves. However, in concert with the British and
                                        other interested external powers we should be prepared to
                                        use the threat of sanctions, including cessation of economic
                                        aid and military supply, if hostile actions should occur or
                                        continue.</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>We believe Chinese military intervention would be even
                                        more unlikely than a West Pakistan request for it. Apart
                                        from their strong disinclination to indulge in high risk,
                                        low benefit adventures across their borders, the Chinese
                                        realize that their forces would have to cross undisputed
                                        Indian territory, which would provoke a major Sino-Indian
                                        conflict. (A seaborne effort or a 400-mile march through
                                        Burma would have the advantage of avoiding Indian territory.
                                        However, the PRC’s capabilities for such efforts are so
                                        limited as to appear to exclude these possibilities.) In the
                                        extremely unlikely event that the Chinese intervene
                                        militarily across Indian (and/or Burmese) territory, we
                                        should render the Indians (and/or the Burmese) political and
                                        possibly material support in seeking to vacate the
                                        aggression. However, we should avoid direct military
                                        involvement, recognizing that the area is not a vital
                                        security interest to the U.S.</item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>If any type of hostilities involving outside forces should
                                        occur, we should support all appropriate international
                                        efforts, including actions within the United Nations, to
                                        bring about an early ceasefire.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Posture:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>If West Pakistan intervention becomes imminent or actually occurs, we
                                would have an interest in doing what we could to avoid bloodshed and
                                restore peace, and to prevent the conflict from escalating beyond a
                                purely East-West Pakistan clash. We should be willing to risk
                                irritating the West Pakistanis in the face of such a rash act on
                                their part, and the threat of stopping aid should give us
                                considerable leverage.</p>
                            <pb facs="d123-12" n="12" xml:id="d123-12"/>
                            <p>We would therefore rule out Alternative Posture 1. Instead, we should
                                initially follow Alternatives 2 and 3, urging the West Pakistanis to
                                desist from military action and consulting appropriately with the
                                Indians. If these efforts should fail, we should then consider
                                Alternatives 4, 5, and 6 as the situation would demand.</p>
                            <p rend="center">PART III</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">CONTINGENCIES AND ACTIONS TO BE TAKEN IN EVENT
                                    OF SEPARATION</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Definitions</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The resultant state in the West Wing would be expected to be
                                considered the “successor state” for most purposes (e.g., except for
                                certain legal relationships relating solely to the East Wing),
                                retaining the name, capital and, at least provisionally, President
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya</persName> as chief of state/
                                head of government. It will herein be designated Pakistan, the word
                                itself being an acronym for areas now contained in, or claimed by,
                                the West Wing. The resultant new state in the East Wing will be
                                called Bangla Desh, the term proposed by Bengali political leaders
                                for renaming their present province which presumably would be
                                utilized as well for an independent state.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">A. Recognition</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Requests to the international community for diplomatic recognition
                                could take one of several forms depending upon the nature of the
                                separation of East and West Pakistan, and our response would vary,
                                as follows:</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Contingency 1: Bangla Desh makes a unilateral
                                    declaration of independence (UDI) which is accepted by Pakistan.
                                    Pakistan itself recognizes Bangla Desh and agrees to establish
                                    diplomatic relations with its government</hi>.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Action:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>We should recognize Bangla Desh promptly. Pakistan (i.e., the West
                                Wing) as the successor state would not require new recognition, and
                                diplomatic relations would continue.</p>
                            <pb facs="d123-13" n="13" xml:id="d123-13"/>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Contingency 2: Pakistan rejects Bangla Desh’s UDI
                                    but does not attempt to resist it by force.</hi></p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Action:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>We should delay slightly in deference to our continuing relations
                                with Pakistan, but should be among the earlier states to recognize
                                Bangla Desh. We should coordinate timing and form of recognition
                                with the United Kingdom. India may well jump in ahead to recognize
                                Bangla Desh. We would not want to appear to Pakistan to be acting in
                                concert with India, and would not coordinate our action with India,
                                although we could inform the Indians just before we recognize.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Contingency 3: Pakistan rejects Bangla Desh’s UDI
                                    and attempts to put down secession by force. As explained in
                                    Part II-C, above, we do not consider this a likely possibility,
                                    but if it should occur we would not expect Pakistan to be able
                                    to maintain its armed intervention for long.</hi></p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Action:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>We would recognize Bangla Desh as soon as it becomes clear that the
                                new government is in effective control and that its independence is
                                an established fact. To do so earlier would complicate our relations
                                with Pakistan while we are endeavoring to persuade it to stop its
                                intervention. To wait too long would get our new relationship with
                                Bangla Desh off to a bad start.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Contingency 4: Pakistan and Bangla Desh separate by
                                    mutual agreement.</hi></p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Action:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>We should recognize Bangla Desh promptly. Pakistan, as the successor
                                state, would not need to be recognized anew.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">B. Form of Recognition</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Contingency 1: In case of agreed
                                separation.</hi></p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Action:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The President should send personal messages to the chiefs of state of
                                the two states extending his best wishes to the new <pb facs="d123-14" n="14" xml:id="d123-14"/> regimes and their
                                people. The messages should be substantially the same and phrased
                                according to the then prevailing circumstances, except that the
                                message to Bangla Desh could express our agreement to establish
                                diplomatic relations. A message should not be sent to one and not
                                the other.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Contingency 2: In case of contested
                                    separation.</hi></p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Action:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Presidential communications should not be sent at the time of the
                                separation. Recognition of Bangla Desh would be accorded by a public
                                announcement or act of establishing diplomatic relations. Our
                                relations with Pakistan would continue.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">C. U.S. Representation in Pakistan and Bangla
                                    Desh</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Action:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Our Ambassador in present Pakistan would become Ambassador to the
                                successor state of Pakistan. As soon as we recognize the state of
                                Bangla Desh, we would propose to the new government that our Consul
                                General in Dacca be designated Charge d’Affaires pending the
                                appointment of an Ambassador; an Ambassador should be appointed as
                                soon as possible, although recognition will be more important to
                                Bengalis than the physical presence of an accredited Ambassador.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">D. Pakistan and Bangla Desh Representation in
                                    the U.S.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Contingency 1: In case of an agreed
                                separation</hi>. We can assume that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Hilaly</persName> would continue to represent
                                Pakistan in the United States. However, we cannot assume that the
                                Bangla Desh regime would ask the present <gloss target="#t_DCM1">DCM</gloss>, a Bengali, to look after its interests; it would,
                                however, name or send someone.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Action:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>We should continue to conduct business with the Ambassador of
                                Pakistan relating to that successor state, and should begin to do so
                                with the designated representative of Bangla Desh as soon as we
                                recognize it. In the interim, we should deal informally with
                                whomever, if anyone, is designated by Bangla Desh.</p>
                            <pb facs="d123-15" n="15" xml:id="d123-15"/>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Contingency 2: In case of a contested
                                    separation</hi>.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Action:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Our actions would have to be more cautious. We should continue to
                                deal with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Hilaly</persName> as
                                the representative of (united) Pakistan until we recognize Bangla
                                Desh as a sovereign state. At the same time, we should keep channels
                                of communication informally open with any designated representative
                                of Bangla Desh. We should stay clear of any disputes concerning the
                                use and ownership of (united) Pakistani property here, emphasizing
                                that this would be a question for settlement between the two
                                states.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">E. United Nations and Other International
                                    Bodies</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Bangla Desh would probably move quickly to attain membership in the
                                United Nations and other international bodies.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Contingency 1: Agreed separation</hi>. It is
                                possible that Pakistan would sponsor the application of Bangla
                                Desh.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Action:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Following U.S. recognition of Bangla Desh’s sovereignty, we should
                                promptly support its membership in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, and such other international bodies as it wishes to
                                join.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Contingency 2: Contested separation</hi>. Under
                                contested conditions, Pakistan might oppose Bangla Desh’s
                                application for <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> membership.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Action:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>As soon as we accord recognition to Bangla Desh, we should also
                                support its membership in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and
                                such other international bodies as it wishes to join.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">F. Emergency and Evacuation</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Law and order situations in either or both of the resultant states
                                could be such that we would want to consider evacuation of
                                dependents and some or all staff.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Contingency 1: In Pakistan—if separation is
                                    contested, but possibly even if agreed</hi>. Some political
                                parties and other public elements are <pb facs="d123-16" n="16" xml:id="d123-16"/> likely to accuse the United States of having
                                engineered the separation, provoking demonstrations and acts of
                                violence against American installations. Under what is likely to be
                                a confused situation, with the principal political party in Pakistan
                                already anti-American, the authorities might not be able to maintain
                                control.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Action:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>If there is any prospect of disturbances, we should affirm to the
                                Government our expectation that it will provide full protection for
                                U.S. citizens and U.S. property. We would also be prepared to put
                                into operation emergency and evacuation plans at whatever time
                                required. Our posts in Pakistan have just reviewed their E&amp;E
                                plans and updated them where necessary.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Contingency 2: In Bangla Desh</hi>. In the event of
                                an agreed separation, law and order in Bangla Desh should not break
                                down, particularly in the city of Dacca. The Awami League Government
                                would enjoy wide popularity and cooperation. Conceivably, if it
                                appeared that the U.S. was opposed to separation, the situation
                                could become tense for us, but appropriate timing of recognition
                                should forestall any serious problem. However, if Pakistan attempted
                                to resist secession by military force, the situation throughout the
                                province, and especially in the cities, could go out of control.
                                Clashes would be between Bengali nationalists and the army, but
                                Americans could easily become caught in the middle.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Action:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>We would notify the local Bangla Desh (or Pakistan) authorities that
                                we expect them to protect U.S. citizens and property, but we would
                                be ready to evacuate families and reduce staff as necessary.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">G. Negotiations in Progress</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Contingency</hi>: At the time of separation, we
                                will probably have under negotiation or discussion with the
                                Government of Pakistan such actions as a <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss>–480 agreement, program and project loan agreements,
                                local currency utilization, military sales and a Fulbright
                                educational exchange agreement which would apply to the East Wing as
                                well as the West.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Action:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>On separation of the two wings, we should temporarily discontinue
                                such negotiations and consider revisions necessitated by the changed
                                circumstances. In order to avoid <pb facs="d123-17" n="17" xml:id="d123-17"/> causing hardship or ill will in either
                                Pakistan or Bangla Desh, we should be prepared to move quickly to
                                adapt such proposals to the needs of, and our interests in, the
                                resultant states and to resume negotiations promptly with both on
                                revised bases. Negotiations with Pakistan could be resumed as soon
                                as practicable and initiated with Bangla Desh as soon as diplomatic
                                relations are established.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">H. Programs in Progress</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Contingency</hi>: There are also a number of
                                official U.S. Government economic, military and other programs and
                                projects in progress in West and East Pakistan which we would have
                                to decide whether to continue or suspend in the event of separation
                                of the two wings. We should be able to continue most ongoing
                                economic aid programs and projects in both Pakistan and Bangla Desh,
                                although some programs will have to be renegotiated. We would also
                                want to reconsider military shipments and orders carefully.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="underline">Proposed U.S. Actions:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Economic aid programs and projects with both new states should either
                                be continued without interruption, pending our determination of
                                whether they should be retained for the longer term in the context
                                of our relations with the two new states, or renegotiated. Ongoing
                                technical assistance programs and loan projects would not be
                                substantially affected since these activities are already clearly
                                divided between the two regions because of their physical
                                separation. Existing agreements would eventually have to be
                                renegotiated with Bangla Desh because all agreements are now with
                                the Government of Pakistan. Current <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> program loans, however, are less clearly defined
                                geographically; and in the event of a separation of the two, wings,
                                such loans would have to be divided between the two new states.
                                Commodities shipped under <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss>–480 are
                                usually designated for either East or West Pakistan, and if the two
                                wings separated, existing agreements should be cancelled and new
                                agreements made, honoring the intent of the original agreements. We
                                would have to consider urgently the disposition of shipments in
                                transit. We would also have to extend a moratorium on Debt
                                repayments until the two wings and the U.S. could work out a
                                mutually satisfactory redistribution of the debt. Other U.S.
                                programs should be reviewed immediately and decisions made on a case
                                by case basis as to whether to continue, suspend or terminate,</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>