<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>141. Conversation Among President Nixon, the President’s Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs (, the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Kissinger), and the Ambassador to Pakistan (), and the Ambassador to
                    Pakistan (Farland))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d141</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">141</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-07-28T15:21:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-07-28T15:54:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Spare parts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-07-28T15:54:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-07-28T15:21:00-05:00" n="141"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d141">
                <head>141. Conversation Among President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="from"
                        >Nixon</persName>, the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName>), and the
                    Ambassador to Pakistan (<persName corresp="#p_FJS1" type="to"
                        >Farland</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d141fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                        Materials, White House Tapes, Recording of Conversation among <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_FJS1"
                            >Farland</persName>, Oval Office, Conversation No. 549–25. No
                        classification marking. The editor transcribed the conversation published
                        here specifically for this volume.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d141fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName> briefed <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> on the developing crisis in Pakistan.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        from="1971-07-28T16:21:00-04:00" to="1971-07-28T16:54:00-04:00">July 28,
                        1971, 4:21–4:54 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: You know, the thing that really
                    concerns us, naturally, as we all know, the miserable campaign, I don’t know
                    what you can do about it while you are here, against Pakistan. Do you think he’s
                    doing—Keating was over here lobbying for the Indians when he was here—do you
                    think he ought to try to say anything good about the Paks while you are here?
                    Could you?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: I can...</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Would it be useful?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I think it would be useful to
                    put out [unclear].</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: I agree, although I was trying
                    to maintain a relatively low profile because I didn’t want to get questions
                    about particulars to the China trip.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: On that you have a perfect thing,
                    you just say I’m not saying anything. [unclear]</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: I saw Chuck Percy today at a
                    luncheon that Frank Kellogg gave at the State Department. And several
                    Congressmen, and they all wondered why my presence wasn’t known, why could I
                    appear before a committee and I had no comment to make. I said I don’t know. I
                    had a conversation with [unclear] this morning and he was quite hopeful that I
                    could appear before one of the committees. I agreed with Charles Bray over at
                    the State Department to give a backgrounder to the press on Friday
                    afternoon.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Good.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s better than testimony
                    [unclear].</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Good. The press likes
                    backgrounders much better. That’s where it counts. The hell with the damn
                    Congress.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: There is another side to this
                    picture, and I can say with complete candor that if we push <persName
                        corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya</persName> to the point where he reacts, the
                    reaction will be such that the entire subcontinent will be [unclear]. I mean
                    he’ll fight. He’ll fight, and he may go [unclear]. If he goes out, and he may go
                    [unclear] it’s going to be [unclear] that ever mankind has seen, in our
                    lifetime. The Chinese will come right down through Assam. [unclear] Furthermore,
                    the Chinese will come across the Mintoka Pass and start guerrilla warfare in
                    Kashmir. And they’ll have everything surrounded. And the vociferous forces in
                    India today [unclear]. That’s a very stark picture but it’s one that’s not
                    overdrawn.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: What do you think our position
                    should be?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: I think we are doing what we
                    should. This is a policy that I joined in. I don’t think we can overplay our
                    hand, but I don’t think we are looking for vociferous, positive action. Mr.
                    President, as I was telling you this morning, that as a matter of actual fact
                    this problem goes back to about the year AD 712, when the Muslims first invaded
                    the Sind. There’s been no peace on the subcontinent since that time because the
                    Hindus and the Muslims have nothing in common whatsoever. Every point of their
                    lives is diametrically opposed—economic, political, social, emotional, despite
                    their beliefs. One prays to idols, the other prays to one God. One worships the
                    cow; the other eats it. Simple as that. And last year there were 521 communal
                    riots in India, acknowledged.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Miserable damn place.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: And what the Indians are
                    really after, that became clear to me on my trip [unclear]. Their thoughts are
                    about East Pakistan because they think that [unclear] West Pakistan. They think
                    that by, well, if they can undermine East Pakistan then in West Pakistan so many
                    forces would be, will unloosen, will be turned loose that the whole Pakistan
                    issue will disappear. The Indians and West Pakistanis they hate each other—</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Oh sure, that’s what they fear.
                    East Pakistan [unclear]. The thing, the bad thing is you are convinced, though,
                    that <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya</persName> will fight?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: Oh, he will.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: He will commit suicide.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I agree completely. He will
                    fight. Just as Lincoln would have fought. To him East Pakistan is part of
                    Pakistan. [unclear]</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: Because of their sense of
                    defeat, the possibility of defeat is a minor consideration as opposed to their
                    sense of national unity. Remember, almost every [unclear] over there recalls the
                    time of partition, back when they had—</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Horrible slaughters?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: The acknowledged figure is over
                    half a million. The figure that most people believe is way in excess of a
                    million people. Fifteen million refugees were on the road.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: What is the situation, I really,
                    of course there are always two sides to everything, but with the Indians
                    [unclear]? Terrible stories [unclear] and so forth.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: They are past masters of
                    propaganda. The Pakistanis don’t—</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: How can you, can you perhaps put a
                    little of that [unclear]. Well anyway, I think if you could, if you could—</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: [unclear]</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Yeah. Okay.</p>
                <p>[Unclear exchange]</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: This matter of arms to
                    Pakistan.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Uh, huh.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: Since March 25 we have sent over
                    2,200 rounds of .22 ammunition for survival rifles for down there, that’s all.
                    This part of our arms deal is just, in guns and the story hasn’t properly—</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: You tell them that’s good. That’s
                    good.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: Forty to fifty percent of what’s
                    in the pipeline is for spare parts for trucks and for communication equipment
                    without which the starving refugees could not be fed.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Good. Good. Good.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: So these are—</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: You ought to lay it right out. And
                    also, I guess everybody’s concerned about [unclear]. Let’s not aggravate the
                    problem; let’s try to help on the problem—East Pakistan. And the main thing
                    let’s not stir it up. It’s stirred up too much. Inevitably it will be a
                    bloodbath down there.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: It will be. It will be all over
                    the subcontinent.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: We warned the Indians very
                    strongly that if they start anything—and believe me it would be a hell of a
                    pleasure as far as I am concerned—if we just cut off every damn bit of aid we
                    give them, at least for whatever it’s worth.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1"
                        >Yahya</persName> told me that they had pinpointed 29 camps within India
                    where guerrillas were being trained. Now I hate to tell you this, Mr. President,
                    but the guerrilla threat is growing by leaps and bounds. They’re averaging 18
                    Pakistanis a day now; they are averaging two bridges a day. Killing that many.
                    And this is [unclear]. And once the refugees get there, they are being
                    prohibited, are prevented from coming back by Indira’s own statement. Political
                    accommodation in her book means Bangladesh. This is bad.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Well, I think we just continue on
                    our line. We, as you know, we’re having a hell of a time keeping the State
                    Department bureaucracies hitched on this thing. They’re basically pro-Indian.
                    When I say “they,” not all. But a lot of them. And they want to believe what the
                    American press is writing. And the Indian press, of course, the American press
                    is the same as the Indian press, follows everything they say.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: Well, my Consul General over in
                    Dacca—</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: He’s no good.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: blew the whistle on the whole
                    thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: He’s bad, isn’t he?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: Well he’s gone. He’s here in the
                    Department now. And the head of the <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> was
                    just as tendentious in his reporting. Got rid of him. Shakespeare got him
                    out.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Good.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>: The one remaining, who is a very
                    critical situation, this fellow Eric Griffel, who is the head of <gloss
                        target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> [Griffel was the associate director in charge
                    of <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> operations in Dacca], he will be out in
                    September. I wish he were out now. I don’t think you could pull him out
                    without—</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Repercussions.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJS1">Farland</persName>:—repercussions on the Hill. And
                    my guess is that he has been instrumental in leaking some of this
                    information.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Sick bastards. You just keep right
                    after it on this thing.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
