<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>152. Memorandum From the Deputy Administrator of the Agency for International
                    Development (Williams) to Secretary of State ) to Secretary of State
                    Rogers</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d152</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">152</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-11-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006378"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public relations</term>
                    <term ref="reckOJp7RF2apAIO3" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85004558"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Amnesty</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="general" subject="public-diplomacy" lcsh-match="no_match">Diplomacy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-11-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="152"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d152">
                <head>152. Memorandum From the Deputy Administrator of the Agency for International
                    Development (<persName corresp="#p_WMJ1" type="from">Williams</persName>) to
                    Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RWP1" type="to">Rogers</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d152fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 15–1 <gloss target="#t_PAK1">PAK</gloss>.
                        Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>. Sent through <gloss
                            target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss> and initialed by <persName
                            corresp="#p_ETLJ1">Eliot</persName>. A stamped notation on a copy of
                        this memorandum in White House files indicates the President saw it. (Ibid.,
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 627, Country Files,
                        Middle East, Pakistan, Vol. VIII, Nov–Dec 71)</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d152fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_WMJ1">Williams</persName> reported to <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> on his recent trip to
                        Pakistan.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-11-05"
                        >November 5, 1971</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                    <item>A.I.D. Deputy Administrator’s Report on Pakistan</item>
                </list>
                <p>A. PRESIDENT <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">YAHYA KHAN</persName>’S CONTROL IN EAST
                    PAKISTAN IS INCREASINGLY LIMITED</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Growing Isolation of President <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1"
                            >Yahya Khan</persName>
                    </hi>. In Islamabad October 27, Ghulam Ishaq Khan, Secretary to the Cabinet,
                    told me that President <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya Khan</persName> was
                    increasingly isolated from events in East Pakistan. He believed the Army’s
                    reporting from East Pakistan had been misleading the President about recent
                    developments. The same points, concerning President <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1"
                        >Yahya Khan</persName>’s growing isolation and misleading reporting from
                    East Pakistan, were made by <persName corresp="#p_AMM1">M.M. Ahmad</persName>,
                    Economic Advisor to the President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Autonomous Army Control in East Pakistan</hi>. The Pakistan
                    Army in East Pakistan has achieved nearly autonomous control of the province, in
                    many respects independent of the policies and direction of President <persName
                        corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya Khan</persName> in Islamabad. Only foreign affairs
                    affecting East Pakistan is firmly in the hands of Islamabad. The relative
                    isolation of President <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya Khan</persName> is
                    probably the result of many factors. Indications of this isolation are that: (a)
                    Army commanders in the East pursue independent military operations, (b) the Army
                    governs the province behind the facade of the puppet civilian Governor Malik and
                    his cabinet—who are completely dependent on the Army for their personal
                    security—with limited reference to Islamabad, <pb facs="d152-02" n="2"
                        xml:id="d152-02"/> (c) little but Pakistani successes and India’s perfidy is
                    reported from Dacca to Islamabad, and (d) President <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1"
                        >Yahya Khan</persName> lacks independent means of observation, reporting and
                    verification of events in the East.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Myth and Reality on Civilian Support in East Pakistan</hi>.
                    President <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya Khan</persName> told us October 28
                    that “civilianization” of government in East Pakistan, under Governor Malik and
                    his Cabinet, is succeeding in stabilizing the political situation. According to
                        <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya Khan</persName>, when elections have
                    filled the vacated Awami League Assembly seats, “political accommodation” for a
                    loyal provincial government will have been completed. Although the Army openly
                    runs these elections, <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya Khan</persName>
                    believes the political stability after elections will assure that India’s
                    strategy of supporting insurrection will have been defeated—and that Mrs.
                        <persName corresp="#p_GI2">Gandhi</persName> will then have nothing in hand
                    to achieve her objectives except recourse to war. The <hi rend="underline"
                        >myth</hi> of growing political stability in East Pakistan is almost
                    certainly fed to <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya Khan</persName> by reports
                    from his civilian Governor and his Army commanders.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="underline">reality</hi> is that Army policies and operations—behind
                    the facade of a civilian government—are progressively and seriously alienating
                    the Bengali population in East Pakistan, and that the seeds of rebellion are not
                    only those sown by India. The wide gap between the myth of growing stability as
                    seen by <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya Khan</persName>, and the reality of
                    political deterioration was most striking from comparing my recent visit to East
                    Pakistan, October 21—26, to observations made during the earlier August 19—25
                    trip.</p>
                <p>B. PAKISTAN ARMY POLICY AND OPERATIONS IN EAST PAKISTAN</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Civil Affairs Run by the Military Advisor to the
                        Governor</hi>. Major General Rao Farman Ali Khan is the Army’s civil affairs
                    specialist with ten years service in the East. As Military Advisor, he sits in
                    the Governor’s House and runs the Province on behalf of the Governor. My call on
                    General Farman Ali Khan October 25th interrupted a meeting with some ten of his
                    military colleagues. They were, he said, selecting the men who would be elected
                    in the next Provincial elections.</p>
                <pb facs="d152-03" n="3" xml:id="d152-03"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Army Policy is Selective Terror and Reprisal</hi>. General
                    Farman Ali Khan described the level of Mukti guerrilla insurgency as somewhat
                    intensified but manageable because the newly trained Bengali guerrillas entering
                    from India feared to take action. Over 1,400 guerrillas had entered Dacca
                    district in the last 30 days but only a few had chosen to fight. He
                    acknowledged, off-the-record, that this was due to the terroristic reprisal
                    policy. He also acknowledged that terror and reprisal had an “unfortunate effect
                    on Bengali attitudes.” But he said, “all Army commanders had concluded that
                    insurgency was more of a problem in areas where the Army had been too lenient
                    and had not demonstrated clean-up operations.”</p>
                <p>The Pakistan Army is one of the best disciplined and professional infantry forces
                    in the world. Despite orders from Islamabad that the Army not engage in
                    terrorist operations against the civilian population—and repeated assurances to
                    U.S. officials to this effect—Pakistan Army commanders continue to carry out
                    terror raids against the population and villages, even within the environs of
                    Dacca and in sight of its large foreign community.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Increasing Chaos in Rural East Pakistan</hi>. General
                    Farman Ali Khan said the Army sought to leave the fighting of the Mukti
                    guerrillas to the newly armed Bengali “Rasikars”, who now numbered 60,000. He
                    acknowledged that “Rasikars”—raised as village levies for guard duty with only
                    ten days training, and without NCOs or officers—did not constitute a disciplined
                    force.</p>
                <p>However, the “Rasikars” are a destabilizing element—living off the land, able to
                    make life and death decisions by denouncing collaborators and openly pillaging
                    and terrorizing villagers without apparent restraint from the Army. With
                    villagers caught between the Rasikars and Mukti guerrillas, law and order is
                    breaking down rapidly in rural East Pakistan. Hence, the rural population is
                    moving either to the cities which are now over populated or going to India. The
                    flow of Muslum refugees to India has recently increased—many of them small
                    land-holders and farmers who are normally the more stable political
                    elements.</p>
                <pb facs="d152-04" n="4" xml:id="d152-04"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Army Policy to Clear East Pakistan of Hindus</hi>. The
                    Pakistan Army is ideologically anti-Hindu and their historic experience in West
                    Pakistan, from the time of partition, has been that Hindus should go to India.
                    Hence, reprisal operations naturally continue to focus against Hindus. Without
                    law or order, except that sanctioned by the Army, Hindu lives and property are
                    not safe in East Pakistan today.</p>
                <p>General Farman Ali Khan accepted the estimate that at least 80 percent of the
                    Hindus had left East Pakistan. He, off-the-record, spoke of about six million
                    refugees who had gone to India and he anticipated that a further 1,500,000
                    refugees would probably go to India “before the situation settles down.”
                    (1,500,000 is a reasonable estimate of the number of Hindus still in East
                    Pakistan.)</p>
                <p>C. FORM AND CONTENT OF <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">YAHYA KHAN</persName>’S
                    DIPLOMACY</p>
                <p>With the Army’s autonomous control in East Pakistan, President <persName
                        corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya Khan</persName>’s role affecting the Eastern
                    Province appears to be primarily in foreign affairs, including the managing of
                    the U.S. relationship. All official American suggestions are immediately taken
                    seriously and lead to major policy statements by President <persName
                        corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya Khan</persName> in Islamabad. The result is “public
                    relations diplomacy”, but it is important not to confuse the form with the
                    substance of policy. Elections, political accommodation, welcoming the return of
                    all refugees, amnesty—these are fine policy pronouncements, but their
                    implementation is in the hands of the Army commanders who govern the Eastern
                    Province, and these Army commanders do not as yet appear subject to foreign
                    influences.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WMJ1">Maurice J. Williams</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
