<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-06-22T05:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-06-22T02:58:00-05:00" n="268" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d268">
                        <head>268. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d268fn1">Source: Library of Congress, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Manuscript
                                Division, Box TS 36, South Asia Chronological File, July 1971-Nov
                                1972. Top Secret; Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes Only. The conversation
                                was held in a guest house.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d268fn2">The President’s Assistant
                                for National Security Affairs <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and Chinese Prime Minister Chou En-lai
                                shared their concern about Soviet influence in South Asia and their
                                opposition to the development of Indian hegemony over the
                                subcontinent.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Peking</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1972-06-22T15:58:00+08:00" to="1972-06-22T18:35:00+08:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">June 22, 1972, 3:58–6:35
                                p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS:</head>
                            <item>Prime Minister Chou En-Lai</item>
                            <item>Ch’iao Kuan-hua, Vice Foreign Minister</item>
                            <item>Chang Wen-Chin, Assistant Foreign Minister (4:40 p.m. to
                                conclusion)</item>
                            <item>Wang Hai-jung, Assistant Foreign Minister</item>
                            <item>Chi Chao-chu, Interpreter</item>
                            <item>Tang Wen-sheng, Interpreter</item>
                            <item>Two Notetakers</item>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>,
                                Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                            <item>Winston Lord, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff</item>
                            <item>Jonathan T. Howe, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>[Omitted here is discussion unrelated to South Asia.]</p>
                        <pb facs="d268-02" n="2" xml:id="d268-02"/>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: There is another question which I originally planned
                            to discuss—the question of the Subcontinent. We will first go into that.
                            We believe we should do this rather quickly because there is still some
                            more about Vietnam we want to discuss.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: All right. Also I
                            want to say a word about Germany to the Prime Minister. Let’s talk about
                            the Subcontinent first.</p>
                        <p>Our assessment is that India is pursuing at the moment a quite aggressive
                            foreign policy. (Prime Minister questions translator’s translation.) And
                            it is in some respects becoming obviously, whatever its own intentions,
                            an extension of some aspects of Soviet foreign policy.</p>
                        <p>For example, the Prime Minister no doubt knows that India has offered to
                            both Indonesia and even to Japan treaties which are word for word the
                            same as its own treaties with the Soviet Union.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: That is right.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: So that if this
                            came to be, it would be in effect an alliance with India which in turn
                            would be linked to the Soviet Union.</p>
                        <p>And I believe also that Indian interests extend as well to Southeast
                            Asia.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: That is so. Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_GI2">Gandhi</persName> has taken over the legacy of her father in his
                            work, The Discovery of India. That was the ambition of Nehru—the
                            ambition of discovery.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: He did not have the
                            energy to carry it out. He was more theoretical.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: Anyway he showed the direction of his ambitions.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Yes. And when we
                            spoke yesterday of a zone of relaxation in Southeast Asia, I want to say
                            to the Prime Minister as far as we are <pb facs="d268-03" n="3" xml:id="d268-03"/> concerned, we would also look with disfavor on an
                            attempt by India to establish hegemony in that area. The Prime Minister
                            may also be aware that when I was asked in Japan about the various
                            proposals for Asian collective security arrangements I stated—not
                            publicly, but since there is no such thing as a private conversation in
                            Japan, I support suppose it became public—that we would join no
                            arrangement which objectively was directed against the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>. If he is not aware, I am telling him
                            now.</p>
                        <p>I think we agree in our analysis of the situation. The immediate problem
                            is that the ability of India to pursue these policies depends to some
                            extent on its ability to gain freedom of action on the Indian
                            Subcontinent. We believe that the strategy of India is to do to West
                            Pakistan what it has already done to East Pakistan by disintegrating it,
                            by bringing about the succession of to Northwestern frontier and
                            Baluchistan. Indeed, when Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_GI2">Gandhi</persName> was in Washington in November and talked with the
                            President she stressed that she did not even talk much about East
                            Pakistan any more. She talked about the betrayal that was involved in
                            West Pakistan. Therefore the problem is whether it is possible to save
                            West Pakistan and thereby absorb some of India’s energies on the
                            Subcontinent rather than free them all for expansion. I’m saying this
                            cold-bloodedly; it’s our analysis.</p>
                        <p>To preserve West Pakistan there are two aspects—one is economic; the
                            other is military. On the economic side we have been able to do quite a
                            bit. We have given $150 million in direct aid and about $180 million
                            through international institutions—that is, the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> share of it.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: That is recently—after the war.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I am talking about
                            since the war, and we are somewhat handicapped because we refused to
                            give any economic assistance to India so we have a complicated
                            Congressional problem with which I will not bore the Prime Minister. But
                            we have not given any aid to India. This is not so much of a punishment
                            because India owes us $3.5 billion and, it will simply refuse to repay.
                            (Chou and Ch’iao laugh).</p>
                        <p>Now the big problem is military assistance to the Pakistanis. We have
                            been prevented by the Democratic Congress from giving aid directly. I
                            wanted to tell the Prime Minister in strictest confidence that when we
                                <pb facs="d268-04" n="4" xml:id="d268-04"/> were in Iran we asked
                            the Shah to organize a consortium of Greece, Iran, Turkey, maybe Jordan,
                            to establish military assistance to Pakistan with American weapons. We
                            did some of this illegally during the war, as the Prime Minister knows.
                            To do it legally we will have to start a small arms program to Pakistan
                            because there is a provision in our law that American weapons can be
                            transferred to third countries only if those countries are eligible to
                            receive American weapons directly. (Chou asks Mr. Chi a question. He
                            answers. Miss Tang also speaks.) We think we can solve that in the next
                            few months.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: I don’t want at all to interfere in internal
                            affairs. However, I want to make a suggestion. I think it would be best
                            that Jordan does not take part in this.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I agree. That will
                            not happen.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: Because Iran and Turkey are somewhat different;
                            there is the question of <gloss target="#t_CENTO1">CENTO</gloss>. But
                            Jordan is not quite in the Arab world.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I agree.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: In December when you went to give them 12 planes by
                            Jordan it was not easy nor did it give any good influence,
                            impression.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: But at that time we
                            had to do it because the Soviet Union was bringing so much pressure on
                            Iran. There was a complicated arrangement. We flew Iranian planes to
                            Jordan and Jordan planes to Pakistan. It was an emergency. This won’t
                            happen again.</p>
                        <p>So in this I wanted to tell the Prime Minister our intention, but
                            something depends on what your intentions are, because if you should
                            have come to the conclusion nothing can be done for Pakistan in the
                            military field then it will be very difficult for us to do it all. But
                            we can and we are prepared to give certain types of equipment that you
                            will find it difficult to supply, and to see whether there can be a
                            combination of Iranian and, Turkish tanks and modern airplanes. And we
                            have also encouraged France to sell airplanes to Pakistan, and they are
                            doing it now.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: We have not stopped our aid to Pakistan. Our aid to
                            Pakistan is continuing. As for our tanks to Pakistan, they are, <pb facs="d268-05" n="5" xml:id="d268-05"/> of course, light tanks. The
                            planes we supply Pakistan are renovated versions of MIG–19s. In fact, to
                            be very honest with you, the renovated MIG–19s we have been giving
                            Pakistan are greater in numbers than those we have been giving Vietnam.
                            We haven’t been giving so many MIG–19s to Vietnam. So what is there so
                            bad about stopping the war in Indochina? Why must we test our weapons on
                            the Indochina battlefield?</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I agree. We don’t
                            want to continue the war in Indochina.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: We will discuss it later. And once the war in
                            Vietnam comes to a stop then we can supply Pakistan even more quickly
                            with our weaponry. We have already agreed to give so many things to
                            them, but we are not able to complete their orders to us. Because East
                            Pakistan lost two divisions of equipment without even fighting.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That was a very
                            stupid deployment.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: But we said nothing. Because we have made it clear
                            that once we have given those weapons to them they have full freedom to
                            make use of them as they like. We have no right to interfere in their
                            affairs. We have not a single adviser there. We don’t want any such
                            prerogatives of interfering in their sovereignty.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: We have no interest
                            in Pakistan except to maintain its independence. We have no other
                            purposes there.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: It is not possible for you not to mind yourself
                            about the Subcontinent because the Soviet Union is attempting to
                            exercise hegemony.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Yes, this is what
                            we are trying to...</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: Britain is already expressing her dissatisfaction.
                            Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: But Britain
                            contributed to this in December.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: To Secretary Home we say, why do you come to realize
                            these things afterwards? And also Foreign Minister Schumann.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: It would be very
                            interesting if you would tell the Europeans about your situation because
                            the Vice Foreign Minister knows last December they made our life very
                            difficult.</p>
                        <pb facs="d268-06" n="6" xml:id="d268-06"/>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: Of the 104 votes in the General Assembly Britain and
                            France were not included, and the Vice Minister openly criticized them
                            about that. But only on 20, 21 December at the Security Council meeting
                            they agreed on the rules of ceasefire after Dacca had fallen, but that
                            was too late already. The General Assembly also voted on December 7.
                            Actually if action was taken at that time, then Dacca would have been
                            saved.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Ch’iao: The greatest procrastinations came about in the Security
                            Council on the 11th and 12th.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I was just going to
                            say that. The British were particularly bad, as the Vice Foreign
                            Minister knows.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: Then the situation was rather clear to some, but it
                            was already too late.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: The art in foreign
                            policy is to be right before it is self-evident.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: That is right. You need foresight.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: So if I may say so,
                            I think a clear analysis of your point of view to both Schumann, who is
                            less steady, and to the British would be very important when they come
                            here. Because Britain is no better off with India for having tried to
                            curry the favor of India than we for having opposed India (Chou
                            laughs).</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: The British think they are still in the days of Lord
                            Mountbatten, but those are days long gone.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: And they try to
                            substitute maneuver for substance. And that can’t be done. But I believe
                            our government, at least this Administration, believes that the Indian
                            extension of Soviet foreign policy, can be very grave throughout
                            Southeast Asia. In the last five years India received one billion two
                            hundred million dollars of military equipment from the Soviet Union.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: So very expensive.</p>
                        <pb facs="d268-07" n="7" xml:id="d268-07"/>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Yes. And produced
                            $1 billion worth of its own. During that same period Pakistan received
                            not quite $500 million, of which most came from you. That includes the
                            domestic production which isn’t great. That explains...</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: India gets her military aid in the form of loans
                            from the Soviet Union?</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Yes. Very low
                            interest loans. I have promised the Vice Chairman to give him some
                            further details, and I will do that if you tell me where I should do
                            it.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: You think it will be all right to have it conveyed
                            through Ambassador Huang Hua?</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I will do that next
                            week. As you know they have given India—they plan to produce MIG–21s in
                            India.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: The characteristics of the MIG–21 actually are not
                            very good. Their maneuverability is even worse than that of the MIG–19
                            and inferior to planes of the same calibre of your country.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That is correct. We
                            are speeding up giving Iran more modern planes so that some of their
                            planes can be free to go to Pakistan. They will still be very good. But
                            they are producing some F-14s and F-15s. And we are speeding that up so
                            that they can give some of their F–4s to Pakistan. That is what I wanted
                            to tell you about our attitude on the Subcontinent.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is conversation unrelated to South Asia.]</p>
                        <pb facs="d268-08" n="8" xml:id="d268-08"/>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: And Pakistan is still remaining a member of <gloss target="#t_CENTO1">CENTO</gloss>?</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Yes, it is still
                            technically a member of <gloss target="#t_CENTO1">CENTO</gloss>. But the
                            major strategy is to give Pakistan enough strength so that India will
                            not be able to attack it; or that it turns itself into a vassal of India
                            and therefore frees India to move into Southeast Asia or other
                            parts.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: Has your diplomatic representative gone to East
                            Pakistan?</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Yes.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: The situation in East Pakistan is not good.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: The situation in
                            East Pakistan is very bad. In the long term I think this will be a
                            cancer for India.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: I think so.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Because if the
                            situation remains chaotic, it will absorb Indian resources and if the
                            situation improves it will be a magnet for West Bengal (Chou laughs).
                            But our impression is that the government in Dacca is so incompetent
                            that the effective administration is in the hands of the Indians.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: It really has the flavor of a colonial regime.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Yes.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: And actually some Indian forces are still remaining
                            in Pakistan.</p>
                        <pb facs="d268-09" n="9" xml:id="d268-09"/>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: As police.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: And officers.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: And also it is
                            surrounded by Indian forces.</p>
                        <p>(At this point, 4:40 p.m., Chang enters.)</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: And so that is about the Subcontinent. As for the
                            Subcontinent we will continue to support the independence of West
                            Pakistan. That is a responsibility that we will continue to carry out.
                            At the same time we shall say West Pakistan is a friendly country to us.
                            And in fact the period of friendship is longer than that with India. But
                            the Pakistanis are rather worried because Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_GI2">Gandhi</persName> has been over the past three
                            months saying everywhere she wants to improve relations with China.
                            Naturally, we haven’t paid any attention to her. As for exchange of
                            Ambassadors with India, we think even that we can wait somewhat. In fact
                            up till now that is the only country with which we have relations but
                            have no Ambassadors. Just petty maneuvers on the part of the
                            Indians.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Their freedom of
                            action is circumscribed by their dependence on Soviet military aid.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: The Indians also have tremendous domestic
                            difficulties. As President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                            said on his visit here, all the loans to India, including those by the
                            World Bank, amount to $10 billion. So India adopts the policy of not
                            repaying.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Not yet, but I am
                            sure that is what she is going to do. (Chou laughs). So far they have
                            only made difficulty about repaying $100 million (Chou laughs).</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: But don’t you have in your hands some of the
                            rupees—the Indian rupees?</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: In counterpart
                            funds.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: They buy grains from you with Indian rupees.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Yes, they do. But
                            we can’t take them out of the country. We can spend them only in
                            India.</p>
                        <pb facs="d268-10" n="10" xml:id="d268-10"/>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: I have probably told you about the history of the
                            story about the situation of my visit to India in 1960 for talks with
                            Nehru, my final visit and my last talk with Nehru. Did I tell you
                            that?</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I don’t remember.
                            Perhaps the Prime Minister can tell me again.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister Chou: That is, in 1960 for the last time I went to New
                            Delhi to have negotiations with Nehru on the Sino-Indian border
                            question. After a week of negotiations, towards the end, I just copied
                            principles cited by Nehru at various periods in the past and said,
                            “let’s agree on those principles.” And even this Nehru refused to agree
                            to. Not a single word of agreement was reached.</p>
                        <p>And then after the breakdown of the negotiations I went to Nepal the next
                            day. On the eve of my departure from Delhi I received some foreign
                            correspondents. At that press conference an American correspondent
                            reminded me, “do you not know the Indian Minister of Food is now in
                            Washington.” I said, “Now I know. Thank you for reminding me of that
                            fact.” And then on the next day in Nepal I saw in the papers that an
                            agreement of a loan on food grains to India, in the amount of 15 million
                            tons of food grains, was signed in Washington to supply India two or
                            three times a year, which was to be repayed in rupees. That was the
                            encouragement on your side to Nehru.</p>
                        <p>And on the other side was encouragement given to him by Khrushchev. That
                            is, Khrushchev in order to obtain the so-called Spirit of Camp David—a
                            spirit which you never recognized—Khrushchev tore up in 1959 a treaty he
                            entered into with us on cooperation in the economic field.</p>
                        <p>At that time, in October 1959, the Indians made a military provocation
                            against us at the Natula Pass on the border with India. The Pass is on
                            the top of the plateau. The Indians when they went up to the Pass they
                            had more casualties, and because the Indians suffered more casualties
                            they [the Russians] said it was China which launched the attack against
                            India. And from that time the Indians believed what Khrushchev told
                            them. Afterwards Neville, the British correspondent, made that
                            clear.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is conversation unrelated to South Asia.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>