<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>376. Paper Prepared in the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d376</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">376</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-12-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1Gk59BaIROJJML" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85116922"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Salvage</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="reczhNQIs9rGlNS1M" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96008124"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Humanitarian assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="reccdibbkraMVDFLb" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2020000630"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Humanitarian relief</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees">Refugee relief</term>
                    <term ref="recQJgxXbB2a4RsHo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00009290"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consortium</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-12-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="376"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d376">
                <head>376. Paper Prepared in the Department of State<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d376fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1"
                            >RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> BANGLA DESH-<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. Secret. The
                        paper is undated but it was sent on December 22, 1971, by Executive
                        Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ETLJ1">Eliot</persName> to <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> under a covering memorandum that
                        indicated it had been prepared in response to a December 16 instruction from
                        the <gloss target="#t_WSAG1">WSAG</gloss> to prepare a paper on the subject
                        of the U.S. relationship with Bangladesh. The covering memorandum indicates
                        the paper was drafted by Constable and cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_LLB1">Laingen</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SDT1"
                            >Schneider</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_VC1">Van Hollen</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName>, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_IJNII1">Irwin</persName>. Presumably the same information
                        applies to the attached study. For a record of the December 16 <gloss
                            target="#t_WSAG1">WSAG</gloss> meeting, see <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v11#d318">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol. XI, South Asia
                            Crisis, 1971, Document 318</ref>. A January 17 memorandum from <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJW1">Davis</persName> to the Departments of State and
                        Defense, the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>, and the <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> indicates that the paper was circulated
                        again for consideration of the Senior Review Group at its meeting on January
                        19. (National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 642, Country Files, Middle East,
                        South Asia, Vol. IV (1972)) For the minutes of the January 19 <gloss
                            target="#t_SRG1">SRG</gloss> meeting, see <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v11#d210">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol. XI, South Asia
                            Crisis, 1971, Document 210</ref>. The reference in the paper to the
                        Hallstein doctrine is to the policy of West Germany to break diplomatic
                        relations with any country that established relations with the German
                        Democratic Republic.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d376fn2">This paper analyzed the U.S.
                        relationship with Bangladesh and argued, in part, for “relatively early
                        recognition.”</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates"
                        calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1971-12-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                        notBefore="1971-12-17T00:00:00-05:00">undated</date>
                </dateline>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="underline">U.S. Relationship with Bangla Desh</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Summary</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The situation in East Pakistan is fluid. In the West, <persName corresp="#p_BZA1"
                        >Bhutto</persName> is taking over power and still hopes to salvage something
                    in the East by means of negotiations. In his conversations with us, he has not
                    given up entirely on the idea, to use his own words, “of the loosest kind of
                    confederal link between East and West.” While we believe a separate Bangla Desh
                    is a reality, we should do nothing which would tend by our own actions to
                    foreclose such an option for him, regardless of how slim the prospects are that
                    he will be able to retrieve something in the East in the aftermath of the Indian
                    military victory.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName> told Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> he would understand the need for U.S.
                    humanitarian assistance to Bangla Desh, so long as it was done in a way that no
                    element of recognition was implied or involved and that it did not otherwise
                    compromise his negotiating efforts. <persName corresp="#p_BZA1"
                        >Bhutto</persName> would probably also agree that we should seek to retain a
                    modest hard-core presence in the form of <pb facs="d376-02" n="2"
                        xml:id="d376-02"/> our Consulate General. This is justified both on
                    immediate security grounds as well as our long-range interests which will be to
                    have a reasonable relationship with whatever entity evolves in the East, and
                    whether or not it retains a loose confederal link with the West. Therefore, the
                    short-run approach of the U.S. should be to maintain low-key informal contact,
                    be helpful through the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> (not through India) in
                    projected humanitarian assistance to the East, and avoid any early move towards
                    recognition, keeping this matter under review as the situation evolves. Over the
                    next month at least we will have to assess carefully <persName corresp="#p_BZA1"
                        >Bhutto</persName>’s tactics and plans regarding the former East wing, the
                    nature of India’s relationship with Bangla Desh, and the Bangla Desh capacity or
                    lack of capacity to exercise effective sovereignty in its own territory.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Discussion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In Islamabad, the new <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName> regime is
                    faced with the immediate problem of determining and articulating its stance
                    toward the East, including therein its attitude on <persName corresp="#p_RSM1"
                        >Sheikh Mujib</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName> told
                    the Secretary on December 18 that he <pb facs="d376-03" n="3" xml:id="d376-03"/>
                    believes there is still a chance for a loose confederal link between East and
                    West and that he will make an effort to this end. His tactics, including those
                    on Mujib, are not yet known.</p>
                <p>In the East, a provisional government of Bangla Desh can be expected to move into
                    Dacca in a matter of days. It will preside over the world’s eighth largest state
                    in terms of population, one of the poorest in terms of development, and a state
                    with enormous problems of rehabilitation and resettlement. The focus of its
                    energies in the short run will need to be heavily internal—establishing itself
                    as a government, rebuilding the administrative structure, and relocating and
                    feeding its people. But it will probably also seek early <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> membership and a maximum in international recognition. Urgent
                    problems of humanitarian relief will probably form the first framework of
                    international (and our own) involvement and role in Bangla Desh.</p>
                <p>Bangla Desh owes its existence at this early date to Indian military action with
                    Soviet backing. This gives the Indians, and through them the Russians, a strong
                    initial position. There are other factors, however, which should <pb
                        facs="d376-04" n="4" xml:id="d376-04"/> cause Bangla Desh leaders to seek to
                    establish some distance between their new country and India. They may find, for
                    example, that Indian forces will not be prepared to Withdraw as rapidly as the
                    Bangla Desh might wish. They are also aware of Indian policies toward such
                    neighbors as Nepal. They are familiar with hard Indian terms in previous
                    India-Pakistan negotiations on matters of great importance to East Pakistan.
                    Bangla Desh is a predominantly Muslim country and, despite statements about
                    secularism, its leadership will be wary about the potential dangers arising from
                    Hindu nationalism next door. Finally, Bangla Desh leaders know they have immense
                    relief and economic problems which another impoverished nation—India—cannot meet
                    and which also cannot be assured from the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>There is some prospect therefore that the Bangla Desh leadership will seek broad
                    international support to help assure their independence from India and the
                    Soviet Union. Over the longer run frictions between India and Bangla Desh seem
                    inevitable. Consequently, there are steps which we can take, both for the short
                    and long term, which may serve to bolster independence from both India and the
                    Soviet Union.</p>
                <pb facs="d376-05" n="5" xml:id="d376-05"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Assumptions for the Immediate Future</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>That Indian forces can be expected to remain in Bangla Desh for a minimum
                        of 30 days and up to six months.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>That security and other considerations require immediate contacts between
                        our Consulate General and Indian/Bangla Desh authorities.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>That <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName>’s comments to date
                        indicate that as a minimum Pakistan will delay recognition and will
                        otherwise seek to avoid dealing officially with Bangla Desh as a separate
                        state for some time to come.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>That the Soviet Union will move toward recognition fairly promptly,
                        depending however on the nature of Pakistan’s attitudes re 3rd country
                        recognition.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>That the Chinese will delay recognition indefinitely.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>That the British and other Commonwealth countries will move fairly
                        promptly toward normal diplomatic ties.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>That relief and refugee assistance to Bangla Desh will remain under <gloss
                            target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> auspices, and that our participation therein
                        need not necessarily raise questions of recognition.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="d376-06" n="6" xml:id="d376-06"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Short Range Posture</hi>
                </p>
                <p>We should delay action on the longer range decision of recognition for the
                    immediate future: <list>
                        <item>—Bangla Desh authorities will be preoccupied in the short range with
                            getting their own house in order and may not attempt to force us to take
                            a decision immediately.</item>
                        <item>—We need at least a month to assess (a) Bhutto’s stance toward the
                            former eastern wing; (b) India’s intentions toward Bangla Desh; and (c)
                            Bangla Desh ability to exercise effective sovereignty in its own
                            territory.</item>
                        <pb facs="d376-07" n="7" xml:id="d376-07"/>
                        <item>—There is good basis under customary international law to ask and
                            expect Bangla Desh authorities to permit our Consulate General to
                            continue consular functions on at least a limited basis, without
                            prejudging the issue of recognition. (A total of 13 countries now have
                            consular representation in Dacca.)</item>
                        <item>—It is not presently clear how and when a Bangla Desh U.N. membership
                            request might arise, but it seems unlikely in the immediate weeks ahead.
                            We should address this issue when it arises, including whatever bearing
                            it might have at the time to our own relationship with that
                            regime.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Assuming the above rationale to be accurate, the following short term posture
                    would commend itself: <list>
                        <item>—We would try to maintain our present hard core staff in Dacca,
                            establishing a minimum working relationship with Bangla Desh <pb
                                facs="d376-08" n="8" xml:id="d376-08"/> and Indian military
                            authorities, making it clear that our doing so does not imply
                            recognition. We could try routinely to keep our <gloss target="#t_USIS1"
                                >USIS</gloss> reading rooms open but avoid other <gloss
                                target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> operations. <gloss target="#t_AID1"
                                >AID</gloss> operations would be restricted to whatever
                            participation is essential to our role in humanitarian relief.</item>
                        <item>—We would quietly convey to Bangla Desh authorities in Dacca and their
                            representatives here that we have the matter of our future recognition
                            under review and that in the interim we would wish to maintain a
                            strictly consular presence.</item>
                        <item>—We would review our position on Bangla Desh <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                                >UN</gloss> membership on the basis of information available when
                            the issue arises.</item>
                        <item>—We would continue to play a role in both the refugee relief (and
                            rehabilitation) effort and former <gloss target="#t_UNEPRO1"
                                >UNEPRO</gloss> operations, but entirely under <gloss
                                target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> auspices. We would channel any <pb
                                facs="d376-09" n="9" xml:id="d376-09"/> foodgrain requests from
                            Bangla Desh authorities through <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                            channels. We would want to get across to Bangla Desh authorities that
                            their actions regarding minorities and humanitarian relief will have a
                            bearing on our future policies toward Bangla Desh.</item>
                        <item>—We would keep Islamabad fully informed of our actions. Meanwhile we
                            would urge as appropriate in our relationship with Bhutto a maximum in
                            moderation in <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> attitudes toward
                            Bangla Desh, and in particular seek to prevent evolution of any kind of
                            “Hallstein Doctrine” approach to the East. We should also convey our
                            view that <persName corresp="#p_RSM1">Sheikh Mujib</persName> remains an
                            important factor in the evolution of Bangla Desh internal and external
                            policies.</item>
                        <item>—We would also want to keep in close touch with the British and other
                            Consortium countries as to both our short and longer range policies
                            toward Bangla Desh.</item>
                        <pb facs="d376-10" n="10" xml:id="d376-10"/>
                        <item>—We would inform India of our position, indicating that our position
                            on recognition will depend inter alia on a commitment on withdrawal of
                            Indian forces and the ability of the Bangla Desh government to assume
                            the responsibilities and obligations of a sovereign and independent
                            state.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Options for the Longer Range Future</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Among the options available to us for the longer term would be to withdraw our
                    present consular presence from Dacca and have no relationship at all with Bangla
                    Desh. We exclude this from consideration, since this would not support our basic
                    policy of seeking a stable Subcontinent free of domination by any of the Great
                    Powers, notably the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>We also exclude, for the longer term, continuing a purely consular presence.
                    Doing so would not serve our basic objective of seeking to limit India and
                    especially Soviet influence. Moreover, the Bangla Desh authorities may fairly
                    soon make our continued consular presence <pb facs="d376-11" n="11"
                        xml:id="d376-11"/> dependent on a decision on our part re recognition and
                    therefore preclude it as a long range policy.</p>
                <p>If these premises are correct, and of course depending on the efforts of Bhutto
                    to explore the basis for reunion on the basis of loose confederation, the issue
                    for the longer range becomes one of timing of recognition. If and when this
                    becomes the issue, we believe that U.S. interests would probably best be served
                    by relatively early recognition, for the following reasons: <list>
                        <item>—We will want to encourage Bangla Desh freedom of action and limit its
                            reliance on the Soviet Union and India. Previous Awami League attitudes
                            toward the U.S. were friendly and these are probably basically
                            unchanged. We have no issues or problems with the emergent state of
                            Bangla Desh. We believe they will actively want a relationship with us,
                            which should permit us to determine the timing of recognition—provided
                            we do not delay too long.</item>
                        <pb facs="d376-12" n="12" xml:id="d376-12"/>
                        <item>—Leaving the field to the Soviets also runs the risk of contributing
                            to a radicalization of the Bangla Desh leadership, a risk which is
                            already real. Again, delay could enhance that risk.</item>
                        <item>—A working relationship with Bangla Desh, established early, may
                            enhance our ability to influence more moderate Bangla Desh attitudes
                            towards Islamabad which in turn could be decisive in the long range
                            posture Islamabad takes towards its former Eastern province. We may be
                            as influential as any outside power in affecting the nature of that
                            posture and trying to preclude any kind of. “Hallstein Doctrine stance”
                            by the <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss>. Eventual Pakistani
                            rapprochement with Bangla Desh (assuming no success in efforts toward
                            reunion) could be important (a) as a further offset to Indian hegemony
                            over the new state and (b) in order to retain some of the advantages of
                            an economic <pb facs="d376-13" n="13" xml:id="d376-13"/> and trade
                            relationship with the former eastern wing.</item>
                        <item>—There is also the practical consideration that a number of very
                            complex financial problems will grow out of the division of assets and
                            liabilities of the two former wings of Pakistan. As a major creditor, we
                            will be involved in this process and benefit in doing so from early and
                            official contacts with Bangla Desh.</item>
                        <item>—Finally, there is the factor of what will be considerable pressure in
                            Congress and in the press for U.S. recognition, growing as other
                            countries recognize. This will find particular focus in the field of
                            humanitarian relief, where our ability to continue an active role beyond
                            an interim period might be restricted in the absence of official Bangla
                            Desh relations.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
