<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-01-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-01-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="383" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d383">
                        <head>383. Telegram 239 From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in India</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d383fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 16 BANGLA DESH. Limited Official
                                Use. Repeated to Bombay, Calcutta, Dacca, Islamabad, and Madras. The
                                attachments cited in the telegram were not found.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d383fn2">The Government of the
                                People’s Republic of Bangladesh appealed to the United States for
                                recognition.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline><placeName>New Delhi</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-01-06">January 6, 1972, 1509Z</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subj:</head>
                            <item>Bangladesh Recognition Appeal</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Following appeal for recognition on letterhead qte government of
                                the People’s Republic of Bangladesh unqte datelined President’s
                                house, Bangabhaban, Dacca, December 30, addressed to President
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and signed
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ISN1">Syed Nazrul Islam</persName>, Acting
                                President, was left with <gloss target="#t_FSL1">FSL</gloss> Embassy
                                receptionist January 6. Format suggests letter may be round robin.
                                    <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> high commission here has
                                received near identical version dated January 4. Qte excelllency, I
                                have the honour to draw your attention to the proclamation of the
                                sovereign independent People’s Republic of Bangladesh on March 26,
                                1971. This declaration representes the unanimous verdict of 75
                                million people of Bangladesh.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Qte the foundation of the nation of Pakistan in 1947 was due in
                                major part to the sacrifice in blood, lives and property of our
                                people. Thereafter, as is well known, the people of Bangladesh were
                                subjected to a long period of ruthless colonial domination,
                                systematic economic exploitation, and gross political and cultural
                                discrimination by successive regimes dominated by the ruling circles
                                of West Pakistan. Over the last several years our people <pb facs="d383-02" n="2" xml:id="d383-02"/> had waged a peaceful and
                                non-violent struggle for the attainment of our basic rights. Even
                                the frustration of effort after effort by successive regimes of
                                Pakistan did not make us resort to violence. We continued our
                                non-violent struggle.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Qte the people of Bangladesh recorded their overwhelming
                                confidence in the leadership and policies of <persName corresp="#p_RSM1">Sheikh Mujibur Rahman</persName> in the
                                elections in 1970. The military rulers postponed the convening of
                                National Assembly repeatedly, and while pretending to negotiate,
                                augmented their military strength. On the black night of March 25,
                                1971, they let loose their army in a pre-meditated assault on the
                                innocent and defenceless men, women and children of our country.
                                they made a special target of the intellectuals, the elite of the
                                youth and the leaders of the workers, peasants and students. This
                                left us with no alternative but to declare independence, and resort
                                to arms.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Qte the policy of repression continued with increasing brutality
                                in the vain hope of liquidating the leadership and reducing the
                                majority of the Bengali speaking people in Pakistan to a minority.
                                Members of the minority communtiites became special victims of the
                                reign of terror. As a result of this policy of genocide, rape, arson
                                and loot, nearly ten million of our men, women and children were
                                driven out and took shelter in India.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Qte we made the formal proclamation of our independence on April
                                10, 1971. Our struggle for liberation gained increased momentum and
                                strength. Nearly 60,000 members of the former East Bengal regiment,
                                East Pakistan rifles and other paramilitary formations identified
                                themselves with the struggle of the people of Bangladesh, and took
                                up arms in defence of our motherland. They were joined by hundreds
                                of thousands of young men whom they trained to defend the
                                sovereignty and independence of their homeland, with a view to
                                release her finally from the bonds of colonial oppression by West
                                Pakistan.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Qte we are glad to inform you, excellency, that this struggle has
                                culminated in success. The liberation army of the People’s Republic
                                of Bangladesh, the Mukti Bahini have been joined by the armed forces
                                of India, at our request, following the unprovoked attack on India
                                by the Pakistani forces of occupation. Our development has not only
                                been welcomed by the broad masses <pb facs="d383-03" n="3" xml:id="d383-03"/> of our people, but the spontaneous and
                                overwhelming support of the entirety of our people has been amply
                                and publicy demonstrated.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Qte the proclamation of independence of the People’s Republic of
                                Bangladesh and subsequent announcements by my government are
                                attached for the information of your excellency’s government. It is
                                reiterated that the basis principles of Oru state policy shall by
                                democracy, socialism, secularism and the establishment of an
                                egalitarian society, where there would be no discrimination on the
                                basis of race, religion, sex or creed. In our foreign relations, we
                                are determined to follow a policy of non-alignment, peaceful
                                co-existence adn opposition to colonialism, racialism, and
                                imperialism in all its forms and manifestation.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>Qte conscious of our responsibility for the large number of
                                citizens of Bangladesh temporarily in India, we would like to assure
                                you of our governments firm intention of organising their
                                expeditious return to their homes.</item>
                            <pb facs="d383-04" n="4" xml:id="d383-04"/>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>Qte my government hereby places on record its ability and
                                willingness to fulfill all international treaties and obligations to
                                which it may have succeeded.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>Qte as the nation of Bangladesh emerges to take its place side by
                                side with the other countries in Asia, Africa, North America and all
                                the non-aligned world, it reaffirms its pledge to follow the
                                principles outlined at Bandung and Lusaka. The valiant struggle for
                                liberation and the heoric efforts of our people to throw off the
                                imperialist yoke twice in one generation is a tangible proof of our
                                adherence to these principles, we will continue to give principled
                                support to all nations in their struggle against colonialism,
                                racialism or imperialism in an all their manifestations. It is
                                accordingly our hope that, in support of these same principles, Your
                                Excellency’s government will now see its way to welcoming us into
                                the family of nations. Speedy recognition by your government would
                                be an acknowledgement of our aspirations. It is also our considered
                                assessment that the granting of this recognition is a most necessary
                                and important step to stabilise <pb facs="d383-05" n="5" xml:id="d383-05"/> the situation in South and Southeast
                                Asia.</item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>Qte please accept, Excellency, the assurances of my highest
                                esteem. Unqte.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_KKB1">Keating</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>