<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>406. Telegram 770 From the Consulate General in Dacca to the to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d406</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">406</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1972-03-03T01:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1972-03-03T01:15:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-03-03T01:15:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-03-03T01:15:00-05:00" n="406"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d406">
                <head>406. Telegram 770 From the <gloss type="from">Consulate General in
                        Dacca</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d406fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 591, Country Files, Middle East,
                        Bangladesh. Secret; Priority; Nodis. <persName corresp="#p_SHHH1"
                            >Saunders</persName> sent a copy of this telegram to <persName
                            corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> on March 3 with a covering memorandum
                        in which he suggested that <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName>
                        approve an instruction to <persName corresp="#p_SHD1">Spivack</persName> to
                        return to Washington for consultation. “The main rationale for bringing him
                        back here would be to gain the time necessary to allow us to recognize only
                        toward the end of March. It seems unlikely that the Bengalis would throw us
                        out if it appeared that we were on the verge of taking a final decision.”
                            <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> returned the memorandum to
                            <persName corresp="#p_SHHH1">Saunders</persName> with a handwritten note
                        instructing that <persName corresp="#p_SHD1">Spivack</persName> be recalled
                        on March 17.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d406fn2">Consul General <persName
                            corresp="#p_SHD1">Spivack</persName> cabled that he felt that “we are
                        approaching the limits of tolerance of <gloss target="#t_GOBD1">GOBD</gloss>
                        in matter of continued operation of this post without <gloss target="#t_US1"
                            >US</gloss> recognition of BD.” He suggested that a decision on
                        recognition be conveyed to the Bangladesh Government by March 9th in order
                        “to do what we intend to do without appearing to be forced into it by <gloss
                            target="#t_GOBD1">GOBD</gloss> action.”</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Dacca</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1972-03-03T06:15:00+00:00">March 3, 1972, 0615Z</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Bangladesh Government Tolerance on Recognition Question</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] appears to confirm
                        impression I have gained from various sources that we are approaching the
                        limits of tolerance of <gloss target="#t_GOBD1">GOBD</gloss> in matter of
                        continued operation of this post without <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                        recognition of BD.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Dacca 722 and Dacca 689 give clear indications of nature of <gloss
                            target="#t_GOBD1">GOBD</gloss> concern. I suspect without being able to
                        prove that there had been an original intention on part of <gloss
                            target="#t_GOBD1">GOBD</gloss> to require closure of this post in
                        response to Samad’s presentaion on Feb 26 had been considered
                        unsatisfactory. Assuming this I can only speculate whether there was a
                        change in <gloss target="#t_GOBD1">GOBD</gloss> attitude between Feb 26 and
                        28 or whether response conveyed by me on latter date was judged satisfactory
                        enough to allow Samad to make favorable decision. Latter seems more doubful
                        proposition of two, since I doubt Samad would have had authority to make
                        decision on spot without consulting Mujib.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Whatever may be the case in regard to foregoing I now believe that we are
                        approaching the crunch. There are several dates which appear significant in
                        this connection. Mujib will return Dacca from his Soviet trip on March 6.
                        Indian troops are apparently scheduled for definitive departure from <gloss
                            target="#t_BD1">BD</gloss> on March 12, which they will do with
                        ceremonial functions to which foreign representitives will be invited. Given
                        fact that President has now returned from China, any of these dates might be
                        selected by <gloss target="#t_GOBD1">GOBD</gloss> as suitable for gesture
                        demonstrating national self-respect by closing us down.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>All other considerations aside, I assume if <gloss target="#t_USG1"
                            >USG</gloss> intends to recognize <gloss target="#t_BD1">BD</gloss> that
                        there will be an interest in doing so at a time when that action will
                        receive <pb facs="d406-02" n="2" xml:id="d406-02"/> optimum favorable public
                        attention. The best date for that purpose would appear to me to fall
                        somewhere in the week of March 6th, preferable the 8th or 9th. If this is
                        case we shold convey this to <gloss target="#t_GOBD1">GOBD</gloss> as soon
                        as possible to avoid their acting earlier.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>If on other hand <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> does not rpt not
                        intend recognize <gloss target="#t_BD1">BD</gloss> with next month, I
                        believe we should be prepared for a demand that this office be closed. In
                        that case I assume that we would seek protection of some other power here
                        (Australians would appear on the job) and try to maintain as much of present
                        physical equipment and custodial staff in place as possible as an American
                        intrests section within the Australian diplomatic mission.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>I raise the question whether our own self-respect does not require that we
                        do what we intend to do without appearing to be forced into it by <gloss
                            target="#t_GOBD1">GOBD</gloss>.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHD1">Spivack</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
