<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-07-29T17:10:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-07-29T17:10:00-05:00" n="73" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d73">
                        <head>73. Telegram 122180 From the <gloss type="from">Department of
                                State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in India</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d73fn1">Source: National Archives,
                                    <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73,
                                    <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 15–1 INDIA. Limited Official
                                Use; <gloss target="#t_Limdis1">Limdis</gloss>. Drafted on July 28
                                by R. Grant Smith (<gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>/INC), cleared
                                by M. Gordon Tiger (<gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>/INC) and by
                                Craig Baxter (<gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_PAF1">PAF</gloss>), and approved by <persName corresp="#p_VC1">Van Hollen</persName>. Repeated to
                                Rawalpindi.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d73fn2">The Department transmitted
                                the text of a letter from Indian Foreign Minister Singh to Secretary
                                of State <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> in which
                                Singh expressed his interest in improving Indo-U.S. relations but
                                warned that a U.S. decision to resume arms sales to Pakistan would
                                have “serious repercussions.”</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-07-29T22:10:00+00:00">July 29, 1970, 2210Z</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subj:</head>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SSS1">Swaran Singh</persName> Letter to the
                                Secretary</item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="d73-01" n="1" xml:id="d73-01"/>
                        <p>Indian Embassy July 28 delivered following letter to Secretary from
                            Foreign Minister, acknowledgment of which is being prepared.</p>
                        <p>QTE My dear Secretary of State,</p>
                        <p>Thank you very much for your kind message sent through your Embassy in
                            Delhi congratulating me on my appointment as Minister for External
                            Affairs. May I reciprocate your sentiments and express the hope that we
                            shall work together in developing further the friendly relations which
                            so happily exist between our two countries in a spirit of mutual
                            understanding and frankness.</p>
                        <p>Your Ambassador, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KKB1">Kenneth B.
                                Keating</persName>, saw me recently and I was glad to discuss
                            briefly with him ways <pb facs="d73-02" n="2" xml:id="d73-02"/> and
                            means of further improvement of our relations. Although this is my very
                            first letter to you, I should like to take this opportunity to share
                            with you some of my thoughts in this regard.</p>
                        <p>It seems to me that there is no conflict in our aims and objectives of
                            mainaining peace and progress in the world and particularly in our
                            region. Our methods may be different; there may also be some difference
                            in emphasis on certain issues but I am convinced that with more frequent
                            contacts at various levels, we can remove some of the irritants that
                            seem to spoil our relations at times and further strengthen the more
                            permanent bonds that unite our two countries and peoples. I can assure
                            you that we shall always give the highest consideration to your feelings
                            and sentiments and take you into confidence in matters that are of <pb facs="d73-03" n="3" xml:id="d73-03"/> mutual concern. I am confident
                            that you on your part would do the same.</p>
                        <p>It is in this spirit of mutual understanding and frankness that I wish to
                            mention some disturbing reports that we have recently heard about the
                            proposed resumption of sale of arms by your country to Pakistan. I need
                            not mention the various reasons why we have opposed such a move. But, I
                            would be less than frank if I did not emphasise the fact that such a
                            move will have very grave and serious repercussions in our country and
                            on the peace and stability of this sub-continent. I hope that you will
                            give full consideration to our views which we have conveyed to your
                            Ambassador and through our Ambassador to you before you take any final
                            decision in the matter.</p>
                        <pb facs="d73-04" n="4" xml:id="d73-04"/>
                        <p>I wish you every success in your efforts to promote peace in the world
                            and strengthen friendship with all countries including our own. The
                            world is passing through difficult times and your country has a special
                            responsibility in preserving peace and stability. We on our part are
                            fully conscious of our own responsibilities and we hope that through
                            mutual cooperation and understanding, we shall be able to work together
                            to achieve our common goals and objectives.</p>
                        <p>I look forward to the pleasure of meeting you when I attend the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> General Assembly Session and having frank
                            and friendly talks with you on various matters which are of concern to
                            both our countries.</p>
                        <p>With all good wishes, Yours sincerely, <persName corresp="#p_SSS1">Swaran
                                Singh</persName>. UNQTE</p>
                        <p>END</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>