<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>81. Information Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near
                    Eastern and South Asian Affairs (Sisco) to Secretary of State ) to Secretary of
                    State Rogers</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d81</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">81</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="south-and-central-asia" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="south-and-central-asia">South Asia</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="81"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d81">
                <head>81. Information Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near
                    Eastern and South Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="from"
                        >Sisco</persName>) to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RWP1"
                        type="to">Rogers</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d81fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss
                            target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>/INC Files: Lot 77 D 51, DTS–Chrons, Oct–Dec
                        1970. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SDT1">Schneider</persName>
                        and cleared by <persName corresp="#p_SWF1">Spengler</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_VC1">Van Hollen</persName>.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d81fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> summarized the Indian and
                        Pakistani reactions to the decision to authorize limited arms sales to
                        Pakistan.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-10-09"
                        >October 9, 1970</date>
                </dateline>
                <pb facs="d81-01" n="1" xml:id="d81-01"/>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                    <item>U.S. Sale of Military Equipment to Pakistan</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Indians have now protested our decision to sell a limited quantity of
                    military equipment to Pakistan, both in New Delhi and in Washington. They have
                    also issued a very starchy public statement indicating their dissatisfaction
                    with our explanations for the sale, The Pakistanis are pleased that we have
                    brought this matter to a conclusion and are cooperating with us closely and
                    discreetly in handling it. President <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1"
                        >Yahya</persName> has publicly announced his plans to dine at the White
                    House October 24 and have a bilateral meeting with the President in
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>In formal oral presentations in New Delhi and Washington October 7 and 8, the
                    Indians conveyed their “strong protest and serious misgivings about our
                    decision.” They were careful to say, however, that they meant this in a
                    “friendly spirit.” The Indian spokesmen (Acting Foreign Secretary in
                    Delhi—Indian Minister in Washington) warned of “the most adverse and violent
                    reaction of Indian public opinion” and expressed concern about the political
                    pressures which our decision would place on Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_GI2"
                        >Gandhi</persName>’s Government. They expressed fear that our sale might
                    seriously affect India-Pakistan negotiations which have been showing some signs
                    of progress. They took serious exception to the rationale for our sale which had
                    been previously conveyed to them. They explained that Pakistan was arming only
                    against India. Therefore, they said the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> must
                        <pb facs="d81-02" n="2" xml:id="d81-02"/> take an extremely serious view of
                    any addition to Pakistan’s armed strength. They claimed that India had expressed
                    similar views with the same force to the Soviet Union about its supply to
                    Pakistan and that the Soviet Union had reacted positively to this warning.</p>
                <p>On October 8, the Indians issued a press statement announcing their protest and
                    indicating that they were not satisfied with U.S. explanations for the sale. The
                    statement alleged that our decision was against the interest of peace in South
                    Asia. It said “the resumption of inflow of arms” to Pakistan, which has
                    committed aggression against India three times, is of grave concern; Pakistan is
                    armed only against India. The statement said that Pakistan used U.S. arms
                    against India in 1965 despite U.S. assurances, and the new U.S. special supply
                    “is not even subject to any such assurances.”</p>
                <p>While we recognize that because of internal political requirements the <gloss
                        target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> had to publicly criticize our sale, we believe
                    their statement goes far beyond what was necessary. They have failed to take
                    into consideration: (1) the limited nature of the sale; (2) that the sale was a
                    one-time exception to our embargo which remains in effect; (3) that we are
                    selling primarily replacements or unsophisticated equipment; (4) that we are not
                    selling tanks. To the contrary, this statement incorrectly refers to the
                    “resumption of inflow of arms” and is likely to provoke additional public
                    reaction rather than control it. Furthermore, the Government of India has
                    reacted much more strenuously to our sale offer than it did to the decisions of
                    the Soviets and the French to supply much larger quantities of military
                    equipment to Pakistan. We have told the Indians here of our views on their
                    statement and instructed Embassy Delhi to express similar serious concern about
                    it.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, we are proceeding to discuss with the Pakistanis arrangements for
                    carrying out our sales offer, a subject which President <persName
                        corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya</persName> will probably raise in general terms
                    with President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> during their
                    bilateral talks.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
