<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-02-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-02-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="183" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d183">
                        <head>183. Message From Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MH1" type="from">Macmillan</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1" type="to">Eisenhower</persName><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d183fn0">Source: Department of State,
                                Presidential Correspondence: Lot 66 D 204. Secret.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-02-23">February 23,
                                1959</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>I promised to send you a further message today giving you my
                                impressions.<note n="1" xml:id="d183fn1">In a message delivered on
                                February 22 <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> promised
                                to give the President a report on his visit to Moscow following his
                                first formal meeting with <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>) For
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>’s account of his
                                visit, see <hi rend="italic">Riding the Storm</hi>, pp.
                                592–632.</note> Although I have only been here 48 hours some of
                            these are already quite clear. From the way in which <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> talked to me throughout
                            yesterday when we were out in the country it was borne in on me that in
                            spite of their great new power and wealth the Russians are still
                            obsessed by a sense of insecurity. The old bogey of encirclement has not
                            yet been laid. Like a poor man who has suddenly made a fortune they feel
                            uneasy in their new situation and they are resentful and nervous of
                            their neighbours. Whenever <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> mentioned the Germans it was possible to
                            sense his hatred and distrust of them.</p>
                        <p>I believe that these feelings of apprehension are just as real as are
                            their misconceptions about Western policy. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> treated me to a diatribe about mistakes which
                            the West had made in the past and about evil intentions which it had
                            nurtured towards Russia. He said that we had made a wrong assessment of
                            the situation after Stalin’s death. We had counted on internal
                            difficulties to enable us to extract concessions. We had even thought
                            “Liberalism” might appear in Russia. We had tried to impose conditions
                            and had followed slogans of containment, roll-back and liberation. Such
                            concessions could not be wrung out of the Soviet Union. He did not
                            accuse us of actually wanting war but said we had created an atmosphere
                            of war.</p>
                        <pb facs="0411" n="386" xml:id="pg_386"/>
                        <p>On Germany and Berlin I detected no signs that there was any weakening in
                            their purpose. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> said
                            that there was no room for manoeuvre or retreat from the position they
                            had put forward. He repeated all the usual logic-chopping arguments in
                            support of his proposals for a free city and for a peace treaty with the
                            two sides of Germany. He said that they insisted on this position
                            “because they saw no other way out”. Berlin, reunification, peace
                            treaty, European security were different questions. Some were more ripe
                            for settlement than others. But in our reply of January 10<note n="2" xml:id="d183fn2">Apparent reference to the Western response of
                                February 16 (see <ref target="#d176">Document 176</ref>); the Soviet
                                note on Germany is dated January 10 (see <ref target="#d124">Document 124</ref>).</note> we had tried to bring them all
                            together. He distrusted our proposals which looked to him like an
                            attempt to draw the Soviet Government into a labyrinth of negotiation
                            which might last for 9 or 10 years. I tried to explain why it was
                            impossible for us to accept their proposals. I said that if the Soviet
                            position was altogether inflexible as <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> had indicated the situation was very serious
                            indeed.</p>
                        <p>For the next day or so I propose to leave it at that and to turn
                            discussion to other topics. We have made a start on disarmament on which
                            they seem ready to be a little more forthcoming. They are at least
                            prepared to discuss in practical terms questions now at issue at a
                            nuclear tests conference. Their attitude is dominated by their
                            conviction that we shall exploit inspection for purposes of acquiring
                            military intelligence; but even so they are open to argument on
                            procedures of control.<note n="3" xml:id="d183fn3">Printed from an
                                unsigned copy.</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>