<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>206. Memorandum of Telephone Conversation Between Secretary of State Dulles
                    and Acting Secretary of State and Acting Secretary of State Herter</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d206</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">206</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-03-06T12:40:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-03-06T12:40:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-03-06T12:40:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-03-06T12:40:00-05:00" n="206"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d206">
                <head>206. Memorandum of Telephone Conversation Between Secretary of State <persName
                        corresp="#p_DJF1" type="from">Dulles</persName> and Acting Secretary of
                    State <persName corresp="#p_HCA1" type="to">Herter</persName>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d206fn0">Source: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                            >Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName corresp="#p_DJF1"
                            >Dulles</persName> Papers, General Telephone Conversations. No
                        classification marking. Drafted by Marian S. Stilson.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1959-03-06T12:40:00-05:00"
                            >March 6, 1959, 12:40 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Secretary telephoned from <persName>Walter Reed</persName>. Said he was
                    feeling better than he had a little while ago; that he had just had a blood
                    transfusion; that he has been feeling very weak; that the injections have all
                    been pretty powerful, that he has lost a lot of weight quickly and has felt
                    weak.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> said he understood the President may be
                    coming out this afternoon and <persName>CAH</persName> said he knew the
                    President hoped to come out around 4:00.<note n="1" xml:id="d206fn1">No record
                        of President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s
                        conversation with <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> during the
                        former’s visit to Walter Reed Hospital from 3:59 to 4:32 p.m. has been
                        found.</note>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> asked what developed this morning.
                        <persName>CAH</persName> said the meeting this morning lasted an hour and a
                        half;<note n="2" xml:id="d206fn2">See <ref target="#d205">Document
                        205</ref>.</note> there was a good deal of probing of what we do under
                    certain contingencies. <persName>CAH</persName> said the President convinced
                    them of the fact that we cannot fight a ground battle around Berlin with the
                    Germans and the Russians—that is out. President said if Soviets take it by force
                    we have to then face up to the big decision but in the meanwhile we would do
                    everything feasible to negotiate. <persName>CAH</persName> said it ended up on a
                    very cheerful note; they went out and saw the press and took the line that it
                    was an interesting session and that they are in complete agreement we would
                    remain firm while continuing all fruitful negotiations. <persName>CAH</persName>
                    said they were trying to get down to brass tacks and <persName>CAH</persName>
                    said he thought it was good to convince them we will not fight a ground
                    battle.</p>
                <pb facs="0463" n="438" xml:id="pg_438"/>
                <p>JFD said that is what he said to <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>;
                    JFD told <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> it has to be a war we
                    can win, not one we are bound to lose.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>CAH</persName> said <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon
                        Johnson</persName> kept trying to get President to make a categoric
                    statement that we had enough strength if it came to war—obviously this was due
                    in part to the political arguments on budget versus defense preparedness—and
                        <persName>CAH</persName> said he thinks the President gave the feeling we
                    are taking all preparations necessary; consulting with our allies in the free
                    world; and confidence that if we had to meet this situation we could.
                        <persName>CAH</persName> said it was interesting that on the Senate side
                    both <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon Johnson</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_DEM1">Dirksen</persName> were strong in coming up to the final
                    decision and making it in favor of war. On the House side, both <persName
                        corresp="#p_RS1">Rayburn</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HC1"
                        >Halleck</persName> said we had to keep saying we would continue
                    negotiations to settle this. <persName>CAH</persName> said there is another
                    session this afternoon. JFD asked with who, and <persName>CAH</persName> said
                    the President was meeting with <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName>
                    and ranking members in Senate and House of Foreign Affairs and Armed Services
                    Committees. JFD expressed some surprise and <persName>CAH</persName> said we
                    were under tremendous pressures from the Hill. In that connection,
                        <persName>CAH</persName> said <persName corresp="#p_FJW1"
                        >Fulbright</persName> announced in the paper this morning he was calling
                        <persName>CAH</persName> up to testify next Tuesday before the Foreign
                    Relations Committee and <persName>CAH</persName> said he thought this was
                    extremely bad. <persName>CAH</persName> said both he and President hope to
                    discuss this with <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> this
                    afternoon. <persName>CAH</persName> said this is not the way to conduct this
                    business at the moment; that even if hearing is in Executive Session, there will
                    most likely be leaks.</p>
                <p>JFD said it must be realized that if the Soviets by threatening to do things by
                    force do destroy our rights and force us to retreat and make concessions, it is
                    just the beginning. JFD said if we are perfectly firm in our position he is
                    personally convinced that there is not one chance in 1000 the Soviets will push
                    it to the point of war.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>CAH</persName> said he didn’t like the British line in <persName
                        corresp="#p_LS1">Selwyn Lloyd</persName>’s message.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d206fn3">On March 5 <persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName>
                        sent <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> a letter that outlined a
                        message from <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName>. The Foreign
                        Secretary believed that the reply to the Soviet note of March 2 should not
                        be rushed; that it could be drafted following <persName corresp="#p_MH1"
                            >Macmillan</persName>’s visits to Paris, Bonn, and Washington; and that
                        it could be delivered after the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                        meeting in April. (<persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>
                        Library, <persName corresp="#p_WAC1">Whitman</persName> File, <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                            >Herter</persName> Series)</note>
                    <persName>CAH</persName> said he showed it to the President and showed him draft
                    reply to Soviet note prepared by <persName corresp="#p_MLT1"
                        >Merchant</persName>.<note n="4" xml:id="d206fn4">See <ref target="#d242"
                            >Document 242</ref>.</note>
                    <persName>CAH</persName> said he recommended to President we go ahead and shoot
                    the draft to our allies instead of waiting until <persName corresp="#p_MH1"
                        >Macmillan</persName> comes here. JFD said <persName corresp="#p_MH1"
                        >Macmillan</persName> is trying to get all the domestic political mileage he
                    can get and JFD said we are not unsympathetic to this since we don’t want to see
                    Bevan win the election, and JFD said within reason there is no objection to
                    giving him an important role as far as the appearance of things is concerned but
                    to JFD’s <pb facs="0464" n="439" xml:id="pg_439"/> mind this whole thing is very
                    vital from the standpoint of our whole <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                    posture and position. JFD said there is no point in having troops there—which
                    are expensive to maintain—if those troops won’t be used if need be.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>CAH</persName> said the President made clear yesterday at <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> that regarding overflights, communications,
                    etc., we can’t go along by ourselves. We would have to pull out of <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. [7–1/2 <hi rend="italic">lines of source
                        text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>CAH</persName> said on the Camp David idea, he was certain the
                    President and <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> would not do this
                    unless JFD could go there. <persName>CAH</persName> said the President felt the
                    facilities there were more comfortable for JFD and he could be taken care of
                    better and be able to rest as JFD felt need of it rather than have JFD
                    travelling back and forth to the White House. <persName>CAH</persName>
                    reiterated he was certain President and <persName corresp="#p_MH1"
                        >Macmillan</persName> would abandon this idea if it were not feasible from
                    JFD’s standpoint. JFD said it is a very awkward situation. JFD said he didn’t
                    want to hold on to the title if he couldn’t do the job. <persName>CAH</persName>
                    said the <gloss target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> should hot worry about this; that
                    all anybody wanted was for JFD to get back into harness. JFD said the doctor
                    told him today there would probably be two weeks more of the X-ray, and said
                    that is a very weakening process and that it will still be going on during the
                        <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> visit, but JFD said
                    treatment can be interrupted without serious impairment. JFD said he is really
                    worried that <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> is going to be
                    prepared to compromise on recognition of the <gloss target="#t_GDR1"
                    >GDR</gloss>, etc., which would be a gain for the Soviet Union. JFD said he
                    doesn’t think they are entitled to get any net gain. Said what is wrong with the
                    Berlin situation? Said we nearly had a war ten years ago and we reached a
                    compromise; the only trouble is it has been going too good from the Communists’
                    standpoint. JFD said this is just so much talk about competition between their
                    system and ours; that when they are competing nearby, they can’t stand the
                    comparison. JFD said that is the only reason in the world for raising this
                    problem. Said West Berlin doesn’t want a change; they don’t mind being occupied;
                    their productivity, population, etc is increasing and conditions are good. JFD
                    said what is all the reason for this excitement? <gloss target="#t_Secy1"
                        >Secy</gloss> then said jokingly that <persName>CAH</persName> could see he
                    had just had a blood transfusion.</p>
                <p>JFD said he would like to see <persName>CAH</persName> over the weekend and
                        <persName>CAH</persName> said he would be available whenever the <gloss
                        target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> wanted him.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
