<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-04-15T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-04-15T09:00:00-05:00" n="262" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d262">
                        <head>262. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the United
                                Kingdom</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d262fn0">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 762.00/4–1559. Secret. Repeated
                                to Berlin, Bonn, Moscow, and Paris.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>London</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-04-15T14:00:00+00:00">April 15,
                                    1959, 2 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>5340. Paris for <gloss target="#t_USRO1">USRO</gloss>. Pass Defense. From
                                <persName corresp="#p_HMJ1">Hillenbrand</persName>. Following are
                            some general impressions after second day of Working Group session.<note n="1" xml:id="d262fn1"><persName corresp="#p_HMJ1">Hillenbrand</persName> was in London as the head of the U.S.
                                Delegation to the Four-Power Working Group, which began work on
                                April 13 (see <ref target="#d270">Document 270</ref>).</note></p>
                        <pb facs="0639" n="614" xml:id="pg_614"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Both Germans and French continue to take extremely cautious
                                position on reunification proposals, and there appears to be little
                                prospect in Working Group of restoring major elements of original US
                                proposals or even German proposals made at Paris meetings.<note n="2" xml:id="d262fn2">See <ref target="#d242">Document
                                        242</ref>.</note> It should, however, be possible to
                                preserve framework of phased plan and to retain a few novelties in
                                its content such as creation of mixed committee prior to holding of
                                free elections. New and peculiar German proposal to use residual
                                authority of occupying powers to implement decisions of mixed
                                committee obviously needs to be reconsidered (see <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 5334).<note n="3" xml:id="d262fn3">Telegram 5334, April 14, transmitted a summary
                                    of the discussion at the second session of the Working Group,
                                    which focused on a German plan for reunification of Germany.
                                    (Department of State, Central Files,
                                762.00/4–1559)</note></item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>[<hi rend="italic">3 lines of source text not declassified</hi>]
                                Having read spate of newspaper speculation about possible
                                confederation proposals, they apparently insist on labeling any
                                contact between East and West Germans beyond those in their own
                                proposals as equivalent to confederation, even though such contacts
                                or institutionalizations thereof involve no executive or other
                                governmental powers. [<hi rend="italic">3 lines of source text not
                                    declassified</hi>]</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>British are playing unusually reticent role. They have put forward
                                no security proposals and their Berlin paper<note n="4" xml:id="d262fn4">A copy of this paper, given to the Department
                                    of State on April 10, was transmitted to Bonn in airgram G–453,
                                    April 10. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 762.00/4–1059)</note>
                                reflected none of willingness to accept basic changes which they
                                allegedly are resigned to. If we may hazard guess, they will not
                                reveal themselves further in present Working Group sessions but will
                                concur without too much difficulty in agreed recommendations reached
                                by Working Group. There have been no hints of any proposals for
                                European security measures not linked to phased plan.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>French generally can be counted on to react almost pathologically
                                to suggestions that <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> might play any
                                significant role. They have, however, indicated at least willingness
                                to consider possibility of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                                function re Berlin as envisaged British paper. We are sending
                                separate cable commenting on French security proposals.<note n="5" xml:id="d262fn5">A copy of this paper was transmitted in airgram
                                    G–897 from London, April 14. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>,
                                    762.00/4–1459)</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_WJH1"><hi rend="strong">Whitney</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>