<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-08-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-09T13:00:00-05:00" n="270" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d270">
                        <head>270. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>Acting on instructions from the Foreign Ministers (see <ref target="#d251">Document 251</ref>), the Four-Power Working Group
                            resumed its deliberations, this time at London, in an attempt to iron
                            out the points among the four Western powers that were still unagreed.
                                <persName corresp="#p_HMJ1">Hillenbrand</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LJ1">Laloy</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HPF1">Hancock</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_BGGV1">von
                                Baudissin</persName> continued as the heads of the United States,
                            French, British, and West German Delegations, respectively. By April 22
                            an agreed draft report was completed for the Foreign Ministers as well
                            as a summary report on the work of the group that was given to the North
                            Atlantic Council on April 23. (Telegram 5520 from London, April 22;
                            Department of State, Central Files, 762.00/4–2259) For extract from the
                            draft report, April 23, see <ref target="#d271">Document 271</ref>.</p>
                        <p>The North Atlantic Council discussed the draft report at its meeting on
                            April 27 (see <ref target="#d275">Document 275</ref>) and the Foreign
                            Ministers of the United States, France, the Federal Republic of Germany,
                            and the United Kingdom devoted four meetings to the report, April 29–30.
                            (See <ref target="#d280">Documents 280</ref>–<ref target="#d282">282</ref>) A copy of the final report, comprising: 1) “The Phased
                            Plan for German Reunification, European Security and a German Peace
                            Settlement,” 2) “Preliminary Draft Principles of a German Peace
                            Settlement,” 3) “Tactics at a Foreign Ministers Conference” with four
                            annexes, and 4) “Berlin,” is in Department of State, Conference Files:
                            Lot 64 D 560, <gloss target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 1276. For text of the
                            phased plan, which was submitted at the Foreign Ministers Meeting on May
                            14 as the Western Peace Plan, see <hi rend="italic">Documents</hi>
                            <pb facs="0664" n="639" xml:id="pg_639"/>
                            <hi rend="italic">on Germany, 1944–1985</hi>, pages 624–629; <hi rend="italic">Foreign Ministers Meeting</hi>, pages 55–60; or <hi rend="italic">Cmd.</hi> 868, pages 218–223; for text of the draft
                            principles, see <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, May 20, 1959,
                            page 15.</p>
                        <p>Documentation on the meetings of the Four-Power Working Group is
                            Department of State, Central Files, 396.1, 396.1–GE, and 762.00.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>