<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-06-10T03:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-06-10T03:30:00-05:00" n="379" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d379">
                        <head>379. Delegation Record Meeting<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d379fn0">Source: Department of State, Conference Files: Lot
                                64 D 560, <gloss target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 1371.
                            Secret.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-06-10T09:30:00+01:00">June 10,
                                    1959, 9:30 a.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center">SMALL STAFF MEETING</p>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PRESENT</head>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName></item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BLE1">Becker</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAH1">Berding</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IJN1">Irwin</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RGF1">Reinhardt</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCA2">Sullivan</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KMV1">Krebs</persName></item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="italic">Secretary’s
                                    Evaluation of Conference Outlook</hi></hi></p>
                        <p>1. The Secretary said that today would be crucial in view of the Russian
                            ultimatum given to us yesterday at the private meeting.<note n="1" xml:id="d379fn1">See <ref target="#d377">Document 377</ref>.</note>
                            He then outlined the substance of the Russian proposal commenting that
                            it took us back to November 27; we have retrogressed seriously. He noted
                            that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> had prepared a
                            good draft of a statement<note n="2" xml:id="d379fn2">Presumably this is
                                the statement circulated as <gloss target="#t_RMDOC1">RM/DOC</gloss>/43, June 11, which is printed in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Ministers Meeting</hi>, pp. 267–271 or <hi rend="italic">Cmd.</hi> 868, pp. 157–160.</note> for him to make
                            at the plenary session today. The Secretary continued that <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> had refused to give us a paper
                            embodying the Russian proposal. He observed that <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> for the last two days had
                            spoken in Russian and that there were more Russian advisers present. No
                            doubt, the Secretary surmised, <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> was speaking for their benefit. He thought
                                <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> would publicize the
                            Russian proposal at the plenary <pb facs="0895" n="870" xml:id="pg_870"/> today. Obviously, he continued, we are at the break-off point if
                                <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> puts up his proposal
                            today. The Secretary then suggested we might consider recessing until
                            July 20. The French feel this is the best thing to do now and that the
                            British, although hesitant at first, appear to think it is the best
                            move. The Secretary said it was necessary for us to point out that the
                            Russian proposal is an ultimatum. He concluded by saying that we have
                            reached a serious point in negotiations and the prospects are not
                            cheery.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Conference Tactics</hi></p>
                        <p>2. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName> thought that there
                            was an important difference between this ultimatum and the ultimatum of
                            November 27 which, as he argued it, seemed to lie in the fact that the
                            present proposal would not become a threat unless or until we accepted
                            it. He suggested that we should guard our flank against <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> saying at the plenary session
                            today that what he was putting forward was a proposal and not an
                            ultimatum. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BLE1">Becker</persName> expressed
                            the view that we should publish the Common Declaration or Communiqué we
                            gave the Russians on June 8<note n="3" xml:id="d379fn3">See <ref target="#d372">Document 372</ref>.</note> in order to bring out
                            as soon as possible our position if the conference should break up. The
                            Secretary thought that since this is really our minimum position there
                            would be disadvantages in disclosing it at this time. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> suggested that if the Soviets
                            refuse a recess and break off the conference, we should then publish our
                            offer.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> suggested that
                            the Secretary not propose a recess at first; a private session could be
                            held. Afterwards we might propose a recess. The Secretary said that we
                            made it clear yesterday to <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> that this proposal is a threat. He thought it
                            interesting that <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> refused
                            to give us the text of his proposal, but instead said he wished to do so
                            at the plenary session. The Secretary digressed to comment on the
                            dangers that faced the Alliance. He thought that the Russians may very
                            well be acting tough because they think that <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> is about to break up (viz. the French attitude) and
                            that there are internal strains in the UK (viz. recent criticism of
                                <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName>).</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Press Matters</hi></p>
                        <p>3. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAH1">Berding</persName> said that we should
                            create the impression in the press that the present situation has been
                            produced by the new Soviet move and that the conference has really been
                            thrown back to November 27 last. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IJN1">Irwin</persName> said that he thought an abrupt recess would cause
                            concern all over the world and he thought it important to place the onus
                            for this directly on the Soviets. In this connection Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> noted Mr. <pb facs="0896" n="871" xml:id="pg_871"/>
                            <persName corresp="#p_HMJ1">Hillenbrand</persName> is preparing a
                            question and answer guidance for Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAH1">Berding</persName>.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Possible Recourse to <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> on Berlin Issue</hi></p>
                        <p>4. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BLE1">Becker</persName> expressed the view
                            that the Russian proposal may have been calculated to force us to break
                            off negotiations and thus open the way for the Russians to conclude a
                            peace treaty with East Germany within two or three days. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> agreed that this might be a
                            deliberate move. If a treaty appeared to be in prospect, we should
                            consider moving into the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> as soon as it
                            was signed. The Secretary said there was no question about this and
                            asked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> whether he had
                            prepared a draft resolution for the Security Council. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> indicated that he had done
                                so<note n="4" xml:id="d379fn4">The draft resolution has not been
                                found.</note> and that the problem was being studied in Washington
                            this week. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> said that
                            if there is a recess followed by signature of a peace treaty, we must be
                            sure that our case is as clean as is possible. We must be able to say we
                            did all we could to continue the negotiations. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> said that we would be covered
                            by having suggested a recess. If the Soviets act unilaterally, during
                            this time it will be they who will bear the onus.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Briefing on Private Meeting for
                                Germans</hi></p>
                        <p>5. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> said that the
                            British had agreed to brief <persName corresp="#p_GWC1">Grewe</persName>
                            on yesterday’s meeting but wanted to defer doing so until this morning.
                                <persName corresp="#p_GWC1">Grewe</persName> came into the
                            Delegation Office last night at 11 o’clock asking to see Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> to get a run-down of the
                            private meeting. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName>
                            said that he had given <persName corresp="#p_GWC1">Grewe</persName> a
                            sanitized version of the private meeting to be transmitted only to
                                <persName corresp="#p_BHV1">von Brentano</persName>.<note n="5" xml:id="d379fn5">A seven-line memorandum for the record of <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName>’s briefing of <persName corresp="#p_GWC1">Grewe</persName> is in Department of State,
                                Conference Files: Lot 64 D 560, <gloss target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss>
                                1384.</note></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Stand-by Plane for Secretary</hi></p>
                        <p>6. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> expressed the view
                            that it would be wise psychologically and otherwise for the Secretary to
                            order a plane to stand by. (See attached telegrams—<gloss target="#t_Cahto1">Cahto</gloss> 100 and <gloss target="#t_Tocah1">Tocah</gloss> 92.)<note n="6" xml:id="d379fn6"><gloss target="#t_Cahto1">Cahto</gloss> 100, June 10, requested that a
                                plane be put on standby. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, Central
                                Files, 110.11–HE/6–1059) <gloss target="#t_Tocah1">Tocah</gloss> 92,
                                also June 10, reported that a plane would be on 4-hour alert
                                beginning June 11. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, Conference Files:
                                Lot 64 D 560, <gloss target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 1331)</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>