<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>385. Telegram From the Delegation to the Foreign Ministers Meeting to the to
                    the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d385</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">385</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-06-12T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-06-12T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="reczJcBmJJ2LmpWWy" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace plan</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recfstIIL5scNKk3A" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="alliances" subject="summit-meeting" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87007171" lcsh-match="exact">Summit Conference</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-06-12T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-06-12T12:00:00-05:00" n="385"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d385">
                <head>385. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Delegation to the Foreign Ministers
                        Meeting</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d385fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 396.1–GE/6–1259. Official Use Only; Priority. Transmitted in two
                        sections and repeated to Bonn, London, Moscow, Paris, Berlin, and <gloss
                            target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>. The U.S. Delegation verbatim record of
                        this session, US/VR/17 (Corrected), and a summary of the verbatim record,
                            <gloss target="#t_USAFE1">US/VRS</gloss>/17, June 12, are <hi
                            rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, Conference Files: Lot 64 D 560, <gloss
                            target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 1373.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1959-06-12T18:00:00+01:00">June 12, 1959, 6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 232. Paris pass <gloss target="#t_USRO1"
                        >USRO</gloss>. Seventeenth Plenary Session held June 12, 10 am to 12:55 pm,
                        <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> Chairman.</p>
                <pb facs="0910" n="885" xml:id="pg_885"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName>, in twenty minute statement<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d385fn1">For text of <persName corresp="#p_LS1"
                            >Lloyd</persName>’s statement, circulated as <gloss target="#t_RMDOC1"
                            >RM/DOC</gloss>/46, June 12, see <hi rend="italic">Foreign Ministers
                            Meeting</hi>, pp. 279–284 or <hi rend="italic">Cmd.</hi> 868, pp.
                        164–168.</note> traced course conference to date, noting Western Peace Plan
                    put forward after much thought and designed meet Soviet criticisms of earlier
                    Western proposals. Said conference had concentrated during past fortnight on
                    limited proposals re Berlin and he had thought there had been some signs of
                    limited progress on limited front until Soviet proposals made public June 10 put
                    us back to situation at time of Soviet note November 27. These proposals
                    contained no new element and were presented under double threat that if not
                    accepted Soviets would turn responsibilities over to <gloss target="#t_GDR1"
                        >GDR</gloss> and would do so in any case at end of one year. Soviet
                    all-German committee proposal simply revival of idea peace treaty must be
                    negotiated by two Germanies.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> then gave background against which
                    Soviet proposals must be viewed. West had two sorts of rights—those flowing from
                    basic fact Nazi surrender and those based on specific agreements. Quoted
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s March twentieth
                        statement<note n="2" xml:id="d385fn2">The statement was made at a press
                        conference at the Kremlin on March 19 and printed in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Pravda</hi> on March 20. For an extract from the press conference,
                        including the statement mentioned by <persName corresp="#p_LS1"
                            >Lloyd</persName>, see <hi rend="italic">Moskau Bonn</hi>, pp.
                        534–538.</note> that West had legal rights in Berlin but these would be
                    extinguished by signature Soviet-<gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> treaty.
                        <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> said West maintained such
                    unilateral action would be illegal and a blow at mutual confidence.</p>
                <p>West could not agree, as Soviets suggested, to say nothing re rights because no
                    guarantee question would not again be raised by Soviets or, in Soviet view,
                    extinguished by signature treaty with <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>.
                    However, West still believed there are ways to solve this problem. Re situation
                    in Berlin, which both sides agree abnormal, conference has considered three
                    facets (1) presence Western troops (2) various activities (3) free access. Re
                    (1) and (2) <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> reviewed Western
                    proposals, saying re (2) that if Soviets object to our formulation that
                    arrangements would cover “greater Berlin,” we would define them as covering East
                    and West Berlin but they must be reciprocal. Re (3) maintained Soviets cannot
                    unilaterally tear up agreements but West thought it possible to work out way to
                    satisfy Soviet wish to give up some of functions they now exercise. <persName
                        corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> concluded by noting <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> had asked what sort of Berlin there
                    would be access to. Answer was one (a) that posed no military threat (idea
                    suggested by <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> that West would
                    place nuclear arms or missiles in Berlin was ridiculous); (b) where troops did
                    not interfere with life of city; (c) where there would be freedom and no
                    violence or subversive activities directed against its neighbor.</p>
                <pb facs="0911" n="886" xml:id="pg_886"/>
                <p>Secretary then (<gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 229)<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d385fn3">Dated June 12, (Department of State, Central Files,
                        396.1–GE/6–1259) For text of <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>’s
                        statement as recorded in the U.S. verbatim record, see <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Ministers Meeting</hi>, p. 284 or Department of State <hi
                            rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, June 29, 1959, p. 951.</note> noted earlier
                    comments by himself and <persName corresp="#p_CDMM1">Couve</persName> on threats
                    contained in <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>’s proposals and
                    called on <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> to repeat in plenary
                    what he had said the day before on subject in meeting with Secretary.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>, in thirty-minute statement,<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d385fn4">For text of <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                            >Gromyko</persName>’s statement, circulated as <gloss target="#t_RMDOC1"
                            >RM/DOC</gloss>/47, June 12, <hi rend="italic">see ibid</hi>., pp.
                        285–291 or <hi rend="italic">Cmd.</hi> 868, pp. 168–173.</note> reiterated
                    past assertion that Soviet proposals contained no threat or “diktat” and hoped
                    such terms would no longer be used. Soviets put forward proposals for temporary
                    Berlin regime, to facilitate liquidation outdated occupation regime. West says
                    occupation would last only until German reunification. But reunification
                    impossible under Western proposals. West must realize Soviets, <gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> and other states do not like occupation regime
                    and desire new arrangements satisfactory to all states concerned. West says
                    troops are no danger to Soviets and must stay in West Berlin to guarantee social
                    order there, but why are guns needed to support an order which no one wishes to
                    change? Re Western objection to one-year time limit for work of all-German
                    Committee, West itself proposed two-and-one-half year limit and thus accepts
                    principle. If one year too short, why not propose another? Re parity, Dr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_BL1">Bolz</persName> has shown this is only
                    arrangement compatible with facts and international law. West says membership
                    should depend on population but this not so in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    or at this conference. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> accused
                    West of threatening Soviets by insisting on maintenance of occupation regime in
                    West Berlin.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> then turned to Summit conference,
                    saying it cannot be approached on basis of deal that it depends on progress at
                    Geneva. If powers really desire find solution for problems, then Summit, or
                    series of summits, could bring about lessening of tensions and strengthening of
                    peace. Anyone who sets “artificial obstacles” on road to summit would accept
                    “grave responsibilities”.</p>
                <p>Re <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName>’s statement that Soviet proposals
                    old, maintained two new elements were one year time limit and linking of Berlin
                    proposals with activities of all-German committee. Re statement Soviet suggested
                    ban on missiles and nuclear weapons ludicrous said what is ludicrous is attempts
                    to minimize this issue and West should have no trouble accepting Soviet
                    proposal. Ended by reiterating Soviet desire reach agreement but repeated
                    Soviets could not sign agreement which perpetuated occupation regime.</p>
                <pb facs="0912" n="887" xml:id="pg_887"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GWC1">Grewe</persName> said<note n="5" xml:id="d385fn5"
                        >For text of <persName corresp="#p_GWC1">Grewe</persName>’s statement,
                        circulated as <gloss target="#t_RMDOC1">RM/DOC</gloss>/A/12, June 13, see
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Ministers Meeting</hi>, pp. 551–553 or <hi
                            rend="italic">Cmd</hi>. 868, pp. 216–218.</note> that after carefully
                    considering Soviet proposals he could only conclude they designed to end private
                    talks which attempting find limited solution Berlin problem. Soviet proposals
                    only increase tension by linking questions which may be soluble with those which
                    are not. Connecting all-German committee established on parity basis with
                    proposals on Berlin is merely device for shifting to Federal Republic blame for
                    failure this conference. Federal Republic agreed to an all-German committee on
                    understanding it would operate within framework of Western proposals for German
                    reunification and its membership would be based on relative populations of two
                    Germanies. Soviet proposals re all-German committee would perpetuate split
                    because <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> representatives would be able
                    prevent any reunification on basis of freedom. Denied there any universal rule
                    supporting parity principle, saying even in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    some states have certain rights not possessed by others and Soviets themselves
                    had assigned differing role as among states they propose take part in drafting
                    and signing treaty with two Germanies. “Free city” proposal unacceptable because
                    would establish three Germanies and would leave West Berlin open to arbitrary
                    interference by <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>. Finally, <persName
                        corresp="#p_GWC1">Grewe</persName> noted time limit in peace plan not linked
                    to announcement unilateral measures would be taken at its expiration.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CDMM1">Couve</persName> said<note n="6" xml:id="d385fn6"
                        >For text of <persName corresp="#p_CDMM1">Couve de Murville</persName>’s
                        statement, circulated as <gloss target="#t_RMDOC1">RM/DOC</gloss>/48, June
                        15, see <hi rend="italic">Foreign Ministers Meeting</hi>, pp. 291–293 or <hi
                            rend="italic">Cmd</hi>. 868, pp. 173–175.</note> he felt discouraged and
                    concerned at present serious situation of conference. Noted Soviets objected to
                    continuation of West Berlin occupation but had proposed as one alternative
                    stationing of token forces of four powers. Where was difference in legal basis
                    for presence of troops of four powers as against three?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName>, in short statement,<note n="7"
                        xml:id="d385fn7">For text of <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName>’s
                        statement as recorded in the U.S. verbatim record, see <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Ministers Meeting</hi>, p. 293.</note> reiterated that West saw
                    threat in Soviet proposals because of contents and fact <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> had made them public. Also noted Soviet
                    denial there was threat. Regretted certain of <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName>’s statements today which might be taken as barring door
                    to further progress. Suggested conference could resume plenary or private
                    session in afternoon or adjourn until Monday, June 15.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said<note n="8" xml:id="d385fn8"
                        >For text of this statement, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p.
                        294.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> had reproached him for making
                    proposals public on June 10 but he had told Western Ministers in private session
                    the day before he would not do so if West agreed to continue discussions in
                    private session with representatives of both Germanies present. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>, however, had wanted plenary.</p>
                <pb facs="0913" n="888" xml:id="pg_888"/>
                <p>Secretary, to set record straight, noted<note n="9" xml:id="d385fn9">For text of
                        this statement, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>
                    </note> he had suggested plenary because only alternative was private session
                    with Germans present. This was type of meeting Ministers had never held and, he
                    thought, would not hold.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> denied<note n="9" target="d385fn9"
                        >For text of this statement, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>
                    </note> he had reproached <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>, had
                    merely noted facts including Soviet denial of ultimatum.</p>
                <p>It was agreed next meeting would be private session at 3:30 p.m. June 15.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Herter</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
