<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-06-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-06-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="419" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d419">
                        <head>419. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d419fn0">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                                396.1–GE/6–2559. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_HMJ1">Hillenbrand</persName> and approved by <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> on July 7.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1959-06-25">June 25, 1959</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Resumption of the Geneva Conference</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Sir Harold Caccia</persName>, British
                                Ambassador</item>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JRW1">R.W. Jackling</persName>,
                                Counselor, British Embassy</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Foy D. Kohler</persName>—<gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HMJ1">Martin J.
                                    Hillenbrand</persName>—<gloss target="#t_GER1">GER</gloss></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Secretary handed a letter to <persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName> for <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Selwyn
                                Lloyd</persName><note n="1" xml:id="d419fn1">Not printed. It stated
                                that <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> had discussed
                                post-Geneva policy with the President and would reply the following
                                week on the U.S. position. A summary of <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>’s conversation with <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> (see <ref target="#d417">Document 417</ref>) was attached to the letter. (Department of
                                State, Presidential Correspondence: Lot 66 D 204, <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> with UK Officials)</note> in reply to a
                            message received from the British Foreign Minister on June 24 through
                            the Ambassador.<note n="2" xml:id="d419fn2">See <ref target="#d415fn1">footnote 1, Document 415</ref></note> The Secretary said that
                            his letter would give the British some idea of how far along we were in
                            preparing for resumption <pb facs="0973" n="948" xml:id="pg_948"/> of
                            the Geneva Conference. He then read to <persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName> excerpts from the preliminary report received
                            from our Ambassador in Moscow of the <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> conversation with <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> to supplement the summary of this
                            conversation attached to the Secretary’s letter.<note n="3" xml:id="d419fn3">Not further identified.</note> In response to the
                            Secretary’s query as to whether the <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> report would be published, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName> indicated that, since <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> was seeing <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> as a former ambassador to
                            the Soviet Union and not in his capacity as journalist, it would
                            presumably not be published.</p>
                        <p>After <persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName> had stressed the
                            urgency of moving ahead with the Western preparations for resumption of
                            the Geneva Conference, the Secretary said he had gone over at
                            considerable length with the President certain ideas similar to those
                            expressed by <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> in his message.
                            While there might be some possibilities in the moratorium concept, the
                            Secretary indicated, we must have assurance that Western rights would
                            not be diminished at the end of the given time period.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName> noted that the difficulty
                            was in determining the basic Soviet position in view of the different
                            statements made by <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> to
                                <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName>, to the press and to
                            individual journalists. The Soviets should be smoked out in the
                            conference room, so that the West would know where it stood. If a
                            satisfactory agreement could be reached on a moratorium period, the
                            question would arise as to just what might be accomplished during the
                            interval. The Secretary said that <persName corresp="#p_BHV1">Von
                                Brentano</persName> had shown a certain receptivity to the idea of
                            German advisers putting their heads together under cover of a Four Power
                            commission. He noted that, in the <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> statement to <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>, the campaign of invective against <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> continued. <persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName> commented that the question
                            about this most recent <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                            effusion was whether it represented genuine conviction or was merely a
                            case of play-acting. The Secretary added that, when <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> presented the Soviet
                            “ultimatum” proposals at Geneva, this was interpreted by some as an
                            effort by <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> to frighten
                            the West into the Summit and thus to enter it on his part in a strong
                            tactical position.</p>
                        <p>In response to <persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName>’s query as
                            to what he might say about United States thinking on the possibility of
                            a moratorium, the Secretary said that we were trying to reduce the
                            concept to a more precise form in order to see its full implications.
                            The President had a draft in front of him,<note n="4" xml:id="d419fn4">See attachment B to <ref target="#d418">Document 418</ref>.</note>
                            but no decision had been made and we could not be sure what would
                            finally emerge. If agreement were reached on some formula, we might be
                            in a more advantageous position than the British to take it up with the
                            French and the Germans. We would try to have something more precise <pb facs="0974" n="949" xml:id="pg_949"/> by Tuesday or Wednesday of
                            next week. <persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName> agreed that
                            United States support of any proposal would carry more weight with the
                            French and Germans than primary advocacy by the British.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName> noted that, despite
                            exaggerated press accounts, Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> had tried to be careful yesterday in the
                            Commons relative to a Summit meeting.<note n="5" xml:id="d419fn5">For
                                text of <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>’s statement
                                to the House of Commons, June 24, see 607 House of Commons, <hi rend="italic">Parliamentary Debates</hi>, 5th Series, cols.
                                1027–1028.</note> He had expressed the hope that the resumed Geneva
                            Conference would permit a Summit meeting to take place. Obviously the
                            British Government still wanted such a Summit meeting, <persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName> continued, but it also wanted
                            to avoid any open break between the Western Powers on this subject. On
                            the assumption that the optimistic interpretation of <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>’s press statement of June
                                19<note n="6" xml:id="d419fn6">For text of this statement, see <hi rend="italic">Foreign Ministers Meeting</hi>, pp. 332–334 or <hi rend="italic">Cmd</hi>. 868, pp. 238–239.</note> was warranted
                            and would be reflected in the Soviet position when the Geneva Conference
                            resumed, the British were wondering how tactically the subject of a
                            Summit could best be handled. <persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName> suggested that it would be desirable if the
                            United States could take the initiative and not leave it to the Soviets
                            to propose a Summit meeting. Perhaps the questions of a precise time
                            period and of the level of troops might be left for decision at the
                            Summit. The Secretary commented that all this depended on the actual
                            progress made by the Foreign Ministers.</p>
                        <p>Both the Secretary and <persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName>
                            agreed that it would be better if the Italian proposal for a <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> ministerial meeting prior to the
                            resumption of the Geneva Conference were dropped. The Secretary made the
                            point that the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> ministers always
                            seemed to want to know what the Western fall-back position is. As soon
                            as this is discussed it tends to become public property. He believed
                            that a factor at Geneva was that the Soviets had heard so much about
                            Western fall-back positions that they could not believe we had none.
                                [<hi rend="italic">5½ lines of source text not
                            declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName> again stressed the urgency
                            of preparing a Western position for Germany. It was desirable, he said,
                            to get something to <persName corresp="#p_CDMM1">Couve</persName> before
                            he left for Madagascar in order to avoid any feeling that the United
                            Kingdom and the United States were “plotting behind his back” while he
                            was away on a trip. The Secretary noted that one problem was how much
                                <persName corresp="#p_CDMM1">Couve</persName> could agree to which
                            the Germans would not accept. It was possible that some tight
                            arrangement existed between the French and Germans to support each
                            others’ views in all respects. The Secretary added that we must make
                            clear that a decision on a moratorium, which would be a big decision to
                            take, must involve a careful evaluation of Western interests in terms of
                            possible alternatives.</p>
                        <pb facs="0975" n="950" xml:id="pg_950"/>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName> expressed the opinion
                            that, if agreement on the Summit could not be reached as a result of the
                            Foreign Ministers’ meeting, <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> would then put on pressure and demand a
                            Summit under crisis conditions. Under such circumstances, the British
                            would be strongly impelled to accept.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName> said that he was taking
                            the line with the Press that his call on the Secretary was to have a
                            general tour d’horizon since it was their first meeting after the
                            Secretary’s return from Geneva. In order to make this line an honest
                            one, he wished to raise briefly a number of other subjects (covered in
                            separate memoranda of conversation).<note n="7" xml:id="d419fn7">The
                                only other memorandum of conversation between <persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Caccia</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> on June 25 that has been
                                found is a five-line memorandum on Laos. (Department of State,
                                Secretary’s Memoranda of Conversation: Lot 64 D 199)</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>