<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>92. Telegram From the Embassy in the Soviet Union to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d92</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">92</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-12-10T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-12-10T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recCErkkm3wP0wOxd" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Air access</term>
                    <term ref="recTNMFmPG15mKxJQ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">European security</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-12-10T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-12-10T05:00:00-05:00" n="92"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d92">
                <head>92. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the Soviet Union</gloss>
                    to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d92fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 762.00/12–1058. Secret. Repeated to London, Paris, and Bonn.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1958-12-10T13:00:00+03:00">December 10, 1958, 1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1247. I believe <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s long
                    conversation with <persName corresp="#p_HHH1">Humphrey</persName> on Berlin
                    question indicates realization on his part of dangers involved and concern over
                    outcome. He and other Presidium members have shown great interest in Western
                    reaction and among others have questioned my Swedish, Austrian and Indian
                    colleagues. While it is clear that neither <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> nor Soviet Government as a whole wishes to run real
                    risk of war, they will be very reluctant to back down if issue is posed in <pb
                        facs="0188" n="163" xml:id="pg_163"/> such a way as to involve great loss of
                    prestige for Soviet Union. If in such circumstances we should use force to
                    maintain access to Berlin they are capable, in my judgment, of allowing East
                    Germans to respond with force. It therefore seems important that in handling the
                    situation we leave open some way for <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> to retreat and save face.</p>
                <p>Difficulty of devising any counter proposals on Berlin are obvious but would
                    appear to me there are elements for a bargain which would leave neither side
                    materially worse off and which Soviets might be brought to accept if West is
                    firmly united in opposition to current Soviet proposals and prepared in last
                    resort to use force. As to concessions on our part there is a wide range of
                    possibilities running from radical to relatively minor window dressing actions.
                    For example, we could consider such actions as 1) withdrawal our troops and
                    their substitution by West German forces and incorporation of West Berlin into
                    West Germany; 2) some steps toward de facto recognition of <gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>; 3) turning over full responsibility for
                    administration West Berlin to Germans, although keeping our troops there; 4)
                    termination of overt Western activities in Berlin such as operation radio
                    station, etc.</p>
                <p>As against concessions of this nature principal concession from Soviet side would
                    presumably be related to problem of access. We might obtain recognition right of
                    commercial air access, some type of corridor under West German control, etc. It
                    might also be possible to devise scheme involving creation free city including
                    East Berlin. This does not, however, appear to me to be profitable line of
                    approach since Soviets unlikely make concession on this point and at same time
                    agree to satisfactory arrangements to ensure access.</p>
                <p>I do not believe Soviet action on Berlin was designed to lead to discussion of
                    German problem as a whole nor do I believe they would formally agree to a
                    meeting for this purpose. Nevertheless I think that at a meeting on the Berlin
                    question it might be possible to draw them into such a discussion particularly
                    if approached from the point of view of European security.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Thompson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
