<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. King to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1866-07-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1866-07-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-07-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-07-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="132"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d132">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. King</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 60.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Rome,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-07-24">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 24, 1866</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> The great events which have followed each other
                    with such startling rapidity during the course of the present month have filled
                    Home with various and exciting rumors. The signal victory of the Prussians at
                    Koniggratz, or Sadowa; the cession of Venetia to France and its acceptance by
                    the Emperor; the unopposed advance of the Italian army into what had,
                    apparently, thus become French territory; the steady progress of the Prussian
                    arms in all directions; the seeming helplessness of Austria; the absolute
                    non-intervention of the other European powers; and, finally, the signing of the
                    preliminaries of peace, all within the brief space of three weeks, make up a
                    chapter in the world’s history of unsurpassed interest. The sympathies of the
                    Papal court and of the clerical party were very openly and strongly with
                    Austria, and deep and general was the regret at the news of her fearful
                    overthrow. On the other hand, a very large proportion of the Roman people hailed
                    with intense delight every triumph of the Italian arms, and are eagerly looking
                    forward to the hour when the national flag shall replace the French tri-color on
                    the castle of St. Angelo.</p>
                <p>What is to be the <hi rend="italic">status</hi> of Rome in the contemplated
                    rearrangement of the map of Europe forms, just now, the general topic of
                    conversation here, and gives rise to all sorts of rumors and conjectures. On
                    Saturday last I was informed by a dignitary of the church, usually very well
                    informed in all political matters, that the Emperor of the French, in reply to a
                    question from the Papal Nuncio at Paris, had said that it would not be in his
                    power to interfere for the protection of the Pope; that he could not control the
                    march of the revolution. On the same day, Marchese Bargagli, the representative
                    here of the ex-Grand Duke of Tuscany, applied to Mr. J. C. Hooker, (of the
                    banking house of Maguay, Pakenham &amp; Hooker, and acting secretary of
                    legation,) to know if he could take charge of his plate and valuables in the
                    event of his being obliged suddenly to leave Rome. The marchese, in explanation,
                    said that the events of the war, so disastrous to Austria, threatened the
                    overthrow of the Papal authority; that France, the only power which could
                    interfere with effect in the Pope’s behalf, was unwilling to do so; that Louis
                    Napoleon had declared his inability to control the march of the revolution, and
                    had notified the Papal Nuncio that his Holiness must make terms for himself; and
                    that, in all probability, his Holiness would be driven to the alternative of
                    abandoning Rome and retiring to Malta, which had again been placed at his
                    disposal by <pb facs="0212" n="138" xml:id="pg_138"/> the British government.
                    Anxious to learn what foundation existed for these reports, I called the next
                    day upon the ambassadors of France and Austria. The former was at Alvano, but
                    the latter I found at home, and enjoyed with him a long and interesting
                    conversation. I was very much struck with the extreme depression under which
                    Baron Hubner seemed to be laboring. The expression of his face, the tones of his
                    voice, the language and sentiments which he uttered, were alike sad,
                    desponding,) almost hopeless. He had had no intelligence, he said, from Vienna
                    for several days, the telegraphic communication being interrupted, and that by
                    mail difficult and irregular. He did not know, therefore, what to anticipate as
                    likely to flow from the proposed conference, or what were the precise terms of
                    the preliminaries of peace. Nor could he, in the absence of such information,
                    form any satisfactory opinion as to the probable effect of the pending
                    negotiations upon the fortunes of the Holy See. I gathered, however, as much,
                    perhaps, from the manner as the matter of the baron’s remarks, that he puts but
                    little trust in Louis Napoleon; that he thinks Prussia and Italy will settle
                    matters pretty much as they please; that Austria must, perforce, acquiesce; and
                    that the prospect for the maintenance of the Pope’s temporal power is, at best,
                    a very doubtful one.</p>
                <p>In the hope of learning something more definite on this interesting topic, I
                    called yesterday upon the cardinal secretary of state, and was glad to find a
                    very marked improvement in his health since my last interview. His Eminence, in
                    reply to my questions, spoke of the future as shrouded in clouds and darkness.
                    His private advices from Vienna, he said, described the condition of things
                    there as terrible. Discouragement, despair, a panic, in fact, prevailed on all
                    hands. Great numbers of families were leaving the city, carrying with them their
                    valuables, &amp;c. The jewels, treasure, and archives of the government had been
                    sent off to Comorn, and if the war continued, Vienna must fall. The
                    preliminaries of peace, however, had been signed, and though the conditions were
                    not yet known, he anticipated that a European congress would be held for their
                    discussion and settlement, in which event the Roman question would come up with
                    the rest. His Eminence spoke, in strong terms, of the aggressive conduct of
                    Prussia, and did not conceal his opinion that Austria was in the right, and had
                    behaved with great moderation and dignity. He commented significantly upon the
                    course pursued by the Emperor of the French, and especially upon the fact that,
                    after the cession of Venetia to Louis Napoleon and its acceptance by him had
                    been officially announced in the Moniteur, the Italian army had crossed the Po
                    and invaded this French territory, without a single French soldier being
                    despatched to its defence. It was impossible, the cardinal said, that Cialdini
                    could have ventured upon so bold and decisive a step without a previous secret
                    understanding between Louis Napoleon and Victor Emanuel. What the nature and
                    extent of this understanding might be was not known, and hence the difficulty of
                    conjecturing what part the Emperor of the French would play in the approaching
                    conference. Apparently he was master of the situation, unless, indeed, the
                    revolution proved stronger than he was, or that this alleged power of the
                    revolution was made to serve as an excuse for carrying out a preconceived
                    purpose. At present, his Eminence in conclusion said, all was quiet in Rome; but
                    its future was involved in doubt. As for the Holy Father, he could only
                    patiently and trustfully abide the event, leaving the issue in the hands of the
                    Great Ruler of the universe.</p>
                <p>I have thus given the substance of the cardinal’s remarks, which left on my mind
                    the impression that his Eminence himself, for the present, at least, was
                    unprepared what to expect as the result of the approaching conference, and
                    unable, therefore, to say what probability exists that Rome, as well as Venice,
                    is about to be absorbed by the newly-formed kingdom of Victor Emanuel. But it
                    cannot be doubted that such is the prevalent opinion, if not hope, in Rome
                    itself; and that, without any change in their faith or diminution in their
                    sentiments <pb facs="0213" n="139" xml:id="pg_139"/> of regard and veneration
                    for the Holy Father, the great body of the Roman people ardently desire to see
                    the ancient mistress of the world become the capital of free, united, and
                    independent Italy.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, with great respect, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>RUFUS KING.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
