<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Yeaman to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d162</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">162</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1866-09-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1866-09-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-09-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-09-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="162"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d162">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Yeaman</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 35.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Copenhagen,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-09-22">
                            <hi rend="italic">Sept.</hi> 22, 1866</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: To-day, at 1 o’clock p. m., her royal highness
                    Princess Dagmar and suite embarked in the Danish royal yacht for St. Petersburg.
                    She is accompanied a part of the way by the entire royal family, and the vessel
                    in which she has embarked will be escorted to St. Petersburg by Danish and
                    Russian men of war. After remaining in that capital for about a month, as the
                    guest of the Emperor, the nuptials of her marriage with the heir apparent to the
                    Russian crown will be celebrated.</p>
                <p>The occasion of her departure was one of great interest and solemnity. Such a
                    display of flags from shipping and from public and private buildings, and such a
                    vast concourse of people were scarcely ever before seen in Copenhagen. Streets,
                    squares, quays, decks, rigging, sea-shore, batteries, and the tops of houses
                    hardly sufficed to contain the people seeking to catch a last glimpse and to
                    wave a last adieu to the fair young girl they were giving to the throne of the
                    greatest empire of modern times.</p>
                <p>The pier against which the ship was moored was set apart for Danish officers and
                    members of the diplomatic corps and their families; and as the royal family
                    passed through that richly-attired throng to the ship’s gangway, the scene
                    became extremely solemn and impressive. The Queen wept palpably. The King, too
                    deeply moved to speak, passed silently along, bowing to the mute spectators, and
                    stooping to gather from the carpet the flowers cast to his daughter. The face of
                    the young princes showed the impress and the fresh traces of a violent spell of
                    emotion, repressed but for a moment in the presence of the public; and without
                    speaking a word she cordially and earnestly took leave of her friends. <pb
                        facs="0245" n="171" xml:id="pg_171"/> The ship moved slowly out into the
                    harbor, the princess stood upon deck by the side of the King, waving her
                    handkerchief to the assembled thousands on shore, and the batteries pronounced
                    the deep farewell salute to her who goes to occupy so prominent a position in a
                    government which may prove to be the firmest and most loyal ally of our own.</p>
                <p>There is not here so much confidence as I would have expected to find touching
                    the result of the proposed proceedings to determine the political relations and
                    allegiance of north Schleswig. A large, perhaps the far greater, part of the
                    people are devotedly attached to the Danish government. But there is a counter
                    feeling at work—a feeling averse to any division of the duchy and the desire to
                    keep it united, no matter under what sovereignty. Speeches have been made
                    against a division by residents of the duchy, addressing themselves to large
                    assemblies in the Danish language, and a deputation favoring permanent
                    annexation to Prussia has been sent to Berlin. The opinion is entertained here
                    that these manifestations are a part of a plan and the fruits of influences
                    under the control and direction of the cabinet at Berlin; a matter about which I
                    have no reliable information, and am in no condition to express any opinion. It
                    is further believed that despatches have been received by both the Prussian and
                    Danish governments from the French and Russian governments affecting the
                    settlement of the duchy question, but their purport and effect have not
                    transpired.</p>
                <p>A government commission has now under consideration the subject of the
                    reorganization of the Danish army, a matter that will be one of the principal
                    subjects of discussion in the next Rigsraad. One measure strongly urged before
                    the commissioners is to require of every able-bodied citizen capable of bearing
                    arms a given term of military service, without the right of substitution. I
                    learn from Count Frys, the foreign minister, that this plan is quite popular
                    with many people, upon the idea that it equalizes all classes and fortunes, and
                    in that regard remarking that “public sentiment here seemed to be more in favor
                    of equality than liberty.” It is uncertain what plan will be adopted</p>
                <p>I am, sir, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GEORGE H. YEAMAN.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
