<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-12-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-12-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="174" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d174">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Portman</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 67.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States in
                                        Japan,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Yedo,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-12-05"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 5, 1865</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In my despatch No. 66, of the 30th ultimo,
                            I had the honor to inform you of the results of the negotiations in
                            which I have lately been engaged in Osacca hay, in concert with the
                            representatives of Great Britain, France, and the Netherlands; and in my
                            despatch No. 64, covering copy of memorandum, (enclosure No. 1,) I
                            submitted the reasons that induced me to unite with those
                            representatives in carrying out the instructions that had been received
                            from their respective governments. I trust you may have been pleased to
                            approve of those reasons. The temporary transfer of the four legations
                            to Osacca, with the full cognizance of the Tycoon’s chief advisers, was
                            so evidently an act of peace and good will towards this government and
                            people, that I did not hesitate in co-operating in that measure, taking
                            also into consideration that the instructions referred to being based on
                            the convention of the 22d October, 1864, my absence on such occasion
                            might prove embarrassing. Under any circumstances I knew, as stated in
                            my despatch No. 64, of the 30th October, that a golden opportunity to
                            place our political and commercial relations with Japan on an improved
                            basis had presented itself; the opportunity should not be missed, and
                            the results have justified my expectations. The squadron, consisting of
                            nine vessels, did not sail on the 31st October, as intended, but one day
                            later, and arrived at Hiogo early on the 4th November. The anchorage at
                            Hiogo was preferred, not only for its excellence, but principally
                            because it was deemed prudent not to approach nearer to Osacca until the
                            state of affairs in that city, temporarily the seat of government and
                            the headquarters of the Japanese army, could have been accurately
                            ascertained. Officers of the legations proceeded to Osacca on that day,
                            bearing four letters, announcing the arrival of the four legations, and
                            also for the purpose of arranging the preliminaries for the proposed
                            negotiations. It was stipulated that Abe Bungo no Kami, a member of the
                            Gorogio, held in higher estimation than his colleagues, should be
                            charged with the negotiations on behalf of the Tycoon; he was stated to
                            be then at Kioto, in attendance upon the Tycoon, who, on that day, in an
                            audience of great ceremony, received the Mikado’s commands to march
                            against Chorhu and suppress his rebellion. The arrival of the legations
                            at this juncture, as anticipated, was most opportune, as it furnished
                            the Tycoon with sound reasons for delaying his operations against Chorhu
                            with an army imperfectly organized and partly mistrusted—a task of great
                            difficulty, if not impossible of successful accomplishment, particularly
                            in this season. It also enabled him to remain near Kioto to guard his
                            interests, which might have been in jeopardy during his absence, from
                            the intrigues of powerful Daimios, some of whom were strongly suspected
                            of sympathizing with Chorhu, and others of coveting the high office of
                            Tycoon of Japan. It was conjectured that the Tycoon’s departure with his
                            forces would be the signal for a palace revolution at Kioto, leading to
                            serious disturbances, and eventually to civil war. The political
                            condition of Japan at that moment, from all that could be learned, may
                            be described without exaggeration as an imperfect state of civil war. A
                            building for conferences, with <pb facs="0264" n="190" xml:id="pg_190"/>
                            limited accommodation for residence, had been selected at Osacca; the
                            preference, however, was given to Hiogo, and all the conferences were
                            accordingly held on board the British flag-ship by the British minister,
                            Netherlands political agent, and myself, at the close of each of which
                            the Japanese ministers proceeded on board the Guerriere, when the same
                            arguments were used by the French minister, who was prevented by
                            indisposition from joining the conferences on board the British
                            flag-ship. This mode of proceeding had the advantage of allowing time,
                            for however brief a space, for considering such proposals as might be
                            made; and also for additional suggestions, it might be desirable to
                            tender during the conferences either on board the British or French
                            flag-ships, between whom, on such occasions, communications were kept up
                            without intermission. Copies of the minutes of two conferences were
                            transmitted with my despatch No. 65, of the 18th ultimo. During the
                            evening of the 11th, Abe Bungo no Kami sent a message to the effect
                            that, in his opinion, there was no necessity for an interview on the
                            following day; he had fully understood, all that had been stated to him,
                            and he would hasten to rejoin the Tycoon, and urge a prompt
                            consideration of the proposals made. I may remark here, that before
                            leaving Yedo I had ascertained that, under any circumstances, this
                            government would prefer the payment of the three million indemnity in
                            full to the opening of Hiogo and the city of Osacca on the 1st January
                            next, as proposed, and hence, that the action of the Senate on the
                            convention of the 22d October, 1864, could in no degree be affected by
                            any subsequent action on the part of the Japanese government.</p>
                        <p>The second conference was held with Tatshibana Idsumi no Kami, a member
                            of the Second Council, who came in place of Abe Bungo no Kami. From the
                            minutes of that conference (enclosure No. 2 of despatch No. 65) you will
                            have perceived that he made the important admission that the formal
                            sanction of the treaties by the Mikado had become a vital question for
                            the Tycoon, and that he would undoubtedly succeed in obtaining it. He
                            stated that fifteen days were required for considering the proposals and
                            framing the reply; ten days from that date, however, were only granted,
                            as being deemed quite sufficient for that purpose. Communications from
                            subordinate officials, such as the governor of Osacca, and others of
                            that rank, were frequently received in the mean time, but those were
                            considered of minor importance and of doubtful reliability. On the 20th,
                            however, a report was received through the senior naval officer
                            commanding some seven armed vessels at Hiogo, that the Mikado had
                            actually asserted his sovereign rights by dismissing from office the
                            Tycoon’s minister, Abe Bungo no Kami, with whom the first interview had
                            been held, for urging the sanctioning of the treaties. Matmai Josu no
                            Kami, another member of the Gorogio, or Tycoon’s minister, had also been
                            dismissed for the same cause. The next step might be an attempt to
                            dismiss the Tycoon himself. This Japanese commodore evidently believed
                            the statement he had made. His seven vessels got up steam and sailed for
                            other ports in the inland sea; it was thought not improbable that the
                            Mikado might attempt to dismiss foreign intercourse in an equally
                            summary manner, and require him to carry out such a decree with the
                            naval force under his command. The report of the naval officer was
                            corroborated by an official statement early on the next day. It was well
                            known, fortunately, that the material power was in the hands of the
                            Tycoon, and all that was requisite for the removal of complications was
                            the prompt and manly exercise of that power. Six of the ten days granted
                            for a reply to the proposals made had nearly elapsed, and no time should
                            be lost, therefore, if any action on the part of the foreign
                            representatives in this emergency were deemed advisable. It was
                            unanimously determined to address an identical letter to the Tycoon to
                            stimulate him to action, and this was done at once. I herewith transmit
                            (enclosure No. 1) a copy of that letter.</p>
                        <p>The precise manner in which that letter was made available by the Tycoon
                                <pb facs="0265" n="191" xml:id="pg_191"/> could not well be
                            ascertained. It may, however, be taken for granted that when the
                            greatest excitement and confusion prevailed in the Kioto councils, the
                            Tycoon, with a few thousand men, proceeded to Fusimi, near Kioto; a very
                            respectful application was slightly pressed, the Mikado yielded, and his
                            formal sanction to the treaties was obtained. This, of course, implies
                            the formal repeal of those offensive laws against foreigners hitherto in
                            force, according to the views of some native legal authorities, and as
                            such appealed to on the various occasions when foreigners had been
                            assassinated.</p>
                        <p>On the 24th ultimo the ten days granted for the reply expired, and in the
                            afternoon of that day Matsudaira Hoki no Kami, the senior member of the
                            Gorogio at Osacca, and suite announced their arrival. They produced (as
                            they stated) the original document, the sanction of the Mikado,
                            translation of which (enclosure No. 2) I herewith transmit. This was
                            accompanied by an official letter from the Gorogio, transmitting a copy
                            of the sanction, and containing the reply to the proposals made, in
                            translation, (enclosure No. 3.)</p>
                        <p>Appended to the copy of the sanction is the translation of the written
                            promise for its promulgation in all parts of Japan. The revision of the
                            tariff on a uniform basis was readily granted. The Mikado’s sanction
                            smoothes the way for reforms, and this was one urgently needed. The
                            indemnity is to be paid in preference to the opening of Hiogo and Osacca
                            on the 1st January, 1866, which is, however, guaranteed on the 1st
                            January, 1868, according to the terms of the extension granted by the
                            United States.</p>
                        <p>The treaties, as well as all the acts of the Tycoon’s government in
                            pursuance thereof, have now become legalized, and the Tycoon is said to
                            be again the supreme executive authority in this empire. It is deemed
                            quite probable that the Chorhu rebellion will now be satisfactorily
                            disposed of without resort to coercive measures. There is also little
                            doubt that many Daimios desired to open ports in their provinces, with a
                            view of collecting revenue; and that all restrictions hitherto
                            interposed to the dealings of their agents with the foreign merchants,
                            except through the custom-houses at the open ports, will be gradually
                            removed by the Tycoon’s government. If this be successfully
                            accomplished, trade is likely to increase greatly. I hope soon to be
                            able to inform you that the government is moving in the right direction,
                            according to the promises they have made. I have the honor to transmit
                            (No. 4) copy of my letter to the British minister in acknowledgment of
                            the hospitality I enjoyed on board her Britannic Majesty’s ship Pelorus
                            during the entire period of the negotiations in Osacca bay, covering one
                            month. If I had been in command of a squadron, no greater facilities
                            could have been at my disposal than those so cordially extended to me by
                            Vice-Admiral King and Captain William H. Haswell, of her Britannic
                            Majesty’s navy. I believe I am not too sanguine when venturing to submit
                            it as my opinion that the formal sanction of the treaties by the Mikado,
                            recognized by all Japanese as the real sovereign of their country, will
                            prove an important result of the recent negotiations, due in a great
                            measure, no doubt, to the perfect unanimity of views and action of the
                            foreign representatives. The Tycoon is under lasting obligations to the
                            four powers for the action taken by them so opportunely for his
                            interests and the true interests of Japan, and by sanctioning the
                            treaties, the Tycoon is recognized as the <hi rend="italic">de
                                facto</hi> chief of the government of this country. Much remains to
                            be done, however. Several Daimios in the Kioto councils reluctantly
                            assented; the relations newly created by this irrevocable act of the
                            Mikado, between himself, the Tycoon, and the more or less sovereign
                            Daimios will have to be adjusted; but a basis for such adjustment
                            appears to have been found at last in the sanction granted, in
                            connection with the various agreements made between the Tycoon and
                            leading Daimios, which are now said to be in course of perfection.</p>
                        <p>I am inclined to share the hopeful views entertained of the future, and
                            expressed without hesitation by the Yedo officials.</p>
                        <pb facs="0266" n="192" xml:id="pg_192"/>
                        <p>At an early day I hope to receive the official communication that the
                            Mikado’s ratification has been promulgated in all parts of this
                            empire.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, sir, very respectfully, your most obedient
                            servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>A. L. C. PORTMAN, <hi rend="italic">Chargé d’Affaires ad interim
                                    in Japan.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">No. 1.</seg></opener>
                            <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United
                                            States,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-11-21"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 21, 1865</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sire</hi>: The formal declarations of your
                                Majesty’s minister have created the impression that the cause of the
                                difficulties experienced in the proper execution of the treaties may
                                be traced to the opposition made by the Mikado and some Daimios of
                                this empire.</p>
                            <p>In order to remove this cause, which injuriously affects American
                                interests, and which is fraught with danger for the peace of Japan,
                                your Majesty’s presence at Osacca, near Kioto, has induced me to
                                urge in person the prompt solution of those difficulties.</p>
                            <p>By approving the obligations entered into by your Majesty with
                                foreign powers, the Mikado and the Daimios will make an end to
                                existing difficulties, and avert future dangers.</p>
                            <p>And in view of facilitating the execution of the convention of the
                                22d October, 1864, it has been proposed to your Majesty, in evidence
                                of friendship, that two-thirds of the indemnity stipulated in the
                                said convention would be relinquished on the three following
                                conditions, viz :</p>
                            <p>1. The sanction to the treaties of the Mikado.</p>
                            <p>2. The opening of Hiogo and the city of Osacca within a period to be
                                fixed by agreement.</p>
                            <p>3. The regularization of import duties on a uniform basis.</p>
                            <p>On the 14th instant your Majesty’s minister stated that ten days
                                would be required for giving an answer to those proposals, and
                                although I had then been here ten days already, their desire was
                                complied with.</p>
                            <p>Seven of those ten days have elapsed and the intelligence is now
                                received that the minister who was sent to Hiogo to meet the foreign
                                representatives has been dismissed.</p>
                            <p>In view of a measure so strange and inexplicable I beg respectfully
                                to submit, sire, that it is clearly your Majesty’s duty to settle
                                pending questions.</p>
                            <p>A good accord between the Mikado, your Majesty and the Daimios will
                                insure pleasant relations between Japan and foreign powers, thus
                                promoting Japanese interests and without in the least affecting
                                Japanese independence.</p>
                            <p>A misunderstanding between those high governing powers may lead to
                                most deplorable consequences.</p>
                            <p>Friends as well as enemies should understand that the treaty powers
                                are firmly resolved upon securing the faithful observance of the
                                treaties concluded with your Majesty.</p>
                            <p>I trust, therefore, that your Majesty, by a conciliatory policy, will
                                succeed in maintaining treaties; at all events notice is hereby
                                respectfully given that on the 24th instant a reply to the proposals
                                made will be expected.</p>
                            <p>Whether favorable or otherwise is for your Majesty to determine, but
                                the reply should be in writing. If an answer be not forthcoming this
                                will be considered a formal refusal of the proposals made.</p>
                            <p>With the most profound respect,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>A. L. C. PORTMAN, <hi rend="italic">Chargé d’Affaires ad
                                        interim of the United States in
                                Japan.</hi></signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>His Majesty the <hi rend="smallcaps">Tycoon</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">of Japan, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">No. 2.</seg></opener>
                            <head>[Translation.]</head>
                            <p>The imperial consent is given to the treaties, and you will therefore
                                undertake the necessary arrangements in connection therewith.</p>
                            <p>To <hi rend="smallcaps">Iyemotshi,</hi> (Tycoon’s name.)</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>[Translation.]</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-11-24"><hi rend="smallcaps">November</hi> 24,
                                    1865</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p>The above decree, having been just issued, shall be communicated to
                                all the Daimios and Hatamotos, without exception.</p>
                            <p>You will be informed of the terms of the proclamation at Yeddo.</p>
                            <p>I hereby put this on record.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>MATSUDAIRA HÔKI NO KAMI.</signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <pb facs="0267" n="193" xml:id="pg_193"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">No. 3.</seg></opener>
                            <head>[Translation.]</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-11-24"><hi rend="smallcaps">November</hi> 24,
                                    1865</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p>We have lately received from you several communications, to which we
                                should have fully replied; but the great pressure of our national
                                affairs has caused the delay, for which we express our regret.
                                However, we now reply to them all together, and hope that you may
                                deem this answer satisfactory.</p>
                            <p>With regard to the treaties, our Tycoon has made such strenuous
                                efforts in his representation at Kioto that the imperial consent has
                                been given, as you will see from the enclosure.</p>
                            <p>With regard to the opening of Hiogo, we are not prepared to discuss
                                that subject at present. However, though we intend to open that
                                place at the expiration of the time fixed by the existing
                                agreements, we will open it at an earlier day if the state of
                                affairs shall permit. As we cannot do so at present, we shall send
                                our orders to Yedo to pay the third instalment of the Simonoseki
                                indemnity the twelfth month of this year, as provided by convention;
                                and we agree to carry out that convention of the 22d October, 1864,
                                according to its stipulations. We fully consent that the tariff be
                                amended, and shall therefore at once send instructions to Midzuno
                                Idsumi no Kami, to conduct as satisfactorily as possible the
                                necessary negotiations to that effect at Yedo.</p>
                            <p>Which we have to state in reply with respect and esteem.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>MATSUDAIRA HOKI NO KAMI.</signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed>MATSUDAIRA SUWO NO KAMI.</signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed>OGASAWARA IKI NO KAMI.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>A. L. C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Portman,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic">Chargé d’Affaires of the United States,
                                        &amp;c.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">No. 4.</seg></opener>
                            <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States in
                                            Japan,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Yedo,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-11-30"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 30, 1865</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I take the earliest opportunity of my
                                return to this place to request you, on my behalf, to tender thanks
                                to Vice-Admiral King, and, through him, to Captain Has well,
                                commanding her Britannic Majesty’s ship Peloras, for the many
                                courtesies so cordially extended to me while a guest on board of
                                that ship during the whole period of the recent important
                                negotiation in Osacca bay.</p>
                            <p>I am well acquainted with naval rules and regulations, and can
                                therefore, to the fullest extent, appreciate those courtesies which,
                                in the absence of a national man-of-war, enabled me to co-operate
                                with my colleagues on that occasion in a manner consistent with the
                                dignity of the United States.</p>
                            <p>I shall not fail to inform my government of all those courtesies,
                                which I am sure will be duly appreciated. I can only express the
                                hope that her Britannic Majesty’s government will measure merit by
                                success, and acknowledge that the distinguished naval officers who
                                so largely contributed towards securing the Mikado’s sanction to the
                                treaties, which, in point of fact, is not less than their
                                ratification, so unquestionably important and so long withheld, are
                                no less deserving than those whose good fortune it was to command in
                                the Simonoseki expedition.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your most obedient, humble servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>A. L. C. PORTMAN, <hi rend="italic">Chargé d’Affaires of the
                                        United States ad interim in Japan.</hi></signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>Sir <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry S. Parkes,</hi> K. C. B , <hi rend="italic">H</hi>. <hi rend="italic">B</hi>. <hi rend="italic">M.’s Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                                        Plenipotentiary in Japan.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>