<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Morris to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d226</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">226</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1866-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1866-08-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="recvFVZiL6ijeo9Lc" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104428"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Political rights</term>
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-08-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="226"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d226">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Morris</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 164.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of United States of America,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Constantinople,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-08-03">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 3, 1866</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose an abstract of the
                    new constitution of the Danubian principalities as adopted by the legislative
                    chambers just adjourned, and also a French translation of the imperial firman
                    changing the order of sucession to the vice-royal throne of Egypt.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I am, sir, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>E. JOY MORRIS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <pb facs="0325" n="251" xml:id="pg_251"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Abstract of the new constitution of Roumania.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>It begins with a direct abnegation of the rule laid down by the Porte, that
                        the principalities are constitutionally separate. The constitution, on the
                        contrary, commenced by asserting that “the united Roumanian principalities
                        form one indivisible state, under the name of Roumania.” The Roumans are to
                        have “liberty of commerce, liberty of teaching, liberty of the press, and
                        liberty of public meeting.” They could scarcely ask more. It remains to be
                        seen if these two last liberties are to exist in more than name. They were
                        supposed to exist under Couza, who had a troublesome habit, notwithstanding,
                        of suppressing what he called “disagreeable journalism.” None, excepting
                        Christians, can obtain the privilege of naturalization, which is to be
                        granted by the legislature. All persons of Rouman birth, born under another
                        government, can, however, claim naturalization by a simple declaration that
                        they renounce all other protection. All Roumans are equal before the law,
                        and no class privileges are permitted. Roumans alone are admitted to civil
                        and political rights. Personal liberty is guaranteed; none can be detained
                        in prison except by judicial order, to be obtained at furthest twenty-four
                        hours after the arrest. No law shall be permitted to authorize the
                        confiscation of property. This provision shows that the Roumans, as well as
                        more enlightened nations, imagine that one legislature can bind its
                        successors. The domicile is inviolable, as is property of every kind. The
                        punishment of death is abolished. The public have the full right of usage of
                        navigable rivers. The rural law, which enfranchises the serfs with an
                        indemnity to the proprietor, is confirmed. The liberty of conscience is
                        declared to be absolute, and all worship tolerated which does not interfere
                        with public morality or with good manners. The orthodox eastern religion is
                        that of the state, and is declared independent of all foreign jurisdiction,
                        retaining at the same time its unity of faith with the Æcumenic orthodox
                        church. With regard to education, the constitution is especially stringent.
                        Primary schools, giving gratuitous instruction, are to be opened in every
                        commune, the attendance at which is compulsory. This is a little piece of
                        Prussian legislation, in accordance, no doubt, with the views of our new
                        hospodar. On the difficult subject of publication and public speaking, the
                        law allows every one the full right of printing or uttering his opinions,
                        with due responsibility if the effects are injurious. The determination of
                        this point is left to the jury, and neither caution-money for the journals
                        nor the censorship are permitted. The press is not to be made liable to the
                        system of “advertisements,” and no journal or publication is at any time to
                        be suspended or suppressed. The liberty of the press, you see, can scarcely
                        be carried further. The people may meet at any time, unarmed, without
                        authorization, except in public places, which are regulated by the police.
                        The liberty of association is granted, as is the privilege of prosecuting
                        public officers by private persons who may consider themselves aggrieved or
                        injured.</p>
                    <p>This is the social part of the arrangement, and in theory assuredly carries
                        liberty to its extreme point. The state constitution provides a prince, a
                        senate, and a chamber of deputies as a legislative body, either of the three
                        having the right of initiating laws. The sittings of the legislative
                        assemblies must be public, but either assembly, on the demand of the
                        president, may form itself into a secret committee. Members appointed by the
                        government to any salaried office whatever must be re-elected, an extension
                        of the English principle perfectly intelligible in Moldo-Wallachia. Any
                        member may address questions to the ministers, and any citizen may present
                        petitions to the legislature. The full right of expression is allowed to
                        members, and their persons are inviolable, except under accusations of gross
                        crimes. The electoral body in each district is divided into four colleges.
                        Persons possessing a yearly revenue of three hundred ducats or more belong
                        to the first, those with revenues from one hundred to three hundred ducats
                        belong to the second, traders paying eighty piastres taxes are placed in the
                        third. The two first each elect a deputy for their own electoral district.
                        The third category elects fifty-eight members, six at Bucharest, three at
                        Jassy and each of six other towns, and two at each of six smaller towns. The
                        fourth college is composed of all who pay taxes, of whatever amount. Fifty
                        of them choose a delegate, and the delegates choose a representative. The
                        chambers are elected for four years. For the senate, each district nominates
                        two members, one for the country, the constituency being land proprietors of
                        at least three hundred ducats yearly, and the other for the chief town of
                        the district, the constituency being house proprietors of the same amount.
                        The universities of Jassy and Bucharest nominate to the senate a member
                        each. Senators must be forty years of age and possessed of an income of
                        eight hundred ducats yearly. This qualification is not enforced for officers
                        in the army or persons who have been members of the ministerial or
                        diplomatic bodies.</p>
                    <p>In applying the constitution to the throne, the Porte is again ignored.
                        Charles of Hohenzollern is declared hereditary prince, failing whose male
                        issue the right of succession reverts to his brothers or their descendants.
                        These failing, the prince may choose his successor from one of the reigning
                        families of Europe, subject to the national approval. The rights are defined
                        with some minuteness, but they are precisely those of any ordinary
                        constitutional sovereign. Coming to the executive, the constitution provides
                        that no member of the reigning family shall be a minister. One minister at
                        least must be present during the debates of the assembly, which may require
                        the attendance of the whole body. The ministers may be prosecuted by the——,
                        and cannot be pardoned by the prince if found guilty, except on the <pb
                            facs="0326" n="252" xml:id="pg_252"/> demand of the assembly itself. All
                        taxes must be voted by the assembly, and an annual budget presented. The
                        remaining regulations refer to matters of form, and are in some instances
                        merely temporary. One is deserving of notice, by which every Roumanian is
                        declared to belong either to the regular army, the militia, or the national
                        guard. This is assuming the principle of conscription as innately applicable
                        to every inhabitant of the provinces.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
