<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-09-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-09-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="261" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d261">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Asboth</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 10.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-09-24"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 24, 1866</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The long detention of Mr. Washburn on his
                            return to Paraguay has become a source of extreme irritation and
                            annoyance. At the same time it has been impossible to maintain any
                            regularity of correspondence upon the subject with the allies, or even
                            with Mr. Washburn himself, during the past year.</p>
                        <p>I have now before me a copy of a definitive correspondence which has
                            taken place between this department and the Brazilian government, which
                            leads me to hope that long before this reaches you the difficulty will
                            entirely have ceased. But among the papers which the record presents is
                            a letter written by President Mitre to Mr. Washburn on the 24th of July
                            last, which distinctly asserts and maintains the right of the allies to
                            make that detention endure according to the pleasure of the allies. The
                            President of the United States cannot consent to hold relations of peace
                            and friendship with even friendly nations, when they make their own
                            interests the rule of exposition, instead of the law of nations.</p>
                        <p>You are therefore instructed to protest with due seriousness against
                            President Mitre’s letter to Mr. Washburn, and to say that this
                            government cannot acquiesce therein.</p>
                        <p>You will read this despatch to the minister of foreign affairs, and give
                            him a copy if he shall desire it.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Alexander Asboth,</hi> Esq., &amp;<hi rend="italic">c</hi>., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.,
                                &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <postscript>
                            <p> P. S.—I transmit herewith copy of the correspondence<note n="*" xml:id="d261fn1">For enclosures, see correspondence with the
                                    United States minister to Brazil.</note> between this department
                                and Mr. Webb, as well as of the letter of President Mitre to Mr.
                                Washburn on the same subject.</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>