<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Lidgerwood to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d269</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">269</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1866-01-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1866-01-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-01-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-01-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="269"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d269">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Lidgerwood</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 5.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Rio de Janeiro,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-01-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 2, 1866</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: * * * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have hitherto refrained from referring to the expected great immigration to
                    this country from the United States, and especially from those States that were
                    recently in a state of rebellion.</p>
                <p>Immigration of the North Americans has been the leading topic of the journals
                    throughout this empire for several months.</p>
                <p>Great advantages have been predicted from the influx of a hard-working,
                    provident, virtuous, and intelligent population, who would bring with them
                    capital, labor-saving implements, and machinery, and who would in a short time
                    supply the present want of laborers, and by their example and energies soon
                    create a prosperity only surpassed by that of the United States.</p>
                <p>Representatives from the southern States of the United States of America,
                    professing to be agents to locate lands for hundreds and thousands of people,
                    have stated, that not only thousands of families, but that even an hundred
                    thousand families, would come to Brazil. These agents have been sent to the
                    interior of several provinces at the expense of this government, have been
                    received with the utmost distinction possible to high dignitaries by the
                    presidents and officials of same, and every effort to induce the promised great
                    immigation has been made by the general government. So far, however, to but
                    little or no effect, as but small numbers have arrived. A few worthy men, with
                    professions, have found employment by the government; some families which
                    arrived several months ago, the heads of which swore that they would rather
                    starve in Brazil than live in wealth in the United States, after losing several
                    members by death, and making fruitless struggles with their own labor as
                    agriculturists, have now applied to the consul and to the American Benevolent
                    Association for money to assist them back to the United States. A number of
                    families still remain.</p>
                <p>My impressions are, therefore, that no immediate large immigration will take
                    place, but that in time, by constant arrivals in small numbers, many of whom
                    will not have money enough to return, there will, eventually, be quite a
                    population of voluntarily expatriated Americans in this country.</p>
                <p>They state that “they have experienced suffering enough in the late rebellion,
                    and hereafter wish to live in peace.” Influenced by that motive, they will not
                    become naturalized Brazilian citizens, in order to avoid military duty to this
                    government. They generally leave the United States without passports. They leave
                    the United States (as they intend) forever, and many of them here boast that
                    they are secessionists, and of their hatred to the Yankees.</p>
                <p>As far as any service due by them to the government of the United States is
                    concerned, they are, with few exceptions, “<hi rend="italic">de facto</hi>” just
                    as much rebels today as when in arms against it.</p>
                <p>At the present moment, almost any breach of peace, or violation of Brazilian law
                    by an American, would be overlooked; but should there be a reaction of sentiment
                    towards them, consequent upon the non-fulfilment of the promises by the
                    representatives of immigation companies, the treatment might be different. <pb
                        facs="0375" n="301" xml:id="pg_301"/> Many Brazilian officials, and
                    specially of the lower order, are men of African descent; and the American
                    immigrant from the southern States, especially if congregated in any number,
                    being accustomed to order men of color, would soon make himself obnoxious to
                    this class, and difficulties would ensue; and under such circumstances, though
                    he had left the United States without a passport, intending never to return to
                    it, cursing our country and its institutions, he would remember in his time of
                    need that he was born an American citizen, and would call upon the
                    representatives of the United States to protect him, and would take the oath of
                    allegiance, regarding it merely as a matter of form.</p>
                <p>The laws of Brazil are probably not excelled by our own, but in some places, far
                    in the interior, they are not always executed or carried out as they should
                    be.</p>
                <p>I submit these remarks to your excellency, as possibly by requirements in the
                    United States that passports shall only be issued to loyal citizens who would be
                    obliged to prove themselves such, in addition to taking the oath, and no others
                    to be considered as citizens, difficulties might be avoided, which I fear may
                    occur here should this immigration continue, by obligations to protect as
                    citizens former bitter enemies, who still retain their animosity and are <hi
                        rend="italic">“de facto”</hi> not citizens.</p>
                <p>The immigrants whom I have met and <hi rend="italic">are</hi> worthy men, I have
                    treated with kindness.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, with great respect, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WILLIAM VAN VLECK LIDGERWOOD, <hi rend="italic">Chargé d’Affaires.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
