<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-07-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-07-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="276" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d276">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Lidgerwood</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 14.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Rio de Janeiro</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-07-05"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 5, 1866</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to inform you that the
                            chief of the scientific expedition from the United States to Brazil,
                            Professor Louis F. Agassiz, left Rio de Janeiro for New York on the 2d
                            instant, having, during his sojourn in this empire, besides subdividing
                            the expedition formed by himself into small parties, and directing them
                            in their researches in the interior provinces, made a personal
                            exploration of the great Amazonian region, part of the province of
                            Ceara, and Rio de Janeiro. From his arrival in Brazil until his
                            departure he has been the <pb facs="0384" n="310" xml:id="pg_310"/>
                            honored recipient of the gracious attention, consideration, and interest
                            in his requirements of his imperial Majesty Don Pedro II.</p>
                        <p>The imperial government placed at his disposal a steamer to ascend the
                            Amazon and its affluents, while the presidents of those vast but
                            sparsely inhabited riparian provinces vied with each other in personally
                            rendering to Professor Agassiz aid in his labors by every possible
                            means.</p>
                        <p>The example of the Emperor and imperial government, in thus honoring and
                            aiding the professor, met, throughout the empire, with a hearty
                            response, and wherever the explorers of the expedition journeyed,
                            whether near the sea-coast or far in the mountains or plains of the
                            interior, they were welcomed and assisted by the authorities and people
                            in the prosecution of their researches.</p>
                        <p>The national aid and hospitality thus bestowed upon the Agassiz
                            expedition enabled it to accomplish in a year more than, unassisted, it
                            could have performed in five, and to increase the scientific collections
                            of the museum at Cambridge to such an extent as to make them at least
                                <hi rend="italic">equal,</hi> if not superior, to any in the
                            world.</p>
                        <p>Upon the 25th June I invited a number of Brazilians of highly eminent
                            position, and members of the imperial government, to take leave of
                            Professor Agassiz, and to partake of a “<hi rend="italic">dejeûner à la
                                fourchette”</hi> which would enable me to express to the imperial
                            government the high appreciation in which the services rendered by it to
                            the scientific expedition would be held by the government of the United
                            States, and would also afford an opportunity to Professor Agassiz to
                            convey personally to the ministers of the cabinet, by whom the favors
                            were conferred, his deep sense of gratitude for the honors and aid he
                            had received, and for the invaluable services rendered to the
                            expedition. It was also my desire that the councillors of the Emperor
                            should have the pleasure and benefit of hearing, socially and
                            informally, a description of the Amazonian region from a <hi rend="italic">savant,</hi> the representative, almost the
                            embodiment, of the science of America, who, by his convincing
                            truthfulness, frankness, and, excepting his desire to see Brazil advance
                            in progress and increase in prosperity, disinterestedness would recount
                            what he had seen and discovered, and his impressions as to the means to
                            be employed in making some beneficial modifications, counteracting
                            present difficulties, which I was confident would have the effect of
                            convincing them of the necessity of granting the free navigation of the
                            Amazon, for Brazil to avail itself of the great, though at present
                            comparatively valueless, wealth of the northern riparian provinces.</p>
                        <p>Among those present were his excellency the Marquis of Olinda,, minister
                            of the empire, (formerly regent of the empire,) and his colleagues,
                            Conselheiro Saraiva, minister and secretary of state for foreign
                            affairs, Conselheiro Paula Souza, minister of commerce and public works,
                            Conselherio do Amaral, undersecretary of state for foreign affairs, and
                            the honorable Tavares Bastos, advocate of the opening of the Amazon and
                            member of the Chamber of Deputies.</p>
                        <p>After the usual formalities several hours were spent socially. Professor
                            Agassiz, to the great pleasure of all present, described the magnitude
                            and immense resources of the region of the Amazon, the great advantage
                            to be gained by Brazil from the immigration there of an active and
                            intelligent population, with his views relative to the means to be
                            employed to accomplish it, first of which was the free navigation of the
                            river.</p>
                        <p>Prior to the offering of the toast— “The imperial government of Brazil”
                            —I made a few remarks in Portuguese, of which the following is the
                            substance:</p>
                        <p>That it was scarcely a year since the scientific expedition of Professor
                            Agassiz left the United States with the view of exploring the scientific
                            treasures which lie hidden, and nearly unknown, in the empire.</p>
                        <p>The expedition upon its departure from the United States was accompanied
                            by the heartfelt wishes of thousands of the good and distinguished men
                            of our country for its success and safe return; and though entirely a
                            private undertaking, <pb facs="0385" n="311" xml:id="pg_311"/> it still
                            assumed more or less of a national character, from the valuable results
                            that were expected to accrue from its labors, and from the President of
                            the United States having, in his message at the last opening of
                            Congress, made special mention of it, and from the governor of the State
                            of Massachusetts having written a letter of thanks to his Majesty the
                            Emperor of Brazil for the kind reception it had met with.</p>
                        <p>Animated by the knowledge of the scientific acquirements of the Emperor,
                            and of the numerous scientific societies honored and protected by him,
                            and confiding in the proverbial hospitality of Brazil, it was not a
                            matter of surprise that our countrymen should have expected to have been
                            received with welcome and aided in their views.</p>
                        <p>Those expectations have been infinitely more than realized, and it is
                            with sentiments of sincere gratitude that I desire to express my high
                            appreciation of the deep interest and inestimable aid accorded to the
                            expedition by all concurring with the wishes of his Majesty the Emperor,
                            from whom emanated instructions for the proper conveyance and
                            requirements of its members.</p>
                        <p>The result of an expedition thus fostered and aided will be of
                            incalculable magnitude, whether considered from a commercial point of
                            view or from a scientific one; and the interest which will be awakened
                            in the United States will attract the attention to Brazil of those whose
                            position and means will enable them to develop, with great benefit to
                            both of our countries, the treasures and illimitable resources of this
                            magnificent empire.</p>
                        <p>It has already created a new and strong tie between the two countries,
                            attaching them yet more by a sentiment of common interest and sympathy,
                            which will last as long as the language we speak. Indeed, the
                            discoveries made by this commission are already facts of history.</p>
                        <p>Profoundly thanking his Majesty the Emperor, and the imperial government,
                            for the aid and gracious reception extended to the scientific expedition
                            in <hi rend="italic">its</hi> name, and as the representative of my
                            government, I proposed the toast above alluded to—”The imperial
                            government of Brazil “—which was responded to by the Marquis of Olinda,
                            who proposed, in his turn, “Our great and good friend, the government of
                            the United States.”</p>
                        <p>Other toasts followed, appropriate to the occasion, and closed with the
                            customary one of “His Majesty the Emperor.”</p>
                        <p>The minister for foreign affairs expressed a regret that Professor
                            Agassiz could not remain any longer, as he might by so doing be the
                            bearer of a decree opening the Amazon to the navigation of all nations,
                            which he hoped would soon be passed.</p>
                        <p>Admiral Godon, commanding the United States South American squadron, and
                            Captain Patterson, of the flag-ship, came before the party separated, in
                            time to be presented to the members of the cabinet who were present, but
                            having only arrived from Montevideo the evening previous, their duties
                            had prevented them from being present at an earlier hour.</p>
                        <p>I have reason to believe that all the objects of the entertainment were
                            accomplished.</p>
                        <p>The imperial pleasure was again made manifest by the Marquis of Olinda,
                            minister of the empire, courteously conveying Professor Agassiz, on the
                            day of his departure, from his residence to the imperial navy yard,
                            where the imperial barge was in waiting to carry him to the mail
                            steamer.</p>
                        <p>Professor Agassiz proceeded in the imperial barge to the United States
                            flagship, and thence in Admiral Godon’s barge to the United States and
                            Brazil mail steamer.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your most obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>WILLIAM VAN VLECK LIDGERWOOD. <hi rend="italic">Chargé d’
                                    Affaires.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>