<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Nelson to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d309</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">309</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1866-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1866-01-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-01-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="309"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d309">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Nelson</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 245.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Santiago de Chili,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-01-16">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 16, 1866</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your despatch No. 117, of December 5th, 1865.</p>
                <p>I am instructed therein to renew my good offices in the sense of a friendly
                    adjustment of the differences between Chili and Spain whenever there shall be
                    any reasonable ground whereon to build a hope of success, and it is suggested
                        <pb facs="0443" n="369" xml:id="pg_369"/> that, in tendering such good
                    offices, it is eminently proper and wise to treat the two powers which are
                    actually at war with equal consideration and courtesy.</p>
                <p>It will give me the greatest pleasure to comply with your instructions in the
                    premises, and I shall omit no effort in the future, as I neglected none in the
                    past, to endeavor to bring about such friendly adjustment. So soon as Mr.
                    Covarrubias shall have recovered from an attack of illness, which has compelled
                    his temporary absence from his post, I will seek an opportunity to confer with
                    him as directed.</p>
                <p>I beg leave respectfully to state, in reference to the equality of treatment of
                    the two belligerent powers, that while I have been careful to manifest the most
                    perfect equality of courtesy in the manner of addressing the government of Chili
                    and the Spanish admiral in the various communications which I have had the honor
                    to address them during the past few months, that equality was destroyed in so
                    far as regarded the matter of such communications by the positions assumed by
                    the parties themselves; while the action of Spain, through her diplomatic and
                    naval representative, was aggressive, unusual, and unfair to those neutral
                    interests which it was my duty to watch over and defend, that of Chili was
                    limited to a simple attitude of defence. Spain demanded, it is true, as stated
                    in your notes to the representatives of that power and of Chili of the 21st and
                    14th of November last, nothing more than an artillery salute, and failing to
                    obtain it, declared war against Chili—a war which was therefore characterized
                    not only by myself, but by all my colleagues of the diplomatic corps as useless
                    and unnecessary. Chili, on the other hand, could not have yielded that salute,
                    demanded as it was in a peremptory tone, under a distinct and arrogant threat in
                    case of refusal, without indelible national humiliation.</p>
                <p>As the representative of a sister republic, whose traditionary policy involves a
                    wakeful jealousy of the aggressions of Europe, residing near a government which
                    has reiterated her earnest sympathy with us in all our trials, and had
                    unfeignedly rejoiced in our success, I could not consistently stand by without
                    earnest remonstrance against the injustice of the aggressor, and as earnest
                    sympathy for the aggrieved.</p>
                <p>This I felt it my duty to do, as the representative of the leading republic of
                    this continent, and. as the protector of the vast commercial interests of my
                    countrymen, sacrificed in one of the most uncalled for and unreasonable of
                    modern wars—a war of pretext and not of principle.</p>
                <p>I am exceedingly gratified to learn that our minister at Madrid has been
                    instructed in the same sense and in the same spirit which dictated your despatch
                    to me. Allow me to express the belief that a peaceful solution of the
                    controversy would be much more probable, if, in addition to the tender of good
                    offices, the United States would remonstrate with Spain upon her unjust and
                    aggressive policy towards Chili. The <hi rend="italic">moral</hi> intervention,
                    at least, of our government to protect the integrity of one of the American
                    republics from unjustifiable attack on the part of an European power was never
                    more urgently needed, nor upon firmer grounds of right and justice.</p>
                <p>Nothing of importance has occurred between the belligerents during the past
                    fortnight.</p>
                <p>On the 27th of December a steam launch from the Spanish iron-clad frigate
                    Numancia, supported by several armed boats from that vessel and from the frigate
                    Berenguela, entered the port of Calderilla, near Caldera, and seized a small
                    steamer anchored there. Although Chilian property, she bore the Colombian
                    flag.</p>
                <p>The authorities being informed at once of this attack, sent a company of the
                    fourth regiment of regulars to the spot to repel it. They opened fire on the
                    boats which were towing out the steamer and obliged them to cast off and retreat
                    with the loss of several men. A second attempt two hours later met with like
                    success. The steamer had been run ashore, and although protected by the guns <pb
                        facs="0444" n="370" xml:id="pg_370"/> of the Berenguela, which kept up a
                    brisk fire of shot and shell, the attacking party was again repulsed. The
                    frigate then fired several broadsides at the steamer, with a view of destroying
                    her but so inaccurate was her aim that one or two shots only passed through her
                    bulwarks. Not a single soldier or spectator was injured by the scores of shot
                    and shell that poured from the batteries of the Berenguela and the howitzers in
                    her launches.</p>
                <p>Don Domingo Santa Maria, late speaker of the Chilian house of representatives,
                    has been appointed envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary of Chili to
                    the republic of Peru, and has been most cordially received by that government.
                    It is said that a treaty of alliance, offensive and defensive, between the two
                    republics, is about to be signed.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to remain, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>THOMAS H. NELSON.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C</hi>.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
