<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-08-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-08-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="41" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d41">
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. J. C. Wright</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName>.</head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#left">No. 3.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Berlin,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-08-27"><hi rend="italic">August</hi> 27, 1866</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that, since
                            my last despatch, the treaty of peace has been signed between Prussia
                            and Austria, and as soon as the instrument is ratified by the respective
                            sovereigns, the Prussian troops will commence evacuating Bohemia and
                            Moravia. Three weeks is the time accorded for the withdrawal of all the
                            troops from Austrian territory. The terms of peace have been agreed upon
                            between Prussia and Bavaria, the latter kingdom paying the sum of thirty
                            million guldens to defray the expenses of the war. It has not been made
                            public whether Bavaria will lose any of her territory or not, but the
                            general impression is that that portion lying north of the river Main
                            will be incorporated with the north German confederation, if not with
                            Prussia itself. Wurtemberg, according to stipulations, pays, as war
                            indemnity, eight million guldens, but remains integral.</p>
                        <p>Baden has already paid her portion into the Prussian exchequer, viz: six
                            million guldens. Hesse-Darmstadt has accorded to Prussia the exclusive
                            right of garrisoning the fortress of Mayence. * * * *</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>JOHN C. WRIGHT.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>