<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-02-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="453" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d453">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Washburn</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Corrientes,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-02-01"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 1, 1866</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> In my last two despatches, written at
                            Buenos Ayres, I advised you of my detention at that place, by reason of
                            the interruption of all communication between Paraguay and the Argentine
                            Republic. I waited then the arrival of Admiral Godon, with our Brazilian
                            squadron, not doubting but that he would send at least one war steamer
                            to be near the scene of the existing hostilities, and would give me a
                            passage above the allied fleet to my post. On his reaching Buenos Ayres,
                            however, he declined sending any vessel from his squadron up the river,
                            and I was left to get to my post as best I could. I accordingly left
                            Buenos Ayres on Thursday, the 25th ultimo, on a merchant steamer, and
                            reached <pb facs="0633" n="559" xml:id="pg_559"/> here the day before
                            yesterday. This is a city of about 14,000 inhabitants, and is situated
                            about twenty miles from what is called the <hi rend="italic">Tres
                                Bocas,</hi> or Three Mouths. At that point the three rivers, the
                            Bermejo, the Paraguay, and the Parana, unite, and the main river below
                            is known as the Parana till its confluence with the Uruguay, below which
                            it is known as the Rio de la Plata. At the extreme southern part of
                            Paraguay the whole army of President Lopez is said to be stationed. He
                            has erected heavy batteries to prevent the passage of any force up
                            either the Paraguay or Parana. The same force can man the batteries that
                            command both rivers, the whole army being stationed just at the
                            confluence of the two. Just opposite, on the left or southern bank of
                            the Parana, the allied forces are encamped. Here they are collecting a
                            large army, which is constantly increasing in number, and being drilled
                            into a fair degree of efficiency. President Mitre is the
                            commander-in-chief of the army, and has been constantly in the field
                            with it since May last. From the best information I can get I judge that
                            in the allied army there are about 62,000 troops, of which 15,000 are
                            Argentines, 7,000 Orientals, and 40,000 Brazilians. Lopez’s army is
                            variously estimated from 35,000 to 40,000.</p>
                        <p>The allies are now preparing boats and pontoons to cross over the Parana
                            and attack Lopez in his stronghold. They have been preparing so long for
                            this invasion that some think they never intend to be ready. They are
                            certainly far from ready now, and from the casual observations I have
                            made, it does not appear to me that they will be ready for a general
                            movement for at least two months to come. The river is very wide at the
                            point El Paso de la Patria, where it is supposed the allies are to
                            cross—at the present high stage of water, not less than a mile and a
                            half. The crossing must be a very difficult and dangerous affair, but it
                            is generally believed that President Mitre understands his business, and
                            will not move till he is very sure of success.</p>
                        <p>The allies have also a very large fleet in the river, consisting of at
                            least sixteen war steamers, of which three are iron-clad, and believed
                            to be invulnerable to anything that President Lopez can send against
                            them. The war fleet nearly all belongs to Brazil, and is being increased
                            at such a rate that when the difficulty with Paraguay is arranged the
                            whole of the Argentine and Oriental Republics will be at the mercy of
                            the Emperor. He will have an immense fleet already in the river, and
                            when the question arises about the payment of the cost of the Paraguayan
                            war his allies must accede to his terms, or he may take possession of
                            every town on the river from the Tres Bocas to the Atlantic ocean,
                            including Buenos Ayres and Montevideo. The Emperor will be slow to send
                            his fleet away until all his questions of dispute with his nearest
                            neighbors are settled. What may be the ultimate intentions of his
                            Majesty in the event of a successful issue of the war against Paraguay,
                            is of course with me a matter of conjecture. But he will certainly be
                            master of the situation, and I am of the opinion that the result will be
                            an enlargement of the area of the imperial dominions.</p>
                        <p>This enlargement must come first from Paraguay. That will be the apple of
                            discord if the prize once falls into the allied hands. Should that
                            country be conquered and erased from the map of nations, Brazil will
                            hardly fail to claim the territory. It is true it is stipulated in the
                            treaty of alliance that the sovereignty of the country shall be
                            respected, and that the people there, when once the Lopez family are
                            driven out, shall be left free and independent to select their own
                            rulers and form of government. But a rupture between the allies is
                            looked for as inevitable as soon as Paraguay is disposed of, and then of
                            course the treaty will be disregarded.</p>
                        <p>From considerations like the foregoing, I am led to conclude that the day
                            of any permanent peace with these countries is remote. Should Paraguay
                            succumb to superior force, both Brazil and the Argentine Republic will,
                            I think, without doubt strive for the territory, and it is for a
                            contingency like this that I would ask for instructions. I would like to
                            be informed whether the United States <pb facs="0634" n="560" xml:id="pg_560"/> would view without remonstrance or objection the
                            annexation of the republic of Paraguay to the empire of Brazil or to the
                            Argentine Confederation, or its division between them.</p>
                        <p>Since my arrival in Corrientes, I have seen none of the military or naval
                            authorities, and consequently I do not know whether I shall be permitted
                            to pass through the lines to Paraguay or not. In the event of a refusal
                            I shall probably return to Buenos Ayres, and if Admiral Godon still
                            persists in refusing me any assistance from the fleet, I must wait till
                            such instructions are sent, either to the admiral or myself, as will
                            relieve me from a position so unpleasant to myself and so little
                            calculated to do credit to the diplomatic service of the United
                            States.</p>
                        <p>The encampment of the allied army is some twenty-two miles from here, and
                            near the Paso de la Patria. I propose to go out there in two or three
                            days, when I shall probably have an interview with President Mitre. The
                            two armies are at what appears to be nearly a dead lock. The only
                            demonstrations made are by the Paraguayans, who send over occasionally
                            small detachments in boats, which return soon after with such trophies
                            as they can collect, including the heads of such as they may surprise.
                            The atrocities committed in this war show that the race has changed but
                            little since the days of Alba and Torquemada.</p>
                        <p>Hoping that under the peculiar circumstances in which I am placed I may
                            be instructed as to what course I shall pursue,</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your most respectful, humble servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>CHARLES A. WASHBURN.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D</hi>. <hi rend="italic">C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>P. S.—I should add that the allies have not blockaded a single port
                                on the river. Their whole fleet is lying opposite or below this
                                city, and there is not a gunboat above here. Merchant vessels of all
                                nations come to this place and depart without interference, and as
                                it is twenty miles below the Tres Bocas, I do not see that there is
                                even a pretext of a blockade of any port of Paraguay, and the allies
                                have not pretended to blockade any of their own ports. The
                                Brazilians have requested the flag officers of the respective
                                national war vessels to send any of them above the allied fleet, and
                                have announced that merchant vessels will be permitted to go up and
                                down past this port. But I do not understand that, they have a
                                shadow of law or right to justify them in enforcing their
                                pretensions, nor do I think they will attempt it.</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>