<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Washburn to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d465</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">465</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1866-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1866-06-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="general" subject="visas" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436" lcsh-match="exact">Passports</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-06-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="465"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d465">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Washburn</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Corrientes,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-06-08">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 8, 1866</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Since the date of my last despatch nothing of
                    importance has transpired between the belligerents, now fronting each other near
                    Humayta. So severe was the loss experienced by both parties in the great battle
                    of the 24th of May, that neither seems to have been in a condition to attack the
                    other. The loss on both sides was not over-stated in my previous despatch.
                    General Mitre in his official report gives the number of wounded in his army at
                    2,645, and the killed at 702. He gives the number of 4,200 killed, and 370
                    wounded, on the side of the Paraguayans. The proportion of killed to wounded of
                    the allied army is as one to eleven and a third, whereas of the Paraguayans
                    nearly four times as many are killed as are reported wounded. Probably some
                    wounded Paraguayans escaped back to their lines, but not many, as on their
                    return they were exposed to a most galling fire from the artillery of the whole
                    allied army. Yet the great disproportion of killed to wounded among the
                    Paraguayans has caused a good deal of comment; and it appears that the
                    Brazilians, much to the disgust of their allies, are disinclined to take
                    prisoners, but kill alike wounded and deserters to their side. This course, it
                    is pretended, is forced upon them by the treachery of the Paraguayans, who had a
                    trick of advancing with the butts of their muskets in the air, crying out that
                    they were deserters, (passados,) until they got so near that each was sure of
                    his man, when they would suddenly bring their weapons to the shoulder and fire,
                    and retreat instantly in the surprise and confusion their treachery had caused.
                    Such tricks cannot successfully be repeated more than once or twice, and hence
                    it is that when any number of Paraguayans are found together, though they make
                    signs of surrendering, they are shot down without trust or mercy. Hence the
                    battles are becoming of a most savage and sanguinary character.</p>
                <p>The two armies are now where they were at the close of the battle of the 24th of
                    May, and it is said that the allies are intrenching there. This leads to the
                    inference that no offensive movement is contemplated by them at present. They
                    are very destitute of horses and are waiting for large re-enforcements of
                    cavalry from the army of Baron Port Allegre, who has crossed over from Brazil
                    and struck the Parana some one hundred and fifty miles above the Paso de la
                    Patria. It is said he has under him from six to eight thousand well mounted
                    cavalry, and that he is now on the way with his whole force to unite with
                    General Mitre. It is not supposed an attack on the Paraguay lines will be made
                    before the junction of these forces. Hence, unless President Lopez makes another
                    charge on the allies, I do not look for much fighting for the next month.</p>
                <p>The naval forces are lying idle and apparently impotent and useless at the Tres
                    Bocas. Two more iron-clads will soon be added to the fleet. One of <pb
                        facs="0656" n="582" xml:id="pg_582"/> them is now in the river, and will
                    soon be here if the water in the river is not too low to admit of her passage so
                    high as this.</p>
                <p>I have not yet had the pleasure of receiving an answer from President Mitre as to
                    whether I am to be permitted to pass through the lines to Paraguay, or not. It
                    is now two months since I visited him at his encampment at the Paso de la
                    Patria, at which time he requested me to wait for an answer till he could
                    consult his government at Buenos Ayres. As two weeks would be ample time for
                    that, I consented, and though I have twice since requested a categorical reply,
                    I have received none. His last communication to me was dated May 19th, in which
                    he said he had not, up to that time, had an answer from his government, but
                    having called its attention to the matter in question for a second time some ten
                    days before, he had no doubt of an immediate decision, which he would
                    communicate to me without delay. Three weeks have passed since then, and I hear
                    nothing, and hence I conclude that I am to be detained here till my government
                    shall give some instructions as to my going on, awaiting here the issue of the
                    war, or recall me. It seems as if the allied authorities were conscious that
                    they had no right to detain me here, and yet they do not want me to go through
                    to Paraguay. So, instead of having the frankness to say <hi rend="italic"
                        >no,</hi> they resort to the most contemptible quibbling and evasion. In the
                    meanwhile I remain here, watching the events of the war, in a very disagreeable
                    place, where the expenses are enormous, and where I feel that it is not my place
                    to be.</p>
                <p>With this I send you a copy of a letter which I addressed to the Brazilian
                    special minister, Señor Octaviana, before I left Buenos Ayres. I should have
                    sent a copy of it soon after it was written; bat receiving no reply to it, I
                    concluded that from some error it had not been received. But not caring to make
                    any direct inquiry, and not learning anything of it incidentally, I mentioned
                    the matter to our minister, Mr. Kirk, requesting him to advise me should he
                    learn whether it had ever been received or not. By the last mail, which arrived
                    two days since, Mr. Kirk writes me that Señor Octaviana told Admiral Godon that
                    he received my letter, but did not choose to answer it. As I wrote you when I
                    was in Buenos Ayres, Señor Octaviana offered me, without any solicitation, a
                    man-of-war to take me to Paraguay. This offer was several times repeated, and in
                    the presence of Mr. Kirk I replied that on the arrival of our squadron doubtless
                    one of our gunboats would go up the river, so that it would not be necessary to
                    avail myself of his kind offer. He repeated that if I should want it, a vessel
                    would be at my disposition at any time.</p>
                <p>After the arrival of our admiral, however, and he found that he would not send up
                    an American war steamer, it seems that Señor Octaviana changed his mind, for on
                    my writing him a note intimating that I would accept a passage in a Brazilian
                    vessel, he did not condescend to answer it. Such is the brief history of this
                    matter.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, very truly, your most obedient and humble servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES A. WASHBURN.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C</hi>.</p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Washburn</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            Octaviana</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Ayres,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-01-18">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 18, 1866</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Your excellency is doubtless fully aware of
                        the events which transpired in Paraguay at the time of the commencement of
                        the war now existing between that country and Brazil, and you are probably
                        equally well aware that at the time of the seizure of the Brazilian steam
                        packet Marquis de Olinda by the Paraguay government, the minister of his
                        Majesty the Emperor of Brazil, the Hon. Cesar Sannan Vianna de Lima, was
                        left in the country with no means of egress for himself, family, or suite.
                        The ports of Paraguay were closed against the departure of any merchant
                        vessel, and no way was left for Senhor Vianna de Lima to get away except by
                        an overland journey so long and difficult as to be utterly impracticable.
                            <pb facs="0657" n="583" xml:id="pg_583"/> Under these circumstances, his
                        Majesty’s minister, having already received his passports, so that he could
                        hold no further official communication with the Paraguay government,
                        appealed to me, as the senior member of the diplomatic body at Asuncion, to
                        obtain for him and his party some means of leaving the country, and such as
                        would be consistent with the dignity and comfort of a public minister.</p>
                    <p>About this time I received from the Secretary of State for my government
                        leave of absence to visit my own country, to which I was anxious and
                        impatient to return. But I immediately responded to his call, and after a
                        long correspondence, and a good deal of vexatious delay, I got the promise
                        of a steamer to take the minister and suite to Buenos Ayres, but on the
                        condition that he should pledge, as its agent and representative, both to
                        the government of Paraguay and that of the United States, that the steamer
                        should return unharmed without unnecessary detention. This pledge was at
                        once given by the minister, and, on behalf of my government, was accepted by
                        me, and the steamer finally left and arrived safely at Buenos Ayres. Having
                        accepted this assurance of the steamer’s safe return, it seemed to
                        necessitate my remaining there in Paraguay till she got back, as my going
                        away might have caused suspicion or distrust; so that what with the time
                        consumed in the correspondence, the getting ready of the steamer, and the
                        time taken for the voyage, I was delayed some six or eight weeks in setting
                        out on my visit to the United States; Hence, I was the same length of time
                        later in my return to the Rio de la Plata than I would have been but for the
                        delay to render this service.</p>
                    <p>This last delay has, owing to peculiar circumstances, seriously interfered
                        with my return to my post as minister of the United States in Paraguay. No
                        steamer of any nation has ascended the river to Paraguay since my arrival in
                        Buenos Ayres on the 4th of November last. Since that time I have been
                        waiting here for one of our national gunboats to come to this river,
                        supposing it would take me to my post. But I learn that the admiral of the
                        Brazilian squadron now in the Plate objects to the passage of any person or
                        vessel above the Tres Bocas, and the admiral of the United States squadron
                        thinks with myself that it is particularly desirable to avoid any
                        complications in the present war, and especially with the government of
                        Brazil, which, during our late gigantic civil war, has shown itself our
                        steady, reliable, and earnest friend. Hence, as no vessel of my own nation
                        will go to Paraguay at present, I must avail myself of such means of getting
                        there as may be open to me. It is under these circumstances that I beg to
                        call the attention of your excellency to the fact that, had I not delayed to
                        assist Senhor Vianna de Lima to leave Paraguay. I should have been back here
                        at least a month and a halt earlier than I was, and in ample time to have
                        gone to Paraguay on one of the neutral gunboats that left for that country a
                        few days before my arrival here. Hence it is, that from my waiting to render
                        an important and vital service to the Brazilian minister, I am suffering all
                        this inconvenience and detention. It is true that this result is not
                        immediate, but it is no less direct, and I am persuaded that I have only to
                        call your excellency’s attention to the facts of the case to secure such
                        action as will relieve me from my present unpleasant position.</p>
                    <p>I avail myself of this occasion to express to your excellency my high regard
                        and distinguished consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>CHARLES A. WASHBURN.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">F. Octaviana de Almeida Rosa,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">of his Majesty the Emperor of Brazil,</hi> &amp;<hi
                                rend="italic">c</hi>.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
