<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-08-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-08-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="473" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d473">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Washburn</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 66.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Ayres,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-08-14">August 14,
                                1866</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have before, on several occasions,
                            called your attention to the magnitude and strength of the Brazilian
                            squadron in the Parana river. I have also mentioned the fact that it has
                            taken little part in the war. Though ostensibly supporting the land
                            forces in the attack, on Paraguay, it has not yet lost a vessel, and not
                            received a half dozen damaging shots. It seems to be the policy of the
                            admiral to keep it out of danger; and I find, on returning to this
                            place, that the opinion is entertained by many, as I have frequently
                            expressed my suspicions to you before, that the fleet is intended for
                            something else than Paraguay. The war was commenced by President Lopez,
                            in the belief that it was the intention of the imperial government, in
                            assisting General Flores, to overthrow the established government of
                            Uruguay, and afterwards to annex that country to the empire. The opinion
                            is now very often expressed, that if the war should terminate favorably
                            to the allies, Brazil will then ask, as compensation for the expenses it
                            has incurred, not only the Banda Oriental, but the provinces of Entre
                            Rios and Corrientes, now a part of the Argentine Republic. This must of
                            course lead to a furious war between the latter and Brazil, for which
                            Brazil would be so well prepared with its enormous fleet that it can lay
                            every important town of the two republics under tribute.</p>
                        <pb facs="0670" n="596" xml:id="pg_596"/>
                        <p>These suspicions of what may happen in a certain contingency, I give only
                            as the suspicions, fears, and surmises of men better informed of the
                            politics of this country than I am. For these reasons it is believed
                            that this government will deny all responsibility for my detention and
                            put it on the Brazilians, as in such an event it will be very anxious
                            for the friendship and moral support of the United States.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, very truly, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>CHARLES A. WASHBURN.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington D.</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">C</hi>.</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>