<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Wright to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d5</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">5</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1866-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1866-02-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-02-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="5"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d5">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Wright</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 20.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berlin,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-02-07">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 7, 1866</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I do not wish to trouble the department with
                    speculations as to anticipated political changes occurring in this country, and
                    only mention the following because they have created an immense sensation and
                    are likely to lead to serious consequences. The intelligence by this despatch
                    will serve to show that there is a want of stability in this government, and the
                    country is fast drifting into a state of things which will either bring on
                    shortly a change of cabinet or arouse the public mind to such a degree, where
                    such a change, when occurring at last, may be attended with revolutionary events
                    and result in a redivision of power among the constituted authorities of the
                    kingdom. The supreme court of justice has just decided that members of
                    Parliament can he held criminally responsible for opinions uttered in debate.
                    This decision, which is to be immediately acted upon in the case of two
                    deputies, has astonished the liberal party in this as well as in every other
                    German state, and alarmed even the feudalists. It is not only unprecedented
                    throughout the German confederacy and at variance with the spirit of the times,
                    the letter of the law, and two prior decisions of the same court, but it has
                    been passed by the supreme tribunal of a country in which the independence and
                    integrity of the judges have been proverbial ever since the days of Frederick
                    the Great. Another measure which has given great dissatisfaction refers to a
                    change in the composition of the House of Lords. The Prussian charter enacts
                    that a House of Lords shall be formed and its composition left to the Kiug.
                    Availing himself of the authority thus delegated to him, Frederick William IV
                    issued a royal ordinance, in accordance with which the House of Lords was
                    composed of hereditary members and members for life, both appointed by the
                    Crown, members elected by the of landed proprietors of noble descent, and
                    members elected by municipal and other corporations. Four years ago the present
                    King, wishing to give the country a pledge of his liberal sentiments, by another
                    royal ordinance reduced the number of the members elected by the landed nobility
                    (who were all extreme conservatives) from ninety to forty-one. Quite recently,
                    however, this latter ordinance has been revoked, his Majesty not only restoring
                    the original number of ninety-one, but renouncing in his own name, as well as in
                    that of his successor, the right to introduce any further alteration in the
                    rules provided for the composition of the upper house, except with the
                    concurrence of that house and the House of Deputies. After this, the only
                    remaining possibility of modifying the reactionary character of the upper house
                    is by the Grown creating a very large number of liberal peers. Until this step
                    be taken the few liberals are even debarred from introducing a motion, the
                    by-laws of that house requiring a motion to be supported by at least twenty
                    members before it can be introduced, seventeen being the entire number of
                    liberals in the house, the upper house being thus protected against the very
                    contingency of a debate upon the liberal topics of the day. Among the many
                    symptoms of prevailing dissatisfaction the following is, pehaps, the most
                    significant. The Prussian charter provides that the king shall not be entitled
                    to become the ruler of any foreign state except with the consent of Parliament.
                    Now, the King holding that the term “foreign state” does not apply to a state
                    embodied with the German confederacy, has recently declared himself Duke of
                    Lauenburg without asking for the permission of Parliament or subjecting the
                    newly acquired duchy to the laws and constitution of Prussia. Thereupon the
                    second chamber of the Prussian Parliament, in its sitting of February 3, has
                    passed a resolution, by a vote of two hundred and fifty-one to forty-four, to
                    the effect that the King has no right to rule or to call himself <pb facs="0080"
                        n="6" xml:id="pg_6"/> the sovereign of Lauenburg pending the consent of the
                    Prussian Parliament. The reasons alleged for this vote are, the term foreign
                    states in the above-mentioned proviso must be interpreted as heretofore, and
                    applying indiscriminately to all states not embodied with Prussia, and that
                    Lauenburg has been conquered by the Prussian army and the cost of war defrayed
                    by the Prussian people. Therefore the motion passed by the second chamber
                    concludes, “the assumption of the King of the ducal title of Lauenburg is null
                    and void.” The above will afford ample evidence that the condition of the
                    country is far from satisfactory, and inspires no confidence in the stability of
                    the cabinet and the solidity of existing constitutional arrangements. It is
                    universally anticipated that the new Parliament, which must be elected in the
                    course of this year, will be stronger in opposition than the present. * * * * *
                    *</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, most respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JOSEPH A. WRIGHT.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
