<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-01-30T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-01-30T05:00:00-05:00" n="134" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d134">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/3729: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China (<persName corresp="#p_JNT1" type="from">Johnson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-01-30T18:00:00+08:00">January 30, 1932—6
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received January 30—10:03 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>158. Following telegram has been sent to Shanghai: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“January 30, 5 p.m.</p>
                                <p>1. Your January 29, 4 p.m. Japanese state that their action in
                                    occupying Chapei was a ‘measure for the protection of their
                                    nationals and a part of the general definite [<hi rend="italic">defense?</hi>] scheme of the Settlement; that it was not
                                    connected with the demands.’</p>
                                <pb facs="0222" n="118" xml:id="pg_118"/>
                                <p>Tokyo’s January 29, 3 [<hi rend="italic">5?</hi>] p.m. to the
                                    Department: Japanese Navy Department states that the landing of
                                    Japanese forces ‘was with an understanding with the Shanghai
                                    municipal authorities to protect Japanese residents outside
                                    Settlement zone.’</p>
                                <p>2. If you consider the above statement an accurate one and if you
                                    consider the Japanese action, even although ill-advised, to have
                                    been motivated as above described it does not seem to me that
                                    the complaint of the Chinese members of the Council that the
                                    Japanese were using the Settlement as a base of operations would
                                    be well founded. (Your January 29, 6 p.m., paragraph 1.) If,
                                    however, you consider the Japanese contention incorrect as to
                                    fact and that their primary purpose was to overawe the Chinese
                                    in the Shanghai area in order to carry out their private
                                    objectives in China, it would then seem to me that the Chinese
                                    had a just complaint that the Settlement was being used as a
                                    base against them. It should seem obvious to the Japanese that
                                    if their troops traverse the Settlement with the object above
                                    stated they are not respecting Settlement neutrality. (Your
                                    January 29, 7 p.m., paragraph 6 of Japanese statement.)</p>
                                <p>3. Please submit your views by confidential code in regard to
                                    foregoing and as to the likelihood of this issue becoming an
                                    urgent one.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_JNT1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>