<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-01-31T22:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-01-31T22:00:00-05:00" n="178" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d178">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/3874: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai (<persName corresp="#p_CES1" type="from">Cunningham</persName>) to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-02-01T11:00:00+08:00">February 1, 1932—11
                                a.m.</date><lb/>[Received 6:20 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Department’s January 29, 6 p.m. This requires a little explanation.
                            It is when some emergency is declared there is appointed a Defense
                            Committee composed of Chairman of Municipal Council, Commander of
                            Shanghai Volunteer Corps and the senior officer of each landing force.
                            These approve the division of the Settlement into sectors for defense
                            purposes, each nationality being assigned by Defense Committee a certain
                            sector. I have not confirmed the actual proceedings this Committee. On
                            the 28th, however, the Japanese Admiral defined the assignment to the
                            Japanese, saying that the Defense Committee allocated that sector of the
                            Settlement for Japanese defense extending from the river following the
                            northern boundary to an undetermined point on Settlement boundary and
                            the Municipal property and road in the tongue (see my telegram January
                            31, 5 p.m.) and when he informed the Committee that in order to protect
                            the International Settlement it would be necessary for him to extend his
                            line westward to the Woosung Railway and eastward to Sawgin Creek the
                            Committee “assented as a temporary measure”. The admiral also emphasized
                            that it was necessary to extend to the railway in order that he might
                            protect the many Japanese residents in that section.</p>
                        <p>Repeated to the Legation and Nanking.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_CES1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Cunningham</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>