<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-02-12T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-02-12T04:00:00-05:00" n="321" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d321">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/4141: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan (<persName corresp="#p_FWC1" type="from">Forbes</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary
                                    of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-02-12T18:00:00+09:00">February 12, 1932—6
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received February 12—9 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>64. Replying to your telegram No. 51, February 11, 4 p.m., the only
                            details I can add to my telegram No. 51, February 7, 10 p.m., are that
                            in endeavoring to work out a formula for some sort of basis for adopting
                            your points in your telegram 34, February 1, 3 p.m.,<note n="22" xml:id="d321fn22"><ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_174"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol.
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 174</ref>.</note> to the
                            objections raised by the Foreign Minister, I had <persName corresp="#p_NEL1">Neville</persName> talk the matter over with the
                            British Ambassador and endeavor to ascertain from his, <persName corresp="#p_NEL1">Neville</persName>’s, contacts in the Foreign
                            Office whether in their opinion any suggestions for a new basis had
                            better originate apparently from Shanghai or from a concert of powers.
                            All this was done <pb facs="0404" n="300" xml:id="pg_300"/> solely with
                            the idea of submitting the recommendations to Washington. I asked
                                <persName corresp="#p_MLCJG1">McIlroy</persName> to develop the same
                            idea through his contacts with the same purpose. In doing this they made
                            no proposition and said they were acting solely as individuals. Both
                                <persName corresp="#p_NEL1">Neville</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MLCJG1">McIlroy</persName> in talking merely urged most
                            favorable consideration by the Japanese of the proposition submitted by
                            you in your telegram 34, February 1, 3 p.m. Although received coldly at
                            first, they were asked to come back later and the propositions submitted
                            to you were given to them orally as what the Japanese felt they could
                            do.</p>
                        <p>The net result of this proposition is that the Japanese are now willing
                            to have the neutral zone, suggested in your telegram 45, February 6, 8
                            p.m., patrolled by neutrals and have abandoned their former position
                            that they must participate in policing this zone. This was their
                            principal concession and we do not understand they have receded from
                            this.</p>
                        <p>I regret extremely if this has proved a position embarrassing to you. Our
                            contacts here are now much more cordial and satisfactory, both in Army
                            quarters and in the Navy where we learn <persName corresp="#p_SSJ1">John</persName>son reports a complete change in their attitude; and
                            we are not conscious here of any change for the worse in the situation.
                            The British Ambassador concurs in this.</p>
                        <p>The local situation is distinctly better in that the tension noted in our
                            telegram No. 34, February 2, 9 p.m.<note n="23" xml:id="d321fn23"><ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_175"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 175</ref>.</note> seems to have died down. There
                            is less uneasiness. In all our conversations with the Government and
                            with individuals a more conciliatory tone is evident.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_FWC1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Forbes</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>