<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-02-12T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-02-12T16:00:00-05:00" n="324" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d324">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/4132: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Minister in Switzerland (<persName corresp="#p_WHR1" type="to">Wilson</persName>), at Geneva</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-02-12T16:00:00-05:00">February 12, 1932—4
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>12. Department’s 10 [bis], February 12, 1 p.m.<note n="28" xml:id="d324fn28">Telegram reads: “Your 18, February 11, 7 p.m.,
                                last paragraph. Please see Department’s No. 32, January 30, 5 p.m.
                                to Consulate. Further reply will follow.” (793.94/4132)</note> With
                            further reference to your 18, February 11, 7 p.m.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>You may tell <persName corresp="#p_DSE1">Drummond</persName> that
                                the question of sending a memorandum on the Shanghai situation for
                                the information of the Council is being considered.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>On the general situation and our views in regard to our
                                responsibilities and the responsibilities of the Council, you may
                                inform <persName corresp="#p_DSE1">Drummond</persName> discreetly of
                                facts and position outlined in the Department’s No. 11 of February
                                11, 3 p.m. to the American Delegation. I perceive no objection to
                                the Council’s making a special and strong appeal to Japan. Any
                                effort which any agency may make at this time toward the objective
                                of bringing the hostilities to an end will have my approval in
                                principle and will in no way conflict with the line of action which
                                I have under consideration.</item>
                            <pb facs="0410" n="306" xml:id="pg_306"/>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>In view of apparent doubt at Geneva with regard to the American
                                Government’s continuing interest and solicitude with regard to this
                                situation, you may say that suspension of my effort in relation to
                                recently advanced proposals of conciliation in no way means that my
                                general concern and my efforts with regard to the whole situation
                                and the problems in general which it presents are abated. Also,
                                state that my desire to cooperate with the League in reference to
                                this whole matter and to take steps where possible concurrently with
                                and parallel to the steps which it takes continues.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Also inform <persName corresp="#p_DSE1">Drummond</persName> in
                                accordance with Department’s 32, January 30, 5 p.m. to the
                                Consulate.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_SHL1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stimson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>