<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Shanghai (Cunningham) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1932v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d429</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">429</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1932-02-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1932-02-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="rec83f6d11c10a4344" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="league-of-nations" subject="league-of-nations">League of Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-02-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-02-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="429"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d429">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.102 S/929</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai (<persName corresp="#p_CES1"
                            type="from">Cunningham</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 8126</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-02-19">February 19,
                            1932</date>.<lb/>[Received March 12.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit a sketch<note n="75"
                        xml:id="d429fn75">Not printed.</note> which might furnish a basis, should
                    occasion arise, of a proposal by which many questions that have threatened the
                    existence of the International Settlement for <pb facs="0508" n="404"
                        xml:id="pg_404"/> some years past would be eliminated, and any future
                    invasion, under the guise of defence of the Settlement, by any power for the
                    purpose of carrying on a military campaign against the Chinese would be
                    prevented. The particular object in transmitting this outline at the moment is
                    to place it in the files of the Department so that it may be referred to
                    economically by cable should occasion arise.</p>
                <p>Mr. Justice <persName corresp="#p_FJR1">Feetham</persName> in his report on
                        Shanghai<note n="77" xml:id="d429fn77">
                        <hi rend="italic">Report of the Hon. <persName corresp="#p_FJR1">Richard
                                Feetham</persName> … to the Shanghai Municipal Council</hi>, in 4
                        volumes (Shanghai, North-China Daily News and Herald, Ltd., 1931–32).</note>
                    suggested that a charter might be procured from the Chinese Government, and
                    therefore the word “charter” is well established in correspondence with
                    reference to some form of municipal government for Greater Shanghai. This
                    outline has been carefully prepared and has been favorably considered in
                    principle by quite a few people. I look with considerable favor upon the
                    proposal myself, generally speaking. I would not call the new administration the
                    “Free Port of Shanghai,” preferring to use the title “Greater Shanghai.”</p>
                <p>Things are happening so rapidly now that I am constrained to believe that an
                    occasion may arise when such a proposal might be opportune. More than a
                    fortnight ago I suggested that such a proposal should be made by the Chinese
                    Government, and this seemed to be viewed with some favor for a few days.
                    However, there is no chance at the present time of the proposal being made by
                    the Chinese Government, and whether there will be in the future remains to be
                    seen. The person responsible for this outline considers that it would be most
                    desirable for the American Government to propose a scheme of this character for
                    the settlement of all questions relative to this great port of Shanghai.</p>
                <p>It is not improbable that before this despatch is received it may be considered
                    desirable to cable a general outline,—I do not know, everything depends upon
                    developments and opportunities. The Department is aware that I have spent a good
                    many years endeavoring to find some solution for the various questions that
                    concern the Shanghai Municipal Council, including the extra-Settlement roads and
                    concomitant questions.<note n="78" xml:id="d429fn78">For further correspondence
                        on Shanghai matters, see <ref target="#pg_89">pp. 89</ref> ff.</note> Some
                    of those interested in this scheme at one time suggested that certain officers
                    should be appointed by the League of Nations. This is no longer in favor
                    locally, since the League of Nations is out of favor at the present time in
                    Shanghai, and therefore they have substituted the Permanent Court of Arbitration
                    at The Hague.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CES1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Edwin S. Cunningham</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
