<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-02-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-02-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="457" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d457">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.01 Manchuria/21</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Chinese Ministry of Foreign
                                    Affairs at Nanking</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Chinese
                                    Legation</gloss></hi><note n="89" xml:id="d457fn89">Copy of
                                telegram transmitted to the Secretary of State by the Chinese Chargé
                                under covering note dated February 23, 1932.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-02-23">February 23, 1932</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Statement of the Chinese Government
                                Concerning the So-Called Independence Movement in Manchuria</hi></p>
                        <p>The Three Eastern Provinces, also known as Manchuria, are always an
                            integral part of China and any usurpation or interference with the <pb facs="0527" n="423" xml:id="pg_423"/> administration therein
                            constitutes a direct impairment of China’s territorial and
                            administrative integrity. Article 1 of the Organic Law of the National
                            Government of October 4, 1928, which was proclaimed in Manchuria as well
                            as the other provinces of the Republic provides that the National
                            Government will exercise all the governing powers of the Chinese
                            Republic. The Provisional Constitution of June 1, 1931, expressly
                            provides that the territory of the Chinese Republic consists of the
                            various Provinces, Mongolia, and Tibet, and that the Chinese Republic
                            will be a unified Republic forever.</p>
                        <p>The territorial, political and administrative integrity of the Chinese
                            Republic, besides being an attribute of a sovereign state according to
                            the international law is guaranteed by Article 10 of the League Covenant
                            and Article 1 of the Nine Power Treaty. Such guarantee has been
                            implemented by Japan when she adhered to the League Council Resolution
                            of the 30th of last September—<note n="90" xml:id="d457fn90"><ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_13"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 13</ref>.</note>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The Council</p>
                                <p>[“] 2. Recognises the importance of the Japanese Government’s
                                    statement that it has no territorial designs in Manchuria;</p>
                                <p>“5. Being convinced that both Governments are anxious to avoid
                                    taking any action which might disturb the peace and good
                                    understanding between the two nations, notes that the Chinese
                                    and Japanese representatives have given assurances that their
                                    respective Governments will take all necessary steps to prevent
                                    any extension of the scope of the incident or any aggravation of
                                    the situation.”</p></quote></p>
                        <p>In the Resolution of the 24th of last October<note n="91" xml:id="d457fn91"><ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_29"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p. 29</ref>.</note> the Council
                            emphasized the importance of these assurances saying that it— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“(3) Recalls the Japanese statement that Japan has no territorial
                                    designs in Manchuria, and notes that this statement is in
                                    accordance with the terms of the Covenant of the League of
                                    Nations, and of the Nine Power Treaty, the signatories of which
                                    are pledged ‘to respect the sovereignty, the independence, and
                                    the territorial and administrative integrity of
                                China.’”</p></quote></p>
                        <p>The Council further notes in the Resolution of the 10th of last
                                December—<note n="92" xml:id="d457fn92"><ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_59"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p.
                                    59</ref>.</note>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“(2) Considering that events have assumed an even more serious
                                    aspect since the Council meeting of October 24th; [”]</p>
                                <p>(The Council) “Notes that the two parties undertake to adopt all
                                    measures necessary to avoid any further aggravation of the
                                    situation and to refrain from any initiative which may lead to
                                    further fighting and loss of life.”</p></quote></p>
                        <pb facs="0528" n="424" xml:id="pg_424"/>
                        <p>This Resolution was also accepted by Japan. The Chinese Delegate who
                            endorsed it declared: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“China would regard any attempt by Japan to bring about
                                    complications of a political character affecting China’s
                                    territorial or administrative integrity (such as promoting
                                    so-called independence movements, or utilising disorderly
                                    elements for such purposes) as an obvious violation of the
                                    undertaking to avoid any further aggravation of the
                                    situation.”</p></quote></p>
                        <p>Now in defiance of all law and solemn obligations the Japanese
                            authorities who are in unlawful occupation of the Three Eastern
                            Provinces are endeavoring to set up in these Provinces a so-called
                            independent government and are trying to compel the Chinese citizens to
                            participate in the puppet organization. The National Government has
                            repeatedly and emphatically protested against the illegal actions of the
                            Japanese Government and hereby again declares that it will not recognize
                            the secession or independence of the Three Eastern Provinces or any part
                            thereof or any administration which may be organized therein without its
                            authority and consent.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>