<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan (Forbes) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1932v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d599</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">599</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1932-03-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1932-03-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recmnRTtwUBtjR3ea" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="receKRNx87Ug7K5bW" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106111"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Pravda</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-03-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-03-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="599"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d599">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">761.94/485</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan (<persName corresp="#p_FWC1"
                            type="from">Forbes</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 520</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-03-10">March 10,
                            1932</date>.<lb/>[Received March 26.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to submit a few comments
                    supplementing my despatch on the subject of Soviet-Japanese relations as
                    affected by the disturbances in Manchuria (Despatch No. 410 of December 5,
                        1931<note n="83" xml:id="d599fn83">Not printed.</note>). The tension which I
                    remarked in that despatch is still apparent, although the situation which causes
                    it has changed to some extent. I may say in beginning that definite information
                    on this subject is difficult to obtain, and because of the constant rumors and
                    stories, an accurate picture of the situation is hard to draw.</p>
                <p>As I reported in my previous despatch, there has been considerable uneasiness
                    among Soviet leaders on account of Japanese military activities in Manchuria
                    near the Soviet border. Added to this is a feeling of apprehension caused by
                    Japanese assistance in the formation of the new Manchurian state with the
                    consequent extension of “imperialistic” influence presumably antipathetic to the
                    Soviets. Some tension might be expected in any nation at the near borders of
                    which military activities were being carried out. In the present case there are
                    further causes: Japanese troops have occupied Chinese territory within a few
                    hours by rail from Vladivostok in a region that has long been considered <pb
                        facs="0659" n="555" xml:id="pg_555"/> a Soviet “sphere of influence”; Japan
                    has demanded and used the Chinese Eastern Railway for transportation of troops
                    despite treaty provisions which would seem to prevent; Japanese have been
                    suspected of supporting White intrigues against Soviet Russia; Japanese troops
                    have been reported as massing on the Korean-Soviet border contrary to the
                    provisions of Article II of the Portsmouth Treaty (I shall discuss these points
                    later). Moreover, the Japanese plan of extension of the Changchun-Kirin railway
                    to the Korean coast constitutes a direct threat to the commerce of the port of
                    Vladivostok, and promises competition to the Chinese Eastern Railway.</p>
                <p>There is plenty of evidence of this apprehension on the part of the Soviets.
                    Reports of utterances of Soviet leaders in Russia, which I shall touch on below,
                    indicate the state of mind in that country. On the other hand, there has been in
                    Japan very little comment, official or otherwise, on the relations between the
                    two countries. There have been, it is true, newspaper reports of massing of
                    Soviet troops in the Maritime Provinces and near Manchuli, but comparatively
                    little notice seems to be paid to these reports. The Japanese Army has long
                    considered Soviet Russia as a potential enemy and apparently regards that
                    country with a mixture of apprehension and disdain. The reported strength of the
                    Soviet Army has long been held up before the Japanese public by the Army to
                    justify its own expenditures. Japan has never forgotten, as I am often reminded
                    by Japanese friends, the action of Russia in 1898 in seizing Kwantung Peninsula
                    after Japan had been forced to relinquish her war-won claims there in 1896 [<hi
                        rend="italic">1895</hi>].</p>
                <p>With the attitude of the two countries in mind, I shall endeavor to comment on
                    recent happenings. The chief fear on the part of Soviet Russia seems to be that
                    the Eastern provinces will be wrested from the Union. More concretely, the fear
                    seems to be that White Russians, supported by Japan, will attempt to duplicate
                    in the Eastern Provinces of the Union what has recently been done in
                    Manchuria.</p>
                <p>On January 30, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>, Chairman of
                    the Council of People’s Commissars, is reported to have stated in an address:
                    “The Russian White guards in Manchuria …<note n="84" xml:id="d599fn84">Omission
                        indicated in original despatch.</note> are openly building plans to break
                    the Far East away from the U. S. S. R. and create with foreign aid a buffer
                    state …<note n="84" xml:id="d599fn1">Omission indicated in original
                        despatch.</note> We are completely occupied in peaceful construction and are
                    doing everything possible to prevent new imperialistic attacks on the
                    Socialistic Republic”. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LM9">Litvinov</persName> at
                    Geneva is quoted as stating in a speech on February 11: “Present events in the
                    Far East which have evoked universal alarm, cannot but cause special anxiety to
                    the Soviet Union, owing to its geographical nearness to the theatre of these
                    events, where huge armies are operating and where anti-Soviet <pb facs="0660"
                        n="556" xml:id="pg_556"/> Russian <hi rend="italic">émigrés</hi> are
                    mobilizing their forces”. A manifesto signed by Defence Commissar <persName
                        corresp="#p_VGKE1">Voroshilov</persName> and issued on the 14th anniversary
                    of the organization of the Red Army, stated: “In the East and West they are
                    laying plans for intervention, preparing public opinion and organizing bands of
                    Russian White guardists for an attack against the Soviet. The White guards, with
                    the support of certain groups of Imperialists, are openly planning to seize the
                    territory of the U.S.S.R. in the Far East”. A United Press despatch from Moscow,
                    dated February 25, states: “The official Tass agency is understood to profess
                    complete confidence in the accuracy of the report (of the formation of a White
                    Russian army in Mukden province under Japanese direction for the purpose of
                    attacking the Maritime Provinces of the Soviet Union) …<note n="85"
                        xml:id="d599fn85">Omission indicated in original despatch.</note> Both
                    Soviet and Japanese representatives here (Moscow) have recently indicated to the
                    United Press representative that the Russian <hi rend="italic">émigrés</hi>
                    constitute the chief menace of war in Manchuria between the Soviet Union and
                    Japan”. The same news agency reports (March 4) a leading article in <hi
                        rend="italic">Izvestia</hi> which quotes from documents supposed to have
                    been written by Japanese of authority urging an early attack upon Soviet Russia.
                    The article declares that the Soviet Government regards the danger as serious,
                    and cites other developments to justify military vigilance, especially the
                    “symptomatic significance of the fact that Japan two months ago did not consider
                    it necessary to reply to a proposal for a pact of non-aggression with the
                    Soviets”. Also mentioned are the intrigues of the White Russian <hi
                        rend="italic">émigrés</hi> in Manchuria which are stated to be on the
                    increase since Japanese occupation has extended.</p>
                <p>These quotations are sufficient to indicate the Soviet feeling toward Japan at
                    present. How much this attitude is justifiable by fact is extremely difficult to
                    ascertain. Soviet leaders seem frequently to be conjuring up bogies of
                    imperialistic intrigues and intervention, and it would probably be a mistake to
                    take their utterances too seriously. There seems, however, to be some evidence
                    that the Japanese military have taken steps to organize White Russian troops,
                    for use either by the new Manchurian government, or in guarding railway lines,
                    but in the absence of definite information I hesitate to do more than make
                    mention of this report. If the Japanese military had any intention of making an
                    attack on the Soviet Far East, they would undoubtedly find useful a nucleus of
                    organized White troops around which the many Russians of white sympathy could
                    rally.</p>
                <p>In connection with this report, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KLM1"
                        >Karakhan</persName>, on February 24, demanded of the Japanese Ambassador in
                    Moscow an explanation of certain developments in Manchuria, according to the
                    United Press. <pb facs="0661" n="557" xml:id="pg_557"/> One question, of four
                    proposed, was in regard to the increased activities of <hi rend="italic"
                        >émigré</hi> Russians in Manchuria against the Soviets, “under the
                    protection and direct support of the Japanese”. The reply of the Foreign Office,
                    transmitted through Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HK1">Hirota</persName>, the
                    Japanese Ambassador, a few days later, stated that there was no truth in the
                    report of assistance by the Japanese Army to the White Russians, and that the
                    Japanese Army was doing all it could to curtail their activities and was ready
                    to suppress any political steps they might take. (I shall refer later to the
                    remaining three questions proposed by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KLM1"
                        >Karakhan</persName>).</p>
                <p>A second source of anxiety to Soviet leaders is the occupation of Manchuria by
                    Japanese troops and the significance of the organization of the new Manchurian
                    state. The formation of the new state in Manchuria has an element of threat to
                    the Soviets. In case the White Russians in Manchuria participate in the
                    formation of the new government and form a part of it, the new state may be
                    expected to have an anti-Soviet bias.</p>
                <p>In Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KLM1">Karakhan</persName>’s questioning, above
                    referred to, a demand was made for “information about the newly established
                    government in Manchuria and its nature”. The reply of the Japanese Government,
                    made a few days later, is highly diverting. It was stated that “the Japanese
                    Government has no connection with it (the Manchurian state) and knows little
                    about it. However, when full details of the new constitution and the
                    organization of the government are learned they will be transmitted”. This bit
                    of apparently diplomatic casuistry has not called forth any further requests for
                    information from the Soviets.</p>
                <p>As I reported in my previous despatch, above referred to, the Soviet government
                    has been forebearing—remarkably so—in regard to Japanese military activities in
                    regions of great strategic interest to Russia. Japanese troops have penetrated
                    as far north as Tsitsihar, Harbin and Imienpo, with scarcely more reaction from
                    the Soviets than the issuing of a warning to abstain from injuring Soviet
                    interests and property. More recently the Soviet government granted permission
                    for the transportation of Japanese troops from Changchun to Harbin, and from
                    Harbin to Imienpo over the Chinese Eastern Railway, although technically a
                    refusal might have been made under provisions of the Portsmouth Treaty. On the
                    14th anniversary of the Red Army the <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> stated,
                    according to the United Press: [“]The actual war between China and Japan and
                    Japanese capture of the chief centers in Manchuria, would have been quite a
                    sufficient ground for Tzarist Russia to interfere in the war. The Soviet
                    government, on the contrary, proposed to Japan to conclude a pact of
                    non-aggression. No provocation will divert Soviet Russia from her firm and
                    invariable policy of <pb facs="0662" n="558" xml:id="pg_558"/> peace”. I
                    believe, as I pointed out in my previous despatch, that the Japanese Government
                    has been pleasurably surprised by this absence of opposition on the part of
                    Russia to Japanese activities. Such opposition would certainly have rendered the
                    problem of the subjugation of northern Manchuria infinitely more
                    complicated.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, the Soviets have not viewed with favor the Japanese conquest. In
                    the first place they foresee the loss of the Chinese Eastern Railway. In an
                    interview with a United Press correspondent at Harbin, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_RJV1">Rudy</persName>, Soviet General Manager of the Chinese
                    Eastern Railway, stated that Japan’s domination of Manchuria suggests that in
                    coming years the Japanese will tolerate no strong foreign economic influence
                    there, such as that which the Chinese Eastern Railway affords the Soviets.
                    Moreover, in his opinion the competition of the Kirin-Seishin Railway, certain
                    to be accomplished shortly under Japanese rule, will deprive the port of
                    Vladivostok of much trade and is destined to make the Chinese Eastern Railway an
                    unprofitable enterprise. He stated that although the Japanese military had been
                    careful to avoid damaging Chinese Eastern Railway property, leading some
                    observers to believe that Japan intends to let Soviet railway interests alone,
                    he understood from certain sources that the Japanese would soon attempt to
                    install in the Chinese Eastern Railway board of directors a group of Chinese
                    officials who are subservient to Japan’s wishes. If this is true, he stated, it
                    would mean the extension of Japanese influence to the single remaining railway
                    in Manchuria over which they have now no control.</p>
                <p>I may at this point mention the remaining two questions raised by Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KLM1">Karakhan</persName>, both of which affect the Chinese
                    Eastern Railway. On or about February 24, the Japanese Military, acting
                    apparently without instruction from Tokyo, requested permission of the Soviet
                    director of the Chinese Eastern Railway to transport Japanese troops over the
                    eastern line to points where Japanese interests were reported threatened by
                    Chinese soldiers. At the same time the Army seems to have asked for reduced
                    fares on the railway for Japanese soldiers. Permission to transport troops from
                    Changchun to Harbin had previously, in January, been granted. As the later
                    request for permission involved sending troops as far as Pogranichnaya, near the
                    Soviet border, it seemed to raise a problem beyond the competence of the Soviet
                    officials of the Chinese Eastern Railway, and the matter was referred to Moscow.
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KLM1">Karakhan</persName> then called upon the
                    Japanese Ambassador for an explanation for these requests, pointing out that
                    under Article VII of the Portsmouth Treaty “Japan and Russia engaged to exploit
                    their respective railways in Manchuria exclusively <pb facs="0663" n="559"
                        xml:id="pg_559"/> for commercial and industrial purposes and in no wise for
                    strategic purposes”.</p>
                <p>In his reply, the Japanese Ambassador disclaimed intention of sending troops
                    further than Imienpo, or possibly Hailin, and stated that no question of the use
                    of the Chinese Eastern Railway for strategic purposes would arise as the
                    Japanese action was purely for “self defence”. Furthermore, he disclaimed any
                    knowledge of the request of the military authorities for reduced fares for
                    Japanese troops. This statement seems to have satisfied Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KLM1">Karakhan</persName>, for on February 28 the permission was
                    granted.</p>
                <p>On this occasion Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KLM1">Karakhan</persName> took the
                    opportunity to call attention to the reported concentration of Japanese troops
                    on the Korean side of the Soviet border, which would be in violation of Article
                    II of the Portsmouth Treaty. This charge was refuted, according to the press on
                    March 9, by the Japanese Ambassador who stated that no additional Japanese
                    troops were being massed on the border. Incidentally, he is reported to have
                    remarked that the Japanese had no intention of engaging the Russian forces, to
                    which Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KLM1">Karakhan</persName> replied that Japan’s
                    intentions were subject to various interpretations. Apparently diplomatic
                    conversations at Moscow are carried on with a minimum of finesse.</p>
                <p>The local press reports that on March 3rd, the Foreign Office stated that it knew
                    nothing about the alleged troop concentration on the Korean border. Lacking any
                    reliable source of information I have been unable to learn whether there is any
                    truth in the Soviet allegation. The Japanese are said to be building extensive
                    port improvements at Seishin and are very likely adding to the fortifications of
                    the town. Possibly engineering contingents have been despatched recently to that
                    region in connection with the plan for the extension of the railway to Kirin,
                    but this is purely conjectural.</p>
                <p>I have, thus far, dealt largely with the Soviet viewpoint in Russo-Japanese
                    relations. There remains to be mentioned Japanese apprehensions of Soviet
                    activities, which have been aroused recently by reports of warlike activities in
                    Soviet territory. The press reported on March 1st that the Foreign Office had
                    received a report from the Japanese Consul General in Vladivostok that he had
                    been reliably informed that 100,000 troops had been concentrated in the Maritime
                    Provinces. The report stated that Vladivostok was being heavily fortified and
                    that munitions and supplies were being collected. One member of my staff who
                    inquired at the Foreign Office was informed that new troops had undoubtedly been
                    moved into the Maritime Provinces, but that the number was not excessive and
                    that the Foreign Office attached no particular significance to the movement. The
                    official <pb facs="0664" n="560" xml:id="pg_560"/> of the Foreign Office stated
                    that the total number of Soviet troops east of Lake Baikal last autumn was
                    estimated to be 60,000, but had now been increased to approximately 70,000.
                    Another member of my staff was informed at the War Ministry that at least
                    100,000 troops had been concentrated in the Maritime Provinces alone. This
                    figure contrasts with the 30,000 troops Japan now maintains in Manchuria.</p>
                <p>I do not think that the Japanese are very much perturbed by these rumors of
                    warlike preparations. They have seen demonstrated unmistakably the conciliatory
                    attitude of the Soviets and are not inclined to consider as a threat what seems
                    to be a mere strengthening of the Soviet frontier garrisons to provide against a
                    possible emergency.</p>
                <p>I am at a loss to explain the absence of editorial comment on Soviet-Japanese
                    relations in recent weeks, in view of the usual readiness of the Japanese press
                    to play up any alleged threat from the north. Perhaps, as I suggested in my
                    previous despatch on this subject, the Japanese Government has impressed on the
                    local newspapers the importance of avoiding antagonizing the Soviets during the
                    present crisis in China.</p>
                <p>In any event the relations between the two countries at present are somewhat
                    tense but not actively unfriendly. This tenseness is not particularly notable,
                    because it is somewhat chronic. I may repeat my conclusion made in my last
                    despatch: “I have reason to believe that both sides are sincere in wishing to
                    avoid complications, and will not willingly be led into an embroilment which
                    would prejudice the success of their own undertakings and interests”. The
                    Japanese would have much to lose by picking a quarrel with Russia at the present
                    juncture when their resources and energies are being expended in the embroglio
                    in China. On the other hand, the Soviets have taken every precaution against
                    being involved in the conflict among their neighbors, have avoided taking steps
                    to oppose or check Japan’s military actions in North Manchuria, and have
                    maintained, in the face of some provocation, a strictly neutral attitude.</p>
                <p>In concluding, I should mention that so far as I am aware no further action has
                    been taken by the Japanese Government in regard to the non-aggression pact
                    proposed by the Soviet Government. The Soviet Ambassador has called at the
                    Foreign Office several times recently in this connection, but I learn that he
                    has been informed that the matter is still receiving the “careful consideration
                    of the Japanese Government”. I do not believe that the Japanese Government has
                    any immediate intention of concluding such a treaty. The Japanese seem to feel
                    that they would not be justified in entering into any new commitments until
                    conditions in the Far East are on a more settled basis.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_FWC1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">W. Cameron Forbes</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
