<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Switzerland (Wilson) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1932v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d608</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">608</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1932-03-11T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1932-03-11T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-03-11T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-03-11T13:00:00-05:00" n="608"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d608">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/4710: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Switzerland (<persName corresp="#p_WHR1"
                            type="from">Wilson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-03-11T19:00:00+01:00"
                            >March 11, 1932—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received March 11—3:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>72. In a conversation this morning with <persName corresp="#p_SSJ1">Sir John
                        Simon</persName> he declared that he was anxious that you should understand
                    the efforts he had been making to harmonize his action in the Assembly with your
                    views. This he added had in some cases not been easy as he had been attacked
                    from different parties in England for his procedure but had kept in front of him
                    the guiding principle of the necessity of complete unity in policy between the
                    United States and Great Britain. I gathered the impression that he would be
                    greatly reassured and would feel his <pb facs="0672" n="568" xml:id="pg_568"/>
                    position strengthened at home if any recognition of his action could be
                    expressed by the American Government.</p>
                <p>He is leaving tonight for Paris and reaches London, Sunday;<note n="88"
                        xml:id="d608fn88">March 13.</note> he will be available by telephone between
                    9 and 10 p.m., London time, Sunday night, at the residence of the Prime Minister
                    or, of course, telegrams could reach him Sunday in London.</p>
                <p>We all feel that part I of this resolution was largely due to his insistence
                    based on his desire to cooperate with you and that if you felt it expedient to
                    send him a word of recognition<note n="89" xml:id="d608fn89">See telegram No.
                        90, March 12, 2 p.m., to the Chargé in Great Britain, <ref target="#pg_577"
                            >p. 577</ref>.</note> it would be appreciatively received.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WHR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
