<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-10-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-10-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="117" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d117">
                        <head>117. Action Memorandum From the Chairman of the Working Group of the
                            Standing Committee on Space Policy (<persName corresp="#p_SL1">Sloss</persName>) to the Chairman of the Standing Committee on
                            Space Policy (<persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d117fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                                Central Foreign Policy Files, P860117–2078. Secret; Noforn. Drafted
                                on October 16 by <persName corresp="#p_SL1">Sloss</persName>; and
                                cleared by <persName corresp="#p_GWE1">Gathright</persName>. Sent
                                through <persName corresp="#p_VGS1">Vest</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> approved a meeting at 11 a.m.
                                on November 18. Tabs 1 and 2 have not been found.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d117fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_SL1">Sloss</persName> outlined the principal
                                issues facing the Standing Committee on Space Policy and recommended
                                convening a meeting of the Committee.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-10-20">October 20, 1975</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="underline">Space Policy Committee - Status Report</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">Purpose</hi> - This memorandum will (a) report on
                            the status of the study being prepared by the working group, (b) suggest
                            the major issues that are emerging in the study, and (c) recommend an
                            early meeting of your Committee in order to give further impetus to the
                            study, and resolve certain procedural issues.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">Status</hi> - You will recall that an outline for
                            the initial study was prepared and agreed upon by the Working Group (Tab
                            1). The initial outline did not include policy options because some
                            members of the <gloss target="#t_WG1">WG</gloss>, notably <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss>, believed this was premature. However, you indicated
                            in response to <persName corresp="#p_GJE1">Jim Goodby</persName>’s
                            earlier memo (Tab 2) that the study should eventually include options.
                            Staff of <gloss target="#t_OMB1">OMB</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> agree, and I have begun to formulate such options for
                            later insertions in the study, but I have not yet discussed them with
                            the <gloss target="#t_WG1">WG</gloss>. This is an important procedural
                            issue which probably will need to be taken up in your Committee at an
                            early date.</p>
                        <p>We have now received and distributed to all participants first drafts of
                            the study prepared by several agencies in response to the study outline.
                            These drafts are incomplete and in some respects inconsistent, but they
                            represent a start. I intend to meet with representatives of each of the
                            agencies individually during the coming week to go over their inputs and
                            suggest changes and additions. I shall ask for revised papers from which
                            we will then prepare a consolidated draft for circulation and comment. I
                            believe it also will be <pb facs="d117-2" n="2" xml:id="d117-2"/>
                            necessary for us to prepare an Executive Summary or Issues Paper in
                            State which will be the main vehicle for presenting the major policy
                            issues and options to your Committee. It will probably be mid-November
                            before we can get agreement on such a paper, and even then there will be
                            major issues on which the various agencies will disagree.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">Issues</hi> - The study is focusing initially on
                            the interface between earth-sensing satellite systems developed for
                            intelligence and civil uses. While at the present time we are dealing
                            primarily with satellites that utilize photography or similar processes
                            to survey the land area of the earth, in due course we also will need to
                            deal with other types of sensors [<hi rend="italic">text not
                                declassified</hi>] and with satellites designed for over ocean use
                            such as <gloss target="#t_SEASAT1">SEASAT</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>As the potential for civil uses of satellite acquired data become more
                            widely appreciated pressures are building among <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> users of this data both to make broader use of
                            classified data and to improve the technical capabilities of
                            unclassified programs. One of the major issues we will have to address
                            in the study is whether, and the extent to which these trends pose a
                            threat to the continued unfettered operation of intelligence
                            satellites.</p>
                        <p>At the same time, we are experiencing resistance from some foreign
                            governments to the sensing from space of their territory, and even more
                            to the open dissemination of the data acquired.</p>
                        <p>I believe we can already see the following five issues emerging in this
                            initial study. The characterization of agency views is, of course,
                            preliminary, but gives same idea of where the differences lie.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(a)</label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="underline">To what extent should <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> be permitted to upgrade
                                        the technical capabilities of its earth-sensing
                                        satellites?</hi>
                                    <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> and some user agencies
                                    favor technical improvements strongly. <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> are
                                    opposed to certain of these on the grounds they will compromise
                                    classified programs. Views within State differ.</p>
                                <pb facs="d117-3" n="3" xml:id="d117-3"/>
                                <p>This will affect <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss>’s future
                                        <gloss target="#t_LANDSAT1">LANDSAT</gloss> programs and is
                                    likely to be a major issue in the planned <gloss target="#t_SEASAT1">SEASAT</gloss> program due to operate in
                                    1978. The problem should be aired at an early date by this
                                    Committee, if <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> are not to decide the issues among
                                    themselves.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>(b)</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="underline">Should broader access be permitted to data
                                    acquired from classified programs either through reducing the
                                    special classifications, declassification or clearing additional
                                    users to permit broader use for civil purposes?</hi>
                                <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> believe this will compromise our intelligence
                                programs. <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> prefers upgrading
                                the capabilities of their programs. The user agencies are the
                                strongest advocates of such a move. <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> would like to be able to use such data to support
                                development programs in foreign countries, and believes it must be
                                downgraded in classification to permit such use.</item>
                            <label>(c)</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="underline">Should the “fact of” classified reconnaissance
                                    programs be publicly acknowledged?</hi>
                                <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> and the user agencies (Interior,
                                Commerce, Agriculture and <gloss target="#t_EPA1">EPA</gloss>) favor
                                declassification for different reasons. <persName corresp="#p_CWE1">Bill Colby</persName> is concerned about problems on the Hill
                                with the current policy while the user agencies seek broader use of
                                classified data. <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> oppose declassification also for
                                different reasons. <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> believes the
                                present policy protects classified systems. <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> believes it helps to protect their separate
                                unclassified programs. Within State there are differences of
                                view.</item>
                            <label>(d)</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="underline">Should the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                                    alter its present position on unrestricted dissemination of data
                                    from unclassified programs in light of pressures from the Soviet
                                    Union and other nations to restrict sensing?</hi> State and
                                    <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> are the strongest
                                supporters of open dissemination. <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> are
                                concerned this may eventually cause political attacks on classified
                                programs.</item>
                            <label>(e)</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="underline">Can the classified and unclassified programs be
                                    combined under a single management (not a single system
                                    however)?</hi> This is a major interest of <gloss target="#t_OMB1">OMB</gloss>. The President has a so expressed
                                an interest in the possibilities of combining the two programs.
                                    <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> are
                                opposed.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>All of these issues will need to be elaborated further in the study and
                            the appropriate options developed. However, I would like to see early
                            agreement to focus the study on these five issues, and I intend to press
                            in this direction with the Working Group.</p>
                        <pb facs="d117-4" n="4" xml:id="d117-4"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">A Space Policy Committee Meeting</hi> - I believe
                            that it would be useful for you to call a meeting of your Committee in
                            the next two weeks. We will not then have a paper for the Committee to
                            consider, but I still believe such a meeting would be helpful for two
                            reasons. First, it would demonstrate that the new committee is taking
                            charge in this area. This could forestall possible efforts by <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> to set policy bilaterally outside the framework of the
                            Committee. For example, they now have working groups examining issues
                            related to <gloss target="#t_SEASAT1">SEASAT</gloss> which are directly
                            relevant to the Space Policy Committee. While <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> have agreed
                            that they will refer policy issues to your Committee, you can appreciate
                            that their definition of what “policy” is could well differ from our
                            own.</p>
                        <p>Second, such a meeting could help me in getting support at the working
                            level for the general approach outlined above. Specifically, I would
                            like to see the senior-level committee agree that the study will develop
                            policy options around the framework of the five issues noted above.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">Recommendation:</hi> That you authorize me to
                            arrange a meeting of the Space Policy Committee at the earliest date
                            convenient for you and the other members.</p>
                        <p rend="right">Approve [JS initialed]<lb/>Disapprove ____________</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>