<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>192. Letter From the Senior Adviser to the Secretary of State and Coordinator
                    for International Narcotics Matters (Vance) to the Chairman of the Senate
                    Subcommittee on Foreign Operations, Committee on Appropriations () to the
                    Chairman of the Senate Subcommittee on Foreign Operations, Committee on
                    Appropriations (Inouye))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d192</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">192</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1976-02-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1976-02-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnVHlyUGFMonlp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="narcotics">Narcotics control</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec99jdV9ZgPMHimw" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="narcotics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85089815"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Narcotics</term>
                    <term ref="recQ2U5eNbEz7Znwk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006006835"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Donor</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-02-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-02-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="192"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d192">
                <head>192. Letter From the Senior Adviser to the Secretary of State and Coordinator
                    for International Narcotics Matters (<persName corresp="#p_VSB1"
                        >Vance</persName>) to the Chairman of the Senate Subcommittee on Foreign
                    Operations, Committee on Appropriations (<persName corresp="#p_IDP1"
                        >Inouye</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d192fn1">Source:
                        Department of State Files, <gloss target="#t_IOTHNP1">IO/T/HNP</gloss>
                        Files, Lot 81 D 327, NAR 76 ORGUN Organizations–United Nations. No
                        classification marking. A handwritten notation on the bottom of the document
                        indicated the letter was copied to Cummins in IO/EX.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d192fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_VSB1">Vance</persName> reviewed efforts to encourage
                        contributions to the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Fund for Drug Abuse
                        Control from other governments and articulated the rationale for continued
                            <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> contributions.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-02-12"
                        >February 12, 1976</date>
                </dateline>
                <p rend="flushleft">Dear Mr. Chairman:</p>
                <p>During the hearings on the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1976 International
                    Narcotics Control Program, your Committee expressed a justifiable concern
                    regarding the level of <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> support to the United
                    Nations Fund for Drug Abuse Control (<gloss target="#t_UNFDAC1">UNFDAC</gloss>).
                    In view of this concern, I wish to inform your Committee of the reasons why we
                    intend to contribute <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1976 monies, under the
                    Continuing Resolution Authority, to the <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> Fund
                    at the Fourth Special Session of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss>
                    Commission on Narcotic Drugs to be held in Geneva, February 16–27, 1976.</p>
                <p>We fully share your Committee’s view that the <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss>
                    Fund should not rely on contributions from the United States as its major source
                    of revenue over an extended period of time.</p>
                <p>We have strongly encouraged the new Executive Director of the Fund, Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_DBJG1">de Beus</persName>, to embark upon a more
                    aggressive fund raising campaign. During his visit to Washington last October,
                    Ambassador de Beus met with a staff member of your Committee and stated that his
                    first and most important priority was to increase financial support from other
                    countries.</p>
                <p>Since that time, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DBJG1">de Beus</persName> has
                    dedicated himself to a major fund raising campaign. Thus far, this has led to a
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> General Assembly resolution, adopted
                    last December, appealing to all countries to increase their support and
                    financial contributions to the Fund. The resolution was followed up by a direct
                    appeal from the Secretary General of the United Nations, to all member
                    governments and by a personal letter from <pb facs="d192-2" n="2"
                        xml:id="d192-2"/> the Executive Director explaining the Fund’s program and
                    financial requirements. Additionally, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DBJG1">de
                        Beus</persName> has scheduled personal visits to selected countries which
                    may be in a position to increase their contributions.</p>
                <p>We are hopeful that these new and vigorous fund raising efforts will result in
                    substantially increased financial support from other sources.</p>
                <p>However, we believe the Fund’s work is so directly important to our national goal
                    of reducing the flow of illegal narcotics to the United States that it is in our
                    national interest to assure that the <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> Fund
                    can continue to function effectively.</p>
                <p>At the February session of the Commission on Narcotic Drugs, which is the time
                    when pledges of financial support are expected to be made, the delegations from
                    other donor countries will be looking to the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                    to determine if we continue to endorse and support the Fund’s narcotics control
                    programs. Therefore, we intend to announce continued <gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >U.S.</gloss> financial support for the Fund from <gloss target="#t_FY1"
                        >FY</gloss> 1976 appropriations. However, we also will make very clear the
                        <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> position that the level of contributions
                    from other sources should be substantially increased. The <gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >U.S.</gloss> Delegation will also undertake private discussions with
                    appropriate delegations from other countries to encourage them to increase their
                    support.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>[signed] <lb/>
                        <persName corresp="#p_VSB1">Sheldon B. Vance</persName>
                        <lb/> Senior Adviser and Coordinator for <lb/> International Narcotics
                        Matters</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
