<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-09-11T21:04:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-09-11T21:04:00-05:00" n="48" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d48">
                        <head>48. Telegram 225459 From the Department of State to the Mission to the
                            United Nations<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d48fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy Files. Secret; Immediate;
                                Exdis, Stadis. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BHC1">Blaney</persName> (<gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>); cleared
                                in <gloss target="#t_L1">L</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_OES1">OES</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_DLOS1">D/LOS</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>; and approved by <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d48fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> issued instructions
                                to guide the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> delegation during
                                the final stages of the August–September (New York) <gloss target="#t_UNCLOSIII1">UNCLOS III</gloss> negotiating
                                session.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-09-12T02:04:00+00:00">September 12, 1976, 0204Z</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Strategy for Remaining <gloss target="#t_LOS1">LOS</gloss>
                                Session</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <head>REF:</head>
                            <item>(A) <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> 3591</item>
                            <item>(B)<gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> 3641</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>From the Secretary for Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LVT1">Learson</persName>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>
                                <p>I appreciate your assessment in reftel and in your daily reports.
                                    While it is clear that we will not wrap up the <gloss target="#t_LOS1">LOS</gloss> negotiations at this session,
                                    it is important that we end on as positive a note as possible.
                                    You should utilize the results of my visit and of my message to
                                    capitals to this effect. We should particularly avoid an air of
                                    confrontation which could provide motivation for unilateral
                                    acts. Confrontation or a mood of pessimism could also overflow
                                    and be harmful to international cooperation generally, and
                                    particularly in other North-South fora. Whenever possible and
                                    appropriate we should indicate to other delegations that the
                                    final days of the conference should contain statements of
                                    positive hope that the <gloss target="#t_LOS1">LOS</gloss>
                                    conference has moved forward even if the texts have not been
                                    changed. We should point out that given the air of confrontation
                                    and stalemate existing earlier, a movement towards seeking a
                                    mutual accommodation of interests has taken place in the last
                                    weeks of the session.</p>
                                <p>In this connection is it not possible to take up again idea of
                                    Castaneda of small group to lead Chairman’s report in direction
                                    of a positive outcome. The specific comments below should be
                                    seen in light of this general orientation.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>I specifically concur with your assessment (para 2C reftel A) that
                                this is not the time to make concessions without assurance from
                                    <gloss target="#t_G771">G–77</gloss> on access for our miners.
                                Under the circumstances, the delegation should hold to a firm line
                                on access in keeping with our position during my most recent visit.
                                Specifically, you may indicate we can only proceed to consider
                                details of part of package that <gloss target="#t_G771">G–77</gloss>
                                desires, especially elaboration of financing, technology transfer
                                and the review clause, if we obtain a similar commitment from the
                                    <gloss target="#t_G771">G–77</gloss> on guaranteed access along
                                the lines proposed by you in para 2(C) reftel A. Should movement on
                                this occur, you can outline to same extent illustrative mechanisms
                                of how financing, etc. Would work as discussed earlier with the
                                concerned agencies. We understand that formal sessions and
                                negotiations at this session have now ceased and there is little
                                chance these issues will formally come up in conference meetings. In
                                addition, information we have indicates that there probably will be
                                no revision in <gloss target="#t_RSNT1">RSNT</gloss> at this
                                session. However, we also understand that Chairman’s reports could
                                reflect what progress that has been made in New York.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>We believe, on balance, that no changes should be made in
                                Committee I text given widespread disagreement over fundamentals of
                                Committee I issues and fact that most of the outstanding issues were
                                not adequately negotiated during this current session. If any
                                changes are made, despite current information, or if Chairman’s
                                report will reflect new positions or indicate areas of agreement
                                then delegation should insist that only basis for compromise would
                                be to improve access system while at the same time including general
                                provisions which assure the ability of the enterprise to get into
                                business through financing of the cost of mining and adding a review
                                clause. This would at least be balanced approach and reflect major
                                effort by <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> to meet <gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss> concerns as part of package which
                                must include access. Statement could then hopefully be made by
                                Conference President that while present text remains a “negotiating”
                                text which is considered by all sides as far from perfect,
                                nevertheless some progress towards agreement was made at this
                                session. These would be reflected in Chairman’s report as
                                representing a reasonable basis for successful negotiations at next
                                session. This would protect all groups and open way at next session
                                for negotiation around package presented during my last
                                visit.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>You should, in any case, work to prevent any inclusion of an
                                agreed quota system in a report noting that this was not negotiated
                                at this session and remains unresolved. On Article 9 (interim
                                production limits), you should similarly work against revision or
                                harmful comments noting that this article was negotiated at first
                                New York session this year on basis of carefully balanced wording
                                and mutual concessions and should not be altered at this session. In
                                this context, you might remind <persName corresp="#p_AHS1">Amerasinghe</persName> and others as appropriate that if
                                Conference revises text or Chairman’s comments are only in direction
                                of <gloss target="#t_G771">G–77</gloss> position, this will likely
                                promote major effort in <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Congress
                                to immediately enact unilateral legislation with blame resting on
                                conference for its radical and unacceptable position.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Within context of present instructions you should work for
                                improvement in Committee II and III and dispute settlement to limit
                                damage to our vital interests. Where interagency agreed flexibility
                                exists on main issues and you believe it necessary to act, you may
                                proceed to work toward compromise positions which will protect
                                    <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> interests in the economic zone
                                and scientific research. If you can influence drafting of C-II and
                                III and dispute settlement reports by respective Chairman you should
                                do so in context that we are not necessarily committed to outcome if
                                overall it does not protect our interests.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Finally, as noted above you should pursue line I took in New York,
                                especially with LDCs, on importance of ending session on a positive
                                note that progress can be made at next session given the efforts
                                made by <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> to break stalemate. While
                                I will be away from Washington for next week or so, you should
                                continue to send me daily reports and inform me if there is anything
                                specifically I can do to be helpful to assist the negotiations
                                during last week, including any interventions in capitals.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>