<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-02-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-02-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="66" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d66">
                        <head>66. National Security Decision Memorandum 318<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d66fn1">Source: Ford Library, National Security Adviser,
                                National Security Decision Memoranda and Study Memoranda, Box 1,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> 318. Confidential. Copies
                                were sent to the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, the Director
                                of Central Intelligence, the Chairman of the Under Secretaries
                                Committee, and the Director of the Office of Management and
                                Budget.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d66fn2">The President approved
                                continuation of an active <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                                presence in the Antarctic and directed federal agencies to support
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSF1">NSF</gloss> programs.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-02-25">February 25, 1976</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>TO:</head>
                            <item>The Secretary of State</item>
                            <item>The Secretary of the Treasury</item>
                            <item>The Secretary of Defense</item>
                            <item>The Secretary of Interior</item>
                            <item>The Secretary of Commerce</item>
                            <item>The Secretary of Transportation</item>
                            <item>The Administrator, Federal Energy Administration</item>
                            <item>The Director, Arms Control and Disarmament Agency</item>
                            <item>Director of National Science Foundation</item>
                            <item>Chairman, Council on Environmental Quality</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> Policy for Antarctica</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The President has reviewed the memorandum forwarded by the Chairman of
                            the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Under Secretaries Committee on
                            November 29, 1975, which deals with funding levels and management
                            arrangements for the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> Antarctic
                            Program.</p>
                        <p>The President reaffirms the importance of maintaining an active and
                            influential United States presence in the Antarctic. Under present
                            budget constraints, the President has decided that the level of <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> activity should be maintained at least
                            at the present level. This is generally described in the report as Level
                            III.</p>
                        <p>The President reaffirms <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> 71, in
                            particular the requirements that the National Science Foundation: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Budget for and manage the entire United States national
                                    program in Antarctica, including the funding of logistic support
                                    activities so that the program may be managed as a single
                                    package.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Continue to fund university research and federal agency
                                    programs related to Antarctica;</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Draw upon logistic support capabilities of government agencies
                                    on a cost reimbursable basis; and</item>
                                <pb facs="d66-2" n="2" xml:id="d66-2"/>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>With approval of the Antarctic Policy Group, use commercial
                                    support and management facilities, in lieu of logistic support
                                    from government agencies, where these are determined by the
                                    National Science Foundation to be cost effective, and by the
                                    Antarctic Policy Group not to be detrimental to the national
                                    interest.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>The President notes that United States national interests in Antarctic go
                            well beyond the normal range of responsibilities of the National Science
                            Foundation and directs that <gloss target="#t_NSF1">NSF</gloss> funding
                            for the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> Antarctic Program should not
                            be at the expense of other <gloss target="#t_NSF1">NSF</gloss> programs.
                            The funds made available to <gloss target="#t_NSF1">NSF</gloss> for the
                            Antarctic are not to be utilized for other purposes.</p>
                        <p>The President agrees that the use of logistic support by the Department
                            of Defense—assisted by the Coast Guard—gives the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> an important flexibility and reach to operate in that
                            area. The <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_DOT1">DOT</gloss> are to maintain the capability to
                            provide the logistic support requested by the National Science
                            Foundation, and are to develop in collaboration with the Foundation, the
                            logistic arrangements and cost structure required to ensure effective
                            and responsive program support at minimum cost.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>Brent <persName corresp="#p_SB1">Scowcroft</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>