<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Baron von Thielmann to Mr. Olney.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1896</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d129</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">129</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1896-08-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1896-08-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1896-08-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1896-08-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="129"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d129">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName type="from">Baron von Thielmann</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Olney</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">German Imperial Embassy</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-08-07">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 7, 1896</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary of State</hi>: Mr. Theodore Runyon, the
                    recently deceased United States ambassador at Berlin, repeatedly, and for the
                    last time in his note of September 18, 1895, called the attention of the foreign
                    office to the question of the importation of cattle and beef from the United
                    States into Germany, and stated in this last note that no case of lung disease
                    (pleuro-pneumonia) had occurred in the United States for years; that at that
                    time the cattle of the United States were free from Texas fever, and that even
                    in case of the accidental occurrence of Texas fever no infection from that
                    disease was to be feared, because the exported cattle, as a rule, were intended
                    for immediate slaughter.</p>
                <p>I have received instructions to transmit to your excellency, in reply to the
                    above-mentioned note from Ambassador Runyon, the inclosed memorandum, which is
                    based upon a decision of the imperial sanitary bureau, and from the contents of
                    which your excellency will gather the reasons which make it appear to the
                    Imperial Government, in the interests of the German cattle breeding, unadvisable
                    to repeal at the present time the prohibition in question.</p>
                <p>The United States, by section 17 of the tariff act of August 28, 1894, still in
                    force, prohibited, in the interests of its own cattle industry, the importation
                    of cattle from any country in the world, and it is only a short time ago that an
                    exception was granted in the case of some few countries by the proclamation of
                    the President of the United States, dated November 8, 1895. The United States
                    Government must therefore admit the right of other countries to protect their
                    own cattle industry in like manner. That, however, such protection, especially
                    against <pb facs="0259" n="165" xml:id="pg_165"/> Texas fever, still appears
                    necessary, in spite of Ambassador Runyon’s assurances to the contrary, is shown
                    with certainty by the fact that certain States of the Union, as, for example,
                    Kentucky, by the quarantine proclamation of July 25, 1895, of the State board of
                    health, have entirely closed their territory against the importation of Southern
                    cattle during nine months of the year. Moreover, a quarantine proclamation of
                    the State of Colorado, dated February 13, 1896, and consequently subsequent to
                    Ambassador Runyon’s last note, asserts the existence of Texas fever in the
                    Southern States.</p>
                <p>With regard to lung diseases among the cattle of the United States, I may at the
                    same time call attention to the fact that the State of New Hampshire, only a few
                    days ago, issued a quarantine ordinance expressly prescribing the “tuberculine”
                    test for all cattle hereafter imported into New Hampshire. It thus appears that
                    the existence of lung diseases among the cattle of other States of the Union is
                    regarded there as certain.</p>
                <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Thielmann.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum concerning the prohibition of the importation
                            of American cattle and fresh beef into Germany.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The prohibition of the importation of American cattle and beef was issued in
                        consequence of cases of Texas fever having been officially ascertained in
                        two cargoes of American cattle at Hamburg on the 28th, 29th, and 30th of
                        September (steamer <hi rend="italic">Persia</hi>), and on the 20th of
                        October, 1894 (steamer <hi rend="italic">Prussia</hi>).</p>
                    <p>The veterinary police views, taken into consideration as the basis of the
                        prohibition of the importation of American cattle, are stated at length in
                        the opinion of the Imperial sanitary bureau, dated November 7, 1894, which
                        was communicated to the United States Government. Since that time no change
                        has taken place in American relations that could justify a repeal of the
                        prohibition. The Texas fever has, on the contrary, increased considerably in
                        development.</p>
                    <p>While, according to the order of the Secretary of Agriculture at Washington,
                        dated February 26, 1892,<note n="1" xml:id="d129fn1">U. S. Dept. of
                            Agriculture, 8th and 9th Annual Repts. of the Bureau of Animal Industry
                            for the years 1891–92, Washington, 1893, <ref target="#pg_178">p.
                                178</ref>.</note> only those sections of the United States lying
                        south of latitudes 36° to 38° and east of longitude 100° were regarded as
                        infected, that territory has been extended to the west coast by the order of
                        February 5, 1895.<note n="2" xml:id="d129fn2">Regulation for Cattle
                            Transportation: Rules and Regulations governing the Operations of the
                            Bureau of Animal Industry, Washington, 1895, <ref target="#pg_26">p.
                                26</ref>.</note> This boundary now extends through the whole
                        continent, chiefly between latitude 32° and latitude 37°, and reaches its
                        most northern point at San Francisco, in the West, under latitude 38°, and
                        at the Potomac, in the East, under latitude 39°. The whole of western Texas,
                        Mexico, and the southern half of California are thereby added to the
                        infected territory.</p>
                    <p>The American authorities have not, therefore, succeeded in confining the
                        disease to the former territory, much less in checking it. Moreover, it has
                        not been made known whether and what measures have been adopted for the
                        extirpation of Texas fever within the infected territory. The regulations
                        issued by the Department of Agriculture at Washington against Texas fever
                        are chiefly confined to the prevention of the spread of that disease to
                        those States of the Union lying north of the boundary designated. During the
                        period from February 15 to December 1, 1895, cattle may be exported from the
                        infected district to other parts of the United States only, subject to
                        certain precautionary measures and for the purpose of immediate slaughter,
                        but freely at any other time. On the other hand, with the approval of the
                        Secretary of Agriculture, cattle from certain parts of the infected
                        territory, when they have been there since January, 1895, and have not come
                        into contact with cattle from the infected territory, may be brought to the
                        States of Colorado, Wyoming, Montana, North Dakota, and South Dakota for
                        pasturage. In the State of Kentucky, which borders immediately upon the
                        infected territory, the prohibition of the importation of cattle from that
                        territory during the period ending December 1, <pb facs="0260" n="166"
                            xml:id="pg_166"/> 1895, and from March 1 to December 1 in future years,
                        was enacted on the 25th of July, 1895; and it was further ordered that all
                        real or suspected cases of Texas fever among the native cattle be
                        immediately reported and the animals in question separated from the others.
                        By an ordinance of April 15, 1895, cattle may be imported from Mexico into
                        the territory of the infected Southern States only under certain conditions,
                        partly for slaughter, partly for pasturage. (Special order concerning
                        importation of cattle from Mexico. Rules and Regulations, etc., p. 31.)</p>
                    <p>In order to prevent the transmission of diseases of animals to foreign
                        countries the Secretary of Agriculture, by an order of October 20, 1890
                        (publications of the Imperial sanitary bureau, 1891, p. 248), ordered a
                        sanitary inspection of the living cattle and sheep intended for exportation
                        to Europe at specially designated ports, and renewed the order, with
                        unimportant changes, on the 7th February, 1895. (Order and regulations for
                        the inspection of cattle and sheep for export. Rules and Regulations, etc.,
                        p. 13.)</p>
                    <p>The measures mentioned are not to be regarded as sufficient to prevent the
                        transmission of Texas fever, as, according to the scientific investigations
                        of Smith and Kilborne, the cattle in the Southern States are to be
                        considered entirely infected, and even in the absence of external symptoms
                        of disease dangerous to foreign cattle as transmitters of the infectious
                        matter. (Investigations into the nature, causation, and prevention of
                        Southern cattle fever, United States Department of Agriculture, Eighth and
                        Ninth Annual Reports, etc., p. 177.) Moreover, there are no means of
                        preventing the cattle from the infected Southern States from being exported
                        by sea, owing to the extent of the coast. Under these circumstances, it is
                        not surprising that Texas fever sometimes breaks out in the Northern States,
                        and is even transmitted to Europe. Thus, according to the statements of the
                        Hamburg state veterinary surgeon, Vollers, the importation of such diseased
                        cattle and of the American cattle ticks, which are the means of
                        communicating Texas fever into British ports, has repeatedly occurred. Apart
                        from the cases of evident sickening, all cattle coming from the infected
                        Southern States, at least, must be regarded as dangerous, as transmitters of
                        the infectious matter, and all cattle that have been in company with such
                        must be considered suspicious. The view held by the Americans, that the
                        shipment of cattle affected by Texas fever can be entirely prevented by the
                        measures adopted by the American Government, appears, therefore, incorrect.
                        So long, however, as the measures adopted in the United States do not
                        suffice to check the disease and to prevent the exportation of sick and
                        suspicious cattle and of the cattle ticks which communicate the contagion,
                        the danger exists for Germany that, after the repeal of the prohibition of
                        the importation, the disease may obtain a firm footing here, too, and that
                        it may spread more widely. In that case it would still be a question
                        whether, in view of the peculiar nature of Texas fever, the veterinary
                        police arrangements in Germany would be sufficient for the effectual
                        extirpation of the disease, or whether they would prove as ineffectual as
                        the measures adopted in the United States of America must be assumed to
                        be.</p>
                    <p>It is asserted on the American side that Texas fever is not contagious, and
                        that it does not spread in northern climates. Attention is called to the
                        fact that during the cold season the importation of Southern cattle does not
                        involve danger, and that it is therefore freely permitted in the Northern
                        States of the Union during the winter months. It is to be remarked, in
                        reply, that the views of scientists as to the nature of Texas fever are not
                        yet by any means fully cleared up. In particular, the statements of Smith
                        and Kilborne as to the mode of transmission [of the disease] are in many
                        respects still obscure, and have not yet been corroborated by the testimony
                        of experts.<note n="1" xml:id="d129fn3">Original Investigations in Cattle
                            Diseases in Nebraska: Southern Cattle Plague, 3d ed., Lincoln, Nebr.,
                            1893.</note> Frank Billings, of Nebraska, an investigator who, as well
                        as those specialists, has published very minute investigations as to Texas
                        fever, has arrived at very different conclusions. According to these the
                        infectious matter also exists in the excrement of the diseased animals.
                        Although Billings does not undervalue the importance of the ticks as the
                        transmitters of the infection, he is of opinion that the infection is most
                        frequently effected by the soiling of sores with the dung of diseased
                        animals. The fact that Smith and Kilborne have shown the blood parasite at
                        liberty in the kidneys gives reason to presume that it is ejected with the
                        urine and thereby causes an infection of the places on which diseased
                        animals have stood.</p>
                    <p>As regards the communication of the disease by ticks especially, the question
                        is not yet decided whether European species of ticks and other insects may
                        not undertake the part of the American cattle tick. Moreover, the
                        characteristics of the various species of ticks, according to sex, stage of
                        development, and according to whether they have sucked themselves full of
                        blood or not, vary so much as to size, color, and form that in the opinion
                        of experts it is difficult to identify the various species with any
                        certainty. Under these circumstances scientific investigation is still
                        needed as to whether the American cattle tick (<hi rend="italic">Ixodes
                            bonis</hi>, Riley’s; <hi rend="italic">Boophilus <pb facs="0261" n="167"
                                xml:id="pg_167"/> bovis</hi>, Curtice) is really a peculiar species
                        confined to the Southern States of the Union. The mode described by Smith
                        and Kilborne of the transmission of the infectious matter from the diseased
                        animals to the ticks, from the ticks to their eggs and the young, which in
                        their turn are said to transmit the infection to the healthy cattle,
                        requires further corroboration, the more so because a process of this kind
                        is remarked nowhere else in nature, least of all among the skin parasites,
                        and the ticks, in particular, have been known heretofore only as vexatious
                        bloodsuckers.</p>
                    <p>During the cold season part of the ticks perish and the surviving portion are
                        prevented from propagating. All experience is wanting as to the effect of
                        the cold weather upon the blood parasites of Texas fever. If the authors of
                        the disease, like the transmitters of the infection, retain their vigor
                        during the colder season even partially, then there is a possibility that
                        they will produce their injurious effects in unison in the following
                        summer.</p>
                    <p>Besides, the danger of the introduction of lung disease (pleura-pneumonia) is
                        involved in the importation of American cattle. The American Department of
                        Agriculture has, it is true, in its order of September 26, 1892 (United
                        States Department of Agriculture, Eighth and Ninth Annual Reports, etc., p.
                        72), declared the country free from the disease. Still, numerous cases have
                        been discovered since that time among the cattle imported into Europe. For
                        instance, according to the official records in Great Britain, there were
                        discovered: <table cols="2" rows="5">
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Cases.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>In the year 1892</cell>
                                <cell role="num">33</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>In the year 1893<note n="1" xml:id="d129fn4">Board of
                                        Agriculture: Annual Rept. of the Director of the Veterinary
                                        Dept. for the year 1893, London, 1894, <ref target="#pg_129"
                                            >p. 129</ref>.</note>
                                </cell>
                                <cell role="num">36</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>In the year 1894</cell>
                                <cell role="num">5</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>In the year 1895 (to September 30)</cell>
                                <cell role="num">5</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>The correctness of the diagnosis of the British experts is disputed by the
                        Americans. It appears, however, from a piece of the lung of an American ox
                        in the collection of specimens of the Imperial sanitary bureau that, in the
                        importation case at Liverpool in November, 1894, there was no doubt of the
                        existence of lung disease. Importations of this disease from America were
                        shown to have occurred in Belgium also in the year 1894. The Belgian
                        minister of agriculture consequently, by order of December 29, 1894
                        (Moniteur Beige, p. 4189; Publications of the Imperial Sanitary Bureau,
                        1895, p. 56), prohibited the importation or passage of cattle from the
                        United States until further notice. There is, besides, in the Pioneer Press
                        (St. Paul, Minn.) of March 23, 1895, an article by Professor Mayo, from
                        which it appears that, as a matter of fact, lung disease is still prevalent
                        in Kansas.</p>
                    <p>There are the following objections to the importation of fresh beef from
                        America:</p>
                    <p>It appears from what has been said that the importation of cattle involves
                        the danger of the introduction of Texas fever. Now, in the case of Texas
                        fever it must be remembered, on the one hand, that the blood is regarded as
                        a communicator of the diseased matter, and on the other hand, that even
                        those animals which have not caught the disease arc looked upon as
                        communicators of the infectious matter if they come from the infected
                        territory or if they have been in company with such diseased animals. As the
                        disease producer has its seat in the blood, it is in all parts of the body
                        and consequently in the flesh. Nothing certain is known as to its further
                        action in slaughtered meat. It can not, therefore, be at once taken for
                        granted that the disease producer loses its injurious qualities with the
                        cooling of the flesh. According to scientific experience, such very small
                        animalcule frequently withstand even very high degrees of cold. It has been
                        proved that diseases of animals may be communicated by the meat. Erysipelas
                        in hogs, especially, is in many cases communicated by the meat and refuse of
                        diseased animals. Under these circumstances, and in view of the great
                        diffusion of Texas fever in the United States, great caution is requisite as
                        regards the importation of fresh beef from America, in spite of the measures
                        adopted there recently for the inspection of animals and meat.</p>
                    <p>By an order of the Secretary of Agriculture at Washington, dated February 7,
                        1895 (Regulations for the inspection of live stock and their products—German
                        Commercial Archives, 1895, p. 377), which was supplemented by one of June
                        14, 1896, (Regulations for the inspection of livestock and their
                        products—German Commercial Archives, 1895, p. 858), the owners of
                        slaughtering establishments (salting establishments, etc.), the meat from
                        which is to be placed on the domestic or foreign market, must apply to the
                        Secretary of Agriculture for the inspection of the animals and meat. A
                        number is to be given officially to each establishment, and a cattle
                        inspector, with the necessary assistants, appointed for each establishment,
                        whose duty it is to inspect the animals both before and after they have been
                        slaughtered, and to remove the animals and meat which have been found to be
                        diseased. By the order of August 28, 1895 (order concerning the exportation
                        of meat), these regulations were to go in force on the 16th September, but
                        the time for their going into force has been postponed several times, the
                        last time to July 1, 1896.</p>
                    <pb facs="0262" n="168" xml:id="pg_168"/>
                    <p>Apart from the fact that there may be difficulties attending the filling the
                        positions of the cattle inspectors and their assistants with the required
                        number of thoroughly schooled and reliable persons, we must first wait to
                        see whether the regulations can, in point of fact, be strictly carried out
                        in every case, and whether the exportation of meat from those slaughtering
                        establishments (salting establishments, etc.), which are not subjected to
                        governmental inspection, will really be prevented.</p>
                    <p>Lastly, it may be remarked, that no microscopical examination of the meat as
                        to the presence of the blood parasites of Texas fever is ordered. Without
                        such an examination the animals which have been infected, but which appear
                        to be healthy under the ordinary inspection, can not be ascertained.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
