<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Uhl to Mr.
                                    Olney.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1896</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d163</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">163</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1896-12-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1896-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183" lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1896-12-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1896-12-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="163" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d163">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Uhl</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Olney</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Embassy
                                        of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-12-31">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 31,
                                    1896</hi>
                        </date>. (Received January 15, 1897.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 228.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit hereto
                            appended a memorandum report of certain military cases, particularly
                            mentioned below, which have not been referred to before in my
                            correspondence with the Department.</p>
                <pb facs="0307" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/>
                <p>Military cases of: 1, Nicholas C. and Samuel P. Nissen; 2, Emil Seyller;
                            3, Wendel Gillen; 4, Emil Weller, and 5, Alphonse Berchem.</p>
                <p>Your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Edwin F. Uhl.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 228.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum military case report.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <list>
                        <item>No. 1. Nicholas C. Nissen and Samuel P. Nissen, brothers, born
                                    in Schleswig-Holstein, emigrated to the United States, where
                                    they became naturalized as citizens, and returned with their
                                    families on a visit to their native place in the spring of 1896.
                                    The embassy first heard from them in May last, when they wrote
                                    to say that they were expecting to be ordered to leave Prussia.
                                    In reply to this letter they were informed that no action could
                                    be taken in anticipation of possible trouble, but that they
                                    should communicate with the embassy at once in case they were in
                                    anyway molested. Nothing more was heard of the matter until July
                                    25 last, when a letter was received from them to say that they
                                    had been ordered to leave by the 1st of August and that it was
                                    impossible for them to be ready to go before the 6th of that
                                    month. Intervention was at once made in their behalf, and on the
                                    2d of August the embassy was informed that they might remain in
                                    Prussia until the 7th without molestation.</item>
                        <item>No. 2. Emil Seyller was born in Alsace-Lorraine and emigrated
                                    to the United States, where he became naturalized as a citizen.
                                    In September last he returned to Germany in order to settle some
                                    business matters, and upon his own request permission to spend
                                    two weeks at his native place was granted him. Subsequently,
                                    upon application to the embassy to interest itself in his
                                    behalf, permission to remain in Alsace for an additional month
                                    was obtained for him.</item>
                        <item>No. 3. Wendel Gillen was born at Heisterberg, in the Rhine
                                    Provinces, in 1870, and emigrated in 1889 to the United States,
                                    where he became naturalized, at Carlyle, Ill., February 27,
                                    1896. In August last he returned to Germany on a visit to his
                                    parents, intending to go back to the United States about October
                                    15. On the 19th of August he was compelled, in order to avoid
                                    arrest, to pay a fine of 200 marks, on account of his having
                                    failed to report for military duty and subsequently, on the 4th
                                    of September, he was ordered to leave Heisterberg within ten
                                    days. He then brought his case to the attention of the embassy,
                                    and on September 14 intervention was made in his behalf, the
                                    result of which was that the money paid by him as a fine was
                                    ordered to be returned to him. He also was able to carry out his
                                    original intention as to the length of his visit, for although
                                    the foreign office informed the embassy on the 13th of November
                                    that the Prussian Government did not find itself in a position
                                    to cancel the order of expulsion in the case, Gillen had, as a
                                    matter of fact, not been molested further, and had of his own
                                    accord left for the United States about the middle of
                                    October.</item>
                        <item>No. 4. Emil Weller, an American citizen of Würtemberg origin,
                                    a resident of the State of Michigan, caused the embassy to be
                                    informed that an attachment upon certain property coming to him
                                    by inheritance had been made on account of his failure to
                                    perform military service in his native country. Upon
                                    intervention made in his behalf in September last, the foreign
                                    office replied to the embassy by indicating a course which if
                                    followed by Weller would result in the removal of the attachment
                                    complained of.</item>
                        <item>No. 5. Alphonse Berchem, formerly a German subject, now an
                                    American citizen, residing in England, who had already been
                                    expelled from Prussia, applied to the embassy to obtain
                                    permission for him to come to Germany for fourteen days. The
                                    embassy made intervention in his behalf in September last, and
                                    in reply was informed that the permission desired would be
                                    granted him upon his addressing the request, as usual in such
                                    cases, to the local police authorities.</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
