<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Olney to Sir Julian Pauncefote.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1896</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d250</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">250</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1896-07-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1896-07-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1896-07-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1896-07-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="250"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d250">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Olney</persName> to Sir <persName
                            type="to">Julian Pauncefote</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-07-16">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 16, 1896</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 441.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: With reference to previous correspondence
                    concerning fires on cotton ships, and particularly to your note of the 19th of
                    February last on the subject, and to the Department’s reply thereto of the 20th
                    of May last, I now have the honor to inclose for your information a copy of a
                    letter of the 13th instant, from the Acting Secretary of the Treasury,
                    transmitting a supplementary report on the subject from the president of the New
                    Orleans Cotton Exchange.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Richard Olney.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 441.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Curtis</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Olney</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Treasury Department,<lb/>Office of the
                                    Secretary</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington, D. C.</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-07-13">
                                <hi rend="italic">July 13, 1896</hi>
                            </date>. (Received July 14.)</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Further replying to your letter of May 1,
                        inclosing copy of a note from the British ambassador, accompanied by a note
                        from Mr. Isaac Knott, of the Prince Line of steamers, I have the honor to
                        transmit herewith copy of a supplementary report from the president of the
                        New Orleans Cotton Exchange, referred to in my letter of May 23, with
                        transmitting letter from the collector of the port.</p>
                    <p>Attention is particularly invited to the following statement of the acting
                        president of the Cotton Exchange: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>If ship’s officers maintain sufficient watchfulness, danger from
                                contents of the men’s ordinary clothing may easily he averted. In
                                short, proper instructions to officers by owners would, if obeyed,
                                obviate cause of complaint.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Respectfully, yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">W. E. Curtis</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Acting Secretary.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure 1 in No. 441.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wilkinson</persName> to the
                                <gloss type="to">Commissioner of Navigation</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Port of New Orleans, La.</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-07-11">
                                <hi rend="italic">July 11, 1896.</hi>
                            </date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In the matter of incendiary fires on cotton
                        ships, referred to in your letter (14388–N) of May 5, 1896, a partial report
                        in relation to which was forwarded May 20. I have now the honor to transmit
                        a letter just received from the acting president of the New Orleans Cotton
                        Exchange, inclosing a report from the principal of the harbor protection
                        police. These communications, with the one previously forwarded will, I
                        think, cover fully the information requested by the Department to enable it
                        to make a reply to the State Department.</p>
                    <p>No violations of section 4472, Revised Statutes, and section 8 of the
                        “passenger act of 1882,” have yet been reported to the United States
                        attorney for prosecution. The two cases cited by the British ambassador at
                        Washington were of vessels which carried freight exclusively, and which were
                        therefore not amenable to the provisions of the passenger act.</p>
                    <p>Respectfully, yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Theo S. Wilkinson</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Collector.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0409" n="315" xml:id="pg_315"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure 2 in No. 441.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss type="from">Acting President New Orleans Cotton Exchange</gloss>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Wilkinson</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">New Orleans Cotton Exchange</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">New Orleans</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-07-10">
                                <hi rend="italic">July 10, 1896</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: I beg to return correspondence,
                        including your letter of May 15 and those of the United States Commissioner
                        of Navigation, the Secretary of State, the British ambassador at Washington,
                        and Mr. James Knott of the Prince Line of steamers, all relative to fires on
                        cotton ships which have sailed from this port. The occurrences especially
                        alluded to in the above letters are those which occurred on the <hi
                            rend="italic">Egyptian Prince</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Tuscan
                            Prince</hi> of the Prince Line of steamers.</p>
                    <p>Inclosed report from Thomas N. Boylan, principal of the harbor protection
                        police of this port, addressed to Secretary Hester of this exchange, gives
                        result of investigation into the matters in question and disposes of the
                        charge of “infamous practices” preferred in Mr. Knott’s letter to the
                        Marquis of Salisbury. As stated by Principal Boylan, there was nothing in
                        either occurrence to indicate incendiarism, the responsibility for the
                        matches and cartridges being attributable to carelessness on the part of the
                        workmen.</p>
                    <p>On the 5th of February, 1895, President Stewart of this exchange wrote you at
                        length in relation to cotton fires on shipboard, showing what this exchange
                        was doing toward protection of cotton controlled by its members and making
                        certain statements and suggestions to which you are respectfully
                        referred.</p>
                    <p>The present correspondence, however, refers to a different branch of the
                        subject and one which could and should be under the control of the
                        shipowners themselves.</p>
                    <p>The local authorities and this exchange can protect cotton on the landing,
                        but after it is placed on board ship the control is vested in the ship’s
                        officers only.</p>
                    <p>It is the custom of the workmen to change their clothes when they go on
                        board, and I am informed that their working garb contains no pockets. Their
                        ordinary apparel is wrapped up and laid aside, to be again assumed when they
                        leave the vessel. Smoking is prohibited by law on the landing, and should
                        be, if it is not, prevented on board by the ship’s officers.</p>
                    <p>There is, therefore, no need for the men to carry matches or to have any
                        explosive material about their persons when at work.</p>
                    <p>If ship’s officers maintain sufficient watchfulness, danger from contents of
                        the men’s ordinary clothing may easily be averted. In short, proper
                        instructions to officers by owners would, if obeyed, obviate cause of
                        complaint.</p>
                    <p>It would seem from the correspondence that the occurrences complained of are
                        attributed to New Orleans only. If such is the intention, it is manifestly
                        unjust, as I am informed that finding matches in cargoes is a common
                        occurrence with vessels bringing cargo to this port, with this
                        difference—that, if I am not mistaken, it is not usual to attribute criminal
                        intent to the carelessness of European laborers who do the work of loading
                        vessels bound for America.</p>
                    <p>Trusting that the foregoing may prove satisfactory, I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Brittin</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Acting President New Orleans Cotton Exchange.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure 3 in No. 441.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Boylan</persName> to the <gloss
                                type="to">New Orleans Cotton Exchange</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Boylan’s Detective Agency</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">New Orleans</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-06-05">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 5, 1896</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: In conformity with your request for data
                        in relation to the fire on steamship <hi rend="italic">Egyptian Prince</hi>
                        and the finding of matches and pin-fire cartridges among cotton of the
                        steamship <hi rend="italic">Tuscan Prince</hi> on arrival at Genoa, I beg to
                        say that when I became aware through the public prints of the above about
                        the 5th ultimo, I caused inquiries to be made by my captain in charge of the
                        harbor protection force, who reported as follows:</p>
                    <p rend="right">“<hi rend="smallcaps">New Orleans</hi>, <hi rend="italic">May 5,
                            1896.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">T. N. Boylan</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Principal Boylan’s
                            Protection Police.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In to-day’s issue of New Orleans Picayune
                        there is published a dispatch from Washington to the effect that the
                        collector of the port of New Orleans has been instructed to make an
                        investigation of the cause of fires on ships loaded with cotton, <pb
                            facs="0410" n="316" xml:id="pg_316"/> and that the attention of the
                        United States Government had been called by the British Government to a
                        complaint made by Mr. James Knott, the owner of the Prince line of steamers,
                        to a fire that occurred in the cotton on board of steamship <hi
                            rend="italic">Egyptian Prince</hi>, and also to the fact that a box of
                        matches and some pin-fire cartridges were found in cotton on board of
                        steamship <hi rend="italic">Tuscan Prince</hi>, and both vessels were loaded
                        at New Orleans.</p>
                    <p>“The steamship <hi rend="italic">Egyptian Prince</hi> arrived in New Orleans
                        on November 13, 1895, and loaded cotton at Meletta &amp; Stoddart’s wharf at
                        head of Third street, and left port on November 24, 1895, and while at sea,
                        about seven days from Gibraltar, fire was discovered in the cotton in fore
                        part of the vessel, and when the vessel arrived at Gibraltar it was found
                        that there were no conveniences there to unload the cargo. A survey was held
                        and the vessel ordered to proceed to Genoa, and hatches were kept battened
                        down to prevent ventilation and keep the fire from spreading; and it was
                        kept under control until the vessel arrived at Genoa, and the cargo was then
                        taken out of the ship.</p>
                    <p>“The steamship <hi rend="italic">Tuscan Prince</hi> arrived in port on
                        December 2, 1895, and sailed on December 17, 1895, and loaded at Meletta
                        &amp; Stoddart’s wharf at head of Third street, and left port on December
                        17, 1895. Mr. A. Rhody, levee clerk for Meletta &amp; Stoddart, informs me
                        that when the vessel was discharging cargo in Genoa there was found in lower
                        hold of main hatch a box of matches and some pin-fire cartridges spread
                        between two bales of cotton, and that they had evidently been placed there
                        when the vessel was being loaded at New Orleans.</p>
                    <p>“The <hi rend="italic">Egyptian Prince</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tuscan
                            Prince</hi> were consigned to Messrs. Meletta &amp; Stoddart, and were
                        loaded by colored screwmen, and A. Besart (colored) was the stevedore for
                        both vessels.</p>
                    <p>“Very respectfully,</p>
                    <p rend="right">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Jas. P. McArdle</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Captain.</hi>”</p>
                    <p>I beg on this subject to call your attention to the following facts: <list>
                            <item>First. This force had no day watchmen on these particular cargoes,
                                the watchmen being on duty from 6 p.m. to 6 a.m. on deck and on
                                wharf after the laborers had knocked off for the day.</item>
                            <item>Second. The only time that watchmen of harbor protection force are
                                on duty in the daytime is on Sundays, when there is no work going
                                on, and then their service is confined to the cargo on wharf.</item>
                            <item>Third. The supervision of cotton on the wharves in the daytime is
                                under the immediate control of the supervisors of the Cotton
                                Exchange.</item>
                            <item>Fourth. When loading, the hold of a vessel is under complete
                                control of the stevedore, who, with his assistants, direct the
                                movements of the laborers. No strangers can, without detection,
                                intrude among the workmen.</item>
                            <item>Fifth. Both of the vessels alluded to were loaded by negro labor.
                                In view of the previous ill feeling existing between the white and
                                colored screwmen, it is not improbable that many of the negroes are
                                still carrying pistols and cartridges (and more than likely were at
                                the time the <hi rend="italic">Tuscan Prince</hi> was loaded) as a
                                matter of self-protection, and the cartridges might have come from
                                one of said colored laborers.</item>
                            <item>Sixth. While no workman smokes when at work in a ship’s hold or
                                handling cotton on wharves, it is a known fact that more or less
                                they smoke and carry loose matches about their persons; such is the
                                case with almost all labor, and the finding of matches among cotton
                                is no uncommon occurrence.</item>
                            <item>Seventh. There is nothing to indicate incendiarism. The
                                responsibility for the matches and cartridges I attribute to
                                carelessness on the part of the workmen. One of them may have laid
                                his pistol, cartridges, and matches on a bale of cotton when
                                changing clothes at knocking-off time, and taken his pistol,
                                forgetting the cartridges and matches. They should, through their
                                foreman and stevedore, be submitted to supervision, for as it is
                                now, beyond your levee supervisors there is no one to oversee or
                                enforce the ordinances among the cotton shipping in the daytime,
                                though in years past, from December, 1880, to June, 1883, three
                                officers of this force were detailed, by direction of committee on
                                protection to shipping, for day duty along river front; and later,
                                from November, 1887, to 1895, the National Board of Maritime
                                Underwriters engaged during the season from October to April two
                                officers of this force to see that all city ordinances were complied
                                with during the day. No such service was per formed last winter. It
                                is only at the locations where the officers of this force are on
                                duty that the ordinances are enforced.</item>
                            <item>Eighth. As to fires on shipboard, I beg to say that my firm belief
                                is that many of said fires are caused by the friction of steel bands
                                while the vessel is at sea. It is to my knowledge that when bales
                                hoisted in a sling have struck the iron combing of a ship’s hatch
                                that sparks were generated and the cotton set on fire, and in some
                                instances quite serious loss ensued, which can be verified by my
                                reports to the committee on protection to shipping of the cotton
                                exchange.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Respectfully submitted, etc,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Thos. N. Boylan</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Principal.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
