<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Lincoln to Mr. Blaine.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1896</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d252</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">252</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1890-04-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1890-04-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038411"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diseases</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recUxK0PiRCnqTXts" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000044"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Farming</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1890-04-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1890-04-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="252"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d252">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Lincoln</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1890-04-05">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 5, 1890</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 208.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to your instruction No. 201, of
                    March 4, ultimo, in relation to the operation of the British contagious diseases
                    (animals) acts upon the importation into Great Britain of cattle and sheep from
                    the United States, I have the honor to acquaint you that, having considered the
                    subject, it seemed to me advisable, before presenting it formally to the Marquis
                    of Salisbury, to have an informal conversation with Mr. Chaplin, the member of
                    the cabinet who, as president of the board of agriculture, is charged with the
                    administration of the above-mentioned acts. Accordingly, on Wednesday the 26th
                    ultimo, at a personal interview with Lord Salisbury, in which I merely
                    introduced the subject, it met with his lordship’s immediate concurrence that I
                    should arrange an interview with Mr. Chaplin, which it was thought might
                    facilitate my subsequent correspondence on the subject with the foreign
                    office.</p>
                <p>In pursuance of an appointment, I thereupon called upon Mr. Chaplin on the 1st
                    instant, there being present with him Mr. Brown, the professional officer of the
                    board. As our interview was nearly an hour in length, I will not undertake to
                    give more than its substance. I soon perceived that there was little if any
                    ground for hoping for a change of Mr. Chaplin’s views that the reported cases of
                    pleura-pneumonia in American cattle were all of the contagious type.</p>
                <p>Mr. Brown expressed no doubt of the possibility of these cases being clearly
                    distinguished from the noncontagious inflammation, and said that in slaughtering
                    many of the noncontagious class of cases were discovered, but no account was
                    made of them, the only published cases being those decided to be contagious.
                    Upon my suggestion that the cases for 1888 and 1889 were in each year only about
                    1 in 6,000 of the cattle imported, indicating the absence of contagion on
                    shipboard, the <pb facs="0414" n="320" xml:id="pg_320"/> reply was, first, that
                    the cattle thrown overboard at sea, of which they had no report beyond their
                    number, might have died from such contagion; and, second, that their experience
                    showed the disease to be a lurking trouble, which might not cause contagion
                    within the time of a voyage, and possibly for months; and that the absence of
                    contagion on shipboard, therefore, was not considered important as a test. The
                    annual report of the department of agriculture for 1889 was presented in
                    Parliament on the 31st ultimo, and will not be in print before the end of this
                    month, but Mr. Chaplin referred to the fact that it shows 47 contagious cases
                    from the United States in 1889, and added that 4 cases had been reported for
                    1890 (I have since learned of 2 more cases just reported). He said thereupon
                    that, having in view the large sum he was asking for with which to stamp out the
                    disease here, he could not, in the face of such reports, see his way to a
                    relaxation of the present restrictions on our cattle.</p>
                <p>Upon my mentioning the ten days’ limitation for slaughter as tending to force
                    sales, it was said, as I understood, that that time is a reduction from a former
                    fourteen days’ period, made at the wish of a large number of consignees of
                    cattle; that in fact most of the cattle are slaughtered well within the limit;
                    and that it was believed that an extension of the period would not affect the
                    market, which is regulated only by the demand for consumption; and that it would
                    require an enlargement of the cattle wharves, which are sometimes so choked,
                    especially at Liverpool, that arriving vessels can not discharge their cargoes
                    for several days. This was suggested as an indication that any benefit to the
                    seller expected from a mere extension of the time for slaughter would be
                    overcome by the competition of new arrivals.</p>
                <p>Of course what I have already mentioned as Mr. Chaplin’s views in relation to the
                    relaxation of the present restrictions upon cattle would influence him against
                    yielding to a British pressure for the free importation of store cattle; but
                    beyond that he, in a passing remark, indicated his belief that the desire in
                    Great Britain for the free importation of cattle from the United States for
                    fattening is entertained by very few; and that if the subject were mooted there
                    would be great remonstrance from the farming community generally. It is clear
                    that upon his present information he would not believe in the soundness of an
                    argument for the free importation of store cattle based on the desire for it
                    being popular here.</p>
                <p>I do not believe I am in error in thinking that, aside from any consideration of
                    protecting the home cattle market (which it may be improper to suspect as having
                    influence), the anxiety in respect to pleuro-pneumonia in cattle, existing both
                    in the board of agriculture and in the House of Commons, is so great as to
                    prevent “free” importation of cattle from the United States until after cases in
                    our cargoes determined here to be contagious are no longer to be found.</p>
                <p>I inclose a clipping from the Parliamentary proceedings of the 1st instant, upon
                    the second reading of the new bill for stamping out the disease among cattle in
                    Great Britain, involving a large expenditure from the treasury, estimated at
                    £140,000 per annum, from wbich it will be seen that the opposition cordially
                    support the Government in the matter. As the case of the Netherlands is therein
                    specially mentioned, it is interesting to note the application of the British
                    acts to the cattle from that country, as shown in the report for 1888. The
                    annual importation for 1875 and 1876 was over 81,000, the cattle being “free” or
                    “not subject to slaughter.” Upon reports not before me, they were <pb
                        facs="0415" n="321" xml:id="pg_321"/> then made “subject to slaughter,” and
                    from that time the annual importation averaged about 40,000. I have not the
                    record of contagious cases before 1884, but for that year, and since, none were
                    reported in cattle from the Netherlands, though they were not put on the “free”
                    list until March 1, 1889.</p>
                <p>In respect to sheep brought from the United States, which under the present rules
                    are also required to be slaughtered within ten days after landing, the
                    conversation led me to believe that the board of agriculture does not now fear
                    contagion from our sheep, and would offer no objection to the United States
                    being put on the list of “free countries” as to those animals, if the preventive
                    laws of the United States as to the importation of sheep from countries in the
                    British list of “prohibited countries” were satisfactory, subject, however, to
                    “conditions of landing” of the character shown at page 17 of the inserted prefix
                    to the Handbook—Contagious Diseases (Animals) Acts and Orders of Council, of
                    which two copies are herewith sent. I was not prepared at the interview to make
                    any statement as to the condition of our laws on the point indicated; and as I
                    should not feel safe in reaching a conclusion from the examination I could make
                    here (remembering, as I do, such obscure methods of legislation as were taken,
                    for instance, in building up the “Signal Service” of the Army, and in the first
                    enactment allowing parties to testify in United States courts), I beg that full
                    information may be sent me.</p>
                <p>If it shall appear that the safeguards are sufficient, it seems to me that it
                    would be advisable to endeavor at once to deal with the restriction upon the
                    importation of sheep as a separate matter, and make so much of a break in the
                    wall.</p>
                <p>In the matter of the proposal to station one or more of the veterinary inspectors
                    of the Department of Agriculture of the United States at the British foreign
                    animals wharves, it was intimated to me that there would be no difficulty about
                    it, and that every facility would be given them to assist in tracing the history
                    of animals reported as affected by contagious diseases.</p>
                <p>There seems, therefore, to be nothing in the way of making at once the
                    application desired by the Secretary of Agriculture, but I suggest that it might
                    be advisable to indicate in the request the number at first thought to be
                    needed. For the years 1888 and 1889 the landings of cattle from the United
                    States were as follows: <table cols="3" rend="bordered" rows="7">
                        <row>
                            <cell>Place of landing.</cell>
                            <cell>1888.</cell>
                            <cell>1889.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Bristol</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2,910</cell>
                            <cell role="num">13,068</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Glasgow</cell>
                            <cell role="num">14,807</cell>
                            <cell role="num">33,394</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hull</cell>
                            <cell role="num">1,248</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2,855</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Liverpool</cell>
                            <cell role="num">70,727</cell>
                            <cell role="num">143,434</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>London (Deptford)</cell>
                            <cell role="num">52,492</cell>
                            <cell role="num">99,902</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Total</cell>
                            <cell role="num">142,184</cell>
                            <cell role="num">292,653</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <p>These figures perhaps indicate the propriety of stationing a chief inspector at
                    London, who would visit Bristol and Hull when necessary, and a subordinate at
                    Liverpool and another at Glasgow. I will therefore await a further instruction
                    by cable or otherwise upon this suggestion and will, upon its receipt, hope to
                    be able to make at once satisfactory arrangements on this point.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert T. Lincoln.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
