<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Coxe to Mr. Olney.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1896</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d310</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">310</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1896-10-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1896-10-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">General Assembly</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1896-10-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1896-10-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="310"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d310">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Coxe</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Olney</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,<lb/>Guatemala and
                                Honduras</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-10-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 15, 1896</hi>
                        </date>. (Received Oct. 28.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 9.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to confirm my cable sent you on
                    last Tuesday, the 13th instant, at 9.30 a.m., as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Honduras ministry of foreign affairs has been abolished and all business
                            referred to Diet at San Salvador under the treaty forwarded to the
                            Department of State July 30, 1895. I have received official notification
                            ratification of treaty. Would like instructions.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>On last Friday, the 9th instant, after the mail to the United States had closed,
                    I received a letter signed “E. Mendoza,” and addressed to me as “United States
                    minister to Honduras” (copy and translation are herewith, marked 1), inclosing a
                    paper stated to be a copy of a so-called treaty of union between the Republics
                    of Honduras, Salvador, and Nicaragua (copy and translation herewith, marked 2).
                    Mr. Pringle informs me that a copy of this treaty, when negotiated by the
                    plenipotentiaries but still unratified, was sent to the Department in Mr.
                    Pringle’s No. 199, of July 30, 1895, hence my reference to this date in my cable
                    for the purpose of identifying the treaty I referred to.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>For reasons above and below stated I desired to have advices from our own consul
                    at Tegucigalpa on the fact of the suppression of the ministry of foreign affairs
                    and reference of diplomatic business to San Salvador and accordingly, on being
                    informed of the circumstance on last Friday, I telegraphed Mr. Little for
                    information. Owing to delay in transmission I did not receive his reply till
                    Monday night. It confirmed the information I had, as above set forth. I
                    thereupon, on Tuesday morning, sent the cable hereinabove confirmed. I have as
                    yet no reply.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>There are two points in the inclosed treaty to whichI take the liberty of calling
                    your particular attention: (1) That by Article I the sovereignty proposed to be
                    exercised is stated to be “temporary;” and (2) that by Article VI this
                    sovereignty is proposed to be exercised not originally, but by delegation.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Macgrane Coxe.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0484" n="390" xml:id="pg_390"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 9.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Mendoza</persName> to <gloss
                                type="to">United States Minister to Honduras</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">San Salvador</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-09-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">September 19, 1896.</hi>
                            </date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I nave the honor to send you herewith a
                        pamphlet copy of the treaty between the Republics of Honduras, Nicaragua,
                        and Salvador, by which they have agreed to form a single political entity
                        for the exercise of their eternal sovereignty, under the name of the Greater
                        Republic of Central America, to be represented by a Diet, composed of three
                        members, chosen each year by the respective legislatures.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Jacinto Castellanos, Dr. E. Constantino Fiallos, and the undersigned have
                        received (merited) this honor at the hands of the Assemblies of Salvador,
                        Honduras, and Nicaragua, and by common consent the first of these will be
                        the president of the Diet, the undersigned secretary, and Dr. Fiallos deputy
                        secretary.</p>
                    <p>In having the honor of submitting the foregoing to your excellency’s
                        attention, it gives me pleasure to assure you that the change effected in
                        the political status of the signatory Republics will in no way affect the
                        relations which have individually existed with the nation which your
                        excellency represents with dignity; but, on the contrary, the Diet will omit
                        no means of cementing them day by day.</p>
                    <p>I embrace, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">E. Mendoza.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 9.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Treaty of union concluded between the Republics of
                            Salvador, Honduras, and Nicaragua.</hi>
                        <note n="1" xml:id="d310fn1">Translation made by Mr. Rodriguez and the
                            Department of State.</note>
                    </head>
                    <p>Their Excellencies General Rafael A. Gutiérrez, General J. Santos Zelaya, and
                        Doctor Policarpo Bonilla, Presidents of the Republics of Salvador,
                        Nicaragua, and Honduras, having met for the important purpose of reaching an
                        understanding with a view to devising means for the permanent establishment
                        of the peace of Central America, and accomplishing the project, so greatly
                        to be desired, of the reconstruction of the former body politic, immediately
                        putting into practice all that is deemed to be easy of execution, pending
                        its final accomplishment, have appointed Their Excellencies the Presidents
                        of Salvador and Nicaragua, their respective ministers of foreign relations,
                        to wit, Doctors Jacinto Castellanos and Manuel C. Matus, and His Excellency
                        the President of Honduras, his minister of public works, to wit, Doctor E.
                        Constantino Fiallos, who, after having exchanged their full powers and found
                        them to be in good and due form, have agreed upon the following
                        articles:</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article I</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Republics of Salvador, Nicaragua, and Honduras shall hereafter form a
                        single political entity, for the exercise of their sovereignty as regards
                        their intercourse with foreign nations, to be known as the Greater Republic
                        of Central America.</p>
                    <p>This name shall continue in use until the Republics of Guatemala and Costa
                        Rica shall voluntarily accept the present treaty, in which case it shall be
                        called the Republic of Central America.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article II</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The signatory Governments do not, by the present treaty, renounce their
                        autonomy and independence as regards the direction of their internal
                        affairs, and the constitution and laws of each State shall remain in force
                        so far as they are not inconsistent with the stipulations hereof.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article III</hi>.</p>
                    <p>For the execution of the provision contained in Article I, there shall be a
                        Diet, composed of one member and one substitute, elected by each of the
                        Congresses of the signatory Republics for a term of three years.</p>
                    <pb facs="0485" n="391" xml:id="pg_391"/>
                    <p>The resolutions of the Diet shall he adopted by a majority of votes, and for
                        their relations with other Governments they shall annually choose from among
                        themselves one, whose duty it shall be to serve as the medium of
                        communication.</p>
                    <p>The Diet aforesaid shall have power to adopt such regulations as may be
                        necessary for the discharge of its functions.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article IV</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The main purpose of the powers conferred upon the Diet shall be to maintain
                        the best harmony with all nations with which the signatory Republics
                        cultivate relations of friendship, and to conclude for that purpose such
                        treaties, conventions, or agreements as may be conducive to that end.</p>
                    <p>In every treaty of friendship that the Diet may conclude, it shall expressly
                        insert a clause providing that all questions that may arise shall,
                        necessarily and without exception, be settled by means of arbitration.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article V</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Until there shall be a general assembly, the ratification of treaties shall
                        be one of the duties of the Congress of each of the Republics; and all
                        treaties shall be considered duly ratified if they have been ratified by a
                        majority of the said Congresses.</p>
                    <p>In like manner, when the Diet shall have to adopt a decision affecting the
                        general interests, it shall proceed in accordance with the opinion of the
                        majority of the said Republics.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article VI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>All questions now pending, or such as may arise hereafter among the signatory
                        Republics and any other nation, shall be passed upon by the Diet in
                        accordance with the data and instructions that shall be communicated to it
                        by the Governments concerned.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article VII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>In case it shall not be possible for the Diet to settle a pending question
                        amicably, or to secure the submission thereof to arbitration, it shall
                        report the matter to all the Governments, to the end that, in conformity
                        with the decision of the majority of them, the Diet may accept or declare
                        war, as may be deemed expedient.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article VIII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>If, unfortunately, any question shall arise among the signatory Governments,
                        the Diet shall resolve itself into a court of arbitration for the purpose of
                        settling the difficulty on the basis of the evidence and arguments that
                        shall be submitted to it by the Governments concerned. If, however, any one
                        of the Governments shall not agree to the decision they shall be bound to
                        appoint, by mutual agreement, an arbitrator who shall pronounce a final
                        decision, on the sole basis of the evidence and arguments submitted, and the
                        decision of the Diet.</p>
                    <p>In case of their inability to agree as to the designation of an arbitrator,
                        one shall be designated by the Diet, being chosen from among the Presidents
                        of the other American Republics.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article IX</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Inasmuch as the principal object of this treaty is to maintain peace and the
                        strictest harmony among the contracting Republics, as the most effectual
                        means of realizing the union, their respective Governments pledge themselves
                        in the most formal and solemn manner, to fulfil the stipulations contained
                        in the foregoing article, within the terms agreed upon by the parties, or,
                        in default thereof, within those fixed by the Diet.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article X</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The power to appoint diplomatic and consular representatives of the Greater
                        Republic of Central America shall be vested in the Diet; and among its
                        functions shall be the reception and acceptance of diplomatic and consular
                        officers accredited to it.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The coat of arms and the flag of the Greater Republic of Central America
                        shall be the same as those of the old Federation.</p>
                    <pb facs="0486" n="392" xml:id="pg_392"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Diet shall sit, by turns, one year in each of the capitals of the
                        contracting Republics, the order of its sessions being decided by lot.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XIII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The salaries of the members of the Diet shall be fixed by their respective
                        Governments, and the common expense shall be divided into equal parts.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XIV.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Within three years, or sooner if possible, the Diet shall prepare a draft of
                        a plan for the definitive union of the signatory Republics in such form as
                        shall seem to it most suitable, and shall lay it before a general assembly
                        consisting of twenty members, elected by each of the Congresses of the
                        Republics aforesaid, immediately after the Diet shall have notified the
                        Governments that it has prepared the draft in question.</p>
                    <p>The assembly shall meet in the place where the Diet shall be sitting, and, at
                        least two-thirds of the members chosen being present, shall proceed to
                        business.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XV.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>This treaty shall be laid before the Governments of Guatemala and Costa Rica
                        by each of the signatory Republics, which shall urge those Governments to
                        adhere to its stipulations.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XVI.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>When this treaty shall have been ratified by the Congresses of the signatory
                        Republics, its ratifications shall be exchanged at any of the capitals one
                        month after the final ratification, it being agreed that the expiration of
                        that period does not imply the lapse of the treaty, and the exchange may,
                        consequently, take place at any time.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XVII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>When a Congress has ratified the treaty, it shall at once proceed to elect
                        the members of the Diet to whom it is entitled, so that the Diet may enter
                        upon the discharge of its duties three months, at the latest, after the
                        exchange of the ratifications.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">In testimony whereof the undersigned ministers
                            have signed this treaty and sealed it with their respective seals, in
                            triplicate, in the port of <placeName>Amapala</placeName>, on <date
                                calendar="gregorian" when="1895-06-20">the twentieth day of June, in
                                the year one thousand eight hundred and ninety-five, being the
                                seventy-fifth year of the Independence of Central
                            America</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Jacinto Castellanos.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">M. C. Matus.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">E. Constantino Fiallos.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>[Here follow the decrees of the Presidents of Salvador, Honduras, and
                            Nicaragua approving the foregoing treaty; also the instrument for the
                            exchange of the ratifications.]</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 9.—Telegram.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Coxe</persName> to Mr. <persName
                                type="to">Mendoza</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Guatemala</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-10-15">
                                <hi rend="italic">October 15, 1896</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>I have the honor to inform your excellency that my powers do not authorize
                        me, without special instructions from my Government, to enter upon official
                        relations with the authorities of a power near which I am not accredited,
                        and that for that reason, much to my regret, I shall be obliged to abstain
                        for the present from treating of diplomatic affairs with the officers of the
                        Greater Republic of Central America.</p>
                    <p>With great consideration,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Macgrane Coxe.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0487" n="393" xml:id="pg_393"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 9.—Telegram.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Coxe</persName> to <gloss
                                type="to">Minister for Foreign Affairs</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,<lb/>Guatemala
                                    and Honduras</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-10-15">
                                <hi rend="italic">October 15, 1896</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>I hasten to advise the illustrious Government of your Republic that I have
                        just sent the following telegram to His Excellency Don Eugenio Mendoza at
                        San Salvador:</p>
                    <p>“I have the honor to inform your excellency that my powers do not authorize
                        me, without special instructions from my Government, to enter upon official
                        relations with the authorities of a power near which I am not accredited,
                        and that for that reason, much to my regret, I shall be obliged to abstain
                        for the present from treating of diplomatic affairs with the officers of the
                        Greater Republic of Central America.”</p>
                    <p>With great consideration,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Macgrane Coxe.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
