<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1896-05-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1896-05-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="427" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d427">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Olney</persName> to
                                    <persName type="to">Baron von Thielmann</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-05-06"><hi rend="italic">May 6,
                                1896</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 149.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to apprise you of
                            the receipt of a dispatch from the vice-consul at Apia, No. 105, of
                            March 23, 1896, treating of municipal affairs in Samoa, and stating
                            that, owing to the disapproval by the chief justice of the resolution of
                            the municipal council accepting the resignation of four councilors (it
                            not having been unanimously approved by the consular board, the German
                            counsel dissenting), the business of the municipality had practically
                            been at a standstill. It appears that the four members who had tendered
                            their resignations absolutely refused to attend any more meetings, and
                            the action of the chief justice made it impossible to call a new
                            election. Mr. Blacklock accordingly shows that such a condition of
                            affairs could not long continue, and says that it was suggested by the
                            British consul that the three consuls call upon the chief justice for
                            the purpose of talking over the situation and seeing whether some plan
                            could not be devised by which a new election might be held, and the
                            situation thus relieved. Mr. Blacklock accepted the suggestion, provided
                            it proved satisfactory to Mr. Geissler, German vice-consul, then in
                            charge of the consulate. Accordingly he was called upon. At first Mr.
                            Geissler seemed averse to anything of a conciliatory nature. He thought
                            the municipal councilors could be and should be forced to attend council
                            meetings; that they had no right to resign, and that they should be
                            punished for daring to attempt such a thing. The British consul and Mr.
                            Blacklock viewed the whole subject in a different light, and after
                            considerable persuasion Mr. Geissler agreed that they—the three
                            consuls—should call upon the chief justice for the purpose stated.</p>
                        <p>The question of inviting Mr. Schmidt, president of the municipal council,
                            to be present came up for discussion. It was decided, however, that he
                            should not be asked, but that the consular body should privately consult
                            with the chief justice. In case he decided to appoint another meeting,
                            at which Mr. Schmidt might be invited, there would be no objection.</p>
                        <p>It was left with Mr. Geissler to notify Mr. Ide of the desire of the
                            consular body, and on March 13, 1896, Mr. Blacklock received a note from
                            the chief justice inviting him to a conference at the latter’s residence
                            in the afternoon of that date.</p>
                        <p>Subsequently, Mr. Geissler explained that he had seen President Schmidt,
                            who insisted upon being present at the interview, and whom, according to
                            a letter of March 13 last from Mr. Geissler, he had invited to be
                            present at the interview of that afternoon.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Blacklock, not having time to make a different arrangement with his
                            colleagues, declined to attend the meeting, and the same day so advised
                            Mr. Ide and the British and German consular representatives in
                            writing.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Geissler orally expressed regret for his action to Mr. Blacklock, and
                            promised never to repeat it. The British consul replied by letter <pb facs="0630" n="536" xml:id="pg_536"/> dated March 20, 1896. While he
                            had personally, he said, no objection to Mr. Schmidt’s presence, in case
                            the invitation had come from the entire body, yet he recognized the
                            previous decision of his colleagues as binding, and the difficulties
                            that must arise if, “after the consular body has deliberately come to
                            one decision, one of its members, unknown to the others, takes action,
                            apparently on behalf of the united consular board, on which his
                            colleagues have no opportunity of expressing an opinion until too late.”
                            He expressed his gratification that Mr. Geissler agreed with the opinion
                            of his two associates and “will not in the future invite persons to our
                            meetings unknown to us, because it is so important that we consuls
                            should work together with that complete harmony and cordiality which,
                            with scarcely an interruption and despite the many changes in the
                            consular representatives, has been maintained ever since the Berlin
                            treaty came into operation in Samoa.”</p>
                        <p>The meeting, however, took place on March 13, 1896, but Mr. Blacklock did
                            not attend. It was mutually understood, however, that if the three
                            councilors who had already tendered their resignations would attend one
                            meeting of the council, to enable the German member, who was going away,
                            to have his resignation accepted, and then renew their resignation, all
                            five would be accepted and a new election called.</p>
                        <p>This arrangement was carried out and a new election provided for.</p>
                        <p>The council concerned consisted of three German subjects, three British,
                            and the president, Mr. Schmidt, who invariably casts his vote with his
                            countrymen.</p>
                        <p>At the last meeting of this council an incident occurred which seems to
                            demand more than a passing notice, and which, if permitted to pass
                            unchallenged, may form a dangerous precedent for the future.</p>
                        <p>It appears that a report in German, and unaccompanied by a translation,
                            was presented to the meeting and was passed by the German members and
                            the president, who slightingly regarded the request of one of the
                            British members that the vote be postponed until he could understand the
                            nature of the report.</p>
                        <p>This report came up before the consular board as it had passed the
                            council, without a translation, and the three consuls were unanimous in
                            deferring consideration thereof until a translation could be
                            obtained.</p>
                        <p>The report was accordingly returned to President Schmidt, who sent it
                            back to the consular board without the desired translation, with a
                            letter stating that he had no officer at his disposal who was able to
                            make the required translation, and that he did not feel justified in
                            engaging an extra official for the purpose.</p>
                        <p>Several days after Mr. Schmidt’s letter, Mr. Geissler, in a communication
                            to his British and American colleagues of March 20, 1896, requested them
                            to meet and consider the report, which he offered to orally explain. His
                            suggestion was not accepted by either Mr. Cusack-Smith or Mr. Blacklock,
                            who replied that he was unable to perceive why the consular board should
                            be forced to resort to such a procedure, and that the whole subject
                            would be referred to his Government. Mr. Geissler protested against this
                            course, but to no avail.</p>
                        <p>The Department perceives nothing in Mr. Blacklock’s action to disprove;
                            and, in making this long statement—for I doubt not all the facts have
                            been laid before His Majesty’s Government—I do so only to show that much
                            of the friction in the Samoan Islands is produced through an attempted
                            arbitrary and unnecessary course adopted by the president of the
                            municipal council, aided by his countrymen. This could be obviated by a
                            course of conduct more considerate, more conciliatory, and more in
                            harmony with the true relations of the several parties concerned. <pb facs="0631" n="537" xml:id="pg_537"/> They are equal in right if not
                            in interest, and it is a grave error to assume to proceed as if the
                            administration of Samoa were virtually and exclusively German, or as if
                            a sort of silent concurrence in all German propositions for the sake of
                            harmony and peace should be the chief function of British and United
                            States representation.</p>
                        <p>I can not conceive that His Majesty’s Government will view the treaty
                            rights of Great Britain or the United States in any such unfavorable
                            light. I accordingly anticipate that such instructions as His Majesty
                            may think the situation demands, with a view to conciliatory and proper
                            action in all such cases in the future, may be addressed to the Imperial
                            consul at Apia.</p>
                        <p>I may remark in conclusion that while the German report herein referred
                            to may not be and in fact, as I understand, is not especially important
                            per se, yet the incident appeared to be one that should be presented for
                            the consideration of His Majesty’s Government, to the end that it might
                            not pass as an unchallenged precedent for the future.</p>
                        <p>I shall give a copy of this note to the British ambassador for the
                            information of Her Majesty’s Government and to Mr. Blacklock for the
                            files of the consulate-general at Apia.</p>
                        <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Richard Olney.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>