<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Tripp to Mr. Olney.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1896</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d5</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">5</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1896-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1896-10-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028935"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Offenses</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recewAfM2kfM3rKFJ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113347"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Retirement</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1896-10-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1896-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="5"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d5">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Tripp</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Olney</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-10-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 1, 1896</hi>
                        </date>. (Received Oct. 16.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 208.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report herewith the very
                    interesting case of Ladislao Sedivy, which has been pending for some time and is
                    just now very favorably concluded.</p>
                <p>The case, as you will observe, involved the delicate question of how far the
                    Austrian Government had the right to punish as a deserter a returning American
                    citizen of Austrian birth who had performed his active military service before
                    emigration, but who was at the time of emigration upon the reserve list and
                    liable to call into active service at any time. It has been contended by the
                    military authorities of Austria-Hungary that all members of the reserve corps
                    are absent from the army on furlough merely, and that any willful absence from
                    the country, including emigration, so that they be unable to respond to any call
                    for active service, makes them deserters so that they can be punished as such;
                    and the minister of foreign affairs, in my first conversation with him, was
                    himself inclined to take this view of the question. As the same question had
                    already arisen in a number of cases, and was liable to frequently arise, owing
                    to the very great number of Austro-Hungarian citizens who have emigrated to
                    America after having performed their active military duty and while their names
                    yet remained on the reserve list, I determined to make this a test case, with
                    the result, as you will observe, that the foreign office here has tardily
                    conceded the position I have taken in the matter, to wit, that a returning
                    American citizen of Austro-Hungarian birth can not be punished for a crime
                    committed by act of emigration, but only for an offense committed before
                    emigration, and that in all cases when the member of the reserve corps emigrated
                    before receiving a call into active service he was guilty of no crime against
                    the military laws of Austria-Hungary, and was not subject to arrest upon his
                    return, nor to punishment as a deserter; that the crime for which the Austrian
                    courts got jurisdiction of the returning citizen was a failure to obey the
                    summons served upon him before emigration. This position is now, as will be
                    observed, conceded, and the military court was directed to confine its inquiries
                    to the question whether Ladislao Sedivy did or did not receive summons calling
                    him into active service before his emigration; and the court having found that
                    he did not, he was accordingly discharged.</p>
                <p>The case is a valuable one as a precedent, and determines a number of cases
                    already pending before the legation.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bartlett Tripp.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 208.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Tripp</persName> to Count
                                <persName type="to">Goluchowsky</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-12-30">
                                <hi rend="italic">December 30, 1895</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: Complaint has been made to this
                        legation by Ladislao Sedivy, a naturalized citizen of the United States,
                        that he has been arrested in Josefstadt, has been enrolled in the
                        seventy-fourth <pb facs="0101" n="7" xml:id="pg_7"/> regiment of infantry,
                        tenth company, and is now held for military duty at that place.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Sedivy sends to the legation his certificate of naturalization, a copy of
                        which is herewith submitted for consideration, which is in proper form, and
                        from which it appears that L. Sedivy was duly naturalized a citizen of the
                        United States before the county court of Jefferson County, in the State of
                        Kentucky, on October 5, 1892.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Sedivy also sends to this legation his passport, No. 4089, which was in
                        due form, issued to him on the 25th day of September, 1895, by the Secretary
                        of State, at Washington, a copy of which is also submitted herewith.</p>
                    <p>Your excellency will agree with me that under no circumstances can Mr.
                        Sedivy, as a naturalized citizen of the United States, be held liable to
                        such military duty under the treaty existing between Austria-Hungary and the
                        United States, and I trust that your excellency will see that the necessary
                        orders are immediately issued for his release and for the cancellation of
                        his enrollment in the army of Austria-Hungary.</p>
                    <p>Thanking your excellency for the prompt and efficient action which has always
                        characterized the conduct of the ministry of foreign affairs in the matter
                        of complaints made by citizens of my country, permit me to take this
                        occasion to renew, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bartlett Tripp.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 208.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Tripp</persName> to Count
                                <persName type="to">Goluchowsky</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-02-07">
                                <hi rend="italic">February 7, 1896</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: On the 30th of December last, by
                        my note numbered 117, I called the attention of your excellency to the case
                        of Ladislao Sedivy, a naturalized American citizen, who, as I was then
                        informed, had been arrested at Josefstadt, in Bohemia, in which note I set
                        forth the facts of the arrest and detention so far as they were then known
                        at this legation, and accompanied my note with a copy of the certificate of
                        naturalization of Mr. Sedivy and of his passport, both of which were in the
                        possession of this legation, and asked for the immediate interposition of
                        the imperial and royal ministry of foreign affairs of Austria-Hungary in
                        behalf of Mr. Sedivy and for his immediate discharge from arrest and
                        imprisonment, if the facts were found in accordance with the statements
                        contained in my note and the complaint made to this legation.</p>
                    <p>I further took occasion to visit your excellency in person and to personally
                        call attention to this case, and to ask to be favored at the earliest moment
                        with a copy of the charges made against this man, and to be informed of the
                        cause of his arrest and detention. I have, however, received no reply from
                        your excellency nor from any official source, but am privately informed that
                        during the time which I had been seeking to intervene in behalf of Mr.
                        Sedivy he has been tried by some tribunal and sentenced to a month’s
                        imprisonment for some crime alleged to have been committed before his
                        emigration.</p>
                    <p>I am sure that some mistake must exist in reference to this matter, and I am
                        quite unwilling to believe that after my intervention Mr. Sedivy would have
                        been tried and condemned and sent to prison in execution of sentence without
                        some notification to me of such purpose <pb facs="0102" n="8" xml:id="pg_8"
                        /> and intention on the part of the Government of Austria-Hungary. I am,
                        therefore, constrained, in view of the apparent reliability of the
                        information in reference to the sentence and imprisonment of Mr. Sedivy, and
                        having ever in mind the continued courtesy with which all my applications
                        have uniformly been received and treated by your excellency, to ask the
                        earliest possible attention of the ministry of foreign affairs to this
                        matter, to the end that a speedy determination of this case may be had and
                        that Mr. Sedivy, who is reported to me to be in poor health and who has been
                        already over two months in prison, may be at once released, and if it be
                        true that he has been tried and condemned without notice and pending the
                        intervention of this legation, that I be favored at once with a copy of the
                        minutes of the procedure, the evidence presented, together with the findings
                        and judgment of the court.</p>
                    <p>Regretting the necessity which obliges me to again call the attention of your
                        excellency to this case, I avail, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bartlett Tripp.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 208.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Count <persName type="from">Welsersheimb</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Tripp</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Vienna</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-02-12">
                                <hi rend="italic">February 12, 1896</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: As a temporary reply to the esteemed note of
                        the 7th of February, No. 121, the ministry of foreign affairs has the honor
                        to inform the honorable minister of the United States that the
                        investigations made by the ministry of foreign affairs on receipt of the
                        note of December 30, 1895, No. 117, relative to the arrest of the
                        naturalized American citizen, Ladislao Sedivy, and the reasons for such
                        proceeding, have not yet been fully brought to a close.</p>
                    <p>Inasmuch, however, as it has been learned from the information so far
                        received that Ladislao Sedivy has been held to answer a charge for a
                        criminal act committed by him and provided for in Article II of the treaty
                        of September 20, 1870, justifying the authorities of his native home to
                        proceed against him, even if in the meantime he has legally acquired
                        American citizenship, the undersigned, pending further investigations, will
                        make known the result to the honorable minister of the United States as soon
                        as the same has been communicated, and he avails himself, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Welsersheimb</hi>, <hi rend="italic">For the
                                Minister.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 208.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Tripp</persName> to Count
                                <persName type="to">Goluchowsky</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-02-15">
                                <hi rend="italic">February 15, 1896</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge
                        the receipt of the very kind and polite note of date February 12, 1896, from
                        the ministry of foreign affairs in reference to the case of Ladislao Sedivy,
                        and I thank your excellency very much for the attention and consideration
                        which my former note, No. 121, of February 7, 1896, has received, but I note
                        with some feeling of surprise a confirmation of the fact unofficially
                        communicated to this legation that the local authorities at Josefstadt have
                        taken jurisdiction of the offense alleged to have been <pb facs="0103" n="9"
                            xml:id="pg_9"/> committed by Mr. Sedivy against the laws of
                        Austria-Hungary under the treaty of September 20, 1870, and have assumed to
                        try and convict him of an offense apparently committed by and not before his
                        emigration.</p>
                    <p>I shall await with anxious interest the result of the investigation, which I
                        am informed by your excellency’s kind note has been instigated by the
                        ministry of foreign affairs, for, it would seem to me, there can be little
                        room for doubt or question that the treaty of 1870 does not and can not
                        contemplate a case in which the returning naturalized American citizen, a
                        former Austrian subject, can be punished for an offense committed by the act
                        of emigration. Such a construction would defeat the very purpose of the
                        treaty itself. It would in effect destroy the right of expatriation
                        expressly granted in Article I of the same compact, for, unless the
                        emigrating citizen may have the privilege of returning again to his native
                        country, his emigration becomes an exile, and to his certificate of
                        naturalization granted by his adopted country there is appended, by such
                        construction, a decree of perpetual banishment. Such a construction of this
                        convention is not worth consideration in the absence of any claim previously
                        made that its language will admit of such perversion.</p>
                    <p>Article II of this treaty is entirely consonant with and not in contravention
                        of the clear enunciation of the right of expatriation of the citizens of
                        either country provided for in Article I.</p>
                    <p>It is a grant of additional rights, not a limitation of the rights already
                        granted.</p>
                    <p>It provides for the cases in which the naturalized citizen of either country,
                        returning to his native country, may be punished for offenses previously
                        committed, but expressly reserving to him all laws of limitation and
                        remission from liability to punishment, and expressio unius est exclusio
                        alterius, for, when the treaty-making powers have chosen to agree upon what
                        particular crimes or in what particular cases punishment shall be inflicted
                        upon former citizens of either country, they necessarily by such enumeration
                        exclude all others not therein enumerated.</p>
                    <p>When, therefore, the high contracting parties here chose to say that the
                        Governments of Austria-Hungary and the United States should have the power
                        to punish the returning native subject for offenses committed before his
                        emigration, they said in equally plain language they shall not have the
                        power to punish him for offenses committed by the act of emigration.</p>
                    <p>This is believed to be too plainly and admittedly the construction of this
                        not unusual language of treaties to demand any elaboration, and it must be
                        contended by this legation that this construction is not weakened and made
                        in any way doubtful by the succeeding clause, which provides: <quote
                            rend="blockquote">
                            <p>In particular, a former citizen of the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy, who
                                under the first article is to be held as an American citizen, is
                                liable to trial and punishment, according to the laws of
                                Austria-Hungary, for nonfulfillment of military duty: <list>
                                    <item>First. If he has emigrated, after having been drafted at
                                        the time of conscription, and thus having become enrolled as
                                        a recruit for service in the standing army.</item>
                                    <item>Second. If he has emigrated while he stood in service
                                        under the flag, or had a leave of absence for an unlimited
                                        time, or belonging to the reserve or to the militia, he has
                                        emigrated after having received a call into service, or
                                        after a public proclamation requiring his appearance, or
                                        after war has broken out.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>There is no apparent purpose on the part of the high contracting parties
                        thereby to limit what has already been made the subject of the two important
                        articles agreed upon, but the introductory words of the additional clause,
                        “In particular,” indicate the clear intention of thereby explaining and not
                        of limiting their plain signification.</p>
                    <pb facs="0104" n="10" xml:id="pg_10"/>
                    <p>The plainest legal rules of construction, therefore, require that these
                        subsequent provisions must, if possible, be construed in consonance with and
                        not in contravention of the preceding general provisions to which they are
                        attached.</p>
                    <p>Bearing this rule of construction in mind, we are at once led to the
                        conclusion that Austria-Hungary, as one of these great contracting powers,
                        did not wish to leave to future doubtful construction the fact that certain
                        military crimes were intended to be included within the general provision of
                        Article II, a construction which might not be given to the general provision
                        of Article II standing alone, and in granting this concession on the part of
                        the other contracting power it is equally evident that she was unwilling to
                        extend such right to all military crimes, and the military crimes punishable
                        under the general provisions of Article II were therefore expressly provided
                        for in the three enumerated clauses—first, second, and third—which provide
                        for three distinct classes of offenses against the military laws of
                        Austria-Hungary, and each of which must be a completed existing offense or
                        military crime before and at the time of emigration.</p>
                    <p>The first contemplates a state of war, a draft, conscription, and actual
                        enrollment of the subject; the second actual service in the army, and the
                        third a retirement from actual service, but holding the soldier still
                        subject to peremptory call and proclamation in case of actual
                        hostilities.</p>
                    <p>In all three of these cases the Government of Austria-Hungary has acquired a
                        certain jurisdiction over the person, and the subject-matter and the crime
                        against the sovereignity of the Government is complete the moment such
                        jurisdiction is lost by any willful act on the part of the subject, such as
                        leaving the service or refusing to obey the call into actual service made on
                        him before emigration.</p>
                    <p>That is to say, if the subject leaves actual service, whether in case of war
                        or peace, or if he fails to obey the call actually made upon him either
                        personally served or by proclamation in case of actual hostilities and
                        thereafter emigrates, he may be punished on his return to his native country
                        for the crime committed, not by the act of emigration, but by failure or
                        refusal to obey the call or by desertion from actual service; but such is
                        not the case when he emigrated before any call or proclamation made or
                        issued, for in such case the Government of Austria-Hungary had acquired no
                        jurisdiction over his person.</p>
                    <p>It could issue no legal call into its army against a person beyond its
                        boundaries and who had perhaps renounced his allegiance to his native
                        country, had availed himself of the right of expatriation, and declared his
                        allegiance to another government.</p>
                    <p>The treaty does not and can not contemplate such a case.</p>
                    <p>Under this construction of the treaty of 1870, the case of Mr. Sedivy could
                        not come under the first or second provision of Article II, for they both
                        provide for cases of actual service, the first in time of war and the second
                        in time of peace, and as he had completed his three years of actual service
                        and had already been two years or more on the retired list, he must come
                        within the third provision if at all, and, as I have already said, he can
                        only be guilty of an offense within the terms of this provision if call for
                        service was made upon him before emigration and while he was within the
                        jurisdiction of Austria.</p>
                    <p>I am confident that no difference of opinion will arise between your
                        excellency and myself in this construction of the provisions of this treaty,
                        which I have only briefly stated.</p>
                    <p>I am led to infer from the note of your excellency that proceedings in this
                        case have not yet been concluded. May I ask, therefore, if the facts of the
                        case be found in accordance with the statement contained <pb facs="0105"
                            n="11" xml:id="pg_11"/> in my note No. 117, of December 30, 1895, and
                        your excellency agree with me in my interpretation of the provisions of said
                        treaty under which the offense is sought to be maintained, that the
                        proceedings be at once directed to be dismissed and Mr. Sedivy be released
                        from confinement. But in case the local authorities for any reason persist
                        in maintaining jurisdiction in the case, I desire to be permitted to
                        intervene and to be advised of the proceedings already taken, the facts
                        relied upon to constitute the offense, and of the statutes and law claimed
                        to give jurisdiction over the person and subject-matter of the offense.</p>
                    <p>Permit me, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bartlett Tripp.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 5 in No. 208.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Tripp</persName> to Count
                                <persName type="to">Goluchowsky</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-02-17">
                                <hi rend="italic">February 17, 1896</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: Since forwarding to your
                        excellency my note No. 122, of date February 15, 1896, in reference to the
                        case of Ladislao Sedivy, I am in receipt of a communication from the United
                        States embassy in Berlin giving me information as to a decision recently
                        rendered by the Imperial court of appeals in Leipsic in the case of F. W.
                        Boehme, a naturalized citizen of the United States, who had been convicted
                        by the lower court for having emigrated to America without performance of
                        military duty under the laws of Germany, in which case the judgment of the
                        lower tribunal was reversed by the court of appeal and Mr. Boehme was
                        directed to be discharged.</p>
                    <p>I am further in receipt of a circular issued by the minister of justice of
                        Germany in reference to naturalized American citizens returning to Germany
                        and their rights under the treaty of February 22, 1868, between the North
                        German Confederation and the United States of America, which contains the
                        provision as to punishment of returning naturalized American citizens for
                        offenses committed before emigration, which it will be observed is almost
                        identical with the general provision of Article II of the treaty of 1870
                        between Austria-Hungary and the United States, and is as follows: <quote
                            rend="blockquote">
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 2. A naturalized citizen of the
                                one party on return to the territory of the other party remains
                                liable to trial and punishment for an action punishable by the laws
                                of his original country and committed before his emigration; saving,
                                always, the limitation established by the laws of his original
                                country.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>I am also in receipt of an instruction to judicial and executive officers
                        from the ministry of justice of Germany in reference to the preceding
                        provision of the Berlin treaty, from which I extract the following: <quote
                            rend="blockquote">
                            <p>Bei Abschluss des zwischen dem Norddeutschen Bunde und den
                                Vereinigten Staaten über die Staatsangehörigkeit der Ausgewanderten
                                verabredeten Vertrags vom 22. Februar d. J. hat die Absicht
                                vorgewaltet:</p>
                            <p>Dass durch die strafbare Auswanderung verwirkte Strafe bei einer
                                Rückkehr des Betreffenden in seine frühere Heimath in Gemässheit des
                                Artikels II jenes Vertrags nicht zur Vollstreckung gebracht werden
                                soll, wenn der Rückkehrende in dem anderen Staate das Heimathsrecht
                                in Gemässheit des Artikels I des gedachten Vertrags erworben
                                    hat.<note n="1" xml:id="d5fn1">The conclusion of the treaty of
                                    February 22 last, agreed upon by the North German Confederation
                                    and the United States concerning the nationality of emigrants,
                                    had the object: That pursuant to Article II of the treaty, the
                                    penalty incurred by a culpable emigration was not to be enforced
                                    upon the return of the party in question to his former home,
                                    when he had acquired citizenship in the other State pursuant to
                                    Article I.</note>
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0106" n="12" xml:id="pg_12"/>
                    <p>From which it will be observed that the view taken by the authorities of
                        Germany is quite in accordance with those expressed in my note, No. 122, of
                        date February 15, 1896, which this is designed to supplement.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bartlett Tripp.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 6 in No. 208.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Count <persName type="from">Welsersheimb</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Tripp</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Vienna</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-09-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">September 16, 1896</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The ministry of foreign affairs has not
                        omitted to address itself to the ministry of public defense after receipt of
                        the esteemed notes dated respectively February 15 and 17 last, numbered 122
                        and 124, in order that investigations be made concerning Ladislao Sedivy, a
                        naturalized citizen of the United States, and the charge made against him
                        for desertion, namely, whether he emigrated after having received summons to
                        report for duty, or whether this order reached him after his arrival in
                        America.</p>
                    <p>The ministry of war, which received information concerning this case from the
                        ministry of public defense, took occasion to refer the matter to the
                        superior military court, which after full investigation of all the data and
                        receipt of all the necessary information has ordered the suspension of
                        proceedings commenced against him by the garrison court at Josefstadt on the
                        29th of January, 1896, in conformity with paragraph 196, B. and G. and M. S.
                        T. O.</p>
                    <p>As seen from the statements, the investigations made by the superior court
                        clearly showed that Ladislao Sedivy, who, by the way, left for America on
                        March 16, last, emigrated before he had received any summons to report for
                        military duty, was subsequently naturalized as a citizen of the United
                        States, and is therefore, according to Article II of the treaty of September
                        20, 1870, with the United States, not liable to military duty.</p>
                    <p>While the ministry of foreign affairs brings the foregoing to the knowledge
                        of the envoy of the United States, the Hon. Bartlett Tripp, it takes
                        occasion to return herewith the inclosures contained in the note of December
                        30, 1895, No. 117, and begs to renew, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Welsersheimb</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">For the Minister of Foreign Affairs.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
