<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Lee to Mr. Rockhill.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1896</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d780</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">780</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1896-12-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1896-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="reckOJp7RF2apAIO3" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85004558"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Amnesty</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1896-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1896-12-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="780"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d780">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Lee</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Rockhill</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate-General</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Habana</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-12-31">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 31, 1896</hi>
                        </date>. (Received January 6, 1897.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 283.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Yesterday noon I visited the Cabaña fort and had
                    a talk with Mr. Julio Sanguily, an American citizen, and formerly a general in
                    the insurgent army. As you know, he was arrested in his house while taking a
                    bath on the 24th February, 1895.</p>
                <p>Sanguily had proved himself a very brave and efficient officer in the Cuban war
                    from 1868 to 1878, and had been wounded seven times. It was therefore naturally
                    supposed that sooner or later he would have <pb facs="0938" n="844"
                        xml:id="pg_844"/> joined the insurgent side of the war now in progress in
                    this island. He had, so far as I am informed, committed no overt act in that
                    direction, and was taken without arms in hand.</p>
                <p>On the 28th of November, 1895, or, say, nine months and four days after he was
                    arrested and thrown into a cell at the Cabaña fort, he was tried and sentenced
                    to be imprisoned for life. An appeal was taken to the supreme court of justice
                    at Madrid, which decreed, upon some technical ground, that Sanguily should be
                    retried.</p>
                <p>On the 21st of December, 1896, his second trial commenced, and ended by his being
                    again sentenced to perpetual imprisonment.</p>
                <p>From this second sentence an appeal has been taken which, whether successful or
                    not, will greatly lengthen the time he has already passed in his cell.</p>
                <p>The lawyer who defended this prisoner in his first trial now looks from the bar
                    of a cell adjoining his in the Cabaña fort, and I am informed that the lawyer
                    who managed his appeal before the Madrid court has suffered in consequence
                    thereof, so that it may be difficult to procure in Madrid another person versed
                    in the law who will consent to manage for Sanguily the appeal proceedings.</p>
                <p>Only a few days after the arrest of Sanguily a proclamation was issued offering
                    amnesty to all persons in arms who would give themselves up. It seems that this
                    ought to apply to persons who had been arrested without arms in hand. Two other
                    Cuban officers of distinction—Ramon Perez Trujillo and José Maria Timoteo
                    Aguirre—were arrested, I am told, at the same time as Sanguily and for the same
                    reason, namely, because it was thought that they would engage in the war. After
                    a short incarceration they were liberated.</p>
                <p>In view of all these facts, and for the additional reason that Sanguily has been
                    in a cell twenty-three months to date, is not in good health, and is suffering
                    from old wounds, I respectfully suggest that the Department bring these facts to
                    the notice of the Madrid Government and ask that instructions be issued that he
                    be released from prison on the condition that he will leave this island and not
                    return until the present war has terminated.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Fitzhugh Lee</hi>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Consul-General.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
