<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1896-04-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1896-04-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="799" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d799">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Olney</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Riddle</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-04-15"><hi rend="italic">April 15,
                                1896</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 938.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I inclose for your information copy of a
                            note with its accompaniment, received from the Turkish minister at this
                            capital, under date of April 8, purporting to communicate the protest of
                            a certain number of Armenians of Harpoot against the presence and
                            teaching of foreign missionaries in that city. I also inclose a copy of
                            my reply to Mavroyeni Bey.</p>
                        <p>As this Government is without present representation at Harpoot, it is
                            proper to instruct you to show this correspondence to the British
                            ambassador and to inquire of Sir Philip Currie whether, in order to
                            carry out the desire of this Government, the good offices of the British
                            vice-consul at Harpoot can be taken advantage of to ascertain the
                            foundation for these extraordinary and, it is firmly believed,
                            calumnious charges so far as they may affect citizens of the United
                            States <pb facs="0950" n="856" xml:id="pg_856"/> engaged in missionary
                            work and teaching at that place, as well as to ascertain the genuineness
                            of the petition in question. Should this disposition in the matter be
                            favorable, you may assure Sir Philip Currie of the great pleasure it
                            will give you, as the representative of this Government, to solicit his
                            kindly offices in this behalf, believing that to do so can not be less a
                            source of satisfaction to him than his compliance therewith can afford
                            gratification to this Government.</p>
                        <p>I may add for your information that this note of Mavroyeni Bey, having
                            been shown to Mr. Terrell while he was recently in Washington, he has
                            indorsed thereon a memorandum to the effect that this memorial was shown
                            to the dragoman of the legation several months ago; that it was sent to
                            the Porte on the heels of the recent massacre at Harpoot, and that the
                            Armenian signers, in their desire to secure personal safety, would have
                            been willing to attach their names to any statement dictated to them,
                            however calumnious and unfounded. It is to be noted that the telegram is
                            without date, and its tardy presentation is perhaps a notable
                            circumstance at the present juncture.</p>
                        <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Richard Olney.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>