<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1896-09-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1896-09-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="810" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d810">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Terrell</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Olney</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-09-11"><hi rend="italic">September 11,
                                    1896</hi></date>. (Received Sept. 26.)</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 980.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herewith the
                            copy of a letter written by Revs. J. W. Baird and J. W. Cole from Bitlis
                            on the 24th ultimo, which conveys the welcome news that their condition
                            there is improved.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">A. W. Terrell</hi>.</signed></closer>
                        <pb facs="0956" n="862" xml:id="pg_862"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 980.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Revs. <persName type="from">Cole and
                                        Baird</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Terrell</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Bitlis</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-08-24"><hi rend="italic">August 24,
                                        1896</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Terrell</hi>: Yours of August 11 is
                                just at hand. As you probably know, your telegram was received, and
                                after a delay of three or four days was answered by a telegram from
                                us. We wrote you on August 11, giving you some account of the
                                situation at that date. Since then matters have quieted down, and
                                the restrictions of the police are so far discontinued that, while
                                all is not as cordial as could be wished, we do not now complain of
                                the present attitude of the authorities at this place.</p>
                            <p>In place of the three undelivered letters, mentioned in our letter of
                                August 11, two, not at all for us, were subsequently delivered; and
                                when the next week’s post arrived Mr. Baird received by it an old
                                letter addressed by his wife, the envelope entirely cut on three
                                sides, but nothing from her pen, though there were some letters from
                                others to her, which she evidently forwarded. Putting on this a
                                liberal and friendly construction, we may say that the letters were
                                received.</p>
                            <p>As there seems to be some hope that Mr. Bergholz will, in the not
                                distant future, get his exequatur, and as such letters go and come
                                from him in a short time, we shall keep your consul, Mr. Bergholz,
                                informed from week to week of our condition. If, however, any grave
                                interference with our work takes place, we shall communicate also
                                direct with you. You may rest assured that we are keeping entirely
                                free from all political matters. We hear of no movement among the
                                Armenians, and suppose them to be quiet and submissive.</p>
                            <p>With many thanks for your exertions in our behalf,</p>
                            <p>Yours, sincerely,</p>
                            <closer><signed><list>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">R. M. Cole</hi>.</item>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">J. W. Baird.</hi></item>
                                    </list></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>