<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1896-09-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1896-09-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="814" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d814">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Terrell</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Olney</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-09-30"><hi rend="italic">September 30,
                                    1896</hi></date>. (Received Oct. 17.)</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1005.]</seg></opener>
                        <p>Sir: I have the honor to inclose a copy of a letter from President Tracy,
                            of Marsovan College, which shows that orders have been issued for the
                            security of the people there.</p>
                        <p>His anxiety for a more liberal iradé for his college is natural, but just
                            now such matters would receive no attention.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">A. W. Terrell.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 1005.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Tracy</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Terrell</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Marsovan</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-09-21"><hi rend="italic">September 21,
                                        1896</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Judge Terrell</hi>: During the last days of
                                our stay in Constantinople the prospect seemed to improve to such a
                                degree that I felt justified in yielding to the earnest desire of
                                the members of our party to return altogether to Marsovan. We
                                therefore came on, and see no <pb facs="0963" n="869" xml:id="pg_869"/> reason so far for regretting the step. I find
                                matters in a much better condition than I expected. There is general
                                quiet, and we believe that stringent orders have been given for its
                                maintenance. College was opened on the 15th instant with nearly 100
                                students; the girls’ department with about 70. We have a guard of
                                regular soldiers in every way polite, quiet, and respectful; indeed,
                                they are attached to us as friends. The officers of the Government
                                are deferential and cordial—never were more so. They manifest
                                confidence in us, and often depend on our judgment and testimony. I
                                feel that we have nothing to fear from the local authorities.</p>
                            <p>There is a question pressing for immediate decision. The matter of
                                the firman for the college is still in abeyance and they demand the
                                taxes for last year and this, amounting to about 40 liras. In a
                                former letter you stated your ground, namely, that while the irade
                                was delayed the taxes should not be paid. It appears that some sort
                                of unsatisfactory firman was issued which, as I suppose, you did not
                                accept. The acceptance of it lies with our legation, not with us. If
                                this paper lies, as Consul Jewett thinks, in the hands of the mearif
                                at Sivas, not accepted by our representative and the correction of
                                whatever is objectionable in it delayed, what shall we do about
                                paying the taxes demanded? I am going this hour to the emlak, and
                                shall tell him that we await an answer from you.</p>
                            <p>I am glad to report all well.</p>
                            <p>Yours, sincerely,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles
                                Tracy.</hi></signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>P. S.—September 24. There are now 120 in the college, and over
                                    100 in the girls’ boarding school.</p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>