<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1896-02-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1896-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="857" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d857">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Olney</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Terrell</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-02-20"><hi rend="italic">February 20,
                                    1896.</hi></date></dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 864.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I send for your information copy of a
                            letter from the Rev. Judson Smith, of Boston, in regard to the
                            investigation of the charges of sedition brought against Mr. Knapp, of
                            Bitlis.</p>
                        <p>The Department sees no reason to question the expediency and practical
                            convenience of conducting that investigation at Constantinople under
                            your own eye and where Mr. Knapp’s friends will be in a position to
                            afford him material support. Your telegram reported that you had adopted
                            this course at the request of the missionaries. Such a course certainly
                            seems better adapted to the case than the alternative of sending
                            consular representatives, British as well as American, and witnesses in
                            Mr. Knapp’s behalf to so remote a spot as Bitlis at the present
                            juncture.</p>
                        <p>I also inclose copy of my reply to Mr. Smith. You will observe that as
                            regards his suggestion that Mr. Knapp’s departure may interrupt, perhaps
                            permanently, the conduct of the important mission at Bitlis, I intimate
                            that you will probably have suggested sending a competent substitute to
                            conduct operations during the absence of the principal.</p>
                        <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Richard Olney.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>