<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Riddle to Mr. Olney.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1896</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d869</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">869</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1896-06-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1896-06-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1896-06-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1896-06-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="869"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d869">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Riddle</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Olney</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-06-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 18, 1896</hi>
                        </date>. (Received July 3.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 897.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit herewith for your
                    further information in the case of Rev. George Knapp copy of a note received
                    from the minister for foreign affairs, with a memorandum annexed which
                    constitutes the only thing in the nature of charges so far presented by the
                    Porte.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">J. W. Riddle</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="1007" n="913" xml:id="pg_913"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 897.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName type="from">Tevfik Pasha</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to"
                                >Riddle</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sublime Porte</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Ministry of Foreign Affairs</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-06-06">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 6, 1896.</hi>
                            </date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Chargé d’Affaires</hi>: I transmit to you herewith,
                        a memorandum containing the information furnished by the governor of Bitlis
                        concerning the conduct of the American missionary, George Knapp.</p>
                    <p>I feel sure that a perusal of this document will lead you to the conclusion
                        that this missionary indulged in intrigues of a nature calculated to disturb
                        public order and security in several provinces of Asiatic Turkey, and that
                        he himself brought about the Bitlis incident.</p>
                    <p>The concurring depositions of many persons abundantly prove this.</p>
                    <p>As the position assumed by Mr. Knapp is not in harmony with the large
                        hospitality enjoyed by American missionaries in the Empire, nor with the
                        friendly relations so happily existing between the two countries, I do not
                        doubt that the United States Government will completely disapprove it and
                        will apply to his case the provisions of the law.</p>
                    <p>Receive, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tevfik.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure in No. 897.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>This missionary, who was one of the principal mainstays of the Hintchagist
                        committee at Bitlis, indulged in all sorts of subversive intrigues. It was
                        at his instigation that Armenian agitators provoked disturbances in the
                        province. In fact, this missionary was always in correspondence with
                        Armenian leaders, among whom were Hany Sarsoun (alias Mourat), chief of the
                        Sassoun and Tabari insurgents, in order to stir up trouble with a view to
                        creating an Armenian principality in Asia Minor, and used to send to Sassoun
                        and elsewhere, under the pretext of distributing aid, emissaries who were
                        charged with the mission of giving most pernicious counsels to the
                        inhabitants. Incited by him, the agitator Ossep, son of Garabet, and several
                        of his Armenian companions, had attempted in the open street at Bitlis to
                        forcibly abduct a Kurdish girl from her parents, at the same time calling
                        the latter by the most abusive names, and blaspheming the Imperial
                        Government and the Musselman religion.</p>
                    <p>This missionary, in company with certain agitators, used to hold meetings at
                        his house or in the churches or at the bishop’s residence in order to
                        prepare the Bitlis incident. It is he who had vagrants in his hire and armed
                        them that troubles might be provoked. He encouraged the credulous Armenians
                        to attack the mosques during the Friday prayer and to kill the faithful, to
                        assassinate MusselMANS. officials and notables whom they met in lonely
                        places, and to urge such of their own nationality as were faithful to the
                        Imperial Government to refuse to pay their taxes and to address such
                        language to the Musselmans as would tend to excite them; in one word, he did
                        his utmost to disturb order and peace. He acted as intermediary in the
                        exchange of guilty correspondence, propagated the most revolutionary ideas,
                        and spread abroad sensational rumors. Refusing to conform to the regulations
                        governing public instruction, he tried to inoculate subversive principles
                        into the minds of his pupils, and sought to induce the Armenians to embrace
                        Protestantism. He persuaded those of them who occupied public places not to
                        go to their posts. It was at the alarm signal given by means of a bell which
                        he had installed near his house that the Armenians shut their shops and
                        attacked the mosques at the time of the Bitlis disturbances.</p>
                    <p>The Armenians, Hamazasp, Serape, and Mampre (the letter Mr. Knapp’s servant),
                        who wounded a certain Kevark Agha Bakkalian, have testified before the
                        examining magistrate that they committed this crime under orders from
                        Missionary Knapp, who promised to give £100 to whomsoever succeeded in
                        killing one or more members of the Bakkalian family, and to provide for the
                        future of his wife and children in addition. They have further testified
                        that it was George Knapp himself who furnished the revolver used in the
                        perpetration of the crime. It is also stated in their depositions that this
                        missionary was aware of all the revolutionary plans of the <pb facs="1008"
                            n="914" xml:id="pg_914"/> Armenians and that he had advised them to
                        assassinate some of their fellow Christians in order that the crime might he
                        attributed to Musselmans. Quite recently Mr. Knapp has used abusive language
                        toward the Musselmans passing in front of his house and has sought to
                        provoke the Musselman population to fresh troubles. All these facts are
                        established by judicial examination.</p>
                    <p>Besides Hamazasp, Serape, and Mr. Knapp’s servant, the persons whose names
                        follow have also made deposition against this missionary.</p>
                    <p>(Here follow nineteen Armenian names.)</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
