<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-09-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-09-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="125" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d125">
                        <head>125. Presidential Determination No. 80–27<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d125fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File, P800136–0539. No
                                classification marking.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1980-09-21">September 21, 1980</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">MEMORANDUM FOR THE UNITED STATES COORDINATOR FOR REFUGEE
                            AFFAIRS</p>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Determination pursuant to Section 2(c)(1) of the Migration and
                                Refugee Assistance Act of 1962, as amended, and Amending
                                Presidential Determination Number 80–24, dated August 7,
                                1980.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Pursuant to Section 2(c)(1) of the Migration and Refugee Assistance Act
                            of 1962, as amended (the “Act”), I hereby determine that Presidential
                            Determination Number 80–24 of August 7, 1980<note n="2" xml:id="d125fn2">See <ref target="#d117">Document 117</ref>.</note> is amended by
                            striking paragraphs two through five of the Determination.</p>
                        <p>I determine that unexpected, urgent refugee and migration needs continue
                            to exist in Florida and in other localities and that it is in the
                            national interest to continue to provide assistance to those Cubans and
                            Haitians arriving in the United States.</p>
                        <pb facs="0317" n="270" xml:id="pg_270"/>
                        <p>I further determine that a total of up to $31,644,173 shall be made
                            available from the United States Emergency Refugee and Migration
                            Assistance Fund for the purposes of processing, transportation, caring,
                            and resettling, and associated administrative expenses, for these Cubans
                            and Haitians. Assistance shall be provided to these persons in
                            accordance with such terms and conditions as the United States
                            Coordinator for Refugee Affairs shall establish on my behalf or for the
                            purposes described in Presidential Determination Number 80–16, as
                                amended.<note n="3" xml:id="d125fn3">See <ref target="#d117fn2">footnote 2, Document 117</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The United States Coordinator for Refugee Affairs is requested to inform
                            the appropriate committees of the Congress of this Determination and the
                            obligation of funds under this authority.</p>
                        <p>This Determination shall be published in the <hi rend="italic">Federal
                                Register</hi>.<note n="4" xml:id="d125fn4">On September 30,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> issued
                                Presidential Determination No. 80–29 which permitted “an additional
                                5000 refugee admission numbers to be available.” (National Archives,
                                    <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy
                                File, P800137–2288)</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1"><hi rend="strong">Jimmy
                                    Carter</hi></persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>