<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>166. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Mexico</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d166</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">166</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-10-21T14:38:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-10-21T14:38:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Visas</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-10-21T14:38:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-10-21T14:38:00-05:00" n="166"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d166">
                <head>166. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Mexico<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d166fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security
                        Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Country File, Box 49, Mexico, 10/79–1/80.
                        Secret; Cherokee; Niact Immediate; Nodis. Drafted in P; approved in P and
                            <gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss>–O.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1979-10-21T19:38:00+00:00">October 21, 1979, 1938Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>275028. Eyes only for Charge. Subject: The Shah’s Illness.</p>
                <p>1. Secret—Entire text.</p>
                <p>2. <gloss target="#t_FYI_1">FYI</gloss>: Rockefeller’s office has informed us
                    that <persName corresp="#p_LPJ_1">Lopez Portillo</persName> sent the following
                    message to the former Shah on October 20 responding to a request made to him by
                    the Shah to permit Shah’s return to Mexico following medical treatment in
                        U.S.:<note n="2" xml:id="d166fn2">The Shah arrived in Mexico on June 10,
                        despite opposition from both the left and the right. (Telegram 9653 from
                        Mexico City, June 10, and telegram 9797 from Mexico City, June 13; National
                        Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy
                        File, D790265–0083 and D790270–0107)</note> Quote: Your home is always
                    Mexico. This is your country. You are always welcome. We are distressed and
                    disturbed by your health. A King should have premier medical treatment, you
                    should go to the United States and we await your return. You can live anywhere
                    in Mexico, be it Cuernavaca, Acapulco, or Mexico City. We will give you security
                    and asylum. Unquote. End <gloss target="#t_FYI_1">FYI</gloss>.</p>
                <p>3. Charge should see that following message is conveyed to <gloss
                        target="#t_GOM_1">GOM</gloss> soonest by whatever channel you deem most
                    appropriate:</p>
                <p>A) We have decided to permit Shah to come to U.S. for private medical treatment
                    on recommendation of French and American doctors who have been treating him.
                    Their medical report has revealed that Shah has serious condition immediately
                    requiring further diagnosis and evaluation, B) We understand that President
                    Portillo has agreed to the Shah’s request to keep open the possibility of his
                    returning to Mexico following his forthcoming medical treatment in the U.S. We
                    wish to express our appreciation for this decision. He and Shahbanu<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d166fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_PFD_1">Farah Pahlavi</persName>, Empress of
                        Iran.</note> will be travelling to U.S. immediately. We do not plan to
                    publicize the travel and we would appreciate your government’s cooperation in
                    maintaining confidentiality. If news of travel leaks, we plan low key
                    confirmation that Shah is coming to U.S. for diagnosis and evaluation. We will
                    keep you informed of developments following further medical evaluation.</p>
                <pb facs="0450" n="403" xml:id="pg_403"/>
                <p>4. Please report Niact Immediate when message delivered and any <gloss
                        target="#t_GOM_1">GOM</gloss> reactions, which we assume will confirm above
                    understanding of <gloss target="#t_GOM_1">GOM</gloss> willingness for Shah to
                    return to Mexico.</p>
                <p>5. We are in touch with Rockefeller group to arrange immediate travel to U.S. and
                    on extremely confidential basis. Shah and Shahbanu have valid U.S. visas, but
                    invalid Iranian passports. Request you appoint and inform us of name of officer
                    to handle documentation. You should arrange passport waiver for entry into U.S.
                    If you cannot insure that it can be done confidentially, please inform us and we
                    will arrange waiver in U.S. at point of entry. Since former Shah and Shahbanu no
                    longer have any claim to governmental authority in Iran, you should insure that
                    visa is B–2 tourist visa (and multiple entry for maximum period of
                    validity).</p>
                <p>6. Current plans are for Shah’s departure from Mexico City for U.S. early
                    tomorrow afternoon (October 22). Rockefeller representatives will be in contact
                    with Embassy. We have given them Charge or Dunn as initial point of
                        contact.<note n="4" xml:id="d166fn4">The Mexican Government was informed by
                        U.S. officials on November 28 that the Shah wished to return to Mexico.
                        Mexican officials proceeded to inform the Shah that his visa, which expired
                        on December 9, would not be renewed and that “he would not want to return
                        for such a brief period.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1"
                            >RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File, P840131–1726) A November 30
                        Intelligence Report concluded that the Mexican Foreign Ministry decision not
                        to renew the Shah’s visa was motivated by: 1) fears of assassination
                        attempts against the Shah, 2) an opportunity to show the independence of
                        Mexico’s foreign policy, and 3) the fact that the Shah had been offered
                        safehaven elsewhere. ([<hi rend="italic">report number not
                        declassified</hi>]; National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss>
                        59, Official Files of [P] <persName corresp="#p_NDD_1">David D.
                            Newsom</persName>, Under Secretary for Political Affairs, Lot 82D85, Box
                        4, SHAH: Asylum Contacts/Panama stay Nov. 1979) In telegram 21803 from
                        Mexico City, December 28, the Embassy reported, “A possible further
                        explanation for <gloss target="#t_GOM_1">GOM</gloss> reaction to the issues
                        surrounding the Shah and U.S. Mexican relations since their decision not to
                        readmit him may be provided by the following interchange between the Shah
                        and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MHB_1">Margain</persName>. According to
                        SRE Under Secretary Rosenzweig-Diaz, when <persName corresp="#p_MHB_1"
                            >Margain</persName> delivered the final <gloss target="#t_GOM_1"
                            >GOM</gloss> decision, the Shah’s immediate reaction was to ask ‛Did you
                        clear this with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>?’ If
                        the Shah’s statement is reported accurately, it was guaranteed to raise
                        Mexican ire.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59,
                        Central Foreign Policy File, P840131–1723)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Christopher</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
