<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>42. Telegram From the U.S. Interests Section in Cuba to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d42</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">42</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1978-12-11T12:56:00-05:00" notAfter="1978-12-11T12:56:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recu3GH1ojKcJBA1c" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Overflight</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048668"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fishery</term>
                    <term ref="rec8uqG4zFwFzxdlO" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104422"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Political prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88004886"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Journalist</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7Bwbos1G7X7n" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2013002394"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">MIG</term>
                    <term ref="recgO0zWiwmY4SEHo" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002995"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Airspace</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general">Fishing rights</term>
                    <term ref="recItilmdY8wKocmo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005329"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Conservation</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85039841"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Dual national</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85098258"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Parole</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-12-11T12:56:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-12-11T12:56:00-05:00" n="42"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d42">
                <head>42. Telegram From the U.S. Interests Section in Cuba to the Department of
                        State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d42fn1">Source: National Archives,
                            <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D780511–0654. Confidential; Immediate.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Havana</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1978-12-11T17:56:00+00:00">December 11, 1978, 1756Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>4098. Subject: Castro Takes Pessimistic Line on US Relations.</p>
                <p>(C) 1. Begin summary: Castro, following signature of <gloss target="#t_GOC_1"
                        >GOC</gloss>-Cuban exile “Final Act” (septel),<note n="2" xml:id="d42fn2">In
                        telegram 4089 from Havana, December 11, the Interests Section reported the
                        signing of the “Final Act” regarding the release of Cuban political
                        prisoners. Approximately 3,600 prisoners were freed and permitted to leave
                        Cuba. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                        Foreign Policy File, D780511–0197)</note> states that relations with US are
                    “going badly”. Cuban leader’s renewed criticism of US administration—heavily
                    laced with sarcasm—is less than evenly balanced by accustomed <pb facs="0142"
                        n="95" xml:id="pg_95"/> favorable comments on certain aspects of
                    administration’s policies vis-a-vis Cuba.</p>
                <p>(C) 2. Castro, for first time publicly discloses and castigates SR–71 overflight
                    and characterizes his failure to fire on aircraft as act of restraint and
                    gesture to avoid embarrassing President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1"
                        >Carter</persName>. He emphasizes that there is no guarantee that this
                    restraint will continue. Castro also condemns <gloss target="#t_USG_1"
                        >USG</gloss> fishery policy and recalls <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>
                    challenge to his personal integrity during Shaba events. Castro says he will not
                    release four of (six) <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> political prisoners
                    “for now”, but is willing to talk about matter with <gloss target="#t_USG_1"
                        >USG</gloss>. Overall, Castro’s attitude toward <gloss target="#t_USG_1"
                        >USG</gloss> is harshest we have seen since 26 of July speech<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d42fn3">In telegram 2157 from Havana, July 27, the Interests Section
                        reported that Castro gave a July 26 speech in which he lambasted President
                            <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>’s human rights policy as
                        hypocritical and attacked the United States for criticizing Cuba’s role in
                        the Non-Aligned Movement. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1"
                            >RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D780308–0628)</note>—in
                    part possibly due to conscious effort on his part to place what may be perceived
                    as conciliatory gestures towards exiles (and indirectly toward <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>) in appropriately “revolutionary”
                    framework.</p>
                <p>End summary.</p>
                <p>(U) 3. Fidel Castro, following signature of “Final Act” with Cuban exile
                    community “representatives”, December 9, held press conference for resident and
                    visiting US and Spanish journalists. In addition to spelling out details of
                    Final Act (septel), Castro discussed his current view of US-Cuban relations.</p>
                <p>(U) 4. Most significantly, Castro declared—contrary to assumption of questioning
                    journalist—that, despite US acquiescence in his political prisoner
                    release/departure plan, US-Cuban relations are not improving, but rather are
                    “going badly”. Castro cited “farce” of MIG–23 issue and SR–71 overflight (“a
                    flagrant violation of sovereign air space”), untrue accusations of Cuban
                    involvement in Shaba (“equal to saying we are liars”), and US fishery policies
                    toward Cuba (“a deception”) to prove his point.</p>
                <p>(C) 5. His references to President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1"
                    >Carter</persName>, although not devoid of now customary praise on certain
                    points (particularly with regard to curtailment of alleged former <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> support for Cuban exile “terrorists”—a step,
                    Castro says, which made his current prisoner release moves possible), contained
                    new elements of ambiguity. He said, for example, that he is not sure how things
                    will turn out with current administration and stated that, although this
                    administration is best he has dealt with, “this has begun to change”. In most
                    sarcastic comments we have ever seen here regarding President <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>, Castro responded to question as to
                    whether he would be willing to invite President to Havana by mocking President’s
                    supposed inability to come here in <pb facs="0143" n="96" xml:id="pg_96"/> face
                    of “reactionary and anachronistic” forces in US. When questioner persisted,
                    Castro added . . . “if <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> wants to
                    come as a tourist, he can come to Cuba anytime he wants.”</p>
                <p>(LOU) 6. Castro elaborated on the following specific developments souring
                    relations with the Carter administration:</p>
                <p>A. SR–71 overflight—Castro said suspension of overflights was one of most
                    appreciated gestures of Carter administration. He allowed there has only been
                    one overflight (November 12), but said such flights are “flagrant violations” of
                    Cuban airspace and Cuba does not recognize US right to monitor Cuban arms. (He
                    repeated that MIG–23 is “tactical defensive” aircraft.) Castro said that he
                    would be within his rights to fire at SR–71, but he has not made a decision to
                    fire because he does not want to “complicate <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1"
                        >Carter</persName>’s position.” On other hand, Castro stated that he is “not
                    disposed to give any guarantee or assurances (regarding safety) of those spy
                    planes.” (Castro, somewhat ironically, said creation of artificial crisis over
                    MIG–23 spurred by “leak” was probably not best move for Carter because domestic
                    political enemies can now portray him as “weak”.)</p>
                <p>B. Fishing—Castro claimed that US promised to respect Cuban “historical fishing
                    rights in US 200 Mile Fishery Conservation Zone when GIFA signed (in 1977).<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d42fn4">See <ref target="#d15">Document 15</ref>.</note> This,
                    he says, was a “deception”. Instead, Castro said, “conditions and requirements”
                    imposed by US are so rigid that it has proved “absolutely impossible” for Cuba
                    to fish in US zone.</p>
                <p>C. Shaba—Castro criticized leak of his conversation with USINT Chief last
                        May<note n="5" xml:id="d42fn5">See <ref target="#d32fn2">footnote 2,
                            Document 32</ref>.</note> and again lambasted “brutal accusation” of
                    Cuban involvement—an “imputation” equal to statement that “we are liars.” Again,
                    sarcastically, Castro said that he would never lie to a child—much less to the
                    “all-powerful master of a great empire” (yet another sarcastic reference to the
                    President).</p>
                <p>D. Embargo—Castro recognized that President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1"
                        >Carter</persName> inherited “the blockade” but charged he is maintaining it
                    and trying to use it as a “weapon of pressure” against Cuba. Castro labeled this
                    as a “crime” and an “indecency”.</p>
                <p>(LOU) 7. On pending policy issue of US political prisoners, Castro said he is not
                    prepared to release them now. (Comment: He referred to four political prisoners.
                    This could mean that Cuban-US dual nationals—Armas Estevez, Hernandez and
                    possibly <persName corresp="#p_BSJ_1">Blanco</persName>-Boix—will be handled
                    with other Cuban prisoners. Other dual national—<persName corresp="#p_TJ_2">Juan
                        Tur</persName>—is apparently being linked with resolution of cases of
                    single-source AMCITs <persName corresp="#p_LL_3">Lunt</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_JE_1">Jackson</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_MCR_1"
                        >Rodriguez Morales</persName>.) Castro stated, how<pb facs="0144" n="97"
                        xml:id="pg_97"/>ever, that he is willing to talk over <gloss
                        target="#t_AMCIT_1">AMCIT</gloss> political prisoners question with <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>.</p>
                <p>(LOU) 8. Regarding <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss>-exile “Final Act”, Castro
                    pushed hard for US acceptance of ex-prisoners and families who were “dragged
                    into counterrevolution by US.” He said that, in light of US “moral obligation”
                    flowing from past policies and Carter’s acceptance of another relic of past
                    policy (Guantanamo) (yet another barb), US cannot reject ex-prisoners. Castro
                    commented that opening up of Cuban port to allow exiles to pick up relatives not
                    documented for entry into US (as was done by Castro in early 1960’s in face of
                        <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> slowness in documenting Cuban
                    emigrants) is not yet necessary. He suggested that, if only, say, 100–150
                    current prisoners per month wish to go to US, Washington can use remainder of
                    monthly (parole) quotas of 400 for ex-prisoners. (<gloss target="#t_FYI_1"
                        >FYI</gloss> He said that only 82 of first list of 400 prisoners now wish to
                    go to US—but that final number could rise to 150. End <gloss target="#t_FYI_1"
                        >FYI</gloss>.) This first list was apparently given to the Cuban community
                    representatives, but has not yet been published or provided to USINT.</p>
                <p>(C) 9. Begin comment: Castro’s barbed solicitousness of President <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>’s supposed domestic political problems
                    plus his taunting if not ridicule of President over other issues strikes us as
                    marked departure from past public statements by the Cuban leader. Previously,
                    Carter administration has been attacked on single issues (Shaba, human rights,
                    et cetera), but Castro’s criticism has not taken on such a programmatic or
                    personal form. Castro’s December 9 statements come close to such an
                    across-the-board attack and are the harshest we have seen since his July 26
                    speech. Nevertheless, the Cuban leader kept his options open by again
                    acknowledging President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>’s
                    positive policies, such as ending of support for exile terrorists and acceptance
                    of Cuban political prisoners. Castro’s unwillingness to write off cooperation
                    with the administration (and his prisoner/emigration gestures—though these are
                    probably motivated also by domestic problems) reflect strong desire on his part
                    to continue opening to US which could bring lifting of trade embargo. At same
                    time, Castro’s escalation of criticism of US may be intended to counterbalance
                    perception among some here that reconciliation with exiles is sell-out to <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> or will ideologically or economically deform
                    Cuban revolution. Criticism, of course, also reflects real Castro hostility to
                    recent US policy toward Cuba and US failure to acquiesce in Cuban activism
                    abroad.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_LLF_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Lane</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
