<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-12-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-12-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="43" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d43">
                        <head>43. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs (Brzezinski) to President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d43fn1">Source:
                                Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material,
                                Country File, Box 13, Cuba, 12/78–4/79. Secret; Sensitive. <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> initialed the memorandum
                                indicating that he saw it.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-12-11">December 11, 1978</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>MIG’s in Cuba</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>On Friday, the Soviets replied to our note<note n="2" xml:id="d43fn2">In
                                a meeting with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> on November 29, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> delivered an oral message
                                regarding the MiGs in Cuba. (Telegram 302435 to Moscow, November 30;
                                National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                                Foreign Policy File, P840139–2032)</note> concerning the MIG’s in
                            Cuba. Their reply is attached at Tab A.<note n="3" xml:id="d43fn3">Undated; attached but not printed. <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> initialed the Soviet note and wrote at the
                                top of the page, “unsatisfactory.”</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is fair to say that the response is unhelpful. It rejects the idea
                            that the MIG–23 aircraft should not be increased; it rejects any
                            relationship between the aircraft and the Understanding of 1962; and it
                            fails to give any assurance that the non-nuclear status of the MIG-23’s
                            includes the MIG 23–D/F which the Soviets refer to as MIG-27’s. (We have
                            questioned them specifically on this point, and their refusal to clarify
                            it is disturbing.)</p>
                        <p>The State Department is preparing a further note to be given to the
                            Soviets. <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Warren Christopher</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_RSR_1">Stan Resor</persName> and David met
                            today and agreed that to leave the exchange of correspondence as is
                            would create great difficulties in regard to SALT.<note n="4" xml:id="d43fn4">In the margin to the left of this paragraph,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> wrote
                                “ok.”</note> At the same time, as you have indicated, we do not want
                            to blow this out of proportion. The new note should be available for
                            your review tomorrow.</p>
                        <p>It is worth noting that Soviet rejection of our concern about MIG-23’s in
                            Cuba is inconsistent with the Soviet concerns about the much less
                            capable carrier aircraft which the British have been considering selling
                            to China. Similarly, our effort to discourage the British from this sale
                            has not been matched by Soviet sensitivity about transfers of MIG-23’s
                            to Cuba.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>