<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-09-06T18:51:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-09-06T18:51:00-05:00" n="71" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d71">
                        <head>71. Telegram From the U.S. Interests Section in Cuba to the Department
                            of State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d71fn1">Source: Carter
                                Library, National Security Affairs, Staff Material, North/South,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PRA_1">Pastor</persName>, Country, Box 15,
                                Cuba, 2/29/80. Secret; Cherokee; Immediate; Nodis.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Havana</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1979-09-06T23:51:00+00:00">September 6, 1979, 2351Z</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>8173. Subject: Likely Castro Reaction on Soviet Troop Issue. Ref: A)
                            Havana 8038.<note n="2" xml:id="d71fn2">See <ref target="#d66">Document
                                    66</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>1. S—Entire text.</p>
                        <p>2. I take it from Secretary’s public statement of Sept 6 that matter of
                            Soviet unit is to be pursued with Amb <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName>.<note n="3" xml:id="d71fn3">Reference is
                                presumably to <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>’s
                                September 5 press conference. See <ref target="#d68fn4">footnote 4,
                                    Document 68</ref>.</note> It is probably as <pb facs="0197" n="150" xml:id="pg_150"/> well not to pursue it further with Cubans
                            at this point. We have raised it with them, as we should have. They have
                            not responded and are not likely to do so. Further demarches at this
                            point would simply invite kind of defiant, stone-wall response which
                            would be unhelpful in defusing situation.</p>
                        <p>3. Bolstered by what now has all appearances of major and resounding
                            foreign policy victory at <gloss target="#t_NAM_1">NAM</gloss> Summit, a
                            victory which increases his worth to and bargaining position with
                            Soviets, Castro will be in no mood to offer explanations and certainly
                            not to take any initiatives in direction reduction or withdrawal. Nor is
                            he likely quietly to acquiesce to any possible Soviet decision to reduce
                            or withdraw units. On contrary, he will use added leverage of Summit
                            victory to prevent any backdown on their part, a la 1962. Cubans
                            regarded Soviet response then as cowardly and still do. 1962 will be
                            uppermost in Cuban minds as they watch Soviet management of troop
                            issue.</p>
                        <p>4. USINT’s assessment that announcement presence of Soviet unit unlikely
                            to influence thinking of many <gloss target="#t_NAM_1">NAM</gloss>
                            delegates (Ref B)<note n="4" xml:id="d71fn4">Not further
                                identified.</note> has been strengthened over past few days. Troop
                            story drew a ho-hum, but to the extent there was any reaction, it was
                            overwhelmingly that announcement was clumsy US effort to influence
                            outcome of Summit. Castro’s soundings were doubtless more complete than
                            our own but must have produced same results. He, then, will likely be
                            operating on assumption that awareness of presence Soviet unit here will
                            not do him any particular harm in the <gloss target="#t_NAM_1">NAM</gloss>.<note n="5" xml:id="d71fn5">In telegram 8377 from
                                Havana, September 9, the Interests Section remarked that although
                                Castro “emerged as a major recognized leader of the <gloss target="#t_NAM_1">NAM</gloss>,” the moderates were able to
                                deflect some of his more anti-West and anti-U.S. initiatives.
                                (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                                Foreign Policy File, D790464–1094)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>5. Given the above, Castro is likely to calculate that most of the
                            factors in the equation are in his favor. He can therefore be expected
                            to take a firm stand and to make it difficult for the Soviets not to do
                            so.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Smith</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>