<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>83. Telegram From the U.S. Interests Section in Cuba to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d83</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">83</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-11-17T21:35:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-11-17T21:35:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMNSn3ulaoClE2c" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003007715"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Hostages</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-11-17T21:35:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-11-17T21:35:00-05:00" n="83"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d83">
                <head>83. Telegram From the U.S. Interests Section in Cuba to the Department of
                        State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d83fn1">Source: National Archives,
                            <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        P840131–1646. Secret; Cherokee; Niact Immediate; Nodis.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Havana</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1979-11-18T02:35:00+00:00">November 18, 1979, 0235Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>10155. Subj: Castro Offers Good Offices. Ref: (A) Havana 10120 (B) State
                        299655.<note n="2" xml:id="d83fn2">In telegram 10120 from Havana, November
                        16, the Interests Section reported that Cuban officials condemned the
                        Iranian decision to take Americans hostage as “irresponsible” and
                        “uncivilized.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59,
                        Central Foreign Policy File, P840131–1648) In telegram 299655 to all
                        diplomatic posts, November 17, the Department announced that the Iranians
                        had decided to release “women and black” hostages. (National Archives,
                            <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D790529–1188) Iranian students seized more than 60 U.S. diplomats and
                        citizens on November 4.</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. (S—Entire text.)</p>
                <p>2. Castro called me to his office tonight to say he has sent message to Iranian
                    authorities as suggested by <persName corresp="#p_PJL_1">Jose Luis
                        Padron</persName> (see Ref A) calling on them to release hostages and
                    offering good offices as President <gloss target="#t_NAM_1">NAM</gloss>. He said
                    he hoped release of women and black hostages was first step on Iranian side
                    toward more rational position. Cuba wished to help defuse situation which had
                    dangerous implications not only for Iran and US but for whole world. If his
                    efforts in this matter are to have any chance of success they would have to be
                    extended with utmost discretion. They should not rpt not become matter of public
                    knowledge.</p>
                <p>3. I indicated appreciation for efforts to obtain release our hostages. I
                    emphasized however that US would not be blackmailed. Taking of hostages was
                    simply unacceptable and first step in defusing situation should be their release
                    unharmed.</p>
                <p>4. Castro expressed full appreciation for US position. He urged that US continue
                    to show prudence and patience under great pressure which had characterized its
                    reaction for past two weeks. US prestige had gained by such coolness while Iran
                    was now left virtually isolated. Thanks to US patience hostages were still alive
                    and chances that Iranian authorities would listen to reason seemed to have
                    increased. US should of course continue to show firmness of purpose but must be
                    patient yet a bit longer. He had impression Iranian authorities might be looking
                    for way out but would need time to get their people under control. He would use
                    any influence he had with them to bring about release <pb facs="0226" n="179"
                        xml:id="pg_179"/> of hostages and defuse situation. He promised to inform me
                    immediately of Iranian reaction to his message.<note n="3" xml:id="d83fn3">In
                        telegram 10338 from Havana, November 25, Smith reported that Cuban Vice
                        President <persName corresp="#p_RCF_1">Carlos Rafael Rodriguez</persName>
                        received a reply from the Iranian Revolutionary Council declining Cuba’s
                        offer of its good offices but suggesting that the Iranians might intend to
                        use the Cubans as a channel to communicate with the United States. (National
                        Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy
                        File, P840133–2368) In telegram 10388 from Havana, November 27, Smith stated
                        that <persName corresp="#p_RCF_1">Rodriguez</persName> declared there was
                        “little more Cuba could do,” but hinted that if the Cubans won a seat on the
                        Security Council, they could be more active about the hostage situation in
                        the United Nations. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss>
                        59, Central Foreign Policy File, P840131–1637)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Smith</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
