<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-01-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-01-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="85" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d85">
                        <head>85. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> and the President’s Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (Brzezinski) to President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d85fn1">Source:
                                Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material,
                                Brzezinski Office File, Subject Chron File, Box 60, Alpha
                                Channel—Cuba, 7/79–9/80. Secret; Sensitive. A handwritten notation
                                by Carter at the top of the page reads, “Zbig, give cc Bob &amp;
                                Mike.”</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1980-01-15">January 15, 1980</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Mission to Cuba</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>As per their discussion with you, <persName corresp="#p_TP_1">Tarnoff</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_PRA_1">Pastor</persName> will travel to Havana on Wednesday and Thursday
                            for talks with Castro in response to his personal request.<note n="2" xml:id="d85fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_PRA_1">Pastor</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_TP_1">Tarnoff</persName> visited Cuba from January
                                16 to January 17.</note> The central purposes of the journey are to
                            listen; to ask questions designed to better understand his views on a
                            range of different issues, including Afghanistan and Iran; to convey our
                            great concern about Cuban subversion in Central America and the
                            Caribbean, troops in Africa, support of extremist groups in Puerto
                                Rico;<note n="3" xml:id="d85fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> underlined this
                                sentence beginning with “convey” to this point and wrote “emphasize”
                                in the margin.</note> and to suggest that we are prepared to
                            consider a new relationship if he is prepared to move toward meeting our
                            concerns. In addition, they will convey your comments and personal
                            concerns about the Soviet invasion in Afghanistan.<note n="4" xml:id="d85fn4">The Soviet Union began military operations against
                                Afghanistan December 25–26, 1978.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">US Objectives</p>
                        <p>Although the objectives below will probably be impossible to achieve at
                            this meeting, <persName corresp="#p_TP_1">Tarnoff</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_PRA_1">Pastor</persName> should try to obtain the
                            following:</p>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Afghanistan</hi>. To explore his views of the
                            invasion and to try to detect whether there is any change in Castro’s
                            perception of Cuba’s relations with the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. To point out to Castro that Cuba’s statements in
                            support of the Soviet invasion would make progress toward normalization
                            of relations with the US politically difficult for us.</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Iran</hi>. To ask Castro to press publicly and
                            privately for the unconditional release of the hostages and to use his
                            influence with the Soviets to try to get them to modify their position
                            on sanctions against Iran.<note n="5" xml:id="d85fn5">In this paragraph,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> underlined
                                “privately” and wrote in the margin, “privately may help.” He also
                                underlined from “use his influence” to the end and wrote in the
                                margin, “fruitless—<hi rend="italic">no</hi>.”</note>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0235" n="188" xml:id="pg_188"/>
                        <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Central America and the Caribbean</hi>. To seek the
                            cessation of: (a) Cuban support (arms, aid, political direction) for
                            groups which are intent on overthrowing or subverting the established
                            governments in the region (particularly El Salvador, Honduras,
                            Guatemala); (b) Cuban encouragement of the use of political violence and
                            intimidation to undercut or suppress democratic institutions
                            (particularly in Jamaica and Grenada); (c) Cuban assistance in building
                            up the Grenadan armed forces to a point clearly in excess of the
                            island’s legitimate security needs and to the point where it constitutes
                            a threat to neighboring islands; and (d) Cuban facilitation of contacts
                            between extremist groups from different countries (and government
                            officials from Nicaragua and Grenada). In discussing Central America and
                            the Caribbean, we should convey our deep concern that Cuba’s support for
                            guerrilla groups could put us on a collision course with serious
                            consequences that we would prefer to avoid.</p>
                        <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Puerto Rico</hi>. To cease the support of extremist
                            groups that practice or have committed acts of violence in Puerto Rico;
                            to adopt a more moderate course on Puerto Rico in the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>, respecting the right of the people of
                            Puerto Rico to determine their future.<note n="6" xml:id="d85fn6">
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> underlined this
                                sentence beginning with “respecting.”</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Cuban Combat Troops Abroad</hi>. To seek the
                            withdrawal of Cuban troops from Angola and Ethiopia and to seek a
                            commitment against introducing or expanding their presence elsewhere
                            (e.g., Yemen, Afghanistan). To suggest that Cuba’s continued military
                            presence in Ethiopia may be a factor leading Somalia toward a closer
                            relationship with the US and a factor leading us to be more receptive to
                            Somalia’s defense needs.<note n="7" xml:id="d85fn7">
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> underlined and
                                highlighted this sentence and wrote in the margin, “may be
                                counterproductive.”</note> In addition, with respect to Angola to
                            suggest that the Cubans may want to use their influence to urge the
                                <gloss target="#t_MPLA_1">MPLA</gloss> to pursue an accommodation
                            with UNITA.</p>
                        <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Soviet Brigade in Cuba</hi>. To question the
                            continued need for a Soviet combat brigade in Cuba and to explore
                            whether the Cubans could under certain circumstances request its
                                withdrawal.<note n="8" xml:id="d85fn8">Carter bracketed and crossed
                                out the phrase, “under certain circumstances.”</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Cuban Objectives—US Response</p>
                        <p>The principal objective of the mission is to listen to Castro and report
                            back. However, if there is any significant movement on the part of the
                            Cubans toward US objectives, or if Castro asks what the US would be
                            prepared to do in response, <persName corresp="#p_TP_1">Tarnoff</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_PRA_1">Pastor</persName>
                            will indicate a general willingness on our part of the US to make some
                            movement on the issue of greatest concern to Cuba (e.g., embargo),
                            without indicating <pb facs="0236" n="189" xml:id="pg_189"/> what we
                            would do precisely. (Our preference would be to disaggregate, to take
                            small steps, like trade on films, medicines, etc., before lifting the
                            overall embargo.)</p>
                        <p>Given the serious internal problems in Cuba, it is conceivable that
                            Castro may ask us to accept another 10–20,000 ex-political prisoners. If
                            he does so, <persName corresp="#p_TP_1">Tarnoff</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_PRA_1">Pastor</persName> would refer the issue to
                            Washington but indicate reservations to Castro given the numbers of
                            Indochinese refugees that the US is now admitting in the wake of the
                            Vietnamese occupation of Kampuchea and repressive internal policies in
                                Vietnam.<note n="9" xml:id="d85fn9">
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> wrote in the margin
                                by this paragraph, “oppose more firmly.”</note>
                        </p>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline">
                                <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                            </note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="strong">Paper Prepared by the Executive Secretary of the
                                    Department of State (<persName corresp="#p_TP_1">Tarnoff</persName>)</hi><note n="10" xml:id="d85fn10">Secret; Sensitive. The paper is apparently talking points for
                                        <persName corresp="#p_TP_1">Tarnoff</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_PRA_1">Pastor</persName>’s meeting with
                                    Castro.</note>
                            </head>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="italic">OUTLINE</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">INTRODUCTORY REMARKS</p>
                            <p>After receiving word of the invitation for me and others to come to
                                Havana, the issue was immediately reviewed at the highest levels of
                                the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>. On Thursday afternoon, Bob
                                and I met with President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> who decided that we should go to Havana. The
                                President asked me to tell you the following:<note n="11" xml:id="d85fn11">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> wrote in the
                                    margin by this paragraph, “this exceeds my level of
                                    interest.”</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>—The President considers the opportunity for us to have this meeting
                                an important one. He received Bob and me to underline his personal
                                interest in this meeting, and to give us our instructions. President
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> also told us that
                                he will listen to our report of this conversation with interest
                                after our return to Washington.</p>
                            <p>—The President has from the beginning of his term been favorable to
                                an improvement of relations between the US and Cuba. The President
                                wants our nations to live in peace together, and he would like to be
                                able to lift the embargo, allowing trade and tourism and other
                                contacts to develop normally between our countries.</p>
                            <p>—The President is interested primarily in receiving a report of your
                                views on the important and critical international issues that affect
                                    <pb facs="0237" n="190" xml:id="pg_190"/> both of our countries.
                                He stressed to me that we should go to Havana with neither threats
                                nor inducements. Mainly to listen.</p>
                            <p>—The President is very preoccupied with the Soviet invasion of
                                Afghanistan which he regards as a threat to international peace. The
                                US and most of the international community regard this violation of
                                the sovereignty of a nation member of the Non-Aligned Movement as
                                abhorrent. The US has no problems with the notion of Cuba being
                                truly non-aligned and neutral, but the closeness of Cuban and Soviet
                                positions on virtually all major international issues has been of
                                concern to us. Speaking with our usual frankness, this closeness
                                seems to have been a factor in the erosion of non-aligned support
                                for Cuba’s bid for a <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Security
                                Council seat in the aftermath of the Soviet invasion of
                                    Afghanistan.<note n="12" xml:id="d85fn12">Mexico was elected to
                                    the Security Council. See <ref target="#d169">Document
                                    169</ref>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>—In an area where Cuba is directly involved, Central America and the
                                Caribbean, we are deeply concerned about Cuban efforts to assist
                                groups working to overthrow established governments by force or
                                undermine democratic institutions.</p>
                            <p>On the subjects that we have proposed to discuss, Afghanistan and
                                then Iran are our major concerns. However, we would also be most
                                interested in your views on developments in areas that we have
                                talked about before: Africa and Puerto Rico. We would also be
                                prepared to discuss issues such as the Soviet brigade in Cuba and
                                the positions adopted by Cuba at the <gloss target="#t_NAM_1">NAM</gloss> summit in Havana last summer.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">ASIDE</p>
                            <p>President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> also wanted
                                President Castro to understand the depth of feeling that exists in
                                the US and the tenacity of sentiment on the Soviet invasion issue.
                                We will have to consider seriously withdrawing from the Olympics, as
                                well as other actions, if in coming weeks the Soviet troops continue
                                to occupy Afghanistan.<note n="13" xml:id="d85fn13">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> wrote below this
                                    sentence, “Would Cuba support move of Olympics?”</note>
                            </p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>