<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-02-27T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-02-27T10:00:00-05:00" n="9" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d9">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 180.03101/48</note>
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">BC–41</note>
                        <head>Secretary’s Notes of a Conversation Held in M. Pichon’s Room at the
                            Quai d’Orsay, Paris, on Thursday, 27th February, 1919, at 3 p.m.</head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1919-02-27T15:00:00+00:00">February 27, 1919, 3 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Present</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Also Present</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">America, United States of</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">present during question 2</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Hon. R. Lansing.</cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">America, United States of</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Hon. H. White.</cell>
                                <cell>Mr. David Magie.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Secretaries</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">British Empire</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Mr. A. H. Frazier.</cell>
                                <cell>Major Hon. W. Ormsby-Gore, M. P.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Mr. L. Harrison.</cell>
                                <cell>Lt. Col. W. H. Gribbon, C. M. G.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">British Empire</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Italy</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>The Rt. Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M., M.P.</cell>
                                <cell>M. Galli.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>The Rt. Hon. Viscount Milner, G. C. B., G. C. M. G.</cell>
                                <cell>M. Piacentini.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Secretaries</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Zionist Mission</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Lt. Col. Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K. C. B.</cell>
                                <cell>Dr. C. Weizmann.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Sir P. Loraine, Bt.</cell>
                                <cell>M. N. Sokolow.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">France</hi></cell>
                                <cell>M. Sylvain Levi.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>M. Pichon.</cell>
                                <cell>M. Spire.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>M. Tardieu.</cell>
                                <cell>M. Ussischkins.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Secretaries</hi></cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>M. Dutasta.</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>M. Berthelot.</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>M. de Bearn.</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Italy</hi></cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>H. E. Baron Sonnino.</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>H. E. Marquis Salvago Raggi.</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Secretaries</hi></cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Count Aldrovandi.</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>M. Bertele.</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Japan</hi></cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>H. E. Baron Makino.</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>H. E. M. Matsui.</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Joint Secretariat</hi></p>
                        <table cols="2" rend="width: 70%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="6">
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">America, United States of</hi></cell>
                                <cell>Colonel U. S. Grant.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">British Empire</hi></cell>
                                <cell>Major A. M. Caccia, M. V. O.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">France</hi></cell>
                                <cell>Captain Portier.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Italy</hi></cell>
                                <cell>Lieut. Zanchi.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Japan</hi></cell>
                                <cell>M. Saburi.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell cols="2"><hi rend="italic">Interpreter:</hi>—Prof. P. J.
                                    Mantoux.</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <pb facs="0170" n="160" xml:id="pg_160"/>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Pichon</hi>, circulated a copy of the
                            following Resolution, which had been received from Colonel House, for
                            formal acceptance by the Conference, and said he understood an agreement
                            had already been reached on the subject:— <seg type="margin">Draft
                                Resolution in Regard to the Procedure for the Determination of
                                Frontiers: (a) Colonel House’s Resolution</seg>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“It is agreed that:—</p>
                                <p>In order to expedite the work of the Conference in defining the
                                    approximate future frontiers of the enemy countries in the
                                    preliminary treaties of peace a Committee composed of one
                                    representative, each, of the United States of America, the
                                    British Empire, France, Italy and Japan, be appointed with the
                                    following terms of reference:— <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>to draw up for the consideration of the Preliminary
                                            Peace Conference the frontiers based on the
                                            recommendations of the territorial Commissions which
                                            have been, or may be, appointed.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>to make recommendations as to any part of the
                                            frontiers of enemy States which are not included in the
                                            scope of any Commission, excepting such frontier
                                            questions as any of the Powers concerned may reserve for
                                            discussion in the first instance at the Quai d’Orsay
                                            Council.”</item>
                                    </list></p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p><seg type="margin">(b) M. Sonnino’s Proposal Regarding: Number of
                                Representatives</seg>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Sonnino</hi> thought it would not be sufficient
                            to have only one representative of each of the Great Powers on the
                            Committee. It might not always be possible for the same representative
                            to attend and, though he might be replaced by a substitute, the latter
                            would find great difficulty in taking part in the deliberations, owing
                            to his not having kept in touch with the previous proceedings. Colonel
                            House had, he believed, originally proposed three representatives. He
                            (M. Sonnino) had agreed that that number was probably excessive, but he
                            thought that each Power should certainly have the right to appoint two
                            representatives, in order to ensure the proper continuity of the
                            work.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lansing</hi> said that his own preference would
                            be for a small Committee of five members, with the power of introducing
                            as many experts as might be thought useful. Consequently, a
                            representative could always be replaced by one of his experts, should
                            the necessity arise.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">M. Sonnino</hi> said that he would not press the
                            matter, but he certainly thought one representative would be too
                            few.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Balfour</hi> said that he would not, himself,
                            fight one way or the other. He enquired, however, whether the difficulty
                            could not be overcome by allowing one representative, with power of
                            substitution.</p>
                        <p><seg type="margin">(c) Proposed Appointment of Permanent Assistant
                                Delegates</seg>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Tardieu</hi> pointed out that the power of
                            substitution already existed. He would suggest, therefore, that each
                            representative should be permitted to have one permanent assistant
                            delegate, who would have the advantage of following the discussions day
                            by day.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">M. Sonnino</hi> enquired whether the permanent
                            assistant delegate would have the power of taking part in the
                            discussions. <pb facs="0171" n="161" xml:id="pg_161"/> He wished to
                            point out that the proposed Committee would not merely be a
                            co-ordinating Committee; it would also have the duty of taking the
                            initiative on all questions which had not been referred to a
                            Commission.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lansing</hi>, intervening, said that his purpose
                            in suggesting five representatives had been to avoid discussion by a
                            large number of people.</p>
                        <p><seg type="margin">(d) Division of Co-ordinating Committee To Be
                                Submitted to Conference of Great Powers</seg>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Sonnino</hi>, continuing, said that it was
                            understood the decisions of the proposed Committee would come before the
                            Conference of the Great Powers before being submitted to a plenary
                            session of the Preliminary Peace Conference.</p>
                        <p>(It was agrees that:—</p>
                        <p>In order to expedite the work of the Conference in defining the
                            approximate future frontiers of the enemy countries in the preliminary
                            treaties of peace a Committee composed of one representative, each, of
                            the United States of America, the British Empire, France, Italy and
                            Japan, be appointed with the following terms of reference:— <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>to draw up for the consideration of the Preliminary Peace
                                    Conference the frontiers based on the recommendations of the
                                    territorial Commissions which have been, or may be,
                                    appointed.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>to make recommendations as to any part of the frontiers of
                                    enemy States which are not included in the scope of any
                                    Commission, excepting such frontiers questions as any of the
                                    Powers concerned may reserve for discussion in the first
                                    instance at the Quai d’Orsay Council.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>It was also agreed that each of the five representatives of the Great
                            Powers should have the right to bring an Assistant with him, in order to
                            ensure continuity in the proceedings.)</p>
                        <p>(At this stage the Zionist Representatives and the technical experts in
                            Zionism entered the Council Chamber.)</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Pichon</hi>, having welcomed the Zionist
                            Deputation, called upon M. Sokolow to address the meeting.</p>
                        <p><seg type="margin">Statement by Zionist Representatives: (a) Statement by
                                M. Sokolow, Member of Zionist organisation</seg>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Sokolow</hi> introduced himself as representing
                            the Zionist Organisation and the Jewish population of Palestine. He had
                            prepared a printed “Statement of the Zionist Organisation regarding
                                Palestine,”<note n="1" xml:id="d9fn1"><p>The “Brief Summary” of the
                                    minutes of this meeting (BC–41a) and the telegraphic report of
                                    the meeting by the American Mission to the Department of State
                                    give the text of this statement as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“1. The High Contracting Parties recognize the historic
                                            title of the Jewish people to Palestine and the right of
                                            the Jews to reconstitute in Palestine their National
                                            Home.</p>
                                        <p>“2. The boundaries of Palestine shall follow the general
                                            lines set out below:—</p>
                                        <p>“Starting on the North at a point on the Mediterranean
                                            Sea in the vicinity</p>
                                        <p>South of Sidon and following the watersheds of the
                                            foothills of the Lebanon as far as Jisr el Karaon,
                                            thence to El Bire, following the dividing line between
                                            the two basins of the Wadi el Korn and the Wadi el Tiem,
                                            thence in a southerly direction following the dividing
                                            line between the Eastern and Western slopes of the
                                            Hermon, to the vicinity West of Beit Jenn, thence
                                            Eastward following the northern watersheds of the Nahr
                                            Mughaniye close to and west of the Hedjaz Railway.</p>
                                        <p>“In the East a line close to and West of the Hedjaz
                                            Railway terminating in the Gulf of Akaba.</p>
                                        <p>“In the South a frontier to be agreed upon with the
                                            Egyptian Government.</p>
                                        <p>“In the West the Mediterranean Sea.</p>
                                        <p>“The details of the delimitations, or any necessary
                                            adjustments of detail, shall be settled by a Special
                                            Commission on which there shall be Jewish
                                            representation.</p>
                                        <p>“3. The sovereign possession of Palestine shall be vested
                                            in the League of Nations and the Government entrusted to
                                            Great Britain as Mandatary of the League.</p>
                                        <p>“4. (Provision to be inserted relating to the application
                                            in Palestine of such of the general conditions attached
                                            to mandates as are suitable to the case.)</p>
                                        <p>“5. The mandate shall be subject also to the following
                                            special conditions: <list>
                                                <item>“(I) Palestine shall be placed under such
                                                  political, administrative and economic conditions
                                                  as will secure the establishment there of the
                                                  Jewish National Home and ultimately render
                                                  possible the creation of an autonomous
                                                  Commonwealth, it being clearly understood that
                                                  nothing shall be done which may prejudice the
                                                  civil and religious rights of existing non-Jewish
                                                  communities in Palestine or the rights and
                                                  political status enjoyed by Jews in any other
                                                  country.</item>
                                                <item>“(II) To this end the Mandatary Power shall
                                                  <hi rend="italic">inter alia:</hi>
                                                  <list>
                                                  <item>“(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Promote Jewish
                                                  immigration and close settlement on the land, the
                                                  established rights of the present non-Jewish
                                                  population being equitably safeguarded.</item>
                                                  <item>“(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Accept the
                                                  co-operation in such measures of a Council
                                                  representative of the Jews of Palestine and of the
                                                  world that may be established for the development
                                                  of the Jewish National Home in Palestine and
                                                  entrust the organization of Jewish education to
                                                  such Council.</item>
                                                  <item>“(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) On being
                                                  satisfied that the constitution of such Council
                                                  precludes the making of private profit, offer to
                                                  the Council in priority any concession for public
                                                  works or for the development of natural resources
                                                  which it may be found desirable to grant.</item>
                                                  </list></item>
                                                <item>“(III) The Mandatary Power shall encourage the
                                                  wisest measure of self-government for localities
                                                  practicable in the conditions of the
                                                  country.</item>
                                                <item>“(IV) There shall be forever the fullest
                                                  freedom of religious worship for all creeds in
                                                  Palestine. There shall be no discrimination among
                                                  the inhabitants with regard to citizenship and
                                                  civil rights, on the grounds of religion, or of
                                                  race.</item>
                                                <item>“(V) (Provision to be inserted relating to the
                                                  control of Holy Places.)”</item>
                                            </list></p>
                                    </quote></p>
                                <p>(Paris Peace Conf. 180.03101/48)</p></note> and he asked
                            permission to distribute copies of the same to the members of the
                            Conference.</p>
                        <pb facs="0172" n="162" xml:id="pg_162"/>
                        <p>Continuing, M. Sokolow said that the Conference would understand his
                            emotions, now that the solemn hour awaited during 18 centuries by the
                            Jewish people had, at length, arrived. The Delegates had come to claim
                            their historic rights to Palestine, the land of Israel, where, in
                            ancient times, the Jewish people had created a civilisation which had
                            since exercised an enormous influence on humanity. There they had lived
                            happily until the country had been lost; since when a long continued
                            martyrdom had been suffered. Now this people possessed no land and no
                            national power. Undoubtedly, happy groups of Jews lived in the countries
                            of Western Europe and in the United States of America; but those where,
                            comparatively speaking, only small groups. The great majority of the
                            Jewish <pb facs="0173" n="163" xml:id="pg_163"/> people did not live in
                            those countries and the problem of the masses remained to be solved. The
                            Jews would never forget that France had been the first to recognise the
                            rights of man and personal liberty, and it was under that influence that
                            the Jews had obtained rights of citizenship in other countries. It was
                            in Great Britain that the ancient traditions of Zionism first took root.
                            It was in Great Britain, and especially in the British Colonies, that
                            the Jews had been able to establish prosperous settlements. In Italy,
                            the Jews had taken an important part in the wars of liberation: the
                            Jewish people there were happy, well organised and able to take a part
                            in the government of the country. In the United States of America,
                            3,000,000 Jews enjoyed the rights of citizenship. Mere rights of
                            citizenship, however, were not sufficient to satisfy the ideals of the
                            Jews, who craved for a national existence. Consequently, for the great
                            suffering majority of the Jews, living in Eastern Europe, a place would
                            have to be prepared where they would be at home and among their own
                            kind. During the late terrible war the Allies had promised to help the
                            Jews to found a Jewish national centre, where the real home of the
                            Jewish people had always been. This was the only possible solution of
                            the Jewish problem. Sustained by that promise, the Jews had been able to
                            organise and to support the Great Powers loyally by creating an entente
                            of all the Jewish parties within the Entente of the Great Powers. Now, a
                            victory of great ideals and of justice having been gained, the hour of
                            deliverance of his unhappy people had struck: and the old Jewish
                            traditions could again be introduced in the land of their ancestors,
                            combined with the ideals of New Europe, thus leading to a
                            re-constitution of a people and the transformation of a country. The
                            memoir which he had circulated merely gave the Zionist plans for the
                            realisation of the hopes of the Jewish people, and, with the permission
                            of the Conference, he would read the following extract:— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The Zionist Organisation respectfully submits the following
                                    draft resolutions for the consideration of the Peace
                                    Conference:— <list>
                                        <label>1.</label>
                                        <item>The High Contracting Parties recognise the historic
                                            title of the Jewish people to Palestine and the right of
                                            the Jews to reconstitute in Palestine their National
                                            Home.</item>
                                        <label>2.</label>
                                        <item>The boundaries of Palestine shall be as declared in
                                            the schedule annexed hereto.</item>
                                        <label>3.</label>
                                        <item>The sovereign possession of Palestine shall be vested
                                            in the League of Nations and the Government entrusted to
                                            Great Britain as Mandatory of the League.</item>
                                        <label>4.</label>
                                        <item>(Provision to be inserted relating to the application
                                            in Palestine of such of the general conditions attached
                                            to mandates as are suitable to the case).</item>
                                        <label>5.</label>
                                        <item>The mandate shall be subject also to the following
                                            special conditions:— <pb facs="0174" n="164" xml:id="pg_164"/>
                                            <list>
                                                <label>(1)</label>
                                                <item>Palestine shall be placed under such
                                                  political, administrative and economic conditions
                                                  as will secure the establishment there of the
                                                  Jewish National Home and ultimately render
                                                  possible the creation of an autonomous
                                                  Commonwealth, it being clearly understood that
                                                  nothing shall be done which may prejudice the
                                                  civil and religious rights of existing non-Jewish
                                                  communities in Palestine or the rights and
                                                  political status enjoyed by Jews in any other
                                                  country.”</item>
                                            </list></item>
                                    </list></p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>In conclusion, he would be ready to answer any questions that might be
                            put to him, but he would, in the first place, ask the Conference to hear
                            his colleague, Dr. C. Weizmann, the President of the Enquiry Committee
                            sent to Palestine on behalf of the Zionist Executive Committee, who
                            would give practical information on the subject of the realisation of
                            the Zionist programme.</p>
                        <p><seg type="margin">(b) Statement by Dr. Weizmann, Member of the Zionist
                                Organization</seg>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. Weizmann</hi> pointed out that the war had left
                            the Jewish people weaker comparatively than any other people in the
                            world. Before the war, six to seven million Jews in Russia had been
                            systematically oppressed but that oppression had possessed the grandeur
                            of a great tragedy, which had acted as a source of inspiration to all
                            Jews. Now, even the grandeur had disappeared, and the community was
                            being ground down by the political machinery which had been set up in
                            Russia. It was impossible for him to make any forecasts, but even the
                            most sanguine would agree that those parts could not settle down for
                            many years to come. Meanwhile the Jews, as the most feeble element,
                            would suffer most, and as a result Jewish emigration, which before the
                            war had reached the figure of 250,000 a year, would increase enormously,
                            whilst at the same time the power of absorption in the countries of
                            Western Europe and of America would considerably decrease. The Great
                            Powers would naturally scrutinise every alien who claimed to enter their
                            countries, and the Jew would be regarded as a typical wandering alien.
                            As a result the Jews would find themselves knocking around the world,
                            seeking a refuge and unable to find one. The problem, therefore, was a
                            very serious one, and no statesman could contemplate it without being
                            impelled to find an equitable solution.</p>
                        <p>In his opinion, the solution proposed by the Zionist organisation was the
                            only one which would in the long run bring peace, and at the same time
                            transform Jewish energy into a constructive force, instead of its being
                            dissipated into destructive tendencies or bitterness.</p>
                        <p>Palestine possessed great possibilities. The country was not very densely
                            populated: There were some 600,000 to 700,000 people occupying 40,000
                            square kilometres, which gave a population of 10 to 15 per square
                            kilometre. On the other hand, in Lebanon, which resembled it in many
                            aspects, the density of the population was 160 <pb facs="0175" n="165" xml:id="pg_165"/> per square kilometre. Consequently, in Palestine
                            there was room for an increase of at least four to five million people,
                            without encroaching on the legitimate interests of the people already
                            there.</p>
                        <p>The Zionists wished to settle Jews in the empty spaces of Palestine,
                            organising the settlements to be created by the expenditure of their own
                            money and the exercise of their brains.</p>
                        <p>The Zionist Association demanded, in the name of the people who had
                            suffered martyrdom for eighteen centuries that they should be able,
                            immediately peace was signed, to tell their co-religionists in the
                            Ukraine, in Poland, and in other parts of Eastern Europe, that they
                            would be taken to Palestine, there to be put on the land. That was the
                            essence of what the Zionists required, and with that object in view they
                            had taken the liberty of drawing up the following resolution:— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“To this end the Mandatory Power shall <hi rend="italic">inter
                                        alia:</hi>— <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Promote Jewish immigration and close settlement on the
                                            land, the established rights of the present non-Jewish
                                            population being equitably safeguarded.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Accept the co-operation in such measures of a Council
                                            representative of the Jews of Palestine and of the world
                                            that may be established for the development of the
                                            Jewish National Home in Palestine and entrust the
                                            organisation of Jewish education to such Council.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>On being satisfied that the constitution of such
                                            Council precludes the making of private profit, offer to
                                            the Council in priority any concession for the
                                            development of natural resources which it may be found
                                            desirable to grant.”</item>
                                    </list></p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>In conclusion, he would add that he spoke in the name of a million Jews
                            who, staff in hand were waiting the signal to move. It would be the duty
                            of the Zionist Association to organise immigration successfully, but the
                            Jewish leaders would be faced with a far greater catastrophe if they
                            found themselves unable to tell their people to wait until they received
                            the signal. For the fulfillment of their plans the Jewish Associations
                            required the support of the Great Powers, and in full hope they left
                            their case in their hands.</p>
                        <p><seg type="margin">(c) Statement by M. Ussischkins, Member of the
                                Executive Committee of the Zionist Association and President of the
                                South Russian Jewish National Assembly</seg>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Ussischkins</hi> said that he appeared before
                            the Conference in his capacity as a member of the Executive Committee of
                            the Zionist Organisation, and also as President of the National Assembly
                            representing 3,000,000 Jews of South Russia, an Assembly which, in the
                            month of November last adopted a resolution proclaiming the historic
                            rights of the Jewish people to Palestine. It was his earnest desire to
                            support the claims submitted by the two previous speakers, the
                            representatives of the Zionist Organisation.</p>
                        <pb facs="0176" n="166" xml:id="pg_166"/>
                        <p><seg type="margin">(d) Statement by M. Spire, on behalf of the French
                                Zionist</seg>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Spire</hi> said that he spoke in the name of the
                            French Zionists, who were not in the majority amongst the Jews in
                            France. He wished to associate himself entirely with the claims put
                            forward by the Zionist Organisation. He felt certain that France, which
                            had ever defended the rights of the oppressed, would support these
                            claims. Furthermore, it was only natural for a French Jew to express
                            those views. It was only on one point that the Zionist movement could
                            disturb the French, namely, on the question of the ancient privileges
                            which the French had always enjoyed in Palestine. In regard to that
                            question, the French Zionists trusted to the justice of the Conference,
                            feeling confident that the mandate would be granted to the country most
                            competent to exercise the power, not only in its own interests, but in
                            the interests of all nationalities.</p>
                        <p><seg type="margin">(e) Statement by M. Sylvain Levi, Professor at the
                                Collège de France, Paris</seg>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Sylvain Levi</hi> said that his only claim to
                            speak was that he had accompanied, on the invitation of the Zionist
                            Association and at the request of the French Government, the Zionist
                            Committee of Inquiry, sent from France to Palestine to report on the
                            Zionist movement. He greatly appreciated the honour which had thereby
                            been accorded to him, since he was not himself a Zionist, and only a Jew
                            by origin, that is, Jewish in sentiment, but French above all.</p>
                        <p>He had devoted much time to the study of this question, and for that
                            reason wished to present certain aspects of the case to the Conference.
                            It would not be necessary for him to call the attention of the
                            Conference to the situation of the Jews in Eastern and Central Europe.
                            His colleagues had already drawn a picture of the indescribable misery
                            which the Jewish people were there suffering. Millions of men who were
                            not at home in the countries in which they lived, felt that they
                            possessed no mother country, and that their national life was confined
                            to intercourse amongst themselves. For these people Palestine was the
                            “country of their ancestors”; the country of their dreams—a sort of
                            terrestrial paradise; and it was there that they thought they would best
                            be able to develop their national energies. That feeling was so strongly
                            implanted in the minds of the Jewish people that it could never be
                            uprooted. The only question was: how could those national ideals best be
                            satisfied? The Zionist movement in Palestine did not propose to initiate
                            an entirely new work; a beginning had already been made, and magnificent
                            results had already been achieved. It would be unnecessary for him to
                            point to the splendid Jewish colonies already established in Palestine
                            under the auspices of Baron Rothschild: Colonies which formed veritable
                            oases in the middle of the surrounding desert. Furthermore, the
                            “Universal Jewish Alliance”, which had been in <pb facs="0177" n="167" xml:id="pg_167"/> existence for over 50 years having been founded on
                            the true principles of the French Revolution, had begun its work in
                            Palestine by the establishment of an agricultural school in 1876.
                            Subsequently, other schools had been opened in other localities, such as
                            Jerusalem, Jaffa, etc. each of which had rendered the greatest service
                            to the people. In the end, Zionism had arisen. To that movement he was
                            legitimately entitled to pay a high tribute, as he did not himself
                            belong to it. Its great merit lay in the fact that it had raised the
                            Jewish moral[e] in those countries of Eastern Europe, where the moral[e]
                            had been fast sinking, by supplying spiritual food and by engendering a
                            true religious feeling. As a result of the feeling so engendered, the
                            desire for Palestine was born. The special task which Zionism had set
                            for itself was to direct a flow of Jewish immigration towards Palestine,
                            especially from Eastern Europe. That was the problem for which a
                            solution now had to be found. With the permission of the Conference he
                            would talk with the frankness of a historian, who desired to face the
                            problem honestly and squarely, without attempting to hide any of the
                            difficulties.</p>
                        <p>The first difficulty lay in the great disproportion which existed between
                            the area of Palestine and the millions of people who might want to go
                            there from Eastern Europe. In the second place, the actual condition of
                            the country, which was at present able to maintain only a small
                            population owing to the climatic and other causes brought about by the
                            action of men and the misgovernment of the authorities. At the present
                            moment, some 600,000 or 700,000 Arabs only dwelt in that country, but it
                            would be impossible for an equal number of Jews to adapt themselves to
                            the same conditions of life, since they had in Europe, and especially in
                            Western Europe, acquired certain methods of life which would not be
                            satisfied by the conditions which were sufficient for the Arabs. In the
                            third place, the masses of people who might wish to return to Palestine,
                            would largely be drawn from those countries where they had been
                            persecuted and ill-treated, and the mentality which such a regime was
                            likely to engender could be easily realised. Those people would carry
                            with them into Palestine highly explosive passions, conducive to very
                            serious trouble in a country which might be likened to a concentration
                            camp of Jewish refugees. The Conference that had created the League of
                            Nations would easily understand that nations could not be created at
                            will, and the realisation of a certain number of aspirations would not
                            suffice to create a national entity. The problem was an extremely
                            difficult one, especially as it would concern Jewish people drawn from
                            so many countries such as Poland, the Caucasus, Balkans, Morocco, Spain,
                            etc.; the fusion of all these people would take time, and the time
                            required might be lengthy. This difficulty had been fully recognised by
                            the Zionist Organisation, <pb facs="0178" n="168" xml:id="pg_168"/>
                            which had attempted to find a solution. A solution had been found and
                            put forward consisting in the creation of an International Jewish
                            Council, which by some means or other (about which he was not quite
                            clear) would act both as the guardian and the political ruler of
                            Palestine. The idea was an ingenious one, but, as a Frenchman of Jewish
                            origin, he feared the results. It would be dangerous to create a
                            precedent whereby certain people who already possessed the rights of
                            citizenship in one country would be called upon to govern and to
                            exercise other rights of citizenship in a new country. In other words,
                            an attempt would be made to apply the principles of the law of Delbrück
                            to the Jews, already sufficiently suspect; and it would in his opinion
                            be a sad beginning to inherit anything of the kind from Germany. In this
                            way people possessing dual rights of citizenship would have been created
                            able to exercise their rights in the country of their residence and also
                            in Palestine, in which they had no rights and which they did not
                            inhabit.</p>
                        <p>The Zionist Organisation, however, placed their confidence in the
                            mandatory system, provided the Jews who decided to settle in Palestine
                            could little by little be granted the right of self-government. The
                            Jewish groups already settled in Palestine clearly showed how quickly
                            they could enter into municipal life, and solve the most difficult
                            problems; some of the Jewish municipalities having even joined together
                            to form, as it were, small autonomous republics, which had only been
                            molested by the Turkish authorities. Having visited the country, he was
                            able to realise that this municipal activity could become national, as
                            soon as the country was occupied by a large Jewish majority.</p>
                        <p>He (Mr. Levi) had previously referred to the spirit of the French
                            Revolution which had led to the creation of the Universal Jewish
                            Alliance. To this spirit all its members adhered. For many years the
                            Jews had, in the countries inhabited by them, claimed equality of
                            rights, but those claims had not yet everywhere been admitted. Under the
                            circumstances, it seemed to him shocking that the Jews, as soon as their
                            rights of equality were about to be recognised in all countries of the
                            world, should already seek to obtain exceptional privileges for
                            themselves in Palestine. Privileges so obtained as a rule did not profit
                            either the giver or the receiver. He had sufficient confidence in the
                            activities and driving force of the ideals of the Jews of Eastern Europe
                            to believe that they would never abandon the attainment of their goal,
                            and even if their other aspirations were to weaken, the time would come
                            when violent upheavals would again cause a flow of emigration towards
                            Palestine, which must, sooner or later, become a purely Jewish
                            territory. He was not in a position, neither was he entitled, to find a
                            solution, but it appeared to him that it might be possible to create
                            some large Jewish Committee by grouping <pb facs="0179" n="169" xml:id="pg_169"/> together all the interested parties, whose
                            function it would be to supervise emigration, to act as bankers, to buy
                            and distribute land, to organise public works, to undertake sanitary
                            measures and to take charge of education, etc., but without possessing
                            any political rights.</p>
                        <p>In conclusion, he wished to place on record the great part played by
                            France in the organisation of the Jews in Palestine. Whatever country
                            might eventually be appointed the Mandatory in Palestine, he trusted
                            France would be permitted to continue her beneficent educational work,
                            by maintaining the schools which had been of such inestimable value to
                            the peoples of Palestine. France and Palestine were both Mediterranean
                            nations, and both, in their own time, had had a great influence on the
                            development of civilisation throughout the world. Leaving out of
                            consideration the political aspect of the case, he would remind the
                            Conference that a very serious and important problem required solution.
                            He neither over-estimated nor under-estimated the virtues of national
                            groups. But it would be admitted that the Jewish race had, during the
                            period of its martyrdom, displayed a magnificent resistance and proved
                            its constant passion for civilisation, high culture and science. It was
                            the Jews in Palestine who first proclaimed those ideals towards which
                            the world was still endeavouring to advance. For those ideals Jews had
                            suffered persecution and death, and they believed that on the shores of
                            the Mediterranean they would find the realisation of their hopes. They
                            believed that, if restored to the conditions which had enabled their
                            ancestors to give rise to the great Hebrew movement, they would again be
                            able to recover their past splendour and to contribute their share
                            towards the regeneration of mankind.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lansing</hi> asked Dr. Weizmann to clear up some
                            confusion which existed in his mind as to the correct meaning of the
                            words “Jewish National Home”. Did that mean an autonomous Jewish
                            Government?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. Weizmann</hi> replied in the negative. The
                            Zionist organisation did not want an autonomous Jewish Government, but
                            merely to establish in Palestine, under a mandatory Power, an
                            administration, not necessarily Jewish, which would render it possible
                            to send into Palestine 70 to 80,000 Jews annually. The Association would
                            require to have permission at the same time to build Jewish schools,
                            where Hebrew would be taught, and in that way to build up gradually a
                            nationality which would be as Jewish as the French nation was French and
                            the British nation British. Later on, when the Jews formed the large
                            majority, they would be ripe to establish such a Government as would
                            answer to the state of the development of the country and to their
                            ideals.</p>
                        <p>The Zionist Association fully realised the great difficulty of the
                            problem, and, in fact, had the problem been an easy one to solve, <pb facs="0180" n="170" xml:id="pg_170"/> it would never have been
                            submitted to the Conference of the Great Powers. On the other hand, the
                            solution suggested would be easier than the solution of the difficulties
                            which would arise if the Jews were left in Russia. The formation of a
                            Jewish organisation had been proposed, embracing all elements that would
                            co-operate in solving the problem to be faced. That Council would have
                            no political rights. Consequently the fear that the Jews would be
                            accused of double allegiance was groundless. On the other hand the Jews
                            outside Palestine must supply the money and the men, and the Council
                            would have to be organised for that purpose and for that purpose only. A
                            similar Council had already existed in the creation of the Jewish
                            Alliance, which had been an international organisation created for the
                            express purpose of establishing schools in Palestine.</p>
                        <p>As a Russian Jew, he was entitled to say that the Jews in Russia lived in
                            an atmosphere which was not conducive to quiet thinking. On the other
                            hand the colonies in Palestine which had been described in such glowing
                            terms by Professor Levi had been created by Russian Jews, and they had
                            succeeded in transforming deserts into flourishing gardens, even under
                            the Turkish yoke.</p>
                        <p>In conclusion, at the present moment Palestine could not hold a large
                            number of people. The Conference had no doubt noticed the discrepancy
                            between the figures which he had given as representing the possible
                            population of Palestine and the number of emigrants, 50,000 to 60,000
                            per annum, which he had subsequently suggested. That was due to the
                            present condition of the country. But the Association desired to
                            transform the country, to make it capable of supporting a much larger
                            number of inhabitants, just as had been done in California and in
                            Tunisia. In the latter country in 1882 around Sfax only 45,000 olive
                            trees were to be found, whereas in 1914, 8,000,000 olive trees had been
                            planted. What had been done in Tunisia might be done even better in
                            Palestine, since the climate and soil in the latter country were
                            infinitely superior. With the help of Jewish funds an Association had
                            been formed to carry out that programme, and it would undoubtedly
                            achieve success. The difficulties to be met with in attempting to solve
                            these problems were nothing if compared with the difficulties to be
                            faced by the Jews living in Eastern Europe, who constituted 96% of the
                            total number of Jews in Europe.</p>
                        <p>In making his statement he spoke for 96% of the Jews of the world, who
                            shared the views which he had endeavoured to express that afternoon.</p>
                        <p>(The Zionist Mission and Experts in Zionism then withdrew)</p>
                        <p>3. <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Pichon</hi> suggested that the following
                            questions should be <pb facs="0181" n="171" xml:id="pg_171"/> considered
                            at the next meeting to be held on Saturday next, March 1st:— <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Report of the Financial Drafting Committee. <seg type="margin">Agenda for Next Meeting (a) Subject for Agenda, Paper
                                        Proposed by M. Pichon</seg></item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Report of the Economic Drafting Committee.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Report on Morocco.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>Statement by the representatives of the Island of
                                    Aaland.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p><seg type="margin">(b) Morocco</seg>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Balfour</hi> said that he had only received a
                            copy of the resolutions concerning Morocco late the previous evening.
                            The question was a very difficult and complicated one, and it would be
                            necessary for him to obtain papers from London. Under these conditions
                            he suggested that the discussion of that question should be adjourned
                            until the following Monday.</p>
                        <p>(This was agreed to.)</p>
                        <p><seg type="margin">(c) Aaland Island</seg>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Balfour</hi>, continuing, said that in regard
                            to the Aaland Islands he understood the people of Aaland wanted to be
                            joined to Sweden. Technically, they were Finnish at the moment, though
                            they had been Russian before Finland became a separate country. He
                            wished to enquire whether it was a matter which the Conference had
                            either the right or the competence to determine.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">M. Sonnino</hi> said that Finland had not been
                            recognised by Italy, so that from the Italian point of view the Islands
                            were still Russian.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. White</hi> reported that the representatives of
                            the Island of Aaland had been to see him, and had stated that they
                            wished to join Sweden, for the reason that modern guns would be able
                            easily to reach Stockholm from the Aaland Islands.</p>
                        <p>But Mr. White had enquired from the representatives how they thought the
                            Conference could deal with the question. They had replied that the
                            Islands of Aaland now formed part of Finland, and Finland had previously
                            belong[ed] to Russia.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">M. Sonnino</hi> expressed the view that the
                            Conference had agreed to reserve all questions appertaining to Russia,
                            such as those relating to the Esthonians, Lithuanians, Lettians and
                            Ukrainians, until the Russian question came under discussion. Only one
                            exception was made, in the case of Poland, because Russia herself, when
                            an Ally, had recognised the independence of that country.</p>
                        <p>Taking these facts into consideration, he thought it would be better to
                            study the whole Russian question at one and the same time, especially as
                            in the case of the Aaland Islands the Conference was being asked to take
                            something from someone and give it to a third party.</p>
                        <p>As a matter of fact, he thought the question fell outside the competence
                            of the Conference, though it might be taken up by the League of
                            Nations.</p>
                        <pb facs="0182" n="172" xml:id="pg_172"/>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">M. Pichon</hi> said that the representatives of the
                            Aaland Islands had also been to see him, basing their request for
                            annexation to Sweden on the ground of the right of peoples to
                            self-determination as enunciated by President Wilson.</p>
                        <p>The representatives of the Aaland Islands had also submitted a <hi rend="italic">memoire</hi>. The Swedish Government had also asked to
                            send representatives to the Conference to discuss this same question. He
                            thought the question of the Aaland Islands should be adjourned until a
                            decision had been reached on the question of Russia.</p>
                        <p>(It was agreed to postpone consideration of the question relating to the
                            Aaland Islands.)</p>
                        <p>It was agreed that the following questions should be discussed at the
                            next meeting to be held on Saturday, March 1st, 1919 at 3 o’clock p.m.:— <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Report of Committee of the Financial Drafting Committee. <seg type="margin">(d) Agenda for Meeting on 1st
                                    March</seg></item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Report of the Economic Drafting Committee.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>4. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Balfour</hi> enquired what action had been
                            taken on the resolution reached the previous day in regard to the
                            creation of a neutral zone in Transylvania. Who would be responsible for
                            carrying out the policy decided upon? <seg type="margin">Neutral Zone in
                                Transylvania</seg></p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">M. Pichon</hi> replied that a despatch had already
                            been sent by the French Government to General Franchet D’Esperey,
                            Commander-in-Chief of the Allied Armies of the Orient, calling on him to
                            take the necessary action.</p>
                        <p>(The meeting then adjourned to Saturday, March 1st, 1919, at 3 p.m.)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>, 28th February, 1919.</p>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>