<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-12-12T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-12-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="165" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d165">
                        <head>165. Report of a Policy Review Committee Meeting<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d165fn1">Source: Carter Library, National
                                Security Affairs, Staff Material, Far East, <persName corresp="#p_OM_2">Oksenberg</persName> Subject File, Box 45,
                                Meetings: 12/6–12/78. Secret. <persName corresp="#p_IKF_1">Inderfurth</persName> sent this report to <persName corresp="#p_OM_2">Oksenberg</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HB_1">Huberman</persName> under a December 13
                                covering memorandum that stated, “Attached is the report which Zbig
                                gave the President yesterday on the above meeting. Please note the
                                President’s ‘OK’ and follow up.” The Summary of Conclusions of the
                                December 12 <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> meeting is <ref target="#d164">Document 164</ref>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1978-12-12T16:00:00-05:00" notBefore="1978-12-12T00:00:00-05:00" when="1978-12-12">undated</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> on China Science and Technology</p>
                        <p>Yesterday’s <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> on China surveyed our
                            entire <gloss target="#t_SnT_1">S&amp;T</gloss> relationship, but
                            decisions were necessary only on the communications satellite. There was
                            unanimous interagency agreement to slightly upgrade the quality of the
                            satellite we are prepared to offer Peking.<note n="2" xml:id="d165fn2">Carter made a checkmark in the margin next to this
                                paragraph.</note> Agreement was also reached to tie in our
                            willingness to provide and launch the satellite with Chinese agreement
                            to purchase ground stations from us rather than would-be Western
                            European or Japanese competitors. Decisions were also reached to
                            continue to minimize the technology to be transferred in the sale.</p>
                        <p>The total package of two satellites, launching, and ground stations is on
                            the order of half a billion dollars and would be extremely important to
                            U.S. industry.<note n="3" xml:id="d165fn3">Carter wrote what appears to
                                be “ok” in the margin next to this paragraph.</note> The meeting
                            also touched on the evolving <gloss target="#t_SnT_1">S&amp;T</gloss>
                            exchange program involving <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss>, NSF,
                            Energy, and Agriculture, all of which are moving according to the plan
                            you have previously approved.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>