<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-01-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-01-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="200" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d200">
                        <head>200. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>) to
                            President Carter<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d200fn1">Source:
                                Carter Library, <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>
                                Donated Material, Subject File, Box 42, Weekly Reports (to the
                                President), 82–90 (12/78–3/79). Secret; Eyes Only. At the top of the
                                page, Carter wrote, “Zbig—Interesting. J.”</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1979-01-26">January 26, 1979</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Weekly Report #86</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>[Omitted here is material unrelated to China.]</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">US–<gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>–China</p>
                        <p>Normalization with China obviously carries with it the risk of Soviet
                            over-reaction and miscalculations in both Peking and Moscow. We are now
                            directly in the middle of a very delicate balancing act—one which is
                            complicated by the fact that both <persName corresp="#p_BL_1">Brezhnev</persName> and Deng are old and we could, even in the next
                            few years, see significant governmental changes in both countries.</p>
                        <p>There is also a ripple effect. The Germans, for example, are already
                            nervous that the Soviet response to our playing “the China card” will
                            result in the Russians playing “the German card.” By this they are
                            evidently concerned that pressure could be brought on Berlin or that
                            some other aspect of Soviet-West German relations could be adversely
                            affected.</p>
                        <p>Thus, it is extremely important for allied solidarity as well as global
                            stability for this three-cornered relationship to be handled with the
                            utmost care. From a political standpoint it is important to maintain
                            momentum with both Peking and Moscow. I believe this means that you
                            should plan on emerging from both the Deng visit and the <persName corresp="#p_BL_1">Brezhnev</persName> visit with concrete plans to
                            visit both China and the Soviet Union before the 1980 election. (You
                            should make some tentative scheduling decisions on this even before you
                            meet with Deng.)</p>
                        <p>Such summits in Peking and Moscow will not only enhance your own prestige
                            but serve as a focus for structuring our relations with both China and
                            the Soviet Union over the next 18 months. They will provide both
                            reassurance of a continuing relationship with both countries and
                            positive incentives for both to maintain a measure of restraint in their
                            mutual relations.</p>
                        <p>My second recommendation is that you take more direct command of our
                            relationship with the Soviet Union. You should insist on <pb facs="0777" n="738" xml:id="pg_738"/> tight personal control of all actions
                            affecting our relationship with the Soviet Union. You have taken this
                            approach in regard to the Middle East and China with significant
                            success. There is a potential for great disarray, given the different
                            ideological views in your Administration. We cannot afford this disarray
                            any longer, but it is likely to intensify in the absence of better
                            discipline.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is material unrelated to China.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>