<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-05-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="244" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d244">
                        <head>244. Memorandum From the Under Secretary of State for Economic Affairs
                                (<persName corresp="#p_CRN_1">Cooper</persName>) to Secretary of
                            State <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d244fn1">Source: Department of State,
                                Executive Secretariat (<gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss>–I) Files:
                                Lot 81 D 117, Principal Memo File, Apr–May–Jun 1979. Confidential.
                                    “<gloss target="#t_CV_1">CV</gloss>” is stamped at the bottom of
                                the first page.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1979-05-18">May 18, 1979</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KJM_1">Kreps</persName>’
                            Mission to China</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KJM_1">Kreps</persName>’ May 5–15 visit
                            to China went very well. It produced many tangible results and was full
                            of good-will on both sides, conveyed in a very businesslike way.
                            Juanita’s performance was excellent. She was characteristically gracious
                            and in full command of the material under discussion.</p>
                        <p>The main tangible results of the visit were the signing of a
                            claims/assets agreement (negotiated and initialled by <persName corresp="#p_BWM_1">Mike Blumenthal</persName> in March)<note n="2" xml:id="d244fn2">See <ref target="#d222">Document 222</ref>.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KJM_1">Kreps</persName> and Zhang Jingfu
                                signed the agreement on May 11. (30 UST 1957; TIAS 9306)</note> and
                            the initialing of a trade agreement negotiated during the course of her
                            visit. We made clear that successful implementation of the trade
                            agreement would depend on the successful conclusion of a textile
                            agreement. Negotiations on that are to resume next week.</p>
                        <p>Credit for the trade agreement goes largely to <persName corresp="#p_BWG_1">Bill Barraclough</persName> and his interagency
                            team, who worked under pressure for 10 days to produce the agreement. In
                            the end, we got satisfactory treatment on most of the issues that we
                            initially sought.</p>
                        <p>In addition, Juanita signed an agreement on trade exhibitions<note n="3" xml:id="d244fn3">This agreement was signed on May 10. (30 UST 4472;
                                TIAS 9470)</note> and four agreements involving scientific and
                            technological (e.g., meteorological) cooperation. We also opened
                            negotiations for a civil aviation agreement and a maritime agreement,
                            but both of those will be difficult. To over-simplify, we want cargo
                            sharing in the maritime agreement and the Chinese want “cargo” sharing
                            in the aviation agreement, whereas in each case the other side
                            objects.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Remarks on China and the Chinese:</p>
                        <p>We were very courteously treated throughout our stay. There was no
                            political haranguing. There was much expression of good-will, followed
                            by businesslike discussion of economic issues. The Chinese very much
                            want to learn about how the international trading system works, and much
                            time had to be spent in explanations to them, both of international
                            practices and of our own laws. They made clear on many oc<pb facs="0918" n="879" xml:id="pg_879"/>casions that they want to follow normal
                            international practices in their trade and financial arrangements. They
                            are used to operating much more on the basis of oral understandings than
                            we, and much of our difficulty in negotiating the trade agreement was
                            getting written down the level of detail which we find appropriate in
                            international agreements. Moreover, Chinese hesitation vis-a-vis these
                            negotiations was induced in part by what they consider their unhappy
                            experience in the claims/assets negotiations. They now feel they yielded
                            too much there, with insufficient assurance of cooperation by us in
                            realizing their claims in the U.S. (this has now been worked out, I
                            hope, satisfactorily.)</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier Deng was very impressive. He conveyed a clear grasp of
                            Chinese needs and problems and he asked excellent questions about U.S.
                            policies in the commercial field. He observed that two questions are
                            asked frequently abroad about China’s rush to modernization: Would China
                            continue on this course, and would it be able to pay its way? In
                            response to the first question, Deng asserted that the policy of opening
                            China up and the absorption of large amounts of foreign capital and
                            technology has not changed in recent months. It is necessary for China’s
                            development over the remainder of the century. He went on to observe
                            that, international speculation notwithstanding, Chinese policy is not
                            made by him alone, but reflects a broad internal consensus. Rather, the
                            Chinese are readjusting their plans to take into account the practical
                            realities and limits to rapid development. In particular, they have
                            discovered a shortage of electricity and inadequacies in their
                            transportation system. Thus, while their fundamental emphasis on
                            agriculture and light industry remains unaltered, a necessary condition
                            for realizing improvements there is additional investment in power and
                            transportation. He also acknowledged a severe shortage of technological
                            and managerial personnel in China. He indicated that to attract foreign
                            capital, China would have to adapt its practices to acceptable
                            international practices. In particular, foreigners would need a say in
                            running joint venture factories, including the right to fire workers;
                            and they would need assurances on their right to remit profits. China
                            accepted this.</p>
                        <p>On the second question, concerning China’s ability to pay, Deng
                            acknowledged this as an important constraint and suggested that for that
                            reason China would look favorably on compensation agreements, i.e.,
                            agreements in which payment is made partly or wholly in terms of
                            Chinese-produced goods. He also underlined the importance of getting
                            greater access to the U.S. market through <gloss target="#t_MFN_1">MFN</gloss> tariff treatment.</p>
                        <p>Deng also questioned us closely, largely for his own information, on our
                            policies regarding controls on exports of technology, and wondered out
                            loud whether we couldn’t relax these controls since they make doing
                            business with American firms difficult.</p>
                        <pb facs="0919" n="880" xml:id="pg_880"/>
                        <p>Throughout our visit there were scattered references to the Gang of Four,
                            but conversations did not dwell heavily on political issues. The
                            question of our granting <gloss target="#t_MFN_1">MFN</gloss> to the
                            Soviet Union was raised by Chinese trade negotiators only after the
                            conclusion of the draft trade agreement, and even then somewhat
                            offhandedly. The question of Taiwan came up only in discussions of civil
                            aviation and maritime issues, where the Chinese authorities emphasized
                            strongly their requirement that we not recognize the <gloss target="#t_ROC_1">ROC</gloss> markings as a “national flag.” They
                            also underlined the necessity of our abolishing any intergovernmental
                            agreements with Taiwan in these areas. They emphasized, however, that
                            these two requirements need not lead to the alteration of actual
                            shipping or aviation between the U.S. and Taiwan.</p>
                        <p>Apart from these few political references, almost all of our discussions
                            were on the prospects and problems of the Chinese economy and on how
                            improved contact with the U.S. and other industrialized countries can
                            help.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>