<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-02-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-02-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="301" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d301">
                        <head>301. Briefing Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for
                            East Asian and Pacific Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">Holbrooke</persName>) to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d301fn1">Source: Department of State, Executive Secretariat
                                Files: Lot 84 D 241, <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_BH_2">Brown</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> Luncheons. Top Secret; Sensitive. Drafted
                                by <persName corresp="#p_AMA_1">Armacost</persName> on February 27.
                                Attached to a February 27 briefing memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_BR_1">Bartholomew</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> before <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>’s February 28 luncheon
                                meeting with <persName corresp="#p_BH_2">Brown</persName> and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>. (Ibid.) At
                                the bottom of the last page of this memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">Holbrooke</persName> wrote, “All this has
                                been coordinated with <persName corresp="#p_BR_1">Reggie
                                    [Bartholomew]</persName>—but no one else, per your instructions.
                                RH.”</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1980-02-27">undated</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center">Technology Transfers and Military Sales to China</p>
                        <p>Harold intends to raise this issue at tomorrow’s <gloss target="#t_VBB_1">VBB</gloss> lunch. The attached paper embodies the recommendations
                            of the <gloss target="#t_EA_1">EA</gloss> “informal group.”<note n="2" xml:id="d301fn2">Tab A, printed below.</note> In toto the steps
                            proposed may suggest substantial adjustments in our policy toward China.
                            In fact, however, these steps essentially implement decisions already
                            adopted.</p>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Munitions Control List.</hi> While this list (Tab A)
                            looks long, it excludes 13 of the 19 categories on the Munitions Control
                            List, and merely identifies those categories and parts of categories
                            from which we will consider items for licensing on a case-by-case
                                basis.<note n="3" xml:id="d301fn3">The list is attached but not
                                printed as Enclosure 1 to Tab A.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Chinese Requests.</hi> Our proposed response to
                            outstanding Chinese requests is outlined in Tab A, Encl. 2.<note n="4" xml:id="d301fn4">Enclosure 2 to Tab A, “Proposed Response to Chinese
                                Request,” is attached but not printed.</note> The Defense
                            Department’s office of Research and Engineering and the Joint Staff have
                            reviewed the list with an eye to possible adverse consequences to our
                            security and that of our Asian friends and allies. Their willingness to
                            approve further discussion of various items reflects a variety of
                            considerations. Some (e.g. Honeywell Level 66 Computers) have previously
                            been sold to the <pb facs="1133" n="1094" xml:id="pg_1094"/>
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. Others (e.g. 100 <gloss target="#t_MB_1">MB</gloss> disk driver or LTN–51 INS) contain
                            technology we have already sold to the <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> for civilian purposes. In still other cases (e.g.
                                <gloss target="#t_IR_1">IR</gloss> sensors) sales would be subject
                            to strict conditions—e.g. early generation systems only.</p>
                        <p>3. <hi rend="italic">U.S. Export Control Categories.</hi> This is a
                            purely cosmetic change, but one which is symbolically important to
                            Beijing and fully consistent with other adjustments in our trade
                            relationship with China.</p>
                        <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Dual Use Technology and <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss>.</hi> While we have informed our <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> partners of our preference for a
                            procedure patterned along the lines of the Polish formula, we have not
                            formally tabled a proposal. It is time that we do so. This will surprise
                            no one and we think our allies will buy this approach.</p>
                        <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Arms Sales, Military Equipment Sales and <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss>.</hi> Bureaucratic simplicity
                            and allied solidarity incline us to favor handling sales of all items
                            destined for military end-use in <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss>. To be sure, the creation of a separate high level
                            committee to handle such items might enable us to avoid taking a
                            position on the record on third country arms sales. But having indicated
                            our own intent to sell military support equipment to China, it is
                            difficult for us to argue that our allies should respond to our requests
                            within <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> while requiring them to
                            seek our views on arms sales outside the existing framework. In any
                            event we would be participants in whatever consultative process was
                            established, and the Russians have probably assumed we have been urging
                            our allies to sell weapons to China whatever we say. (<gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> was, of course, established to
                            restrict, not promote sales.)</p>
                        <p>6. <hi rend="italic">The Package as a Whole.</hi> There is a larger
                            policy question: How should we play these decisions in relation to our
                            current efforts to orchestrate a coordinated allied response to Soviet
                            action in Afghanistan? Announcement of these measures at this time could
                            invite some charges—e.g. from Europeans—that we are acting in a hasty
                            fashion to stick it to the Russians. While such allegations will
                            undoubtedly surface, we believe they are manageable because they are
                            wide of the mark.</p>
                        <p>—In fact these steps are not that new; they represent essentially a
                            codification of decisions already announced at least in general terms.
                            To that extent they have already been discounted by Moscow and others.
                            Beijing expects them; failure to follow through would be hard to explain
                            to the Chinese who may, however, be disappointed that we have not been
                            more forthcoming.</p>
                        <p>—They do not get us out ahead of our allies, who will welcome a clearer
                            definition of our intentions regarding military equipment sales to China
                            and our agreement to handle arms sales within <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss>. Cer<pb facs="1134" n="1095" xml:id="pg_1095"/>tainly
                            we should consult further with the allies on these steps prior to any
                            public announcements.<note n="5" xml:id="d301fn5">An unknown person,
                                probably <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>, underlined
                                all except the first word of this sentence.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>—Congressional sensitivities must also be accommodated through prior
                            consultations.</p>
                        <p>—We should emphasize in backgrounders to the press that we will continue
                            to process requests carefully on a case-by-case basis.</p>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline">
                                <hi rend="strong">Tab A</hi>
                            </note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="strong">Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of
                                    Defense for International Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_PN_1">Platt</persName>), the Assistant Secretary
                                    of State for East Asian and Pacific Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">Holbrooke</persName>), and <persName corresp="#p_SRW_1">Roger Sullivan</persName> of the National
                                    Security Council Staff to Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_BH_2">Brown</persName>, Secretary of State
                                        <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>, and the
                                    President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>)</hi><note n="6" xml:id="d301fn6">Top Secret; Sensitive.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1980-02-26">February 26, 1980</date>
                                </dateline></opener>
                            <list type="subject">
                                <head>SUBJECT</head>
                                <item>Technology Transfers and Military Equipment Sales to
                                    China</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">1. Sale of Military Equipment to China</p>
                            <p>We must provide U.S. industry with further guidance on the sale of
                                military equipment to China. For domestic purposes we prefer to do
                                this in terms of categories of the Munitions Control List, which
                                conforms to existing laws and regulations, is familiar to U.S. and
                                foreign industry, and can be understood as a comprehensive and
                                definitive statement of our policy. The announcement could be made
                                through the Munitions Control Newsletter. A proposed announcement,
                                which includes only those categories which are consistent with our
                                policy of not selling arms to China, is at Enclosure 1. Specific
                                items will be subject to a case-by-case review.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Recommendation.</hi> That you approve the approach
                                outlined above and the announcement at Enclosure 1.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">2. Chinese Requests</p>
                            <p>During Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BH_2">Brown</persName>’s
                                visit, the Chinese provided him, through his representative Dr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DGP_1">Dinneen</persName>, a list of items
                                which they <pb facs="1135" n="1096" xml:id="pg_1096"/> wished to
                                purchase. It was implied that these items would be for military
                                use.</p>
                            <p>We have reviewed this list using two criteria: (1) the level of
                                technology and (b) consistency with our policy of sale of support
                                equipment but not weapons. Enclosure 2 represents our analysis and
                                identifies items which we are prepared to discuss further, items
                                which require further clarification by the Chinese before we are
                                willing to engage in technical discussions with them, and items
                                which we are not prepared to discuss further.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Recommendation.</hi> That you authorize us to
                                respond to the Chinese list along the lines shown in Enclosure 2.
                                This would be in addition to informing them of our policy on
                                military equipment sales as outlined in the proposed announcement in
                                the Munitions Control Newsletter (Enclosure 1).</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">3. U.S. Export Control Categories for
                                China</p>
                            <p>In the regulations implementing the U.S. Export Administration Act,
                                China is included in Category Y along with Albania, the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, and the other Warsaw Pact
                                countries except Romania, Hungary, and Poland. Inclusion of China in
                                Category Y with the Soviet Union is an unnecessary irritant in our
                                relations with China. Changing the name of the category would not
                                affect our policy on exports to China or any other country. Nor
                                would it directly affect <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss>
                                since this category is used only within the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Recommendation.</hi> That the Department of
                                Commerce be instructed to revise its regulations issued pursuant to
                                the Export Administration Act to provide a separate category for
                                China.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">4. Dual-Use Technology and <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss>
                            </p>
                            <p>We have held political discussions with our principal <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> partners and informed them
                                that we wish to establish exception procedures for the transfer of
                                technology to China which are similar to those that nominally exist
                                for Poland. While there is some disagreement with the French on the
                                adoption of a formal procedure versus an informal one, our other
                                major <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> partners are amenable
                                to proposals to treat exceptions for dual-use export licenses to the
                                    <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> more favorably than for the
                                Warsaw Pact. We believe that in the end the French will go along
                                with a formal procedure.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Recommendation.</hi> That we instruct our
                                delegation to <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> to propose a
                                formal procedure along the lines of the Polish formula.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">5. Arms Sales, Military Equipment Sales and
                                    <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss>
                            </p>
                            <p>Our allies have repeatedly pressed us to change our policy on the
                                handling of third country arms sales, because of the extreme
                                difficulty of justifying <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss>
                                controls on non-weapons if there are no apparent <pb facs="1136" n="1097" xml:id="pg_1097"/> controls on weapons sales. Our
                                recent decision to approve sales of military support equipment to
                                China, which we have already told our <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> partners will be submitted to <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> for review, makes our present
                                policy of keeping weapons sales out of <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> seem even less logical. In the long term,
                                allowing the most important decisions on allied exports to China to
                                be undertaken outside of <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss>
                                seriously undercuts the rationale for the organization and could
                                tempt <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> members to circumvent
                                the organization on major non-weapons sales to the Soviet Union as
                                well as to China.</p>
                            <p>There are basically two options:</p>
                            <p>—Option A: Create a special committee within <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> to handle sales for military
                                end use to include arms, military equipment and dual-use
                                technology.</p>
                            <p>—Option B: Handle all sales of arms and equipment—whether for
                                military or civilian end use—through the existing <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> framework.</p>
                            <p>We believe that Option B now represents the best approach. This is a
                                change from our recommendation in 1978. It would respond to strong
                                representations of our allies that the <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> members judge all sales, whether for military or
                                civilian end use, by the same standards. The existing <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> structure is designed to deal
                                with all categories of technology—dual-use, weapons and military
                                equipment, and nuclear. Using it would avoid the complication and
                                consequent confusion that establishment of an additional
                                consultative mechanism would entail. This option would promote
                                allied unity and would clearly strengthen <gloss target="#t_COCOM_1">COCOM</gloss> at a time when we are trying to tighten controls
                                on the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Recommendation.</hi> That you approve Option
                                B.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">6. Consultations</p>
                            <p>We will have to consult with appropriate members of Congress
                                concerning our guidelines for military equipment sales before they
                                are published. Moreover, Congress would have to be informed of our
                                intended changes to the implementing regulations of the Export
                                Administration Act to provide a separate category under the Act for
                                China. We do not anticipate any significant opposition from the
                                Congress providing consultation is broad and undertaken sufficiently
                                in advance of announcements.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>