<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-06-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-06-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="312" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d312">
                        <head>312. National Intelligence Estimate<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d312fn1">Source: Central Intelligence Agency, Center for the
                                Study of Intelligence, Master File. Secret; [<hi rend="italic">handling restriction not declassified</hi>]. According to notes
                                on the title page, the <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_DIA_1">DIA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_NSA_1">NSA</gloss>, and the intelligence organizations of the
                                Department of State, the Army, the Navy, the Air Force, and the
                                Marine Corps participated in the preparation of this estimate. The
                                Director of Central Intelligence issued the estimate with the
                                concurrence of the National Foreign Intelligence Board. Information
                                available as of June 5 was used in its preparation.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <gloss target="#t_NIE_1">NIE</gloss> 11/13–80</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1980-06-05">June 5, 1980</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center">SINO-SOVIET RELATIONS IN THE EARLY 1980’S</p>
                        <p rend="center">Key Judgments</p>
                        <p>The probabilities over the next three to five years strongly favor
                            continuity over change in the Sino-Soviet relationship. There is latent
                            dynamism in the relationship but changes, if they come, are likely to be
                            marginal. Nevertheless, there is a possibility—perhaps one chance in
                            10—of larger changes toward either armed conflict or significant
                            improvement in the relationship.</p>
                        <p>The future course of the relationship is likely to be influenced more by
                            an evolution in Chinese perceptions and initiatives than by movement on
                            the part of the Soviet Union. The incentives keeping China on its
                            current course are powerful, but the consensus support for present
                            policies, although widespread, does not appear to be universal.
                            Significant changes in Chinese attitudes toward the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, if they occur, would likely be a
                            byproduct of a Chinese reassessment of geopolitical factors,
                            particularly the international role of the United States.</p>
                        <p>The present Soviet leadership, although interested in some amelioration
                            of relations with China, is unlikely to pay an important political price
                            to accomplish this. A successor leadership is likely to take the same
                            view. The Chinese, in turn, also want to limit tensions, but also are
                            unlikely to moderate their very high demands on the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. Minor progress in the economic
                            sphere, however, is possible even in the absence of movement on the
                            intractable border issue.</p>
                        <p>Steady increases in as well as modernization of the Soviet forces
                            opposite China are likely to continue over the next several years, but
                            Moscow does not appear to have either the desire or intention to attack
                            China, and probably would not do so unless severely provoked. The nature
                            of what constitutes provocation in the Soviet mind, however, may be in
                            flux, and this could be a complicating factor in China’s assessments of
                            its options.</p>
                        <pb facs="1156" n="1117" xml:id="pg_1117"/>
                        <p>The situation in Indochina, and in particular current Soviet ties to
                            Hanoi, has added a new dimension to the Sino-Soviet competition and is a
                            further obstacle to resolution of the conflict. The Chinese appear to
                            wish to avoid renewed hostilities on their southern border but have not
                            renounced this option; a situation in which China posed a military
                            threat to Hanoi or to the survival of the Vietnamese regime would be the
                            most plausible trigger for direct Sino-Soviet hostilities.</p>
                        <p>The United States is a central factor in the calculations of both Beijing
                            and Moscow. The Chinese view the United States as a source of help in
                            the Four Modernizations, as a facilitator in their increasing intimacy
                            with Japan and Western Europe, and as at least an ambiguous deterrent in
                            Soviet military calculations about China. Thus, both Sino-US economic
                            ties and especially the overall US posture in the international arena
                            are likely to affect Beijing’s estimate of its ability to fend off
                            Moscow.</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> fears the possibility of
                            growth in the Sino-US security relationship, but Moscow is not likely to
                            offer Washington major inducements to prevent such growth. The Chinese
                            are probably prepared to accommodate a considerable range of US
                            attitudes on the direct security relationship so long as Washington does
                            not significantly compromise important Chinese interests in its dealings
                            with the Soviet Union.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is the body of the estimate.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>