<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>323. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in China</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d323</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">323</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1980-10-14T08:09:00-05:00" notAfter="1980-10-14T08:09:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="arms-transfers"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91001417"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arms sales</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="recdDEAik5EmT8luP" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="organization-of-american-states"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87007400"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Coast Guard</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="air-safety"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Civil aviation</term>
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-10-14T08:09:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-10-14T08:09:00-05:00" n="323"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d323">
                <head>323. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in China<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d323fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        P870123–0585. Secret; Immediate; Nodis. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_JDN_1">Darryl Johnson</persName> (EA/C) and approved by
                            <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_FCWJ_1">Freeman</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_NJD_1"
                            >Negroponte</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1980-10-14T13:09:00+00:00">October 14, 1980, 1309Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>274184. Subject: Secretary’s Meeting with Chinese Ambassador. Ref: Beijing 10000
                        (Nodis).<note n="2" xml:id="d323fn2">In telegram 10000 from Beijing, October
                        10, <persName corresp="#p_WL_1">Woodcock</persName> reported that Deng had
                        expressed dismay with recent U.S. decisions regarding arms sales to Taiwan
                        and an agreement between the <gloss target="#t_AIT_1">AIT</gloss> and the
                            <gloss target="#t_CCNAA_1">CCNAA</gloss> on privileges and immunities.
                        (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                        Policy File, P900105–0785) The agreement was signed on October 2.</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. (S) entire text.</p>
                <p>2. Summary. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MES_1">Muskie</persName> called in
                    Chinese Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_CZ_1">Chai Zemin</persName> on October
                    13 to review the bilateral relationship and the issues of difference which have
                    recently arisen. The Secretary underscored his personal involvement and
                    commitment to the improvement in relations, and reiterated the President’s
                    commitment to implement strictly the joint communiqué of December 15, 1978.<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d323fn3">See <ref target="#d171">Document 171</ref> and <ref
                            target="#d171fn2">footnote 2</ref> thereto.</note> Deputy Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> then spelled out in
                    detail our views on the <gloss target="#t_AIT_1">AIT</gloss>–<gloss
                        target="#t_CCNAA_1">CCNAA</gloss> Agreement on Privileges and Immunities
                        (<gloss target="#t_PnI_1">P and I</gloss>), and on the reported sale of five
                    “warships” to Taiwan. The Secretary noted the unfortunate timing of these
                    developments in the midst of our election campaign and assured Chai that they
                    were not politically motivated. He also said that Taiwan has its own reasons for
                    portraying our relationship in a different light, but we will continue to abide
                    by our bilateral commitments to China. <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1"
                        >Christopher</persName> regretted the premature leak on the grain agreement
                    and urged that it be concluded without delay. Chai responded that we continued
                    to have differences over Taiwan, and that when issues such as continued US arms
                    sales to Taiwan or the <gloss target="#t_PnI_1">P and I</gloss> agreement
                    emerge, China “cannot but raise its objections.” However, Chai did not link the
                    current or future status of US–China relations to these issues. The Secretary
                    said that we expected China to watch developments regarding Taiwan
                    closely—indeed, it should do so. But China should also understand that US policy
                    has been consistent in the direction of better relations and that we are abiding
                    by our commitments. Chai agreed to press for early conclusion of the grain
                    agreement. End summary.</p>
                <p>3. The Secretary met with Chinese Ambassador Chai at 11:00 a.m. on October 13.
                    Also attending were Deputy Secretary <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1"
                        >Christopher</persName>, <pb facs="1179" n="1140" xml:id="pg_1140"/> Acting
                        <gloss target="#t_EA_1">EA</gloss> Assistant Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_NJD_1">Negroponte</persName>, EA/C Director <persName
                        corresp="#p_FCWJ_1">Freeman</persName>, EA/C Political Section Chief
                        <persName corresp="#p_JDN_1">Johnson</persName>, and interpreter <persName
                        corresp="#p_CV_1">Chang</persName>. Ambassador Chai was accompanied by his
                    interpreter <persName corresp="#p_ZW_2">Zhou Wenzhong</persName>.</p>
                <p>4. Chai began by welcoming this opportunity to meet with the Secretary and
                    commented that the Secretary’s schedule had been extremely busy since he had
                    taken office and that it had not been possible for them to hold a separate
                    meeting previously. The Secretary replied that even though they had not held a
                    separate meeting, China had been very much in his mind during his months in this
                    position. He noted that he had gone to China as the head of a Senate delegation
                    in the fall of 1978 and at the time had not been aware of the substantial
                    movement towards the normalization of relations. He had hoped through this visit
                    to help that process, and this was a major reason for going. The trip had been
                    one of the most stimulating and interesting he had ever made as a US Senator, he
                    said, adding that in Shanghai, Beijing, Guilin and Canton he had been impressed
                    that the Chinese people seem to be so extremely busy. When the President had
                    announced, together with the Chinese leaders, the decision to normalize
                    relations, he had felt a personal stake in and a sense of satisfaction with this
                    step.</p>
                <p>5. In Shanghai and elsewhere he and the others in his delegation had carried on a
                    continuous political dialogue with their Chinese hosts and with other officials,
                    and through this dialogue had acquired a sense of the important issues to be
                    faced in building a new relationship with China. As a member of the Senate
                    Foreign Relations Committee, he had been involved in taking the necessary
                    legislative steps to implement the President’s decision. There had been a great
                    deal of debate at the time, yet less than might have been expected given the
                    history of difficulties between us in the past. In his state and elsewhere the
                    reaction to normalization had been very positive and in the two years since that
                    time the support has remained strong and even increased. This was a very
                    satisfying development. This support was strengthened by the rapid pace in the
                    improvement of relations which would not have been thought possible two years
                    ago. It was a happy day recently when the President hosted the signing of four
                    new agreements in the Rose Garden.<note n="4" xml:id="d323fn4">See <ref
                            target="#d319">Document 319</ref>.</note> This event got good media
                    coverage in the US and was seen widely as a positive and constructive
                    celebration of our new relationship. It is important to understand, the
                    Secretary continued, that normal relations between the US and China have
                    widespread public support in this country. It is a relationship based upon
                    mutual benefit, but it also has a warm human component. It is unavoidable,
                    however, that there will from time to time be incidents or issues of difference
                    which need explaining. He welcomed the opportunity therefore to try <pb
                        facs="1180" n="1141" xml:id="pg_1141"/> to clear up some issues which had
                    arisen recently and to avoid misunderstandings.</p>
                <p>6. Ambassador Chai replied that relations have indeed grown very rapidly. Since
                    January 1, 1979, the two governments have resolved many problems and have
                    reached agreement in many areas. The relationship has evolved in a “generally
                    satisfactory” manner. But sometimes there are problems which need to be resolved
                    in order to help the further development of relations. The international
                    situation—that is, the global strategic situation—required our two countries to
                    cooperate more closely. This cooperation meets the needs and interests of both
                    peoples. He said that as Chinese Ambassador, it was his mission to promote this
                    cooperation.</p>
                <p>7. One subject which we have discussed from time to time, but on which we still
                    disagree in some manner or other, is Taiwan. We have discussed this issue since
                    the establishment of diplomatic relations and the passage of the Taiwan
                    Relations Act (<gloss target="#t_TRA_1">TRA</gloss>), but the problems still
                    exist. When they emerge, it is necessary that both sides pay attention to them
                    so as to avoid differences—the emergence of new differences. Taiwan is a
                    sensitive issue within China, and a sensitive issue within the US–China
                    relationship. He (Chai) had talked with Deputy Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> on this issue several times.
                    China’s views have been clearly stated to Department of State officials in
                    Washington and by the Chinese Foreign Ministry to Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_WL_1">Woodcock</persName> in Beijing. There is therefore no need
                    to repeat these points at this time, he concluded.</p>
                <p>8. Deputy Secretary <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> then said
                    that he would like to address two issues which have recently become irritants in
                    the relationship. He reiterated that there was strong support in the US for
                    normal relations and that the communiqué of December 15, 1978 is the basis of
                    our relations. President Carter is personally committed, and has ordered all
                    others to implement the terms of the communiqué scrupulously; we have done so
                    and will continue to do so.</p>
                <p>9. On the specific issue of privileges and immunities for Taiwan representatives
                    in this country, the Taiwan Relations Act calls for “functional immunities” for
                    representatives of <gloss target="#t_CCNAA_1">CCNAA</gloss> to carry out their
                    nongovernmental commercial, cultural and other activities in this country.
                        <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> said that he himself had
                    explained to the Ambassador at the time that these would not be full diplomatic
                    immunities. The new agreement had been no secret, but was known to be under
                    negotiation and the direction of these negotiations had been explained earlier.
                    It is important to distinguish the agreement itself from the Taiwan reaction to
                    it, which has been exaggerated and self-serving. The agreement itself is
                    entirely consistent with the intentions of both the Taiwan Relations Act and of
                    the joint communiqué. It says explicitly that the two organizations are
                    unofficial and the actual P’s and I’s <pb facs="1181" n="1142" xml:id="pg_1142"
                    /> which have been granted are limited to those specified in the agreement. It
                    does not confer other P’s and I’s which the Ambassador and other foreign
                    diplomats have on matters like taxation, blanket immunity from arrest, etc. The
                    official press on Taiwan has portrayed the agreement as having a more official
                    character. We have let our concern about this inaccurate portrayal, and other
                    problems, be known very clearly.</p>
                <p>10. The timing of this agreement was unfortunate, but it was not part of any
                    effort to appeal to voters who may favor stronger US support for Taiwan. Ideally
                    the agreement should have been timed differently, but it is important to
                    understand that this was not a political act.</p>
                <p>11. Concerning reports that the US was selling five warships to Taiwan, this too
                    was greatly exaggerated. The vessels in question are an oiler, a floating
                    drydock, and a survey ship, all of which are about thirty to thirty-five years
                    old, and can hardly be seen as provocative. The two others are coastal patrol
                    boats, but no decision has been made about their transfer yet because they may
                    be needed by our own Coast Guard. Among the old vessels two have been leased to
                    Taiwan for several years, and the transaction now is really a means of
                    terminating a relationship rather than expanding one.</p>
                <p>12. Turning to the grain agreement, the Deputy Secretary said we regretted the
                    premature leak in our press, but as the Ambassador was well aware, this was a
                    common problem in our free society with a very aggressive press. We hoped
                    nevertheless that this disclosure would not delay the initialing, the signing,
                    and the announcing of the agreement. The President himself wanted to announce it
                    and to use the occasion to underscore the importance he personally attaches to
                    the relationship with China.</p>
                <p>13. Chai responded that before the <gloss target="#t_TRA_1">TRA</gloss> had been
                    passed Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_HH_2">Huang Hua</persName> had
                    raised the question of privileges and immunities and other related questions
                    with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WL_1">Woodcock</persName>, and he (Chai)
                    had raised them with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName>.
                    The Chinese had stated their opposition to some provisions of the Act. But the
                    Congress passed it anyway including some of those provisions. At the signing
                    ceremony the President said that he would implement the act in accordance with
                    the joint communiqué. But in the twenty-one months since normalization, the US
                    has in some respects dealt with Taiwan purely on the basis of the Taiwan
                    Relations Act. This “cannot but evoke a response from our side.” Concerning the
                    recent developments, the continuation of US arms sales is tantamount to
                    interference in China’s internal affairs. “The US recognizes Taiwan as a part of
                    China,” he said. Therefore to continue selling arms is tantamount to
                    interference and China must react. Concerning the <gloss target="#t_PnI_1">P and
                        I</gloss> agreement, even though it says that it is unofficial and
                    nongovernmental, in fact it grants the equivalent of dip<pb facs="1182" n="1143"
                        xml:id="pg_1143"/>lomatic privileges and immunities and diplomatic status to
                    the Taiwan representatives. The only exceptions, so far as China can see, are,
                    for example, that the members of this organization are not listed on the
                    Diplomatic List or given diplomatic ID cards. In essence, therefore, this is the
                    same as other <gloss target="#t_PnI_1">P and I</gloss>, and differs only in
                    form. China raised this point in the past but never accepted the American
                    position. The objections are no different now than before, but the US side
                    signed this agreement anyway. China cannot ignore this development. Concerning
                    the five ships, the issue is that it is yet another arms transaction to Taiwan.
                    After the previous announcement of arms sales, China objected. But the US is
                    continuing to sell arms.</p>
                <p>14. Concerning the civil aviation agreement, which was recently concluded, the US
                    had undertaken to issue a statement concerning the Taiwan flag and symbols on
                    its air carrier. But the Embassy has not seen this statement. There has been no
                    mention of it in the US press and China is not aware that the statement was ever
                    issued.</p>
                <p>15. EA/C Director <persName corresp="#p_FCWJ_1">Freeman</persName> responded that
                    the statement had been publicly distributed on the afternoon of September 17
                    during a background meeting with members of the press. We had been pleasantly
                    surprised to find that a pro-<gloss target="#t_KMT_1">KMT</gloss> newspaper in
                    New York, the <hi rend="italic">Shijie Ribao</hi> on September 19 had carried
                    the statement in Chinese almost in full. Xinhua had inexplicably not attended
                    the background briefing and therefore may not have received the statement. We
                    would be happy to supply it. Regarding that statement, we have done what we said
                    we would do.</p>
                <p>16. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> said that he wanted
                    to respond to one point which the Ambassador had made, namely to emphasize that
                    the immunities which are granted in the new agreement are not essentially the
                    same as those granted to diplomats. There is more than a formal difference. We
                    would be happy to have our experts discuss this point with the Chinese Embassy
                    to point out what the differences are. The agreement does not confer broad
                    immunities but is limited and specific.</p>
                <p>17. He then asked whether the Ambassador could predict when the grain agreement
                    might be concluded. Chai replied that in his meeting with Assistant Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">Holbrooke</persName> on Thursday, <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Staffer <persName corresp="#p_SRW_1"
                        >Sullivan</persName> had raised the question of the agreement and the timing
                    of the announcement. The Ambassador had immediately cabled Beijing and had
                    received the reply that it would not be possible to announce it until the formal
                    procedures had been completed. This involved approval by the State Council and
                    it would not be appropriate to announce the agreement or to initial it before
                    the State Council had approved it. However, he added, he did not expect this to
                    take very long and he undertook to report the Deputy Secretary’s views and to
                    urge the early conclusion of the agreement.</p>
                <pb facs="1183" n="1144" xml:id="pg_1144"/>
                <p>18. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MES_1">Muskie</persName> then said that the
                    status of Taiwan has been a sensitive issue before and since the normalization
                    of relations. We had sought to resolve it on a pragmatic basis, realizing that
                    we would not meet all of the conditions which China would have preferred. We
                    know that China will watch this issue closely, and it should do so. But China
                    should also keep in mind that the constant thrust of our approach is to
                    solidify, expand and develop further our relationship with the <gloss
                        target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss>. It is unfortunate that in the current
                    political campaign the question of “official,” or “unofficial” relations with
                    Taiwan have muddied the issue. The Secretary said he could assure the Chinese
                    that our relationship with Taiwan is strictly unofficial, and it will stay that
                    way. We meticulously abide by the understandings reached between the two
                    governments two years ago. Ambassador Chai said that if both sides handle our
                    relations on the basis of the joint communiqué, they would continue to
                    progress.</p>
                <p>19. Comment: Chai was careful not to state or imply that our relations would
                    suffer as a result of current irritations. His phrase, repeated in different
                    contexts, was that the Chinese “cannot but voice our objections” when issues
                    like these arise. He also avoided debating specific points, but reiterated
                    China’s consistent opposition to continued US arms sales to Taiwan and to the
                    implication that the <gloss target="#t_PnI_1">P and I</gloss> agreement confers
                    a degree of official status for Taiwan representatives. Interestingly, he placed
                    arms sales ahead of <gloss target="#t_PnI_1">P and I</gloss> in his response to
                    the Deputy Secretary, and made it clear that China’s objection was to arms sales
                    per se, not specifically or exclusively to the recent transaction involving
                    naval vessels. Finally, Chai’s tone throughout the seventy-five minute meeting
                    was cordial and pleasant, very much in keeping with the tone which the Secretary
                    set of clearing the air between friends.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Christopher</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
