<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>209. Telegram Secto 10198 From the Secretary’s Delegation to the to the
                    Embassy in Pakistan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d209</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">209</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-08-30T04:13:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-08-30T04:13:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recP1TxBSuFrpDZ2S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Interim agreement</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="arms-transfers"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91001417"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arms sales</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="foreign-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-08-30T04:13:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-08-30T04:13:00-05:00" n="209"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d209">
                <head>209. Telegram Secto 10198 From the <gloss type="from">Secretary’s Delegation
                    </gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Pakistan</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d209fn1">Source: Library of Congress,
                        Manuscript Division, Kissinger Papers, Box CL 203, Geopolitical File,
                        Pakistan, Chronological File, 16 Aug. 1975–12 March 1976. Secret; Immediate;
                            <gloss target="#t_NODIS1">Nodis</gloss>. It was repeated immediate to
                        the Department of State.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d209fn2">Secretary of State <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> cabled a response to Prime
                        Minister <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName>’s concerns about
                        possible increased Soviet activity in South Asia and included further points
                        for Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BHA3">Byroade</persName> to convey to
                            <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName> in person.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Alexandria, Egypt</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1975-08-30T09:13:00+00:00">August 30, 1975, 0913Z</date>.</dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Message for Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list type="references">
                    <head>Ref:</head>
                    <item>State 202508 Tosec 100162</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Please transmit following from me to Prime Minister <persName
                            corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName>.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>Begin message:</p>
                        <p>Dear Mr. Prime Minister:</p>
                        <p>Since I understand that you plan to visit Saudi Arabia this coming
                            monday, I thought it might be helpful to give you a brief report on the
                            current status of the Middle East negotiations. Since coming to the
                            area, I have been engaged in the intensive negotiations in an effort to
                            help Egypt and Israel achieve a further interim agreement which would,
                            in our view, constitute a significant step toward the just and lasting
                            peace in the Middle East which remains our overriding objective. The
                            negotiations have been difficult. The Israelis are concerned about the
                            military and strategic implications of withdrawal from the passes and
                            oil fields in Sinai in circumstances <pb facs="d209-02" n="2"
                                xml:id="d209-02"/> where an end to belligerency and peace still lie
                            in the future. The Egyptians, for their part, are concerned about
                            entering political undertakings that are of significance to the Arab
                            world generally in circumstances where much of their and other Arab
                            territory remains occupied and the legitimate interests of the
                            Palestinians remain unfulfilled. Despite these political constraints on
                            both sides, I believe we have made considerable progress and that the
                            chances for achieving this agreement are good even though a number of
                            obstacles remain to be overcome and a successful conclusion is not yet
                            fully assured. I want to emphasize in particular that President Sadat
                            has approached the negotiations with genuine statesmanship, and that we
                            have had heartening support from our Saudi friends.</p>
                        <p>I recognize that there is concern in the Arab world that this agreement,
                            if achieved, will lead to diminished interest in further negotiations
                            for an overall settlement of all aspects of the Arab-Israeli problem. It
                            is our firm intention, however, that there must be on-going
                            negotiations—however difficult they will be and however much time they
                            may take—with respect to the Syrian and other aspects of the problem.
                            Our national interests require nothing less. I am certain that the Saudi
                            leaders would be assured by any encouragement you could give them. The
                            President and I are determined to pursue this effort, and, despite some
                            of the difficulties we are experiencing at home, I am confident that the
                            American Congress and people will support our peace efforts and our
                            policies of strengthening relations with our Arab friends. The very
                            achievement of a new agreement should have a positive effect on the
                            psychological atmosphere and, if II is scrupulously implemented and
                            observed, can broaden the basis of confidence which is needed for both
                            sides to take the hard political decisions that will be required as the
                            negotiating process goes forward in the months ahead.</p>
                        <p>I would also like to take this occasion, Mr. Prime Minister, to tell you
                            how pleased the President and I were to hear from you in your letters of
                            June 13 regarding your concerns for Pakistan’s security. I regret that
                                <pb facs="d209-03" n="3" xml:id="d209-03"/> the demands of the
                            Middle East negotiations have delayed my sending you a considered
                            response before this. I have discussed your letters in detail with the
                            President and he has asked me to assure you that we are sympathetic to
                            your concerns. It was with these in mind that the President ordered the
                            lifting of the embargo on arms sales to Pakistan last February. We are
                            also committed to do what we can to help meet your food and economic
                            assistance requirements in the year ahead. This is an integral part of
                            our efforts to assure Pakistan’s continued security and well-being. I
                            have Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BHA3">Byroade</persName> to
                            convery our views on various specific points you raised in you earlier
                            letter.</p>
                        <p>Immediately before my departure for the Middle East, the President shared
                            with me your August 17 letter to him, re-emphasizing your concerns in
                            the context of recent conversations between your representatives and
                            Soviet diplomats in Kabul. Upon my return to Washington, I will discuss
                            this subject with the President, and he will, of course, be responding
                            to you. Meanwhile, I understand you are seeking clarification from the
                            Soviet Government of the significance of the statements made by its
                            officials in Kabul, and I hope you will keep Ambassador <persName
                                corresp="#p_BHA3">Byroade</persName> informed.</p>
                        <p>Warm regards,</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>
                        </p>
                        <p>End message</p>
                    </item>
                    <pb facs="d209-04" n="4" xml:id="d209-04"/>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>In conveying the above message to Prime Minister <persName
                                corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName>, you should make the following
                            points:</p>
                        <p>We were pleased to note the Prime Minister’s expression, in his June
                            letters, of continuing support for the Simla process. We have also noted
                            the wise policies of caution and restraint shown by the GOP during this
                            delicate period of difficulties in India.</p>
                        <p>It is our view that continued progress under the Simla process will
                            reduce the possibility of renewed hostilities on the subcontinent. The
                            immediate interest of the United States, and one which we fully share
                            with Pakistan, is to avert such an eventuality. It was with this
                            objective in mind that the Secretary conveyed to Foreign Minister
                            Gromyko in May the seriousness which the United States would regard an
                            Indian attack against Pakistan. We have every reason to believe that the
                            Soviet leadership has fully understood the position of the United States
                            on this question.</p>
                        <p>Direct involvement by the Soviet Union and China in a South Asian
                            conflict would, of course, have implications of the gravest nature and
                            would be of great concern to the United States. The response of the
                            United States would be a matter for consideration by the executive <pb
                                facs="d209-05" n="5" xml:id="d209-05"/> branch in close consultation
                            with the Congress in accordance with the requirements of our
                            constitution and our obligations under the 1959 Mutual Cooperation
                            Agreement with Pakistan.</p>
                        <p>The President and the Secretary are hopeful that they will have the
                            opportunity to hold talks in Peking with leaders of the People’s
                            Republic of China later this year. These talks would provide an
                            opportunity to discuss the full range of security issues affecting
                            relations between our countries and Pakistan, and ways in which our
                            government might continue to assist Pakistan in its efforts to maintain
                            its security.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary was most appreciative that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AA8"
                                >Aziz Ahmed</persName> has communicated to the Chinese our concern
                            about the effect which their propaganda has on our ability to mobilize
                            domestic support for the PRC’S security.</p>
                        <p>In discussing your letters in Washington, I found a deep and continuing
                            interest in the administration in Pakistan’s security and welfare, and a
                            strong desire to be helpful in ways that are in accordance with our own
                            legislative and constitutional requirements.</p>
                        <p>As I know you are aware from you own discussions with American leaders,
                            including Senators and Congressmen, the United States is not able to
                            undertake additional formal security commitments, outside the framework
                            of our formal treaties and executive agreements.</p>
                        <p>With regard to the recent statements made by Soviet representatives to
                            Pakistani officials in Kabul concerning the Durand Line, if these in
                            fact represent a change in Soviet policy toward Pakistan, we would of
                            course view them with grave concern.</p>
                        <p>We will be interested to have your further views on the Soviet position,
                            following your further conversations with Soviet representatives.</p>
                    </item>
                    <pb facs="d209-06" n="6" xml:id="d209-06"/>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>In addition to the substantive points above, you should seek to correct
                            the differences which exist between what I said to <persName
                                corresp="#p_AA8">Aziz Ahmed</persName> in Ankara on May 22 and the
                            interpretation of these remarks contained in <persName corresp="#p_BZA1"
                                >Bhutto</persName>’s letters of June 13. The following should be
                            made so that the record will be clear:</p>
                        <p>During my Washington consultations, I reviewed the minutes of the
                            conversation between Minister <persName corresp="#p_AA8">Aziz
                                Ahmed</persName> and Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                                >Kissinger</persName>. Our record contains some important nuances
                            which if not precisely grasped, could lead to misunderstandings which we
                            both want to avoid.</p>
                        <p>The secretary informed <persName corresp="#p_AA8">Aziz Ahmed</persName>
                            he had told the Soviets that we would hold them responsible for the use
                            made of their equipment anywhere, and especially in Pakistan.</p>
                        <p>(<persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName>’s letter to the President
                            states: “Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> informed
                            Mr. <persName>Ahmed</persName> that he had spoken to.... Gromyko in very
                            strong terms to the effect that an Indian attack on Pakistan with Soviet
                            equipment would invite a response from the United States.”)</p>
                        <p>The Secretary asked <persName corresp="#p_AA8">Aziz Ahmed</persName> if
                            we could ask the Chinese what their response would be if Pakistan is
                            attacked. The Secretary also indicated that a general war following an
                            Indian attack on Pakistan and involving the Soviets and Chinese would
                            have the gravest implications for the whole of Asia and for U.S. policy
                            in the area. (<persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName>’s letter to
                            the Secretary states: “.... I was relieved to hear from Mr. <persName
                                corresp="#p_AA8">Aziz Ahmed</persName>.... what you planned to tell
                            the Chinese about the action the United States would take if the Soviet
                            Union attacked China for coming to Pakistan’s assistance in the event of
                            an Indian attack on Pakistan.” <persName corresp="#p_BZA1"
                                >Bhutto</persName>’s letter to the President states: “Dr. <persName
                                corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>.... added that, if China
                            posed the counterquestion as to what the United States would do in such
                            an event an attack on Pakistan), it would be informed that if India
                            attacked Pakistan and China came to its help and if in consequence the
                            Soviet Union attacked China, the <pb facs="d209-07" n="7"
                                xml:id="d209-07"/> United States would not be able to stay out of
                            that situation.)</p>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
