<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-01-15T03:55:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-01-15T03:55:00-05:00" n="264" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d264">
                        <head>264. Telegram 212 From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Nepal</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d264fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 84, Katmandu Embassy Files: Lot 78 F
                                115, SOC 1976. Limited Official Use. It was drafted by David
                                Fischer, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>; cleared by <gloss target="#t_USAID1">USAID</gloss>; and approved by ADCM James
                                Falzone. In telegram 985, March 3, the Embassy reported further on
                                constitutional protections and legal strictures on individual
                                freedoms in Nepal. (Ibid.)</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d264fn2">The Embassy responded to the
                                Department’s request for information on human rights in
                                Nepal.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline><placeName>Kathmandu</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-01-15T08:55:00+00:00">January 15, 1976,
                            0855Z</date>.</dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                            <item>Human Rights and Development</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="references">
                            <head>REF:</head>
                            <item>AIDTO Circular A–687, Dec. 19, 1975</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Mission has reviewed referenced airgram and welcomes opportunities
                                it presents to increase emphasis on human rights implications for US
                                assistance programs.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Long history of US assistance to Nepal has probably had
                                significant, albeit indirect, effect on development of respect for
                                basic human rights. A feudal society only 25 years ago, Nepal has
                                made rapid progress in developing a political system which if
                                autocratic, cannot be described as authoritarian. [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>]</item>
                            <pb facs="d264-02" n="2" xml:id="d264-02"/>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Our greatest impact in the human rights area is probably the
                                experiences gained by over 2000 AID participants trained in
                                Western—particularly American-value systems, including the respect
                                for basic human dignity. These persons have risen to positions of
                                considerable importance and leadership in the society and their
                                influence has been felt all the more given the limited numbers of
                                educated persons to man key positions throughout the country. It is
                                no exaggeration to say that it is difficult to find administrators
                                at the joint secretary or above in virtually all government offices
                                who have not been exposed at one time or another to American values
                                through direct experience. This elite constitutes a fairly important
                                pressure group in assuring that basic human rights are not trampled
                                upon, even in a country whose monarchical powers are supreme. They
                                are, for example, the “intellectual class” which has successfully
                                pressed for the release of political prisoners in Nepal and which
                                has forced the government to restrict the application of
                                “catch-all-laws” used in the past to harrass political
                                dissidents.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Through our emphasis on creating an adequate <pb facs="d264-03" n="3" xml:id="d264-03"/> infrastructure in health and education
                                we have successfully created new institutions which not only aid the
                                economically and intellectually depressed rural areas of Nepal, but
                                also institutions which provide direct participation by relatively
                                large segments of society. Although it is difficult to make a
                                definitive judgment on larger philosophical question cif whether
                                economic assistance promotes human rights, experience over 25 years
                                in Nepal indicates slow, but steady, progress towards a political
                                and economic system promoting and protecting basic rights. In that
                                period the use of cruel and inhuman punishment has all but
                                disappeared: arbitrary arrest has been vastly reduced, and the right
                                of freedom of expression, although not comparable to the United
                                States, is not severely restricted. It is something of an anomaly
                                that Nepal, one of the few remaining monarchies in the world,
                                currently enjoys more fundamental rights than other countries in the
                                area.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>That this situation exists is, in part at least, the result of
                                increasing confidence of the nation’s leadership that economic
                                development need not be a threat to political stability. US
                                assistance through aiding the country’s economic development has
                                likely increased Nepal’s political stability and confidence in
                                maintaining a sovereign and independent state without the need to
                                resort to immoral or inhuman methods to remain in power.</item>
                            <pb facs="d264-04" n="4" xml:id="d264-04"/>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Consequently, we believe our development programs have had a
                                positive if largely indirect impact on human rights in Nepal.
                                However, we have not in the past directed our programs specifically
                                on human rights. While we believe opportunities to carry out
                                programs in such politically sensitive areas by foreign aid donors
                                are very constrained, we do believe there are some limited ways in
                                which we can directly help enhance or protect those rights. For
                                example, we would support a modest program to provide financial
                                assistance to organizations such as “World Peace Through Law” to
                                allow Nepalese participation. Similarly direct assistance to
                                “Amnesty International”, which has played an important “watch dog”
                                role in Nepal, or the International Commission of Jurists would not
                                only demonstrate our continuing concern over human rights but would
                                have a direct effect on those <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss>
                                officials concerned with the administration of justice. A SEADAG
                                conference, although politically sensitive, devoted to the broader
                                question of human rights and development efforts could serve the
                                same purpose. Above all, we would urge an increase in exchanges and
                                participant grants to be devoted to those directly involved, be they
                                local administrators or central government authorities in the field
                                of law.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_CWI1">Cargo</persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>