<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-06-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-06-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="32" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d32">
                        <head>32. Memorandum From the Executive Secretary of the Department of State
                                (<persName corresp="#p_ETLJ1" type="from">Eliot</persName>) to the
                            President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d32fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, AID (U.S.)
                                15–8 Bangladesh. Limited Official Use. It was drafted by Lawrence
                                Lesser (<gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>/PAB); and cleared by
                                    <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>/PAB, EB/OFP, and AID/ASIA/DP. R. H. Miller signed
                                his name above <persName corresp="#p_ETLJ1">Theodore
                                    Eliot</persName>’s typed signature.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d32fn2">The memorandum discussed the
                                relationship between stability and the provision of food aid. The
                                tight U.S. grain supply posed a problem for the fulfillment of U.S.
                                aid pledges for fiscal 1973–74.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-06-20">June 20, 1973</date>.</dateline>
                        <pb facs="d32-01" n="1" xml:id="d32-01"/>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>U.S. Wheat for Bangladesh</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The government of <persName corresp="#p_RSM1">Sheikh Mujibur
                                Rahman</persName> is losing the confidence of the people as economic
                            problems continue to go unsolved and the expectations of a
                            newly-independent people are unrealized.</p>
                        <p>Availability of food, especially rice, at stable prices is essential to
                            the preservation of the authority of the BDG and of law and order in the
                            major urban areas of Dacca and Chittagong. Should government stocks be
                            exhausted, civil unrest is expected to follow, with unpredictable
                            consequences for the present <gloss target="#t_BDG1">BDG</gloss>, and
                            for stability in South Asia.</p>
                        <p>Bangladesh needs an estimated 2.5 million tons of food-grain imports in
                            calendar year 1973 in order to maintain subsistence levels for its
                            population. Against this need the <gloss target="#t_BDG1">BDG</gloss>
                            has purchased some 1.1 million tons on world markets, has pledges from
                            countries other than the U.S. for almost 700,000 tons, and has a pledge
                            from the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> for the remaining 700,000
                            tons, 200,000 tons of which were shipped early in the year.</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> intends to finance the remainder
                            of its pledge through the use of bilateral grant funds for 200,000 tons,
                            and under PL–480, Title I for 300,000 tons. All of it should he made
                            available for distribution during the period of the greatest scarcity
                            immediately preceding the main annual rice harvest in late November and
                            December. In order to meet this schedule shipments must be completed
                            from U.S. ports during the first quarter of FY–1974 (i.e. not later than
                            September 1973).</p>
                        <pb facs="d32-02" n="2" xml:id="d32-02"/>
                        <p>Because of the unusually tight U.S. grain position, USDA has not been
                            able to set an allocation for foodgrains to be made available worldwide
                            under congressional financing in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>–1974,
                            nor even for the first quarter of <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>–1974. No decision is expected until July 6, making it
                            virtually impossible to meet the Bangladesh requirement on a timely
                            basis. Furthermore, the allocation levels presently being discussed for
                            the first quarter of <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>–1974 are too low
                            to permit Bangladesh to get more than 300,000 tons.</p>
                        <p>In order to meet our commitment, shipments of wheat must leave U.S. ports
                            for Bangladesh early in July. It is recommended that an exception be
                            made permitting shipment of at least 100,000 tons of wheat in advance of
                            decisions scheduled for July 6 on the overall scale of the Title I
                            program.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_ETLJ1">Theodore L. Eliot, Jr.</persName>
                                <lb/> Executive Secretary</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>