<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-07-20T18:13:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-07-20T18:13:00-05:00" n="6" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d6">
                        <head>6. Telegram 143450 From the <gloss type="from">Department of
                                State</gloss> to the Embassy in Afghanistan<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d6fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy Files. Secret; Immediate;
                                    <gloss target="#t_EXDIS1">Exdis</gloss>. It was drafted by
                                Arthur Rovine (L/<gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>); cleared by
                                    <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>/PAB, <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>; and approved by Mark Feldman (L). It was repeated
                                immediate to Ankara, and to Bonn, Islamabad, London, Rome, and
                                Tehran.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d6fn2">The Department encouraged the
                                tentative contacts between representatives of the Daoud regime and
                                the Embassy.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-07-20T23:13:00+00:00">July 20, 1973,
                            2313Z</date>.</dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Diplomatic Relations With Daud Regime</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="references">
                            <head>Refs:</head>
                            <item>A. State 142393; B. Kabul 5319; C. Kabul 5325</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Department appreciates Embassy’s discreet contacts with Daud and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NMA2">Naim</persName> and recommendation
                                in ref. B. We also appreciate full reporting from Embassy indicating
                                steps regime has taken to consolidate its position and its apparent
                                success in exerting effective control throughout country.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The basic thrust of our approach is to play any question about
                                recognition in as low a key as possible with a view to avoidance of
                                seeming to approve or disapprove the new government. This is in
                                accordance with Department practice for the past several years, and
                                with S-Res. 205 (1969) “that it is the sense of the Senate that when
                                the United States recognizes a foreign government and exchanges
                                diplomatic representatives with it, this does not imply that the
                                United States necessarily approves of the form, ideology, or policy
                                of that foreign government.” In brief, the Department’s policy is to
                                minimize to the greatest extent possible recognition questions.
                                Uncertainties generated by the traditional recognition policy, which
                                many equated with approval, have not served United States interests
                                well. Therefore, although we have not yet formally moved to French
                                practice of recognizing states rather than governments, we attempt
                                to avoid direct address to the question of recognition wherever
                                possible. Generally, once the situation has clarified, the new
                                regime is firmly established, and other governments have begun to
                                recognize or formally to continue diplomatic relations, we find an
                                appropriate opportunity to advise the new government of our
                                intention to maintain diplomatic relations. Recognition is not
                                mentioned but may be implied. In several recent cases, however,
                                where there have been elements of continuity in the situation
                                (including the recent abrogation of the monarchy in Greece) the
                                Department has taken the position that no question of recognition
                                arises. To do so in this case where no elements of continuity are
                                apparent would be another significant step in the direction of a
                                general policy in which the United States does not formally
                                recognize governments but merely determines whether to maintain
                                diplomatic relations with them. We are presently considering whether
                                to take this step.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Until consultations completed per ref A, Embassy should maintain
                                routine working contacts and hold open lines of communication to
                                government offices; avoid formal acts that might be construed as
                                recognition; and avoid statements suggesting that recognition is a
                                major question that we shall formally or dramatically decide and
                                announce.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item> We strongly support your effort to establish informal channels of
                                communication to Daud and wish to emphasize that questions of
                                recognition discussed above do not in any way restrict your
                                flexibility in establishing informal contact with new authorities.
                                In short, contacts are being maintained and we have no objection to
                                your providing your interlocutor with a written record of any
                                informal message you wish to communicate, which record could be
                                transmitted to Daud. The thrust of your message can be that we look
                                forward to friendly and constructive relations.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RKW1">Rush</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>