<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>117. Memorandum From Acting Secretary of State Acheson to the Members of the
                        National Intelligence Authority
                    Source: Central Intelligence Agency
                        Historical Files, HS/CSG–2227, Job 83–00739R, Box 2, Folder 3. Top Secret.
                        Drafted by E.O. Briggs. Covered by an August 5 note
                        signed with Acheson’s typed initials,
                        addressed to Secretaries Forrestal
                        and Patterson and Admiral Leahy, asking that the memorandum
                        be discussed at the NIA meeting on August 7.
                        The covering note also contains a footnote stating that a copy of the
                        memorandum was given to the CIG Assistant
                        Director for Special Operations by Assistant Secretary Braden on August 6.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945-50Intel</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d117</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">117</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-08-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-08-05T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-08-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-08-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="117" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d117">
                <head>117. Memorandum From Acting Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_AD1" type="from">Acheson</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Members of the
                        National Intelligence Authority</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d117fn0">Source: Central Intelligence Agency
                        Historical Files, HS/CSG–2227, Job 83–00739R, Box 2, Folder 3. Top Secret.
                        Drafted by <persName>E.O. Briggs</persName>. Covered by an August 5 note
                        signed with <persName corresp="#p_AD1">Acheson</persName>’s typed initials,
                        addressed to Secretaries <persName corresp="#p_FJV1">Forrestal</persName>
                        and <persName corresp="#p_PRP1">Patterson</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_LAWD1">Admiral Leahy</persName>, asking that the memorandum
                        be discussed at the <gloss target="#t_NIA1">NIA</gloss> meeting on August 7.
                        The covering note also contains a footnote stating that a copy of the
                        memorandum was given to the <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss> Assistant
                        Director for Special Operations by Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BS1">Braden</persName> on August 6.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-08-05">August 5, 1946</date>.</dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Replacement of <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> Personnel in Latin
                        America by Personnel of the new Central Intelligence Group</item>
                </list>
                <p>Federal Bureau of Investigation agents who since 1940 have been performing
                    security intelligence functions in Latin America are scheduled to be replaced by
                    personnel of the now Central Intelligence Group under <persName corresp="#p_VLGHS1">General Vandenberg</persName>. A schedule (copy
                        Attached)<note n="1" xml:id="d117fn1">Not found Attached to the source text
                        but probably the same as the schedule Attached to the letter from <persName corresp="#p_VLGHS1">Vandenberg</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_BS1">Braden</persName>, July 29. (Ibid.) See the Supplement.</note> has been
                    drawn up by the <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss> for discussion with Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_HJE1">Hoover</persName>, calling for progressive
                    assumption of intelligence functions between February 15 and May 15, 1947. In
                    the meantime, however, orders have been transmitted by the <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> directing that the respective offices be closed
                    and <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> personnel be withdrawn.</p>
                <p>There is grave danger in this situation that the excellent <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> organization in Latin America may disintegrate
                    before it can be taken over by new personnel of the <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss>. This would be a major blow to the effectiveness of our
                    security intelligence work in the Latin American field, from which it might take
                    us many years to recover.</p>
                <p>Since the withdrawal movement started, messages of concern, apprehension or alarm
                    have been received from <hi rend="italic">every American Ambassador</hi> in
                    Latin America, testifying to the excellent work accomplished since the
                    establishment of the Legal Attaché service of the <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> in Latin America, and recommending with the utmost urgency that
                    the change-over be gradual and orderly. The Ambassadors have in particular
                    recommended that no <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> personnel be withdrawn
                    until successors have arrived and have had sufficient time and opportunity to
                    familiarize themselves with the work.</p>
                <p>The Department of State shares in every respect the views expressed by our
                    Ambassadors in the field. When a similar step was contemplated <pb facs="0315" n="287" xml:id="pg_287"/> last year, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName> sent a letter (Top Secret, November 30, 1945—copy
                        enclosed)<note n="2" xml:id="d117fn2">Not found.</note> to the then Director
                    of the Bureau of the Budget, in which he stated: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The situation is so serious…that I recommend as strongly as I can the
                            immediate provision of sufficient funds to enable the Federal Bureau of
                            Investigation to maintain its security intelligence service in the other
                            American republics until a definitive decision shall have been taken on
                            the over-all integrated intelligence plan <hi rend="italic">and that
                                plan put in effective operation</hi>.” (Underscoring supplied.)<note n="3" xml:id="d117fn3">Printed here as italics.</note>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The integrated plan referred to by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName> has now been adopted, but it has not yet been put “in
                    effective operation”. In order to safeguard the existing organization and to
                    provide for an orderly transition, it is urgently recommended that a
                    Presidential directive be sent to the Federal Bureau of Investigation, covering
                    the following points.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1)</label>
                    <item>In effecting the transfer of responsibility for security intelligence
                        operations in Latin America from the Federal Bureau of Investigation to the
                        Central Intelligence Group, it is essential that the turnover be orderly and
                        that the existing <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> intelligence
                        organization, together with its facilities, equipment and records, not be
                        impaired.</item>
                    <label>2)</label>
                    <item>No <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> personnel now serving in Latin
                        America should be withdrawn until after replacement <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss> personnel have arrived. There should then be a period of
                        time, deemed by the American Ambassador concerned to be sufficient, for the
                        new personnel to familiarize themselves with the nature, scope and details
                        of the work, prior to the departure of <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss>
                        personnel.</item>
                    <label>3)</label>
                    <item>In some cases, present <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> personnel may
                        desire to transfer to the <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss>. This should
                        be facilitated, and the opportunity should be afforded for all such
                        personnel considered by <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss> to be qualified
                        to transfer to the <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss> rolls.</item>
                </list>
                <p>I consider the foregoing to be of the utmost urgency and importance in connection
                    with national security.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
