<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>142. National Intelligence Authority Directive No. 2Source: Central Intelligence Agency Historical Files,
                        HS/HC–244. Confidential. This “tentative” version was approved at the
                        February 8 NIA meeting. Appendices A–C are
                        in the Supplement under cover of a February 11 memorandum from Souers. (National Archives and Records
                        Administration, RG 59, Records of the Department of State, Decimal File
                        1945–49, 101.5/2–1146)</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945-50Intel</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d142</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">142</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-02-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-02-08T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-02-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-02-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="142" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d142">
                <head>142. National Intelligence Authority Directive No. 2<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d142fn0">Source: Central Intelligence Agency Historical Files,
                        HS/HC–244. Confidential. This “tentative” version was approved at the
                        February 8 <gloss target="#t_NIA1">NIA</gloss> meeting. Appendices A–C are
                        in the Supplement under cover of a February 11 memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_SRASW1">Souers</persName>. (National Archives and Records
                        Administration, RG 59, Records of the Department of State, Decimal File
                        1945–49, 101.5/2–1146)</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-02-08">February 8, 1946</date>.</dateline>
                <p rend="center">ORGANIZATION AND FUNCTIONS OF THE CENTRAL INTELLIGENCE GROUP
                    (Tentative)</p>
                <list type="references">
                    <head>REFERENCES</head>
                    <label>A.</label>
                    <item>The President’s letter of 22 January 1946, establishing the National
                        Intelligence Authority</item>
                    <label>B.</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_NIA1">N.I.A.</gloss> Directive Number 1<note n="1" xml:id="d142fn1">
                            <ref target="#d141">Document 141</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Pursuant to the President’s letter of 22 January 1946, designating the
                        undersigned as the National Intelligence Authority, the Central Intelligence
                            <pb facs="0360" n="332" xml:id="pg_332"/> Group is hereby constituted
                        and will be activated this date by the Director of Central Intelligence. In
                        accordance with personnel authorizations approved by this Authority, the
                        Departments of State, War, and the Navy will assign personnel to the Central
                        Intelligence Group, and make reliefs and replacements, upon the Director’s
                        requisition. The approved initial personnel authorization is enclosed
                        (Appendix “A”).</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The initial authorization provides the minimum personnel necessary for the
                        tasks of organizing, surveying pressing problems, and meeting initial
                        requirements. As soon as practicable the Director will submit his
                        recommendations for augmentation of the Group.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Initial principal offices and sub-divisions shall be as shown on the chart
                        (Appendix “B”), with functions as follows:<list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Director of Central Intelligence</hi>—Responsible
                                for all operations of the Central Intelligence Group in accordance
                                with the President’s letter of 22 January 1946 and Directives of the
                                National Intelligence Authority. He will make the assignments of all
                                personnel in the Group. At the appropriate time, he will select an
                                Assistant Director from each of the four personnel contingents
                                (State, Army, Navy, Air), one of whom he may designate as his
                                Deputy.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Administrative Section</hi>—This Section will
                                perform all necessary administrative and security functions of the
                                Group, and will provide the Secretariat for the National
                                Intelligence Authority.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Central Reports Staff</hi>—This Staff will assist
                                the Director in accomplishing the correlation and evaluation of
                                intelligence relating to the national security, and in accomplishing
                                appropriate dissemination within the Government of the resulting
                                strategic and national policy intelligence.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Central Planning Staff</hi>—This Staff will assist
                                the Director in planning for the coordination of intelligence
                                activities related to the national security, and in preparing
                                recommendations regarding the establishment of such over-all
                                policies and objectives as will assure the most effective
                                accomplishment of the national intelligence mission.</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Central Intelligence Services</hi>—The Central
                                Intelligence Services shall be such operating agencies as may
                                hereafter be established upon approval of this Authority under the
                                provisions of paragraph 3c of the President’s Directive of 22
                                January.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Initial Tasks</hi>. The Director of Central Intelligence
                        will give first priority to the following tasks: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Production of daily summaries containing factual statements of the
                                significant developments in the field of intelligence and operations
                                related to the national security and to foreign events for the use
                                of the President, the members of this Authority, and additional
                                distribution shown in Appendix “C”.</item>
                            <pb facs="0361" n="333" xml:id="pg_333"/>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Conducting a survey of existing facilities for collection of
                                foreign intelligence information, and submission of appropriate
                                recommendations.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State</hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d142fn2">No signatures or any annotation indicating the
                        directive was signed appears on the source text.</note>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Secretary of War</hi>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Secretary of the Navy</hi>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Personal Representative of the President</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
