<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>196. Memorandum From the General Counsel of the Central Intelligence Group
                        (Houston) to the Director
                    of Central Intelligence (Vandenberg)Source:
                        Central Intelligence Agency Historical Files, HS/HC–803, Item 13. No
                        classification marking. The source text was a transcript prepared for the
                        CIA Historian on June 6, 1952.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945-50Intel</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d196</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">196</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-06-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-06-13T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-06-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-06-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="196" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d196">
                <head>196. Memorandum From the General Counsel of the Central Intelligence Group
                        (<persName corresp="#p_HL1" type="from">Houston</persName>) to the Director
                    of Central Intelligence (<persName corresp="#p_VLGHS1" type="to">Vandenberg</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d196fn0">Source:
                        Central Intelligence Agency Historical Files, HS/HC–803, Item 13. No
                        classification marking. The source text was a transcript prepared for the
                        CIA Historian on June 6, 1952.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-06-13">June 13, 1946</date>.</dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Administrative Authority of <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>On 22 January the President directed the <gloss target="#t_NIA1">NIA</gloss> to plan, develop and coordinate Federal foreign
                        intelligence activities, to assure the most effective accomplishment of the
                        intelligence mission related to national security. He further directed the
                        respective Departments to assign persons and facilities, which persons shall
                        collectively form the <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss> under the Director
                        thereof to assist <gloss target="#t_NIA1">NIA</gloss>. The mission of the
                        Director of <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss> is to correlate, evaluate
                        and disseminate intelligence, <hi rend="italic">making full use of the staff
                            and facilities of intelligence agencies;</hi> to coordinate activities
                        of such agencies <pb facs="0552" n="524" xml:id="pg_524"/> and recommend
                        over-all policies and objectives for the national intelligence mission; and
                        to perform for “said intelligence agencies such special services of common
                        concern as the National Intelligence Authority determines can be more
                        efficiently accomplished centrally”.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item> The above appears to give the complete administrative authority of <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss>. As outlined, it is purely a coordination
                        function with no substance or authority to act on its own responsibility in
                        other than an advisory and directing capacity. Thus, it has no power: <list>
                            <label>(A)</label>
                            <item>To take personnel actions;</item>
                            <label>(B)</label>
                            <item>To certify payrolls and vouchers;</item>
                            <label>(C)</label>
                            <item>To authorize travel;</item>
                            <label>(D)</label>
                            <item>To procure supplies directly for itself or enter into
                                contracts.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>All the above are fundamental technicalities which apply equally to
                        vouchered and unvouchered funds. </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Thus, the essential problem is that <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss>
                        has no power to expend Government funds. The Secretary of War could give the
                        Director, <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss>, unvouchered funds to spend at
                        the latter’s discretion, but even so the certification of the voucher would
                        have to be done by the Secretary. A good example of the problem is the case
                        of a civilian employee now assigned to <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss>
                        full time. The classification sheet and personnel action papers are headed
                        not “<gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss>”, but “State, War and Navy
                        Departments,” and actual payment is made on the payroll of one or the other
                        of these Departments as may be appropriate. The case in question is paid on
                        War Department Contingencies payroll. If necessary or expedient for one
                        reason or another, he could be cut off War Department and be put on either
                        State or Navy payrolls. A body serving <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss>
                        could be built up in this way, but it would still be in the form of
                        facilities furnished by the Departments, just as Army officers are assigned
                        for duty with the Director but remain on the Army finance records for pay
                        and administration. A time element is injected by Public Law 358, which in
                        brief provides that no funds may be made available to any agency or
                        instrumentality which remains in existence for more than one year without a
                        specific appropriation from Congress during that year. Consequently, after
                        22 January 1947, Departments could not even furnish unvouchered funds to the
                        Director, <gloss target="#t_CIG1">CIG</gloss>, and it would be questionable
                        whether the Departments could furnish personnel and supplies paid for out of
                        vouchered funds. </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HL1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Lawrence R. Houston</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="1" xml:id="d196fn1">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
