<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-06-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="286" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d286">
                    <head>286. Memorandum From the Director of the Policy Planning Staff(<persName corresp="#p_KGF1" type="from">Kennan</persName>) to the Under Secretary
                        of State (<persName corresp="#p_LRA1" type="to">Lovett</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d286fn0">Source: National Archives and
                            Records Administration, RG 59, Records of the Department of State,
                            Policy Planning Staff Files 1947–53: Lot 64 D 563, Box 719, Pol &amp;
                            Psych Warfare. Top Secret. The source text contains the handwritten
                            annotation, “Contents presented orally 6/8/48.”</note></head>
                    <dateline><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-06-08">June 8, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                    <p>The Staff of the National Security Council has under discussion the attached
                            paper<note n="1" xml:id="d286fn1">This memorandum has two attachments,
                                <ref target="#d284">Documents 284</ref> and <ref target="#d285">285</ref>.</note> relating to secret operations. It is our
                        understanding that the paper represents the results of discussions which
                        took place at a full Council meeting on June 3.</p>
                    <p>This is a project which I believe emanates largely from the initiative of the
                        Policy Planning Staff, which has been trying for several months to help
                        devise some means by which this Government could conduct political warfare
                        as an integral part of its foreign policy.</p>
                    <p>The proposal embodied in the attached paper does not appear to us to meet
                        this need, and we feel that the arrangements which it envisages might easily
                        operate to cause embarrassment to this Government.</p>
                    <p>It is our view that these things, if they are to be done at all, must be done
                        under the intimate direction and control of this Department. If this cannot
                        be arranged (and I understand the difficulties which stand in the way), I
                        think it would be better to withdraw this paper entirely and to give up at
                        this time the idea of attempting to conduct political warfare.</p>
                    <p>This is a heavy decision to take, because our policy in Europe, in
                        particular, will remain severely hampered in application unless it is
                        supplemented <pb facs="0731" n="703" xml:id="pg_703"/> in this way. But two
                        of the most important elements of our European policy: namely, the
                        administration of the ERP, and the control of policy with respect to
                        Germany, have already passed largely out of the hands of this Department;
                        and rather than have a third major factor of European policy handled
                        elsewhere in the Government, I think it would be better not to have it
                        handled at all.</p>
                    <p>I therefore ask permission to inform Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SRASW1">Souers</persName> that the State Department wishes to withdraw this
                            paper.<note n="2" xml:id="d286fn2">There is no indication in the source
                            text whether the recommendations were approved or
                        disapproved.</note></p>
                    <p>I further recommend that this Department request the cancellation of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 4, which is not operating
                        satisfactorily.</p>
                    <p>Should you not wish the enclosed paper to be withdrawn from the agenda of the
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>, I would appreciate it if you would
                        let me know whether there are any modifications of it you would wish to have
                        made before it comes before the Council for final approval.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KGF1">
                                <hi rend="strong">George F. Kennan</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>