<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>349. Memorandum for the President of the Discussion at the 14th Meeting of the
                    National Security CouncilSource:
                            Truman Library, Papers of
                            Harry S. Truman, President’s
                        Secretary’s Files, Subject File. Top Secret. Drafted on July 2.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945-50Intel</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d349</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">349</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-07-01T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-07-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="349" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d349">
                <head>349. Memorandum for the President of the Discussion at the 14th Meeting of the
                    National Security Council<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d349fn0">Source:
                            <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> Library, Papers of
                            <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Harry S. Truman</persName>, President’s
                        Secretary’s Files, Subject File. Top Secret. Drafted on July 2.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-07-01">July 1, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of agenda items 1–3, U.S. civil aviation policy toward
                    the Soviet Union and its satellites, U.S. position with respect to support for
                    Western Union and other related free countries, and the U.S. position on
                    providing military assistance to nations of the non-Soviet world.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">4. Proposed <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Intelligence
                        Directive Re “Communications Intelligence”</hi> (Memo for <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> from Executive Secretary, same subject, dated
                    June 15, 1948.)<note n="1" xml:id="d349fn1">Not found.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SRASW1">Souers</persName> said that the question of
                    legality which he had raised has now been corrected in the proposed Directive.
                    He said that the other question which he had raised involved only a matter of
                    form since no other board had ever been created under the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>. He stated, however, that, from his point of
                    view, the proposal by the Intelligence Advisory Committee was just as agreeable
                    a solution.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HRAR1">Admiral Hillenkoetter</persName> explained the two
                    points of difference. He said that his proposal was to achieve coordination
                    under the aegis of the Director of Central Intelligence but with the unanimous
                    concurrence of the Board. The <gloss target="#t_IAC1">IAC</gloss> proposal
                    placed the Board directly under the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> but
                    required unanimous concurrence, including the Director of Central Intelligence.
                    He said that either solution appeared acceptable. His feeling, however, was that
                    his wording, which was based upon Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SRASW1">Souers</persName>’ suggestion, was more consonant with the National
                    Security Act of 1947.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SRASW1">Souers</persName> explained that the <gloss target="#t_IAC1">IAC</gloss> feels that no one person should be in the
                    position of a single advocate before the Council. He said that the <gloss target="#t_IAC1">IAC</gloss> proposal would place the Board directly under
                    the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>, would require that it operate only on
                    unanimous agreement, would enable it to elect its own chairman, but would
                    require that it come up to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> when
                    disagreements arise.</p>
                <p>In answer to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RKC1">Royall</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HRAR1">Admiral Hillenkoetter</persName> stated that this
                    Directive would not affect a merger of Army and Navy communications intelligence
                    activities.</p>
                <pb facs="0895" n="867" xml:id="pg_867"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The National Security Council:</hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d349fn2">Paragraphs a–b and the Note constitute <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 73. (National Archives and
                        Records Administration, RG 273, Records of the National Security Council,
                        Record of Actions, Box 55)</note>
                    <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>Noted the comments by the Director of Central Intelligence and the
                            Executive Secretary, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>, that they saw
                            no serious objection to the revisions of paragraphs 1 and 7 of the
                            proposed <gloss target="#t_NSCID1">NSCID</gloss> recommended by the
                            Intelligence Advisory Committee.</item>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>Approved the proposed National Security Council Intelligence
                            Directive, subject to amendment of paragraphs 1 and 7 thereof as
                            recommended by the Intelligence Advisory Committee.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Note:</hi> The proposed Directive as approved subsequently
                    issued as <gloss target="#t_NSCID1">NSCID</gloss> 9<note n="3" xml:id="d349fn3">
                        <ref target="#d435">Document 435</ref>.</note> and transmitted to the
                    appropriate Departments and Agencies for information and action.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of agenda items 5–7, handling of <gloss target="#t_SANACC1">SANACC</gloss> papers, atomic warfare policy, and <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> status of projects.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
