<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-02-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="368" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d368">
                    <head>368. Memorandum From <persName type="from">Daniel DeBardeleben</persName>
                        to the <gloss type="to">Acting Deputy Assistant Director for Special
                            Operations, Central Intelligence Agency</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d368fn0">Source: Central Intelligence Agency Records, Job
                            86-B00269R, Box 5. Top Secret. The addressee has not been further
                            identified.</note></head>
                    <dateline><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-02-17">February 17, 1949</date>.</dateline>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>The <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> Report</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Below are listed my comments on certain passages in the body of Chapter VIII,
                        “The Collection of Secret Intelligence,” and my remarks concerning the
                        conclusions and recommendations which appear at the end of the chapter.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>It is recommended that representatives of State, War and Navy be
                            assigned to ICS in order more effectively to direct our activities in
                            the collection of intelligence and more helpfully to evaluate the
                            information which we collect. Both in direction and evaluation we can
                            reasonably expect to receive greater assistance from the user agencies.
                            Several schemes have been tried in the past to stimulate more detailed
                            direction and more conscientious evaluation. Regrettably there still
                            remains much to be desired and this proposal may be the answer to the
                            problem. British MI-6 has for a long time followed such a general
                            principle with, I understand, gratifying results. Certainly this
                            possibility should be explored to the fullest.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>It is recommended that administrative services be an integral part of
                            the <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss> organization for several obvious
                            reasons. I agree.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>It is true that no plan for rotation of personnel on a world-wide
                            basis has yet been worked out. It is doubtful whether this organization
                            should ever attempt wholesale rotation of operating personnel between
                            continental areas except in those unusual cases where individuals have
                            equal qualifications for work in more than one area. Our present
                            rotation plan of encouraging our people to remain at their present posts
                            as long as possible, consistent with cover, is entirely sound during
                            this formative stage of our existence. Consistent with cover, the longer
                            an individual can remain in his area of assignment, the more valuable he
                            becomes to us. This fact will be more greatly emphasized as we succeed
                            in placing our representatives under unofficial cover where they can
                            remain as a part of the community for indefinite lengths of time without
                            arousing curiosity and suspicion. Rotation in <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss> must be very carefully considered to the end that we
                            will not deprive ourselves of the knowledge and experience <pb facs="0957" n="929" xml:id="pg_929"/> of our representatives
                            concerning various areas simply to adopt an appealing policy of
                            world-wide rotation. The latter would require starting from scratch in
                            new jobs which would greatly retard the accomplishments of this
                            organization.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>It is recommended that <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_OPC1">OPC</gloss> and Contacts Branch, all covert
                            activities, be combined in one covert office and placed under a
                            responsible head. There seems to be much to recommend such an
                            organization provided the peculiar demands of these three offices be
                            provided for and no attempt be made to perform centrally certain
                            functions for the three offices which are in no sense common to
                            them.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>It is recommended that closer coordination be effected in occupied
                            areas between <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss> and to clandestine
                            operations of the occupying authority. Such coordination is highly
                            desirable and I believe is gradually improving. [<hi rend="italic">2
                                lines of source text not declassified</hi>]</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>It is recommended that procedures for handling defectors be worked out
                            with the concurrence of the interested agencies. Such a procedure is
                            very important and is now in the process of being determined through the
                            work of two committees—one dealing with the problem of defectors abroad,
                            the other considering the handling of defectors in the United States.
                            The work of these two committees will eventually be drawn together and
                            overall policy and procedures will result.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>It is pointed out that contact between agents and our official
                            representatives abroad should be avoided. Such avoidance is <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss> policy and steps are continuously being
                            taken to observe and follow strictly such policy; however, there will
                            always be certain cases where this policy must be violated and a
                            calculated risk taken. There is no way in which the conduct of espionage
                            can be made entirely safe. It should be our endeavor to avoid
                            unnecessary risks.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>It is pointed out that cover for <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss>,
                            CIA here in Washington is unsatisfactory. The conditions as to housing
                            and the admission by employees of <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss>
                            that they are CIA are undesirable, but there appears to be no immediate
                            solution. When the activities of <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss>
                            were placed in a separate office in CIA it was assumed that CIA would
                            provide cover for <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss>. This assumption
                            seemed reasonable at the time because it was expected that CIA would be
                            recognized by the public and the other departments of the Government as
                            primarily a research organization performing centrally an overt function
                            for the Government; however, because of unfortunate publicity, CIA is
                            rather recognized as a clandestine organization with the result that
                                <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss> is regrettably providing cover
                            for the overt activities of CIA. It does seem desirable to have <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss> quartered in a large building where
                            other activities are conducted and where <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss> personnel are not singled out. Further, it would be
                            advantageous to adopt some cover name for <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss> and its allied activities which would not bring to mind
                            espionage and clandestine activity.</item>
                        <pb facs="0958" n="930" xml:id="pg_930"/>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>It is recommended that the <gloss target="#t_CE1">CE</gloss>
                            activities of <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss> be expanded and that
                            closer cooperation with <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> be realized.
                            This is an entirely sound recommendation and every possible effort will
                            be made to accomplish such ends.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Conclusions and Recommendations</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d368fn1">This refers to the Conclusions and Recommendations of
                            Chapter VIII of the <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName>
                            Report. (National Archives and Records Administration, RG 59, Records of
                            the Executive Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files:
                            Lot 66 D 148, Box 1555) See the Supplement.</note>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Referred to above.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Referred to above.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Referred to above.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>In process.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>Every effort is presently being made to increase the use of unofficial
                            cover for our representatives abroad. [<hi rend="italic">13 lines of
                                source text not declassified</hi>]</item>
                        <label>(6)</label>
                        <item>Referred to above.</item>
                        <label>(7)</label>
                        <item>Referred to above.</item>
                        <label>(8)</label>
                        <item>No comment.</item>
                        <label>(9)</label>
                        <item>Agree. It seems reasonable that <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss>
                            should enjoy the privilege of disseminating its product in a fashion
                            comparable to the procedures followed by other collectors.</item>
                        <label>(10)</label>
                        <item>Accomplished.</item>
                        <label>(11)</label>
                        <item>Agree—highly important.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="strong"> DDeB </hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>