<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="54" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d54">
                    <head>54. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_BJF1" type="from">Byrnes</persName> to Secretary of War <persName corresp="#p_PRP1" type="to">Patterson</persName> and Secretary of the
                        Navy <persName corresp="#p_FJV1">Forrestal</persName><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d54fn0">Source: <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> Library, Papers of <persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clark M. Clifford</persName>, National Intelligence Authority.
                            Confidential. The date is handwritten on another copy of the source
                            text. (Ibid.)</note></head>
                    <dateline><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-10">December 10, 1945</date>.</dateline>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>National Intelligence Authority</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>By letter of September 20, 1945, the President gave me the following
                            instructions:<quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“I particularly desire that you take the lead in developing a
                                comprehensive and coordinated foreign intelligence program for all
                                Federal agencies concerned with that type of activity. This should
                                be done through the creation of an interdepartmental group, heading
                                up under the State Department, which would formulate plans for my
                                approval. This procedure will permit the planning of complete
                                coverage of the foreign intelligence field and the assigning and
                                controlling of operations in such manner that the needs of both the
                                individual agencies and the Government as a whole will be met with
                                maximum effectiveness.”</p></quote></p>
                    <p>Attached is a Plan for carrying out the President’s directive.<note n="1" xml:id="d54fn1">Entitled Establishment of a National Intelligence
                            Authority, December 3, 1945. See the Supplement.</note> It has been
                        recommended to me by my Staff Committee after several weeks of discussion
                        and study, and I now recommend it for your favorable consideration.</p>
                    <p>Attention is invited especially to the following points:<list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>The Plan sets up a National Intelligence Authority consisting of
                                the Secretary of State as Chairman and the Secretaries of War and
                                Navy, but authorizes the Chairman to call in the heads of other
                                Departments and agencies on matters of special interest to
                                them.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>The Plan is designed to make fullest use of the intelligence
                                resources of all agencies of the Government, by coordinating their
                                efforts under a comprehensive, Government-wide program. The proposed
                                machinery is an interdepartmental organization under the Authority,
                                with personnel drawn from existing agencies, rather than an
                                independent agency with a separate budget. This is considered
                                advantageous because it tends (1) to avoid publicity and (2) to
                                reduce competition and duplication between the central agency and
                                the intelligence organizations of existing departments and
                                agencies.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>Executive direction of the central agency is put in the hands of
                                an official of the Department of State, but it is provided that the
                                Secretaries <pb facs="0166" n="138" xml:id="pg_138"/> of War and
                                Navy must approve the person selected. In that manner the
                                coordinating responsibility of the State Department for matters
                                involving foreign affairs is recognized, but the executive is made a
                                representative of the Authority as a whole, and not merely of a
                                single Department.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>The central Secretariat is envisaged as a working staff of
                                personnel contributed primarily by the State, War and Navy
                                Departments.</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>The Plan does not preclude any centralized intelligence operations
                                (either under the central agency or outside of it) which may prove
                                feasible and desirable as the program of the Authority is developed.
                                It provides planning mechanisms that may well lead to centralization
                                of intelligence responsibilities in many of the specialized fields,
                                either (1) by vesting responsibility for a particular field in a
                                single existing agency or (2) by bringing together the working units
                                of several agencies on a subject into a joint unit under direction
                                of the Authority.</item>
                            <label>f.</label>
                            <item>With respect to clandestine activities (“secret intelligence” and
                                “counter-espionage”) I understand the prevailing opinion to be that
                                such operations, if they are to be conducted, might well be under a
                                central agency; and the Plan sets up machinery for study of that
                                problem in detail and for development of specific operating plans in
                                those fields.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>The central agency is conceived in the first instance as a coordinating and
                        planning mechanism, whose mission is to develop the comprehensive program
                        envisaged by the President; to determine foreign intelligence requirements
                        on a Government-wide basis, and to recommend means and methods for meeting
                        those requirements, making use of all the intelligence resources of the
                        Government. Many agencies, in addition to the State, War and Navy
                        Departments, are engaged in collection and analysis of foreign information,
                        including the Treasury, the Departments of Agriculture, Commerce and Labor,
                        the Tariff and Maritime Commissions, the Federal Reserve Board and numerous
                        others. Such agencies can make important contributions to foreign
                        intelligence if they work under a coordinated program, so that, within their
                        special fields, they may serve the needs of other Government agencies as
                        well as their own.</p>
                    <p>Under the Plan as proposed, the primary coordinating mechanism is a group of
                        interdepartmental Committees for the various fields of intelligence, which,
                        in addition to their planning functions, will “Serve as a continuing group
                        responsible for maintaining a coordinated program and for reviewing the
                        adequacy and efficiency of all operations involved in the carrying out of
                        such a program.” Tentative suggestions for the principal Committees to be
                        formed are shown on the chart annexed hereto.<note n="2" xml:id="d54fn2">Not
                            printed; see the Supplement.</note></p>
                    <pb facs="0167" n="139" xml:id="pg_139"/>
                    <p>Foreign intelligence is a vast and complicated subject, touching upon almost
                        all fields of human knowledge. The problems that it involves do not lend
                        themselves to quick and easy solutions. They must be attacked in detail, and
                        from a long-range standpoint, and on a comprehensive basis. It is believed
                        that the annexed Plan permits that kind of an approach to the subject and
                        gives promise of good results if the execution of the Plan is put in
                        competent hands.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">
                                <hi rend="strong">James F. Byrnes</hi>
                            </persName><note n="3" xml:id="d54fn3">Printed from a copy that
                                indicates <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName> signed the
                                original.</note>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>