<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-07-20T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-07-20T06:00:00-05:00" n="112" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d112">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">861.77 Chinese Eastern/55: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-07-20T19:00:00+08:00">July 20, 1929—7
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 8 p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>604. Legation’s 602, July 20, 2 p.m.<note n="93" xml:id="d112fn93">Not
                                printed.</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>From a report made by the Naval Attaché concerning a trip made by
                                him to Manchuria last month, it would appear that the question of
                                some action being taken by the Manchurian authorities with regard to
                                the Chinese Eastern Railway had been under consideration for some
                                time, certain advisers advocating confiscation of the railway and
                                another set of advisers suggesting assumption of control with all of
                                the liabilities and assets. Among the arguments advanced for the
                                assumption of control by China are the obligations which China is
                                said to have under article V of the nine-power treaty relating to
                                principles and policies concerning China<note n="94" xml:id="d112fn94"><ref target="frus1922v01#pg_276"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 276</ref>, <ref target="frus1922v01#pg_280">280</ref>.</note> and under
                                resolution 12 of the Washington Conference regarding the Chinese
                                Eastern Railway<note n="95" xml:id="d112fn95"><ref target="frus1922v01#pg_297"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p.
                                        297</ref>.</note> and the obligation “in the nature of a
                                trust” which China may be deemed to have in view of the terms of
                                resolution 13 of the Washington Conference regarding the Chinese
                                Eastern Railway.<note n="96" xml:id="d112fn96"><ref target="frus1922v01#pg_298"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p.
                                        298</ref>.</note> Although the foregoing provisions were
                                drawn up with a view to holding China responsible for
                                “discrimination”, the view is now maintained by the advisers of the
                                Mukden Government that China cannot carry out her engagements in
                                these particulars without assumption of full control of the
                                railway.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>It is further argued that since the Peking agreement of May 31,
                                1924, provides (article 2) that “the railway is a purely commercial
                                enterprise” and (article 6) that “the Governments of the two
                                contracting parties further pledge themselves not to engage in
                                propaganda against the political and social systems of either
                                contracting party”, the Chinese are justified in taking over the
                                railway inasmuch as the provisions of these articles have been
                                repeatedly broken by the Soviet Government, the railway, its funds
                                and employees being used for political purposes in undermining the
                                Government of China.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Code text by mail to Tokyo.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">MacMurray</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>