<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-03-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-03-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="18" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d18">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.114 I’m Alone/55</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Canadian Minister</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Massey</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-03-28">March 28, 1929</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to your visit to
                            the Department on March 26, 1929, when you requested that you be
                            furnished with a statement of the facts concerning the sinking of the
                            vessel <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> by the United States Coast Guard
                            on March 22 last.</p>
                        <p>According to information furnished by the appropriate authorities of this
                            Government, the <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> was a notorious
                            smuggling vessel, having been engaged in smuggling liquor into the
                            United States for several years. It is stated that until the latter part
                            of 1928, the <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> operated on the New
                            England Coast and had caused the Coast Guard forces a great deal of
                            trouble. During the latter part of 1928, the <hi rend="italic">I’m
                                Alone</hi> changed its base of operations to Belize, British
                            Honduras.</p>
                        <p>On February 2, 1929, the <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> cleared from
                            Belize for Nassau with a cargo of liquor, and six days later the vessel
                            was sighted by the United States Coast Guard off the coast of Louisiana.
                            The <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> returned to Belize on March 6,
                            1929, in ballast without having proceeded to the destination for which
                            it cleared on February 2. On March 12, 1929, the <hi rend="italic">I’m
                                Alone</hi> again cleared from Belize with a cargo of liquor, this
                            time for Hamilton, Bermuda.</p>
                        <p>On March 20, 1929, the <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> was sighted by
                            the United States Coast Guard vessel <hi rend="italic">Wolcott</hi>
                            northwest of Trinity Shoal, within approximately ten and one half miles
                            of the Coast of the United States. The <hi rend="italic">Wolcott</hi>
                            ordered the <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> to heave to for boarding
                            and examination, but this order was ignored, whereupon the <hi rend="italic">Wolcott</hi> fired a warning shot across the bow of
                            the <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> and repeated its command for the
                            vessel to heave to. When the second command was not complied with, the
                                <hi rend="italic">Wolcott</hi> fired through the sails and rigging
                            of the vessel. The <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> was proceeding
                            seaward and the <hi rend="italic">Wolcott</hi> took up the chase. The
                                <hi rend="italic">Wolcott’s</hi> gun jammed and it could not
                            therefore stop the <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> but it kept in close
                            chase and reported <pb facs="0168" n="24" xml:id="pg_24"/> the incident
                            to the Commanding Officer of the Coast Guard Base at Paseagoula,
                            Mississippi, who dispatched the vessels <hi rend="italic">Dexter</hi>
                            and <hi rend="italic">Dallas</hi> to assist the <hi rend="italic">Wolcott</hi>.</p>
                        <p>The <hi rend="italic">Wolcott</hi> continued the pursuit of the <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> and, according to statements of the
                            appropriate authorities, was at all times within sight of it. The Coast
                            Guard vessel <hi rend="italic">Dexter</hi> overhauled the <hi rend="italic">Wolcott</hi> close up with the <hi rend="italic">I’m
                                Alone</hi> about eight a.m. on March 22 with the latter vessel
                            heading toward Yucatan. The Commander of the <hi rend="italic">Dexter</hi> ordered the <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> to heave
                            to but the master of the latter vessel refused saying that he would be
                            sunk rather than stop. The commanding officer of the <hi rend="italic">Dexter</hi> then spoke to the master of the <hi rend="italic">I’m
                                Alone</hi> through a megaphone and informed him that the <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> would be sunk unless it obeyed the
                            command to stop. Warning shots were fired ahead, and, when the vessel
                            did not stop, the <hi rend="italic">Dexter</hi> fired through the
                            rigging and later put about a dozen shots into the hull of the <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi>. It is stated that the sea was too
                            rough to permit the <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> to be boarded and
                            seized by force and that furthermore the master of the <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> waved a revolver in a threatening manner indicating
                            that he would resist forcibly any attempt to board his vessel.</p>
                        <p>The <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> sank about 9:05 a.m. on March 22, in
                            latitude 25°41’ and longitude 90°45’. The Coast Guard vessels picked up
                            the members of the crew of the <hi rend="italic">I’m Alone</hi> with the
                            exception of one person who was drowned. When the body of this seaman
                            was taken from the water, the members of the Coast Guard worked for more
                            than two and one-half hours in an attempt to resuscitate him but without
                            avail.</p>
                        <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">W. E.
                                    Castle</hi>, Jr.</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>