<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-08-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-08-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="184" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d184">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">861.77 Chinese Eastern/230</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Secretary of State</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-08-20">August 20, 1929</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The Chinese Minister asked for an interview at twelve o’clock.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>He told me that he had brought to me the note<note n="58" xml:id="d184fn58"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> which he
                                had discussed with Mr. Cotton<note n="59" xml:id="d184fn59">Joseph
                                    P. Cotton, Undersecretary of State.</note> during my absence ten
                                days ago; that his government had decided to make it public as we
                                had suggested, by communicating it to the various signatories of the
                                Kellogg Pact; that he was finding some difficulty in doing this
                                because China did not have diplomatic relations with many of those
                                signatories, but that his note was being given out, as I recall it,
                                to certain capitals like London, Paris and others, and that he, Dr.
                                Wu, was distributing it among his colleagues here from other
                                countries. He said that his country would welcome any assistance in
                                making it public. I asked him if he wished to have us give it to the
                                press. He told me that he did.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>He told me that he wished to repeat to me what he had told Mr.
                                Johnson, namely, that his country was mobilizing 60,000 troops to
                                protect their frontier. I asked him what the purpose of mobilizing
                                was, as to whether it was to protect the frontier or the railway and
                                he told me that the report which he had from his government did not
                                say which. He afterwards told me that these troops were Manchurian
                                troops, local troops, and not from the South of the Wall.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>He told me that his government had directed him to bring to the
                                notice of this Government a direct violation of Chinese territory
                                resulting in casualties to Chinese troops which was contained in the
                                report from Chang Hsueh Liang, who is in command of the Army of
                                Manchuria. This report from Chang Hsueh Liang was dated August 19
                                and was to the effect that the Russians having designs on
                                    Dalainor<note n="60" xml:id="d184fn60">Presumably
                                    Chalainor.</note> in order to cut the Chinese [Eastern] Railway
                                between Manchuli and Hailar had made an attack on the afternoon of
                                August 16 at 3:30 upon Dalainor. The attack had begun at 3:30 and
                                lasted until 7:30. The Chinese lost one platoon commander and
                                twenty-five men killed, and one company commander, one platoon
                                commander and between twenty and thirty men wounded. That same night
                                at 3:30 a.m., on the morning of the 17th at the Dalainor Mines
                                Russian forces opened artillery attack which was still going on on
                                the date of the report. The Nanking Government had replied to Chang
                                Hsueh Liang to go no further than self defense actually
                                required.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Minister Wu said that he himself had communicated directly with
                                Chang Hsueh Liang and that the latter had stated that there were
                                repeated incursions of Russians across the line, but that he was
                                keeping his troops in control pursuant to instructions from
                                Nanking.</item>
                            <pb facs="0438" n="294" xml:id="pg_294"/>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Minister Wu had received word from a Chinese news agency that
                                1,000 Chinese were being forcibly compelled to dig trenches and do
                                other military work in the maritime provinces which includes
                                Vladivostok.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I asked Minister Wu how about the White Russians and he admitted that
                            Chang Hsueh Liang had White Russians enlisted in his forces much as the
                            French had the Foreign Legion. There were also many White Russians in
                            that entire country who, being without means of support had become
                            little better than bandits, but this was a situation which had lasted
                            for several years and he did not think that any of the despatches to the
                            press had reported that any organized Chinese forces had transgressed
                            the Siberian border. This was said in response to a statement of mine
                            that it was very difficult for neutral observers to distinguish between
                            the rights and wrongs of border skirmishes and that in case the
                            situation came down to a conflict brought on in that way it was very
                            difficult for neutral observers to form a clear opinion as to which
                            country was in the right. I took occasion again to point out the
                            importance in this respect of governmental action by China in clearing
                            her skirts for the original impression she had given of being wrong in
                            regard to the Chinese Eastern Railway. He admitted that public
                            impression had been given and asked me again what could be done. I told
                            him that there must be many ways of making clear the difference between
                            China protecting herself against propaganda on the one hand and
                            infringing the Russian rights in the railroad management on the other,
                            and that it seemed to me she ought to be able to make some public
                            disclaimer of anything like the latter intention and to make an offer
                            which would make this clear.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>