<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-12-01T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-12-01T16:00:00-05:00" n="298" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d298">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">861.77 Chinese Eastern/536: Circular
                            telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                Certain <gloss type="to">Diplomatic
                                Representatives</gloss></hi><note n="45" xml:id="d298fn45"><p>In
                                    Albania, Austria, Belgium, Bulgaria, Canada, Chile, Costa Rica,
                                    Cuba, Czechoslovakia, the Free City of Danzig, Denmark, the
                                    Dominican Republic, Egypt, Ethiopia, Finland, Greece, Guatemala,
                                    Honduras, Hungary, the Irish Free State, Latvia, Liberia,
                                    Mexico, The Netherlands, Nicaragua, Norway, Panama, Persia,
                                    Peru, Poland, Portugal, Rumania, Siam, Spain, Sweden,
                                    Switzerland, Turkey, Venezuela, and Yugoslavia.</p>
                                <p>The circular telegram was also sent December 1, 6 p.m., to the
                                    diplomatic representatives in Germany (No. 95), Italy (No. 79),
                                    and Japan (No. 123); Great Britain (No. 321), with a request to
                                    relay it to Australia, New Zealand, South Africa, and India;
                                    France (No. 395), with a request to relay it to Afghanistan, and
                                    (No. 396, 7 p.m.), with request that Belgium, Denmark, and
                                    Latvia respectively be requested to relay it to Luxemburg,
                                    Iceland, Estonia, and Lithuania (861.77 Chinese Eastern/524,
                                    530, 532, 535).</p>
                                <p>On December 2, 1929, 4 p.m., the Legation in Poland (No. 68) and
                                    the Consul in the Free City of Danzig were instructed that the
                                    former should relay the circular telegram to Poland and, through
                                    Poland, to the Free City of Danzig (861.77 Chinese Eastern/556,
                                    557).</p></note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-12-01T16:00:00-05:00">December 1, 1929—4
                                p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1. I desire that you call immediately upon the Minister for Foreign
                            Affairs, or whatever officer is in charge of the Foreign Office in his
                            absence, and make orally a statement substantially as follows: The
                            American Government has been engaged in discussions with the Governments
                            of several of the other Powers signatory to the Pact of Paris in regard
                            to the situation in Manchuria. During the past few days organized
                            Russian forces have been in conflict with organized Chinese forces near
                            Dalainor in Northern Manchuria. It is credibly reported that many
                            casualties occurred and that thousands of the inhabitants <pb facs="0516" n="372" xml:id="pg_372"/> of the neighboring towns have
                            been driven from their homes. Although the causes of the conflict are in
                            dispute and the accounts are somewhat contradictory, it is clear that
                            serious encounters between military forces of China and Russia have
                            occurred. It is also clear that during the months since this controversy
                            began no effective steps have been taken by the Chinese and Russian
                            Governments looking toward an arbitration of the dispute or its
                            settlement through neutral conciliation or other pacific means. The
                            efficacy of the Pact of Paris depends upon the sincerity of the
                            Governments which are party to it. Its sole sanction lies in the power
                            of public opinion of the countries, constituting substantially the
                            entire civilized world, whose governments have joined in the Covenant.
                            If the recent events in Manchuria are allowed to pass without notice or
                            protest by any of these Governments the intelligent strength of the
                            public opinion of the world in support of peace cannot but be
                            impaired.</p>
                        <p>We have found in our discussions referred to above a community of view
                            with regard to the fundamental principles. There has been in these
                            discussions no suggestion of intervention of any kind. Discussions have
                            been directed to discovering the best means of expressing the opinion of
                            each of the nations by way of remonstrating against the use of force by
                            either side in this controversy.</p>
                        <p>2. The Government of the United States on its part has communicated to
                            China and to Russia a statement as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The Government and people of the United States have observed
                                    with apprehensive concern the course of events in relations
                                    between China and Russia in the phase which has developed in
                                    reference to the situation in Northern Manchuria since July
                                    10.</p>
                                <p>On July 18 this Government took steps, through conversations
                                    between the Secretary of State and the diplomatic
                                    representatives at Washington of five Powers, to see that the
                                    attention of the Chinese and the Russian Governments be called
                                    to the provisions of the Treaty for the Renunciation of War, to
                                    which both China and Russia were signatories. Both the Russian
                                    and the Chinese governments then made formal and public
                                    assurances that neither would resort to war unless attacked.
                                    Since that time that Treaty has been ratified by no less than
                                    fifty-five Powers, including China and Russia.</p>
                                <p>The American Government desires again to call attention to the
                                    provisions of the Treaty for the Renunciation of War,
                                    particularly to Article II, which reads, ‘The High Contracting
                                    Parties agree that the settlement or solution of all disputes or
                                    conflicts of whatever nature or of whatever origin they may be,
                                    which may arise among them, shall never be sought except by
                                    pacific means’; and the American Government takes occasion to
                                    express its earnest hope that China and Russia will refrain or
                                    desist from measures of hostility and will find it possible in
                                    the near future to come to an agreement between themselves upon
                                    a method for resolving by peaceful means the issues over which
                                    they are at present in controversy. The American Government
                                    feels that the respect with which China and Russia will <pb facs="0517" n="373" xml:id="pg_373"/> hereafter be held in
                                    the good opinion of the world will necessarily in great measure
                                    depend upon the way in which they carry out these most sacred
                                    promises.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>3. It is desired that in presenting the above communication you lay
                            urgent stress upon the importance at this moment to the world movement
                            toward peace that the Powers that have so unreservedly joined in the
                            Covenant of the Pact of Paris record themselves publicly and to the two
                            Powers so unhappily embroiled as condemning a recourse to arms for the
                            solution of this controversy and as believing that a solution should be
                            reached by pacific means. You will conclude by expressing this
                            Government’s earnest hope that the Government to which you are
                            accredited will find it possible as a party to the Pact of Paris to
                            participate in this action by issuing on its part a statement along
                            lines similar to that quoted above and at the same time communicating
                            its views to the Governments of China and Russia. I am addressing
                            communications in this sense to the Governments of all of the countries
                            party to the Pact, and I am informing the press with regard to the
                            statement addressed by the American Government to China and to Russia
                            and with regard to this circular communication.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Stimson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>