<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in China ( (MacMurray))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1929v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d621</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">621</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1929-10-28T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1929-10-28T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-10-28T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-10-28T19:00:00-05:00" n="621"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d621">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.933/159: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-10-28T19:00:00-05:00"
                            >October 28, 1929—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>354. Reference your 927, October 25, 5 p.m.</p>
                <p>(1) Your telegram reached the Department at 2:50 p.m., October 25, and, before it
                    was decoded, the Department was informed by a Secretary of the French Embassy,
                    who called, that his Foreign Office had been informed regarding these
                    discussions, including the explanation by you of my views and the offer by you
                    to withhold until November 1 the note from the United States Government. The
                    desirability of a simultaneous dispatch of the several notes, which should
                    coincide in purport, was urged by the French Government.</p>
                <p>It was explained to the French officer that the United States Government wished
                    to cooperate as far as possible with the other governments; that the withholding
                    by you of the American reply until November 1 is quite approved, as there is no
                    desire to be precipitate; that the instructions sent you were based on the
                    feeling that the formulae hitherto considered tentatively by you and your
                    colleagues could not be regarded as applicable for adoption in the American
                    reply, because, as is well known to all concerned, the United States
                    Government’s willingness to negotiate was affirmed expressly in its note dated
                    August 10. A further explanation followed along the lines of my 342, October 22,
                    5pm., paragraph 2. The view was also advanced that the Department’s readiness to
                    delay sending the American note in reply is qualified because of the feeling
                    that the sooner the powers reply the greater will be the advantage from having
                    done so.</p>
                <p>(2) Referring to your paragraph 2: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>To the unanimous views of the Ministers I am not indifferent.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>On this point my views remain as they were stated in the first two
                            paragraphs of my 342.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Developments in the past few years and the Nationalist movement’s
                            character and exigencies, I feel, make it inevitable for the present
                            Chinese Government, or any other one, to insist upon abolition of
                            extraterritorial jurisdiction. Therefore, an offer of negotiations, I
                            feel, provides the sole possible means whereby denunciation of treaty
                            provisions may be delayed and the period of transition may be protracted
                            and ameliorated so as to safeguard, through a graduated process of
                            relinquishment as agreed upon, the position of American citizens
                            hereafter in China.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Though I do not desire to force the pace, yet I do not wish the
                            Chinese to be able to contend that they were driven to take arbitrary
                                <pb facs="0759" n="615" xml:id="pg_615"/> unilateral action because
                            of a refusal by the powers, the United States included, to face the
                            issue with them. I believe, also, that an attempt to divert attention to
                            the Provisional Court at Shanghai, a specific question, by sidetracking
                            the general question of extraterritorial jurisdiction, would be
                            difficult.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>(3) Toward the views and the convenience of the other powers I wish to be
                    altogether considerate. The manner of replying, the substance of the notes, and
                    the time of their delivery I consider important. You may, as suggested, delay
                    the American reply.</p>
                <p>(4) The text which I have submitted in itself carries, I feel, a sufficiently
                    concrete proposal, stating definitely, as it does, that the negotiations shall
                    be directed to devise a method for relinquishing extraterritorial rights
                    gradually, as to either designated territorial areas or particular kinds of
                    jurisdiction, or both, provided, etc. It would be unwise technically, I feel, at
                    this time to make a more restrictive proposal to the Chinese, enabling them
                    thereby to contend that evidently there is no intention on the part of the
                    United States to consider the entire problem, and this would afford the Chinese
                    a specious pretext for a unilateral denunciation next January 1. What I have
                    proposed offers, I believe, a sufficient safeguard against any Chinese
                    expectation or representation of agreement by the United States Government to
                    early and unconditional abolition of extraterritoriality, nor will it leave the
                    Chinese with any possible excuse for declining an attempt to deal by agreement
                    with the matter.</p>
                <p>Finally, I feel that a demand of the Chinese first to make concrete proposals
                    would, if responded to at all, which I do not expect it would be, enable them to
                    proffer proposals not susceptible of acceptance. The makers of such a demand
                    would thus be put in a very unfortunate position.</p>
                <p>(5) Again, for what it may be worth, I invite attention to your 861, October 5,
                    noon.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stimson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
