<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State ( (Johnson) ) of a
                    Conversation Between the Acting Secretary of State and the British Chargé (
                    (Campbell))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1929v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d631</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">631</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1929-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1929-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="631"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d631">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.933/172</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Johnson</hi>) <hi rend="italic">of a Conversation Between the
                        Acting Secretary of State and the British Chargé</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Campbell</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-11-15">November 15,
                            1929</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Campbell called upon the Acting Secretary<note n="16" xml:id="d631fn16"
                        >Joseph P. Cotton, Under Secretary of State.</note> to say that under
                    instructions from his Government he desired to inform us that his Government
                    hoped that we would not reach final conclusions with regard to instructions to
                    Mr. MacMurray on the subject of Chinese extraterritoriality until his Government
                    had an opportunity to present through him their reasons for the abolishment of
                    extraterritorial rights by categories of cases rather than by geographical
                    areas. He stated that he had in his possession these arguments and would like to
                    present them at some convenient time.</p>
                <p>The Acting Secretary asked me if I could see Mr. Campbell on the subject and I
                    told Mr. Campbell at his convenience I would discuss the matter with him.</p>
                <p>Mr. Campbell also stated that his Government had been approached by the Chinese
                    Government to begin separate negotiations on this subject and his Government had
                    replied that it could not agree to separate negotiations, that it thought
                    negotiations should be undertaken in Peking and that it also felt that
                    negotiations should be conducted jointly with the powers. Mr. Campbell stated
                    that he had been instructed to ask whether we agreed with that point of view.
                    Mr. Campbell was told that the matter had not been considered or settled yet but
                    that we would be very glad to inform him on this matter before final
                    instructions were sent.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>N[<hi rend="smallcaps">elson</hi>] T. J[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ohnson</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
