<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-12-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-12-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="641" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d641">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.933/213</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State</hi>
                                (<hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-12-02">December 2, 1929</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The Chinese Minister called upon me this morning, by arrangement,
                            pursuant to the conversation which he had with the Secretary <pb facs="0774" n="630" xml:id="pg_630"/> on November 21, to discuss the
                            question of extraterritoriality. He brought with him Mr. Liang, a
                            secretary of the Legation, whom he introduced to me and stated that he
                            had brought him along as of possible assistance in answering any
                            questions as Mr. Liang had been in the Provisional Court at Shanghai.
                            …</p>
                        <p>After some conversation on extraneous subjects the Chinese Minister
                            referred to the question of extraterritoriality and I handed to him, and
                            gave a copy thereof to Mr. Liang, the attached statement. Upon reading
                            it the Chinese Minister commented that it was the final paragraph of our
                            note to the Chinese Government<note n="27" xml:id="d641fn27">Dated
                                August 10, 1929; for text, see telegram No. 254, August 1, to the
                                Minister in China, <ref target="#pg_596">p. 596</ref>.</note> in
                            reply to their note asking for the abolishment of
                                extraterritoriality.<note n="28" xml:id="d641fn28">Dated April 27,
                                1929; for text, see note of May 2 from the Chinese Minister, <ref target="#pg_559">p. 559</ref>.</note> I said that it was and
                            that as it stated, it was the only basis upon which we were prepared to
                            conduct the negotiations and I desired to give it to him and use it
                            myself as the basis from which we would begin any discussion we might
                            have. I pointed out to the Minister that this communication raised two
                            questions which would have to be settled and I wished to propound to him
                            now the first question, and I asked him whether he had any suggestion to
                            offer, for his part, of a method for the gradual relinquishment of
                            extraterritorial rights either as to designated territorial areas or as
                            to particular kinds of jurisdiction, or as to both.</p>
                        <p>The Chinese Minister said he had no suggestion to make, that as his
                            Government desired the abolishment of extraterritoriality naturally they
                            would have no suggestion to make.</p>
                        <p>I replied to him that that seemed to put the entire responsibility upon
                            us of devising a means for the gradual abolishment of
                            extraterritoriality and that discussions could only continue in case he
                            would be willing to consider some method that we might propose, inasmuch
                            as we were not prepared to accept the Chinese Government’s only
                            proposal, namely, that of immediate abolishment.</p>
                        <p>The Chinese Minister stated that he felt that if we could agree on
                            abolishment that then it would be possible for them to discuss how that
                            might be accomplished. I stated that it was obvious that we could not
                            agree on sudden or immediate abolishment. The Minister stated that he
                            felt that the abolishment, whether immediate, sudden or gradual was all
                            the same thing. I stated that might be as it might be. I said that in
                            view of the fact that his Government was placing upon us the entire
                            responsibility for devising a method for the gradual abolishment of
                            extraterritoriality it now remained for me to consider some method. I
                            said that we had been unable as yet to determine on any particular
                            method but were considering several lines of <pb facs="0775" n="631" xml:id="pg_631"/> thought. I said that one line we were considering
                            contemplated the possibility of enforcing Chinese law through the
                            instrumentality of American judicial tribunals now existing in China,
                            but that before we could reach any definite conclusions as to the
                            efficacy of such a method, I would need to have from him some
                            information along the lines of the second question laid down in this
                            communication which 1 had handed to him, namely, as to what steps had
                            been taken and what improvements had been achieved by the Chinese
                            Government in the enactment and effective enforcement of laws based on
                            modern concepts of jurisprudence. I asked him if he was prepared to give
                            me any information with regard to that which we could have for
                            study.</p>
                        <p>The Minister said he thought that he could give us some information. I
                            asked him specifically for copies of laws which had been promulgated and
                            which had been enforced. I pointed out that I already possessed a copy
                            of the first book of the Civil Code of the Republic of China covering
                            the general principles of the code promulgated by the National
                            Government on the 23 of May, 1929. He asked me what I thought of it. I
                            told him that in so far as I had been able to read it, it seemed a very
                            interesting and valuable contribution, but the most important part
                            remained to be seen, namely, the civil code of the laws and I asked him
                            whether he had a copy of that and he told me he had not, that it was not
                            yet finished and that it covered a range of subjects which would
                            probably be the most difficult to codify and that it would probably be
                            the last code that would be completed. I said this code was of profound
                            interest to us in any discussion of this subject that we might have and
                            that I would like to have any and all information that he could give me
                            in regard to it and also in regard to the establishment and maintenance
                            of courts for the enforcement of these laws.</p>
                        <p>The Chinese Minister promised to gather this information for me. The
                            conversation here ended.</p>
                        <closer><signed>N[<hi rend="smallcaps">elson</hi>] T. J[<hi rend="smallcaps">ohnson</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>