<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State ( (Johnson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1929v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d875</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">875</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1929-05-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1929-05-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86005172"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific research</term>
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-05-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-05-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="875"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d875">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">031.11 American Museum of Natural History (4th
                    Asiatic)/17</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Johnson</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-05-20">May 20,
                            1929</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Chinese Minister called at noon by appointment. The Minister stated that he
                    had called for the purpose of informing the Secretary of two replies he had
                    received to his two messages concerning the Roy Chapman Andrews Expedition, one
                    message sent as the result of his conversation with Doctor Sherwood<note n="24"
                        xml:id="d875fn24">George H. Sherwood, director of the American Museum of
                        Natural History, New York.</note> and the other message sent as the result
                    of his conversation with the Secretary on May thirteenth.</p>
                <p>The Minister stated that in reply to his first telegram, the Minister for Foreign
                    Affairs at Nanking stated that the question had previously been handled by an
                    organization for the preservation of antiquities in North China and had not been
                    up for consideration by the Minister for Foreign Affairs, but now that it was
                    before the Government, the National Legislature (Legislative Yuan) was giving
                    consideration to a law on the subject of the preservation of antiquities which
                    would be general in its application, and it was hoped then that the question of
                    the Andrews Expedition could be properly handled.</p>
                <p>The Secretary asked the Minister whether he had communicated to his Government
                    the Secretary’s anxiety with regard to the future prospects of the Andrews
                    Expedition as every day’s delay was making it less probable that the Expedition
                    would be successful and the Minister’s remark that the matter was to be dealt
                    with by the Legislature sounded ominous. The Minister stated that he was coming
                    to that: that in a second telegram, a personal one from the Foreign Minister,
                    Mr. C. T. Wang, to himself in reply to the second telegram reporting his
                    conversation with the Secretary, the Foreign Minister had stated that the
                    Secretary of State should not be worried about <pb facs="0987" n="843"
                        xml:id="pg_843"/> the matter as he was sure that every just consideration
                    would be given to the requirements of Mr. Andrews.</p>
                <p>The Secretary stated that he felt these replies did not quite meet the situation,
                    that it was not a question of human antiquities whose preservation for
                    historical and national reasons he could understand and sympathize with, but it
                    was a question of scientific research into the remains of early prehistoric
                    life, of interest to the entire world, a research in which all peoples would
                    equally benefit, which was being held up by the Chinese at the present time. Mr.
                    Andrews was not a new investigator in this field. He had proved his ability by
                    previous expeditions and was now asking for permission to proceed on an
                    expedition for this coming summer and he was being delayed by requirements and
                    demands which the Secretary said appeared to be most unusual and most
                    burdensome. The Secretary felt that perhaps the Chinese Government did not
                    appreciate the fact that further delay was calculated to jeopardize the entire
                    expedition as the summer would soon be over and communication impossible.</p>
                <p>The Chinese Minister stated that he felt the requirements which the Secretary
                    referred to had been made by inexperienced persons engaged in cooperating with
                    this party in North China; that he felt sure the authorities at Nanking could
                    and would recognize the importance of the matter. He said that he would
                    telegraph again and that he hoped to have a more favorable reply to his next
                    telegram. He said that after all the dinosaur bones had been there a long time
                    and perhaps a delay of a day or two would not make too much difference. The
                    Secretary stated that of course it was quite true that the dinosaur bones had
                    been sitting a long time but that the expedition was in the field and could not
                    wait and it was very important that something be done very soon.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>N[<hi rend="smallcaps">elson</hi>] T. J[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ohnson</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
