<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in China ( (MacMurray) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1929v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d894</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">894</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1929-02-02T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1929-02-02T04:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-02-02T04:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-02-02T04:00:00-05:00" n="894"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d894">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">493.11N15/287: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-02-02T17:00:00+08:00"
                            >February 2, 1929—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 5:58 p.m.<note n="54" xml:id="d894fn1">Telegram in eight
                            sections.</note>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>83. 1. Following from the American members of the Nanking Separations Commission:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Commission has verified and assessed all American claims other than the
                            following:</p>
                        <p>(1) The American Government Claim. Chinese Commissioners in letter
                            January 28<note n="55" xml:id="d894fn2">Not printed.</note> have quoted
                            instructions sent to British Commissioners by British Minister under
                            date of November 16, 1928 (see our despatch of December 31<note n="55"
                                xml:id="d894fn3">Not printed.</note>), and have renewed request that
                            the American Government take similar action in presenting its claims in
                            the same detailed form as private claims. American Commissioners will
                            make no reply pending further instructions. In addition to total stated
                            in Shanghai’s telegram No. 325 of October 31, noon, Navy personnel <pb
                                facs="1004" n="860" xml:id="pg_860"/> claims totalling American
                            $339.30 and Mexican $97 have been received by the American Commission
                            from the Nanking Consulate which states copies were at same time
                            transmitted to Legation which it is presumed will include such claim in
                            notification supplemental to notification November 7, 1928.</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>2. Chinese Commissioners were duly notified of the Department’s No. 315
                            of last September 17, 4 p.m.,<note n="56" xml:id="d894fn4">
                                <ref target="frus1928v02#pg_359">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1928, vol. <hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 359</ref>.</note> in reference
                            to interest on claims and informally questioned proposal but stated that
                            matter would be referred to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs for a
                            ruling. Later the Chinese Commissioners intimated that at least some
                            compromise on the Department’s proposal might be reached, this leading
                            American Commissioners to hope for eventual success. To clarify such
                            highly unsatisfactory status of the case, American Commissioners have
                            persistently pressed for definite reply as to the attitude of the
                            National Government but the Chinese Commissioners with equal insistence
                            have plead their inability to obtain definite statement from the
                            Ministry of Foreign Affairs.</p>
                        <p>American Commissioners in support of the Department’s proposal have
                            informally cited cases, while Chinese Commissioners have cited 1911
                            revolution claim settlement when interest was waived. However, this
                            waiver was the result of special action taken <hi rend="italic">in
                                misericordia</hi>. This morning all hopes for satisfactory solution
                            of the matter were ended when Chinese Commissioner Young orally informed
                            American Commissioners that instructions finally had been received from
                            his Government and that Chinese Commissioners definitely cannot agree to
                            payment of interest on any claim. When again pressed for written
                            statement in the matter, Young with reluctance finally promised to go on
                            formal written record as to the position of the Foreign Office and has
                            just submitted letter reading in part as follows: <quote
                                rend="blockquote">
                                <p>‘We feel that the undertaking of the National Government to make
                                    compensation in full for all personal injuries and material
                                    damages does not include the payment of interest which question
                                    was never brought up during the negotiations which led to the
                                    Federal Government settling the Nanking incident.’</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>7. Respecting paragraph (1) of section 1, the Legation in a telegram instruction
                    of January 15th authorized the American Commissioners to reaffirm their position
                    that, under the identic note issued to the American and Chinese Commissioners by
                    their respective Governments, they are to accept and approve the American
                    Government’s claim as presented and that it is therefore not within the
                    competence of the Commission in any way to question this claim.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">MacMurray</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
