<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Colombian Minister ( (Olaya))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1929v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d918</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">918</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1929-02-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1929-02-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec81deb9Nh3WRhWg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Commercial
                        aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-02-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-02-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="918"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d918">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">821.7961/36</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Colombian Minister</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Olaya</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-02-23">February 23,
                            1929</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the conversations which you
                    have had recently with the Department of State regarding the facilities which
                    aircraft of United States registry will enjoy in Colombia for commercial
                    aviation service and, reciprocally, in the United States including the Panama
                    Canal Zone aircraft of Colombian registry, I take pleasure in confirming, by
                    means of the present note, the understanding at which we have arrived, to
                    wit:</p>
                <p>Commercial aircraft of United States registry will have permission to fly along
                    the Atlantic and Pacific Coasts of Colombia and over the territory immediately
                    adjacent thereto; to land on land or water, fuel, make repairs, and ship and
                    discharge passengers, mail and cargo, in the Atlantic and Pacific ports of
                    Colombia where there are authorities charged with carrying out the pertinent
                    regulations, subject to regulations and provisions equivalent to those
                    established for commercial aircraft of Colombian registry in the enclosures to
                    this note.<note n="2" xml:id="d918fn2">Enclosures not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Reciprocally, commercial aircraft of Colombian registry will have permission to
                    land on land or water in the Atlantic and Pacific ports of the United States
                    including those of the Panama Canal Zone, and to fly between the ports of the
                    Canal Zone following the route designated by the Governor of the Panama Canal,
                    fuel, make repairs and ship and discharge passengers, mail and cargo, subject to
                    the regulations and provisions which are enclosed with the present note, as
                    follows:</p>
                <p>For the continental United States, the Air Commerce Act of 1926 and the
                    Regulations promulgated pursuant thereto; for the Panama Canal Zone, Executive
                    Orders Nos. 4971 and 5047 of September 28, 1928, and February 18, 1929,
                    respectively, and the Provisional Regulations of the Governor of the Panama
                    Canal issued pursuant thereto.</p>
                <p>All aircraft must carry out the respective Governmental regulations of both
                    countries.</p>
                <p>If either of the two Governments decides to terminate the permission to which
                    this agreement refers or to modify the regulations or provisions, it will give
                    ninety days’ previous notice thereof to the other Government.</p>
                <pb facs="1027" n="883" xml:id="pg_883"/>
                <p>It is understood that the two Governments agree and will endeavor to give the
                    greatest possible facilities to aircraft in international commercial
                    communication service in order that they may land on land or water, fuel, and
                    carry out the other services above mentioned with all desirable speed and
                    efficacy.</p>
                <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Frank B. Kellogg</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
