<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-02-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="925" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d925">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.3731/304</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Cuban Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Ferrara</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-02-20">February 20, 1929</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that
                            the Department received in due time the note of January 10, 1929, in
                            which you <pb facs="1038" n="894" xml:id="pg_894"/> state that your
                            Government has carefully examined the Department’s note of June 13, 1928
                            and its enclosed study by the United States Tariff Commission regarding
                            the effects of the Reciprocity Treaty. Your observation has been noted
                            that the statements made in the study coincide in part with your
                            Government’s views but to a certain extent do not; and your belief has
                            also been noted that an analytical examination of the statistics and
                            deductions “would not be conducive to the success of these negotiations”
                            since, you observe, the differences that could be found are due to
                            differing appreciations of the facts.</p>
                        <p>Your allusions to the intimate and cordial relations both political and
                            commercial which, ever since the establishment of the independence of
                            Cuba, have subsisted between our countries have been read with
                            appreciation as has also your statement that your Government “does not
                            aspire to anything else but to find a solution for the future that will
                            be of common interest”; and I wish to assure you that my Government also
                            desires that the relations between the two countries shall be mutually
                            advantageous.</p>
                        <p>With reference to the suggestion, on page 17 of the English translation
                            which you supplied with your note, that your Government “would be
                            willing to enter into an understanding on the basis of a reciprocal
                            interest, whereby Cuba be granted the free entry of her sugar for a
                            limited quantity”, I wish to say that careful consideration is being
                            given to the matter and that another communication will be addressed to
                            you as soon as adequate study shall have been given to this suggestion
                            and to your explanations and arguments.</p>
                        <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Frank B. Kellogg</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>