<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-12-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-12-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="980" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d980">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">883.5122/11</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The American Minister in Egypt</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gunther</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Egyptian Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                                (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Yeghen
                                Pasha</hi></persName>)<note n="43" xml:id="d980fn43">Copy
                                transmitted to the Department by the Minister in Egypt in his
                                despatch No. 298, December 7, 1929; received January 3,
                            1930.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-12-06">December 6, 1929</date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 170</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of Your Excellency’s circular note No. 48–2/1 (cir. 81) of
                            November 11, 1929,<note n="44" xml:id="d980fn44">Not printed.</note>
                            reminding me of the note which Your Excellency’s predecessor had
                            addressed to the Chargé d’Affaires on August 7, last, communicating a
                            draft decree relative to the Ghaffir Tax and requesting that the matter
                            be submitted to my Government with a view to obtaining its consent to
                            the application of the provisions of this decree to Americans residing
                            in Egypt.</p>
                        <p>In reply, I have the honor to inform Your Excellency that my Government
                            will be glad to give its consent to the application of the Ghaffir Tax
                            to Americans resident in Egypt if and when the other powers enjoying
                            capitulatory rights in Egypt consent thereto.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to invite Your Excellency’s consideration to the
                            expediency of redrafting, in the interest of clarity, Article 2 of the
                            above mentioned draft decree. As at present drafted, it is not perfectly
                            clear that the tenant could not be held liable for a greater proportion
                            of his annual rental than that actually due at the moment when the owner
                            of the property may default in the matter of the payment of the Ghaffir
                            Tax. Your Excellency might wish to consider including a phrase in this
                            Article to the effect that the tenant may only be held liable, at any
                            time, for the actual amount of rental already due at that moment, that
                            is to say, at the time the tax is collected. It is understood, of
                            course, that the tenant may deduct the tax from the rental due to his
                            landlord.</p>
                        <p>In a recent informal conversation with His Excellency Waguih Pasha, he
                            informed me that certain substantial improvements were being made in the
                            Ghaffir service in the rural districts and that he felt that hereafter
                            no one residing in the rural districts would have cause for complaint.
                            As Your Excellency is undoubtedly aware, heretofore Americans having
                            property or business interests in rural Egypt have found it necessary to
                            employ their own independent guards. I know that it would be a source of
                            gratification to my Government if in due course I might be acquainted
                            with the measures of improvement instituted by the Royal Egyptian
                            Government for communication to interested Americans.</p>
                        <p>I avail myself [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Franklin Mott
                            Gunther</hi></signed></closer>
                        <pb facs="1106" n="962" xml:id="pg_962"/>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>[In a note dated February 13, 1930, the Egyptian Minister for Foreign
                                Affairs informed the American Minister in Egypt of the approval by
                                the capitulatory powers of the draft decree (883.5122/13), but the
                                decree was not promulgated. In a note dated January 25, 1931, the
                                Egyptian Minister for Foreign Affairs announced the intention to
                                promulgate a modified decree as of January 1 (883.5122/20). The
                                Secretary of State in instruction No. 36, March 24, 1931, informed
                                the Minister in Egypt: “In view of the fact that the new Egyptian
                                law is even less restrictive than that to which this Government
                                originally consented, your action in the matter [reiterating
                                American consent] is approved.” (883.5122/21). The law as
                                promulgated was published on May 2, 1931, in the <hi rend="italic">Journal Officiel</hi>, No. 43.]</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>