<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>United States Delegation Journal</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d172</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">172</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-09-11T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-09-11T10:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="sovereignty" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696" lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="draft-treaty" lcsh-match="no_match">Draft treaty</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="u-n-charter">U.N. Charter</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-09-11T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-09-11T10:00:00-05:00" n="172" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d172">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">United States Delegation Journal</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-chapter-heading" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-09-11T16:00:00+01:00">September 11, 1946, 4 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> (PC) (Journal) 39</p>
                <p>The Chairman announced that the Commission would proceed to examine the two
                    amendments to Article 2 submitted by Australia and <pb facs="0468" n="424" xml:id="pg_424"/> Great Britain. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SAT1">Stirling</persName> (Australia) stated that the Australian amendment
                    (C.P.(H/P)Doc. 6)<note n="78" xml:id="d172fn1">
                        <p>The proposals contained in C.P. (H/P) Doc. 6 were as follows:</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Article 2</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Renumber present Article 2, Article 2 Paragraph (1).</p>
                        <p>Add following paragraphs:— <list>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>“Hungary undertakes that in order to fulfil the obligations
                                    under paragraph 1 of this article, those obligations shall be
                                    recognised as fundamental laws and that no law, regulation or
                                    official action shall conflict or interfere with those
                                    obligations, nor shall any law, regulation or official action
                                    prevail over them.”</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>“The State to which territory is restored under Article 1 (4)
                                    of this Treaty shall take all measures necessary to secure to
                                    all persons within the territory, without distinction as to
                                    race, sex, language or religion, the enjoyment of human rights
                                    and of the fundamental freedoms, including freedom of
                                    expression, of press and publication, of religious worship, of
                                    political opinion and of public meeting.”</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>“Such State undertakes that, in order to fulfil its
                                    obligations under paragraph 3, those obligations shall be
                                    recognised as fundamental laws, and that no law, regulation or
                                    official action shall conflict or interfere with those
                                    obligations, nor shall any law, regulation or official action
                                    prevail over them.”</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </note> would add three additional paragraphs to Article 2. The first paragraph
                    was in effect a restatement of the principles of the minority treaties. There
                    had been criticism in some quarters that Australia was “trying to break in an
                    open door”. However, doors sometimes closed and the Australian Delegation was
                    looking to the future. The Delegate of the U.S.S.R. and Byelo-Russia spoke in no
                    uncertain terms against the amendment, arguing that the Hungarian Government had
                    already taken action to repeal laws of a discriminating nature. Moreover, the
                    preamble of the new democratic constitution of Hungary gave sufficient
                    protection. The Australian amendment trespassed on the sovereignty of Hungary,
                    while the draft treaty and the <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> Charter
                    covered all eventualities.</p>
                <p>The Australian Delegate stated he had hoped to have some positive support for his
                    amendment. Australia, even if 17,000 miles away, was able to see clearly that
                    the question of minorities in Europe was of great importance, particularly after
                    his Delegation’s experience in Paris. He said he would not press for paragraphs
                    1 and 3 of his amendment. However, the second paragraph of the Australian
                    amendment was designed to give rights to the inhabitants of any “restored”
                    territory. <persName corresp="#p_HVS1">Viscount Hood</persName> (U.K.) moved
                    that discussion be deferred until such time as the Commission had taken a
                    decision on the question of ceding territory. M. <persName corresp="#p_NKV1">Novikov</persName> (U.S.S.R.), contending that the Australian proposal had
                    been rejected as a whole in two other commissions (Finland and Rumania) stated
                    that there was no purpose in discussing it in connection with ceded territory,
                    since in the case of Hungary, territory would be ceded to an Allied country
                    (i.e., Czechoslovakia). After considerable argument in which the Czech
                    Delegation also spoke in opposition to the Australian amendment, a point of
                    order was raised on the motion for deferment after 2 members had spoken for the
                    U.K. amendment and 2 against. A vote <pb facs="0469" n="425" xml:id="pg_425"/>
                    was then taken on the question of postponing further consideration, which
                    resulted in 9 delegations against postponement and 4 in favor (U.K., U.S.,
                    Australia, India). Discussion then continued on the Australian amendment. M.
                        <persName corresp="#p_BEAS1">Bebler</persName> (Yugoslavia) spoke for
                    twenty-minutes against the Australian amendment. He restated the arguments of
                    the Czecholovak and U.S.S.R. Delegations, but sharply attacked Australia’s
                    motives, pointing out its amendment would support reaction in Hungary. The
                    Australian Delegate said rather bitterly that Australia had not made amendments
                    with the idea of helping Australia or any group of countries, but only to
                    further the economic and political stability of Europe. In the future if the
                    treaties broke down, it could not be said that Australia had not attempted to
                    establish at least some principles for peacemaking. The question then came to a
                    vote, in which all members of the Commission were against the second paragraph
                    of the amendment except Australia.</p>
                <p>The Chairman proposed that the Commission proceed to examine the U.K. amendment
                    to the same article<note n="79" xml:id="d172fn2">The amendment was proposed in
                        C.P. (H/P) Doc. 10; for text, <hi rend="italic">mutatis mutandis</hi>, see
                        footnote 71, <ref target="#pg_418">p. 418</ref>.</note> but before
                    discussion could be opened the U.S.S.R. Delegate (M. <persName corresp="#p_NKV1">Novikov</persName>) raised a point of procedure, contending that in
                    accordance with a letter from the General Secretariat no amendments could be
                    offered after the deadline of August 20, unless they were new proposals or
                    unless amendments were designed to reach a compromise on controversial
                        amendments.<note n="80" xml:id="d172fn3">Regarding the August 20 deadline,
                        see the extract from the Verbatim Record of the 19th Plenary Meeting, August
                        15, <ref target="#pg_236">p. 236</ref>.</note> There then followed a two
                    hour discussion on the question of procedure which had all the earmarks of a
                    filibuster. The Chairman suggested this question of procedure be referred to a
                    plenary session of the Conference. The Czechoslovak Delegate moved adjournment,
                    with the U.K. Delegate making it clear that the question should remain on the
                    agenda of the next meeting. The Commission finally adjourned at 8 p.m.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
