<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-09-17T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-09-17T04:00:00-05:00" n="198" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d198">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source"><gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>
                                Files</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">United States Delegation Journal</hi></head>
                            <dateline>
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-chapter-heading" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-09-17T10:00:00+01:00">September
                                    17, 1946, 10 a.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> (PC)
                                (Journal) 44</p>
                            <p>The Commission began final approval of the Italian Treaty.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_TMGF1">General Theron</persName>, (South
                                Africa) proposed that Articles 49, 50, 51 and Annex 4 A of the
                                Italian Treaty be discussed by a naval subcommittee. This proposal
                                was withdrawn when it was opposed by <persName corresp="#p_SLGNV1">General Slavin</persName> (USSR) and Admiral
                                    <persName>Conolly</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_TMGF1">General Theron</persName> then introduced his amendment to
                                Article 39 which proposed a five-year time limit for maintenance in
                                force of the provisions of the article after which time the Security
                                Council could modify them.<note n="22" xml:id="d198fn1"><p>All South
                                        African amendments to the military clauses of the Italian
                                        Treaty were contained in C.P. (Mil) Doc. 9, September 14.
                                        The introduction of that document was as follows:<quote rend="blockquote"><p>“The South African Delegation,
                                                after hearing the observations of the Italian
                                                Delegation on the following articles, submits that
                                                they merit further consideration and therefore moves
                                                that they be considered as amendments, as revised in
                                                certain instances. The South African Delegation in
                                                bringing these proposals as amendments before the
                                                Commission, is weighed thereto by the fact of
                                                Italy’s two years’ co-belligerency with the Allies,
                                                and which we regard as having been given but scant
                                                recognition in the proposals by the Council of
                                                Foreign Ministers.”</p><p>The amendments proposed
                                                were those contained in Part II of Observations on
                                                the Draft Peace Treaty with Italy by the Italian
                                                Government, <ref target="frus1946v04#pg_117">vol.
                                                  <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p.
                                            117</ref>.</p></quote></p></note> After some <pb facs="0515" n="471" xml:id="pg_471"/> debate during which Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_AVA1">Alexander</persName> (UK) and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SLGNV1">General Slavin</persName> opposed
                                the amendment, a vote was taken and the South African amendment was
                                defeated by a vote of 16–4, with Australia, the Netherlands and New
                                Zealand supporting South Africa and Brazil absent. Article 39 was
                                then finally accepted. The South African amendment to Article 40 was
                                defeated with the French Delegation being most prominent in
                                opposition. The vote was 19 against, 1 for, and 1 absent. Article 40
                                was then adopted with the amendment of the French [<hi rend="italic">US</hi>] Delegation previously accepted by the Commission.<note n="23" xml:id="d198fn2">Regarding the Commission’s previous
                                    consideration of article 40, see the United States Delegation
                                    Journal accounts of the 6th Meeting, August 29, and the 7th
                                    Meeting, August 31, <ref target="#pg_309">pp. 309</ref> and <ref target="#pg_329">329</ref>, respectively.</note></p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_TMGF1">General Theron</persName> withdrew his
                                amendments to Articles 41 and 43 since the principles involved had
                                been rejected by the Commission. Article 41 was then adopted with
                                the correction which had been accepted in the 7th meeting. Article
                                42 was accepted unanimously.</p>
                            <p>The New Zealand amendment to Article 43 was withdrawn following
                                explanation of the wording of the Article by the French Delegate and
                                Article 43 was adopted.<note n="24" xml:id="d198fn3"><p>The
                                        amendment proposed to revise paragraph 4 as follows:<quote rend="blockquote"><p>“4. In Sicily and Sardinia Italy
                                                shall be prohibited from constructing any <hi rend="italic">permanent</hi> naval, military and
                                                air-force installations or fortifications except for
                                                such accommodation for security force as may be
                                                required for tasks of an internal
                                            character.”</p></quote></p></note> Articles 44 (new
                                draft by UK), 45, 46, 46A and 46B were adopted without
                                discussion.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_MRAS1">Admiral Manola</persName> (Yugoslavia)
                                asked that discussion of the Yugoslav amendment to Article 47 [C.P.
                                (Gen.) Doc.1.U.15], based upon the Albanian memorandum, be discussed
                                in connection with Annex 4A, rather than with Article 47. The
                                Chairman proposed going on to Article 48. <persName corresp="#p_TMGF1">General Theron</persName> said that the draft
                                treaty treated the Italian fleet as war booty and moved the
                                amendment suggested by the Italian memorandum as a new paragraph.
                                Captain <persName>Pryce</persName> (US) spoke in opposition to the
                                South African amendment saying that the U.S. Delegation believed it
                                was in disagreement with the terms of surrender signed by Italy, and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_TMGF1">General Theron</persName> withdrew
                                his amendment following this statement. Article 48 was adopted in
                                its original form. The South African amendment to Article 49 which
                                proposed that Italy be allowed to salvage submarines and their
                                equipment for use of the steel, machinery, etc., was rejected by
                                17–1, with 2 abstentions (Belgium, Netherlands), Brazil absent. The
                                U.S. amendment to Article 48 [<hi rend="italic">49</hi>]<note n="25" xml:id="d198fn4">For text of article 49 as revised by the United
                                    States amendment, see C.P. (Plen) Doc. 17, Report of the
                                    Military Commission on the Italian Treaty, <ref target="frus1946v04#pg_412">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p. 412</ref>.</note> was accepted by a vote of
                                19–1, after Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AVA1">Alexander</persName> had
                                said there was no disagreement between UK and US, Byelo-Russia
                                    against,<note n="26" xml:id="d198fn5">The United States
                                    Delegation Minutes indicate that Byelorussian negative vote was
                                    inadvertent (<gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Files).</note>
                                Brazil absent. Article 49 was adopted as amended, <pb facs="0516" n="472" xml:id="pg_472"/> the word “ships” being replaced by the
                                words “naval vessels”. Next meeting was set for 10:00 a.m.,
                                September 18.</p>
                        </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>