<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>United States Delegation Journal</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d251</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">251</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-09-26T12:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-09-26T12:30:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-09-26T12:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-09-26T12:30:00-05:00" n="251" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d251">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">United States Delegation Journal</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-chapter-heading" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-09-26T18:30:00+01:00">September 26, 1946, 6:30 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> (PC) (Journal) 53</p>
                <p>The Chairman (Mr. <persName>Byrnes</persName>) opened the meeting by saying that
                    the time had come after over a month of the most free and open debate to try to
                    complete the work of the Conference. The floor was given to M. <persName corresp="#p_KE1">Kardelj</persName> (Yugoslavia) who began speaking on the
                    question of the Greek-Albanian frontier. The Chairman called the speaker’s
                    attention to the fact that he was not speaking on a matter set out in the
                    agenda. He said that the Delegate could speak in favor of a motion to substitute
                    another question in the agenda and if the motion were accepted by the Conference
                    the subject could be discussed; otherwise not. M. <persName corresp="#p_KE1">Kardelj</persName> continued and the Chairman had to again call him to
                    order. <persName corresp="#p_BAM1">M. Baranovsky</persName> (Ukraine)
                    unrecognized by the Chair called out that the speaker should be allowed to
                    continue. He was silenced once but had to be quieted a second time before
                    subsiding. M. <persName corresp="#p_KE1">Kardelj</persName>
                    <pb facs="0614" n="570" xml:id="pg_570"/> completed his speech asking for a
                    definite settlement of the 30th of August decision of the Conference that the
                    Greek-Albanian frontier question be discussed at the next Plenary meeting.<note n="60" xml:id="d251fn1">See the United States Delegation Journal account of
                        the 25th Plenary Meeting, August 30, <ref target="#pg_321">p.
                        321</ref>.</note> The Greek Delegation withdrew the motion upon which this
                    decision had been made and after some debate by <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">M.
                        Molotov</persName> it was agreed that the question was no longer on the
                    agenda of the Conference.<note n="61" xml:id="d251fn2">The Greek Delegation
                        indicated that it was willing that the subject be withdrawn from the agenda,
                        but reserved the right to bring the matter to the attention of the Council
                        of Foreign Ministers (<gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Files: Verbatim
                        Record).</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary General read a letter from M. <persName corresp="#p_BDG1">Bidault</persName> written in the name of the Council of Foreign Ministers
                    which suggested a schedule for the remaining work of the Conference. The
                    Conference agreed to the four points of M. <persName corresp="#p_BDG1">Bidault</persName>’s letter together with the proposals of the Secretary
                    General for implementing them.<note n="62" xml:id="d251fn3">The text of
                            <persName corresp="#p_BDG1">Bidault</persName>’s letter is contained in
                        the Verbatim Record of the meeting. For the substance of the four-power
                        proposals it presented, see the United States Delegation Minutes of the 5th
                        Informal Meeting of the Council of Foreign Ministers at the Paris Peace
                        Conference, September 24, <ref target="#pg_538">p. 538</ref>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
