<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>United States Delegation Journal</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d257</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">257</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-09-27T15:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-09-27T15:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-09-27T15:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-09-27T15:30:00-05:00" n="257"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d257">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">United States Delegation Journal</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-chapter-heading" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1946-09-27T21:30:00+01:00">September 27, 1946, 9:30 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> (PC) (Journal) 54</p>
                <p>The Commission received the report of the subcommittee set up to study the
                    definition of “United Nations shipping” and to prepare an agreed text to replace
                    paragraph 1 of Annex 4 C.<note n="79" xml:id="d257fn1">See C.P. (Plen) Doc. 29,
                        Report of the Commission on the Draft Peace Treaty with Rumania, <ref
                            target="frus1946v04#pg_434">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp.
                            434</ref>, <ref target="frus1946v04#pg_449">449</ref>.</note> (The other
                    paragraphs of this Annex had been rejected by the Commission). The report
                    contained three proposals for addition to paragraph 8(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)
                    of Article 24: (A) a text prepared by Drafting Committee and supported by the
                    majority of the subcommittee, (B) a U.S. text supported by the U.S. and Greece,
                    and (C) a Greek text, also supported by the U.S. and Greece. The Greek
                    Representative at the outset withdrew proposal (C), however.</p>
                <p>Proposal (A) defined as <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> property vessels
                    registered in a United Nation or flying the flag of a United Nation, while the
                    U.S. proposal (B) added vessels owned by United Nations or their nationals. Mr.
                        <persName>Thorp</persName> (U.S.) explained that he considered it necessary
                    that no definition should have the effect of restricting the benefits of Article
                    24 (restoration of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> property) to vessels
                    registered in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> ports or flying <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> flags. It was clear that proposal (A) might be so
                    construed and in fact some members of the subcommittee had so construed it. The
                    U.S. amendment, Mr. <persName>Thorp</persName> said, would not permit recovery
                    by collaborators whose vessels flying Rumanian flags remained in Rumanian
                    service with the full consent of their owners after Rumania entered the war. In
                    order for a <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> owner whose vessel was flying the
                    Rumanian flag to be entitled to the benefits of Article 24, it would be
                    necessary to establish that the vessel was treated as enemy property by Rumania
                    or ceased to be at the free disposal of the owner as the result of Rumanian
                    wartime control measures. The U.S. was opposed to the argument that <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> nationals who for business reasons before the war
                    registered their vessels in ports other than those which later became <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> ports or flew flags other than those which later
                    became <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> flags, were <hi rend="italic">ipso
                        facto</hi> to be considered collaborators. The U.S. accepted an amendment to
                    the draft, proposed by the U.K. representative to clarify the relationship of
                    the definition to the other provisions of Article 24. The Czechoslovak
                    representative defended the subcommittee majority draft, stating that it was
                    hard to believe there were any ships in Rumania belonging to <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> nationals, but flying the <pb facs="0623" n="579"
                        xml:id="pg_579"/> Rumanian flag or registered in Rumania, which at the same
                    time had been subjected to special Rumanian measures of control. These ships
                    were considered Rumanian ships and the fact they were in Rumania and flying the
                    Rumanian flag proved their owners had placed them at the disposal of the
                    Rumanian Government. M. <persName corresp="#p_GVS1">Gerashchenko</persName>
                    (U.S.S.R.) also spoke for the subcommittee draft. He said that Greek ships (for
                    example) had been registered in Rumania at the free will of their owners. The
                    ships might well have been used for war purposes, and their owners probably made
                    profits. Though no one had confiscated them, the U.S. proposal would require
                    that they be returned under Article 24, with compensation for loss or damage.
                    The conditions of return ought to be effected by bilateral agreement between
                    Greece and Rumania. There was furthermore no reason why Greece should get
                    compensation for loss or damage to such ships.</p>
                <p>Proposal (B), the U.S. text, with the modification proposed by the U.K., was
                    adopted by a vote of 8 to 5 (France abstaining). It was agreed the text would
                    become the second subparagraph of paragraph 8(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) of
                    Article 24.</p>
                <p>The U.K. reservation in the footnote to Article 23, paragraph 7, was thereupon
                    withdrawn and Article 23 as a whole was approved unanimously.</p>
                <p>The U.K. footnote to Article 24, paragraph 1, was also withdrawn, and this
                    paragraph was approved unanimously (completing the action on Article 24).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
