<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>United States Delegation Journal</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d272</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">272</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-10-01T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-10-01T04:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-01T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-10-01T04:00:00-05:00" n="272" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d272">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">United States Delegation Journal</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-chapter-heading" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-10-01T10:00:00+01:00">October 1, 1946, 10 a.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> (PC) (Journal) 58</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Rapporteur</hi> made a statement (CP(IT/P) Doc 101)<note n="22" xml:id="d272fn1">Not printed.</note> to the Commission recalling the
                    types of recommendations which might be made by the Commission to the Conference
                    under the rules and asking for majority and minority reports on the several
                    articles requiring them by not later than Midday Wednesday in order that they
                    might be included in the <hi rend="italic">Rapporteur’s</hi> report to be
                    circulated on Thursday. The Chairman outlined the Commission’s schedule for the
                    remainder of the week as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Tuesday afternoon and Wednesday—discussion of Article 16 and the Statute
                            for Trieste</p>
                        <p>Thursday—to be left free for the <hi rend="italic">Rapporteur’s</hi>
                            report</p>
                        <p>Friday and Saturday morning—discussion of his report and its final
                            adoption.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The representative of Yugoslavia introduced and then spoke in favor of his
                    Delegation’s amendment (CP(IT/P) Doc 96)<note n="22" xml:id="d272fn2">Not
                        printed.</note> to Article 78 which would provide that the treaty comes into
                    effect when ratified by the four sponsoring powers and by “the Allied and
                    Associated Powers who are neighbors of Italy and whose territory was occupied by
                    Italy”. The amendment was defeated by 13 votes to 5, with two abstentions. The
                    Australian Delegation withdrew the deferred portion of its amendment (CP(IT/P)
                    Doc 15) [C.P.(Gen)Doc, 1. B. 1] to the preamble relating to human rights and the
                    Commission thereafter adopted the 5th paragraph of the preamble.</p>
                <p>The Commission then considered the report of the Subcommittee on the Yugoslav
                    amendment for a new Article 11(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) (CP(IT/P) Doc 100)
                    concerning the restitution to Yugoslavia of archives and objects <pb facs="0653" n="609" xml:id="pg_609"/> of artistic, historic and religious value with
                    respect to that portion of the territory Italy will cede to Yugoslavia. After
                    some discussion among the British, Soviet and Yugoslav Delegates a modification
                    of the Subcommittee’s redraft of the amendment was accepted in the following
                    sense: in paragraph 2 of the revised draft amendment, first line after the words
                    “all objects” add “of public legal character”. That portion of the amendment
                    (Doc 100) creating a new Article 11(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) was adopted by the
                    Commission by 19 votes to 1, the U.S. casting the negative vote. That part of
                    the report (Doc 100) amending the first paragraph of Annex 3 was adopted
                        unanimously.<note n="23" xml:id="d272fn3">C.P. (IT/P) Doc. 100 is not
                        printed. For text of the new article 11a and for text of the first paragraph
                        of Annex 3 as amended, see C.P.(Plen) Doc. 24, report of the Commission,
                            <ref target="frus1946v04#pg_309">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp.
                            309</ref> and <ref target="frus1946v04#pg_310">310</ref>,
                        respectively.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Chairman read a report from the Military Commission regarding the use of the
                    words “demilitarization” and “complete demilitarization” in Articles 11, 12 and
                        42.<note n="24" xml:id="d272fn4">For text of the Military Commission’s
                        interpretation, see footnote 34, <ref target="#pg_613">p. 613</ref>.</note>
                    It was the recommendation of the Military Commission that the word
                    “demilitarization” be used uniformly in all three articles and that a
                    description of “demilitarization” as included in the Military Commission’s
                    report should be attached to the treaty as Annex 5D. The Military Commission’s
                    report was accepted and the Ukraine amendment (CP(Gen)Doc 1.R.1) to Article 12
                    was withdrawn. Consequently the second sentence of Article 12 (which had been
                    deferred—see Journal No. 48, September 21) was adopted unanimously by the
                    Commission with a Soviet reservation regarding the Greek amendment to this
                    article referring to certain Greek-Turkish agreements.<note n="25" xml:id="d272fn5">See the United States Delegation Journal account of the
                        28th Meeting, September 21, <ref target="#pg_501">p. 501</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The report of the Legal and Drafting Commission on the Yugoslav amendment for a
                    new Article 13(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) (CP(IT/P) Doc 102) providing for the
                    option by Italian citizens of Yugoslav citizenship and their subsequent removal
                    to Yugoslavia was next considered. The Yugoslav Delegation proposed an
                    additional paragraph 3 to the report of the Legal and Drafting Committee which
                    reads as follows: “All provisions applying to persons who opt for Italian
                    nationality under Annex 3(6) shall equally apply to the transfer of properties
                    belonging to persons who opt for Yugoslav nationality according to this
                    Article.” The Chairman suggested that the Commission vote on the entire article
                    and, in view of the economic implications of the new paragraph proposed by the
                    Yugoslavs, it be referred to the Economic Commission. The Yugoslav amendment, as
                    redrafted by the Legal and Drafting Commission, (Doc. 102) was adopted by the
                    Commission by a vote <pb facs="0654" n="610" xml:id="pg_610"/> of 19 to 1. The
                    U.S. vote, in the affirmative, was conditioned on the approval of the last
                    paragraph (5) by the Economic Commission for Italy.<note n="26" xml:id="d272fn6">For text of the new article 13 <hi rend="italic">a</hi> adopted here, see
                        C.P. (Plen) Doc. 24, Report of the Political and Territorial Commission for
                        Italy, <ref target="frus1946v04#pg_312">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>,
                            p. 312</ref>. See also C.P. (Plen) Doc. 28, Report of the Legal and
                        Drafting Commission on the Draft Peace Treaty with Italy, <ref target="frus1946v04#pg_419">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 419</ref>, <ref target="frus1946v04#pg_428">428</ref>, and the United States Delegation
                        Journal account of the 33rd Meeting of the Economic Commission for Italy,
                        October 2, <ref target="#pg_630">p. 630</ref>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
