<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-04-28T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-04-28T08:00:00-05:00" n="135" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d135">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Council/4–2848: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_DLW1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-04-28T14:00:00+01:00">April 28,
                                    1948—2 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1792. <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1696. As the Department
                            is aware the agreed report of the Berlin Working Party (TRI/4) which
                            considered the various problems in regard to the future German
                            government showed little progress.<note n="1" xml:id="d135fn1">The
                                reference here is to the Final Report of Working Party No. 5 of the
                                Military Governors’ Conference at Berlin, document MGC/<gloss target="#t_P1">P</gloss>(48) 8, April 9, <ref target="#pg_170">p. 170</ref>. Document TRI/4, March 4 of the London Conference
                                on Germany is not printed, but its substance is set forth in
                                telegram 894, <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1616, March
                                5, from London, <ref target="#pg_131">p. 131</ref>.</note> During
                                <persName corresp="#p_CDM1">Couve de Murville’s</persName> visit to
                            Berlin General <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> handed him a
                            compromise proposal (see Berlin’s 898, April 16 to Department repeated
                            Paris as 164<note n="2" xml:id="d135fn2">Not printed; it transmitted the
                                text of the “<persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> paper” on
                                the political structure for Western Germany (862.011/4–1648). The
                                essential substance of that paper was reported upon in telegram 821,
                                April 9, from Berlin, <ref target="#pg_175">p. 175</ref>.</note>)
                            and subsequently the three military governors agreed to transmit
                                <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay’s</persName> paper to the present
                            London meeting as a basis for discussion.</p>
                        <p>Last Friday <persName corresp="#p_CDM1">Couve de Murville</persName>,
                            after preliminary discussion with <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>,
                            submitted a French counter-proposal. This was followed by a British
                            redraft on political organization dated April 26. <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> was prepared to base discussion at
                            this meeting on the French counter-proposal as it is believed better
                            progress could be made working from one paper which seems to offer the
                            possibility of agreement. However, the British paper is not without
                            merit. Both the French counter-proposal and British redraft are quoted
                            below. These are now the basis of current discussions on German
                            political organization.</p>
                        <p>At yesterday’s meeting there was reached considerable area of tentative
                            agreement on the language in the French counter-proposal below. Thus
                            paragraphs 1, 2 and 3 were agreed but there was no agreement on
                            paragraph 4 on the key question of whether the delegates to the
                            Constituent Assembly would be “designated” or elected. Paragraph 5 was
                            agreed but paragraph 6 is still wide open. In that connection please
                            note paragraph 4 of British redraft below. There was no particular
                            difficulty about paragraph 7 and on the point here involved of
                            ratification by the states it was agreed that the states would be the
                            new ones after whatever boundary changes are eventually approved. <pb facs="0242" n="208" xml:id="pg_208"/> It should also be said in that
                            reference that the British and French are wide apart on the question of
                            the boundaries of the future north Rhine-Westphalia, Paragraph 8 was
                            agreed with the amendment of “this committee” in the second sentence to
                            read “the Minister Presidents”. Paragraph 9 also seemed to find
                            agreement. Paragraph 10, it was agreed, would be replaced by paragraph 8
                            of British redraft. There was discussion without agreement on the
                            question of approval or disapproval by the Military Governors of the
                            several actions to be taken by the Germans. British and US agreed that
                            disapproval could be indicated by majority but the French desired more
                            time to consider this point.</p>
                        <p>It was also tentatively agreed that the provisions of paragraph 11 are
                            not necessary in the present paper.</p>
                        <p>Today a working party is endeavoring to bring the French and British
                            papers into a single draft. After another attempt by US, British and
                            French delegates to harmonize views, Benelux, which has not yet
                            participated in these discussions, will be asked for views.</p>
                        <p>Text of French and British drafts follow:</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">French Counter-Proposal</hi>.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Three commanders-in-chief will, not later than blank, call for
                                meeting of Presidents of States of their respective zones. This
                                meeting will be instructed to examine boundaries of the several
                                States in view of determining what modifications might be proposed
                                to commanders-in-chief. This survey will be carried out recognizing
                                traditional patterns, and avoiding, to extent feasible, creation of
                                States which are either too large or too small in comparison with
                                the other states composing the federation. This survey will take
                                place in close contact with allied authorities, so as to enable them
                                to take their decision before meeting of Constituent
                                Assembly.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Meeting of Minister-Presidents shall be informed of decisions
                                taken as to convening of Constituent Assembly. It will be instructed
                                to communicate those decisions to the various States and to make the
                                necessary arrangements.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Constituent Assembly will be held not later than September 1, 1948
                                to prepare constitution to be ratified by states composing the
                                federation.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Delegates to this Constituent Assembly shall be designated, in
                                each of existing States, under procedure and regulations as adopted
                                by each of these States.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Number of delegates from each State will be in proportion that its
                                population is to total population of participating States. Total
                                number of delegates will be determined by dividing total population
                                from last census by 750,000.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Constituent Assembly will draft democratic constitution which will
                                establish for States composing the federation a government structure
                                of federal type which will protect rights of participating states
                                and which will contain guarantees of individual rights and freedom.
                                (This paragraph to be completed.)</item>
                            <pb facs="0243" n="209" xml:id="pg_209"/>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Constitution as prepared by Constituent Assembly will be examined
                                by occupying powers to determine its compliance with general
                                principles stated in paragraph six. If constitution as prepared by
                                Constituent Assembly does meet these principles, it will be
                                submitted for ratification by states composing the federation under
                                such rules and procedures as these may adopt. When constitution has
                                been ratified by two-thirds of the states, it will become the
                                constitution of the federation. It will come into force and will be
                                binding upon all states. Thereafter, any amendment to constitution
                                must be ratified by like majority of the states.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>Constituent Assembly shall designate committee consisting of one
                                representative from each of the States which will form the
                                federation. This committee, in cooperation with governments of
                                existing States, will take necessary steps for election in due time
                                of Assemblies of such States boundaries of which will have been
                                modified. These Assemblies and those of the States boundaries of
                                which have not been modified shall determine conditions for
                                ratification of constitution as stated in paragraph 7 above.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>As soon as constitution has been voted, Constituent Assembly will
                                be dissolved and committee mentioned in paragraph 8 will be
                                instructed to submit constitution for ratification of States
                                composing federation. Within thirty days following coming into force
                                of constitution, this committee shall also provide for establishment
                                of institutions as determined for by constitution.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>Commanders-in-Chief shall determine control and administration
                                powers which occupying authorities intend to retain subsequent to
                                coming into force of constitution, as regards federal government as
                                well as governments of the States.</item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>Prior to coming into force of constitution, it is impracticable to
                                establish trizonal allied control. However, in interim period,
                                certain steps have or will be taken to ensure full economic
                                coordination of trizonal area and French zone of occupation. Steps
                                which have already been taken are: mint banking policy under
                                tripartite allied banking commission; agreement in principle to
                                currency reform in trizonal area. Remaining steps which should be
                                taken as soon as conditions of implementation will have been agreed
                                upon by Commanders-in-Chief are: common management of export and
                                import by tripartite Allied export-import agency and common custom
                                policy.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">British Redraft</hi>.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Three military governors will not later than blank call joint
                                meeting of Ministers President their respective zones to tell them
                                that they have decided to authorize them to arrange for convention
                                of Constituent Assembly to which any German <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> will be permitted to send delegates.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>(A) In order that serious anomalies in present arrangement of <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> boundaries may be rectified before
                                constitution ratified (see paragraph 5 below) Ministers President
                                will be asked to examine this matter and to report within one month
                                to Military Governors as to what modification they think desirable.
                                Ministers President may conduct this examination in any way which
                                appears to them appropriate. Military Governors will consider their
                                report, and will take steps to <pb facs="0244" n="210" xml:id="pg_210"/> put into effect such recommendations as they
                                agree to accept. Where Military Governors fail to agree, no change
                                will be made. <p>(B) Constitution will provide machinery to enable
                                    changes to be made in boundaries of <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>, subject to approval of people of <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> affected. Any residual problems
                                    regarding <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> boundaries not settled by
                                    procedure in (A) above will be settled subsequently by this
                                    machinery.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Ministers President shall also be told to make necessary
                                arrangements to ensure (A) that Constituent Assembly should meet as
                                soon as possible and not later than September 1, 1948; (B) that
                                delegates to this Assembly should be elected by the people of the
                                several <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> under the electoral
                                procedures and regulations adopted by the several <hi rend="italic">Laender;</hi> (C) that the number of delegates from each <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> should be in the proportion that its
                                population is to total population of participating <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>, total number of delegates being determined by
                                dividing total population at last census by 750,000.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Constitutent Assembly will draft a democratic constitution which
                                will establish for the German Federation (<hi rend="italic">Bundesstaat Deutschland</hi>) a governmental structure which
                                will protect rights of <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> and contain
                                guarantees of individual rights and freedom. In particular,
                                constitution must provide that: (A) legislature is bicameral, with
                                one Chamber representing the states; (B) chief of state (if any) is
                                not directly elected and is not given direct emergency powers; (C)
                                federation enjoys only those powers expressly delegated to it; (D)
                                    <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> have a minimum exclusive power of
                                legislation and administration in fields of education, culture, and
                                religious affairs, public health, public welfare, police and local
                                government; (E) <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> have sufficient
                                independent sources of revenue to carry out their functions.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Constituent Assembly will also prepare transitional provisions
                                which will lay down procedure for ratification of constitution, and
                                holding of elections as provided in constitution. These transitional
                                provisions must provide that when at least two-thirds of <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> participating in Constituent Assembly
                                have ratified constitution it will come into force and be binding
                                upon all participating <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>. They must
                                also provide for establishment of the government of the German
                                federation within thirty days after entry into force of
                                constitution.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Constitution and transitional provisions will be submitted to
                                Military Governors to determine their compliance with general
                                principles stated above before they are put to <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> for ratification.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Constituent Assembly will be prorogued as soon as its tasks have
                                been completed. It may, however, set up, in transitional provisions,
                                committee of one representative from each of proposed <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> which, in cooperation with <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> governments, will ensure execution of
                                transitional provisions and establishment of the institutions
                                provided for in constitution.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>Prior to entry into force of constitution, there shall be a
                                determination of control and administrative powers which occupying
                                authorities intend to retain as regards both proposed government of
                                the German federation and the governments of the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_DLW1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Douglas</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>