<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Associate Chief of the Division of Western European Affairs ( (Wallner) )
                    to the Counselor of Embassy in France ( (Bonbright))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-01-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recP2zv9bjAjSyYPT" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-01-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="14"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d14">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">French Desk File: Lot 53 D 246: File
                    “Germany”</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Associate Chief of the Division of Western European
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_WW1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wallner</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Counselor of Embassy in France</hi>
                        (<persName corresp="#p_BJCH1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bonbright</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">personal and secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-01-16">January 16,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Jamie</hi>: Deliberately we have not yet answered your
                    cables concerning the French protest on bizonal reorganization, because we feel
                    it is better to wait until the matter is thoroughly clarified in Washington, and
                    you know how difficult it is thoroughly to clarify in Washington policy matters
                    concerning Germany.</p>
                <p>I think that at this stage the following points emerge: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>In London bizonal reorganization and conversations with the French
                            were discussed in water-tight compartments. The connection between them
                            never seems to have been established in the minds of American and
                            British officials and no discussions took place at any time about
                            whether or when the French should be informed or consulted.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>The atmospherics, but not the record, of the <persName
                                corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_MGC1"
                                >Marshall</persName> conversations indicated future collaboration
                            with the French on future German questions. Consequently, the French
                            have some cause for being both surprised and hurt at the manner of
                            announcement of the Frankfurt decisions. </item>
                        <pb facs="0062" n="28" xml:id="pg_28"/>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>As for substance the French have absolutely no kick coming since no
                            commitment was made or even contemplated that they would be either
                            consulted or informed concerning bizonal reorganization.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>The British and ourselves had a different conception of how far and
                            how quickly and with how little consultation <persName
                                corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RSBH1"
                                >Robertson</persName> should proceed in bizonal reorganization.
                            However, both Washington and London was [<hi rend="italic">were</hi>]
                            equally surprised at both the scope of the Frankfurt decisions and the
                            dramatic manner of their presentation to the world.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>Until the French join trizonia and assume responsibility therefor,
                            they cannot logically expect to have either a voice or a veto in bizonal
                            matters. However, no understanding has yet been reached on this. In
                            cases such as the present one, the French should be relieved that they
                            are not called upon to approve measures which in some respects conflict
                            with their doctrine on Germany. I believe an understanding must be
                            reached whereby the French voice in German decisions will be in exact
                            ratio to the responsibilities which they are willing to assume.</item>
                        <label>(6)</label>
                        <item>Public opinion in France on the German problem has not been allowed to
                            evolve with the times. The armed truce by the political parties on this
                            subject has frozen French thought on Germany as it was in 1944 when it
                            differed hardly at all from; 1919. The average Frenchman thinks a
                            Frankfurt Government as dangerous as a Berlin Government: he has not
                            digested the significance of the latest <gloss target="#t_CFM1"
                                >CFM</gloss>, and his Government, with a persistence which according
                            to our standards would add up to treachery, has kept him in the dark
                            about the facts of life. He must be told not to tremble at the Frankfurt
                            mouse as if it were a Berlin lion.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Perhaps before you get this letter the whole thing will be considerably
                    clarified.</p>
                <p>I do not conceal my very real disappointment at a development Which contributes
                    to disharmony with the French on the German question at a time when I had hoped
                    that at last a common understanding was about to be reached. As you know, I have
                    been plugging for such a common understanding for two years.</p>
                <p>Very best,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WW1">W. <hi rend="smallcaps">Wallner</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
