<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-03T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-03T07:00:00-05:00" n="141" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d141">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Council/5–348: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_DLW1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-03T13:00:00+01:00">May 3,
                                    1948—1 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1890. <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1710. Agree with your
                            paragraph 2 <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1551, April 30
                                (<gloss target="#t_Secdel1">Secdel</gloss> 1568).<note n="1" xml:id="d141fn1">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_211">p.
                                211</ref>.</note> As to paragraph 1, entertain considerable doubts
                            because: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Soviet military authorities might take the opportunity to
                                    permit delegates from eastern zone’s <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> to attend. In this event, even though
                                    delegates were chosen by elections, we could be certain they
                                    would be of Soviet selection, subservient to their
                                    orders.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>These delegates would presumably be under instructions to use
                                    the Assembly as a platform for propaganda, as an instrument for
                                    sowing the seeds of discord among the western <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> and for attempting to persuade delegates to
                                    reject such private and friendly counsel to the German delegates
                                    as the occupying powers, during the course of the deliberations,
                                    may give.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Even though the delegates from the Soviet <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> were unsuccessful in dissuading the other
                                    delegates from accepting broad principles of the constitution
                                    which we desire, the five <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> in the
                                    Soviet zone might, with two or three <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> in the western zones, by, rejecting the
                                    constitution, delay or prevent the acceptance of the
                                    constitution by ⅔ of the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>, which
                                    will probably be a condition precedent to making the
                                    constitution effective.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>These doubts were expressed at a meeting with the French and British
                            delegations, and generally concurred in by them. In subsequent papers
                            the language in the British re-draft, to which your cable refers, was
                            deleted, no distinction is made between the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> of the western zones and the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> of the eastern zone, phrases like “various states” are
                            used, and the matter is left to the Ministers President to determine.
                            However, under the latest draft the military governors will make the <pb facs="0254" n="220" xml:id="pg_220"/> communication to the Ministers
                            President, presumably of the western <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Suggest that the best method of avoiding the appearance of a purely
                            western German government, is to make it clear that additional <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> may at any time, by accepting the
                            constitution and establishing for each a <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>
                            constitution not inconsistent with the constitution for the German
                            government as a whole, join the federation. This either the Ministers
                            President will probably do, or the constitution itself will make
                            provision for, or both devices will be used.</p>
                        <p>Hope you agree. Appreciate your comments and hope you will give them to
                            us unsparingly.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_DLW1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Douglas</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>