<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Paper Agreed Upon by the London Conference on Germany</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d155</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">155</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recwCJKUNlNbGDoDy" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93002779"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Judiciary</term>
                    <term ref="rec9aDoDi7sluDnsm" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="civil-rights"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026371"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil rights</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="155"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d155">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Files: Lot M–88: Box 118: File—TRI
                    Documents</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Paper Agreed Upon by the London Conference on Germany</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d155fn1">This paper was agreed upon at the informal meeting
                        of the London Conference on Germany on May 11; see telegram 2072, <gloss
                            target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1732, May 12, from London, <hi
                            rend="italic">supra</hi>. It was Annex H to the Report of the London
                        Conference on Germany, <ref target="#pg_309">p. 309</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">TRI/15 (Final)</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Letter of Advice to Military Governors Regarding German
                        Constitution</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The Governments of the three Occupying Powers recognise that there are
                            several ways in which the decentralised Federal Government provided in
                            TRI/13 (Final)<note n="2" xml:id="d155fn2">
                                <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_305">p.
                                305</ref>.</note> can be obtained, and that it is impossible to
                            determine if the Constitution satisfies the requirements of a
                            decentralised Federal Organisation until it has been examined in its
                            whole context.<lb/>However, the three Governments believe that a
                            desirable governmental structure for Germany should, to the maximum
                            extent possible, provide: <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>For a bicameral legislative system in which one of the houses
                                    must represent the individual states and must have sufficient
                                    power to safeguard the interests of the states;</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>That the executive must only have those powers which are
                                    definitely prescribed by the Constitution and that emergency
                                    powers, if any, of the executive must be so limited as to
                                    require prompt legislative or judicial review;</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                <item>That the powers of the Federal Government shall be limited to
                                    those expressly enumerated in the Constitution and in any case
                                    shall not include education, cultural and religious affairs,
                                    Local Government and Public Health (except, in this last case,
                                    to secure such coordination as is essential to safeguard the
                                    health of the people in the several States); that its powers in
                                    the field of public welfare be limited to those necessary for
                                    the co-ordination of social security measures; that its powers
                                    in the police field be limited to those approved during the
                                    period of the occupation by the occupying powers<note n="*"
                                        xml:id="d155fn3">
                                        <p>The following understanding was reached on this
                                            subject:</p>
                                        <p>The Military Governors must decide in detail what powers
                                            the Federal Government should have as regards
                                            police.</p>
                                        <p>When the German Constituent Assembly presents its
                                            proposals for the Constitution, the Military Governors
                                            will disapprove the grant of any powers regarding police
                                            exceeding those which they have accepted by agreement
                                            among themselves as being necessary. [Footnote in the
                                            source text.]</p>
                                    </note> and thereafter as defined by international
                                    agreement;</item>
                                <pb facs="0275" n="241" xml:id="pg_241"/>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                <item>That the powers of the Federal Government in the field of
                                    public finance shall be limited to the disposal of monies
                                    including the raising of revenues, for purposes for which it is
                                    responsible; that the Federal Government may set rates and
                                    legislate on the general principles of assessment with regard to
                                    other taxes for which uniformity is essential, the collection
                                    and utilisation of such taxes being left to the individual
                                    States; and that it may appropriate funds only for purposes for
                                    which it is responsible under the Constitution;</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                                <item>That the Constitution should provide for an independent
                                    judiciary to review federal legislation, to review the exercise
                                    of federal executive power, to adjudicate conflicts between
                                    Federal and <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> authorities as well as
                                    between <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> authorities and to protect
                                    the civil rights and freedom of the individual.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                                <item>That the powers of the Federal Government to establish federal
                                    agencies for the execution and administration of its
                                    responsibilities should be clearly defined and should be limited
                                    to those fields in which it is clear that state implementation
                                    is impractical.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The Military Governors are charged with the examination of the
                            Constitution in terms of these guiding instructions bearing in mind that
                            the purpose of such examination is to test the provisions of the
                            Constitution as a whole to determine whether they guarantee a federal
                            type of government.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-12">12 May,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
