<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-26T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-26T19:00:00-05:00" n="195" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d195">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Council/5–2748: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_DLW1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-27T01:00:00+01:00">May 27,
                                    1948—1 a. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>2296. <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1761. Informal meeting
                            heads four delegations German talks this afternoon<note n="1" xml:id="d195fn1">Presumably the afternoon of May 26.</note>
                            discussed remaining point at issue in basic political organization paper
                                (TRI/13<note n="2" xml:id="d195fn2">For the final version of the
                                paper under reference, TRI/13 (Final), May 31, see <ref target="#pg_305">p. 305</ref>.</note>). See previous discussion
                            same point <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1742, May 20.<note n="3" xml:id="d195fn3">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_262">p.
                                262</ref>.</note> Discussion was without result as French were
                            unwilling to recede from their former position, being strongly opposed
                            to election of delegates to Constituent Assembly. <persName corresp="#p_CDM1">Couve de Murville</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MR2">Massigli</persName> made clear that they feared
                            procedures adopted for selection of delegates to Constituent Assembly
                            would prejudge manner selecting members of Lower House under
                            constitution and that French Govt was not in favor of elections carried
                            out directly by populations of the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> but
                            favored elections by individual <hi rend="italic">Landtage</hi>. Basis
                            for French views was fear of taking step which would pave way for
                            another <persName>Hitler</persName>. In reply to direct question whether
                            French would vote against approval of constitution which provided for
                            direct election of members of Lower House, <persName>Couve</persName>
                            replied he did not know but that this was possible.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_DLW1">Douglas</persName> pointed out that
                            conditions proposed for German constitution as well as fact Prussia was
                            no longer in position to dominate German states removed dangers feared
                            by French. For example, unlike Weimar Constitution, Upper House would
                            have considerable powers; emergency powers article similar to Article 48
                            (Weimar) would not be permitted; citizenship in <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> as well as in Federal state would be provided for;
                            elections would be carried out on <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> basis
                            under arrangements to be made by individual <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName>
                            <pb facs="0329" n="295" xml:id="pg_295"/> stressed US experience in
                            bizonal economic administration indicated German representatives
                            considered themselves representatives of <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>
                            and were sensitive to states rights; that <hi rend="italic">Landtage</hi> members US Zone were extremely jealous of their
                            rights and opposed to a high degree of centralization. <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> felt French favored weak govt and
                            pointed out strong assembly, jealous of its rights, was probably best
                            guarantee against outsider gaining power and setting up
                            dictatorship.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_CDM1">Couve de Murville</persName> felt that fact
                            Soviets preferred highly centralized state was strong argument in favor
                            of setting up decentralized state. He insisted system proposed by US/UK
                            would lead to centralized state. He was sure that delegates elected to
                            Constituent Assembly would consider themselves as representing German
                            people as whole and would come up with constitution providing for
                            elections to Federal legislature by people as a whole.</p>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> in course of discussions had
                            suggested compromise proposal whereby Article 4 would read “the
                            delegates to this Constituent Assembly will be selected in each of the
                            existing states.” Agreed minute to Article 4 would read approximately as
                            follows: “Military Governors after consultation with the
                            Ministers-President will determine the method of selection, giving full
                            weight to the dominating opinion of the Ministers-President.”</p>
                        <p>In reply to question <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> stated
                            Military Governors would present question to Ministers-President, who
                            would be permitted only about an hour to come to decision since it would
                            be disastrous to permit question to become political issue in Germany by
                            prolonged debate. If Ministers-President did not in time all take clear
                            cut position Military Governors would decide question on basis majority
                            vote.</p>
                        <p>This proposal was not discussed in detail but did not apparently meet
                            with favorable reception. Therefore whole issue still remains
                            unsolved.</p>
                        <p>Sent Dept as 2296; repeated <gloss target="#t_USPolAd1">USPolAd</gloss>
                            Berlin 147 and American Embassy Paris 235.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_DLW1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Douglas</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>