<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d369</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">369</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-01-03T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-01-03T10:00:00-05:00" n="369" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d369">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The final plenary meeting of the London Conference on the Ruhr appears to have
                    been held on the afternoon of December 19. At this meeting, for which no U.S.
                    Delegation minutes were prepared, the conferees approved a Draft Agreement
                    (document RC/21 Final, December 19), and Additional Agreed Minutes suggested by
                    the U.S. Delegation (document RC/23, December 19). Neither RC/21 nor RC/23 <pb
                        facs="0611" n="577" xml:id="pg_577"/> is printed. Copies of document RC/21
                    were carried to Washington personally by <persName corresp="#p_BBH1">Ben
                        Brown</persName> of the U.S. Delegation. Copies of the Draft Communiqué and
                    added agreed minutes were transmitted to Washington by telegram. Copies of these
                    documents were also later transmitted to the Department as enclosures to
                    despatch 53, January 12, 1949, from London, not printed (740.00119 Control
                    (Germany)/1–1249). Following the December 19 plenary meeting, members of the
                    various delegations began to depart from London. Meetings, however, continued
                    among the remaining delegation members until December 24 to settle remaining
                    points of difference concerning the Draft Agreement, the Agreed Minutes, and the
                    Communiqué. These meetings included three six-power meetings (on December 20,
                    21, and 22) and two American-British meetings (on December 22 and 23–24). U.S.
                    Delegation minutes of these meetings are included in <gloss target="#t_CFM1"
                        >CFM</gloss> Files, Lot M–88, Box 126. Following the departure for the
                    United States on December 22 of Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DLW1"
                        >Douglas</persName> and Alternate U.S. Representative <persName
                        corresp="#p_JWG1">Jackson</persName>, the United States was represented in
                    the continuing conversations by Chargé <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Julius
                        Holmes</persName> and First Secretary <persName corresp="#p_TWC1">William
                        Trimble</persName>. During the final negotiations in London, the American
                    representatives and the Department of State maintained close contact in a series
                    of trans-Atlantic telephone conversations. Copies of more than a score of these
                    conversations covering the December 19–24 period are included in <gloss
                        target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Files, Lot M–88, Box 126, File—Misc Documents.
                    These telephone conversations were at times supplemented by exchanges of
                    telegrams. The final texts of the Draft Agreement on the Ruhr and the Communiqué
                    were transmitted to the Department in telegrams 5371, <gloss target="#t_Ruhrto1"
                        >Ruhrto</gloss> 66, and 5371, <gloss target="#t_Ruhrto1">Ruhrto</gloss> 67,
                    December 26, 1 p. m. from London, respectively, neither printed (740.00119
                    Control (Germany)/12–2648). The texts of the Communiqué and Draft Agreement as
                    released to the press on December 28 are printed on the following pages together
                    with the revised text of the Agreed Minutes, which was not made public.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
