<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Frank G. Wisner, Deputy to the Assistant Secretary of State for Occupied Areas</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d433</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">433</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-02-17T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-02-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="433" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d433">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 EW/2–1748</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by <persName corresp="#p_WFG1" type="from">Frank G. Wisner</persName>, Deputy to the Assistant <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss> for Occupied Areas</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-02-17">February 17,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Secretary informed Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFG1">Wisner</persName> that at
                    the Cabinet Meeting of February 16th,<note n="1" xml:id="d433fn1">See also a
                        portion of Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_FJV1">Forrestal’s</persName> account of this Cabinet luncheon in <hi rend="italic">Forrestal Diaries</hi>, p. 379.</note> the Cabinet had
                    accepted without reservation or any <pb facs="0765" n="731" xml:id="pg_731"/>
                    form of qualification the five recommendations<note n="2" xml:id="d433fn2">For
                        the text of the recommendations under reference here, see <ref target="#pg_727">p. 727</ref>.</note> which were made to them. The
                    proposed terms of reference for the working group provided for in the first
                    recommendation were not submitted to or considered by the Cabinet, since the
                    Secretary wished to devote further consideration to these terms of reference.
                    Various members of the Cabinet indicated that they were pleased by the proposal
                    for a working group which would re-examine the plant lists, and one or more
                    stated that they felt that this step would be very well received by the
                    Congress.</p>
                <p>The President stated quite firmly that he did not want any general change made in
                    the German reparation program (presumably referring to the various Congressional
                    and Cabinet recommendations that the entire program be abandoned). He inquired
                    of the Secretary whether the proposals contemplated any “change in the Potsdam
                    Agreement”. The Secretary replied by pointing out that there was a proposal to
                    change some Potsdam provisions relating to reciprocal deliveries in that a
                    strict <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> arrangement was proposed. The
                    President stated that this was regarded by him as a very minor modification and
                    that he was not particularly concerned about it in view of the fact that the
                    Russians have violated so many of the important provisions of the Agreement and
                    the further fact that they have already accused the United States and Great
                    Britain of every conceivable type of violation.</p>
                <p>The Secretary told the Cabinet that the State Department had never seen Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman’s</persName> memorandum of January
                        23<note n="3" xml:id="d433fn3">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_716">p. 716</ref>.</note> and
                    that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LRA1">Lovett</persName> had no recollection
                    whatever of having received this memorandum. Accordingly, the contents of this
                    memorandum had not been available at the time the Secretary wrote his letter to
                    Senator <persName corresp="#p_VA1">Vandenberg</persName>.<note n="4" xml:id="d433fn4">Regarding the Secretary of State’s letter of February 4 to
                        Senator <persName corresp="#p_VA1">Vandenberg</persName>, see the editorial
                        note, <ref target="#pg_717">p. 717</ref>.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FJV1">Forrestal</persName> likewise stated that he had never
                    gotten a copy of the <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> memorandum,
                    although Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> was quite insistent
                    that he had made copies available to the members of the Cabinet.</p>
                <p>The Secretary concluded by approving the proposed terms of reference after making
                    a few changes in the form of the memorandum.<note n="5" xml:id="d433fn5">The
                        memorandum under reference is printed <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WFG1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Frank</hi> G. <hi rend="smallcaps">Wisner</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
