<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Editorial Note</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d492</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">492</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-01-03T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Reparations</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-12-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-01-03T10:00:00-05:00" n="492" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d492">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                </head>
                <p>On October 20 in Paris and on October 22 in London, <persName corresp="#p_HGM1">George Humphrey</persName>, Chairman of the Industrial Advisory Committee
                    of the Economic Cooperation Administration, held a number of meetings with
                    French and British officials on various aspects of the problems of reparations
                    and dismantlement. <persName corresp="#p_HGM1">Humphrey</persName> was
                    accompanied by members of the staff of the Industrial Advisory Committee, and he
                    was joined in London by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DLW1">Douglas</persName>. Participating in these talks for France were <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Hervé Alphand</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RJ2">Jacques Rueff</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_PFD1">François de
                        Panafieu</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_H1">Lord Henderson</persName>,
                    General <persName corresp="#p_RSBH1">Robertson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MRM1">Roger Makins</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_SRB1">Roger Stevens</persName> participated for the United Kingdom. Records of
                    these meetings are included in Department of State file 740.00119
                    EW/10–2048.</p>
                <p>On October 27, the United States, the United Kingdom, and France issued to the
                    press a three-power statement announcing that agreement had been reached among
                    the three governments that there was need for a review of certain aspects of
                    reparations and dismantlement lists. The review, to be carried out by the
                    Industrial Advisory Committee of the Economic Cooperation Administration with
                    the cooperation of the United Kingdom and French Governments, was to determine
                    which plants scheduled for reparation might better serve general <pb facs="0864" n="830" xml:id="pg_830"/> European recovery if retained in Germany. For the
                    text of the tripartite statement, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, November 7, 1948, page 584, or <hi rend="italic">Germany
                        1947–1949</hi>, page 424.</p>
                <p>The statement had been prepared by American, British, and French representatives
                    in London following preliminary discussions in Paris and London between
                    representatives of the Industrial Advisory Committee and French and British
                    officials.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
