<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The United States Political Adviser for Germany
                        (
                        Murphy
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d523</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">523</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-03-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-03-03T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="propaganda" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443" lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="rec577cb840b7a9a75" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="potsdam-agreement">Potsdam Agreement</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="523" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d523">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/3–348: Airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Political Adviser for Germany</hi>
                        (<persName corresp="#p_MRD1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-03">March 3,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>A–182. Reflection on the course of events at the Allied Kommandatura<note n="1" xml:id="d523fn1">The Kommandatura was the chief inter-Allied governmental
                        organ for Berlin. It was composed of the four Allied Commandants for Berlin
                        (Colonel <persName corresp="#p_HCF1">Frank Howley</persName>—United States;
                        Major General <persName corresp="#p_HMGEO1">E. O. Herbert</persName>—United
                        Kingdom; <persName corresp="#p_GBGJ1">Brigadier General Jean
                            Ganeval</persName>—France; Major General <persName corresp="#p_KMGAG1">A. G. Kotikov</persName>—Soviet Union) and their advisers and
                        assistants.</note> during first two months of 1948 seems to lead to the
                    conclusion that Soviet tactics have again changed. Reference to the numerous
                    airgrams from this Mission reporting Kommandatura meetings will show that
                    following the breakdown of the London Conference there was a relatively
                    harmonious period in which the atmosphere was comparatively friendly and
                    agreement could be reached without too much difficulty on matters of second-rate
                    importance. The friendly atmosphere continued through the first three weeks of
                    January but the ability to reach agreement steadily decreased. Beginning roughly
                    with the meeting of the Commandants on January 21 the atmosphere has steadily
                    deteriorated and the Commandants have been brought to a point at which it
                    appears that agreement is impossible on even the most routine questions.</p>
                <p>The Soviet delegation now seizes upon every question on the agenda and every
                    statement by any other delegation no matter how simple, how friendly or how
                    innocent, to launch violent propaganda attacks on the other three delegations.
                    It may be said that the attacks are directed against the U.S., British and
                    French delegations in that order. Recently the French have received their full
                    share of insults. It is impossible to discuss any question objectively or
                    concisely. The last five sessions have lasted for from nine to eleven and a half
                    hours.</p>
                <p>We know that Soviet tactics frequently serve only a temporary aim and they may
                    well be reversed tomorrow. Their present tactics, however, seem designed to
                    irritate, confuse and tire the other three delegations with the possible aim of
                    trapping them into unwise decisions out of sheer exhaustion and impatience, or
                    to goad them into some precipitant reaction upon which the Soviets could seize
                    as a pretext for breaking up the Kommandatura in a manner favorable to their
                    propaganda.</p>
                <p>It is perhaps not without significance that Soviet diatribes return again and
                    again to one of three points. First, they continually charge the Western
                    delegations with violation of multipartite agreements, frequently mentioning
                    specific accords such as the Potsdam Agreement. Second, they continually charge
                    the American and British delegations <pb facs="0913" n="879" xml:id="pg_879"/>
                    with the intention to disrupt quadripartite harmony and the quadripartite
                    administration of Berlin. This was the burden of their charges on March 2 (see
                    my airgram no. 181, March 3<note n="2" xml:id="d523fn2">Not printed; it reported
                        on the 5th Meeting of Allied Commandants for Berlin, March 2 (740.00119
                        Control (Germany)/3–348).</note>). Third, they allege that it is the
                    intention of the other Allies to use Berlin as a means of interfering in the
                    affairs of the Soviet Zone.</p>
                <p>It has been demonstrated in the past that the Soviet Government (like the Nazi
                    Government) charges the other person with those things which it itself intends
                    to do. It is therefore pertinent to ask whether the constant reiteration of the
                    above-mentioned three charges in sessions during the past five weeks presages a
                    Soviet intention to break up the quadripartite administration of Berlin. It must
                    be emphasized that there has been no explicit evidence at any level of such an
                    intention. It may only be suspected as an implicit result of Soviet
                        tactics.<note n="3" xml:id="d523fn3">In a message of March 5 to Lt. Gen.
                            <persName corresp="#p_CLGSJ1">Stephen J. Chamberlin</persName>, Director
                        of Intelligence, Army General Staff (<persName corresp="#p_FJV1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Forrestal Diaries</hi>
                        </persName>, p. 387), General <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName>
                        warned that subtle changes in Soviet attitude suggested the possibility of a
                        sudden outbreak of war in the near future.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
