<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        Soviet Ambassador (
                        Panyushkin
                    )This note was handed to Ambassador
                            Panyushkin by the Secretary of
                        State on the morning of July 6. On the same day, the British Government
                        transmitted an identic note to the Soviet Ambassador in London, and the
                        French Government presented its separate note to the Soviet Ambassador in
                        Paris. For the text of the French note, see Cmd. 7534, pp. 49–50.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d575</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">575</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-07-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-07-06T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="quarantine-blockade" subject="blockade" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919" lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="food" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184" lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="health-care" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005773" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Medical supplies</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="human-rights" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379" lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-07-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-07-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="575" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d575">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/7–648</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Soviet Ambassador</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PAS1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Panyushkin</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d575fn1">This note was handed to Ambassador
                            <persName corresp="#p_PAS1">Panyushkin</persName> by the Secretary of
                        State on the morning of July 6. On the same day, the British Government
                        transmitted an identic note to the Soviet Ambassador in London, and the
                        French Government presented its separate note to the Soviet Ambassador in
                        Paris. For the text of the French note, see Cmd. 7534, pp. 49–50.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-07-06">July 6,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: The United States Government wishes to
                    call to the attention of the Soviet Government the extremely serious
                    international situation which has been brought about by the actions of the
                    Soviet <pb facs="0985" n="951" xml:id="pg_951"/> Government in<note n="2" xml:id="d575fn2">In the draft note agreed upon by <persName corresp="#p_SSW1">Strang</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MR2">Massigli</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_DLW1">Douglas</persName>
                        and reported upon in telegram 2929, July 2, from London, not printed, the
                        remaining portion of this paragraph read as follows: “… instituting a
                        blockade against the sectors in Berlin occupied by the United States, Great
                        Britain and France. The United States Government regards these measures of
                        blockade instituted by the Soviet military authorities in Germany as a clear
                        violation of existing agreements concerning the administration of Berlin by
                        the four occupying powers.” (740.00119 Control (Germany)/7–248)</note>
                    imposing restrictive measures on transport which, amount now to a blockade
                    against the sectors in Berlin occupied by the United States, United Kingdom and
                    France. The United States Government regards these measures of blockade as a
                    clear violation of existing agreements concerning the administration of Berlin
                    by the four occupying powers.</p>
                <p>The rights of the United States as a joint occupying power in Berlin derive from
                    the total defeat and unconditional surrender of Germany. The international
                    agreements undertaken in connection therewith by the Governments of the United
                    States, United Kingdom, France and the Soviet Union defined the zones in Germany
                    and the sectors in Berlin which are occupied by these powers. They established
                    the quadripartite control of Berlin on a basis of friendly cooperation which the
                    Government of the United States earnestly desires to continue to pursue.</p>
                <p>These agreements implied the right of free access to Berlin. This Fight has long
                    been confirmed by usage. It was directly specified in a message sent by
                    President <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> to Premier <persName corresp="#p_SGIV1">Stalin</persName> on June 14, 1945,<note n="3" xml:id="d575fn3">
                        <ref target="frus1945v03#pg_135">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 135</ref>–<ref target="frus1945v03#pg_136">136</ref>.</note> which agreed to the
                    withdrawal of United States forces to the zonal boundaries, provided
                    satisfactory arrangements could be entered Into between the military commanders,
                    which would give access by rail, road and air to United States forces in
                        Berlin.<note n="4" xml:id="d575fn4">In the draft cited in footnote 2 above
                        the text read as follows from this point: “This proposal was accepted by
                        Premier <persName corresp="#p_SGIV1">Stalin</persName> in his reply dated
                        June 16, 1945. In accordance with this understanding, the United States,
                        whose armies had penetrated deep into Saxony and Thuringia, parts of the
                        Soviet zone, withdrew its forces to its own area of occupation in Germany
                        and took up its position in its own sector in Berlin. Thereupon the
                        agreements in regard to the occupation of Germany and Berlin went into
                        effect. The United States would not have so withdrawn its troops from a
                        large area now occupied by the Soviet had there been any doubt whatsoever
                        about the observance of its agreed right of free access to its sector of
                        Berlin. The right of the United States to its position in Berlin thus stems
                        from precisely the same source as the right of the Soviet Union. It is
                        impossible to assert the latter and deny the former.”</note> Premier
                        <persName corresp="#p_SGIV1">Stalin</persName> replied on June 16<note n="5" xml:id="d575fn5">
                        <ref target="frus1945v03#pg_137">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 137</ref>.</note> suggesting a change
                    in date but no other alteration in the plan proposed by the President. Premier
                        <persName corresp="#p_SGIV1">Stalin</persName> then gave assurances that all
                    necessary measures would be taken, in accordance with the plan. Correspondence
                    in a similar sense took place between Premier <persName corresp="#p_SGIV1">Stalin</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CW1">Churchill</persName>.
                    In accordance with this understanding, the United States, whose armies had
                    penetrated deep into Saxony and Thuringia, parts of the Soviet zone, withdrew
                    its forces to its own <pb facs="0986" n="952" xml:id="pg_952"/> area of
                    occupation in Germany and took up its position in its own sector in Berlin.
                    Thereupon the agreements in regard to the occupation of Germany and Berlin went
                    into effect. The United States would not have so withdrawn its troops from a
                    large area now occupied by the Soviet Union had there been any doubt whatsoever
                    about the observance of its agreed right of free access to its sector of Berlin.
                    The right of the United States to its position in Berlin thus stems from
                    precisely the same source as the right of the Soviet Union. It is impossible to
                    assert the latter and deny the former.</p>
                <p>It clearly results from these undertakings that Berlin is not a part of the
                    Soviet zone, but is an international zone of occupation. Commitments entered
                    into in good faith by the zone commanders, and subsequently confirmed by the
                    Allied Control Authority, as well as practices sanctioned by usage, guarantee
                    the United States together with other powers, free access to Berlin for the
                    purpose of fulfilling its responsibilities as an occupying power. The facts are
                    plain. Their meaning is clear. Any other interpretation would offend all the
                    rules of comity and reason.</p>
                <p>In order that there should be no misunderstanding whatsoever on this point, the
                    United States Government categorically asserts that it is in occupation of its
                    sector in Berlin with free access thereto as a matter of established right
                    deriving from the defeat and surrender of Germany and confirmed by formal
                    agreements among the principal Allies. It further declares that it will not be
                    induced by threats, pressures or other actions to abandon these rights. It is
                    hoped that the Soviet Government entertains no doubts whatsoever on this
                    point.</p>
                <p>This Government now shares with the Governments of France and the United Kingdom
                    the responsibility initially undertaken at Soviet request on July 7, 1945, for
                    the physical well-being of 2,400,000 persons in the western sectors of Berlin.
                    Restrictions recently imposed by the Soviet authorities in Berlin have operated
                    to prevent this Government and the Governments of the United Kingdom and of
                    France from fulfilling that responsibility in an adequate manner.</p>
                <p>The responsibility which this Government bears for the physical well-being and
                    the safety of the German population in its sector of Berlin is outstandingly
                    humanitarian in character. This population includes hundreds of thousands of
                    women and children, whose health and safety are dependent on the continued use
                    of adequate facilities for moving food, medical supplies and other items
                    indispensable to the maintenance of human life in the western sectors of Berlin.
                    The most elemental of these human rights which both our Governments are solemnly
                    pledged to protect are thus placed in jeopardy by these restrictions. It is
                    intolerable that any one of the occupying authorities should attempt to impose a
                    blockade upon the people of Berlin.</p>
                <pb facs="0987" n="953" xml:id="pg_953"/>
                <p>The United States Government is therefore obliged to insist that in accordance
                    with existing agreements the arrangements for the movement of freight and
                    passenger traffic between the western zones and Berlin be fully restored. There
                    can be no question of delay in the restoration of these essential services,
                    since the needs of the civilian population in the Berlin area are
                    imperative.</p>
                <p>Holding these urgent views regarding its rights and obligations in the United
                    States sector of Berlin, yet eager always to resolve controversies in the spirit
                    of fair consideration for the viewpoints of all concerned, the Government of the
                    United States declares that duress should not be invoked as a method of
                    attempting to dispose of any disagreements which may exist between the Soviet
                    Government and the Government of the United States in respect of any aspect of
                    the Berlin situation.</p>
                <p>Such disagreements if any should be settled by negotiation or by any of the other
                    peaceful methods provided for in Article 33 of the Charter in keeping with our
                    mutual pledges as copartners in the United Nations. For these reasons the
                    Government of the United States is ready as a first step to participate in
                    negotiations in Berlin among the four Allied Occupying Authorities for the
                    settlement of any question in dispute arising out of the administration of the
                    city of Berlin. It is, however, a prerequisite that the lines of communication
                    and the movement of persons and goods between the United Kingdom, the United
                    States and the French sectors in Berlin and the Western Zones shall have been
                    fully restored.<note n="6" xml:id="d575fn6">
                        <p>In the draft cited in footnote 2 above, the text had four paragraphs
                            instead of this final one. They read: “Such disagreements, if any,
                            should be settled by the peaceful method of negotiation in keeping with
                            our mutual pledges as copartners in the United Nations. It is for these
                            reasons that the Government of the United States submits the following
                            proposal: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Full communication between the United States, United Kingdom
                                    and French sectors of Berlin and the western zones for allied
                                    and German personnel and freight shall be restored. When this
                                    has been done, we shall be ready to negotiate on a four power
                                    basis for the settlement of any question arising out of the
                                    administration of Berlin, particularly the question of currency,
                                    which may be in dispute among the powers.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>These negotiations shall proceed through the Military
                                    Governors in Berlin.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>If, after a reasonable unstated time, there is still a dispute
                                    among the Military Governors any question arising out of the
                                    administration of Berlin, the United States Government would be
                                    prepared to join with the other occupying powers in referring
                                    such matters still in dispute to the appropriate organ of the
                                    United Nations for consideration and decision.”</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">G. C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
