<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-09-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-09-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="664" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d664">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">862.515/9–2543</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Soviet Ambassador</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PAS1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Panyushkin</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d664fn1">The Soviet Government transmitted
                                identic notes to the United Kingdom and French Governments. For the
                                Soviet Government’s translation of this note, see <hi rend="italic">The Soviet Union and the Berlin Question</hi>, pp.
                                54–57.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">No. 177</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics presents his
                            compliments to the Acting Secretary of State of the United States and,
                            upon instructions from the Soviet Government, has the honor to
                            communicate the following: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The Government of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics has
                                    acquainted itself with the note of the Government of the U.S.A.
                                    of September 22, 1948<note n="2" xml:id="d664fn2">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> concerning the
                                    negotiations of the four powers which have taken place in Moscow
                                    and Berlin on the question of <pb facs="1216" n="1182" xml:id="pg_1182"/> introducing the German mark of the Soviet
                                    zone as the sole currency in Berlin and of removing the
                                    restrictions on communication, transport, and trade between
                                    Berlin and the western zones of Germany.</item>
                                <label> </label>
                                <item>In this connection the Soviet Government considers it
                                    necessary to state that the position taken by the Government of
                                    the U.S.A. not only does not facilitate but on the contrary
                                    makes more difficult the reaching of an agreement concerning the
                                    settlement of the situation in Berlin which has arisen as a
                                    result of effecting a separate currency reform and introducing a
                                    special currency in the western zones of Germany and the western
                                    sectors of Berlin, which constituted a measure that was most
                                    far-reaching in execution of the policy of dismemberment of
                                    Germany on the part of the Governments of the U.S.A., Great
                                    Britain, and France.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>In its note the Government of the U.S.A. points out three
                                    questions at issue which were mentioned by the Governments of
                                    the U.S.A., Great Britain, and France in their <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of September 14<note n="3" xml:id="d664fn3">See telegram 1101, September 12, to Moscow,
                                            <ref target="#pg_1152">p. 1152</ref>, and footnote 3
                                        thereto.</note> and the Government of the U.S.S.R. in its
                                        <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of September 18,
                                        1948.<note n="4" xml:id="d664fn4">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1162">p.
                                            1162</ref>.</note>
                                </item>
                                <label> </label>
                                <item>The Government of the United States of America states that a
                                    further continuation of negotiations on the aforesaid questions
                                    on the present basis would be useless and considers that, in
                                    order to create conditions which would permit a continuation of
                                    negotiations, it is necessary to remove the provisional
                                    restrictions on transport between Berlin and the western zones
                                    which were introduced by the Soviet Command to protect the
                                    interests of the German population as well as the economy of the
                                    Soviet occupation zone and of Berlin itself.</item>
                                <label> </label>
                                <item>Such a statement of the Government of the U.S.A. is a direct
                                    contradiction of the agreement reached on August 30 in Moscow
                                    between the four Governments (the directive to the Military
                                        Governors<note n="5" xml:id="d664fn5">See telegram 1776,
                                        August 27, from Moscow, <ref target="#pg_1085">p.
                                        1085</ref>, and footnote 3 thereto.</note>) in which it was
                                    said: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“The Governments of France, the United Kingdom, the
                                            United States, and the U.S.S.R. have decided that,
                                            subject to agreement being reached among the four
                                            military governors in Berlin for their practical
                                            implementation, the following steps shall be taken
                                            simultaneously: <list>
                                                <item>“(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Restrictions on
                                                  communications, transport and commerce between
                                                  Berlin and the western zones, and also on the
                                                  movement of cargoes to and from the Soviet zone of
                                                  Germany, which have recently been imposed, shall
                                                  be lifted;</item>
                                                <item>“(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) The German mark of
                                                  the Soviet zone shall be introduced as the sole
                                                  currency for Berlin, and the Western mark ‘B’
                                                  shall be withdrawn from circulation in
                                                  Berlin.”</item>
                                            </list>
                                        </p>
                                    </quote>
                                </item>
                                <label> </label>
                                <item>From the text of the agreement cited above it is evident that
                                    during the negotiations in Moscow the four governments agreed on
                                    the simultaneous <pb facs="1217" n="1183" xml:id="pg_1183"/>
                                    lifting of restrictions in respect to trade and communications
                                    between Berlin and the western zones and on the introduction of
                                    the German mark of the Soviet zone as the sole currency for
                                    Berlin. The Soviet Government insists on this, because the
                                    situation created by the separate measures of the western powers
                                    means that the three governments do not confine themselves to
                                    their sovereign administration of the western zones of Germany
                                    but wish at the same time to administer also the Soviet zone of
                                    occupation in currency and finance matters by introducing their
                                    own separate currency in Berlin, which is in the center of the
                                    Soviet zone, thus disrupting the economy of the eastern zone of
                                    Germany and, in the final analysis, forcing the U.S.S.R. to
                                    withdraw therefrom.</item>
                                <label> </label>
                                <item>The Soviet Government considers it necessary that the
                                    agreement reached in Moscow be carried out and believes that
                                    further negotiations can be successful only if the other three
                                    governments also adhere to this agreement. If the Government of
                                    the U.S.A. repudiates the agreement reached on August 30, only
                                    one conclusion can be drawn therefrom, namely, that the
                                    Government of the U.S.A. does not wish any agreement between the
                                    U.S.S.R., the U.S.A., Great Britain, and France on the question
                                    of settling the situation in Berlin.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>In as much as the position of the Governments of the U.S.A.,
                                    Great Britain, and France was stated in the note of September 22
                                    concerning the three questions at issue, the Soviet Government
                                    considers it necessary to do likewise: <list>
                                        <label>
                                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>As regards air communication between Berlin and the
                                            western zones, the establishment by the Soviet Command
                                            of control over the transport of commercial cargoes and
                                            passengers is just as necessary as in the case of
                                            railway, water, and highway transport. The air routes
                                            cannot remain without control, since an understanding
                                            has been reached between the four governments to the
                                            effect that the agreement must provide for the
                                            establishment of appropriate control in regarding to
                                            currency circulation in Berlin and trade between Berlin
                                            and the western zones.</item>
                                        <label>
                                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>In the directive to the Military Governors adopted by
                                            the four governments on August 30 the control functions
                                            of the four-power financial commission in regard to the
                                            execution of financial measures connected with the
                                            introduction and circulation of a single currency in
                                            Berlin were explicitly provided for. <lb/> The Soviet
                                            Government considers it necessary that this agreement be
                                            carried out, including the maximum reduction of
                                            occupation costs in Berlin as provided for in that
                                            agreement, and the establishment of a balanced budget in
                                            Berlin, which has not been considered in the Berlin
                                            negotiations to date.</item>
                                        <label>
                                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>The Soviet Government has already expressed its
                                            agreement that trade between Berlin, third countries,
                                            and the western zones of Germany be placed under the
                                            control of the four-power finance commission. The Soviet
                                            Government now declares its willingness to establish
                                            four-power control over the issuance of import and
                                            export licenses also, provided agreement is reached on
                                            all other questions.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <pb facs="1218" n="1184" xml:id="pg_1184"/>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Thus the reaching of agreement on the question of the
                                    situation in Berlin depends now, first of all, on whether the
                                    Governments of Great Britain, the United States of America, and
                                    France aspire to such an agreement.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-09-25">September 25,
                                1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>