<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d681</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">681</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-10-13T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-10-13T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-10-13T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-10-13T16:00:00-05:00" n="681"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d681">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BC/10–1348: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret   us urgent</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_Niact1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                        </gloss>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-10-13T22:00:00+01:00"
                            >October 13, 1948—10 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 312. Eyes Only <persName
                        corresp="#p_LRA1">Lovett</persName> from <persName corresp="#p_JP1"
                        >Jessup</persName>. Following is summary and analysis of developments in
                    Berlin situation here.</p>
                <p>The six members of <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> not directly involved have
                    been meeting almost daily under <persName corresp="#p_BJA1"
                        >Bramuglia’s</persName> chairmanship. McNaughton assures us that they take
                    the line that they are not a committee of the Council but are a group of members
                    seeking information and not attempting mediation. Checks with various members of
                    the six confirm impression Bramgulia has steadfastly acted in concert with the
                    other five after consultation and has not gone off on any tangents of his own.
                    Our <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 280, October 11,<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d681fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1216">p. 1216</ref>.</note>
                    informed you concerning <persName corresp="#p_BJA1">Bramuglia’s</persName>
                    questions to us and the memorandum reply agreed upon by UK, France and US. After
                    receipt and consideration by the six of our memorandum, <persName
                        corresp="#p_BJA1">Bramuglia</persName> saw Vishinsky and put to him two
                    points: first, the simultaneous lifting of Soviet and Western Powers
                    restrictions on transport, communications, etc., and, second, possible meeting
                    of the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Question of simultaneity between lifting the blockade and <gloss target="#t_CFM1"
                        >CFM</gloss> meeting was not clearly expressed in the second point and we do
                    not know just how <persName corresp="#p_BJA1">Bramuglia</persName> presented it.
                    Personally, so far as <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> meeting is concerned,
                    I believe issue of simultaneity is relatively unimportant since we have declared
                    and are prepared to reaffirm willingness for <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>
                    meeting immediately after lifting of blockade. Appropriate formula to this
                    effect could be drafted. Vishinsky indicated reserved position on first point,
                    said second point was satisfactory and then raised currency question. Vishinsky
                    said as personal opinion he thought this might be settled on basis “<persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> proposal”.</p>
                <p>Our information on this point came from Urdaneta who is not sufficiently familiar
                    with the problem to be able to identify which “<persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                        >Molotov</persName> proposal” was referred to. Vishinsky stated he would
                    have to consult his government and would reply to <persName corresp="#p_BJA1"
                        >Bramuglia</persName> not later than today. Understand reply just received
                    and the six will discuss it this evening.</p>
                <p>We will know its content by morning.<note n="2" xml:id="d681fn2">
                        <p>Telegram <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 327, October 14, from
                            Paris, not printed, transmitted the unofficial text of <persName
                                corresp="#p_VAY1">Vyshinsky’s</persName> reply as follows: <quote
                                rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“1. The <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> should remove the
                                    question of Berlin from its agenda. 2. The USSR does not accept
                                    Point One of the <persName corresp="#p_BJA1"
                                        >Bramuglia</persName> questionnaire of October 11, on the
                                    ground that it is contrary to the agreement of the Four Powers
                                    prescribing the simultaneity of the two following measures: (A)
                                    The USSR on the one hand, and the US, UK, and France on the
                                    other, will lift the restrictions placed by the one on
                                    communications, transport and commerce between Berlin and the
                                    Western Zones of Germany, by the others on the transport and
                                    commerce between their zones and the Soviet Zones; (B)
                                    Simultaneous with the lifting of these restrictions the
                                    German-Soviet mark will be established as the sole currency in
                                    circulation in Berlin and the Western mark will be withdrawn
                                    from circulation. 3. The question of Berlin ought to be referred
                                    to the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> and there treated in
                                    conformity with the agreed directive of August 30, 1948, to the
                                    four military commanders. 4. The <gloss target="#t_CFM1"
                                        >CFM</gloss> ought to resolve the problem of Germany as a
                                    whole as well as the situation in Berlin in conformity with the
                                    Potsdam agreement.” (501.BC/10–1448)</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                    </note> Reply will be shown to the Three Western Governments with request for
                    comment and the six <pb facs="1254" n="1220" xml:id="pg_1220"/> will then
                    reconsider the situation. Although not yet settled, possibility is at this stage
                        <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> would meet and <persName corresp="#p_BJA1"
                        >Bramuglia</persName> would report on the activities of the six. Presumably
                    Three Western Governments and possibly other members of six would then comment.
                    Probably no resolution would be introduced at that meeting. Members of the six
                    assure us no resolution will be introduced by any of them without prior
                    consultation with us. Cannot now exclude possibility that nature of Vishinsky
                    and our comments might lead to further “seeking information” by the six. But we
                    have been strongly urging desirability prompt <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                    session to counter Soviet propaganda that <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                    members accept Soviet theory <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> is incompetent.
                    Earliest possible date of next <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> meeting would
                    be Saturday, but deferment until Monday not unlikely.</p>
                <p>Conversations with members of the six indicate they fundamentally support the
                    position of US–UK–France and when time comes will vote with us. I anticipate
                    possibility six may attempt to draft some resolution which while inherently
                    supporting us would avoid direct language condemning Soviet but would seek to
                    advance possibility Soviet acceptance or acquiescence and lead to further <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> consideration.</p>
                <p>I feel strongly we would antagonize some of our supporters if any counter
                    measures against Soviet were taken in Berlin before they are satisfied their
                    informal procedures or <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> action has reached the
                    limits of possible utility. Unless Vishinsky reply is far better than
                    anticipated, I would expect discussions on some <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                        >SC</gloss> resolution in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> next week with
                    possibility vote might not be taken until week after. Sure you appreciate our
                    problem keeping other <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> members in line and
                    laying solid foundation for possible eventual action in <gloss target="#t_GA1"
                        >GA</gloss> while avoiding any suggestion to Russians that we are weakening
                    on our position. [<persName corresp="#p_JP1">Jessup</persName>.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
