<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                            Acting Secretary of State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d690</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">690</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-10-27T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-10-27T11:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="quarantine-blockade" subject="blockade" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919" lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="foreign-currency" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Currency</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="confidence-building-measures" subject="safeguards" lcsh-match="no_match">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="regulation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662" lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-10-27T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-10-27T11:00:00-05:00" n="690" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d690">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">507.BC/10–2748: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-10-27T17:00:00+01:00">October 27, 1948—5 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 503. Eyes Only <persName corresp="#p_LRA1">Lovett</persName> from <persName corresp="#p_JP1">Jessup</persName>. At meeting with Secretary yesterday approval was given
                    to memo relating to future courses of action in Berlin case, summary of which is
                    set forth below.<note n="1" xml:id="d690fn1">The full text of the memorandum was
                        sent as an enclosure to a letter from <persName>Bancroft</persName> to
                            <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Reber</persName>, October 28, not printed
                        (740.00119 Control (Germany)/10–2848).</note> Memo based on assumption that
                    case remains on <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> agenda and any program would
                    be fully coordinated with French and UK.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Reference to <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>. Although we would probably
                        receive overwhelming supporting vote in <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>,
                        recommended that this step not be taken at present stage on ground that it
                        would make actual settlement of case more difficult and mere <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> condemnation would not result in lifting
                        blockade; furthermore present flexibility and potential of <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> or other influential delegates would be
                        lost.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Wait and see period of ten days to three weeks. This course would involve
                        deliberate non-action in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and at same time
                        taking steps in Berlin first of which would be introductions Western mark B
                        as sole currency in Western sectors. Recommended that this step not be taken
                        until after other measures have been tried on the ground that it would
                        indicate a conclusion that there is no likelihood of securing Soviet
                        agreement to any solution of problem and that steps taken in Berlin would be
                        interpreted in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> and elsewhere as deliberate
                        aggravation of the situation.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Attempt to carry out <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> resolution despite
                        Soviet veto. This program could be put into effect by a letter to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> President referring to USSR statement that it
                        wants a settlement and that blockade measures are necessary to protect
                        economy of Soviet Zone. Letter would inform President that Western powers
                        would present rail, road and barge traffic at border Soviet Zone on stated
                        future date, that such traffic would be subject to safeguards against
                        currency abuse, that meeting of Military Governors would be called, that
                        restrictions imposed by <pb facs="1271" n="1237" xml:id="pg_1237"/> Western
                        powers would be lifted and thereafter a <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>
                        meeting held. If traffic were permitted to move through Soviet Zone Military
                        Governors would immediately meet. Recommendation that this procedure not be
                        followed at present stage on ground that no indication that Soviets would
                        acquiesce and that it would exclude the six neutral members of <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> from participating in attempt to find a
                            solution.<note n="2" xml:id="d690fn2">
                            <p>In a memorandum October 26, not printed, <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName> had stated the following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“I do not feel that the proposals designed to put the
                                        Security Council resolution into effect despite USSR veto
                                        are very practicable or desirable. They are based on certain
                                        assumptions, such as that the USSR wants a settlement, which
                                        are by no means proven. It continues to place us in a
                                        position of being something in the nature of begging for a
                                        solution. Also there are serious disadvantages to sending a
                                        train up to the border in the almost certain knowledge that
                                        it would be turned back under humiliating conditions.”
                                            <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName> then
                                        expressed his preference for the course of action outlined
                                        in paragraph 4. (501.BC/10–2648)</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Implementation of arrangements for currency, etc., through an
                        intermediary. This procedure would make use of intermediary actually to
                        frame the kind of regulation for currency in Berlin which under <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> resolution would have been drawn up by
                        Military Governors. Procedure has many variants, one of which was suggested
                        in Department’s 4124 of October 22.<note n="3" xml:id="d690fn3">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1231">p.
                            1231</ref>.</note> Another variant would be for <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> to ask the <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> to have
                        operational arrangements prepared and authorize him to use such experts as
                        he desired. Another variant would be to have President make similar request
                        to <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> in order to avoid formal <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> resolution. Both Soviet and Western Powers
                        might be invited to supply <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> or neutral
                        experts with suggestions as to terms of satisfactory operational
                        arrangements.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Authority of <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> or expert group might be either
                    to prepare operational arrangements which would be submitted to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> for consideration and adoption as recommendation
                    to the parities or for submission to the parities for voluntary agreement.
                    Consideration should be given to time of lifting the blockade in relation to
                    report of <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> or export group.</p>
                <p>Recommendation that immediate steps be started along this line. Wide variation
                    and flexibility of possibilities within general framework of this procedure make
                    it desirable to discuss forthwith with British and French so that we may obtain
                    their general reaction and so that we can work on elaboration of details of the
                    plan.</p>
                <p>Secretary is meeting <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bevin</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> this afternoon, but not probable that
                    program set forth in paragraph 4 above will be discussed.</p>
                <p>Sent Department <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 503; repeated London Eyes
                    Only <persName corresp="#p_DLW1">Douglas</persName> as 1120, Berlin Eyes Only
                        <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> as 659. Department repeat Moscow Eyes
                    Only <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName> as 563. [<persName corresp="#p_JP1">Jessup</persName>.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
