<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom ( (Douglas) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d84</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">84</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-03-03T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-03-03T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recSj13D27GJZ1DiT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Allocations</term>
                    <term ref="recUInGVZ0Y3MeuOS" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recibBhfq1Nhuo5rk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87004890"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec0YIEoMSlyPKAGO" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="general-agreement-on-tariffs-and-trade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001009859"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">GATT</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recxByt4hmF6omKym" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018002867"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Demilitarization</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recZPk3NUzYF5Hlcn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85076821"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Life expectancy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-03T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-03T19:00:00-05:00" n="84"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d84">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Council/3–448: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_DLW1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   <gloss target="#t_Niact1">niact</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-04T00:00:00+00:00"
                            >March 4, 1948—midnight.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>875. <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1612. 1. This is second message on
                    status of Ruhr discussion.<note n="1" xml:id="d84fn1">See telegram 876, <gloss
                            target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 1611, <hi rend="italic"
                        >supra</hi>.</note> It deals with points which as of the close of today’s
                    plenary session were disagreed. Paragraphs 5, 8 and 10 of the report of the
                    working party are involved.</p>
                <p>2. With respect to paragraph 5 the British at today’s plenary session submitted
                    the following new text: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The functions of the international control agency shall, in the light of
                            existing or future international agreements, be as follows: <list>
                                <label>(A).</label>
                                <item>To make allocations of coal, coke and steel from the Ruhr as
                                    between German consumption and export, in order to insure
                                    adequate access to supplies of these products for the free
                                    countries of Europe as well as for Germany; and, subject to the
                                    provisions of paragraph 8 below, to insure the fulfillment of
                                    the terms of such allocations.</item>
                                <label>(B).</label>
                                <item>Subject to the provisions of paragraph 8 below, to prevent the
                                    German Govt or German management from instituting or carrying
                                    out artificial measures or practices in connection with the
                                    movement of these products in international trade.</item>
                                <label>(C)</label>
                                <item>To exercise such controls as are provided for in paragraph 8
                                    below.”</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>With respect to (A) the US proposed to amend the text by striking “make” and
                    inserting “control the making of”, and by inserting after “German consumption
                    and export”, “as may be necessary”. The French insist on the British language
                    with respect to the first amendment; The British will accept either; Benelux
                    prefer the British but will probably accept either. The clause starting “in
                    order to” with or without the US amendment is objectionable to the French and
                    probably to Benelux as representing a curtailment of the powers of the agency.
                    It reflects a position taken strongly by the US and accepted by the UK that the
                    agency shall not have the power to restrict the quantity of these products
                    exported from the Ruhr.</p>
                <p>With respect to (B) the US will propose to strike “in connection with the” and to
                    substitute “which interfere with the normal”. This draft omits the last clause
                    of the original US proposal reading “and <pb facs="0161" n="127" xml:id="pg_127"
                    /> to assure to the governments and nationals of other countries
                    nondiscriminatory access to these products on terms of equality with German
                    nationals or authorities”. We are disposed to accept the deletion. This arises
                    out of a growing concern, which we shall want to express with respect to the
                    paragraph as it now stands, with the unfavorable position in which these
                    restrictions may place German management until nations which trade with Germany
                    have agreed to apply the principles of the <gloss target="#t_ITO1">ITO</gloss>
                    or the <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> to Germany. Except for these US
                    amendments we believe the paragraph is agreed although the UK may propose to
                    strike it on the technical ground that the subject matter is covered in
                    paragraph 8.</p>
                <p>The US has a technical amendment to this paragraph (C) to which the UK has
                    informally agreed which would make it read “to exercise such controls as are
                    assigned to it in accordance with the terms in paragraph 8 below”.</p>
                <p>3. In this afternoon’s meeting the British proposed the following text for
                    paragraph 8: “During the same phase the commanders-in-chief concerned will
                    maintain such control over the Ruhr coal, coke and steel industries as may be
                    necessary to ensure (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) that the export commitments of
                    Germany are carried out, (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) that the mandatory
                    requirements of the occupying powers are met, (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) that
                    the disarmament provisions of present agreements or of a future treaty are not
                    infringed thereby, (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) that the German Government or
                    German management do not institute or carry out artificial measures or practices
                    in connection with the movement in international trade of coal, coke and steel
                    from the Ruhr.</p>
                <p>“The powers as under (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) and (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)
                    shall at the end of the period in which the allied powers exercise supreme
                    authority in Germany be transferred to the international control agency. The
                    powers exercised by the occupying authorities under (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)
                    shall at a time to be decided, be transferred to such authority, or authorities,
                    as may be designated by international agreement to ensure the continued
                    demilitarization and disarmament of Germany.”</p>
                <p>The US will propose a technical amendment to strike in the first sentence
                    “commanders-in-chief” and substitute “the occupying authorities”. The US will
                    also propose to amend (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) by inserting after “Germany”
                    the words “as determined by the International Control Agency”. Both these
                    changes were agreed by the working party this morning and it is believed their
                    omission in the British draft was accidental. The US will make the same
                    proposals with respect to (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) as have been discussed
                    under 5 (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>).</p>
                <p>Except for these comments it is believed that 8 is all agreed up to the last
                    sentence. Herein lies the widest difference of opinion thus far. This language
                    is a US proposal which is not acceptable to the French <pb facs="0162" n="128"
                        xml:id="pg_128"/> or to Benelux who wish the powers under (<hi rend="italic"
                        >c</hi>) to be transferred to the International Control Agency.</p>
                <p>This afternoon the UK proposed as a compromise to strike the last sentence and
                    amend the first sentence to read “the powers as under (<hi rend="italic"
                    >a</hi>), (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) and (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) shall, at
                    the end of the period in which the allied powers exercise supreme authority in
                    Germany, be transferred to the International Control Agency, except insofar as,
                    especially in the case of (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>), other arrangements for
                    achieving these purposes may be laid down in the peace settlement or by other
                    international agreement”. The US proposed that the last sentence be amended to
                    read “The powers exercised by the occupying authorities under (<hi rend="italic"
                        >c</hi>) shall be transferred to such authority as may by the terms of a
                    peace settlement or other international agreement be designated for the purpose,
                    provided that if no such authority is established the powers herein mentioned
                    shall be transferred to the International Control Agency”. Neither proposal was
                    accepted by the French or Benelux representatives but they were not rejected.
                    Their desire to see this power lodged in this agreement in the agency derives
                    from a fear that other arrangements may not be made and from a strong feeling
                    that even if other arrangements are made the life expectancy of the
                    International Control Agency is substantially better than that of any body set
                    up for disarmament purposes for all of Germany.</p>
                <p>4. Today the UK proposed and the US accepted a revised version of the original US
                    draft on paragraph 10 reading as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“This agreement shall not prejudice the conclusion of subsequent
                            arrangements for the better coordination of the Ruhr coal, coke and
                            steel resources with those of other areas. Any such subsequent agreement
                            would not invalidate so far as the Ruhr is concerned the provisions
                            agreed to herein”.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The French and Benelux representatives requested time to consider this proposal.
                    Heretofore they have agreed in principle but objected strongly to the inclusion
                    in this agreement of a provision which suggests that the agency set up by it and
                    considered by them permanent might be superseded.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DLW1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Douglas</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
