<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>153. Letter From Soviet General Secretary Brezhnev to President to President
                    Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d153</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">153</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-11-10T16:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-11-10T16:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recWpOYNUONIWKYCh" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85109354"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Explosion</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec75960867e175c12" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="arab-israeli-dispute">Arab-Israeli conflict</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe">Conference on
                        Security and Cooperation in Europe</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recAynYh8uzxYGQRH" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Strategic arms</term>
                    <term ref="recMqCyaCVCS2rBsP" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Equal security</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recoGY8BsVctNF3tT" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="arab-israeli-dispute" subject="arab-israeli-dispute" lcsh-match="no_match">Arab-Israeli conflict</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons" subject="nuclear-weapons" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127" lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear war</term>
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="alliances" subject="summit-meeting" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87007171" lcsh-match="exact">Summit meetings</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-11-10T16:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-11-10T16:30:00-05:00" n="153"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d153">
                <head>153. Letter From Soviet General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI_1"
                        >Brezhnev</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1"
                        >Nixon</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d153fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Material, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 69, Country Files—Europe—<gloss
                            target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1"
                            >Dobrynin</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>,
                        Vol. 20, October 12–November 21, 1973. No classification marking. A
                        handwritten note at the top of the page reads, “Hand delivered to Gen.
                            <persName corresp="#p_SB_1">Scowcroft</persName> by Yuri Babenko 4:30
                        p.m. 11/10/73.” Babenko was a Third Secretary in the Soviet Embassy.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1973-11-10T16:30:00-05:00">undated</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Mr. President,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I have received and carefully studied your letter of November 3.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d153fn2">
                        <ref target="#d152">Document 152</ref>.</note> As well as you, we want to be
                    sure that on the basis of fundamental agreements and understandings that we have
                    previously achieved we shall not only overcome the present Middle East crisis
                    but we shall also move even further ahead in strengthening relations between our
                    countries. We, on our part, from the very beginning of events in the Middle
                    East, proceeded from this very perspective and correspondingly built our line of
                    actions in accordance with them.</p>
                <p>At the same time it is obvious to us that in order to proceed further along this
                    path it is very important not simply to damp down temporarely the acuteness of
                    the Middle East crisis but to do away with its roots. To do otherwise would mean
                    to act contrary to the lesson that latest events in the Middle East taught
                    us.</p>
                <p>Certainly, to find cardinal solutions for the Middle East is not an easy task. In
                    this case one needs selfcontrol and tact but not less also energy and principled
                    approach. Without this nobody and nothing can gurantee us from a new explosion
                    in the Middle East with possible even greater complications. We now believe in
                    this as firmly as when we warned you before about unexpectedness and dangers
                    lying in wait for us in the Middle East.</p>
                <p>I shall not now touch upon the details of the Middle East problem, we have done
                    this more than once, and soon they will be a subject of negotiations between
                    sides concerned with active participation of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                        >USSR</gloss> and the US, what we have agreed between ourselves. I shall
                    emphasize only one thing: the key element of the Middle East settlement was and
                    still is the question of withdrawal of Israeli troops from all the Arab
                    territories occupied by them in 1967 with simultaneous provision for guaranteed
                    security—with the participation of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                    and the US—of all states of that area, including Israel.</p>
                <p>To make the progress in the Soviet-American relations more stable and less
                    painful it is very important also, in our view, to draw correct <pb facs="0659"
                        n="626" xml:id="pg_626"/> conclusions from the latest developments, both
                    taking place in the Middle East and accompanying them.</p>
                <p>You write, Mr. President, that throughout the difficult days of the Arab-Israeli
                    conflict you have kept carefully in mind the second of the Basic Principles of
                    relations between the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and the US, and you
                    quote in your letter certain parts of that Principle. Neither did and do we
                    forget even for a minute both the quoted by you and other provisions of the
                    Basic Principles, including those related to preventing the development of
                    situations capable of causing a dangerous exacerbation of the relations between
                    the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and the US or situations capable of
                    increasing international tensions. We also remember and strictly follow the
                    Agreement on the Prevention of Nuclear War, including its Article IV, providing
                    for urgent consultations between the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and
                    the US when certain situations emerge.</p>
                <p>Since you yourself touched upon the importance for the sides of living up to the
                    provisions of the above basic documents and in order to make that question
                    completely clear for the future, I should frankly tell you, that some steps
                    taken by the US in this period of time cannot be considered by us as fully
                    corresponding to the letter and spirit of those documents. I have already
                    informed you about my opinion regarding that matter, and I do not think it is
                    necessary now to touch upon the issue again.<note n="3" xml:id="d153fn3">See
                            <ref target="#d149">Document 149</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I believe it extremely important that we and you have common understanding of
                    what has happened and that both sides make equally correct conclusions from
                    that.</p>
                <p>I agree with you that the fundamental documents signed at the two Soviet-American
                    summit meetings have passed the test in the concrete situation and that now it
                    is in real life that their deep substance has already been reconfirmed. The fact
                    was also proved that the peace of the world greatly depends on the actions and
                    policies of our two countries. That once again emphasizes the responsibility
                    resting upon their leadership and necessity of exerting all efforts to remove
                    dangerous hotbeds of conflicts. Everybody will benefit from that and none will
                    lose with the exception of those who would seek profit for themselves from the
                    opposite development of events. And such forces, as you know, do exist.</p>
                <p>It is with satisfaction that we note your reaffirmation of our agreement of
                    bringing the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe to successful
                    conclusion in the near future. I am convinced that through joint efforts of our
                    countries the success of that Conference will <pb facs="0660" n="627"
                        xml:id="pg_627"/> be ensured inspite of the artificial obstacles which are
                    sometime being created on its path.</p>
                <p>We consider it important in this respect to have between us an understanding
                    regarding the necessity to strictly adhere to the principle of noninterference
                    into internal affairs of states. I recall that you had fully agreed with the
                    necessity to adhere to this principle strictly. Secretary of State <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> spoke about it in his recent talks
                    with <persName corresp="#p_GAA_2">A. A. Gromyko</persName> in Washington.<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d153fn4">See <ref target="#d137">Document 137</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>We also believe in the success of the negotiations which started recently in
                    Vienna on the reduction of armed forces and armaments in Central Europe. As we
                    have already told you it would be probably unrealistic to put before us the goal
                    of achieving at once major reductions. It is important, however, to commence the
                    process of reducing armed forces and armaments in that area and, as I have
                    recently stated in public, the Soviet Union would be prepared to such reductions
                    already in 1975. Evidently, we will have additionally to exchange views on this
                    matter in a more specific way. The most important thing here is not to try to
                    change the existing situation to the detriment of the interests of security of
                    any of the parties.</p>
                <p>As for the negotiations on the limitation of strategic arms going on in Geneva,
                    indeed, no special progress has been shown as yet there. Attaching great
                    importance to that question, we are considering all its aspects now. We shall be
                    also prepared to review carefully those concrete thoughts which some time ago
                    Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> promised to send us by the
                    end of October but which we have not yet received. In this question as well, the
                    main thing now as it was in the past is that, while taking any steps on the
                    limitation of strategic arms, the interests of neither side are infringed upon
                    and equal security for them is provided, taking into account as well the unequal
                    strategic position of both sides. Proceeding from that main premise, we would
                    like to find real points in common between our respective positions and to work
                    out a joint good basis for agreement. Of course, we agree that a confidential
                    exchange of views on that question should continue between Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> and Secretary of State <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>.</p>
                <p>We share the satisfaction, expressed by you, Mr. President, concerning the fact
                    that the bilateral relations between our countries continue to develop and that
                    numerous agreements, signed during the past two years, are being in general
                    successfully carried out.</p>
                <p>This cannot be said, however, about one sphere of our relations.</p>
                <p>I have in mind the issues of trade and economic relation which presently happen
                    to be to a large extent in a suspended condition be<pb facs="0661" n="628"
                        xml:id="pg_628"/>cause the question of granting the Soviet Union the
                    most-favored-nation treatment in trade with the US remains unsolved.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d153fn5">A reference to the administration’s attempts to either
                        delete Title IV of the 1973 Trade Bill, which included the <persName
                            corresp="#p_JHM_1">Jackson</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_VCA_1"
                            >Vanik</persName> Amendment, or delay Congressional consideration of the
                        bill. For documentation, see <ref target="frus1969-76v31#d188">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume XXXI,
                            Foreign Economic Policy, 1973–1976, Documents 188</ref>–<ref
                            target="frus1969-76v31#d199">199</ref>.</note> To-day the respective
                    understanding reached at Moscow meeting and confirmed during my visit to the
                    United States still remains unrealized.</p>
                <p>It is, of course, up to the American side to define how and at what moment to
                    better solve this problem. We cannot, however, remain unconcerned when attempts
                    are being made to somehow tie up the problem of granting the most-favored-nation
                    treatment for the Soviet Union with other completely unrelated questions, when
                    the solution of this problem is in essence being conditioned by the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> position at the Middle East
                    negotiations.</p>
                <p>If some people in the United States continue to consider that the Soviet Union
                    allegedly is interested in development of economic ties with the US more that
                    Americans themselves, and therefore, they say, attempts should be made to get
                    from the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> “an additional price” for it at
                    the expense of some principal concessions to the detriment of our social and
                    state system, then I would like once more to stress the following.</p>
                <p>We stand for the development of large scale and long-term trade, economic,
                    scientific and technological ties between our countries. We are convinced that
                    such their development would be mutually beneficial to the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and the US on purely practical grounds as
                    well, and at the same time that would make our political relations more stable.
                    But there is only one possible basis for the development of Soviet-American
                    relations including the economic sphere: full equality of the sides and complete
                    non-interference into each other’s internal affairs.</p>
                <p>Speaking about all this I and my colleagues would like to tell you that we view
                    with understanding the complexities you have to face in undertaking certain
                    steps aimed at the deepening of the cooperation between our countries in
                    accordance with the letter and spirit of the agreements concluded between
                    us.</p>
                <p>Without claiming for ourselves the right to go deeper into the question of the
                    source of these difficulties since one can easily slip into analyzing some
                    aspects of purely internal situation in the US, we would like to emphasize that
                    we do value very much your efforts directed at the implementation of those
                    agreements between us which have not been carried out yet. We have not also
                    passed by your repeated statements to the effect that the commitment taken by
                    the Amer<pb facs="0662" n="629" xml:id="pg_629"/>ican side in the field of
                    strengthening economic ties between the Soviet Union and the US will be
                    fulfilled.</p>
                <p>We would like to think that you and your closest assistants and aides see better
                    what has to be done on the American part to bring this whole matter to the
                    successful end.</p>
                <p>We would like, so to say, to wish you in a personal human way energy and success
                    in overcoming all sorts of complexities, the causes of which are not so easy to
                    understand at a distance.</p>
                <p>For the understandable reasons our wishes of success relate first of all to the
                    field of developing Soviet-American relations, the great significance of which
                    for easing further international tensions in the world has been already properly
                    appreciated by the peoples including peoples of our countries.</p>
                <p>In conclusion, I would like to tell you, Mr. President, once again with full
                    certainty that our determination to proceed further along the path of decisive
                    improvement in the Soviet-American relations has not diminished as a result of
                    the events in the Middle East. And we note with satisfaction that you are also
                    resolved, as your letter says, to persevere on the chosen course.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_BLI_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_BLI_1">L. Brezhnev</persName>
                        <note n="6" xml:id="d153fn6">Printed from a copy that bears <persName
                                corresp="#p_BLI_1">Brezhnev</persName>’s typed signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
