<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-07-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-07-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="9" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d9">
                        <head>9. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>) and the
                            Executive Director of the Council for International Economic Policy
                                (<persName corresp="#p_FP_1">Flanigan</persName>) to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d9fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Institutional Files (H-Files), Box
                                H–235, Policy Papers, <gloss target="#t_NSDM_1">NSDM</gloss> 179.
                                Secret; <gloss target="#t_EXDIS_1">Exdis</gloss>. Sent for action.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SH_3">Sonnenfeldt</persName> forwarded the
                                memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                                under a covering July 15 memorandum with the recommendation that he
                                sign it. According to an attached routing memorandum, it was sent to
                                the President for decision on July 17.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1972-07-15">undated</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_CCC_1">CCC</gloss> Regulations Affecting
                                US-Soviet Grain Sale and Maritime Agreement</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>In accordance with NSAMs 220<note n="2" xml:id="d9fn2">For <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss> 220, “U.S. Government Shipments
                                by Foreign Flag Vessels in Cuban Trade,” see <ref target="frus1961-63v11#d277"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations,</hi> 1961–1963, volume XI, Cuban Missle crisis
                                    and Aftermath, Document 277</ref>.</note> and 340<note n="3" xml:id="d9fn3"><gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss> 340, “U.S.
                                Government Shipments by Foreign Flag Vessels in North Vietnam
                                Trade,” is in the Johnson Library, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> File, National Security Action Memoranda, <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss> 340.</note> of February 5, 1963
                            and January 25, 1966, Commodity Credit Corporation regulations include
                            the provision that any commodity exported under a financing agreement
                            shall not be shipped from the United States on a vessel which has called
                            at a Cuban port or a North Vietnamese port. The Secretaries of State,
                            Commerce and Agriculture have sent you the joint memorandum at Tab
                                A<note n="4" xml:id="d9fn4">Attached but not printed is the undated
                                memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_PPG_1">Peterson</persName>,
                                Butz, and Acting Secretary <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName>.</note> reviewing the dangers this presents
                            to the new $.75 billion US-Soviet grain sale and the related US-Soviet
                            maritime agreement.</p>
                        <p>Our best estimate is that approximately 90% of the Russian ships which
                            could be utilized to carry the grain have been to Cuban or North
                            Vietnamese ports since the effective dates of NSAMs 220 and 340. Thus,
                            Soviet agreement to shipping arrangements consistent with NSAMs 220 and
                            340 is improbable.</p>
                        <p>The specific problem is that of having Soviet tankers call first at Cuban
                            ports to deliver oil, then at US ports to pick up <gloss target="#t_CCC_1">CCC</gloss>-financed grain shipments—an
                            arrangement that would be prohibited by <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss> 220 policy. The underlying problem that thus arises is
                            an indirect relaxation of our shipping sanctions against Cuba.</p>
                        <pb facs="0058" n="25" xml:id="pg_25"/>
                        <p>The 1971 US–<gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> grain deal<note n="5" xml:id="d9fn5">On June 10, 1971, the White House announced the
                                removal of export controls on agricultural products, among other
                                things. The restriction that required that half of all grain shipped
                                to the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> be on American vessels
                                was lifted, and longshoremen, who initially protested loading the
                                grain on non-American ships, eventually consented to loading
                                American grain on Soviet ships. See Seymour M. Hersh, <hi rend="italic">The Price of Power: <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> in the Nixon White House</hi> (New
                                York: Summit Books, 1983), pp. 343–349.</note> provided for carriage
                            in third-flag ships, avoiding this problem. As noted in the joint
                            memorandum, the maritime negotiations to date are premised on a targeted
                            one-third US and one-third Soviet participation in bilateral shipping
                            (the provision for US participation being essential for <gloss target="#t_ILA_1">ILA</gloss>/maritime unions’ willingness to work
                            Soviet ships in US ports).<note n="6" xml:id="d9fn6">On July 9, the <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi> reported with regard to the
                                grain agreement (see <ref target="#d7">Document 7</ref>) that “all
                                but one maritime union—the International Longshoremen’s Association,
                                headed by Thomas W. (Teddy) Gleason, have agreed to a compromise
                                U.S. government proposal under which one-third of the cargo would be
                                hauled in U.S. flag ships, one-third in Soviet ships and one-third
                                in ships of other countries.” (Carroll Kirkpatrick, “Russia to Buy
                                $750 Million in U.S. Grain,” <hi rend="italic">Washington Post,</hi>
                                July 9, 1972, p. A1)</note></p>
                        <p>The carriage of oil to Cuba makes grain shipments to Russia an
                            economically attractive round trip for the Soviet vessels. Unless these
                            ships can be so employed, the entire US-Soviet maritime agreement may be
                            unacceptable to the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>State, Commerce and Agriculture believe that, if the grain sale is not to
                            be jeopardized, there will have to be a change to the policy of applying
                                <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss> 220 to <gloss target="#t_CCC_1">CCC</gloss> commercial export credit sales. The
                            Departments note that any such change would pose substantial foreign
                            policy and domestic political problems:</p>
                        <p>—The availability of major US grain shipments would make Soviet shipping
                            to Cuba more attractive to the Soviets—this would indirectly benefit
                            Cuba.</p>
                        <p>—The US has urged other nations not to trade with Cuba; resistance to
                            this policy has increased significantly; any change in US policy—even on
                            a one-time basis or only in recognition of the realities of Russian bulk
                            ship operations—will undoubtedly be read as a softening of our position
                            and be seized upon by others as justifying a broadening of their ties
                            with Cuba, including resuming or expanding trade. Thus, our difficulties
                            in holding the line on existing policy will be sharply increased by the
                            proposed action.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">—Any such relaxation in the economic blockade of Cuba
                                by the United States and others would raise strong objections among
                                anti-Cuban and anti-Communist elements in the United
                            States.</hi></p>
                        <p>In light of these problems, the State Department recommends that the
                            minimum relaxation necessary in <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss>
                            220 policy be made—i.e., a one-time exception for the US-Soviet grain
                            sale, an exception applying only to Soviet, not third-flag ships.
                            Further, State recommends that <pb facs="0059" n="26" xml:id="pg_26"/>
                            this decision be carefully conveyed to <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> member states before it is made public knowledge.</p>
                        <p>Because commercially financed US exports are prohibited from being
                            shipped on Soviet ships, Commerce and Agriculture believe a broader
                            relaxation exempting <hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_CCC_1">CCC</gloss> commercial</hi> export sales from <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss> 220 policy is preferable. They
                            believe this can be justified because of the short-term credit, largely
                            commercial nature of the program. They note that <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss> 220 does not apply to EX-IM, and
                            they suggest that it should not apply to <gloss target="#t_CCC_1">CCC</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>There are two significantly different interpretations and resultant
                            courses of action, one favored by <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry
                                Kissinger</persName> and the other favored by <persName corresp="#p_FP_1">Peter Flanigan</persName>.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital"><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s Position</p>
                        <p>In my opinion, we have not yet sufficiently tested the Soviets to see if
                            they can be pressured into agreeing to shipping arrangements consistent
                            with our <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss> 220 policy. It is
                            conceivable, considering, for example, the philosophy underlying the
                            Summit Declaration of Principles on unacceptability of unilateral
                            advantage and the very great interest the Soviets have in US grain, that
                            the Soviets might agree to carry this grain in Soviet ships <hi rend="italic">not</hi> engaged in the Cuban trade. Accordingly,
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_PPG_1">Peterson</persName> should be
                            instructed to press the Soviets hard on this issue. If you agree, I will
                            personally review the importance of this approach with <persName corresp="#p_PPG_1">Pete Peterson</persName> before his Moscow
                            trip.</p>
                        <p>If this does not succeed, the foreign policy and domestic risks of
                            changing <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss> 220 policy have to be
                            weighed against the risk of jeopardizing the grain sale to the Soviets.
                            I believe that the grain sale is of sufficient importance to take the
                            risks that may be involved with making a one-time <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss> 220 policy exception solely for
                            purposes of the sale. I agree with State that the one-time exception
                            will pose lesser problems from the foreign policy viewpoint. Most
                            important it would avoid giving the impression that there has been a
                            general relaxation in our policy toward Cuba.</p>
                        <p>I do not concur with the Commerce/Agriculture recommendation that <gloss target="#t_CCC_1">CCC</gloss> export sales be exempted from <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss> 220 policy at this time, because
                            this complex subject has not yet received sufficient study—the overall
                            implications for US policy toward Cuba and North Vietnam have not yet
                            been fully thought through. A prompt interagency study on this issue is
                            required.</p>
                        <p>I recommend that you approve guidance that would:</p>
                        <p>—Instruct the <persName corresp="#p_PPG_1">Peterson</persName> Delegation
                            to make a determined effort to obtain Soviet agreement to shipping
                            arrangements consistent with <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss>
                            220;</p>
                        <pb facs="0060" n="27" xml:id="pg_27"/>
                        <p>—If this effort fails, authorize the Delegation in the maritime
                            negotiations to agree to shipping arrangements solely for purposes of
                            the grain deal based on a one-time exception to <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss> 220 policy; and</p>
                        <p>—At the same time, instruct the US agencies concerned to undertake a
                            detailed review of the overall <gloss target="#t_CCC_1">CCC</gloss>
                            exemption issue for consideration by the <gloss target="#t_SRG_1">SRG</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Accordingly, I recommend that you approve the <gloss target="#t_NSDM_1">NSDM</gloss> at Tab B<note n="7" xml:id="d9fn7">Printed as <ref target="#d11">Document 11</ref>.</note> transmitting the above
                                instructions.<note n="8" xml:id="d9fn8"><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> initialed the Approve option on behalf of
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>.</note></p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital"><persName corresp="#p_FP_1">Flanigan</persName>’s
                            Position</p>
                        <p>In my opinion, <persName corresp="#p_PPG_1">Peterson</persName> will be
                            put in an untenable position if he insists that they, after buying $750
                            million of US grain, are directed after the fact not to use their ships
                            for its transport. Ninety percent of the Soviet fleet has been to Cuba,
                            and the economies of the grain deal demand use of two ships. I do not
                            believe Secretary <persName corresp="#p_PPG_1">Peterson</persName>
                            should be asked to take this unreasonable position.</p>
                        <p>It is agreed that the grain agreement and the shipping agreement are of
                            sufficient importance to warrant taking the foreign policy and political
                            risks involved in changing the <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss>
                            220 policy only in regard to shipping. Although we must expect similar
                            policy changes by other <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> members, we
                            can still maintain our overall policy of economic denial to Cuba.</p>
                        <p>I recognize that this rationale can also be applied to <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss> 340 and North Vietnam, but I view
                            even indirect relaxation of that policy as politically untenable.</p>
                        <p>I believe that a one-time exception is more damaging to our position than
                            waiving the <gloss target="#t_CCC_1">CCC</gloss> prohibition. The
                            immediate risks of criticism and relaxation of economic sanctions by
                            other <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> nations are no greater in
                            exempting all <gloss target="#t_CCC_1">CCC</gloss> commercial export
                            sales than a “one-time” exception, and in addition is more rationally
                            defensible. In addition, it obviates the necessity of subsequent
                            “one-time exceptions” when the next grain deal, or another commercial
                            deal, is consummated, which deals are the purpose of the <persName corresp="#p_PPG_1">Peterson</persName> visit.</p>
                        <p>I do concur that State should carefully convey the decision to <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> member states before it is made public
                            knowledge.</p>
                        <p>I recommend that you approve guidance that would instruct the <persName corresp="#p_PPG_1">Peterson</persName> Delegation to agree to
                            shipping arrangements based on a change in the interpretation of <gloss target="#t_NSAM_1">NSAM</gloss> 220 to the <gloss target="#t_CCC_1">CCC</gloss> regulations.</p>
                        <pb facs="0061" n="28" xml:id="pg_28"/>
                        <p>Accordingly, I recommend that you approve the <gloss target="#t_NSDM_1">NSDM</gloss> at Tab C<note n="9" xml:id="d9fn9">Attached but not
                                printed.</note> transmitting the above instructions.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>