<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>50. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d50</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">50</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-05-29T03:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-05-29T04:45:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recWpOYNUONIWKYCh" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85109354"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Explosion</term>
                    <term ref="reczz1d8j78JEEJZg" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031551"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Continental shelf</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recvKzKYvgKzjgPFZ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-bases"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085159"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military bases</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-05-29T04:45:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-05-29T03:30:00-05:00" n="50"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d50">
                <head>50. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d50fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Records of
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry Kissinger</persName>, 1973–1977, Entry
                        5403, Box 23, Classified External Memoranda of Conversations, May–December
                        1975. Secret;<gloss target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>. The meeting was held
                        in Ambassador Firestone’s residence. <persName corresp="#p_FGR1"
                            >Ford</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                        were in Brussels for a meeting of the North Atlantic Council. An undated
                        White House briefing paper by <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> is in the <persName corresp="#p_FGR1"
                            >Ford</persName> Library, National Security Adviser, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff for Europe, Canada, and Ocean
                        Affairs: Convenience Files, 1974–1977, Box 69, <persName corresp="#p_FGR1"
                            >Ford</persName> Trips File, May–June 1975 European Trip-<gloss
                            target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> 3. An undated Department of State
                        background paper is ibid., Trip Briefing Books and Cables for President
                            <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName>, 1974–76, Box 8,
                        Presidential Trip Files, Briefing Book—<gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                        Background. Another undated Department bilateral briefing paper is ibid.,
                        Briefing Book—<gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Bilaterals 3.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Brussels</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1975-05-29T09:30:00+01:00" to="1975-05-29T10:45:00+01:00"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date">May 29, 1975, 9:30–10:45 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Greek:</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>Prime Minister Caramanlis</item>
                    <item>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_BD6">Bitsios</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TJA2">John Tzounis</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador Molyviatis, Office of the Presidency</item>
                    <item>U.S.:</item>
                    <item>The President</item>
                    <item>Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Lieutenant General <persName corresp="#p_SB3">Scowcroft</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Assistant Secretary for European Affairs <persName corresp="#p_HAA4"
                            >Hartman</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>President: (The first few remarks were made during the picture taking and I did
                    not hear them all.) We want very much to be helpful on the Middle East. I am
                    looking forward to my meeting with Sadat.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: That is very important.</p>
                <p>President: There is a great interest in Greek affairs in the United States and I
                    am very pleased to have this meeting. We have many good citizens who came from
                    Greece. You know they have a large organization called <gloss target="#t_AHEPA1"
                        >AHEPA</gloss>.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: Yes and they are very
                    passionate too.</p>
                <pb facs="0188" n="162" xml:id="pg_162"/>
                <p>President: They are all good American citizens and traditionally they have been
                    leaders in their community.<note n="2" xml:id="d50fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_SB3"
                            >Scowcroft</persName> met with <gloss target="#t_AHEPA1">AHEPA</gloss>
                        leaders on April 25, 12:45–1:25 p.m. (Memorandum of conversation; Ford
                        Library, National Security Adviser, Memoranda of Conversations, Box 11,
                        4/25/75)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Caramanlis: Yes, there is a new generation now and I understand you have as many
                    as two million.</p>
                <p>President: No, I think there are three million. One of them had a great influence
                    on my life when I worked in a restaurant in my hometown.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: I was saying to your Foreign
                    Minister that he is the toughest negotiator.</p>
                <p>President: Mr. Prime Minister, we have been greatly impressed and we are
                    favorably inclined toward you and what you are trying to do in Greece. We think
                    that you have had a major success in your elections and, indeed, I am envious of
                    your majority. It is our strongly held belief and feeling that there should be a
                    democratic development in Greece. This is what Americans wanted and we were very
                    pleased by the return of democracy to Greece. We hope and trust that we will be
                    able to work together both in our bilateral relations and in your region and the
                    world.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: Mr. President, I would like to thank you too for meeting me at this
                    critical time. I would also like to thank you for the trouble and time which you
                    have taken and the offers of help which you have made. In times when we have to
                    face such large problems the help of friends such as the United States is very
                    much valued. We are establishing a democracy but it needs consolidation. To do
                    so we must solve the current problems. The dictatorship left many unpleasant
                    situations but I can assure you that in a year or so Greece will be a healthy
                    democracy. We have solved the problem of the return of parliamentary democracy,
                    we have solved the problem of the Monarchy and this next week we will have a
                    constitution. There will be no abnormality remaining. I must tell you in all
                    frankness that I have been able to do much of this because the people have put
                    their trust in me. Beyond these successes we have also been able to re-establish
                    discipline in the Army but for all of this trust to be justified there must be
                    success in dealing with our many problems. If not, the confidence in me will
                    erode in time. And this is particularly true of the Greek-Turkish problems, the
                    Cyprus situation and the economy. Now, Mr. President, how do you wish to
                    proceed?</p>
                <p>President: We greatly admire all that you have accomplished in restoring
                    democracy to Greece and in restoring order and authority. It <pb facs="0189"
                        n="163" xml:id="pg_163"/> is a tribute to your great leadership. We too
                    recognize that if the moment is not seized when problems can be solved then the
                    solution is impossible. I would like to discuss Cyprus and Greek-Turkish
                    relations and how we can be helpful to you.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: Let me begin by discussing recent history. Before my return to power
                    there was a coup in Cyprus caused by the Greek Junta and they got rid of
                    Makarios. The Turks claimed to act as a guarantor power which they said gave
                    them the right to restore the legitimate regime and protect the Turkish
                    population. The guarantee as written into the London and Zurich Agreements
                    provides that it is for the restoration of legitimacy and the protection of
                    territorial integrity. Legitimacy was restored in three days after the invasion.
                    I came back and took over the government of Greece and <persName
                        corresp="#p_CG3">Clerides</persName> took over in Nicosia. After that there
                    was no reason to remain on Cyprus. The purpose of the guarantee was achieved.
                    But they are still there. Several weeks later they occupied 40 percent of the
                    island. I remember those days very well because your Foreign Minister woke me up
                    at four o’clock in the morning. There was no shred of excuse for the second
                    Turkish move. You don’t just create strategic plans overnight. The military
                    operation must have been planned for some time. The occupation of 40 percent of
                    the island follows very closely a military plan known as Attila. This proves
                    premeditation. Two hundred thousand refugees were created by this move. You can
                    say it is not huge but the total population of the island is only half a
                    million. They also took in the 40 percent the largest area in resources. On
                    August 14 I faced an explosion in my Army and among the population. I went to
                    the General Staff Headquarters and they demanded that I act. There was pressure
                    for a declaration of war. Naturally everyone felt humiliated but I took the
                    unpopular decision to tell the people to be quiet and trust me. I said that we
                    would get help from our friends to find the solution. In that dramatic moment I
                    had three choices: first, go to war; second, withdraw from politics once again
                    or, third, withdraw from the military side of <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss>. I chose the third alternative as the least painful. That is
                    the story of Cyprus. It is very difficult to prove something that is
                    self-evident but the Turks are in the wrong. The Greeks have shown moderation in
                    spite of everything that has happened. We still show moderation. For a long time
                    the Turks have asked for a geographic federal solution. In our view there should
                    have been a return to the London and Zurich Agreements but we have accepted a
                    geographic federation on two conditions: first, that the territory controlled by
                    the Turks be in relation to the percent of their population and, second, that
                    the solution allow for a return of refugees. This would be an honorable and
                    reasonable solution but the Turks continually want to present us with fait
                    accompli. What should we do?</p>
                <p>President: We think we should proceed from the assumption of the facts as they
                    are.</p>
                <pb facs="0190" n="164" xml:id="pg_164"/>
                <p>Caramanlis: Before you comment, let me finish my explanation. Beyond Cyprus we
                    have the problems in the Aegean. We are in favor of the status quo which has
                    existed since 1913. But the Turks are continually creating problems about the
                    continental shelf, about air corridors and, in fact, they want to split the
                    Aegean Sea which would mean that many of our islands would be in a Turkish sea.
                    We have proposed taking the matter to the <gloss target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss>
                    but the Turks, while accepting this in principle, refused in Rome to draw up the
                    documents which would refer the case to the <gloss target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss>.
                    I must tell you that if all of these matters are not solved and they are
                    prolonged they could lead to war and that should not be excluded. In both
                    countries tempers are running very high and it would be a shame if war were to
                    break out under the noses of our Allies. I have done and will do all that I can
                    to avoid war but we need to return to a comprehensive approach which will
                    contribute to averting this danger. Again I cannot and will not indicate how you
                    can help. That is something you must decide for yourselves.</p>
                <p>President: The two most important questions are Cyprus and the Aegean. We would
                    like to contribute to a solution of these problems. We feel certain developments
                    in that area are unfortunate for <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and they
                    have created tremendous problems in the United States. Something must be done.
                    We have a reflection of this in our Congress where aid to Turkey has been cut
                    off. We feel that that action has been harmful to our influence with the Turks
                    and our ability to get concessions from the Turks. We were able to reverse the
                    action in the Senate and it is possible we will be able to change views in the
                    House. It is my feeling that if Congress retains the limitation our influence
                    will be lessened. Therefore, we have held many consultations with Congressmen.
                    We have told them that we need additional time to clear up this festering
                    unhealthy situation in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. We have told them
                    how harmful it is if something is not done and that we are approaching the time
                    when the Turkish authorities may close U.S. military bases which will be harmful
                    in terms of our overall defense. We have said that it is time for Congress to
                    act and the sooner the better. We are encouraged by the talks going on in Vienna
                    between the two communities and we hope that progress will be achieved. But I
                    must say that our leverage is lessened as long as the embargo on Turkish aid
                    remains.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: May I add a word, Mr.
                    President, on the Turkish political situation. This is my assessment of the
                    domestic problem.</p>
                <p>Caglayangil wants a settlement. <persName corresp="#p_DS1">DEMIREL</persName>
                    basically wants a settlement but he is very fearful that <persName
                        corresp="#p_EN1">Erbakan</persName> will break up his coalition if he moves
                    toward a settlement. I have told the President, Mr. Prime Minister, that I am
                    ready to form a government in Turkey because I have talked to all the
                    politicians. I have seen the heads of all the parties and I have told them all
                    that now is the time to settle this matter. The key is <persName
                        corresp="#p_EB1">Ecevit</persName>. If you and he were the Prime Ministers
                    dealing with this problem <pb facs="0191" n="165" xml:id="pg_165"/> I am
                    convinced it will be settled. In opposition, however, <persName corresp="#p_EB1"
                        >Ecevit</persName> will use this issue to try and break up the coalition. I
                    had a long talk with him in Ankara.<note n="3" xml:id="d50fn3">See <ref
                            target="#d226fn3">Document 226 and footnote 3</ref> thereto.</note> I
                    know him well. He used to be a student of mine.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: That’s why we Greeks suspected you were pro Turk.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: <persName corresp="#p_DS1"
                        >DEMIREL</persName> is afraid to lose his majority. If he had your majority
                    he would probably favor a quick settlement but <persName corresp="#p_DS1"
                        >DEMIREL</persName> needs the restoration of American aid so that he can
                    show that he has achieved something. To help him we are prepared to take a
                    public position against what <persName corresp="#p_EB1">Ecevit</persName> is
                    saying in the right circumstances. I have told <persName corresp="#p_EB1"
                        >Ecevit</persName> directly that he should not wish to take responsibility
                    for leaving this problem unsolved and causing a dangerous situation to develop.
                    There are two issues: There is a growing nationalism against the United States
                    and there is an historical antipathy against the Greeks. But let me give you my
                    assessment. Now is the time for a rapid move toward a settlement. We have
                    already convinced the Turks first that they are going to have to give up some
                    territory and, second, that the central government has to have some power. We do
                    not believe that you can get the territory back down to 18 percent even though
                    what you say is just. But there has to be a contraction of what the Turks now
                    hold. We have never explored the question of percentages but it must be
                    considerably less than 40 percent. The trouble is that the Turks now have an
                    alibi to do nothing because of the aid embargo. <persName corresp="#p_DS1"
                        >DEMIREL</persName> is scared of <persName corresp="#p_EB1"
                        >Ecevit</persName>.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: I understand all this but what you seem to be saying is that because
                    of these ridiculous internal problems we, the Greeks, must pay. This is crazy
                    and unreasonable that we should have to pay blackmail. Now let me talk about
                    aid. I know that you have discussed this with the Foreign Minister
                        indirectly.<note n="4" xml:id="d50fn4">On April 16 <persName
                            corresp="#p_SGSJ1">Springsteen</persName> sent a memorandum to Snowcroft
                        reporting on the status of the Greek request for aid, initiated on January 4
                        when <persName corresp="#p_KJB1">Kubisch</persName> met with the Greek
                        Ministers of Economic Coordination, Defense, and Foreign Affairs in Athens.
                        Greece remained primarily interested in grant military assistance, which was
                        problematic owing to its problems with Turkey over Cyprus and the Aegean.
                        (Ford Library, National Security Adviser, Presidential Country Files for
                        Middle East and South Asia, 1974–77, Box 10, Greece 3)</note> Aid can be
                    used in two ways in this situation: first, as a threat…</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: Yes, that would have been the
                    best way.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: Or you can cut off the aid and say that you will resume it when
                    reasonable progress has been made. We tried the first for months and no result
                    was achieved. Now we are trying the second and we still have no result. The
                    Turks are not acting in good faith. They are unreasonable. I have not taken a
                    position. If I were to say something in public <pb facs="0192" n="166"
                        xml:id="pg_166"/> I would have to disapprove restoring aid to fit public
                    opinion in my country. We cannot shout from the housetops that we want aid
                    restored to Turkey. Despite these pressures I have made no public statement.</p>
                <p>President: I understand your position completely but we must have a change in
                    this action. There is little or no chance to make progress in the negotiations
                    while the embargo lasts. Historically, as you know, I have always given full
                    support to close U.S.-Greek ties. I have a personal feeling about the history
                    and future of Greece and I support you. But if we don’t get a solution to this
                    problem it will make all of our tasks more difficult. I have done my utmost to
                    get American Greeks to change their minds. Once the cut-off is lifted then I can
                    judiciously handle the timing and the amount of aid given to Turkey. But the
                    Turks will not move until we have removed the embargo. It will complicate our
                    bases and Western security. I hope negotiations can be seen to be making
                    progress in order to get the Congress to move but I appreciate your public
                    position.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: I understand. I do not wish to become involved in U.S. internal
                    politics. Even if the aid ban is lifted, I do not believe the Turks will be more
                    reasonable. Their internal difficulties will continue. Therefore, the problem
                    will not be any different.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: I agree with you that if aid
                    is resumed it will still be difficult to get a settlement but if it is not, it
                    will be impossible. Also let me emphasize what the President just said to you
                    that if aid is restored the Administration can restrict its flow (<persName
                        corresp="#p_BD6">Bitsios</persName> explains in Greek). Even with aid
                    restored it is going to be very very difficult to get a solution but now the
                    Turks have the alibi and they do not fear pressure. We wish to assure you of our
                    desire to be helpful and we recognize that the only solution is to get the Turks
                    to make solutions.</p>
                <p>President: If the Congressional aid ban is removed, then it will be up to me. I
                    have the flexibility. It will be up to the Executive Branch to decide.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: This fellow <persName
                        corresp="#p_EN1">Erbakan</persName> [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                        declassified</hi>]. He will do something to try and prevent a negotiation.
                    That is why it is very important to neutralize <persName corresp="#p_EB1"
                        >Ecevit</persName>. Without <persName corresp="#p_EB1">Ecevit</persName> no
                    settlement is possible.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: Your conclusion is disappointing. Instead of asking concessions from
                    the Turks you seem to be asking why the Greeks won’t pay.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: The Turks must give up three
                    things: first, territory; second, a federal government with real powers; and,
                    third, some refugee return. There are no concessions from the Greeks on those
                    items.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: I don’t see much light here. In any case, I will see Demirel myself
                    on Saturday. I have a solution soon on the way and if it is not an honorable and
                    just solution, there can be no viable peace on Cyprus. We are just buying future
                    trouble.</p>
                <pb facs="0193" n="167" xml:id="pg_167"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: It is not in our interest to
                    do anything to weaken the Prime Minister.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: Nor do I wish to weaken myself. If the solution is unjust, it is not
                    viable. You should know that from history.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: What should we say to the
                    Turks?</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: It is difficult to say. I told you how I see the situation and
                    perhaps you and the Foreign Minister can discuss this further tomorrow.<note
                        n="5" xml:id="d50fn5">
                        <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> met with <persName corresp="#p_DS1"
                            >DEMIREL</persName> and Caglayangil later the same morning; see <ref
                            target="#d227">Document 227</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>President: We would certainly not advocate an unjust solution but a continuation
                    of this problem is worse. We are in favor of an honorable solution but we would
                    very much appreciate it if you could indicate to us how we can be helpful. A
                    suggestion of what we might say and we would be happy to do it. This is in our
                    mutual Western interest.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: This is a case of the two sides having difficulty and the third party
                    giving a suggestion to the wrong one. The Turks are at fault. Therefore, it is
                    up to the Turks for moral and political reasons to come forward with a proposal.
                    They are the ones that should be pressured. We are ready to defend our interests
                    and we will fight if we have to. This is a question of national pride but I am
                    trying to block it. How long can we go on feeling humiliated? There is great
                    pressure to react. I have tried to be moderate in order to facilitate a
                    solution. Ask the Turks what their intentions are. If there is a war Turkey will
                    be the first victim because they will open the way to the Soviets. We will not
                    fall to the blackmail of Turkey. When people feel humiliated the Army is very
                    pro-Caramanlis although there is beginning to be some criticism. I may be forced
                    to reconsider the policies of my country. The most helpful thing you can do is
                    to say to the Turks what you have already said to us but say it publicly that
                    the United States will not tolerate military action.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: We have already said this
                    privately. If there is any move in the Aegean, there will be total American
                    opposition.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: The Turks moved on to Cyprus as a guarantor. We too are guarantors
                    and I have the right to send troops there. You should say publicly that you will
                    not allow any action that could lead to war. You should say publicly that you
                    will help avoid war. This will make the Turks more reasonable.</p>
                <p>President: We oppose any military operation and we will make a maximum effort to
                    avert a war. We will work to avoid such a situation from arising, but if I’m to
                    be able to put pressure on Turkey then I must get the aid restored. I am
                    confident that if the limitation is removed it will help in the negotiations. We
                    oppose military action in the Aegean.</p>
                <pb facs="0194" n="168" xml:id="pg_168"/>
                <p>That is our position. There is some question as to whether we should say that
                    publicly but the policy is clear and we would oppose military action whether by
                    Turkey or any other party. This is the same position we have taken in the Middle
                    East where we have opposed military action. We believe that a stalemate leads to
                    the temptation to use force.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: What should we do. My experience I have used to give you my advice on
                    what you could do to create hope but you must make the final judgment. If you
                    say something in public it will not provoke a reaction but instead create a
                    better climate. It will urge moderation and it will also state that the United
                    States will not allow any side to take military action.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: I am going to be briefing the
                    press, perhaps we can plant a question and I can respond along the lines the
                    Prime Minister has suggested.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: In order to avoid any misunderstanding let me speak in total and
                    sincere frankness. I do not believe in hiding my thoughts and avoiding
                    substance. What I am recommending is not to protect Greece when I ask you to
                    make this statement. If it comes to a question of protecting Greece I will
                    protect Greece through our own actions. But I am asking for a statement like
                    this only to make the Turks more reasonable.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: If there is a danger of war,
                    we would totally oppose military action.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: This will relieve the Turks of their threats. If the Turks act in any
                    way that is provocative this will help.</p>
                <p>President: I think we can handle this in answering a press question and the
                    Secretary will do this.<note n="6" xml:id="d50fn6">In telegram <gloss
                            target="#t_SECTO1">Secto</gloss> 02047 from Brussels, May 30, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> relayed the text of his press
                        conference of May 29. In his prepared statement, he said about Greek-Turkish
                        tensions: “We believe that while these negotiations are going on, neither
                        side should take any military actions or make any military threat or take
                        any steps that could lead to military action, and we have expressed that
                        conviction to the parties concerned.” (National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy Files,
                        1975)</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: What I would say is that we
                    would strongly oppose military action by either side in this conflict.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: Or any action that could lead to a deterioration.</p>
                <p>President: We can respond in this way. This hopefully will be helpful. We can
                    make this clear just as we did in the Middle East.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: Let me explain our attitude toward <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss>. We were forced to withdraw from the military part of the
                    Alliance. It gave us no pleasure to do so. There was no other way. We can only
                    change this when the reasons for this action have been removed. The causes must
                        <pb facs="0195" n="169" xml:id="pg_169"/> be lifted. If I return to the
                    military part of the Alliance before the problem is solved and we later get into
                    a conflict what will happen to the Alliance then. First we must restore
                    normality. I have explained the problems. I have not told you how they can be
                    settled but we hope that you will do your best to help.</p>
                <p>President: We want Greece back in the Alliance.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: I am for the Alliance. I am the most pro-Western politician in my
                    country.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Secretary</persName>: We’ve always admired your
                    great statesmanship.</p>
                <p>Caramanlis: This has even been detrimental to my political fortunes.</p>
                <p>President: If we can help we will do what we can. We will do all that we can. We
                    want the Cyprus problem solved and we want the Greeks back in <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
