<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-09-21T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-09-21T21:00:00-05:00" n="223" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d223">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00/9–2254: Telegram</note>
                        <head>No. 223<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Consul at Strasbourg (<persName corresp="#p_ANDREWSGD1" type="from">Andrews</persName>) to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d223fn1">Repeated to Paris, London, Brussels, Bonn, and The
                                Hague.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Strasbourg</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-09-22T03:00:00+01:00">September 22, 1954—3
                                    a.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>56. <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendes-France</persName>’s
                            speech before Consultative Assembly<note n="2" xml:id="d223fn2">The
                                second part of the Sixth Ordinary Session of the Consultative
                                Assembly of the Council of Europe met in Strasbourg Sept. 13–24. For
                                a record of these meetings, see <hi rend="italic">Minutes of
                                    Proceedings</hi> (Strasbourg, 1954) and <hi rend="italic">Official Report of Debates</hi> (Strasbourg, 1954).</note> was
                            no success. Assembly, predisposed suspect and mistrust <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendes</persName> as “anti-European”, was
                            visibly not impressed by speech which was generally unclear on all
                            critical points, disjointed, uninspired and uninspiring. None of his
                            remarks called forth any expression of approval and applause at end of
                            his address was spotty and perfunctory. Even Prime Minister’s entourage
                            privately acknowledged that speech had failed secure support for French
                            proposal.</p>
                        <p>Criticism of <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendes</persName> plan
                            voiced in subsequent speeches by <persName corresp="#p_TEITGENPH1">Teitgen</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MOLLETG1">Mollet</persName> underlined weakness French position.
                            “Pro-European” parliamentarians with whom we talked were discouraged.
                            They saw little chance France play any constructive role in immediate
                            future. <persName corresp="#p_GERSTENMAIERE1">Gerstenmaier</persName>,
                            German Christian Democrat, was particularly emphatic in his disapproval
                                <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendes</persName> proposals,
                            stating privately, “This is no basis for us, absolutely not, no
                            basis”.</p>
                        <p>Opinion in assembly naturally divided. <persName corresp="#p_STRUYEP1">Struye</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_FENSJJ1">Fens</persName> told us this morning that proponents European
                            integration disappointed over speech and vice versa for others. However,
                            former said he approved speech on ground it would eventually permit
                            German incorporation in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_FENSJJ1">Fens</persName> believed <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendes-France</persName> would do
                            everything possible prevent any form German rearmament and that his
                            purpose in London<note n="3" xml:id="d223fn3">This is a reference to the
                                Nine-Power and Four-Power Conferences scheduled to meet in London
                                beginning Sept. 28; for documentation concerning the London
                                Conference, see <ref target="frus1952-54v05p2#pg_1294">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, Part 2, pp. 1294</ref> ff.</note>
                            would be advance such unacceptable propositions <pb facs="0452" n="404" xml:id="pg_404"/> that he would be able tell National Assembly he
                            had done his best for France.</p>
                        <p>In press conference following his address, <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendes</persName> in response to various
                            questions repeatedly disclaimed any intention of advocating neutralist
                            position and emphasized necessity for strengthening Atlantic solidarity.
                            He declined, however to discuss German entry into <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> or provide any details of his plan
                            for German rearmament.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_ANDREWSGD1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Andrews</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>