<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 415Memorandum by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Near
                    Eastern, South Asian, and African Affairs (Jernegan) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v06p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d415</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">415</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-06-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-06-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-06-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-06-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="415"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d415">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.41/6–1753</note>
                <head>No. 415<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Near
                        Eastern, South Asian, and African Affairs (<persName
                            corresp="#p_JERNEGANJD1" type="from">Jernegan</persName>) to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d415fn1">A notation on the source text by <persName
                            corresp="#p_OCONNORRL1">O’Connor</persName> indicates that it was seen
                        by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName> on June 19.
                        Copies of this memorandum were also sent to <persName corresp="#p_SMITHWB1"
                            >Smith</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MATTHEWSHF1"
                            >Matthews</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MACARTHURDII1"
                            >MacArthur</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BOWIERR1">Bowie</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_MERCHANTLT1">Merchant</persName>, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_ROBERTSONWS1">Robertson</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-06-17">June 17,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MERCHANTLT1">Merchant</persName>’s Memorandum of
                        June 15 on US–British Relations<note n="2" xml:id="d415fn2">
                            <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>I share Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MERCHANTLT1">Merchant</persName>’s concern over
                    the fissures existing between British and American policy in the Far East and
                    Near East. I likewise agree that the maintenance of the British alliance is
                    vital.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MERCHANTLT1">Merchant</persName> suggests as a solution
                    that we support the British “in the execution of jointly agreed policies in the
                    Middle East” in return for complete British support for our policies in the Far
                    East. I feel sure that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BYROADEHA1">Byroade</persName>
                    would agree with me that this would <pb facs="1041" n="993" xml:id="pg_993"/>
                    not constitute an acceptable solution from our point of view even if the British
                    accepted it.</p>
                <p>For a long time we have been trying to follow policies in the Near East which
                    were “jointly agreed” with the British. The difficulty has been either that, in
                    some instances, we were unable to agree or, more often, that the agreed upon
                    policy proved unsuited to the political climate of the Middle East and therefore
                    accomplished little except to make both the British and ourselves increasingly
                    unpopular. The mere fact of our agreement with the British was bitterly resented
                    by the Middle East governments concerned. Recent policy thinking in the
                    Government therefore has been along the lines of greater rather than less
                    freedom of action for the United States in this field.</p>
                <p>If a bargain of the sort suggested by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MERCHANTLT1"
                        >Merchant</persName> were to mean anything to the British, it would have to
                    mean that the United States committed itself to follow the British lead on all
                    major problems, to an even greater extent than has been the case up to now. I am
                    convinced this would destroy all of our influence in the Arab World and Iran and
                    most of it in South Asia. (We do still possess influence in the area, despite
                    the damage done by our past association with the British.)</p>
                <p>To tie ourselves to the tail of the British kite in the Middle East at the
                    present juncture, in my opinion, would be to abandon all hope of a peaceful
                    alignment of that area with the West. Unless there is a marked change in British
                    policy the result would be either that both the British and ourselves would be
                    driven out completely or that we would have to maintain ourselves in the area by
                    force at heavy material cost and even greater cost in terms of moral standing
                    throughout the non-European world.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
