<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 431President Eisenhower to Prime Minister Churchill</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v06p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d431</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">431</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-03-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-03-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="431"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d431">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWER1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName
                        corresp="#p_EISENHOWER1">Eisenhower</persName> papers, <persName
                        corresp="#p_WHITMANAC1">Whitman</persName> file</note>
                <head>No. 431<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">President <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWER1" type="from"
                            >Eisenhower</persName> to Prime Minister <persName
                            corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1" type="to">Churchill</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-03-19">March 19,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1">Winston</persName>
                    </hi>: I have pondered over your letter.<note n="1" xml:id="d431fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> You are quite right in your estimate of
                    my grave concern at the steady increase in methods of mass destruction. Whether
                    or not the specific possibilities of devastation that you mention are indeed
                    demonstrated capabilities, the prospects are truly appalling. Ways of lessening
                    or, if possible, of eliminating the danger must be found. That has been my
                    principal preoccupation throughout the last year.</p>
                <p>It was after many weeks of thinking and study with political and technical
                    advisers that I finally reached the conclusions which we talked over at Bermuda
                    and which were embodied in my eighth of December address to the United Nations
                    Assembly. As you are well aware, that plan was designed primarily as a means of
                    opening the door of world-wide discussion—with some confidence on both
                    sides—rather than as a substantive foundation of an international plan for the
                    control or elimination of nuclear weapons. But honest, open technical
                    discussions on an internationally supported plan to promote peaceful uses of
                    this new science might lead to something much more comprehensive.</p>
                <p>Since last December, we have been following up this matter as actively as its
                    technical character permits. <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Foster</persName>
                    had two or more <pb facs="1066" n="1018" xml:id="pg_1018"/> talks with <persName
                        corresp="#p_MOLOTOVVM1">Molotov</persName> when they were at Berlin. We have
                    a draft plan which, after consultation with your people and those of two or
                    three other countries, will, I expect, be transmitted to the Soviet Union
                    through diplomatic channels, as agreed, probably next week.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d431fn2">Regarding the U.S. proposals on atomic energy, see <ref
                            target="frus1952-54v02p2#pg_1372">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>,
                            Part 2, p. 1372</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>While there have been some indications that the Soviets might want to confuse the
                    issues with extraneous political matters, on the whole it is encouraging that
                    they so far seem prepared to accept businesslike procedures.</p>
                <p>In its entirety the problem is one of immensity and difficulty, as you so
                    graphically stated. But I repeat that I deem it important to make a beginning in
                    an exchange of views, which, as you suggest, could open up new and more hopeful
                    vistas for the future.</p>
                <p>I doubt whether the project on which we are engaged would, at this moment, be
                    advanced by a meeting of heads of government. In fact, I can see that such a
                    meeting might inject complications. From our side, there is the question of
                    France, which is very delicate at the moment. The Soviets have indicated that,
                    if there were oral conversations, they would want to bring in the Chinese
                    Communists.</p>
                <p>My impression is that matters are in a reasonably good way, but that they require
                    constant concern and vigilance and, I hope, frequent and intimate personal
                    exchanges of views between the two of us.</p>
                <p>With warm regard,<note n="3" xml:id="d431fn3">A draft reply to <persName
                            corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1">Churchill</persName>, dated Mar. 17, which was
                        prepared by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName> and
                        which is the same in substance as this letter, is in Presidential
                        Correspondence, lot 66 D 204, “<persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWER1"
                            >Eisenhower</persName> Correspondence with <persName
                            corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1">Churchill</persName>”.</note>
                </p>
                <p>As ever</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ike</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
