<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 484Agreed Minute on Egypt</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v06p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d484</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">484</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-06-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-06-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="484"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d484">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 60 D 627, CF 339</note>
                <head>No. 484<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Agreed Minute on Egypt</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d484fn1">Attached to the source text was a cover sheet which
                        indicated that it had been approved by <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1"
                            >Dulles</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1">Eden</persName> at
                        their meeting on June 27 (see <ref target="#d478">Document 478</ref>) and
                        that it was circulated within the U.S. Delegation as CEV MEMO–12.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-27">June 27,
                            1954</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The British stated their intention to place their new proposals as discussed in
                    the Washington talks before the Egyptians in the immediate future. The US agreed
                    to follow up the British approach, stressing our support for the British
                    proposals. After the approach has been made, the British plan to make public
                    announcement that they have taken the initiative in resuming discussions, unless
                    it develops in their talks that greater progress can be made on a secret basis.
                    If the British make such an announcement, the US would make a statement
                    welcoming the resumption of negotiations and emphasizing the importance from the
                    US point of view of early agreement.</p>
                <p>If the Suez Base talks start satisfactorily the US would begin negotiating with
                    Egypt the necessary cover agreements required before US assistance can be
                    extended. It is understood that these agreements would not be signed prior to
                    signature of the Heads of Agreement between the British and the Egyptians on the
                    Suez Base. Should protracted delays result due to unforeseen circumstances
                    further consultations might be required regarding the extension of US
                    assistance.</p>
                <p>The US agreed that, while there should be no legal connection between the Suez
                    Base agreement and the US assistance agreements, a way would be found to
                    indicate to the Egyptians that US assistance would be conditioned upon Egyptian
                    fulfillment of the Base Agreement. This should be accomplished in a manner which
                    would not indicate to the Egyptians an advance distrust that they would in fact
                    not live up to the agreement.</p>
                <pb facs="1174" n="1126" xml:id="pg_1126"/>
                <p>The US also agreed to support publicly the principle of freedom of transit
                    through the Suez Canal to be reaffirmed by the British and Egyptians.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
