<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="488" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d488">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 60 D 627, CF
                                    337</note>
                                <head>No. 488<lb/><hi rend="italic">Declaration by President
                                            <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWER1">Eisenhower</persName>
                                        and Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1">Churchill</persName></hi></head>
                                <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-29">June 29,
                                            1954</date>.</dateline></opener>
                                <p>As we terminate our conversations on subjects of mutual and world
                                    interest, we again declare that: <list>
                                        <label>(1)</label>
                                        <item>In intimate comradeship, we will continue our united
                                            efforts to secure world peace based upon the principles
                                            of the Atlantic Charter, which we reaffirm.</item>
                                        <label>(2)</label>
                                        <item>We, together and individually, continue to hold out
                                            the hand of friendship to any and all nations, which by
                                            solemn pledge and confirming deeds show themselves
                                            desirous of participating in a just and fair
                                            peace.</item>
                                        <label>(3)</label>
                                        <item>We uphold the principle of self-government and will
                                            earnestly strive by every peaceful means to secure the
                                            independence of all countries whose peoples desire and
                                            are capable of sustaining an independent existence. We
                                            welcome the processes of development, where still
                                            needed, that lead toward that goal. As regards formerly
                                            sovereign states now in bondage, we will not be a party
                                            to any arrangement or treaty which would confirm or
                                            prolong their unwilling subordination. In the case of
                                            nations now divided against their will, we shall
                                            continue to seek to achieve unity through free elections
                                            supervised by the United Nations to insure they are
                                            conducted fairly.</item>
                                        <label>(4)</label>
                                        <item>We believe that the cause of world peace would be
                                            advanced by general and drastic reduction under
                                            effective safeguards of world armaments of all classes
                                            and kinds. It will be our persevering resolve to promote
                                            conditions in which the prodigious nuclear forces now in
                                            human hands can be used to enrich and not to destroy
                                            mankind.</item>
                                        <label>(5)</label>
                                        <item>We will continue our support of the United Nations and
                                            of existing international organizations that have been
                                            established in the spirit of the Charter for common
                                            protection and security. We urge the establishment and
                                            maintenance of such associations of appropriate nations
                                            as will best, in their respective regions, preserve the
                                            peace and the independence of the peoples living there.
                                            When desired by the peoples of the affected countries we
                                            are ready to render appropriate and feasible assistance
                                            to such associations.</item>
                                        <label>(6)</label>
                                        <item>We shall, with our friends, develop and maintain the
                                            spiritual, economic and military strength necessary to
                                            pursue these purposes effectively. In pursuit of this
                                            purpose we will seek every <pb facs="1179" n="1131" xml:id="pg_1131"/> means of promoting the fuller and
                                            freer interchange among us of goods and services which
                                            will benefit all participants.</item>
                                    </list></p>
                                <closer><signed><list>
                                            <item><persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWER1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Dwight D.
                                                  Eisenhower</hi></persName></item>
                                            <item><persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Winston S.
                                                  Churchill</hi></persName></item>
                                        </list></signed></closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>