<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-07-05T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-07-05T08:00:00-05:00" n="54" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d54">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00/7–552: Telegram</note>
                        <head>No. 54<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                                    (<persName corresp="#p_GIFFORDWS1" type="from">Gifford</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                    State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d54fn1">Repeated to Paris
                                and Bonn.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>priority</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-07-05T14:00:00+01:00">July 5, 1952—2
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>77. Re <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss>s 67<note n="2" xml:id="d54fn2">See <ref target="#d52fn2">footnote 2, Document
                                    52</ref>.</note> and 68,<note n="3" xml:id="d54fn3"><ref target="#d52">Document 52</ref>.</note> July 3.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HOODVS1">Hood</persName> head of Western
                            Organization Dept, <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> has shown
                                <gloss target="#t_Emboff1">EmbOff</gloss> translation Fr memo of
                            June 27 and rough drafts of reply to Fr and covering memo to <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1">Eden</persName> which have been cleared “at
                            working level”.</p>
                        <p>Fr memo briefly indicated that Fr propose to use <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> Plan Assembly to undertake
                            task of creating supra-national political authority and “that any
                            existing or future community should be subordinated to it” meaning,
                            according to <persName corresp="#p_HOODVS1">Hood</persName>, coal and
                            steel and defense communities and such possible future communities as
                            agricultural. <persName corresp="#p_HOODVS1">Hood</persName> indicated,
                            as above implies that Fr do not explicitly contemplate that whole
                            panoply of powers of a central government shall be conferred at one
                            stroke on political authority, but that <persName corresp="#p_MONNETJ1">Monnet</persName> seems to be thinking primarily of taxation.
                                <persName corresp="#p_HOODVS1">Hood</persName> added that control
                            over foreign affairs would necessarily come next. Memo stated that other
                            members Council of Europe to be invited “under conditions to be
                            determined.” <persName corresp="#p_HOODVS1">Hood</persName> added that
                            now <persName corresp="#p_MONNETJ1">Monnet</persName>’s idea is for
                                <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> Plan six to get
                            together without too many others except United States and UK in on
                            study. Memo also mentioned participation in study by ministers of six
                            countries.</p>
                        <p>Draft reply in substance makes three points that: (a) study by <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> Plan Assembly shall be
                            within “framework of Council of Europe”, (b) it shall be “in harmony
                            with <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1">Eden</persName> proposals for Council
                            of Europe,” and (c) to this end Brit urge that six ministers at meeting
                            July 12 accept <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1">Eden</persName> proposals
                            and put them immediately into effect by setting up <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> Plan Assembly “from outset
                            within framework of Council of Europe.”</p>
                        <p>Two page draft covering memo says “<persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> made it clear that it wld be contrary to Fr
                            ideas for six to proceed to set up political authority on their own;”
                            that best means of assuring close UK assoc with evolution of political
                            auth wld be early decision by French and partners to accept <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1">Eden</persName> Council of Europe proposals and
                            give them immediate effect so that from outset Strasbourg Assembly <pb facs="0148" n="100" xml:id="pg_100"/> sitting in restricted session
                            will serve as Assembly of <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> Plan.</p>
                        <p>Memo said <persName corresp="#p_HAYTERWG1">Hayter</persName> considered
                            Fr motives to be strategic, to weld <gloss target="#t_GER1">Ger</gloss>
                            into Western Europe and tactical, to disarm Fr Socialists and <gloss target="#t_RPF1">RPF</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Memo stated main objection to Fr proposals was that they were premature
                            and that it was doubtful to what extent public opinion in six countries
                            was prepared for this major development. In this connection memo did not
                            differentiate between proposals for initiating a study which wld
                            presumably be one of best ways to prepare public opinion for ultimate
                            action and substantive action proposals which study might recommend, but
                            said that any attempt to discourage study bound to be misunderstood in
                            United States and on continent.</p>
                        <p>Only one sentence in memo dealt with effect on Brit interests: “our
                            interest lies in ensuring that the political auth is developed within
                            the framework of an organization in which we play a full and active
                            part.” <persName corresp="#p_HOODVS1">Hood</persName> acknowledged that
                            if political auth created and carried to logical development with Brit
                            assent wld constitute reversal of Brit policy of centuries brought about
                            by new world power situation resulting from last war. He acknowledged
                            acute Brit concern at possibility of development of new power across
                            channel of magnitude which wld overshadow UK. In connection with United
                            States interest in developing continental federation, he commented that
                            it had in effect some of aspects of creating by design what United
                            States had fought two world wars to prevent. In reponse to direct
                            question he expressed opinion without appearance of conviction that UK
                            wld assent to such development. He did not respond to speculative
                            comment that there might well be considerable sentiment for keeping any
                            new arrangements on continent as loose as possible. Though above
                            considerations not mentioned in draft memo to <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1">Eden</persName>, <gloss target="#t_Emboff1">EmbOff</gloss> gained impression they are being carefully and
                            prayerfully weighed.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HOODVS1">Hood</persName> said Fr do not expect Brit
                            reply before end of next week, but <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> hopes to get it out Tuesday or Wednesday and in any
                            event in time for Ministers mtg July 12. He said did not know if Fr had
                            presented their proposals to United States or when they intended to do
                            so.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_GIFFORDWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Gifford</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>