<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-07-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-07-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="60" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d60">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00/7–1152</note>
                        <head>No. 60<lb/><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Finance and Economic
                                Adviser at the Embassy in France (<persName corresp="#p_TOMLINSONWM1" type="from">Tomlinson</persName>) to
                                the Ambassador in France (<persName corresp="#p_DUNNJC1" type="to">Dunn</persName>)</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d60fn1">Transmitted to
                                the Department of State as enclosure 1 to despatch 104 from Paris,
                                July 11.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-07-05">July 5, 1952</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>In a conversation with me before his departure for London to participate
                            in discussions on British policy towards European federation, <persName corresp="#p_HAYTERWG1">Hayter</persName> made following points: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> in talks
                                    with <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1">Eden</persName> last week on
                                    this subject had been quite vague and had left an impression in
                                    London of French Cabinet intentions which differed from the
                                    reports <persName corresp="#p_HAYTERWG1">Hayter</persName> had
                                    received in Paris from the Foreign Office and <persName corresp="#p_MONNETJ1">Monnet</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_HAYTERWG1">Hayter</persName> thought this
                                    confusion was one of the reasons that the British reaction to
                                    the French proposals had initially been rather negative, and he
                                    hoped he could clarify the question during his visit.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item><p><persName corresp="#p_HAYTERWG1">Hayter</persName> said he
                                        was anxious that the British Government give a clear
                                        indication that it supported the idea of the <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> Plan Assembly
                                        taking an immediate initiative in drafting proposals for a
                                        European political community.</p>
                                    <p>I told him that you had discussed the matter briefly with the
                                        Secretary and his party while in London and that their
                                        reaction had been favorable. We were, of course, anxious
                                        that the French proposal be made in a way which would
                                        encourage a quick ratification of the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> Treaty and would not risk
                                        postponement. In particular, we did not wish the
                                        arrangements for participation of the Council of Europe in
                                        this affair to open up new questions of approach or
                                        membership.</p>
                                    <p><persName corresp="#p_HAYTERWG1">Hayter</persName> agreed
                                        that France and the other countries had always asked for
                                        public approval of the <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> Plan and the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> on the basis that a common political
                                        authority would follow. He seemed to support fully the
                                        French Government view that work had to be at least started
                                        on the creation of a political authority before the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> Treaty could be ratified.
                                            <persName corresp="#p_HAYTERWG1">Hayter</persName> also
                                        agreed that the U.S. and the U.K. could not permit
                                        themselves to be pictured as opposing or wishing to delay
                                        the creation of such a political authority. If this
                                        happened, the U.S. or the U.K. might delay the ratification
                                        of the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> or at least be
                                        blamed for any difficulties the countries might have in
                                        obtaining <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>
                                        ratification.</p></item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item><p><persName corresp="#p_HAYTERWG1">Hayter</persName> said
                                        that his Government did not insist on the details of the
                                        so-called <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1">Eden</persName>
                                        proposals. The proposals had been presented <pb facs="0160" n="112" xml:id="pg_112"/> primarily to indicate a
                                        willingness of the U.K. to associate with the development of
                                        political unity on the Continent and that his Government
                                        would be quite willing to work out changes the Continental
                                        countries might wish to propose.</p>
                                    <p>I replied that at first the U.S. Government had been quite
                                        skeptical about the results of the <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1">Eden</persName> proposals but, while
                                        the vagueness of the proposals had created some confusion,
                                        at the same time there had been a very positive gain in
                                        obtaining the support of the French Socialists and others to
                                        close British association with, rather than participation
                                        in, the Continental grouping. In my view, therefore, care
                                        should be taken so that the eventual solution could somehow
                                        be interpreted as consistent with the <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1">Eden</persName> proposals. <persName corresp="#p_HAYTERWG1">Hayter</persName> thought this
                                        could be worked out and commented that there would not have
                                        been a problem if <persName corresp="#p_SPAAKPH1">Spaak</persName> had not insisted on giving the
                                        impression that the <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1">Eden</persName> proposals were in direct conflict with
                                        the <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>
                                        Plan.</p>
                                    <p><persName corresp="#p_HAYTERWG1">Hayter</persName> said that
                                            <persName corresp="#p_MONNETJ1">Monnet</persName> had
                                        pressed even harder than <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> for a new and closer U.S. and U.K.
                                        association with the <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> Plan Grouping. He seemed to be
                                        seeking some positive formula to insure that the U.S. and
                                        U.K. association with the <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> Plan countries would develop along
                                        together with the gradual approach of these countries to a
                                        European Federation. <persName corresp="#p_MONNETJ1">Monnet</persName> was quite insistent that the
                                        framework of the Council of Europe is not now adequate for
                                        this development and that more positive results could be
                                        obtained in the framework of the North Atlantic
                                        Community.</p></item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_HAYTERWG1">Hayter</persName> confirmed
                                    that there was no question of French proposing that <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> Plan Assembly be
                                    made a constituent Assembly. In fact, the French Government
                                    would probably resist going beyond the progressive approach of
                                    having the <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>
                                    Plan Assembly prepare a draft Treaty limiting the initial powers
                                    of the European political authority to those necessary to take
                                    over <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> and the <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> Plan. The really
                                    new element was the idea for European elections for a European
                                    Assembly early in 1953. <persName corresp="#p_HAYTERWG1">Hayter</persName> seemed to accept <persName corresp="#p_MONNETJ1">Monnet</persName>’s views that if a
                                    decision to have these elections could be taken now, many of the
                                    present difficulties, not only with <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> and the <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> Plan, but also in connection with German
                                    and Italian elections next year would be solved.</item>
                            </list></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>