<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-11-17T02:37:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-11-17T02:37:00-05:00" n="108" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d108">
                        <head>108. Telegram From the Embassy in Kuwait to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d108fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                                1970–73, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 23 KUW. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Kuwait</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-11-17T07:37:00+00:00">November 17, 1971,
                                0737Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>1293. Subject: Kuwaiti Internal Security and Defense Programs.</p>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi>. There has been a remarkable shift in
                            the past two years in Kuwaiti attitudes toward the United States. Today
                            we have excellent possibilities of working out mutually beneficial
                            relationships in the security, military and commercial fields which
                            should spin-off beneficially in all directions. All of this could be
                            locked-in in the course of the next few months, although detailed
                            contracts will naturally involve time. Hundreds of millions of dollars
                            in export sales are potentially involved<note n="2" xml:id="d108fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_WJP1">Walsh</persName> made this argument
                                during his August consultation trip to Washington. During this trip,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_WJP1">Walsh</persName> told
                                representatives of the Department of Defense that Iran was not the
                                only answer to problems in the Persian Gulf and that the Arab
                                governments were both willing to act responsibly as the British
                                withdrew and to form closer ties with the United States. The United
                                States, he argued, could not afford to ignore a military market in
                                Kuwait of $100 million. (Memorandum from Lieutenant General Donald
                                V. Bennett, Director, <gloss target="#t_DIA1">DIA</gloss>, to
                                Moorer, August 23; ibid., <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 218,
                                Records of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, Records of Admiral Moorer, Box
                                17, 091 Kuwait)</note> as well as the possibility of making a major
                            contribution to the peace and prosperity of this region. All of this is
                            occurring against the back-drop of the turbulence of the region and the
                            unresolved Arab-Israeli conflict. As the Kuwaitis have quietly
                            contemplated their future in the midst of turbulence, they have decided
                            that their future rests with us. The doors are open.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">End summary.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>2. In the course of the past two years there has been a remarkable
                            reversal of <gloss target="#t_GOK1">GOK</gloss> attitudes toward the
                            United States. Starting from a position of bristling antagonism they
                            have come full circle to a position of intimacy and basic trust. This is
                            particularly true in respect to internal security and defense
                            matters.</p>
                        <p>3. Long and patient discussions with senior Kuwaiti officials have
                            contributed to their high level decision to strengthen their internal
                            security and defense forces in coordination with the United States. This
                            decision now has been formally confirmed by the Supreme Defense
                                Council.<note n="3" xml:id="d108fn3">As reported in telegram 1227
                                from Kuwait, October 24. (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss>
                                59, Central Files 1970–73, DEF 12–5 KUW)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>4. Two years ago Kuwait internal security was a forbidden city to all
                            foreigners, except the British, and it was evident that there was an
                            inner sanctum closed to them. Gradually, however, the Kuwaitis relaxed
                                <pb facs="0378" n="345" xml:id="pg_345"/> in respect to <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> with the first breakthrough being in the
                            field of physical security and narcotics. The superb performance of the
                            Secret Service during the Vice President’s visit was quite helpful.
                            Subsequently the Minister of Interior requested our help in terms of
                            training, equipment and technical assistance in establishing a security
                            command center. This, in turn, led to the successful visit of Major
                            General Abdul-Latif al-Thowaini to the United States. It is my
                            expectation that in the weeks ahead we will complete arrangements with
                            the Kuwaitis which will prove of inestimable value here and elsewhere in
                            the region for years to come. It should cover the entire spectrum of
                            security interests.</p>
                        <p>5. When I arrived in Kuwait I found the Crown Prince, the Minister of
                            Defense and Interior, and other significant Kuwaitis bristling over the
                            fact that Kuwait was not eligible for <gloss target="#t_FMS1">FMS</gloss> treatment. The ultimate removal of this anachronism had
                            a significant effect on their reactions to <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and to me as an Ambassador. It has had broad and
                            favorable ramifications on many issues.</p>
                        <p>6. In the defense field it has opened up a new game with most promising
                            implications for our export sales, our relations with Kuwait, and our
                            possibilities of contributing to peace and cooperation in the Gulf area.
                            The small Kuwaiti military forces have been traditionally equipped by
                            the British, although American trucks and sundry other commercial-type
                            equipment show up in their inventory. Our first major equipment sale
                            consisted of two Lockheed Hercules aircraft (L–100–20).<note n="4" xml:id="d108fn4">See <ref target="#d78">Document 78</ref>.</note>
                            The negotiation was extended, enlightening to both sides, and extremely
                            valuable in terms of our mutual relations. There have been many
                            spin-offs from it. When it was over Shaykh Sa’ad apologized for their
                            indecisiveness. He and Major General <persName corresp="#p_MMS1">Mubarak</persName> explained that it reflected lack of experience
                            with our documentation and negotiating methods, and their bitter
                            experience with the British over the years. No one should misunderstand
                            the bitterness of the Kuwaitis in respect to their past contracts with
                            the British. They are absolutely convinced that they have been
                            consistently cheated—and there is some evidence to support their
                            beliefs.</p>
                        <p>7. Last summer Shaykh Sa’ad told me that the government had decided to
                            strengthen its military forces across the board and wished the United
                            States to help them. This led to a <gloss target="#t_GOK1">GOK</gloss>
                            request to Lockheed to manage their planned air defense system program.
                            Lockheed produced its first rough cut last month and will return in
                            about a week with a more detailed draft.</p>
                        <p>8. Meanwhile in an absolutely astounding reversal of traditional Kuwaiti
                            customs, Major General <persName corresp="#p_MMS1">Mubarak</persName>
                            has raised with me the possibility of seconding an American military
                            officer directly to him as a <pb facs="0379" n="346" xml:id="pg_346"/>
                            technical adviser and the Minister of Defense has sent me a letter
                            requesting that “the authorities concerned in the Department of Defense
                            in Washington be contacted to send a team, expert in air defense matters
                            to prepare the necessary studies and research to set up an air defense
                            system for Kuwait.” While eschewing a negative response I have suggested
                            that Lockheed is quite capable of preparing the basic air defense study.
                            We now have, however, a direct invitation for the introduction of
                            American military advisers in Kuwait. The potential advantages and
                            disadvantages should be carefully studied in Washington.</p>
                        <p>9. Lockheed is proceeding on the basis of a number of assumptions given
                            to them by the Kuwaitis and variously influenced by me, namely, 1) in
                            the next ten years the primary potential enemy is Iraq; 2) an objective
                            is military/political collaboration with Saudi Arabia, Bahrain, the
                            Federation, and hopefully, Iran; 3) there must not be a confrontation
                            with Iran; 4) weaponry in region should be compatible. This essentially
                            means Lockheed, Northrop, Raytheon, and Bell in Saudi Arabia, Kuwait and
                            Iran; 5) Lockheed has been told by Major General Mubarak to leave the
                            Lightnings out of its calculations and has been asked to act as the
                                <gloss target="#t_GOK1">GOK</gloss>’s agent in disposing of all air
                            equipment currently held by the Kuwaiti Air Force except the two
                            Hercules.</p>
                        <p>10. The throttles are down and the companies are swarming in. Lockheed’s
                            President was here in late October and we believe we have set the stage
                            for the sale of three Jet Stars, and I suspect two more Hercules. They
                            will be back in about one week with the second stage of their air
                            defense study and with a firm Jet Star proposal, embodying Kuwaiti
                            requests for technical modifications of the inner configuration of the
                            plane which appear reasonable.</p>
                        <p>11. About ten days ago Northrop made a first class opening sales pitch to
                            which the Kuwaitis responded by requesting thirty planes (6 trainers and
                            24 FSEs). Northrop will return about Nov 27 with a technical team. If
                            this contract can be worked out, it will significantly help the Northrop
                            production line.</p>
                        <p>12. In response to Shaykh Sa’ad’s request to me, a Bell Helicopter
                            representative is expected here soon. Sa’ad tells me flatly they wish to
                            buy Bell helicopters and I suspect the opening number is sixteen.</p>
                        <p>13. Raytheon was also here last week with an attractive <gloss target="#t_GCA1">GCA</gloss> proposal in response to Sa’ad’s
                            approach to me and my subsequent visit to Andover. Down the road a bit,
                            and dependent upon the Lockheed air defense study, a request for a Hawk
                            briefing team is possible.</p>
                        <p>14. The proposal by Fitzgeralds Laboratories for a small navy is also
                            under study but the Kuwaitis wish to delay this until January while they
                            focus on air defense. They simply do not have the skilled manpower to do
                            everything in a tight span.</p>
                        <pb facs="0380" n="347" xml:id="pg_347"/>
                        <p>15. On the army side, I have persuaded Sa’ad to put the possibility of
                                <gloss target="#t_TOW1">TOW</gloss> missiles on the shelf and to
                            concentrate in the interim on 106 recoilless rifles. In a practical
                            sense, they have no anti-tank equipment today.</p>
                        <p>16. Manifestly there are big export possibilities in this picture with
                            many potential commercial spin-offs. To cite but several, we would not
                            today be on a verge of Jet Star sales if the need had not been made
                            apparent to Sa’ad and others over a long time and if Lockheed had not
                            done such a good sales job on the Hercules. Lockheed, in turn, clearly
                            sees the sales possibilities for further Hercules and the 1011, although
                                <persName>Douglas</persName> is a competitor. Again, the Lockheed
                            people have done quite a job in demonstrating the need for <gloss target="#t_GCA1">GCA</gloss> equipment. This and our chipping away
                            is pushing the Kuwaitis into belatedly getting at the task of
                            modernizing their airfield. I have now been informally asked if we could
                            make available an <gloss target="#t_FAA1">FAA</gloss> adviser to the
                            Ministry of Public Works. In conjunction with them we are trying to
                            develop the technical justification. If this can be worked out it would
                            enhance our chances to get the construction and management contract for
                            the field. Northrop, among others, is warmly interested in competing for
                            this lucrative contract. It is clear to me that we have a splendid
                            opportunity to work out with the Kuwaitis a complete association in the
                            civil and military aviation field. This would enhance our sales position
                            in the entire region and could, again, contribute to fruitful
                            relationship between the people of the region.</p>
                        <p>17. All of this also carries over into intellectual circles. The Kuwaitis
                            now invite us into their university and we are trying to work out
                            relationships between Kuwait University and American universities
                            involving American professors here. One slide-off possibility is a
                            Smithsonian scientific chair and a Smithsonian/Kuwaiti/others
                            oceanography study of the Gulf. The potential benefits should be
                            manifest. Our STAG lecturers are now enthusiastically received. Two
                            years ago they could not get a visa.</p>
                        <p>18. If what I have outlined can be worked out, it would involve several
                            hundred millions of dollars in export sales and great possibilities of
                            mutual benefit for <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and the people of
                            the region. Furthermore, it would undoubtedly contribute to a lucrative
                            spin-off in terms of non-military equipment. The Kuwaitis have been so
                            burned, or at least have felt deeply so, by the British, French and
                            Commies in past deals that they are absolutely set to go American.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WJP1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Walsh</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>