<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>151. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d151</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">151</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-05-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recfABRQvTqVuIjoA" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="rec75960867e175c12" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="arab-israeli-dispute">Arab-Israeli conflict</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="recP1TxBSuFrpDZ2S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Interim agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-05-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="151"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d151">
                <head>151. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d151fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                        Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> SAUD–<gloss
                            target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis1"
                            >Nodis</gloss>. The meeting took place in the Oval Office. All brackets
                        are in the original. King <persName corresp="#p_FAAAS1">Faisal</persName>
                        was in Washington for an official visit May 27–30. <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> sent the President briefing
                        papers on May 26 for his meeting with <persName corresp="#p_FAAAS1"
                            >Faisal</persName>. (Ibid, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 937,
                        VIP Visits, Saudi Arabia King <persName corresp="#p_FAAAS1"
                            >Faisal</persName> Visit, May 1971) The President and King <persName
                            corresp="#p_FAAAS1">Faisal</persName> met over lunch. (Memorandum of
                        conversation, May 27; ibid.) <persName corresp="#p_ETLJ1">Eliot</persName>
                        handed a copy of the memorandum of conversation to <persName
                            corresp="#p_FAAAS1">Faisal</persName> before his departure. (Memorandum
                        from <persName corresp="#p_DJW1">Davis</persName> to <persName
                            corresp="#p_ETLJ1">Eliot</persName>, May 29; ibid., <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> SAUD–<gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >US</gloss>)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1971-05-27">May 27,
                            1971</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>King <persName corresp="#p_FAAAS1">Faisal</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Camille Nowfel, Interpreter</item>
                    <item>Isa Sabbaugh, Interpreter</item>
                </list>
                <p>[Note: The following record represents the gist of each party’s remarks from
                    interpreter’s notes, not a verbatim transcript.]</p>
                <p>President: We’re interested in seeing to it that the relations between our two
                    countries continue to be as friendly as they have been and to grow stronger and
                    closer in the future. I would be interested in Your Majesty’s views on matters
                    relating, not only to the Middle East, but to other areas of the world. We wish
                    to listen to Your Majesty’s opinions and wise counsel.</p>
                <pb facs="0514" n="481" xml:id="pg_481"/>
                <p>King: I am grateful for Your Excellency’s reference to the good relations between
                    our two countries and for your desire that these relations be strengthened in
                    the days ahead. We share this hope with you not only because it is in our mutual
                    interest that the bond of friendship between us be strengthened, but also
                    because that would be in the interest of other countries and peoples. We do
                    believe, however, that further strengthening our relations is of primary
                    importance to us.</p>
                <p>President: Does His Majesty wish to discuss any matters pertaining to our
                    bilateral relations, or does he feel that such matters can be taken up at other
                    levels of our governments, such as the Department of Defense or the State
                    Department?</p>
                <p>King: I would like to say that the relations and the cooperation between us are
                    most gratifying. Of course, there are certain matters with respect to which we
                    would hope to have <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> assistance, but I would not
                    want us to impose on you, Mr. President.</p>
                <p>We are accused in the area of being the agents and lackeys of the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. In fact, we are accused of even actually
                    conspiring with the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> against the other
                    countries of the area. This kind of accusation, however, is really inspired by
                    both Communism and Zionism, which we consider as twins. I mentioned to Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> during our meeting in Saudi
                        Arabia<note n="2" xml:id="d151fn2">See <ref target="#d149">Document
                            149</ref>.</note> that I believe that Communism is the child, the
                    offspring of Zionism. Zionism is in collusion with Communism for the destruction
                    of the world. I would like to repeat what I said to Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> in Saudi Arabia—that we are in fact
                    worried about what Zionism is seeking to bring about in the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. It is trying to shatter the high principles and
                    values held so dearly in the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. God forbid that
                    such attempts be successful, but they may be unless we heed the warning. All
                    these things we read and hear about—disturbances among labor, student
                    demonstrations, civil unrest, anti-war marches, etc.—are the result of clever
                    calculation on the part of Zionism and Communism in order to bring about a
                    social and political upheaval in the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and to
                    weaken the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> in its struggle against
                    Communism.</p>
                <p>By seeking to bring the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> to throw in its lot
                    with Israel, Zionism hopes to bring about an irreparable estrangement between
                    the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and the Arab world. Of course, we in Saudi
                    Arabia would not permit such an attempt to affect our relationship with the
                        <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. Even if greater and more serious
                    accusations are leveled against us, we will not allow that or anything else to
                    influence our relations with the United States.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately, world Zionism is in alliance with Communism, and it has sought to
                    portray the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> as the Arabs’ arch enemy. By
                    insisting and publicizing the notion that Israel is the only ally the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss> has in the area <pb facs="0515" n="482"
                        xml:id="pg_482"/> and that therefore the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                    is helping Israel to defeat the Arabs, Zionism is only helping Communism achieve
                    its objectives in the Middle East.</p>
                <p>What I have said to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> and
                    am repeating now— namely, that Israel should disappear as a political entity, as
                    a name— does not mean that we are advocating the destruction of the Jews. We’re
                    talking only about the Zionist state.</p>
                <p>From what we read and hear, we get the impression that much of the turmoil in the
                        <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> (civil disturbances and anti-war
                    demonstrations) is the result of Zionist activity in the <gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >US</gloss>, and this extends to the government, to labor, and to business.
                    We appreciate the difficulties you face, Mr. President, in having to cope with
                    these pressures and influences.</p>
                <p>As far as the Palestinian question is concerned, our ultimate aim is that there
                    be established the State of Palestine, which is neither Arab/Moslem nor Jewish
                    nor anything else, but a state where the Palestinians will be able to live on
                    equal footing with everybody else, where there will be no discrimination between
                    Muslim, Christian or Jew. Such a state would make it possible for the
                    Palestinians who are strewn all over to be brought back together. The
                    Palestinians, both Muslims and Christians, could coexist with the Jews within
                    such a state.</p>
                <p>In response to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>’ inquiry
                    as to whether or not I thought that Communism was deeply entrenched in the
                        <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>, I replied— and would like to repeat
                    here—that we believe that the resolution of the Arab-Israeli problem in a just
                    and right way would be the most effective and surest step toward the removal of
                    Communist presence in the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>. I should like to
                    emphasize, Mr. President, that now is precisely the time to render help and
                    support to the Egyptian leadership.</p>
                <p>President: Does His Majesty believe President Sadat will continue in power?</p>
                <p>King: This would depend on what develops as far as the Arab-Israeli conflict is
                    concerned. If Sadat is given the needed assistance and support at this juncture
                    in such a way as to expedite the settlement of the problem, then he would have
                    the necessary strength to stand up against any counter-revolution and to stem
                    the tide of any movement that might rise for his overthrow. Otherwise he will be
                    vulnerable. The army is on his side. He should be given the support he needs to
                    ward off any threat that may be directed against him.</p>
                <p>President: Is it His Majesty’s opinion that the same thing is true of King
                        <persName corresp="#p_HIT1">Hussein</persName>?</p>
                <p>King: Precisely so. Communism is striving to bring down King <persName
                        corresp="#p_HIT1">Hussein</persName>.</p>
                <p>President: Let me talk very candidly about our policy. I am sure His Majesty is
                    aware of the fact that this is a very emotional issue. Before Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> took his trip and throughout
                    my administration, <pb facs="0516" n="483" xml:id="pg_483"/> I have insisted
                    that our decisions in this respect should not be politically motivated. I have
                    told the members of my administration that our purpose should be the
                    establishment of good relations with all the countries of the Middle East. We
                    shall continue to stand by our commitment—that Israel has the right to exist and
                    have secure borders. But we in this office—as I have told all my advisers—we
                    shall follow a policy that is fair to all concerned and not tilted in a
                    direction in favor of one country. This is difficult, but I believe His Majesty
                    should know that we have an administration which is fair and even-handed and
                    interested in reaching a settlement as soon as possible. I supported Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>’ plan and have directed
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> to seek a settlement
                    quickly. We want to normalize our relations with the <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                        >UAR</gloss>, with Sudan, and with other countries in the area. Also we want
                    His Majesty to know that we believe it is important that he is pursuing a policy
                    which aims at preventing the radical elements from having their way in the Gulf
                    area. Also we support the Shah’s effort in this respect. We realize that both
                    China and the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> are trying to infiltrate
                    this area. We want you to know that we support your efforts also. Which of the
                    two influences does His Majesty consider the more dangerous in the area—the
                    Chinese or the Russian?</p>
                <p>King: The source is one and the same. Communism is Communism, irrespective of the
                    means it uses. It is unfortunate that such countries as Turkey, Iran, Kuwait,
                    the Philippines, Greece, Italy, and others, which were once very closely allied
                    with the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>’ policy, are now establishing
                    relations with mainland China. I should be candid enough to say in this
                    connection that there are those who say that this is being done at the behest of
                    the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. There is an increasing advocacy for the
                    establishment of relations with Communist China. Lebanon, South Arabia and
                    others are now leaning in this direction. It seems that the Chinese are
                    concentrating their efforts now on South Arabia so as to make it a jumping board
                    for increased activity in other parts of the area. We are trying, and we need
                    your help, to stem this tide and eradicate this unwanted influence. We have
                    helped the Yemen Arab Republic to combat Communist influence. I would urge the
                        <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> to extend help in this respect—to lend
                    your helping hand to the Yemen Arab Republic, even in the absence of diplomatic
                    relations with that country.</p>
                <p>As to the domestic factors with which you have to cope in the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss>, I do appreciate your problem, Mr. President, and
                    realize that in your decisions you seek not to be influenced by internal
                    political considerations. I wish the American people could understand the
                    predicament which their President is in when he has to make decisions in the
                    interest of the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> without regard to domestic
                    political pressures. This is a fact I always mention to Americans who visit
                    me.</p>
                <p>As for your observation regarding Israel, Mr. President, I should like to point
                    out that Israel was the aggressor. It was Israel that started <pb facs="0517"
                        n="484" xml:id="pg_484"/> the war. And Israel must withdraw from the
                    territories it occupied. We believe in the principle that no profit should
                    accrue from military aggression. If this principle is followed, then the results
                    of the 1967 aggression can be eradicated. This does not mean that I will
                    recognize Israel. But we have no objection to a settlement which is acceptable
                    to the contiguous Arab countries. I believe that an expeditious settlement could
                    deal a fatal blow to Communist influence in the area. If a settlement is not
                    reached quickly, I believe it will be impossible to deal successfully with
                    Communism later. Unless a solution of the problem is found soon, the pro-Soviet
                    elements in the Arab countries will have their hand strengthened. These are the
                    observations I wanted to bring to your attention, Mr. President.</p>
                <p>President: Your Majesty and I have a good understanding of our respective
                    positions. We will, at the highest levels of our governments, support progress
                    in our mutual interest. As for the Middle East as a whole, we here want to
                    pursue all efforts in the direction of peace in that area.</p>
                <p>King: I would like to express my best wishes for Your Excellency’s success in
                    your endeavors.</p>
                <p> [At this point Prince <persName corresp="#p_NAASP1">Nawwaf</persName>, Amb.
                    Suwayel, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pharaon</persName>, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">General
                        Haig</persName> were invited to join the discussion.]</p>
                <p>President: His Majesty and I have had a very good discussion. We find that our
                    bilateral relations could not be more friendly. We discussed the more difficult
                    problem of the broad area of the Middle East and Persian Gulf/Indian Ocean area.
                    I have found the discussion very profitable. This administration is committed to
                    a policy of seeking the normalization of the situation there. His Majesty
                    understands our internal problems, but Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1"
                        >Rogers</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> and all
                    of us shall continue to strive toward the settlement of the problem in the
                    interest of peace and justice in the area.</p>
                <p>King: I do appreciate the President’s problems and difficulties, but hope that
                    further efforts can be made so that we may not have to continue to live under
                    the Communist threat. Otherwise it will be too late. If things are allowed to
                    drag on, then the Communist influence in the area will become too strong for us
                    to cope with.</p>
                <p>President: I share His Majesty’s concern about the danger of letting things drag
                    on and the need for expeditious progress. The State Department is proceeding on
                    this basis.</p>
                <p>King: I would like to talk about Israel’s demand for secure borders and the
                    Israeli insistence on the retention of the Golan Heights, Sharm el-Sheikh,
                    Jerusalem and the Gaza Strip. What, in fact, are secure borders? As far as
                    Jerusalem is concerned, we will never agree that it continue to be under Israeli
                    domination. Israel occupied these <pb facs="0518" n="485" xml:id="pg_485"/>
                    territories by aggression. We demand that Israel go back to the pre 1967
                    borders. Then the details of secure borders can be discussed.</p>
                <p>As for the Suez Canal, it would be in our selfish interest to have it reopened.
                    If the Canal is reopened, trade between us and other nations will be facilitated
                    and our financial aid to Egypt will be discontinued. The advantages of reopening
                    the Suez Canal are plentiful, as far as we are concerned. But the Communists are
                    advocating the reopening of the canal because that will facilitate their entry
                    into the Persian Gulf and Indian Ocean areas. It will be easier for them to
                    spread their influence throughout that area.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName>: The reopening of the Suez Canal
                    will benefit the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and give access to the
                        <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. But we feel that an interim agreement
                    cannot be a substitute for the overall solution. It does not touch other vital
                    matters which are part of the problem—Jerusalem, the Palestinians, etc. But we
                    are interested in keeping the initiative going. The political efforts of the
                    President, bulwarked by <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> power, can create the
                    kind of political condition (climate) which would be favorable to our interests
                    and where Soviet influence can be reduced.</p>
                <p>King: The reopening of the Suez Canal will not check the Soviet danger. Israel
                    will continue in occupation of Arab territory, no telling for how long. The
                    danger I have talked about will therefore continue to loom high in the
                    interim.</p>
                <p>President: There is no disagreement between us on the urgency of reaching a
                    settlement. I am sure that Your Majesty and we are going to continue working on
                    an urgent basis. We shall have the chance to talk further at the luncheon.</p>
                <p>King: One more point I would like to make. Should Israel be made to feel that if
                    she continues to spurn all efforts for peace she will lose the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss>’ support, then she might become more flexible.
                    But on the other hand, if she feels that, no matter what position she takes, she
                    can nevertheless count on <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> support, then she
                    will do nothing to help the cause of peace. It seems to me that Israel is more
                    representative of the Communist world than she is of the free world, although
                    the general impression is that Israel is the bulwark of democracy in the Middle
                    East. The Soviets were more ardent in their support for the creation of Israel
                    than the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> was. Should a miracle occur and the
                        <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> discontinue its support of Israel, I
                    predict that the Soviets and all Communists will make a roundabout turn in their
                    stand vis-à-vis Israel and rush to her help and preservation. It is advantageous
                    for the Communists to have Israel remain as a thorn in <gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >US</gloss>–Arab relations. Golda Meir is now on her way to Finland to
                    attend a Socialist convention. The Socialists meeting in Finland are the same as
                    Communists.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
