<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-09-17T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-09-17T07:00:00-05:00" n="255" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d255">
                        <head>255. Transcript of a Telephone Conversation Among the President’s
                            Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>), the Assistant Secretary of State
                            for Near Eastern and South Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">Sisco</persName>), and the Permanent Under Secretary in
                            the British Foreign Office (<persName type="to">Greenhill</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d255fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Telephone Conversations,
                                Box 30, Chronological Files. No classification marking. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> were in Washington and
                                Greenhill was in London. The conversation was on the “secure
                                phone.”</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-09-17T08:00:00-04:00">September 17, 1970, 8 a.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: Can we discuss the present situation in Amman
                            for a moment?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Yes.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: What is the latest report you have from the
                            city?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: That the army has secured the
                            western hills and is moving on the road past the Intercontinental Hotel
                            into the city. It has secured the southern hills but hasn’t yet gotten
                            into the heart of the city.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: Do you think the King’s claim that he will have
                            the hostages by tonight is valid?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: We can’t judge that. We do
                            judge that the whole operation will take longer than a day. But it is
                            also our judgment that he can defeat the Fedayeen by himself.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: I don’t know whether you have seen the text of
                            what we have proposed Bern Group should put out this afternoon.<note n="2" xml:id="d255fn2">See telegram 152282 to Bern, September 17,
                                0032Z. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59,
                                Central Files 1970–73, AV 12 <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: No, I haven’t seen it. I have
                            Joe <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> on the line also.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: Have you seen it Joe?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">S</persName>: No. I am up on all
                            the wire traffic but haven’t seen that.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: We have proposed that the Bern Group should put
                            out the following communiqué: “The five governments are ready to open
                            negotiations upon the proposal of the <gloss target="#t_PFLP1">PFLP</gloss> as soon as the <gloss target="#t_PFLP1">PFLP</gloss>
                            provides the Bern Group with all the demands including the release of
                            the people the <gloss target="#t_PFLP1">PFLP</gloss> wants. We have
                            furnished [omission in the original] on this basis. Meanwhile, we will
                            hold the <gloss target="#t_PFLP1">PFLP</gloss> responsible for the
                            hostages in Jordan.”</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">S</persName>: Offhand my reaction
                            is that sounds very good. It’s the precise position we discussed with
                            you and the others in yesterday’s meeting.<note n="3" xml:id="d255fn3">Presumably the September 16 meeting of the Bern Group; see <ref target="#d250fn4">Document 250 and footnote 4
                                thereto</ref>.</note> We will need to discuss it here with the
                            others. We want to evaluate the impact <pb facs="0748" n="715" xml:id="pg_715"/> of such an announcement on the evolving situation
                            on the ground. My own reaction is quite sympathetic and we will let you
                            know.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: Okay, secondly, have you received any
                            representations from the Germans?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: No, to what effect?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: You will be receiving one to the same effect as
                            one they sent to us. What it amounts to is that they are thinking if we
                            can’t keep the five-power basis, we could proceed by a four-power or a
                            three-power one, or finally a two-power collective agreement for a
                            unilateral agreement for each of us to do the best with our
                            hostages.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: If you have no other comments
                            of a general nature I will return to the meeting I left for this
                                conversation.<note n="4" xml:id="d255fn4">See <ref target="#d254">Document 254</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: Okay. Joe, we are of course very concerned with
                            the hostages. There are three possible courses if you abandon the
                            five-power approach: the four of us could say that the European
                            prisoners would be exchanged for all the hostages except for the three
                            Israelis.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">S</persName>: But those there are
                            also Americans.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: They are not pure Israelis?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">S</persName>: No, they are
                            Americans.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: Then that would only be feasible for you if all
                            the hostages, period?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">S</persName>: Right, this deal is
                            not a deal for us. We’re satisfied that those two or three have an
                            American connection here, they carry American passports. That’s the
                            problem.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: But theoretically it’s a possible deal for all
                            the European prisoners if <hi rend="italic">all</hi> the hostages?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">S</persName>: But how does that
                            differ from the announcement you were talking about? If this deal were
                            available … we’ve been trying to get it. But the other side is insisting
                            on this exchange.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: But in view of this situation they might agree.
                            There is another deal, that in view of the danger, Germany, the Swiss
                            and ourselves would swap our prisoners for our hostages, leaving you
                            unprovided for. Finally, we could agree among ourselves that no one
                            would approach the other.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">S</persName>: I can tell you we
                            have difficulties with all three. Moreover, your government would want
                            to weigh carefully the outcry in this country against your taking this
                            action. It would be strong and you should be sure that your ministers
                            understand that.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: But there would also be an outcry in this
                            country. If we don’t agree to bargain, our people get killed.</p>
                        <pb facs="0749" n="716" xml:id="pg_716"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">S</persName>: But who knows
                            whether a separate deal is really feasible?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: That’s true, but people would say “why didn’t
                            you try?”</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">S</persName>: As soon as I’m out
                            of this meeting we will consider the first proposal, the communiqué. But
                            you should know that we have now gone to the Israelis directly.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: Saying what?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">S</persName>: Saying basically
                            that we want to act together.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: Have you gone as far as to say that they must
                            pitch in?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">S</persName>: Yes, for the first
                            time we have gone to them for concrete and unilateral contributions.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: Well, Israel is saying to us that they can’t
                            agree to anything because they are waiting for you.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">S</persName>: We’ve gone now, so
                            let’s see what we get on that and also get back to you on the
                            communiqué.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: Okay, let me recapitulate our conversation. You
                            will consider the text of the communiqué, you will continue saying to
                            Israel that they must make a contribution. And you will consider our
                            other proposals.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">S</persName>: Yes, but our interim
                            reaction to them is negative. Let’s not talk in terms of proposals—“Line
                            of thought” is better.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>G</persName>: Okay. The Bern meeting is at 2:30 this
                            afternoon.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">S</persName>: Okay, if we need an
                            hour or two delay you’ll understand.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>