<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-09-19T10:54:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-09-19T10:54:00-05:00" n="268" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d268">
                        <head>268. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Switzerland</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d268fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, PS 7–6
                                JORDAN. Confidential; Flash. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_STW1">Seelye</persName> and Frank Trinka (EUR/AIS), and approved by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_STW1">Seelye</persName>. It was repeated
                                to Beirut (Flash), Amman, Bonn, London, Tel Aviv, and Geneva.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-09-19T15:54:00+00:00">September 19, 1970,
                                    1554Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>154331. Subject: Proposed Text Bern Group Message. Ref: Bern 2369; Beirut
                            7915, Beirut 7925.<note n="2" xml:id="d268fn2">Telegram 2369 from Bern,
                                September 19, 1220Z, transmitted the British text of a proposed Bern
                                Group message. In telegram 7915 from Beirut, September 19, 0935Z,
                                and telegram 7925 from Beirut, September 19, 1333Z, the Embassy
                                reported on discussions with <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss>
                                officials. (All ibid.)</note>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>We are prepared support new <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                                formula for message with addition of sentence suggested by Swiss and
                                your proposed amendment <pb facs="0786" n="753" xml:id="pg_753"/>
                                this sentence as well as further change in penultimate sentence (see
                                below). Redraft takes into account comments made by Prime Minister
                                Meir to Secretary.<note n="3" xml:id="d268fn3">The record of Meir’s
                                    September 18 discussion of the hostages with <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> is in telegram 154300 to
                                    Amman, Bern, Bonn, London, and Tel Aviv, September 19, 0311Z;
                                    see <ref target="frus1969-76ve01#d73">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume
                                        E–1, Documents on Global Issues, 1969–1972, Document
                                        73</ref>.</note>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss></hi>: Our current assessment
                                based on Meir’s comments is that while <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> will probably agree to initial three <gloss target="#t_PFLP1">PFLP</gloss> demands made of them (release of
                                Swiss, 2 Algerians and 10 Lebanese soldiers), Israelis very unlikely
                                agree to release of Palestinian prisoners. <hi rend="italic">End
                                        <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss></hi>.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>
                                <p>Text would thus read as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“The governments hold responsible for the safety of the
                                            hostages all those in whose hands they may be. The
                                            governments call upon those holding hostages to provide
                                            information on their whereabouts and wellbeing. They
                                            require that the hostages should be brought to a safe
                                            place which in the view of the governments is a
                                            prerequisite to an orderly transfer. The governments
                                            stand ready to consider at any time proposals for the
                                            release of all hostages. They also reaffirm their
                                            mandate to the <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss>.”</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </p>
                                <p>If above not acceptable, do not concur. Request instructions.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Imperative that Bern group reaffirm as soon as possible mandate to
                                    <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss> in view Beirut 7915 which
                                indicates <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss> reps cabling for
                                instructions and requesting presence <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss> rep with authority to negotiate re
                                hostages.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">For Beirut</hi>: You should make absolutely clear
                                to <gloss target="#t_PFLP1">PFLP</gloss>, as well as to <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss> reps in Beirut, that <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> has in no way accepted <gloss target="#t_PFLP1">PFLP</gloss> conditions and continues to
                                insist on package approach. This means that either all hostages must
                                be released or none at all. Beirut 7926<note n="4" xml:id="d268fn4">Telegram 7926 from Beirut, September 19, 1335Z, reported the
                                    view of the <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss>
                                    representatives that the U.S. Government and Israeli Government
                                    had “agreed in principle that Israel should release some
                                    Palestinians it holds.” The <gloss target="#t_PFLP1">PFLP</gloss> sought a guarantee from the U.S. Government
                                    that Israel would release a specified number of prisoners.
                                    (Ibid.)</note> just received. You should emphasize to <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss> that <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> cannot guarantee any Israeli undertaking in regard
                                to release of hostages and, as indicated para 1 above, likelihood of
                                Israel agreeing to release Palestinian prisoners is slim. We are
                                disturbed at how Boissard and Boissier seem to be so unaware of what
                                has gone on up to now. You should straighten them out.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">For Bern</hi>: At today’s meeting you should refer
                                to conversation between Embassy Beirut and <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss> reps (Boissier and Boissard) and urge that Bern
                                group assures that <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss>
                                headquarters provide background information to their reps in Beirut
                                re state of play in negotiations and positions of various parties up
                                to now.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Rogers</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>