<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-09-21T05:15:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-09-21T05:15:00-05:00" n="295" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d295">
                        <head>295. Transcript of a Telephone Conversation Among the President’s
                            Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>), the President’s Deputy Assistant for
                            National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName>), and Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d295fn1">Source:
                                National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                                Presidential Materials, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Telephone Conversations, Box 30,
                                Chronological Files. No classification marking. The time, “prob.
                                about 6:15 am,” is handwritten. All brackets are in the
                                original.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-09-21T06:15:00-04:00">September 21, 1970, about 6:15
                                    a.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName>,
                            sir.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: The Secretary said he had to
                            go to the Men’s Room—he can’t take the call right away. The President
                            added another condition.<note n="2" xml:id="d295fn2">See <ref target="#d294">Document 294</ref>.</note> Did you hear it?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: No, I did not.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: They should announce if they
                            go in on ground that they’d withdraw if the Syrians withdraw, and I
                            think he’s right—that if it gets unstuck, if the Jordanians collapse,
                            then it’s a new situation anyway.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: That’s correct.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: I think that’s right. You
                            know, they can’t act like maniacs. Should we have the <gloss target="#t_WSAG1">WSAG</gloss> meeting anyway?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: Oh, I think you are going to have to.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Well, I hate to tell that many
                            people so much. I think they should confine it to principals.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: Yeah, I wouldn’t tell them so much. One thing
                            that’s concerned me, <persName>Henry</persName>, is how this thing
                            evolves, assuming that this all goes as outlined. The situation in
                            Amman, the Sit Room tells me, is getting worse, and we may be faced
                            with—concurrently—this U.S. citizen problem. Some thought in sorting
                            that out should be applied; in other words, I gather they intend to
                            react in the area involved.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: That’s right.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: So this could possibly be a concurrent action.
                            It was demanded in terms of our citizens, and I wonder if we shouldn’t
                            convey the possibility of that.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: To whom? <persName corresp="#p_RY1">Rabin</persName>?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: Yeah. I don’t know that it’s a good idea, but if
                            they get in there—see, you just don’t know broad a front they intend to
                            move on. I wouldn’t think they would want to get locked into that
                            problem.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: It is deteriorating in
                            Amman?</p>
                        <pb facs="0854" n="821" xml:id="pg_821"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: Yes.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: I thought they had the
                            stinking town under control.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: I think they probably did; I think they have
                            sped some more people in there, too. This thing’s been set up—this is a
                            typical Soviet exercise.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: What would have happened if
                            the King hadn’t moved? They would have moved against him.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: Oh, he would have been overthrown within two or
                            three months, I think, and decisively.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: I think less than that—that’s
                            the only thing. I now see the game plan. They were going to use the
                            peace talks to overthrow the King and in the meantime strengthen the
                            Egyptians.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: Sure.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: And then really put the
                            squeeze on the Israelis.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: That’s right.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: That’s the only thing that
                            makes sense.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: That’s right. And, in the meantime, obviously
                            they bilk the Syrians. They’ve just been active across the board.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: You don’t think …</p>
                        <p>[At this point, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>
                            joined the conversation]</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Hello.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: Hi,
                            <persName>Henry</persName>.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Let me continue where I was
                            before. (1) Then I talked to the President and gave him those facts. He
                            said that that, of course, made it more difficult obviously and that I
                            should start calling around to people who had been in the meeting in the
                            evening, starting with <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> to
                            get their views. I placed a call to <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> and just as I got him, the President called
                                me.<note n="3" xml:id="d295fn3">See <ref target="#d292">Document
                                    292</ref>.</note> He said he had thought about it….</p>
                        <p>[The Signal Operator interrupted to say Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> wanted to speak with General
                                <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName>]</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: No, just leave him on here
                            now. No, leave this conversation uninterrupted except for the
                            President.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: (Cont’d) … and said that he
                            had made the following decisions: First, that we should communicate to
                            the Israelis: (1) the action must succeed; (2) it has to succeed
                            diplomatically as well as militarily—for this purpose, our preference is
                            for air in the first instance, but that if they believe ground forces
                            are essential, we would support that also. Ground forces, however,
                            should be used inside Jordan; this was <pb facs="0855" n="822" xml:id="pg_822"/> in reference to when Joe was in the office and he
                            came in and Joe said he thought the best thing for the Israelis would be
                            to start attacking from the Golan Heights into Syria. The President says
                            that is militarily good, but politically not good. Those were the five
                            points he wanted me to communicate. I told him maybe we should have a
                            meeting of everybody. He said no, that’s what he wants to do, but of
                            course, anyone who wants to protest can do so to him. Now, he added,
                            when he interrupted before, a sixth point which is that they should be
                            told that if they go in on the ground, they should announce that they
                            will withdraw when the Syrians withdraw or if the Syrians withdraw. I
                            said, “what if the situation gets completely unstuck in Jordan?” He
                            said, “That’s a different problem, but the correct diplomatic posture is
                            to go in and say they’ll withdraw as soon as the Syrians withdraw.” So,
                            this is where we stand. I haven’t done anything else.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: Have you told them?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: No, no, no. I wouldn’t do that
                            without talking to you. But I got the call from <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> that I had placed earlier. I just
                            told him and told him I was going to call you immediately, and <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> said he was coming in to the
                            office. Those are the only people who have been contacted.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: There are two things: (1) I
                            gather from Al that he felt that the Israelis would not do anything
                            until tomorrow. Is that right? Did they pass?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: I would guess by tonight our
                            time—uh, tomorrow night our time (Monday night our time) is our
                            instinct. They didn’t say.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: Yeah, but in any event, we’d
                            have … it’s 1:00 in Amman.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: I would think Tuesday morning
                            Amman time.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: Did you say that they wanted
                            an answer right away?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Within two hours or so.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: I wonder what the …</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Well, I think they have to get
                            their forces ready.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: We have here a cryptic message
                            which just came in. [<hi rend="italic">1½ lines not declassified</hi>]
                            the Israelis have landed forces from helicopters in Syria.” What do you
                            think of that?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: I haven’t. For all we know,
                            they may be running around there already.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: That’s what I mean.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: That’s not my impression,
                            though. I don’t believe that. Al, you were in on that conversation. Was
                            it your impression that they could be moving?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: No, I think they could be feinting a little
                            bit.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: I don’t believe it.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: I don’t believe it either.</p>
                        <pb facs="0856" n="823" xml:id="pg_823"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Unless they are absolutely
                            tricking us, and I don’t see what advantage it is to them to trick us
                            about asking our support for a move that they say they’ll make later and
                            then make it ahead of time. At any rate, they gave us no indication of
                            that, though.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: Well, it seems to me there are
                            a couple of things we should be doing—certainly a couple have come to
                            mind right away. (1) Once this happens, and the chances of saving the
                            King are probably pretty slim anyway; I can’t imagine any Arab can
                            survive very long if he has to call upon the Israelis to save him.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Well, my guess would be that
                            he would disassociate himself.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: Uh-huh.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: I don’t think he can admit
                            that he called them—that he asked for air strikes.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: Yeah, probably not. If that is
                            the case, and you are probably right, although I am never convinced that
                            anything can be held in confidence though if they decide to leak—just
                            because the British certainly know about it, too—but, in any event,
                            assume it doesn’t leak, then what if Eban(?) says to the Arabs that the
                            Israelis have, without request from Jordan, invaded their land, which
                            will probably mean an Arab-Israeli conflict. I don’t see how <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> can stand by and do nothing if
                            it doesn’t appear that this was done at the King’s request.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Well, they’ve stood by before.
                            Well, you do something.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: When did they stand by
                            before.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: The Egyptians haven’t, but all
                            the other Arabs have stood by while the Egyptians were being …</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: Oh, yeah. I was trying to put
                            it the other way around though.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: No, no—the Egyptians haven’t
                            stood by; but the Egyptians have never had the choice of standing
                            by.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: No, but if Nasser’s going to
                            have to be standing with the Arabs, he can’t …</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: No, I think it’s reasonable
                            that he’ll do something, and I think Joe thinks he’ll do something.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: Which means really that we’ll
                            be faced with the problem if he does that if Israel doesn’t succeed,
                            that they’ll call on us.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Succeed against the
                            Egyptians?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: Yeah, against whoever would be
                            helping IF THEY are not …</p>
                        <p>In other words, when the President lays down the pre-condition that they
                            have to succeed, I suppose they’d say to themselves, “well, we agreed,
                            too.”</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: But, I think what the
                            President’s phrase, “action must succeed” means it’s to lead into ground
                            action. I think what we have to expect is this, IN MY judgment, Bill.
                            There’s no doubt that the action will <pb facs="0857" n="824" xml:id="pg_824"/> succeed and there’s no doubt, I think, that the
                            Israelis can handle the Egyptians together with the Syrians. The
                            question that arises is, if the Soviets intervene and there we would be
                            obliged to help support them, I don’t think there is … I cannot conceive
                            that the Israelis can’t handle the Egyptians and Syrians combined. What
                            do you think, Al?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: I think that’s so.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: That certainly has been
                            everyone’s assessment.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>H</persName>: I don’t think there’s too much the Egyptians
                            could do although I think they would try to do something. I don’t think
                            they have much they can do other than to start the artillery falling, in
                            which case the Israelis will act.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: I think that’s the only thing,
                            myself, that can be done—that they can do. I think the realistic
                            occasion for American intervention will arise when … if the Soviets were
                            to intervene one way or the other. And we would have to be prepared to
                            be very tough in warning them off. There is a corollary to this move.
                            Within the area, I think it can be handled—with a lot of excitement, but
                            I think it can be handled.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: Well, it’s awfully damned
                            difficult to make these judgments. That certainly would be my judgment
                            and I think it’s the judgment of those over here. Well, the trouble with
                            that is, so was everybody confident that the King could handle the
                            Fedayeen and apparently can’t. Leaving Syria out, we can’t handle them
                            in Amman ‘cause that seems …</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: I was never so confident of
                            that one.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: Most people were, though.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Yeah, I know most people were,
                            though.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: I didn’t hear anybody express
                            any real reservations.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Well, I was … after the first
                            few days’ reports, I also saw that he could. But, be that as it may, if
                            the Israelis can’t handle the Arabs, they can’t be bailed out by us. We
                            won’t have enough forces to bail them out. We only have one decision.
                            But since all of our policy has been based on the assumption that the
                            military balance hadn’t turned against them and that they were still
                            superior … that I don’t think is going to happen.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: In our weighing it, we were
                            thinking about it in terms of Egypt and Jordan. I don’t know as we were
                            thinking about it in terms of Syria and Iraq, but, you know, I never
                            heard anybody express any doubt about it including the Israelis. They’ve
                            always thought they could.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: And they repeated that again.
                            And we checked yesterday with <persName corresp="#p_MTH1">Moorer</persName> at the meetings. He thinks … but that’s, of
                            course, subject to the same theories (queries?) that you’ve put before.
                            They also thought they probably could handle the Fedayeen.</p>
                        <pb facs="0858" n="825" xml:id="pg_825"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">R</persName>: Well, I think the question
                            probably in my mind now is the time problem, whether we have to give
                            them an answer so soon if they aren’t actually going to invade. If this
                            cryptic message is incorrect and they aren’t going to actually invade
                            until sometime tomorrow morning—in other words, if we have 24 hours, I
                            wonder why they need so much advance. I can see how they can sort of get
                            ready with it, but I don’t see why they have to know for sure. Because
                            the information we had was to the effect that [End of tape]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>