<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-02-04T07:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-02-04T07:30:00-05:00" n="77" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d77">
                        <head>77. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Iran</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d77fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 33 PERSIAN GULF. Secret. It was
                                repeated to Jidda, Kuwait, London, New Delhi, and <gloss target="#t_CINCSTRIKECINCMEAFSA1">CINCSTRIKE/CINCMEAFSA</gloss>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-02-04T12:30:00+00:00">February 4, 1970,
                                1230Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>418. Subject: U.S. Persian Gulf Policy.</p>
                        <p>1. Latest draft of Persian Gulf policy paper<note n="2" xml:id="d77fn2">See <ref target="#d76fn2">footnote 2, Document 76</ref>.</note>
                            recently received here strikes us in general as comprehensive,
                            reasonable analysis of problems to be expected in post-British era and
                            of possible measures for meeting them. Following comments offered in
                            light of problem as seen from Tehran: <list>
                                <label>(A)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <p>We find ourselves unable share paper’s optimism (page 19)that
                                        potential Gulf instability unlikely be of magnitude threaten
                                        U.S. interests or oil operations. As we see it here a vacuum
                                        will inevitably be created when British pull out end of
                                        1971. Basic question is not whether there will be vacuum but
                                        who will fill it and when (i.e., before or after end of
                                        1971). If by end 1971 no arrangements (informal though they
                                        may be) have been made for at least a limited degree of
                                        cooperation between some of more important moderate riparian
                                        states, it is difficult to believe that radical Arabs, aided
                                        and encouraged by Soviets, will fail to exploit vacuum to
                                        detriment of our vital interests. Today Prosy seems already
                                        serving as base for radical Arab subversive activities and
                                        even for armed attack on moderate Arab regimes.</p>
                                    <p>Indeed paper (page 12) recognizes radical groups may be able
                                        to seize one or more governments in 3 to 5 years. Japanese
                                        Ambassador tells me in strict confidence <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> deeply concerned re future
                                        of Gulf because Gulf oil essential to Japan’s very life. He
                                        pointed out smaller sheikhdoms that have struck oil are
                                        having to import Arab speaking teachers, technicians, etc.,
                                        and they come largely from Egypt, Syria and Palestine and
                                        will facilitate radical efforts to take over. In absence of
                                        new and constructive developments Japanese Middle East
                                        experts who recently examined question only give Kuwait
                                        regime about three years before it succumbs to radicals and
                                        if there is Arab-Israel settlement, Japanese believe
                                        radicals will almost immediately step up actions against
                                        moderates.</p>
                                    <p>Paper’s recognition that Soviets are devoting greatly
                                        increased attention to Gulf and to Soviet presence there
                                        also seems support this conclusion as does generally held
                                        international estimate that Gulf oil <pb facs="0280" n="247" xml:id="pg_247"/> will be vitally important to Soviet
                                        and satellite requirements in next 10 to 15 years. Soviets
                                        already have foot in oil door and Iraq through exploitation
                                        of north Rumaila concession.</p>
                                </item>
                                <label>(B)</label>
                                <item>We are not quite so sanguine (page 10) that Iraq’s
                                    preoccupation with Arab-Israel, Kurds, and dispute with Iran
                                    will prevent it from undertaking, with Soviet encouragement,
                                    more active subversive role against weak, moderate Arab regimes
                                    in Gulf arena. Certainly if vacuum develops end of 1971 there
                                    will be almost irresistible temptation to subversive
                                    activity.</item>
                                <label>(C)</label>
                                <item>As to intra-Gulf tensions, paper seems obsessed with
                                    difficulties and obstacles to any meaningful cooperation (even
                                    informal) between Iran and moderate Arab regimes. While there
                                    are of course major obstacles and paper’s estimate seems valid
                                    for recent years—and indeed it may continue to be so—we do not
                                    believe that we should take a defeatist stand on this issue for
                                    vitally important period ahead. Until comparatively recently
                                    Iran’s attitude was not constructive. However, with prospect of
                                    vacuum developing after British withdrawal, Iran’s attitude has
                                    changed and it is now seeking allay fears and suspicions of Arab
                                    Gulf states by treating their leaders with respect (recent
                                    visits of Sheikhs of Sharja and Ras-al-Khaimah) and extending
                                    assistance to Saudi Arabia so that some arrangement for
                                    cooperation between Iran and moderate Gulf states can be
                                    developed. While at this juncture prospects are not very bright,
                                    when or if it becomes obvious to some moderate Arab regimes that
                                    unless something is done a vacuum may develop which could result
                                    in the disappearance their present attitude towards Arab-Iran
                                    cooperation.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bahrein settlement involving Iranian abandonment of its traditional claim
                            and acceptance of Bahrein membership in <gloss target="#t_FAA1">FAA</gloss> if Bahrein so desires could increase possibility of at
                            least informal cooperation which could result in partially filling
                            vacuum of British departure. In any event we feel that it serves <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> interests to encourage Iran-Arab
                            cooperation in Gulf where this can be done without being
                            counterproductive, as it can be done in Iran. (See E below.)</p>
                        <p>2. Following are views re certain matters on which paper indicates early
                            decisions needed: <list>
                                <label>(A)</label>
                                <item>Future of <gloss target="#t_MIDEASTFOR1">MIDEASTFOR</gloss>.
                                    We believe continuation <gloss target="#t_MIDEASTFOR1">MIDEASTFOR</gloss> useful demonstration of <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> interest in peace and stability
                                    of region. Conversely, its withdrawal, unless riparian states so
                                    desired, might be interpreted as <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> indifference to future of region. Until there is
                                    Bahrein settlement, it awkward to discuss this matter with Shah.
                                    However, when Bahrein’s future decided, we believe Shah’s hands
                                    will be free to adopt more tolerant attitude, particularly if an
                                    independent (or <gloss target="#t_FAA1">FAA</gloss> federation
                                    member) Bahrein is agreeable to continued home porting there of
                                        <gloss target="#t_MIDEASTFOR1">MIDEASTFOR</gloss>. If
                                    necessary I could discuss this matter with Shah before <pb facs="0281" n="248" xml:id="pg_248"/> Bahrein settlement
                                    basing my presentation on assumption that independent Bahrein
                                    agrees to continuation home porting of <gloss target="#t_MIDEASTFOR1">MIDEASTFOR</gloss> in Bahrein.
                                    However, it very delicate matter and pending Bahrein settlement
                                    Shah may feel unable to be very forthcoming on future
                                    arrangements re territory he considers traditionally
                                    Iranian.</item>
                                <label>(B)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> policy toward <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> membership for <gloss target="#t_FAA1">FAA</gloss> for single states. (No
                                    comment.)</item>
                                <label>(C)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> arms policy toward Gulf Arabs.
                                    We concur <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> should be prepared
                                    to consider any actual requests for sales carefully on case by
                                    case basis in light our over-all Gulf policy. While Iranians
                                    might be sensitive if these small states sought massive arms
                                    shipments which they obviously could not use and which might
                                    become a windfall arms cache in unfriendly hands, a reasonable
                                    policy of arms shipments should not disturb them, particularly
                                    since <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> would probably prefer
                                    to have us rather than some other states supply them.</item>
                                <label>(D)</label>
                                <item>Foreign Service posts in area. Both political factors and
                                    commercial considerations argue for establishment of additional
                                    Foreign Service presence in lower Gulf. In first place, with
                                    increasing oil revenues to small Gulf states our commercial
                                    interests alone, on which our balance of payments so heavily
                                    depend, would seem to require a presence that could assist
                                    American business and industry more effectively than now in
                                    getting a greater share of this lucrative and steadily expanding
                                    market, which British obviously hope to retain largely for
                                    themselves. While such a presence could be relatively low
                                    profile, it would enable us to explain our policies and, if
                                    coupled with some cultural and technical assistance, could lead
                                    to a slow expansion of our over-all influence. If we retain
                                        <gloss target="#t_MIDEASTFOR1">MIDEASTFOR</gloss> in Gulf,
                                    it should not be only <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> presence
                                    there and if we withdraw it a commercial and political presence
                                    would still serve our own best interest.</item>
                                <label>(E)</label>
                                <item>We also suggest a considered decision would be useful as to
                                    whether we discreetly encourage, where we can do so without
                                    being counter-productive, cooperation between moderate Arab
                                    riparian states and Iran looking to arrangements that could
                                    strengthen security and stability in Gulf. While in no way
                                    underestimating difficulties of such cooperation in security and
                                    other fields, we think that if it could take form (even though
                                    it initially might be very informal) it would hold best hope for
                                    filling vacuum caused by British withdrawal and thus contribute
                                    to maintenance of peace and stability in this vital area so
                                    essential to our own balance of payments and other interests and
                                    even more essential to our <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                                    and Japanese allies. This does not involve our “sponsorship” of
                                    such an arrangement but discreet “encouragement” where
                                    possible.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>