<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Spain ( (Hammond) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1928v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d128</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">128</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1928-08-17T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1928-08-17T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-08-17T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-08-17T10:00:00-05:00" n="128"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d128">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.0012Anti-War/244: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Spain</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hammond</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">San Sebastian</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-08-17T16:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 17, 1928—4 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[Received 4:02 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>77. Your telegram August 16, 1 p.m. After the Council of Ministers held at
                    Corunna on August 14, General Primo de Rivera gave the following communication
                    to the press with regard to Spain’s position relative to the anti-war pact:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Kellogg pact has been communicated to Spain and its signature or
                            collaboration has been requested. Spain will give its approval or will
                            communicate such reservations as it may deem expedient but it is a
                            significant proof of the consideration in which Spain is held. The
                            Ambassador of the United States himself, making a journey of 900
                            kilometers from San Sebastian to Mondariz, came to see me to inform me
                            of the negotiations of this international matter and to give an account
                            of the details thereof. This fact is a proof of consideration for Spain
                            and I have personally expressed my gratitude to Mr. Hammond for his
                            coming to Mondariz leaving his wife ill at San Sebastian.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>[Paraphrase.] From the foregoing the Department will perceive that Primo de
                    Rivera has not only accepted situation in regard to nonparticipation of Spain as
                    one of the original signatories of the treaty for the renunciation of war but
                    has also been able to find in my visit to Mondariz a matter for national
                    self-congratulation and a continued proof of the esteem which Spain enjoys
                    abroad.</p>
                <p>I do not consider it advisable, therefore, to take matter up again with the Prime
                    Minister until after his arrival in San Sebastian on the 25th of this month. At
                    that time I shall talk to him along lines of your telegram and shall urge
                    Spain’s prompt adherence to the treaty. [End paraphrase.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hammond</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
