<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-08-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-08-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="143" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d143">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.3712Anti-War/4</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Judah</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-08-30"><hi rend="italic">August 30,
                                        1928</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received September 5.]</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 414</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my despatch No. 413
                                of August 29, 1928,<note n="31" xml:id="d143fn31">Not
                                    printed.</note> I have the honor to transmit herewith for the
                                Department’s information a copy of a note just received from the
                                Cuban Under Secretary of State in connection with the adherence of
                                Cuba to the Multilateral Treaty for the Renunciation of War,
                                together with a copy of an enclosure therewith comprising certain
                                remarks of President Machado on this subject, and my reply
                                    thereto,<note n="32" xml:id="d143fn32">Reply not printed.</note>
                                as well as translations of the first two documents.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Noble Brandon
                                Judah</hi></signed></closer>
                            <pb facs="0293" n="165" xml:id="pg_165"/>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg></opener>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">The Cuban Under Secretary of State</hi>
                                        (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Campa</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American
                                        Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Judah</hi></persName>)</head>
                                <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-08-29"><hi rend="italic">August 29,
                                            1928</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 858</seg></opener>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Ambassador</hi>: I have the honor to
                                    acknowledge receipt of Your Excellency’s note dated August 27th,
                                    informing me, in behalf of your Government, that on that date
                                    there had been signed in Paris a treaty whereby the governments
                                    of Germany, the United States, Belgium, France, Great Britain,
                                    Canada, Australia, New Zealand, the Union of South Africa, the
                                    Irish Free State, India, Italy, Japan, Poland and Czechoslovakia
                                    renounce war as an instrument of national policy in their mutual
                                    relations and bind themselves to submit the arrangement of all
                                    differences which may arise in the future between them to
                                    pacific means of solution.</p>
                                <p>Although in the <hi rend="italic">Note Verbale</hi> of this
                                    Department dated the 28th I expressed to Your Excellency the
                                    opinion of this Government with regard to this Treaty and its
                                    intention to adhere thereto as soon as the protocol for the
                                    signing thereof provided in Article Three should be opened in
                                    Washington, today, in behalf of the Government of the Republic I
                                    am able to inform you that on proposal of the President of the
                                    Republic, the Cabinet resolved formally to adhere to the Treaty
                                    as soon as possible, for which purpose, telegraphic instructions
                                    were transmitted to the Chargé d’Affaires at Washington. I must
                                    add that immediately after said resolution was approved, the
                                    Cabinet Meeting adjourned, thereby paying a marked homage to the
                                    signing of said Pact, which will undoubtedly mark an epoch in
                                    the Destiny of Nations.</p>
                                <p>I also desire to express to Your Excellency the appreciation of
                                    this Department for supplying it with the English and French
                                    texts of said Pact.</p>
                                <p>Permit me to enclose a copy of the declarations of President
                                    Machado, made today at the termination of the Cabinet meeting,
                                    which express his absolute identification and that of the people
                                    of Cuba with this peace policy set forth in the Paris Treaty and
                                    from which justice and well-being are to be derived for all the
                                    nations.</p>
                                <p>I avail myself [etc.]</p>
                                <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Miguel Angel
                                        Campa</hi></signed></closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Subenclosure—Translation]</seg></opener>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">Statement by President Machado</hi></head>
                                <p>The Republic of Cuba will adhere to the multilateral treaty
                                    signed in Paris on August 27th, called the Kellogg Pact, whereby
                                    the nations <pb facs="0294" n="166" xml:id="pg_166"/> condemn
                                    war as a system of solving international controversies and bind
                                    themselves to use pacific means in the case of a
                                    disagreement.</p>
                                <p>For more than three years my Government has collaborated
                                    sincerely in the efforts made by humanity to organize peace.</p>
                                <p>Our diplomatic action, active and persevering, was shown to be
                                    such in every international conference, whether it was
                                    universal, such as the League of Nations, or regional, such as
                                    the Sixth International American Conference of Habana.</p>
                                <p>I am convinced of the effectiveness of this agreement which will
                                    join the nations by sacred ties, and which is to serve as a
                                    foundation for the beneficial interests of peace, just as in the
                                    past other treaties created motives for hatred and for violence
                                    which carried states toward pain and ruin.</p>
                                <p>Blessed be this America of ours from which has come forth this
                                    admirable gesture of concord which will favor the pacific
                                    development of the human race, making it impossible for the work
                                    of collective labor in which every nation has its share and
                                    responsibility to be destroyed in an insane hour of greed or
                                    madness!</p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>