<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Mexico ( (Morrow))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1928v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d181</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">181</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1928-09-26T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1928-09-26T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-09-26T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-09-26T15:00:00-05:00" n="181"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d181">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.1212Anti-War/6: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Morrow</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-09-26T16:00:00-04:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 26, 1928—4 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>263. Your 256 September 14, 3 p.m.<note n="82" xml:id="d181fn82">Not
                        printed.</note> Please hand the following note to the Acting Minister of
                    Foreign Affairs: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“I have the honor to inform Your Excellency that I did not fail to
                            communicate to my Government the substance of your note of September 14,
                                1928,<note n="83" xml:id="d181fn83">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_202">p.
                                202</ref>.</note> in which you informed me that the Mexican
                            Government awaited the announcement of the coming into effect of the
                            general treaty for the Renunciation of War in order to take the
                            necessary steps formally to establish its adherence. I am now instructed
                            by my Government to express its high appreciation of the gracious
                            sentiments of Your Excellency in regard to the Treaty.</p>
                        <p>“Adherence to this treaty may properly be completed by the deposit with
                            the Government of the United States of an instrument of adherence in
                            accordance with the constitutional requirement of the adhering state in
                            becoming party to treaties. This procedure may be followed as soon as
                            the Government of Mexico desires. There is no need to await ratification
                            by the Powers which signed the Treaty on August 27. Adherences completed
                            prior to the instant when the treaty becomes effective will
                            automatically make adhering powers parties to the treaty at that
                            instant.</p>
                        <p>[“]My Government has instructed me to express its cordial hope that the
                            Government of Mexico will be among the first of the countries which
                            complete the process of adherence, thus contributing to the prompt and
                            universal acceptance of a treaty which signalizes the deep and abiding
                            friendship between our two countries.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kellogg</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
