<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Ethiopia ( (Southard) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1928v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d188</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">188</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1928-10-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1928-10-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-10-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-10-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="188"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d188">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.8412Anti-War/5</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Ethiopia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Southard</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Addis Ababa</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-10-29">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 29, 1928</hi>.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received November 28.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 86</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the Department’s
                    circular instruction of September 17th, 1928, enclosing two authenticated copies
                    of the multilateral treaty for the renunciation of war, and indicating that the
                    instrument of adherence might be executed immediately in accordance with the
                    legal procedure of the Ethiopian Government.</p>
                <p>Promptly upon receipt of these copies a few days ago I took up with the Ethiopian
                    Government the matter of adherence and ratification.</p>
                <pb facs="0354" n="226" xml:id="pg_226"/>
                <p>As reported by telegraph to the Department on October 28th, 1928,<note n="91"
                        xml:id="d188fn91">Not printed.</note> His Majesty, King Tafari, on that date
                    sealed, signed and ratified the treaty. The act of sealing and signing by His
                    Majesty constitutes also complete and final ratification in accordance with
                    existing legal procedure of the Ethiopian Government.</p>
                <p>One copy of the sealed, signed, and ratified treaty is forwarded herewith. The
                    Amharic inscription on the seal reads in English: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“King Tafari, Heir to the Throne and Regent Plenipotentiary of the Empire
                            of Ethiopia.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Translation of the Amharic inscription or writing under the seal
                    is as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Seal affixed, signed, and approved (adhered to), Tekemt 18th, 1921
                            (October 28th, 1928), Year of Mercv, Addis Ababa. On behalf of the
                            Government of the Empire of Ethiopia. (Signed). Tafari Makonnen.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The three parenthetical words or phrases above are my own, added to make clearer
                    the translation from the Amharic. There is no exact term in Amharic for “adhere”
                    or “act of adherence”. Approved, accepted, and similar words, have the same
                    meaning in Amharic as does adhere in English. The seal also legally establishes
                    adherence. By the Ethiopian calendar the current year is 1921 A. D. The
                    corresponding date by our own calendar is given in parentheses immediately
                    following the Ethiopian date.</p>
                <p>Each Ethiopian official has his own special seal for legalizing and
                    authenticating his signature. Only the Empress, the King, and the Abouna (head
                    of the state church) may place their seals above or before the inscription or
                    signature. All others place the seal below and after the inscription and
                    signature.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Addison E. Southard</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
