<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-08-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-08-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="256" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d256">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A16/65</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Statement by the American Representative</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi>) <hi rend="italic">in the Fourth Meeting
                                of the Second Session of the Special Commission, August 29,
                                1928</hi><note n="60" xml:id="d256fn60">Extract from minutes
                                transmitted to the Department by the American Representative in
                                report No. 3, Sept. 3; received Sept. 14.</note></head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1928-08-29">August 29, 1928</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p>Yesterday the discussion turned on the question of aviation, and certain
                            reserves were made, which make it essential, in our opinion, to offer a
                            statement.</p>
                        <p>The American Government has consistently urged the fullest publicity for
                            all production of war material of both private and public
                            manufacture.</p>
                        <p>In submitting a reserve to Article 1, category 4, which I am about to
                            offer, I desire to state that full information concerning the production
                            in the United States of America of aircraft and aircraft engines for
                            civil and commercial purposes is available to the public in Government
                            publications.</p>
                        <p>From this fact it is evident that no question can arise of the good faith
                            of my Government in this matter; nor can anyone surmise that we suggest
                            the possibility of limitation of Category 4 for the purposes of secrecy.
                            Nevertheless, in the Preparatory Commission for Disarmament, and in
                            various subcommittees growing out of that Commission, the American
                            representatives have never failed to make clear our point of view that
                            limitation of civil and commercial aircraft is unacceptable.</p>
                        <p>Lest any doubt in the future should arise as to our attitude on this
                            point, we think it advisable to insert a note explaining that in this
                            Draft Convention we do not change our attitude as to our views against
                            the incorporation of all aircraft and aircraft motors as implements of
                            war, as they are described under the heading of Article l.<note n="61" xml:id="d256fn61">For text of the reservation, see remark 3, under
                                art. 1, of the preliminary draft convention, <hi rend="italic">infra.</hi></note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>