<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>International Convention and Protocol for the Abolition of Import and Export
                    Prohibitions and Restrictions, Signed at Geneva, November 8, 1927, Together With
                    a Supplementary Agreement and Protocol, Signed July 11, 1928</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1928v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d271</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">271</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1927-11-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1927-11-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87004890"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International trade</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec2r0t2UkWjO2ZV1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004011274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Subsidies</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec83f6d11c10a4344" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="league-of-nations" subject="league-of-nations">League of Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec90c76a0ac666292" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="public-health" subject="public-health">Public Health</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-11-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-11-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="271"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d271">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Treaty Series No. 811</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">International Convention and Protocol for the Abolition of
                        Import and Export Prohibitions and Restrictions, Signed at Geneva, November
                        8, 1927, Together With a Supplementary Agreement and Protocol, Signed July
                        11, 1928</hi>
                    <note n="93" xml:id="d271fn93">In English and French. French text not printed.
                        Convention and protocol signed on the part of the United States, January 30,
                        1928. Supplementary agreement and protocol signed on the part of the United
                        States, July 31, 1928. Ratification advised by the Senate, with reservation,
                        September 19, 1929 (legislative day of September 9); ratified by the
                        President; September 20, 1929; ratification of the United States deposited
                        at Geneva, September 30, 1929; proclaimed by the President, March 6,
                        1930.</note>
                </head>
                <p>The President of the German Reich; the President of United States of America; the
                    President of the Austrian Federal Republic; His Majesty the King of the
                    Belgians; His Majesty the King of Great Britain and Ireland and of the British
                    Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India; His Majesty the King of the
                    Bulgarians; the President of the Chilian Republic; His Majesty the King of
                    Denmark; His Majesty the King of Egypt; the President of the Estonian Republic;
                    the President of the Republic of Finland; the President of the French Republic;
                    His Serene Highness the Governor <pb facs="0465" n="337" xml:id="pg_337"/> of
                    Hungary; His Majesty the King of Italy; His Majesty the Emperor of Japan; the
                    President of the Latvian Republic; Her Royal Highness the Grand-Duchess of
                    Luxemburg; His Majesty the King of Norway; Her Majesty the Queen of the
                    Netherlands; the President of the Polish Republic; the President of the
                    Portuguese Republic; His Majesty the King of Roumania; His Majesty the King of
                    the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes; His Majesty the King of Siam; His Majesty the
                    King of Sweden; the Swiss Federal Council; the President of the Czechoslovak
                    Republic; the President of the Turkish Republic:</p>
                <p>Having regard to the resolution of the Assembly of the League of Nations dated
                    September 25th, 1924;</p>
                <p>Being guided by the conclusions of the International Economic Conference held at
                    Geneva in May 1927, and agreeing with the latter that import and export
                    prohibitions, and the arbitrary practices and disguised discriminations to which
                    they give rise have had deplorable results, without the grave drawbacks of these
                    measures being counterbalanced by the financial advantages or social benefits
                    which were anticipated by the countries which had recourse to them;</p>
                <p>Being persuaded that it is important for the recovery and future development of
                    world trade that Governments should abandon a policy which is equally injurious
                    to their own and to the general interest;</p>
                <p>Being convinced that a return to the effective liberty of international commerce
                    is one of the primary conditions of world prosperity; and</p>
                <p>Considering that this object may best be achieved by resort to simultaneous and
                    concerted action in the form of an international convention;</p>
                <p>Have appointed their plenipotentiaries, namely:</p>
                <p>[Here follows list of names of plenipotentiaries.]</p>
                <p>Who, having communicated their full powers, found in good and due form, have
                    agreed to the following provisions:</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1</p>
                <p>The provisions of the present Convention shall apply to prohibitions and
                    restrictions imposed on the importation into the territories of any High
                    Contracting Party of goods the produce or manufacture of the territories of any
                    other High Contracting Party, and to prohibitions and restrictions imposed on
                    the exportation of goods from the territories of any High Contracting Party to
                    the territories of any other High Contracting Party.</p>
                <pb facs="0466" n="338" xml:id="pg_338"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 2</p>
                <p>Subject to the exceptions provided for in the following articles, the High
                    Contracting Parties undertake to abolish within a period of six months from the
                    date of the coming into force of the present Convention, in so far as the
                    respective territories of each of them are concerned, all import and export
                    prohibitions or restrictions, and not thereafter to impose any such prohibitions
                    or restrictions. During this period each of the High Contracting Parties will
                    adopt all appropriate measures in order to reduce existing prohibitions and
                    restrictions to a minimum and will refrain from imposing any new prohibitions or
                    restrictions.</p>
                <p>Further, the High Contracting Parties undertake to adopt the necessary measures
                    to ensure that the provisions of the present Convention are strictly observed by
                    all authorities, central or local, and that no regulation is issued in
                    contravention thereof.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 3</p>
                <p>Should the High Contracting Parties, in pursuance of their legislation, subject
                    the importation or exportation of goods to certain regulations in respect of the
                    manner, form or place of importation or exportation, or the imposition of marks,
                    or to other formalities or conditions, they undertake that such regulations
                    shall not be made a means of disguised prohibition or arbitrary restriction.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 4</p>
                <p>The following classes of prohibitions and restrictions are not prohibited by the
                    present Convention, on condition, however, that they are not applied in such a
                    manner as to constitute a means of arbitrary discrimination between foreign
                    countries where the same conditions prevail, or a disguised restriction on
                    international trade: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Prohibitions or restrictions relating to public security.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Prohibitions or restrictions imposed on moral or humanitarian
                            grounds.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Prohibitions or restrictions regarding traffic in arms, ammunition and
                            implements of war, or, in exceptional circumstances, all other military
                            supplies.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Prohibitions or restrictions imposed for the protection of public
                            health or for the protection of animals or plants against disease,
                            insects and harmful parasites.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Export prohibitions or restrictions issued for the protection of
                            national treasures of artistic, historic or archaeological value.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Prohibitions or restrictions applicable to gold, silver, coins,
                            currency notes, banknotes or securities.</item>
                        <pb facs="0467" n="339" xml:id="pg_339"/>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>Prohibitions or restrictions designed to extend to foreign products
                            the regime established within the country in respect of the production
                            of, trade in, and transport and consumption of native products of the
                            same kind.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>Prohibitions or restrictions applied to products which, as regards
                            production or trade, are or may in future be subject within the country
                            to State monopoly or to monopolies exercised under State control.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 5</p>
                <p>Nothing in this Convention shall affect the right of any High Contracting Party
                    to adopt measures prohibiting or restricting importation or exportation for the
                    purpose of protecting, in extraordinary and abnormal circumstances, the vital
                    interests of the country.</p>
                <p>Should measures of this character be adopted, they shall be applied in such a
                    manner as not to lead to any arbitrary discrimination against any other High
                    Contracting Party. Their duration shall be restricted to that of the causes or
                    circumstances from which they arise.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 6</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The High Contracting Parties, recognising that there exist in the case of
                        certain of them situations of fact or of law which prevent the latter from
                        immediately undertaking, as regards certain specified products, the
                        engagements entered into under the previous articles, have deemed it
                        equitable to authorise these High Contracting Parties to make a reservation
                        in regard to certain temporary exceptions, which the latter undertake to
                        withdraw as soon as the circumstances from which they arise cease to
                        exist.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Moreover, the High Contracting Parties, recognising that the abolition of
                        certain import or export prohibitions or restrictions applied by some of
                        them would involve the latter in grave difficulties, and that, moreover,
                        these prohibitions or restrictions do not prejudicially affect the trade of
                        other countries, have also deemed it equitable to authorise these High
                        Contracting Parties to make a reservation in regard to these
                        exceptions.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The Annex to the present Convention sets forth the exceptions coming
                        within the provisions of the two preceding paragraphs, which have been
                        agreed to on this day’s date in favour of the High Contracting Parties who
                        are mentioned by name in the Annex and who have signed the Convention on
                        that date.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Exceptions which the High Contracting Parties may desire to claim
                        subsequently to that date shall be dealt with in accordance with the
                        procedure laid down in the Protocol to the present Convention.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0468" n="340" xml:id="pg_340"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 7</p>
                <p>Should one of the High Contracting Parties be obliged to adopt any measure of
                    prohibition or restriction against products of any foreign country, whether the
                    Convention be applicable to that country or not, he shall frame the measure in
                    such a way as to cause the least possible injury to the trade of the other High
                    Contracting Parties.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 8</p>
                <p>If a dispute arises between two or more High Contracting Parties as to the
                    interpretation or application of the provisions of the present Convention—with
                    the exception of Articles 4, 5 and 6, and of the provisions of the Protocol
                    relating to these articles—and if such dispute cannot be settled either directly
                    between the parties or by the employment of any other means of reaching
                    agreement, the parties to the dispute may, provided they all so agree, before
                    resorting to any arbitral or judicial procedure, submit the dispute with a view
                    to an amicable settlement to such technical body as the Council of the League of
                    Nations or the parties concerned may appoint. This body will give an advisory
                    opinion after hearing the parties and, if necessary, effecting a meeting between
                    them.</p>
                <p>The advisory opinion given by the said body will hot be binding upon the parties
                    to the dispute unless it is accepted by all of them, and the parties, if they
                    all so agree, may either after resort to such procedure, or in lieu thereof,
                    have recourse to any arbitral or judicial procedure which they may select,
                    including reference to the Permanent Court of International Justice as regards
                    any matters which are within the competence of that Court under its Statute.</p>
                <p>If a dispute of a legal nature arises as to the interpretation or application of
                    the provisions of the present Convention—with the exception of Articles 4, 5 and
                    6, and of the provisions of the Protocol relating to these articles—the parties
                    shall, at the request of any of them, refer the matter to the decision of the
                    Permanent Court of International Justice or of an arbitral tribunal selected by
                    them, whether or not there has previously been recourse to the procedure laid
                    down in the first paragraph.</p>
                <p>In the event of any difference of opinion as to whether a dispute is of a legal
                    nature or not, the question shall be referred for decision to the Permanent
                    Court of International Justice or to the arbitral tribunal selected by the
                    parties.</p>
                <p>The procedure before the body referred to in the first paragraph above or the
                    opinion given by it will in no case involve the suspension of the measures to
                    which the dispute refers; the same will apply in the event of proceedings being
                    taken before the Permanent Court of <pb facs="0469" n="341" xml:id="pg_341"/>
                    International Justice—unless the Court decides otherwise under Article 41 of its
                    statute—or before the arbitral tribunal selected by the parties.</p>
                <p>Nothing in the present Convention shall be construed as prejudicing the rights
                    and obligations derived by the High Contracting Parties from the engagements
                    into which they have entered with reference to the jurisdiction of the Permanent
                    Court of International Justice, or from any bilateral conciliation or
                    arbitration conventions between them.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 9</p>
                <p>Any High Contracting Party may, either upon ratifying the present Convention or
                    thereafter, declare that he undertakes, in regard to any other High Contracting
                    Party accepting the same obligation, to extend the application of the provisions
                    of paragraph 3 of Article 8 to any dispute which may arise in connection with
                    the interpretation or application of the provisions of the present Convention,
                    including all or part of Articles 4, 5 and 6, and whether or not the dispute is
                    of a legal nature.</p>
                <p>Any High Contracting Parties who do not give the undertaking referred to in
                    paragraph 1 as regards Articles 4, 5, and 6, or certain parts of these Articles,
                    and as regards the provisions of the Protocol relating thereto, may make the
                    provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 of Article 8 applicable to these matters as
                    between themselves.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 10</p>
                <p>Any High Contracting Party may at the time of signature, ratification or
                    accession declare that, in accepting the present Convention, he does not assume
                    any obligations in respect of all or any of his colonies, protectorates or
                    territories under suzerainty or mandate; and the present Convention shall not
                    apply to any territories named in such declaration.</p>
                <p>Any High Contracting Party may give notice to the Secretary-General of the League
                    of Nations at any time subsequently that he desires that the Convention shall
                    apply to all or any of his territories which have been made the subject of a
                    declaration under the preceding paragraph, and the Convention shall apply to all
                    the territories named in such notice ninety days after its receipt by the
                    Secretary-General of the League of Nations.</p>
                <p>Any High Contracting Party may at any time declare that he desires that the
                    present Convention shall cease to apply to all or any of his colonies,
                    protectorates or territories under suzerainty or mandate, and the Convention
                    shall cease to apply to the territories named in such declaration one year after
                    its receipt by the Secretary-General of the League of Nations.</p>
                <pb facs="0470" n="342" xml:id="pg_342"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 11</p>
                <p>Nothing in the present Convention shall prejudice the rights and obligations
                    which the High Contracting Parties may derive from international Conventions in
                    force to which they are parties.</p>
                <p>The present Convention shall not prejudice the provisions of any bilateral
                    agreements in force at the present date between the High Contracting Parties
                    which establish, in regard to import and export prohibitions or restrictions, a
                    more liberal regime than that established by the provisions of the present
                    Convention.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 12</p>
                <p>The present Convention shall not in any way affect rights and obligations arising
                    from the Covenant of the League of Nations.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 13</p>
                <p>The High Contracting Parties shall, within twelve months after the coming into
                    force of the present Convention in their territories, communicate to one another
                    through the Secretary-General of the League of Nations a report on the steps
                    taken to give effect to the provisions of the Convention.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 14</p>
                <p>The present Convention, of which the French and English texts are both authentic,
                    shall bear this day’s date.</p>
                <p>It shall be open for signature until January 1st, 1929, on behalf of any Member
                    of the League of Nations or of any non-Member State represented at the
                    Conference which drew up this Convention or to which the Council of the League
                    of Nations shall, for this purpose, have communicated a copy of the present
                    Convention.</p>
                <p>Members of the League of Nations and non-Member States on whose behalf the
                    Convention has been signed prior to February 1st, 1928, may avail themselves of
                    the procedure referred to in Article 6, paragraph 4.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 15</p>
                <p>The Present Convention shall be ratified.</p>
                <p>The instruments of ratification shall be deposited with the Secretary-General of
                    the League of Nations, who shall notify the receipt thereof to all Members of
                    the League and to the non-Member States referred to in the previous article.</p>
                <pb facs="0471" n="343" xml:id="pg_343"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 16</p>
                <p>On and after January 1st, 1929, any Member of the League of Nations or any State
                    referred to in Article 14 may accede to the present Convention.</p>
                <p>This accession shall be effected by a notification made to the Secretary-General
                    of the League of Nations, to be deposited in the archives of the Secretariat.
                    The Secretary-General shall at once notify such deposit to all who have signed
                    or acceded to the Convention.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 17</p>
                <p>The present Convention shall come into force under the conditions and on the date
                    to be determined at the meeting provided for hereinafter.</p>
                <p>Between June 15th and July 15th, 1928, the Secretary-General of the League of
                    Nations shall invite the duly accredited representatives of the Members of the
                    League of Nations and of non-Member States on whose behalf the Convention shall
                    have been signed on or before June 15th, 1928, to attend a meeting at which they
                    shall determine: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The reservations which, having been communicated to the High
                            Contracting Parties in accordance with Article 6, paragraph 4, may, with
                            their consent, be made at the time of ratification;</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The conditions required for the coming into force of the Convention
                            and, in particular, the number and, if necessary, the names of the
                            Members of the League and of non-Member States, whether they are
                            signatories or not, whose ratification or accession must first be
                            secured;</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The last date on which the ratifications may be deposited and the date
                            on which the Convention shall come into force if the conditions required
                            under the preceding paragraph are fulfilled.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>If, on the expiration of this period, the ratifications upon which the coming
                    into force of the Convention will be conditional have not been secured, the
                    Secretary-General of the League of Nations shall consult the Members of the
                    League of Nations and non-Member States on whose behalf the Convention has been
                    ratified and ascertain whether they desire nevertheless to bring it into
                    force.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 18</p>
                <p>The present Convention may be denounced by a notification in writing addressed to
                    the Secretary-General of the League of Nations on behalf of any Member of the
                    League of Nations or of any non-Member State after the expiration of a period of
                    five years reckoned from the date on which the Convention shall have entered
                    into force.</p>
                <p>Such denunciation shall take effect twelve months after the date <pb facs="0472"
                        n="344" xml:id="pg_344"/> on which it is received by the Secretary-General
                    of the League of Nations, and shall operate only in respect of the Member of the
                    League of Nations or the non-Member State on whose behalf it is made.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, the Convention may be denounced on behalf of any Member of the
                    League of Nations or any non-Member State after the expiration of the third year
                    from the date of the present Convention, if, after that period, any one of the
                    exceptions allowed in virtue of Article 6, paragraph 1, still exists. This
                    denunciation shall take effect six months after the date on which it is received
                    by the Secretary-General, and shall operate only in respect of the Member of the
                    League of Nations or the non-Member State on whose behalf it is made.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, the Convention may be denounced on behalf of any Member of the
                    League of Nations or of any non-Member State after the expiration of the fifth
                    year from the date of the present Convention, if, after that period, such Member
                    of the League of Nations or non-Member State considers that any one of the
                    exceptions allowed by the High Contracting Parties at the meeting provided for
                    in Article 17 has impaired the effects of the present Convention.</p>
                <p>This denunciation shall take effect six months after the date on which it is
                    received by the Secretary-General, and shall operate only in respect of the
                    Member of the League of Nations or the non-Member State on whose behalf it is
                    made.</p>
                <p>Any denunciation made in accordance with the foregoing provisions shall be
                    notified immediately by the Secretary-General of the League of Nations to all
                    the other High Contracting Parties.</p>
                <p>If, as a result of denunciations, the conditions for the coming into force of the
                    Convention which the High Contracting Parties may lay down at the meeting
                    provided for in Article 17 should no longer be fulfilled, any High Contracting
                    Party may request the Secretary-General of the League of Nations to summon a
                    Conference to consider the situation created thereby. Failing agreement to
                    maintain the Convention, each of the High Contracting Parties shall be
                    discharged from his obligations from the date on which the denunciation which
                    led to the summoning of this Conference shall take effect.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 19</p>
                <p>If, before the expiration of the period of five years mentioned in paragraph 1 of
                    Article 18, notifications should be addressed to the Secretary-General of the
                    League of Nations on behalf of one-third of the Members of the League of Nations
                    and of non-Member States to which the present Convention applies, informing him
                    that they desire the Convention to be revised, all the Members of the League of
                    Nations and all non-Member States to which the Convention <pb facs="0473"
                        n="345" xml:id="pg_345"/> applies agree to take part in any consultation
                    which may be held for this purpose.</p>
                <p>If the revision has taken place before the end of the fifth year from the date of
                    the coming into force of the present Convention, any Member of the League of
                    Nations or non-Member State who has not accepted the revised Convention shall
                    have the right to denounce the present Convention, without regard to the period
                    of five years provided for in paragraph 4 of Article 18. Such denunciation shall
                    take effect on the date on which the revised Convention comes into force.</p>
                <p>If the revision has taken place in the course of the fifth year from the date of
                    the coming into force of the present Convention, the period of denunciation
                    referred to in paragraph 1 of Article 18 will be prolonged by one year.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">annex to article</hi> 6</p>
                <p>In accordance with Article 6, paragraph 3, and with Section IV (<hi rend="italic"
                        >d</hi>) of the Protocol, each of the exceptions maintained in favour of the
                    countries mentioned below is only admitted under the terms of the present
                    Convention if the country concerned appends its signature<note n="*"
                        xml:id="d271fn92">Among the countries referred to in this Annex, the
                        following signed the Convention on November 8th, 1927: Germany, Austria,
                        Belgium, Great Britain, etc., Egypt, France, Hungary, Italy, Japan,
                        Luxemburg, Roumania and Czechoslovakia. [Footnote in the original.]</note>
                    thereto on this day’s date, and if, on that same date, the prohibition or
                    restriction which it seeks to maintain is still in force.</p>
                <p rend="center">I. <hi rend="italic">Exceptions agreed to under Paragraph 1</hi>
                </p>
                <table cols="3" rows="15">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Germany</cell>
                        <cell>Coal, coke, peat, lignite, briquettes</cell>
                        <cell>import and export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Scrap iron and scrap of other metals and alloys</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Austria</cell>
                        <cell>Scrap iron and scrap of other metals and alloys</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Belgium</cell>
                        <cell>Scrap iron and scrap of other metals and alloys</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Great Britain</cell>
                        <cell>Synthetic organic dyestuffs and colours or colouring matter containing
                            them, as well as organic intermediate products used in the manufacture
                            of such dyestuffs, colours and colouring matter</cell>
                        <cell>import</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>France</cell>
                        <cell>Scrap iron and scrap of other metals and alloys</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <pb facs="0474" n="346" xml:id="pg_346"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Hungary</cell>
                        <cell>Scrap iron and scrap of other metals and alloys</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Italy</cell>
                        <cell>Scrap iron and scrap of other metals and alloys</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Japan</cell>
                        <cell>Synthetic organic dyestuffs and colours or colouring matter containing
                            them, as well as organic intermediate products used in the manufacture
                            of such dyestuffs, colours and colouring matter</cell>
                        <cell>import</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Rice</cell>
                        <cell>import and export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Luxemburg</cell>
                        <cell>Scrap iron and scrap of other metals and alloys</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Roumania</cell>
                        <cell>Scrap iron and scrap of other metals and alloys</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Used machinery for industrial installations</cell>
                        <cell>import</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Czechoslovakia</cell>
                        <cell>Coal, coke, peat, lignite, briquettes</cell>
                        <cell>import and export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Scrap iron and scrap of other metals and alloys</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p rend="center">II. <hi rend="italic">Exceptions agreed to under Paragraph 2</hi>
                </p>
                <table cols="3" rows="8">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Egypt</cell>
                        <cell>Live-stock (exportation subject to licence)</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Eggs, during certain months of the year</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Organic fertilisers, including pigeon-manure, slaughter-house offal
                            and dried blood</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>United States of America</cell>
                        <cell>Helium gas</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Italy</cell>
                        <cell>Iron ores</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Corn</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Roumania</cell>
                        <cell>Ores of iron, copper and manganese</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Crude oil</cell>
                        <cell>export</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">In faith whereof</hi> the delegates have signed the present
                    Convention.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Done</hi> at <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1927-11-08">the eighth day of November, one
                            thousand nine hundred and twenty-seven</date>, in a single copy, which
                        shall be deposited <pb facs="0475" n="347" xml:id="pg_347"/> in the archives
                        of the Secretariat of the League of Nations, and of which authenticated
                        copies shall be delivered to all Members of the League of Nations and
                        non-Member States represented at the Conference.</dateline>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Germany</hi>
                        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Trendelenburg</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">United States of America</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>At the moment of signing the International Convention for the Abolition of
                        Import and Export Prohibitions and Restrictions, and the Protocol to the
                        Convention, I, the undersigned, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                        Plenipotentiary of the United States of America to Switzerland, duly
                        empowered to sign the said Convention and Protocol, declare, pursuant to
                        instructions from my Government, that the United States, in accordance with
                        Article 10 of the Convention, does not assume any obligation in respect of
                        the Philippine Islands and that I sign the Convention and Protocol subject
                        to the following reservations and conditions with respect to the United
                        States of America: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That prohibitions or restrictions designed to extend to exported
                                products the regime established within the country in respect of the
                                production of, trade in, and transport and consumption of such
                                products in domestic commerce are not prohibited by the said
                                Convention, provided, however, that such prohibitions or
                                restrictions shall not be applied in such a manner as to constitute
                                a means of arbitrary discrimination between foreign countries or a
                                disguised restriction on international trade.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That the said Convention affects neither the tariff systems nor
                                the treaty-making methods of the participating countries nor the
                                measures taken to ensure the application thereof, including measures
                                to counteract dumping, bounties, subsidies, unfair methods or acts
                                in foreign trade, undervaluation or discrimination.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hugh R. Wilson</hi>
                        <lb/>30-I-28</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austria</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">E. Pflügl</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Belgium</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Brunet</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">F. van Langenhove</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <pb facs="0476" n="348" xml:id="pg_348"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Great Britain and Northern Ireland and those Parts of the
                            British Empire which are not separate Members of the League of
                            Nations</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>I declare that my signature does not include any of His Britannic Majesty’s
                        colonies, protectorates or territories under suzerainty or mandate.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">S. J. Chapman</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">India</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Under the terms of Article 10 I declare that my signature does not include
                        the territories in India of any Prince or Chief under the suzerainty of His
                        Majesty.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Atul C. Chatterjee</hi>
                        <lb/>26-IV-28</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bulgaria</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Prof. Georges Danaïllow</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Chile</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>At the moment of signing the present Convention, the undersigned declares, on
                        behalf of his Government: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That he is fully convinced that Nos. 1 and 3 of Article 4 cannot
                                be invoked by the other High Contracting Parties to prohibit or
                                restrict the importation into their territories of Chilian nitrate
                                of soda, principally employed in agriculture.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That, in the Chilian Government’s opinion, the Convention affects
                                neither the tariff system nor the treaty-making methods of the
                                participating countries, nor the measures taken to ensure their
                                application, including the measures intended to counteract the
                                effects of dumping.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">E. Villegas</hi>
                        <lb/>14-VI-28</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Denmark</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Subject to reservation as regards Greenland.<note n="94" xml:id="d271fn94"
                            >Translation made by the Secretariat of the League of Nations.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Clan</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Egypt</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sadik. E. Henein</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Estonia</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">C. R. Pusta</hi>
                        <lb/>30-I-28</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Finland</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Rafael Erich</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <pb facs="0477" n="349" xml:id="pg_349"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">France</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>On signing the present Convention, France declares that by its acceptance it
                        does not intend to assume any obligation in regard to any of its Colonies,
                        Protectorates and territories under its suzerainty or mandate.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">D. Serruys</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hungary</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Baranyai Zoltán</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Di Nola</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Japan</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>In signing the International Convention for the Abolition of Import and
                        Export Prohibitions and Restrictions we, the undersigned, declare that the
                        provisions of Article 8 of the present Convention are in no way derogatory
                        to the acts of the Japanese judicial authorities in the application of
                        Japanese laws and decrees.<note n="95" xml:id="d271fn95">Translation made by
                            the Secretariat of the League of Nations.</note>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">N. Ito</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Tsushima</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Latvia</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Duzmans</hi>
                        <lb/>31-I-28</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Luxemburg</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Albert Calmes</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Nomoay</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Georg Wettstein</hi>
                        <lb/>31-I-28</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">The Netherlands</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Posthuma</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">De Graaff</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">F. M. Wibaut</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Poland</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">F. Sokal</hi>
                        <lb/>31-I-28</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Portugal</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Francisco de Calheiros e Menezes</hi>
                        <lb/>31–1–28</p>
                    <pb facs="0478" n="350" xml:id="pg_350"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Roumania</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="3" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">D. J. Gheorghiu</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">César Popescu</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>Subject to ratification by the Roumanian Government and Parliament.<note
                            n="96" xml:id="d271fn96">Translation made by the Secretariat of the
                            League of Nations.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Const. Fotitch</hi>
                        <lb/>24-I-28</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Siam</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charoon</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sweden</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Einar Hennings</hi>
                        <lb/>2-XII-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Switzerland</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. Stucki</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Czechoslovakia</hi>
                        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ibl</hi>
                        <lb/>8-XI-27</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Turkey</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Kemal</hi>
                        <lb/>14-V-28</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">protocol to the convention</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>At the moment of signing the Convention of to-day’s date for the Abolition of
                        Import and Export Prohibitions and Restrictions, the undersigned, duly
                        authorised, have agreed on the following provisions, which are intended to
                        ensure the application of the Convention:</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Section I—ad article</hi> 1</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The words “territories of the High Contracting Parties” employed in
                            the Convention refer only to territories to which it is made
                            applicable.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Should the Customs territory of any High Contracting Party include
                            territories which are not placed under his sovereignty, these
                            territories are also to be regarded as “territories” within the meaning
                            of the Convention.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>In view of the fact that within or immediately adjacent to the
                            territory of India there are areas or enclaves, small in extent and
                            population in comparison with such territory, and that these areas <pb
                                facs="0479" n="351" xml:id="pg_351"/> or enclaves form detached
                            portions or settlements of other parent States, and that it is
                            impracticable for administrative reasons to apply to them the provisions
                            of the Convention, it is agreed that these provisions shall not apply to
                            them.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>India, however, will apply as regards the areas or enclaves in question a
                        regime which will respect the principles of the Convention and facilitate
                        imports and exports as far as practicable, and will refrain from imposing in
                        regard to them any new measures of prohibition or restriction which would
                        not be authorised by the provisions of the Convention, unless there should
                        be no other means of ensuring the collection of customs and excise
                        duties.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Section II—ad article</hi> 2</p>
                    <p>As regards the application of Article 2, the obligation accepted by Canada
                        binds only the Federal Government and not the Provincial Governments, which,
                        under the Constitution, possess the power of prohibiting or restricting the
                        importation and exportation of certain products into or from their
                        territories.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Section III—ad article</hi> 4</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) <hi rend="italic">ad No. 4.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The protection of animals and plants against disease also refers to measures
                        taken to preserve them from degeneration or extinction and to measures taken
                        against harmful seeds, plants, parasites and animals.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) <hi rend="italic">ad No. 7.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The High Contracting Parties, although they have refrained from making any
                        reference to measures relating to “standard” products and definitions of
                        products, declare that this paragraph must be interpreted as in no way
                        interfering with the practice followed by certain countries of subjecting
                        the exportation of their products to certain conditions as to quality with
                        the object of preserving the reputation of those products and at the same
                        time of offering a guarantee to the foreign purchaser. They declare, on the
                        other hand, that they interpret the paragraph in question as prohibiting
                        recourse to any system of classifying or defining products which is employed
                        as an indirect means of restricting the importation of foreign products or
                        of subjecting importation to a regime of unfair discrimination.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) <hi rend="italic">ad No. 7.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The High Contracting Parties declare that prohibitions or restrictions the
                        sole object of which is either to prevent imported goods <pb facs="0480"
                            n="352" xml:id="pg_352"/> from escaping the payment of the customs
                        duties applicable thereto, or in exceptional cases to prevent the
                        importation of certain goods which would reduce the revenue from the duties
                        imposed on certain other goods, may only be established or maintained, if no
                        other effective means exist of securing the said revenue.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) <hi rend="italic">ad No. 7.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The High Contracting Parties declare that if, on account of the constitution
                        of certain States and the different methods of internal control which they
                        employ, it should prove impossible to secure complete similarity of
                        treatment between native and imported products, any such difference in
                        treatment must not have the object or effect of establishing an unfair
                        discrimination against the latter.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) <hi rend="italic">ad No. 8.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The High Contracting Parties declare that they have solely in view monopolies
                        each of which applies only to one or more specific articles.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Section IV</hi>—<hi rend="smallcaps">ad article</hi>
                        6</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) <hi rend="italic">ad No. 1.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The High Contracting Parties who have made the reservations referred to in
                        paragraph 1 of Article 6 declare that they do not regard their acceptance of
                        the provisions of Article 18, paragraph 3, as an undertaking on their part
                        that the circumstances which compelled them to make these reservations will
                        have ceased to exist at the end of three years, but as entitling any High
                        Contracting Party to resume his freedom of action if, in the event of these
                        circumstances not having changed within the said period, he considered that
                        his economic conditions were detrimentally affected by the maintenance of
                        any of the prohibitions or restrictions to which the aforesaid reservations
                        refer.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) <hi rend="italic">ad No. 2.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>By allowing the exceptions referred to in Article 6, paragraph 2, the High
                        Contracting Parties have not intended to give perpetual recognition to their
                        existence, but merely to indicate that the necessity of abolishing these
                        exceptions is not so imperative, in view of their slight importance in
                        international trade.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) <hi rend="italic">ad No. 2.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The High Contracting Parties declare that, by accepting in the case of
                        Roumania, in consideration of her exceptional situation of fact and of law,
                        the reservation concerning crude oil in accordance with Article 6, paragraph
                        2, they have not in any way agreed to measures of prohibition or restriction
                        for this product, which they regard as being of very great importance for
                        the world market. The High Contracting <pb facs="0481" n="353"
                            xml:id="pg_353"/> Parties feel confident that, as soon as circumstances
                        allow her to do so, Roumania herself, acting in the spirit of the preceding
                        paragraph (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) above, will abolish this prohibition,
                        and, in the meantime, that she will take into account the interests of the
                        neighbouring contracting countries.</p>
                    <p>The Roumanian Delegation fully associates itself with this dec laration.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) <hi rend="italic">ad No. 4.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">(i) <hi rend="italic">Scope of the Provision</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>As regards paragraph 4, it is understood that any claims for exceptions which
                        may be put forward after the date of the present Convention shall refer only
                        to prohibitions or restrictions in force on that same date.</p>
                    <p rend="center">(ii) <hi rend="italic">Procedure</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Any High Contracting Party may make known by a communication addressed
                            to the Secretary-General of the League of Nations any prohibitions or
                            restrictions which he desires to be able to maintain in virtue of
                            paragraphs 1 and 2 of Article 6. Such communication must reach the
                            Secretary-General before February 1st, 1928. It shall state the
                            conditions, if any, on which the High Contracting Party in question
                            would be prepared to abandon such prohibitions or restrictions.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>As soon as possible after February 1st, 1928, the Secretary-General of
                            the League of Nations shall notify the High Contracting Parties of all
                            applications which he has received under the preceding paragraph.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Any High Contracting Party wishing to make observations on any
                            applications so communicated may forward such observations to the
                            Secretary-General of the League of Nations not later than May 1st, 1928.
                            As soon as possible after that date, the Secretary-General will inform
                            the High Contracting Parties of all observations received.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Any applications and observations made by the High Contracting Parties
                            shall be examined at the meeting provided for in Article <hi
                                rend="italic">17</hi> of the Convention.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Section V—ad article</hi> 7</p>
                    <p>The expression “trade of the High Contracting Parties” signifies the trade of
                        their territories to which the Convention applies.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Section VI</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Prohibitions or restrictions applying to prison made goods are not within the
                        scope of the Convention.</p>
                    <pb facs="0482" n="354" xml:id="pg_354"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Section VII</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Should any prohibitions or restrictions be imposed within the limits laid
                        down by the Convention, the High Contracting Parties shall strictly adhere
                        to the following provisions as regards licences: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The conditions to be fulfilled and the formalities to be observed
                                in order to obtain licences shall be brought immediately in the
                                clearest and most definite form to the notice of the public;</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The method of issue of the certificates of licences shall be as
                                simple and stable as possible;</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The examination of applications and the issue of licences to the
                                applicants shall be carried out with the least possible
                                delay;</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The system or [<hi rend="italic">of</hi>] issuing licenses shall
                                be such as to prevent the traffic in licences. With this object,
                                licences, when issued to individuals, shall state the name of the
                                holder and shall not be capable of being used by any other
                                person.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>As regards the allocation of quotas, the High Contracting Parties, without
                        pronouncing upon the method to be adopted, consider that an equitable
                        allocation of such quotas is one of the essential conditions for the
                        equitable treatment of international trade.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">In faith whereof</hi> the Plenipotentiaries have signed
                        the present Protocol.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Done</hi> at Geneva the eighth day of November, one
                        thousand nine hundred and twenty-seven, in a single copy, which shall be
                        deposited in the archives of the Secretariat of the League of Nations, and
                        of which authenticated copies shall be delivered to all Members of the
                        League of Nations and non-Member States represented at the Conference.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Germany</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. Trendelenburg</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">United States of America</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hugh R. Wilson</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austria</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">E. Pflügl</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Belgium</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Brunet</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">F. van Langenhove</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Great Britain and Northern Ireland, and those Parts of the
                            British Empire which are not separate Members of the League of
                            Nations</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>I declare that my signature does not include any of His Britannic Majesty’s
                        colonies, protectorates or territories under suzerainty or mandate.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">S. J. Chapman</hi>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0483" n="355" xml:id="pg_355"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">India</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Under the terms of Article 10 of the Convention I declare that my signature
                        does not include the territories in India of any Prince or Chief under
                        Suzerainty of His Majesty</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Atul C. Chatterjee</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bulgaria</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Prof. Georges Danaïllow</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Chile</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">E. Villegas</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Denmark</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Subject to reservation as regards Greenland.<note n="97" xml:id="d271fn97"
                            >Translation made by the Secretariat of the League of Nations.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Clan</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Egypt</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sadik. E. Henein</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Estonia</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">C. R. Pusta</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Finland</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Rafael Erich</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">France</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Subject to the reservations made on signing the Convention.<note n="97"
                            xml:id="d271fn91">Translation made by the Secretariat of the League of
                            Nations.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">D. Serruys</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hungary</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Baranyai Zoltán</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Di Nola</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Japan</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Subject to the reservations made on signing the Convention.<note n="97"
                            xml:id="d271fn90">Translation made by the Secretariat of the League of
                            Nations.</note>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">N. Ito</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Tsushima</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Latvia</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Duzmans</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Luxemburg</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Albert Calmes</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Norway</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Georg Wettstein</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">The Netherlands</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Posthuma</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">De Graaff</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">F. M. Wibaut</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Poland</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">F. Sokal</hi>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0484" n="356" xml:id="pg_356"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Portugal</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Francisco de Calheiros e Menezes</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Roumania</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="3" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">D. J. Gheorghiu</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">César Popescu</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>Subject to ratification by the Roumanian Government and Parliament.<note
                            n="98" xml:id="d271fn98">Translation made by the Secretariat of the
                            League of Nations.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Const. Fotitch</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Siam</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charoon</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sweden</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Einar Hennings</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Switzerland</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. Stucki</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Czechoslovakia</hi>
                        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ibl</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Turkey</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Kemal</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Annexed Declaration</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The delegations of France, Greece, Hungary, Italy, Portugal, the Kingdom of
                        the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes and Switzerland, present at the International
                        Conference for the Abolition of Import and Export Prohibitions and
                        Restrictions, desire to place it on record that, though they have abstained,
                        in the desire not to place any obstacle in the way of the success of the
                        Conference and not to raise between the participating States a controversy
                        on a question of principle which could lead to no definite conclusion, they
                        are nevertheless fully convinced that the prohibition of viticultural
                        products cannot be justified on the ground of the provisions of Article 4,
                        No. 4, of the Convention.</p>
                    <p>Geneva, November 8th, 1927.</p>
                    <table cols="2" rows="8">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">France</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">D. Serruys</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Greece</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Vassili Dendramis</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Hungary</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Baranyai Zoltán</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Di Nola</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Portugal</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">F. de Calheiros e Menezes</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Const. Fotitch</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Switzerland</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">W. Stucki</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Chile</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>The Government of the Chilian Republic accedes to the Declaration annexed to
                        the Convention and, like the delegations of France, Greece, Hungary, Italy,
                        Portugal, the Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes and Switzerland, it
                        is convinced that the prohibition of viticultural products cannot be
                        justified on the ground of the provisions of Article 4, No. 4, of the
                            Convention.<note n="98" xml:id="d271fn89">Translation made by the
                            Secretariat of the League of Nations.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">E. Villegas</hi>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0485" n="357" xml:id="pg_357"/>
                    <p rend="center">SUPPLEMENTARY AGREEMENT</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">to the convention of november 8th, 1927, for the
                            abolition of import and export prohibitions and restrictions</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The President of the German Reich; the President of the United States of
                        America; the President of the Austrian Federal Republic; His Majesty the
                        King of the Belgians; His Majesty the King of Great Britain and Ireland and
                        of the British Dominions Beyond the Seas, Emperor of India; His Majesty the
                        King of the Bulgarians; the President of the Chilian Republic; His Majesty
                        the King of Denmark; His Majesty the King of Egypt; the President of the
                        Estonian Republic; the President of the Republic of Finland; the President
                        of the French Republic; His Serene Highness the Governor of Hungary; His
                        Majesty the King of Italy; His Majesty the Emperor of Japan; the President
                        of the Latvian Republic; Her Royal Highness the Grand Duchess of Luxemburg;
                        His Majesty the King of Norway; Her Majesty the Queen of the Netherlands;
                        the President of the Polish Republic; the President of the Portuguese
                        Republic; His Majesty the King of Roumania; His Majesty the King of the
                        Serbs, Croats and Slovenes; His Majesty the King of Siam; His Majesty the
                        King of Sweden; the Swiss Federal Council; the President of the Czechoslovak
                        Republic; the President of the Turkish Republic.</p>
                    <p>Having regard to the Convention signed at Geneva on November 8th, 1927, for
                        the Abolition of Import and Export Prohibitions and Restrictions;</p>
                    <p>Having regard to the provisions of Article 17 of the said Convention;</p>
                    <p>Have appointed as their Plenipotentiaries for the meeting provided for in the
                        said Article, namely:</p>
                    <p>[Here follows list of names of plenipotentiaries.]</p>
                    <p>Who, having communicated their full powers, found in good and due form, have
                        agreed on the following provisions, intended to supplement the provisions of
                        the aforesaid Convention, of which they shall form an integral part.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article A</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Annex to Article 6 of the Convention of November 8th, 1927, is
                        supplemented as follows for the benefit of the countries named
                        hereafter:</p>
                    <p rend="center">Exceptions agreed to under Paragraph 1</p>
                    <table cols="3" rows="7">
                        <row>
                            <cell>Bulgaria</cell>
                            <cell>Rose trees and roots and shoots</cell>
                            <cell>Export</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Chile</cell>
                            <cell>Scrap iron and scrap zinc</cell>
                            <cell>Export</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Mares</cell>
                            <cell>Export</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="0486" n="358" xml:id="pg_358"/>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Czechoslovakia</cell>
                            <cell>Hop shoots</cell>
                            <cell>Export</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Portugal</cell>
                            <cell>Fine wool</cell>
                            <cell>Export</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Cork in the raw state</cell>
                            <cell>Export</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Sweden</cell>
                            <cell>Scrap iron</cell>
                            <cell>Export</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">Exceptions agreed to under Paragraph 2</p>
                    <table cols="3" rows="4">
                        <row>
                            <cell>Czechoslovakia</cell>
                            <cell>Quartzite</cell>
                            <cell>Export</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Estonia</cell>
                            <cell>Platinum, precious stones, pearls and corals (in a rough state or
                                finished, loose or mounted)</cell>
                            <cell>Export</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Portugal</cell>
                            <cell>Pine resin</cell>
                            <cell>Export</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>United States</cell>
                            <cell>Helium gas</cell>
                            <cell>Export</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article B</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The High Contracting Parties agree that, in the event of the Agreements
                        concluded on this day’s date relating to the Exportation of Hides and Skins
                        and Bones not coming into force in default of the necessary ratifications,
                        each of them shall be authorised to submit subsequent requests for
                        exceptions which they were entitled to submit under the provisions of
                        Article 6 of the Convention and the annexed Protocol, and which they have
                        not submitted in view of the aforesaid Agreements.</p>
                    <p>Such requests for exception shall be addressed to the Secretary-General of
                        the League of Nations before September 30th, 1929, and shall be notified by
                        him to the High Contracting Parties before October 31st, 1929.</p>
                    <p>The High Contracting Parties undertake to meet without delay upon receiving
                        an invitation from the Secretary-General in order to examine the requests
                        for exceptions referred to above.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article C</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The High Contracting Parties agree that the Convention in order to be brought
                        into force, must have secured either ratification as provided for in Article
                        15 or accession as provided for in Article 16 of the said Convention on
                        behalf of at least eighteen Members of the League of Nations or non-Member
                        States.</p>
                    <p>The ratifications must be deposited before September 30th, 1929.</p>
                    <p>Each of the High Contracting Parties shall have the right to inform the
                        Secretary-General of the League of Nations at the moment of the deposit of
                        his ratification or of the notification of his accession that he makes the
                        entry into force of the Convention, in so far as he is concerned,
                        conditional on ratification or accession on behalf of certain <pb
                            facs="0487" n="359" xml:id="pg_359"/> countries, without, however, being
                        entitled to specify countries other than those named below: <list>
                            <item>Austria</item>
                            <item>Czechoslovakia</item>
                            <item>France</item>
                            <item>Germany</item>
                            <item>Great Britain</item>
                            <item>Hungary</item>
                            <item>Italy</item>
                            <item>Japan</item>
                            <item>Poland</item>
                            <item>Roumania</item>
                            <item>Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes</item>
                            <item>Switzerland</item>
                            <item>Turkey</item>
                            <item>United States of America</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Secretary-General of the League of Nations shall immediately inform each
                        of the High Contracting Parties of each ratification or accession received
                        and of any observations by which it may be accompanied in conformity with
                        the preceding paragraph.</p>
                    <p>On October 31st, 1929, the Secretary-General of the League of Nations shall
                        notify all the Members of the League and non-Member States on behalf of
                        which the Convention has been signed or acceded to under Article 16 of the
                        Convention of the ratifications deposited and accessions notified before
                        September 30th, 1929.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article D</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>If it appears from the communication of the Secretary-General of the League
                        of Nations, which is referred to in the last paragraph of the preceding
                        Article, that the conditions required in virtue of the first three
                        paragraphs of the said Article and of the annexed Protocol have been
                        fulfilled by September 30th, 1929, the Convention shall come into force on
                        January 1st, 1930.</p>
                    <p>In the contrary event, the procedure laid down in the last paragraph of
                        Article 17 of the Convention shall be followed.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">In faith whereof</hi> the above-mentioned
                        Plenipotentiaries have signed the present Agreement.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Done</hi> at Geneva on the eleventh day of July, one
                        thousand nine hundred and twenty-eight, in a single copy, which shall be
                        deposited in the archives of the Secretariat of the League of Nations;
                        certified true copies shall be forwarded to all the Members of the League of
                        Nations and all the non-Member States represented at the Conference.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Germany</hi>
                        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ernst Trendelenburg</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">United States of America</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hugh R. Wilson</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austria</hi>
                        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Richard Schuller</hi>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0488" n="360" xml:id="pg_360"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Belgium</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Brunet</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">F. van Langenhove</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Great Britain and Northern Ireland and all parts of the
                            British Empire which are not separate Members of the League of
                            Nations</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>I declare that my signature does not include any of His Britannic Majesty’s
                        Colonies, Protectorates or territories under suzerainty or mandate.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">S. J. Chapman</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">India</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">H. A. F. Lindsay</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bulgaria</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>On signing the present Supplementary Agreement, Bulgaria declares that it
                        shall be ratified and put into force as soon as the national currency shall
                        be re-established in gold.<note n="2" xml:id="d271fn2">Translation made by
                            the Secretariat of the League of Nations.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">D. Mikoff</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Chile</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Tomás Ramirez Frias</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Denmark</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Clan</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">William Borberg</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Egypt</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sadik E. Henein</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Estonia</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Schmidt</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Finland</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Rudolf Holsti</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Gunnar Kihlman</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">France</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>On signing the present Supplementary Agreement France declares that by its
                        acceptance it does not intend to assume any obligation in regard to any of
                        its Colonies, Protectorates and territories under its suzerainty or
                            mandate.<note n="2" xml:id="d271fn88">Translation made by the
                            Secretariat of the League of Nations.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">D. Serruys</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hungary</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Nickl</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Di Nola</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">P. Troise</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Japan</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ito</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Tsushima</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <pb facs="0489" n="361" xml:id="pg_361"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Latvia</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Duzmans</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Luxemburg</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Albert Calmes</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Norway</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gunnar Jahn</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Netherlands</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="3" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Posthuma</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">F. M. Wibaut</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">S. de Graaff</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Poland</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">François Dolezal</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Portugal</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">A. d’Oliveira</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">F. de Calheiros e Menezes</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Roumania</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="3" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Antoniade</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">D. T. Gheorghiu</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Cesar Popesco</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="3" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Const. Fotitch</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Georges Curcin</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Siam</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charoon</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sweden</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Einar modig</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Switzerland</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. Stucki</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Czechoslovakia</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ibl</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Turkey</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Subject to reservation as regards Article B.<note n="3" xml:id="d271fn3"
                            >Translation made by the Secretariat of the League of Nations.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hassan</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">protocol to the supplementary agreement</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>At the moment of proceeding to the signature of the Supplementary Agreement
                        to the International Convention for the Abolition of Import and Export
                        Prohibitions and Restrictions signed on this day’s date, the undersigned,
                        duly authorised, have agreed on the following provisions, which are intended
                        to ensure the application of the Supplementary Agreement:</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Section I</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The High Contracting Parties declare that, in the text of the Supplementary
                        Agreement of this day’s date, the expression “the Convention” <pb
                            facs="0490" n="362" xml:id="pg_362"/> shall be taken to mean both the
                        International Convention for the Abolition of Import and Export Prohibitions
                        and Restrictions dated November 8th, 1927, and the Supplementary Agreement
                        of this day’s date.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Section II</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ad Article A.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Cork in the raw state, in respect of which an exception has been
                            allowed for Portugal, does not include scrap cork, or cork in
                            agglomerated form, in shavings, or in sheets.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Although the exceptions set out in Article A, like those appearing in
                            the Annex to Article 6 of the Convention, have been allowed on the
                            condition that the countries benefiting thereby shall sign the present
                            Supplementary Agreement on the day of the general signature, it has
                            appeared equitable to grant an extension of time up to August 31st,
                            1928, inclusive, to Bulgaria, Portugal and the United States of
                            America.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>As regards the exception of hop shoots which has been agreed to in
                            favour of Czechoslovakia under paragraph 1 of Article 6 of the
                            Convention, the High Contracting Parties declare that their consent has
                            been given in return for the written undertaking entered into by the
                            Czechoslovak delegation to allow the free export of this product to all
                            countries which now or in the future guarantee Czechoslovakia by
                            legislative or contractual measures the protection of the appellation of
                            origin of Czechoslovak hops.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Section III</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ad Article B.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The High Contracting Parties agree to recognise in the case of Italy the
                        application of the provision of the Protocol to the International Agreement
                        relating to the Exportation of Bones (Section 1, <hi rend="italic">ad</hi>
                        Article 1 (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)), in the event of the said Agreement
                        coming into force.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Section IV</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ad Article C.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Owing to the position of the United States in consequence of a short
                            Session of Congress in the year 1928–29, the High Contracting Parties
                            agree that, if the ratification of the United States has been asked for
                            under paragraph 3 of Article C and has not been deposited by September
                            30th, 1929, the Convention shall come into force on January 1st, 1930,
                            provided that all the other countries on which the entry into force of
                            the Convention depends and the total number of which would in this case
                            be reduced to seventeen shall have notified the Secretary-General of the
                            League of Nations of their ratifications or accessions before September
                            30th, 1929, and provided no objection <pb facs="0491" n="363"
                                xml:id="pg_363"/> is raised before November 15th, 1929, by any of
                            the countries which, at the time of the deposit of their ratification or
                            accession, made the entry into force of the Convention, in so far as
                            they were concerned conditional upon the ratification or accession of
                            the United States. If any objection is raised, the last paragraph of
                            Article 17 of the Convention shall apply.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The High Contracting Parties declare that, in drawing up the list of
                            countries which appears in Article C, they have been chiefly guided by
                            the interdependence of certain interests emphasised in the course of the
                            proceedings of the Conference.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>They have thought it unnecessary to mention countries the inclusion of which
                        would be justified only by the importance of economic interests or
                        considerations of geographical situation.</p>
                    <p>If they have not mentioned certain countries, it is because those countries
                        at present impose no prohibitions of any importance. The High Contracting
                        Parties think they can rely upon their ratification or adhesion.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">In faith whereof</hi> the above-mentioned
                        plenipotentiaries have signed the present Protocol.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Done</hi> at Geneva on the eleventh day of July, one
                        thousand nine hundred and twenty-eight, in a single copy, which shall be
                        deposited in the archives of the Secretariat of the League of Nations;
                        certified true copies shall be forwarded to all the Members of the League of
                        Nations and to all the non-Member States represented at the Conference.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Germany</hi>
                        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ernst Trendelenburg</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">United States of America</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hugh R. Wilson</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austria</hi>
                        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Richard Schuller</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Belgium</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Brunet</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">F. van Langenhove</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Great Britain and Northern Ireland and all parts of the
                            British Empire which are not separate Members of the League of
                            Nations</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>I declare that my signature does not include any of His Britannic Majesty’s
                        Colonies, Protectorates or territories under suzerainty or mandate.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">S. J. Chapman</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">India</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">H. A. F. Lindsay</hi>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0492" n="364" xml:id="pg_364"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bulgaria</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">D. Mikoff</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Subject to the reservation made on signing the Supplementary Agreement.<note
                            n="5" xml:id="d271fn5">Translation made by the Secretariat of the League
                            of Nations.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Chile</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Tomás Ramirez Frias</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Denmark</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Clan</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">William Borberg</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Egypt</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sadik E. Henein</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Estonia</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Schmidt</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Finland</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Rudolf Holsti</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Gunnar Kihlman</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">France</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Subject to the reservations made on signing the Supplementary Agreement.<note
                            n="5" xml:id="d271fn4">Translation made by the Secretariat of the League
                            of Nations.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">D. Serruys</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hungary</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Nickl</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Di Nola</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">P. Troise</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Japan</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">N. Ito</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Tsushima</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Latvia</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="3" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Duzmans</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Luxemburg</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Albert Calmes</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Norway</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gunnar Jahn</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Netherlands</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="3" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Posthuma</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">F. M. Wibaut</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">S. de Graaff</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Poland</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">François Dolezal</hi>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0493" n="365" xml:id="pg_365"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Portugal</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">A. d’Oliveira</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">F. de Calheiros e Menezes</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Roumania</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="3" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Antoniade</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">D. T. Gheorghiu</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Cesar Popesco</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Const. Fotitch</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Georges Curcin</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Siam</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charoon</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sweden</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Einar Modig</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Switzerland</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. Stucki</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Czechoslovakia</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ibl</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Turkey</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Subject to reservation as regards Article B.<note n="6" xml:id="d271fn6"
                            >Translation made by the Secretariat of the League of Nations.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hassan</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Annexed Declaration</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Austrian, German and Hungarian delegations, in accepting in favour of
                        Czechoslovakia the exception of <hi rend="italic">quartzite</hi> under
                        paragraph 2 of Article 6 of the Convention, declare that their consent has
                        only been given in return for an undertaking on the part of Czechoslovakia
                        to maintain, as long as the Convention remains in force, the export quotas
                        and conditions provided for in special treaties or arrangements. <table
                            cols="2" rows="4">
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Germany</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>Dr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ernst Trendelenburg</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Austria</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. Richard Schuller</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Hungary</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Nigel</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Czechoslovakia</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Ibl</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <postscript>
                    <p>[The Senate resolution of September 19, 1929, giving advice and consent to
                        the ratification of the convention and protocol of November 8, 1927 and the
                        supplementary agreement and protocol of July 11, 1928, contained the
                        following reservation:</p>
                    <p>“It is understood that the provision of Section VI of the Protocol to the
                        Convention, excepting from the scope of the Convention prohibitions or
                        restrictions applying to prison made goods, includes goods the product of
                        forced or slave labor however employed.”]</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
