<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-07-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="320" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d320">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">572.F1/224</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Minister in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Harrison</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-07-31"><hi rend="italic">July 31,
                                1928</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 74</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: During the International Radio Conference
                            held in Washington from October 4 to November 25, 1927,<note n="86" xml:id="d320fn86">For radiotelegraph convention, see <ref target="frus1927v01#pg_288"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1927, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p.
                                    288</ref>. For proceedings of the conference, see S. Ex. Doc. B,
                                70th Cong., 1st sess., p. 77.</note> a Special Committee was
                            organized to consider what action should be taken with respect to the
                            report drawn up at Cortina d’Ampezzo, Italy, in 1926, by the “Committee
                            for the Study of Code Language”, provided for by the International
                            Telegraph Conference held at Paris in 1925.<note n="87" xml:id="d320fn87">See <ref target="frus1925v01#pg_287"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1925, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 287</ref> ff.</note></p>
                        <p>At its fourth plenary session the International Radio Conference adopted
                            the following resolution: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <list>
                                    <item>“1. The Washington Conference is not qualified to deal
                                        with the question of code language previously studied by the
                                        Committee of Cortina d’Ampezzo;</item>
                                    <item>“2. In view of the provisions of Article 15 of the
                                        International Telegraph Convention of St. Petersburg<note n="88" xml:id="d320fn88">Signed July 10/22, 1875; League
                                            of Nations Treaty Series, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">lvii</hi>, p. 213.</note> and the reservation
                                        formulated by some telegraph administrations not represented
                                        at Washington, the Committee constituted by the
                                        Radiotelegraph Conference can not transform itself into an
                                        International Telegraph Conference to deal with the question
                                        of code language.</item>
                                </list>
                                <p>“Because the solution to be given to the proposals of the Cortina
                                    Committee is of an urgent character, the recommendation is
                                    expressed that the next International Telegraph Conference,
                                    which is to meet at Brussels in 1930, be advanced in accordance
                                    with the rules of Paragraph 88 of the International Telegraph
                                    Regulations (Paris, 1925),<note n="89" xml:id="d320fn89"><hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 201.</note> and be held in
                                    1928, it being understood that only the question of code
                                    language shall be treated there.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <pb facs="0584" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/>
                        <p>As the French Government is charged with the handling of matters relating
                            to the International Telegraph Union this Government advised the French
                            Government of the action taken on the subject at the Washington
                            Conference and the French Government, through the International Bureau
                            of the Telegraph Union at Berne, requested members of the Union to
                            advise the French Government and the International Bureau whether they
                            desired that the Brussels Conference be advanced from 1930 to 1928.</p>
                        <p>The American Minister at Berne reported on April 23, 1928,<note n="91" xml:id="d320fn91">Not printed.</note> that he had been advised by
                            the International Bureau that the necessary ten countries had requested
                            that the Brussels Conference be held in 1928. The Minister at Berne
                            further stated, on April 28, 1928,<note n="91" xml:id="d320fn90">Not
                                printed.</note> that it was believed that the Conference at Brussels
                            would be convened in September or October next.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador of Belgium at this Capital, in a note dated July 18,
                                1928,<note n="91" xml:id="d320fn93">Not printed.</note> stated that
                            the Conference would be held at Brussels beginning September 10, 1928,
                            and on behalf of his Government extended an invitation to this
                            Government to send representatives to the Conference.</p>
                        <p>As the Conference to be held at Brussels will consider the report of the
                            Special Committee drawn up at Cortina d’Ampezzo in 1926, dealing with
                            the question of the use of code language and the related question of the
                            rates to be charged in connection with the use of code language,
                            American concerns engaged in export and import business will be
                            seriously affected by the results of the Conference. This is
                            particularly true since some of the proposals involve the raising of
                            rates for the handling of telegrams. It was believed, therefore, that it
                            would be highly desirable for the United States to participate in the
                            Conference and, accordingly, the invitation issued by the Belgian
                            Government was accepted.<note n="91" xml:id="d320fn94">Not
                                printed.</note></p>
                        <p>The Department recommended to the President that the American delegation
                            consist of yourself as chairman, Mr. John Goldhammer, vice president of
                            the Commercial Cable Company, and Mr. Charles Henry Shedd, Department
                            Manager for Swift and Company, Chicago.<note n="91" xml:id="d320fn95">Not printed.</note> The President replied on July 26, 1928,<note n="91" xml:id="d320fn96">Not printed.</note> and stated that he
                            approved the appointment of the persons named as the American
                            representatives to the Brussels Conference.</p>
                        <p>It is expected that the other representatives will be accompanied by Mr.
                            William B. Vallance, of this Department, Lieutenant E. M. Webster,
                            United States Coast Guard, Major William F. Friedman, War Department and
                            Mr. Harry F. Coulter, Department of Commerce, as technical advisors, Mr.
                            Fernand L. J. Dumont as translator <pb facs="0585" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/> and possibly four clerical assistants. The
                            delegation probably will sail from New York on August 25, 1928, and
                            should arrive in Brussels in sufficient time to confer with you before
                            the Conference is convened.</p>
                        <p>You are instructed to proceed to Brussels and you should arrange the
                            departure from your post so that you may arrive at Brussels not later
                            than September 8, 1928. You will, of course, be allowed your
                            transportation expenses and subsistence at the rate of fifteen dollars
                            per day for the time that you are away from your post in connection with
                            this Conference.</p>
                        <p>For your information the Department encloses a copy of Documents of the
                            Committee on the Study of Code Language; a translation of the final
                            report of that Committee; a copy of a report by Major William F.
                            Friedman entitled “Report on the history of the use of Codes and Code
                            Language, the International Telegraph Regulations pertaining thereto,
                            and the bearing of this history on the Cortina Report”; a copy of the
                            Stenographic Report of the Hearing on July 25, 1928, regarding the
                            Cortina report and a copy of a letter dated June 29, 1928, and a
                            questionnaire which was sent to a number of the large users of the
                            telegraph, cable and radio communication facilities.<note n="92" xml:id="d320fn92">Enclosures not printed.</note> The report of the
                            Cortina Committee constitutes the agenda for the Conference.</p>
                        <p>Specific instructions to govern the American delegation at the Conference
                            will be prepared and sent to you as soon as possible.</p>
                        <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">W. R.
                                    Castle</hi>, Jr.</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>