<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Minister in Honduras (
                    (Summerlin))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1928v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d585</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">585</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1928-08-30T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1928-08-30T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-08-30T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-08-30T12:00:00-05:00" n="585"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d585">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">714.1515/800: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Minister in Honduras</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Summerlin</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-08-30T13:00:00-04:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 30, 1928—1 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>81. From the tenor and tone of the latest note from the Honduran Government
                    transmitted in your 103, August 23, 9 a.m., the Department is satisfied that no
                    useful purpose will be served by pursuing this correspondence further, at least
                    until, as the result of your further <pb facs="0902" n="774" xml:id="pg_774"/>
                    conversations with the Honduran authorities you report a change in their present
                    attitude, and the Department does not, therefore, contemplate making any reply
                    to this communication. For your personal information and guidance in informal
                    conversation however the Department desires to make the following observations: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The Department of course gave more than the “slightest examination” to
                            the Convention which established the Central American Tribunal before
                            submitting the arbitration proposal to Honduras and Guatemala. This
                            proposal was made only after a careful and conscientious study of the
                            Convention as the result of which the Department concluded that the
                            Tribunal is competent to function in this matter, and after considering
                            the arguments presented by Honduras the Department finds no reason to
                            change its conclusion.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>With reference to that part of the note of the Honduran Government
                            which refers to the arbitration proposal made by Mr. Davis at Cuyamel on
                            April 23, Mr. Davis states that he did not suggest either formally or
                            informally that either the agreement to arbitrate announced at
                            Washington in 1923 by representatives of both Governments at the Central
                            American Conference, or the 1914 Treaty should form the basis of the
                            proposed arbitration. The fact that he proposed arbitration by an
                            arbitrator or “arbitral board” bears out this conclusion. A perusal of
                            Mr. Davis’ proposal shows that while reference is made to the
                            announcement made in 1923 this reference was included merely to show
                            that both countries had shown a desire to arbitrate the controversy. The
                            Department’s proposal of June 4 is, therefore, simply an amplification
                            of Mr. Davis’ proposal and suggested that the existing Mixed Commission
                            should draw up a protocol of arbitration, which this Commission had not
                            hitherto had the opportunity to do.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The suggestion that the Arbitral Tribunal should “take into
                            consideration political, economic and commercial interests of both
                            countries” cannot in the Department’s opinion be interpreted as barring
                            from consideration arguments based on historical grounds. The Department
                            has no reason to believe that Guatemala has so interpreted it. In any
                            case this point could and should be made perfectly clear in drawing up
                            the protocol of submission.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>In making the suggestion mentioned the Department had no reason to
                            believe that the consideration by the Arbitral Tribunal of the
                            political, economic and commercial factors involved would in any way
                            weaken the case of Honduras since the Department understands that that
                            country has strongly established interests of this nature in the
                            disputed territory. Moreover, the Department was confident that the
                            submission of the question to arbitration on these bases would be
                            equally fair to both countries and offer the best way to a practicable
                            solution.</item>
                        <pb facs="0903" n="775" xml:id="pg_775"/>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>The Department is much concerned at the continued refusal by Honduras
                            to submit this question to arbitration on the bases already accepted by
                            Guatemala. Honduras has insistently claimed that Guatemala has from time
                            to time penetrated the disputed territory and through gradual
                            encroachment has established illegal control in a considerable section
                            of that territory. If this claim is true it should be apparent to
                            Honduras that leaving the situation in its present unsatisfactory state
                            would open the way to further penetration by Guatemala in the disputed
                            area. The proposed arbitration offers Honduras an opportunity to end the
                            situation to which she objects, and to establish her claims in the
                            disputed area. It appears to the Department that Honduras in declining
                            to accept the proposal is assuming the responsibility for the
                            continuance of this situation.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>The Department also desires you to submit your personal views as to
                            the reasons prompting the Honduran Government’s refusal to accept the
                            Department’s suggestion and the possibility that this suggestion may
                            ultimately be accepted either after the elections or by another
                            administration.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>In your conversations with the Honduran authorities please also bear
                            in mind the considerations set forth in the Department’s telegram No.
                            65, July 20, 7 p.m. and in the memorandum accompanying the Department’s
                            instruction No. 272, dated July 24.<note n="52" xml:id="d585fn52"
                                >Instruction No. 272 and accompanying memorandum not printed;
                                substance of the memorandum was transmitted to the Minister in
                                Honduras in Department’s telegram No. 65, July 20, 7 p.m., <ref
                                    target="#pg_755">p. 755</ref>.</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Castle</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
