<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-01-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-01-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="685" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d685">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">196.6/1070</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Senate Bill No. 2945, 70th Congress, First
                                Session</hi><note n="18" xml:id="d685fn18">Introduced in the Senate
                                by Mr. La Follette, Jan. 27 (calendar day, Jan. 31), 1928; read
                                twice and referred to the Committee on Commerce.</note></head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1928-01-27">undated</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p rend="flushleft">A <hi rend="smallcaps">Bill</hi> relating to the payment
                            of advance wages and allotments in respect of seamen on foreign vessels,
                            and making further provision for carrying out the purposes of the
                            Seamen’s Act, approved March 4, 1915.<note n="19" xml:id="d685fn19">38
                                Stat. 1164.</note></p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Be it enacted by the Senate and House of
                                Representatives of the United States of America in Congress
                                assembled</hi>, That the first paragraph of paragraph (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) of section 10 of the Act entitled “An Act to
                            remove certain burdens on the American Merchant Marine and encourage <pb facs="0959" n="831" xml:id="pg_831"/> the American foreign-carrying
                            trade, and for other purposes,” approved June 26, 1884, as amended, is
                            further amended to read as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) This section shall apply to payments
                                    of advance wages and allotments, in respect of seamen on foreign
                                    vessels, whether made within or without the United States or
                                    territory subject to the jurisdiction thereof, as well as to
                                    payments of advance wages and allotments in respect of seamen
                                    upon vessels of the United States; except that no criminal
                                    penalty under this section shall be imposed for a violation of
                                    this section in respect of a seaman upon a foreign vessel if
                                    such violation occurs outside the United States and territory
                                    subject to the jurisdiction thereof. The courts of the United
                                    States shall be open to seamen for suits for payment of wages,
                                    irrespective of whether the wages were earned upon a vessel of
                                    the United States or a foreign vessel, or within or without the
                                    United States or territory subject to the jurisdiction thereof,
                                    and in any such suit the provisions of this section shall be
                                    applicable. Any master, owner, consignee, or agent of any
                                    foreign vessel who violates the provisions of this section
                                    within the United States or territory subject to the
                                    jurisdiction thereof shall be liable to the same penalty to
                                    which the master, owner, or agent of a vessel of the United
                                    States would be liable for a similar violation.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>