<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-08-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-08-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="776" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d776">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">863.51 Relief Credits/149</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Economic Adviser</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Young</hi>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-08-16"><hi rend="italic">August 16,
                                1928</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The Austrian Minister called this morning to discuss the question of the
                            steps to be taken in further reference to the loan and debt settlement.
                                <pb facs="1041" n="913" xml:id="pg_913"/> He said that he had just
                            received a letter from Dr. Schüller, stating that the Austrian
                            Government confidently expects an early adjustment of the difficulties
                            with Italy which lead to the blocking by the latter of the loan
                            proposal. The Austrian Chancellor had, with great reluctance, deemed it
                            advisable to make a statement to the effect that the questions arising
                            in the Italian Tyrol are regarded by Austria as wholly of Italian
                            domestic concern. The Italian representative, who had just returned to
                            Vienna, had stated that Mussolini would change his attitude on the
                            Austrian loan. Mr. Prochnik gathered that a settlement of the Austrian
                            debt to Italy on the lines of the settlement made with the other
                            European creditors is likely within a very few weeks.</p>
                        <p>The Minister stated that the Austrian Government had assured the European
                            creditors other than Italy that it would make no settlement with Italy
                            on terms more favorable to the latter than the terms embodied in the
                            settlement made with the other creditors.</p>
                        <p>The Minister then raised the question of further procedure in the United
                            States. He wondered whether it would not be better to drop the Bill
                            introduced at the last session of Congress and submit the definitive
                            terms of a debt settlement. He stated that the Austrian Government would
                            be prepared to sign with the United States a debt agreement embodying
                            terms analogous to those already agreed upon with the European creditors
                            (except Italy) with a clause added to the effect that, in the event of
                            granting more favorable terms to any other creditors, similar terms
                            would be granted to the United States. I stated that I would discuss
                            with the Treasury and others the question involved as to the tactics to
                            be followed, and talk with him further.</p>
                        <p>I told the Minister that, having in mind the likelihood of a definite
                            proposal by Austria as to settlement of the debt, it would be desirable
                            that the Austrian Government submit full data in support of any proposal
                            it might make. I recalled my previous requests for such data, and that
                            the data had not been supplied. I further stated that other Governments
                            in proposing debt settlements had furnished very full data. The Minister
                            said that he had written for data, but that his Government had
                            apparently not understood exactly what we wanted. He asked whether I
                            would send him quite informally a statement on the subject. I undertook
                            to consider the matter.</p>
                        <closer><signed>A[<hi rend="smallcaps">rthur</hi>] N. Y[<hi rend="smallcaps">oung</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>