<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Special Mission at Lausanne</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1923v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1006</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1006</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1923-06-01T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1923-06-01T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1923-06-01T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1923-06-01T16:00:00-05:00" n="1006"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1006">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">867.602 Ot 81/334: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Special Mission at Lausanne</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1923-06-01T17:00:00-04:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 1, 1923—5 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>161. Your telegram 380 of May 29. The Department’s attitude has been
                    substantially set forth in telegrams 22 of April 13 to Berne<note n="67"
                        xml:id="d1006fn67">See footnote 56, <ref target="#pg_1201">p.
                        1201</ref>.</note> and 105 of April 20 to Lausanne,<note n="68"
                        xml:id="d1006fn68">Not printed.</note> which you mention, and in 124 of May
                    4 to Lausanne. The Department has not received any copy of the concession as
                    ratified. The Department did not have any part in obtaining the concession and
                    believes that any conflict in claims should be settled by the interested parties
                    among themselves and with the Governments concerned. Should Pellé insist upon
                    bringing the matter up in the conference you may discreetly use the points
                    emphasized by the Department in its telegrams. You should avoid a direct offer
                    of arbitration, but stress the fact that this Government desires fair play and
                    reciprocal regard for valid rights and that its interest is in assuring equality
                    of opportunity.</p>
                <p>The representations by Ambassador Jusserand, described in my 113 of April
                        27,<note n="69" xml:id="d1006fn69">Not printed; see memorandum of a
                        conversation between the Secretary of State and the French Ambassador, Apr.
                        16, <ref target="#pg_1204">p. 1204</ref>.</note> have not been followed up,
                    and he has not presented to the Department any data concerning the French claims
                    which it is alleged are in conflict with the Chester concession. We wish to
                    avoid creating the impression that the issue is one to be settled between the
                    Governments of the United States and France. Your attitude in discouraging Pellé
                    from making a formal written communication is therefore approved. The
                    Department, however, would not wish to have you act in such a manner as to make
                    it possible for Pellé to say that you had kept him from informing <pb
                        facs="1339" n="1215" xml:id="pg_1215"/> you regarding French claims. It
                    would be helpful if you could informally and discreetly obtain any facts
                    regarding these claims.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hughes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
