<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1923-06-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1923-06-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="1021" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1021">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">211.31/31</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Venezuela</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Cook</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Caracas</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1923-06-11"><hi rend="italic">June 11,
                                1923</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received June 26.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 381</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to reply to the
                            Department’s written instruction No. 802 of May 29, 1923 (File No.
                            211.31/30), in regard to the Instrument of Ratification by the
                            Venezuelan Government of the Extradition Treaty between the United
                            States and Venezuela and additional article thereto.</p>
                        <p>I respectfully state that in accepting and transmitting to the Department
                            an Instrument which ratified only the Spanish text, I did not do so
                            inadvertently. Two officials of the Venezuelan Foreign Office (one, the
                            Chef du Protocol) brought the Instrument of Ratification to this
                            Legation to compare it with our Instrument of Ratification. At that time
                            I promptly called their attention to the fact that their Instrument was
                            only in Spanish, while ours incorporated both the English and Spanish
                            texts, and that my instructions required that the Instrument which I
                            should accept <pb facs="1379" n="1255" xml:id="pg_1255"/> for
                            transmission to Washington should incorporate both the English and
                            Spanish texts. These official representatives of the Venezuelan Foreign
                            Office assured me, however, that it was not their custom to incorporate
                            any other than the Spanish text and they cited as examples treaties with
                            Great Britain and with Italy. Moreover, on the day of going to the
                            Ministry for Foreign Affairs to exchange ratifications, I again
                            officially stated that the Instrument which the Venezuelan Government
                            was furnishing me should incorporate both the English and Spanish texts,
                            and they again, after a consultation in the Foreign Office, assured me
                            that it was not the practice of Venezuela to use other than the Spanish
                            text in the Instrument of Ratification.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to add that when conforming with the Department’s
                            instructions in returning today the Venezuelan ratification of the
                            Spanish text, to obtain in substitution therefor an instrument of
                            ratification by Venezuela incorporating the English as well as the
                            Spanish text, the Foreign Office again repeated the statement that it
                            was not their practice to include other than the Spanish text; and I had
                            to inform them that it was absolutely necessary that the Instrument of
                            Ratification contain both texts.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Willis C. Cook</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>