<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Great Britain ( (Harvey))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1923v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d152</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">152</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1923-03-21T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1923-03-21T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1923-03-21T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1923-03-21T17:00:00-05:00" n="152"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d152">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.01 M 31/152: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harvey</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1923-03-21T17:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 21, 1923—5 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>61. Reference your despatch No. 1748 of October 11, 1922, and to enclosed British
                    note of September 30,<note n="12" xml:id="d152fn12">
                        <ref target="frus1922v02#pg_304">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 304</ref> and <ref
                            target="frus1922v02#pg_330">330</ref>, respectively.</note> subject
                    African mandates. Please present to Lord Curzon a note as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“With reference to Your Lordship’s note of September 30, 1922, regarding
                            the British mandates for the administration of certain <pb facs="0353"
                                n="229" xml:id="pg_229"/> former German territories in tropical
                            Africa and the proposed treaties relative thereto, I have the honor to
                            inform Your Lordship that my Government, animated by the desire of
                            reaching an early agreement with the British Government in this matter,
                            and in view of the assurances contained in paragraph 5 of your note that
                            the British Government has not the slightest intention to discriminate
                            against United States nationals or institutions by subjecting their
                            operations to restrictions not equally applicable to British nationals
                            and institutions, is disposed to accept the wording proposed by the
                            British Government for Article 8 of the Mandate for East Africa and
                            Article 7 of the Mandates for Togoland and the Cameroons, which is
                            substantially similar to paragraph 1 of Article 2 of the Treaty between
                            the United States and Japan, regarding the former German Islands North
                            of the Equator,<note n="13" xml:id="d152fn13">
                                <ref target="frus1922v02#pg_600">
                                    <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 600</ref>.</note> without
                            making this acceptance subject to the insertion in the treaties of an
                            additional article.</p>
                        <p>It is understood, however, that such acquiescence in the proposals of the
                            British Government with regard to African Mandates in no way affects the
                            position heretofore taken by the Government of the United States with
                            regard to American missionary and educational institutions in
                            territories which may come under A mandates.</p>
                        <p>My Government regrets that, with regard to the preamble of the African
                            treaties, it is unable to concur in the proposal set forth in Paragraph
                            7 of Your Lordship’s note. However, the Government of the United States,
                            having in mind the position taken in Paragraph 5 of the British note of
                            October 2,<note n="14" xml:id="d152fn14">
                                <ref target="frus1922v02#pg_304">
                                    <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 304</ref>.</note> as to the
                            preamble for the treaty relating to the Palestine mandate, and the
                            desirability of making the treaties with Great Britain and the treaties
                            with France as to the African territories identical in form and
                            substance, is confident that the British Government will not find it
                            impossible to adopt the text proposed in a memorandum to the British
                            Ambassador of July 8, 1922,<note n="15" xml:id="d152fn15">
                                <ref target="frus1922v02#pg_322">
                                    <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 322</ref>.</note> which text is
                            substantially the same as that used in the French treaties which have
                            been recently signed.<note n="16" xml:id="d152fn16">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_8">pp. 8</ref>
                                ff.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>I have the honor to state further that my Government is willing to
                            proceed immediately to the signature of these proposed conventions, the
                            full texts of which are contained in the drafts transmitted
                            herewith.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>[Paraphrase.] You are requested to draw up texts of conventions, in which you
                    should follow draft contained in Department’s telegram of July 10,<note n="17"
                        xml:id="d152fn17">
                        <ref target="frus1922v02#pg_325">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 325</ref>.</note> altered as
                    follows:</p>
                <p>In article 1 of the treaty you should use the words “consents to”, and also add
                    the phrase “hereinafter called the mandated territory”.</p>
                <p>For article 7 of the mandates for Togoland and Cameroons, and for article 8 of
                    mandate for East Africa, you should employ wording suggested in British note of
                    September 30.</p>
                <pb facs="0354" n="230" xml:id="pg_230"/>
                <p>The Department is much gratified that negotiations with French Government have
                    reached satisfactory conclusion by signature on February 13 of treaties relating
                    to African territories under French mandate. There is well-founded expectation
                    also that in a few days an identical treaty will be signed at Brussels
                    respecting Belgian mandate in Africa.<note n="18" xml:id="d152fn18">
                        <ref target="frus1923v01#pg_433">Vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p.
                            433</ref>.</note> The Department hopes that as early as possible you
                    will proceed to signature of proposed British treaties. Requisite full powers
                    will be supplied to you by cable.</p>
                <p>In order to avoid possible errors in this instruction as transmitted, the Paris
                    Embassy has been asked to forward to you copies of English text of treaties with
                    France which you should compare with your own draft. Preamble of French treaties
                    should be particularly noted and followed in British treaties. [End
                    paraphrase.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hughes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
