<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1923-03-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1923-03-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="217" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d217">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">868.48/392</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The General Secretary, Near East Relief</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Vickrey</hi></persName>)
                                <hi rend="italic">to the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Phillips</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                        York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1923-03-08"><hi rend="italic">March 8,
                                1923</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received March 9.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Confirming our conversation of last
                            Saturday, I submit herewith a copy of the Report of Near East Relief
                            that has been presented to Congress for the calendar year 1922.<note n="4" xml:id="d217fn4">See S. Doc. No. 343, 67th Cong., 4th
                                sess.</note></p>
                        <p>Replying more specifically to the questions that were suggested in the
                            course of our conversation, I submit the following statements:</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Total Relief Disbursements since
                                1915:</hi></p>
                        <p>The total relief disbursements in the Near East as shown by page 11 of
                            the accompanying Auditor’s Report, were $60,890,194.75. This Auditor’s
                            Report of cash disbursements, however, does not include flour secured
                            through the U. S. Grain Corporation and the American Relief
                            Administration, valued at $12,800,000. Nor does it include certain other
                            contributions of clothing, commodities and medical supplies which would
                            bring the total of relief disbursements under the general direction of
                            Near East Relief in this area to December 31, 1922, to
                            $82,266,548.38.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">2. <hi rend="italic">Total Relief Disbursements for the
                                calendar year 1922:</hi></p>
                        <p>The relief disbursements for the calendar year 1922, as shown on page 10
                            of the accompanying Auditor’s Report, amounted to $11,649,695.32.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">3. <hi rend="italic">Emergency Relief:</hi></p>
                        <p>As to the proportion of the above disbursements that may be classified as
                            “emergency relief”, we might, without serious inaccuracy, call all of it
                            “emergency relief,” since even our orphanage and child welfare work was
                            originally caused, and during the past year has been greatly increased
                            by war, evacuations, deportations, fire and other disasters wholly
                            beyond the control of the helpless, and for the most part, innocent
                            victims.</p>
                        <p>In a more restricted sense however, of the phrase “emergency relief”, our
                            work for the past year will divide itself into two almost exactly equal
                            portions: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Our so-called normal orphanage or child welfare budget would
                                    not exceed $6,000,000.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The special emergency work resulting from the Smyrna fire and
                                    related disasters, the evacuation of the Cilician, Marmora and
                                    Black Sea ports, the feeding and care of refugees at Black Sea
                                    and Cilician ports and in transit <pb facs="0448" n="324" xml:id="pg_324"/> from Asia to Greece, the transfer of
                                    children from our orphanages in Anatolia to Greece and Northern
                                    Syria, and other emergency expenses, resulting from recent
                                    military and political changes in the Near East, account for the
                                    additional expenditures of the year 1922, amounting to
                                    $5,649,695.32.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">4. <hi rend="italic">Plans for immediate future—General
                                Relief:</hi></p>
                        <p>As to plans for the immediate future, we would like to be relieved
                            immediately of all responsibility in connection with adult refugee or
                            general relief work.</p>
                        <p>The emergency relief work of the past few months has practically absorbed
                            all of our reserve resources, in addition to the funds received in
                            response to the special emergency appeal. We have not the resources with
                            which to continue indefinitely, general refugee relief, and moreover,
                            feel that it is a burden that should be borne by the responsible
                            governments. We have at no time given relief to adult refugees if there
                            was any prospect of securing the necessary food or shelter from
                            government or other sources. Likewise, we have never given relief free
                            of charge if there was any possibility of providing work for the
                            destitute.</p>
                        <p>The situation, however, at Smyrna and on the islands of the Aegean,
                            immediately following the Smyrna fire and later among the refugees from
                            Anatolia, crowding into the Black Sea ports, Constantinople, the ports
                            of Cilicia and North Syria, were such as to make self-support wholly
                            impossible, and relief from the responsible government manifestly
                            impracticable. Under these circumstances, our relief workers, with their
                            organization covering the area for orphanage and child welfare work,
                            felt there was no alternative but to extend their operations to the
                            starving and the destitute, regardless of age or sex, though a
                            disproportionately large number of the refugees were women and
                            children.</p>
                        <p>As to the immediate future, we can possibly [, by] straining our
                            resources, continue to give general relief for another two or three
                            months, and as conditions are at present among the refugees in the Black
                            Sea ports, Constantinople, Aleppo and Northern Syria, we do not see how
                            we can refuse some general relief without practically pronouncing death
                            sentence upon unfortunate women and children, who, for the most part,
                            are innocent of any crime. We feel strongly, however, that this burden
                            should be shifted to responsible governments, and we will probably be
                            obliged soon to discontinue general relief from sheer lack of adequate
                            private resources.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">5. <hi rend="italic">Plans for immediate
                                future—Orphanage or Child Welfare Work:</hi></p>
                        <p>Our policy with reference to the continuation of orphanage or child
                            welfare work will, in part, depend upon the desires of our own
                            government.</p>
                        <pb facs="0449" n="325" xml:id="pg_325"/>
                        <p>We feel that we now have a constituency and organization throughout the
                            United States that will support us, if requested, in continuing our
                            child welfare program, which, for the immediate future may involve a
                            budget of approximately $6,000,000. per year, but decreasing gradually
                            each year as the children leave our institutions or through the
                            development of industrial relief, are brought to self support.</p>
                        <p>This child welfare work at present, in addition to the children in
                            refugee camps and concentration centers, includes 25,000 orphans who are
                            now being cared for in Russian Armenia, all Armenians, and most of them
                            of Turkish origin; 15,000 in Greece, of whom at least 10,000 are
                            Armenians and therefore not properly a charge upon the Greek Government;
                            11,000 in Syria, of whom 10,000 are Armenians; and probably less than
                            5,000 in Northwest Persia, Constantinople and elsewhere.</p>
                        <p>So far as the financial burden is concerned, we can probably, with the
                            continued cooperation of the American public, provide the necessary
                            support for the orphanage and child welfare work if desired.</p>
                        <p>Most of these children, so far as we can ascertain, have no known
                            responsible relative upon whom their support can be thrown, and most of
                            them have no legal claim upon any government that is sufficiently
                            sympathetic to accept responsibility for their support.</p>
                        <p>Aside from the humanitarian phases of this child welfare work, we see in
                            it a strategic opportunity for the expression of American altruism and
                            sending forth from these orphanages ambassadors of good will, industrial
                            progress and international cooperation.</p>
                        <p>While willing to continue, for the present, the care of such orphans as
                            cannot be returned to their relatives or otherwise provided for, we
                            earnestly request that we be relieved at the earliest possible moment of
                            all responsibility in connection with adult relief work.</p>
                        <p>May we respectfully suggest, that it may be desirable to draw two rather
                            clear lines of demarkation in any analysis or proposed solution of the
                            relief problem in the Near East?</p>
                        <p>1. A distinction may be made between, <list>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>the refugees, Greek and Armenian, who are now in Greece, under
                                    friendly sympathetic government, and who at the present time are
                                    being cared for by the American Red Cross with some government
                                    cooperation, and</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>the refugees, who, though driven or removed from their homes
                                    in Anatolia, are still on Turkish or Asiatic soil. These latter
                                    dare not return to their former homes; they cannot as yet find
                                    passage, welcome or a satisfactory haven in a foreign land. They
                                    are under the military control of a confessedly unfriendly
                                    government. They are legally citizens of Turkey, but practically
                                    without a country to <pb facs="0450" n="326" xml:id="pg_326"/>
                                    which they can look for sympathetic cooperation in regaining
                                    self-support.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>It is evident that more time will be required to re-establish the second
                            class, who are still on Asiatic soil, than will be required for the
                            former on European soil, and it may be necessary to continue general
                            relief in Asia for a somewhat longer period than will be necessary in
                            Greece. In both areas however, general relief from America should be
                            discontinued as early as practicable without unnecessary loss of
                            life.</p>
                        <p>2. A distinction may be drawn between, <list>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>general or adult relief, and</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>orphanage or child welfare work.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Adult relief should certainly be discontinued as soon as any provision
                            can be made for government aid or work to provide the necessities of
                            life. Likewise the support of Greek or other orphans, who are on their
                            native soil and under sympathetic government, should be transferred as
                            rapidly as possible to the responsible government.</p>
                        <p>In the case of those orphans, however, who were born or whose parents
                            were born in the Ottoman empire, and who therefore have no legal or
                            national claim upon any friendly government, it does not seem equally
                            practicable to throw their support upon foreign governments that have
                            generously given them a haven of refuge, but which have no legal
                            responsibility for providing for their continued work.</p>
                        <p>We assume that any statement given to the public concerning the
                            discontinuance or the transfer of responsibility for refugee work in
                            Greece, will be so phrased as not to jeopardize the continued financial
                            support of such orphanage, child welfare and other apparently necessary
                            phases of relief work in the Near East as may be approved by the
                            Department, and possibly the statement can be made to assist materially
                            such work.</p>
                        <p>We will be very glad to cooperate with the Department in any further
                            consideration of solutions of this problem.</p>
                        <p>Respectfulty yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles V.
                            Vickrey</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>