<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-12-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-12-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="455" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d455">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">894.51 Or 4/2</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Economic Adviser of the Department
                                of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Young</hi>)<note n="52" xml:id="d455fn52">Notation on margin: “Approved by the Sec. and read
                                to Messrs. Ailes and Roberts of Riggs Bank, agents of Nat. City Co.,
                                Dec. 16, 3 p.m. by Mr. Mac-Murray and me. A. N.
                            Y[oung].”</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-12-16"><hi rend="italic">December 16,
                                    1922</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Proposed statement to be made to representatives of the
                            National City Company regarding the proposed loan of $20,000,000 to the
                            Oriental Development Company.</p>
                        <p>The Department of State has given careful consideration to the proposal
                            that bonds of the Oriental Development Company of Tokio should be
                            floated in the United States for the purpose of financing development
                            work in which this company is interested in regions outside of Japan,
                            namely, in the South Sea Islands, Singapore, Straits Settlements,
                            Manchuria and Mongolia.</p>
                        <pb facs="0628" n="504" xml:id="pg_504"/>
                        <p>In other connections the attention of the Department has been drawn from
                            time to time to instances in which the proceeds of foreign loans floated
                            in the United States have been utilized in third countries with the
                            effect of promoting the activities of competitors of American
                            enterprises. It has been suggested that the employment of American funds
                            in this manner is prejudicial to American enterprises that have invested
                            their capital and are employing their energies in operations in foreign
                            countries and that besides it tends to restrict opportunities for the
                            further investment of American capital.</p>
                        <p>This Department could only regret the employment of funds derived from
                            loans floated in the United States in such manner as to prejudice
                            legitimate American enterprises in parts of the world other than the
                            country which (or whose nationals) may borrow in the United States, and
                            accordingly feels that it should scrutinize as carefully as possible
                            loan projects laid before it that may present such a situation.</p>
                        <p>In view of the foregoing, and after careful consideration, the Department
                            regrets that it is unable to view with favor the loan in question.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>