<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1923-06-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1923-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="462" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d462">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/4325</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The President of the Riggs National Bank</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Milton E.
                                Ailes</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Second Assistant
                                Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Harrison</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1923-06-07"><hi rend="italic">June 7,
                                1923</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: Referring again to the
                            matter of the South Manchurian Railway loan, I have the honor to enclose
                            the original of a letter which I have just received from Mr. R. M.
                            Byrnes, Vice President of the National City Company of New York,<note n="58" xml:id="d462fn58">Not printed.</note> in which he reviews the
                            history of previous negotiations at the State Department for the purpose
                            of setting the record straight, as Mr. Byrnes sees it.</p>
                        <p>On page four of Mr. Byrnes’ letter he states that he clearly understands
                            from the letter of the Department of State addressed to me under date of
                            May 23 that the Department does not regard with favor such a loan, but,
                            before giving a final reply to that effect to the National City
                            Company’s representative in Japan, the National City Company would
                            appreciate it if I would inquire from the State Department whether, if a
                            loan were issued in this country, and all the proceeds thereof were
                            spent for equipment and materials in this country, the State Department
                            would have any objection to its negotiation and flotation.</p>
                        <p>Will you kindly consider the matter from the standpoint of the
                            expenditure of the entire proceeds of the proposed loan in the United
                            States, and let me know as conveniently soon as possible if the State
                                <pb facs="0633" n="509" xml:id="pg_509"/> Department would be
                            favorable or unfavorable to such loan on such condition?</p>
                        <p>Very respectfully,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">M. E. Ailes</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>