<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1923-11-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1923-11-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="684" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d684">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">816.51/341</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                Senator <persName type="to">Couzens</persName></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1923-11-28"><hi rend="italic">November 28,
                                    1923</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Senator Couzens</hi>: I have received your
                            letter of November 15, 1923, in which you again discuss the question of
                            the Salvador loan and express the opinion that difficulties might arise
                            between this Government and the Governments of other countries, should
                            our public officers be generally engaged in deciding matters of
                            arbitration between foreign Governments and citizens of the United
                            States.</p>
                        <p>It has been customary in contracts between American companies and Latin
                            American Governments to provide for the arbitration of controversies by
                            disinterested third parties, sometimes specified in the contract and
                            sometimes left to be selected by common accord when the occasion might
                            arise. In some instances the contract has designated an official of the
                            United States Government as arbiter. In the case of the Salvador loan
                            both parties desired to provide in the contract a definite procedure for
                            the settlement of disputes. They therefore expressed a desire that the
                            Secretary of State should consent to use his good offices in arranging
                            for the submission of such disputes to arbitration by the Chief Justice
                            of the United States, if he were able and willing to act, or by some
                            other member of the federal judiciary who might be in a position to
                            undertake the duties of arbiter. Since it was manifestly desirable, in
                            the interest of American citizens who might <pb facs="0952" n="828" xml:id="pg_828"/> buy the bonds, that there should be an appropriate
                            manner of deciding controversies between them and the Government of
                            Salvador, I consented that the Secretary of State should use his good
                            offices in the manner requested. I felt that a provision for the
                            settlement by arbitration of controversies which would otherwise be
                            likely to resolve themselves into diplomatic claims would be most
                            helpful in preventing friction between this Government and the
                            Governments of other countries.</p>
                        <p>The stipulations of the exchange of notes with Salvador of course imply
                            no obligation whatever upon the Chief Justice, or upon any other federal
                            judge, to act as arbiter if he does not consider it convenient and
                            proper to do so. I do not consider it probable that the members of our
                            federal judiciary will be called upon to act very frequently in
                            questions arising under this loan agreement, because it is not, of
                            course, contemplated that any dispute should be submitted to a member of
                            our federal judiciary for arbitration until it has proved incapable of
                            settlement by direct negotiations between the interested parties. If,
                            however, a situation did arise where the services of one of our judges
                            were invoked, I should imagine that he would deem it a public service to
                            assist in bringing about a settlement of a controversy which might
                            otherwise injuriously affect not only the interests of some thousands of
                            American citizens, but also the friendly relations between this
                            Government and one of its neighbors.</p>
                        <p>In conclusion permit me to express my appreciation of your courtesy in
                            communicating to me your views upon this matter. I hope that the
                            information furnished above will prove useful to you, and I shall be
                            very glad to furnish any further information which you may desire.</p>
                        <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles E.
                            Hughes</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>