<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-12-18T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-12-18T06:00:00-05:00" n="778" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d778">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">867.602/28: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Special Mission at
                                        Lausanne</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Lausanne</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-12-18T12:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">December
                                            18, 1922—noon</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received 12:34
                                    p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                            <p>121. Ismet informed Child last night during conversation which had
                                been prompted by representations received from some other source
                                that:</p>
                            <p>No economic concessions in Turkey were being given to foreigners in
                                return for political concessions at Lausanne. The principle of the
                                Open Door meets with entire approval from the Turkish
                                Government.</p>
                            <p>Bidders offering the best terms would be awarded contracts for
                                carrying out public development or construction projects in Turkey,
                                and no consideration would be given to nationality of the bidder or
                                to other matters not related to the welfare of the enterprise. Ismet
                                observed that if, for example, Americans or Italians or others
                                should present their bids before the definite award of a contract
                                for the building of a port at Mersina, the concern which offered the
                                best terms would be granted the contract, although for months the
                                French had been negotiating for a concession and their proposals
                                were under discussion at the moment in Angora.</p>
                            <p>Ismet made explicit declaration that the Turkish Government was not
                                trading its petroleum properties or interests to any foreign <pb facs="1052" n="928" xml:id="pg_928"/> power in return for
                                equivalent concessions to Turkey in drafting the treaty at
                                Lausanne.</p>
                            <closer><hi rend="smallcaps">Am</hi>[<hi rend="smallcaps">erican</hi>]
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mission</hi></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>