<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Special Mission at Lausanne to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1923v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d943</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">943</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1923-07-25T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1923-07-25T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recLrhH3r9BIhQsGe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046582"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Extradition</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1923-07-25T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1923-07-25T06:00:00-05:00" n="943"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d943">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.672/132: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Special Mission at Lausanne</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lausanne</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1923-07-25T12:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 25, 1923—noon</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received 1:14 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>555. Referring to Mission’s 554. Ismet suggested during conversation last night
                    that we might sign a general treaty and an extradition treaty, supplementing
                    them by an exchange of letters in which the question of claims could be treated
                    separately. It had been <pb facs="1245" n="1121" xml:id="pg_1121"/> already
                    suggested to us informally by one of the Turkish experts that the most promising
                    course would be to sign the treaties, upon an understanding that they will be
                    presented to our respective Governments for ratification only if accompanied by
                    a claims convention to be negotiated within the next few weeks. This would give
                    undesirable emphasis to the economic aspect of our negotiations; but if the
                    understanding on the claims convention can be made binding, and if it is
                    perfectly clear that the treaties actually signed are accepted conditionally,
                    our legal position should remain unimpaired. It is possible that eventually we
                    may have presented to us the alternative of consenting to an arrangement of this
                    sort or abandoning our present tentative agreements. In case the Department
                    might be ultimately disposed to assent to some such proposal there are two
                    possible ways to give it effect: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>By an article in the treaty declaring that the question of claims is
                            reserved for a subsequent convention which will accompany the general
                            treaty when submitted for ratification.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>By omitting the claims article from the treaty but supplementing it by
                            an exchange of notes expressly setting forth the understanding that an
                            agreement on claims must be reached before the treaty will be submitted
                            for ratification.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>We request instructions.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
