<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-03-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-03-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="16" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d16">
                    <head>16. Memorandum From the Director of the International Cooperation
                        Administration (<persName corresp="#p_HJB1" type="from">Hollister</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d16fn1">Source:
                            Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, Administration Series, <persName corresp="#p_HHCJ1">Hoover, Herbert, Jr.</persName> Top
                            Secret.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-03-14"><hi rend="italic">March 14,
                            1956</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Henry Cabot Lodge</persName>’s
                            Memorandum to the President</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Answering your request of March 9th<note n="2" xml:id="d16fn2">Not found in
                            Department of State files.</note> that I give you a report in connection
                        with the President’s memorandum which enclosed Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Henry Cabot Lodge</persName>’s memorandum datelined
                        Paris, March 5th,<note n="3" xml:id="d16fn3"><ref target="#d15"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi></ref>.</note> I am enclosing [for] you
                            memoranda<note n="2" target="d16fn2">Not found in Department of State
                            files.</note> which have been submitted with respect to the various
                        parts of this report by different people in my organization.</p>
                    <p>Of course, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> has
                        raised points which are basic in the whole foreign aid program and have been
                        given a great deal of thought by me, as well as, I am sure, by my
                        predecessors in this work. Some of the issues raised cannot be settled
                        conclusively one way or another. Let me comment briefly on the five points
                        he has made.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item><p>The trouble with the “flashy” project is that, in general, it does
                                not stand the test of time, and if our effort is to be a
                                constructive one, the brief publicity achieved by the flashy project
                                may well be more than counteracted by the ultimate disappointment
                                when a project turns out to have been flashy and nothing else.</p>
                            <p>Of course, we have long since decided not to try to make a country
                                take something it does not want—what Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> refers to as the “Mother
                                Superior” attitude, but it seems to me we would be equally foolish
                                to spend a substantial amount of money to give a country something
                                it wants if it isn’t good for it.</p></item>
                        <pb facs="0104" n="72" xml:id="pg_72"/>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item><p>Obviously, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName>’s suggestion that we should be able to act quickly
                                is basic. I think we have demonstrated that we can act quickly when
                                an emergency arises. Examples have been given in the memoranda which
                                I enclose. It must be realized, however, that speed in embarking on
                                an expensive program, or one that involves some substantial policy
                                decision, can frequently do more harm than good.</p>
                            <p>In any organization, particularly government bureaucracy, one must be
                                continually alert to the elimination of red tape, and I think an
                                organization such as this, where communication, except by cable,
                                takes many days, we are always striving to improve our mission
                                personnel so that more discretion and authority can be given to the
                                field, and thus permit regular programs to go forward
                            faster.</p></item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>We, of course, are all agreed as to the desirability of authority for
                            long-term <hi rend="italic">projects</hi>. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> refers to five or six-year <hi rend="italic">programs</hi>. You will remember that I recommended
                            that the long-term authority be made applicable to programs as well as
                            projects.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>This suggestion deserves study. Remembering the ill-fated <gloss target="#t_UNRRA1">UNRRA</gloss>, and realizing the enormous
                            overhead percentage cost of the international organizations now
                            operating, I wonder whether we want to get into larger multilateral
                            programs under the United Nations unless there is some very definite
                            political advantage.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName>’s statement
                            here is indisputable, but it only covers a part of our program. Many of
                            the countries with which we are dealing achieved their independence a
                            good many years ago, and there is no relationship between our economic
                            aid and this achievement. It would seem to me that the thing to stress
                            is the fact that we have reached great heights through complete freedom
                            of all kinds, that we support it everywhere, and that one thing we have
                            demonstrated is that we are only too anxious not only to free, but to
                            assist countries which through the hazards of war have come under our
                            domination.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HJB1"><hi rend="strong">John B.
                                    Hollister</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>