<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-12-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-01-07T18:14:00-05:00" n="244" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d244">
                    <head>244. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>On March 5, <persName corresp="#p_FAS1">Arthur S. Flemming</persName> sent a
                        letter to United States importers of crude oil stating that when the Suez
                        crisis had ended, his office would have another look at the country’s crude
                        oil imports picture in order to determine if the national security was
                        substantially impaired by such imports. The letter asked each importing
                        company to submit an estimate of its imports planned for the 6-month period
                        immediately following the reopening of the Suez Canal or the Iraq Petroleum
                        Company pipeline, or both. On the basis of these estimates, the Office of
                        Defense Mobilization would determine whether the projected volume of imports
                        into United States Districts I–IV in the immediate post-Suez period would be
                        in line with permissible 1954 rations. If not, the office would request
                        revised estimates from the companies in an attempt to determine whether
                        Section 7 of the Trade Agreements Act should be applied to limit imports.
                        The letter also stated that in determining any action which might be taken
                        to limit oil imports into the United States, due consideration would be
                        given to using normal import patterns as a base period rather than emergency
                        diversions. (Department of State, Central Files, 411.006/3–857)</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>