<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-08-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-08-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="114" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d114">
                        <head>114. Note From the Director of the Policy Planning Staff (<persName corresp="#p_WPD_1">Wolfowitz</persName>) to Secretary of State
                                <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d114fn1">Source: Department of State,
                                Executive Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> Records,
                                Memoranda and Correspondence from the Director of the Policy
                                Planning Staff to the Secretary and Other Seventh Floor Principals:
                                Lot 89D149, <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> Chrons <gloss target="#t_PW_1">PW</gloss> Chrons to <gloss target="#t_SecS_1">Secy</gloss> AUG 1982. Confidential. <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>’s stamped initials appear
                                at the top of the memorandum. In the top right-hand corner of the
                                memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> wrote:
                                “Paul—An interesting paper—Pls organize a discussion of people
                                inside Gov’t (say 6 or 8, no more than 10) to spend an hour or two
                                with me on this—some time in the next month. G.”</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-08-27">August 27,
                                1982</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Mr. Secretary:</p>
                        <p>We received some very general guidance from <gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss> that you wanted a paper on <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> strategy for the Pacific. We have tried earlier to
                            develop an overall strategy just for East Asia. Even here, where our
                            Asia expert is not burdened with the concentration on a particular
                            bilateral relationship, that effort foundered on the difficulty of
                            looking at Asian policy as anything more than a series of bilateral, or
                            at most sub-regional, policies. There is a real question whether it
                            makes sense to look at Asia any other way, given among other things, the
                            deep differences that divide the region, the possible tensions between
                            such an effort and smaller regional groupings (such as <gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss>) that we are seeking to encourage,
                            and the advantages to the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> of
                            dealing with individual countries bilaterally rather than <hi rend="italic">en bloc</hi>.</p>
                        <pb facs="0487" n="418" xml:id="pg_418"/>
                        <p>The attached paper does not actually present a strategy for the Pacific,
                            with all of the necessary country detail. Nor does it present a plan for
                            a Pacific-wide institution (another subject that <gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss> thought you might be interested in). Rather, it
                            addresses the issue of whether either of these enterprises is worth
                            pursuing further.</p>
                        <p>My own feeling is that it does make sense to look at the region as a
                            whole, despite the arguments mentioned above and the unquestioned need
                            to pay primary attention to our rich and varied bilateral relationships.
                            We already have to do so in developing our military strategy. That is
                            paradoxical since the security issue is one subject on which it would be
                            pointless to try to organize a Pacific community. Nevertheless, the
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> military role underpins the
                            stability that is essential if the remarkable dynamism of the region is
                            to continue. Broadening our strategy to include a political and economic
                            dimension could: <list>
                                <label>1)</label>
                                <item>help to secure and strengthen our basic security role;</item>
                                <label>2)</label>
                                <item>expand our participation in the economic growth of the
                                    region;</item>
                                <label>3)</label>
                                <item>provide a useful complement to our European policy (and
                                    perhaps a bit of a nudge to the Europeans); and, finally,</item>
                                <label>4)</label>
                                <item>if skillfully managed, might help to overcome some of the
                                    sense in this country that our involvement in foreign affairs is
                                    increasingly nothing more than a formula for taking on the
                                    burden of other people’s problems.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Those are my hunches, but before proceeding further I would like to get
                            some more precise guidance from you—and from others in the
                            Department—about where we should be heading. Hopefully, the attached
                            paper can be a useful vehicle for that discussion.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WPD_1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Paul Wolfowitz</hi>
                                </persName><note n="2" xml:id="d114fn2"><persName corresp="#p_WPD_1">Wolfowitz</persName> signed “Paul” above his typed
                                    signature.</note>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <pb facs="0488" n="419" xml:id="pg_419"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline">
                                <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                            </note>
                            <head>Information Memorandum From the Director of the Policy Planning
                                Staff (<persName corresp="#p_WPD_1">Wolfowitz</persName>) to
                                Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName><note n="3" xml:id="d114fn3">Confidential.
                                    Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RRS_1">Randolph</persName> on
                                    August 26; cleared by <persName corresp="#p_GJD_1">Glassman</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_AAP_1">Adams</persName> initialed the top of the memorandum and
                                    wrote “8/27.” A stamped notation in the top right-hand corner of
                                    the memorandum reads: “’82 AUG 27 P2:08.” Table III, “US Trade
                                    with East Asia, January to December 1981,” was not
                                found.</note></head>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian">undated</date></dateline>
                            <list type="subject">
                                <head>SUBJECT</head>
                                <item>US Posture Toward the Pacific Basin</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">Introduction</p>
                            <p>In an article entitled “Illusions of Distance,”<note n="4" xml:id="d114fn4">Printed in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Affairs</hi>, Vol. 46, No. 2 (January 1968), pp.
                                    242–255.</note>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WAJ_1">Albert Wohlstetter</persName> once
                                cautioned against “mechanical regionalism:” <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“. . . Some (economic) unions might represent a gain; some
                                        surely would be a loss, particularly if their composition
                                        were determined solely on the basis of criteria as unrelated
                                        to economic efficiency as contiguity. They may be mainly
                                        rival exporters of the same commodities. . . . Neighborhood
                                        in international relations, as Jacob Viner has pointed out,
                                        has never guaranteed neighborly feelings, and often has
                                        prevented them. . . Indeed, one of the largest defects of
                                        regionalism in the postwar period has been a frequent
                                        neglect of the hard truths of differences in political
                                        interest inside regions and the varying bonds of interests
                                        with countries outside. Regionalism, which has seemed a
                                        halfway house between nationalism and a utopian
                                        universalism, has itself sometimes been a kind of utopia for
                                        hard-headed Realpolitikers. . .”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>Despite those cautions—but with them in mind—it is worth considering
                                whether <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> interests in the
                                Pacific might in some way be usefully served by considering the
                                region as a whole and developing a strategy for it. As a basis for
                                such a consideration, this paper considers: (1) what are US
                                interests in the Pacific region; (2) whether, and in what respects,
                                it is useful to look at the Pacific region as a whole; and (3)
                                whether the Pacific should receive increased emphasis in our overall
                                strategy and if so whether that is best done through existing
                                bilateral relationships or whether some broader organizational
                                arrangement would be useful.</p>
                            <pb facs="0489" n="420" xml:id="pg_420"/>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">I. The US in the Pacific</p>
                            <p>(A) <hi rend="italic">Dynamism of the Pacific Region</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>The Pacific Basin is an area of remarkable economic growth and
                                    dynamism. This is based in part on the region’s wealth of human
                                    and natural resources. It is also based on successful Asian
                                    adaptations of some of our most fundamental economic and
                                    political principles. This makes the Pacific region a showcase
                                    for key American values.</item>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>In recent years the Pacific area has witnessed the emergence
                                    of: <gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss>; economic dynamism
                                    among the <gloss target="#t_NICs_1">NICs</gloss>; Japan as a
                                    global economic power with growing international
                                    responsibilities; a somewhat more open China; a more activist
                                    Australia with major trade links to Japan and a substantially
                                    more powerful and growing Soviet presence. These developments
                                    increasingly engage major US interests.</item>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>US trade is shifting toward the Pacific. In 1981 US
                                    Asia-Pacific trade surpassed trade with all of Western Europe.
                                    If our key trading partners, Mexico and Canada (also Pacific
                                    nations) were included, this shift would appear even more
                                    pronounced (see Table II).<note n="5" xml:id="d114fn5">Not
                                        attached is Table II, “US Trade With Major Areas
                                        1981.”</note> In addition to major trade in consumer goods
                                    and machinery, the US relies on the Pacific for more than 90% of
                                    its natural rubber, and large amounts of imported wool, tin,
                                    meat, plywood, bauxite, sugar and oil. In the latter part of
                                    1981 Indonesia replaced Nigeria as our second largest source of
                                    oil, after Saudi Arabia. On the export side, the Pacific has now
                                    surpassed the <gloss target="#t_EEC_1">EEC</gloss> as our
                                    largest market for agricultural products (see Table IV).<note n="6" xml:id="d114fn6">Not attached is Table IV, “Rank of
                                        Country as Importer of Commodity from the US in
                                        1981.”</note></item>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>The Pacific is an area of comparative stability at present,
                                    despite deep antagonisms and substantial military imbalances.
                                    These latter factors also make it prone to instability, should
                                    current political balances be disrupted.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>(B) <hi rend="italic">US Interests and Objectives in the Pacific
                                    Region</hi></p>
                            <p>The US is the only major Pacific power, in a comprehensive sense
                                (political/military/economic). It enjoys significant trade and
                                positive political relationships with most nations of the region (an
                                advantage not shared by the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>).
                                US interests and objectives in the region should include: <list>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>Strengthening of formal and informal security cooperation
                                        with and among friendly states, so as to create a favorable
                                        security <pb facs="0490" n="421" xml:id="pg_421"/>
                                        environment in which the enormous potential of the region
                                        can be realized. In this context, should the US encourage:
                                        (1) greater reliance on American power; (2) greater
                                        self-reliance; (3) greater reliance on other regional powers
                                        (such as Australia and Japan); or (4) some combination of
                                        these strategies?</item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>Promotion of communication/cooperation among friendly
                                        states in the area (e.g., closer Japan-<gloss target="#t_ROK_1">ROK</gloss>, Japan-Australia, <gloss target="#t_ROK_1">ROK</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss>, Australia-<gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss>-Pacific Island ties) as a means of
                                        strengthening regional political stability.</item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>Strengthening economic ties with the growing economies of
                                        the region in a manner which will promote strong economies
                                        and the free trading system, counteract protectionist
                                        pressures, and create a strong market for US exports.</item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>Encouragement of economic growth in regional <gloss target="#t_LDC_1">LDC</gloss>s through balanced
                                        multilateral and bilateral aid, and private sector
                                        involvement (e.g., investment and technology
                                        transfer).</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>(C) <hi rend="italic">Other Possible Objectives of a Comprehensive
                                    “Pacific” Approach</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>Develop a comprehensive global policy, more effectively
                                    linking friends and interests in the Atlantic with those in the
                                    Pacific.</item>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>Develop a coherent focus of US interest outside Europe, as a
                                    means of developing visible alternatives to a Euro-centered
                                    strategy.</item>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>Improve US export competitiveness through the development of a
                                    more effective working relationship between the US Government
                                    and business communities.</item>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>Develop an initiative which would add a new sense of dynamism
                                    and direction to US foreign policy, and help to build and
                                    maintain the domestic consensus needed to maintain a strong US
                                    role in the Pacific.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">II. US Policy: What Basis for a Regional
                                Focus?</p>
                            <p>(A) <hi rend="italic">Pacific Rim vs. Pacific-Oriented
                                Countries</hi></p>
                            <p>(1) Location on the Pacific Rim alone does not create shared
                                interests. The core of a Pacific policy should focus on these states
                                with a common Pacific orientation. Such an orientation clearly
                                exists among the US, Japan, Australia/New Zealand, <gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss>, South Korea, Taiwan, Hong
                                Kong, and (on a smaller scale) the Pacific Island states. Common
                                interests include market-oriented economic systems, significant
                                trade, investment and capital flows, a greater or lesser adherence
                                to Western democratic values, and shared (explicit or implicit)
                                security concerns.</p>
                            <pb facs="0491" n="422" xml:id="pg_422"/>
                            <p>(2) Canada and Mexico, though not fundamentally oriented toward the
                                Pacific, are also Pacific nations. As our #1 and #3 trading partners
                                Canada and Mexico, when taken together with East Asia, constitute
                                the top three areas of US economic interest, aside from Western
                                Europe.</p>
                            <p>(3) The Pacific countries of Latin America are seeking to expand
                                their Pacific ties, and therefore should not be excluded from a
                                Pacific policy. For the moment, however, their hemispheric
                                orientation suggests that they relate to US Pacific-wide interests
                                in only a secondary sense.</p>
                            <p>(4) The Soviet Union at present relates to US and other Pacific-area
                                interests primarily—but very importantly—in the security area.<note n="7" xml:id="d114fn7">An unknown hand changed “related” to
                                    “relates.”</note> Our desire to encourage the constructive
                                integration of China into the world community suggests that China
                                should clearly be part of our Pacific policy. Chinese security
                                concerns and developmental objectives link it to the US and the
                                Pacific. The overlap of shared interests is only partial, however,
                                and systemic differences may, for the time being, preclude
                                integration of the <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> into a
                                broader Pacific community.</p>
                            <p>(B) <hi rend="italic">How Do US Interests Interact with Those of the
                                    Other Pacific Nations?</hi></p>
                            <p>(1) <hi rend="italic">Trade and Economic</hi></p>
                            <p>There is considerable regional interdependence in trade flows. The
                                pattern, however, is asymmetrical, with domination by the US and
                                Japan. With the exception of the United States and Japan, whose
                                regional trade is only a fraction of their global trade, all market
                                economies in the Asia-Pacific region do over 50% of their trade
                                within the region. The importance of regional trade is greatest for
                                the <gloss target="#t_LDC_1">LDC</gloss>s. The <gloss target="#t_NICs_1">NICs</gloss> fall in the middle, with heavy
                                regional trade, but a declining fraction of the total as they seek
                                to expand into wider global markets. (See Table I.)<note n="8" xml:id="d114fn8">Not attached is Table I, “Pacific Bain
                                    Intraregional Trade (1981 data).”</note></p>
                            <p>Significant interdependence also exists in regional investment and
                                aid flows, with the US and Japan again as the principal
                                investors/donors (this is despite the fact that US investment in
                                East Asia—$22 billion in 1981—is only about 11% of total overseas
                                investment, and US bilateral aid to the region is significantly less
                                than it was 10 years ago).</p>
                            <p>(2) <hi rend="italic">Political Interests</hi></p>
                            <p>A sense of political community is at best incipient. Outside of
                                already-existing groupings, the region is divided by distance,
                                ideology (in the case of the Communist states), history (e.g.,
                                profound historic animosities toward Japan that affect relations
                                with Korea, China and <pb facs="0492" n="423" xml:id="pg_423"/> the
                                    <gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss>s), economic competition
                                (between the US and Japan and among several of the <gloss target="#t_NICs_1">NICs</gloss>), and aligned/non-aligned
                                distinctions. Nevertheless, shared political interests do exist.
                                Common security concerns underlie political and military ties with
                                the US and in some cases with each other. Growing trade ties serve
                                as a unifying as well as a diving force. Generally harmonious
                                relations with the US and an array of shared bilateral US interests
                                with nearly all Pacific nations is a further thread which runs
                                throughout the Pacific Basin.</p>
                            <p>(3) <hi rend="italic">Security</hi></p>
                            <p>All states in the Pacific (with the exception of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, North Korea, and Indochina),
                                whether aligned or non-aligned, share a common interest in
                                preventing the growth of Soviet regional power. To a greater or
                                lesser extent, all states (outside of the South Pacific and the
                                    <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> itself) share a common fear
                                of China. On both counts, the US is looked to as the explicit or
                                implicit guarantor of regional security. This reliance could
                                increase if Sino-Soviet tensions were to significantly lessen. With
                                US support providing the underpinning of Pacific area stability,
                                from a security perspective the region should be looked at as a
                                whole.</p>
                            <p>In the wake of the US withdrawal from Vietnam and declining global
                                capabilities during the Carter Administration, deep and persistent
                                doubts remain in Asia concerning the reliability of US defense
                                commitments. While progress has been made during the past two years
                                in reassuring Asian friends and allies, continued efforts will be
                                required to demonstrate our sustained role as a Pacific power.</p>
                            <p>At present we have no pressing security problems in the Pacific. We
                                should not forget, however, that this is the area where the US has
                                fought its two major post World War II conflicts. This is no
                                accident. Though quiescent, there are great military imbalances in
                                the region. The local balance favors the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, the <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss>, Vietnam
                                and North Korea, leading to a heavy dependence on the US for a
                                countervailing role. That dependence is aggravated by the rapid
                                increase of Soviet military forces in the area. The substantial
                                stability of recent years is in part a product of tensions and
                                conflicts among actual or potentially hostile countries. This
                                situation makes the US continually vulnerable to the possibility of
                                a Sino-Soviet rapprochement, and individual national susceptible to
                                political or military intimidation.<note n="9" xml:id="d114fn9">An
                                    unknown hand changed “national” to “nations.”</note></p>
                            <p>(C) <hi rend="italic">Has the US Given Sufficient Attention to Its
                                    Pacific Ties?</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>Growing US interests in the Pacific Basin, both economic and
                                    political, may require greater US engagement.</item>
                                <pb facs="0493" n="424" xml:id="pg_424"/>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>While lacking the same ties of history and culture, our
                                    present level of Pacific involvement has grown to the point
                                    where it is arguably comparable to the Atlantic. We should
                                    consider, therefore, moving toward a policy which would place
                                    our Pacific and Atlantic relationships more on a par.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">III. Proposals for a “Pacific Community”
                                Mechanism</p>
                            <p>Over the past 15 years a number of proposals have been made for the
                                formation of a Pacific Basin-wide organization, to draw together the
                                threads of an incipient Pacific Community.</p>
                            <p>(A) <hi rend="italic">Structure</hi></p>
                            <p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>First officially articulated by the Japanese in 1967 with
                                        a proposal for a Pacific Free Trade Area (<gloss target="#t_PAFTA_1">PAFTA</gloss>). <gloss target="#t_PAFTA_1">PAFTA</gloss> was to function as an
                                        equivalent and counterweight to the <gloss target="#t_EEC_1">EEC</gloss>. This idea led to the initiation of a
                                        conference series, the Pacific Trade and Development
                                        Conference (<gloss target="#t_PAFTAD_1">PAFTAD</gloss>),
                                        which has included eleven meetings since 1968. Participants
                                        have been mostly academics and businessmen.</item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>Organization for Pacific Trade and Development (<gloss target="#t_OPTAD_1">OPTAD</gloss>) was proposed by the
                                        Conference as a successor concept to <gloss target="#t_PAFTA_1">PAFTA</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_OPTAD_1">OPTAD</gloss> would be modeled after
                                        the <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss>, and would
                                        include the five Pacific members of <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss>, the <gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss>s and South Korea, with
                                        special status for Taiwan, Hong Kong and the Pacific Island
                                        states. Its organization would consist of a secretariat in
                                        each member country with regional problems being dealt with
                                        on a task force basis.</item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>Other proposals for Pacific Basin cooperation include the
                                        formation of a private, non-governmental body with limited
                                        consultative functions, as a preliminary step toward an
                                            <gloss target="#t_OPTAD_1">OPTAD</gloss>-type
                                        structure.</item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>In 1978 Japan’s Prime Minister Ohira added new impetus to
                                        the discussion by publicly calling for a new Pacific area
                                        association. Further momentum was also given by the Canberra
                                        Pacific Community Seminar, held in Australia in September
                                        1980 pursuant to a joint communique by the Japanese and
                                        Australian governments.<note n="10" xml:id="d114fn10">Held
                                            at Australian National University, September 15–17,
                                            1980. In telegram 272163 to all East Asian and Pacific
                                            diplomatic posts and Ottawa, October 12, 1980, the
                                            Department transmitted the text distributed to the press
                                            in Canberra regarding the results of the conference.
                                            (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                            Electronic Telegrams, D800488–0163)</note> It also
                                        became clear in Canberra, however, that there existed
                                        substantial <gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss>
                                        opposition to the setting up of a Pacific-wide
                                        inter-governmental organization. The result was the
                                        establishment of a Pacific Cooperation Committee (<gloss target="#t_PCC_1">PCC</gloss>), which was to be a
                                        private, <pb facs="0494" n="425" xml:id="pg_425"/> informal
                                        body composed of 25 unofficial representatives of the
                                        countries attending the conference.</item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>On July 31 of this year South Korea’s President <persName corresp="#p_CDH_1">Chun Doo Hwan</persName> issued a
                                        call for a Pacific Basin Summit.<note n="11" xml:id="d114fn11">In telegram 8123 from Seoul, August 4,
                                            the Embassy discussed Chun’s proposal, outlining the
                                            five principles designed to aid in the creation of a
                                            “‘Great Pacific Age’,” noting: “The proposal remains
                                            vague, but the <gloss target="#t_ROK_1">ROKG</gloss>
                                            seems determined to pursue the idea despite the apparent
                                            lack of enthusiasm for it on the part of other potential
                                            participants.” (Department of State, Central Foreign
                                            Policy File, Electronic Telegrams,
                                        D820404–0008)</note></item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>(B) <hi rend="italic">Attitudes of Pacific Nations</hi></p>
                            <p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>Japan has historically been the strongest proponent of a
                                        Pacific Basin Community. (Japan has an important interest in
                                        regional stability and open markets, as its principal
                                        markets and sources of raw materials are in or pass through
                                        the region.)</item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>Significant support exists in Australia, on an unofficial
                                        basis (as demonstrated by <gloss target="#t_PM_1">PM</gloss>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_FM_2">Fraser</persName>’s backing for
                                        the 1980 Canberra Conference).</item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>South Korea can be presumed to be supportive.</item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item><gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss>, which is
                                        essential to any Pacific organization, is skeptical. The
                                            <gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss>s are concerned
                                        that: <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>the concept remains too unfocused to be of
                                                interest;</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>the United States and Japan will dominate any
                                                Pacific region organization;</item>
                                            <label>(3)</label>
                                            <item><gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss>’s
                                                non-aligned status will be compromised by great
                                                power involvement;</item>
                                            <label>(4)</label>
                                            <item><gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss> as an
                                                organization will be submerged or divided;</item>
                                            <label>(5)</label>
                                            <item>economic benefits may also entail political costs
                                                (in terms of sovereignty).</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>The US has taken a non-committal position. While offering
                                        passive support, we have been clearly unenthusiastic.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">IV. Possible US Strategies (Should We Support
                                a Pacific Mechanism?)</p>
                            <p>It should be considered whether a bilateral approach to regional
                                problems alone is sufficient. US interests are currently being
                                effectively served by bilateral diplomacy, but emerging regional
                                challenges—particularly in the fields of trade, investment, aid, and
                                resource development—suggest that a broader, multilateral approach
                                could serve as an effective supplement. Possible options are:</p>
                            <pb facs="0495" n="426" xml:id="pg_426"/>
                            <p>(A) <hi rend="italic">Continue Our Present Bilateral Approach
                                    Essentially Unchanged</hi></p>
                            <p>Outside of annual consultations with <gloss target="#t_ANZUS_1">ANZUS</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss>, US
                                problems and objectives in the Pacific region are addressed on an
                                essentially bilateral basis. Continuation of this policy would
                                conserve resources and avoid the compromises which necessarily come
                                with broader multilateral endeavors. Regarding a possible Pacific
                                Community organization, the United States would aim to let the idea
                                mature at a private level before committing itself to government
                                involvement. Without active US support, it can be expected that the
                                Pacific Basin concept will not advance in the near future beyond
                                private and academic circles.</p>
                            <p>(B) <hi rend="italic">Assume a More Active Posture</hi></p>
                            <p>(1) <hi rend="italic">Expand our Existing Bilateral Efforts</hi></p>
                            <p>This should include increased conceptual focus within the Department
                                on means for enhancing our Pacific relationships. The level and
                                number of high-level visits might be expanded. Bilateral
                                consultations on subjects of mutual interest (military as well as
                                economic and political) could be intensified. In addition, thought
                                should be given to the shifting of additional human and financial
                                resources to the Pacific area.</p>
                            <p>(2) <hi rend="italic">In Addition to Expanding Bilateral Efforts,
                                    Consider Moving in the Direction of a Multilateral Approach to
                                    the Pacific, Looking Toward Making First Steps to Build a
                                    Pacific Community Consultative Mechanism.</hi></p>
                            <p>This approach would focus on the Pacific area in a manner both
                                directly and indirectly supportive of US interests. Common concerns
                                might be addressed through either:</p>
                            <p>(a) a broadly-based, general consultative mechanism; or</p>
                            <p>(b) more narrowly-focused, functionally-oriented working groups,
                                organized initially on an <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> basis.</p>
                            <p>Initial topics for region-wide consultation might include the
                                promotion of regional trade and investment, the management of
                                trading relationships so as to forestall protectionism and support
                                the free market system, the coordination of regional aid flows, the
                                facilitation of technology transfer, or the management of marine
                                resources. Though essentially economic, common efforts along the
                                above lines could have the added advantage of indirectly nurturing
                                support for US political and strategic interests in the Pacific by
                                encouraging a general perception of shared interests among nations
                                friendly to the US and emphasizing US interest in the Pacific.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>