<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>118. Information Memorandum From the Director of the Policy Planning Staff
                    (Wolfowitz) to Secretary of State Shultz) to Secretary of State Shultz</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d118</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">118</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1982-09-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1982-09-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="arms-transfers"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91001417"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arms sales</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recyQwssZrUcxu4Pw" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Detente</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077241"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Linkage</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recIW1xgHEanEAKPW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133192"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technology transfer</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-09-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-09-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="118"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d118">
                <head>118. Information Memorandum From the Director of the Policy Planning Staff
                        (<persName corresp="#p_WPD_1">Wolfowitz</persName>) to Secretary of State
                        Shultz<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d118fn1">Source: Department of
                        State, Executive Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> Files,
                        Memoranda and Correspondence from the Director of the Policy Planning Staff
                        to the Secretary and Other Seventh Floor Principals: Lot 89D149, <gloss
                            target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> Chrons <gloss target="#t_PW_1">PW</gloss>
                        Chrons to <gloss target="#t_SecS_1">Secy</gloss> SEP 1982. Secret. Bremer’s
                        stamped initials appear at the top of the memorandum. Another stamped
                        notation reads: “82 SEP 24 P4:44.” A notation in an unknown hand, presumably
                            <persName corresp="#p_KPS_1">Kaplan</persName>’s, indicates that copies
                        were sent to <persName corresp="#p_HJH_1">Holdridge</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_HJT_2">Howe</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_WVA_1"
                            >Walters</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_DKW_1">Dam</persName>, and
                            <persName corresp="#p_ELS_1">Eagleburger</persName>. Also scheduled for
                        publication in <ref target="frus1981-88v28">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. XXVIII, China,
                            1981–1983</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1982-09-22">September 22, 1982</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Some Differing Thoughts on Our Emerging China Strategy</item>
                </list>
                <p>Agreement on the Joint Communique between the United States and China marks the
                    beginning of a new phase in US-China relations.<note n="2" xml:id="d118fn2">See
                            <ref target="#d117fn8">footnote 8, Document 117</ref>.</note> This will
                    not permit, however, a simple resumption of the US-China relationship as it
                    existed before these negotiations began. In the interim, Chinese policy has
                    undergone significant changes. In the last year Beijing has moved to distance
                    itself from the US, and has become more openly critical of US positions
                    internationally.</p>
                <p>Despite the Communique (and in some ways because of it) the Taiwan question will
                    continue to be a major irritant in US-China relations. Beijing clearly does not
                    accept our interpretation of the Communique, and can be expected to sustain its
                    pressure for an early termination to Taiwan arms sales and for an implicit right
                    to consultation whenever future sales are made.</p>
                <p>Under these circumstances, a close <rs corresp="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic"
                        >alliance</rs> or association with the Chinese is likely to be out of reach.
                    It will be important, therefore, that future US initiatives be premised on
                    balance and reciprocity in the relationship. If not, the Chinese may perceive us
                    as suitors and, paradoxically, feel greater liberty to adopt a standoffish
                    posture. We share many of the points of view of <gloss target="#t_EAP_1"
                        >EA</gloss> on this subject. But we favor a more cautious strategy, one
                    which sets very modest expectations for the relationship. We might, for example,
                    1) pursue a consciously low-key <pb facs="0518" n="449" xml:id="pg_449"/>
                    policy, the pace of which is measured by the degree of positive interest which
                    Beijing itself demonstrates in the US relationship; or 2) pursue a more
                    forward-leaning—but still carefully modulated—policy aimed at extending
                    incentives in return for concrete benefits.</p>
                <p>I have attached as Tab A a more detailed elaboration of this issue and of
                    possible policy alternatives. After reading it, you may wish to schedule a short
                    discussion with <persName corresp="#p_HJH_1">John Holdridge</persName>,
                        <persName corresp="#p_HJT_2">Jon Howe</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_WVA_1">Vernon Walters</persName>, Larry, Ken<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d118fn3">References are to <persName corresp="#p_ELS_1"
                            >Eagleburger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DKW_1"
                        >Dam</persName>.</note> and myself. Once we adopt a basic style in the new
                    relationship, we will have to live with it for a while.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Tab A</hi>
                    </note>
                    <head>Paper Prepared in the Policy Planning Staff<note n="4" xml:id="d118fn4"
                            >Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RRS_1">Randolph</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_GJD_1">Glassman</persName> on September
                            22.</note>
                    </head>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian">undated</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <p rend="center">PLANNING CONSIDERATIONS FOR <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                            >U.S.</gloss>-CHINA POLICY</p>
                    <p>The recent agreement to a joint communique opens the door for the resumption
                        of a more positive <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-China relationship.
                            <hi rend="italic">Nevertheless a simple return to the relationship we
                            enjoyed one year ago is improbable.</hi> The last year has been a
                        sobering experience in <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-China relations.
                        The Chinese have shown themselves to be hard bargainers, with a strong sense
                        of their own interests and how to project them. Those interests often differ
                        from our own. We can expect in the coming year and beyond that the Chinese
                        will continue to take a tough line with the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                            >U.S.</gloss>, particularly on Taiwan matters, and will continue to act
                        more from concrete self-interest than from a conceptual commitment to the
                        benefits of cooperation.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Momentum to Where?</p>
                    <p>We will need to be no less hard-headed. If, as <gloss target="#t_EAP_1"
                            >EA</gloss> has pointed out, it is important to establish a sense of
                        “momentum” and “steady growth” in the relationship, <hi rend="italic">it
                            will be</hi> no less <hi rend="italic">important to identify from an
                            early point the limits and the potential of that relationship and the
                            goal that we want to establish momentum toward</hi>. This kind of
                        analysis will be necessary if we are to properly determine the extent and
                        limits of the investment in our Chinese ties.</p>
                    <p>In partial answer to that question, I believe that China—because of its size,
                        location, and anti-Soviet orientation—offers a range of potential strategic
                        benefits, both globally and regionally. It is also in <pb facs="0519"
                            n="450" xml:id="pg_450"/> our interest to encourage a stable China,
                        constructively tied to the West and to the world community, since a hostile
                        or instable China could move closer toward the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                            >USSR</gloss>, and could threaten <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                        friends and interests in Asia.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">We must, nevertheless, be cautious in our evaluation of
                            the possible extent of “strategic cooperation” with the <gloss
                                target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss>. Already the basis for strategic
                            cooperation has begun to contract</hi>. This is evidenced in part by the
                        significantly curtailed nature of the strategic portion of our joint
                        communique, and by the Chinese desire during the later stages of the
                        negotiations to further restrict or to eliminate it entirely. <hi
                            rend="italic">Beijing has recently moved to publicly distance itself
                            from the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                        </hi>, and has become more openly critical of <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                            >U.S.</gloss> positions internationally. In part, this was a reaction to
                        the uncertainty of the Taiwan arms negotiations. More broadly, though, the
                            <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> now appears to be moving away from
                        a perceived partnership with the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                        against the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, and toward a position
                        less identified with uncompromising anti-Sovietism. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Efforts are accelerating to cultivate Third World nations</hi> and <hi
                            rend="italic">even radical states close to the Soviets</hi>. While
                        near-term <rs corresp="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic">detente</rs> between
                        Beijing and Moscow remains unlikely, and while China will continue to oppose
                        Soviet “hegemonism,” <hi rend="italic">some relaxation of Sino-Soviet
                            relations in the political</hi>, <hi rend="italic">cultural and economic
                            fields has already begun</hi> and can be expected to continue. Communist
                        Party Chairman Hu Yaobang’s recent speech to the Twelfth Party Congress
                        stands as only the latest indicator of the changing nature of the <gloss
                            target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-China relationship.<note n="5"
                            xml:id="d118fn5">In telegram 12046 from Beijing, September 4, the
                            Embassy transmitted a summary of the address. (Department of State,
                            Central Foreign Policy File, Electronic Telegrams, D820460–1101)</note>
                        Based on this realignment, we can expect that <hi rend="italic">Beijing will
                            seek to avoid the appearance of either <rs corresp="recwBHUin5Stz6rON"
                                type="topic">alliance</rs> or alignment with the United States, and
                            while continuing to pursue policies “parallel” to our own, will in the
                            future follow an increasingly independent policy.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">A Modulated Policy</p>
                    <p>Overall, <hi rend="italic">these developments indicate the need for a <gloss
                                target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> policy which is positive and cordial,
                            but less expensive and more at arm’s length than was once
                            anticipated</hi>. We should continue to encourage the pursuit and
                        coordination of parallel interests wherever possible, but with a more
                        limited set of expectations than in the past regarding the prospects for
                        true cooperation. In particular, <hi rend="italic">much greater attention
                            must be given to the need to modulate future U.S</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >initiatives to the constructiveness of actual Chinese behavior</hi>.
                        This will be necessary to ensure a proper balance in the relationship, and
                        to avoid a situation in which the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> is
                        cast in the role of suitor. The perception of a United States which is
                        overly anxious to build a close relationship could serve to encourage those
                        in the <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> who are inclined to leverage us
                        on issues where differences <pb facs="0520" n="451" xml:id="pg_451"/> still
                        remain, and, paradoxically, those inclined to distance themselves from us in
                        order to maintain an independent image. This suggests, among other things,
                        the need to maintain appropriate restraint on the pacing and timing of
                        future initiatives toward Beijing, including near-term high-level
                        visits.</p>
                    <p>In this context, <hi rend="italic">we need to ask not only how we can advance
                            our China relationship by actions designed to meet Chinese demands or
                            expectations, but also what concretely we ourselves want or expect to
                            gain from the Chinese</hi>. While, as some have suggested, it may be
                        desirable to loosen controls on technology exports to the <gloss
                            target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> or to go forward in the area of peaceful
                        nuclear cooperation (an enhanced focus on <rs corresp="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G"
                            type="topic">economic development</rs>, China’s principal national
                        objective, may in fact be our best strategy for the moment), these actions
                        should not occur in a vacuum. Instead they should be related to a clearly
                        demonstrated Chinese desire for constructive cooperation. <hi rend="italic"
                            >We should not give something for nothing</hi>. As outlined below, this
                        could be measured by concrete indicia. In addition, we should also consider
                        the possible negative sanctions available (such as the withholding of
                        technology) should Beijing again threaten a retrogression or should Chinese
                        policies turn in a direction decidedly hostile to <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                            >U.S.</gloss> interests.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Pressure and Firmness on Taiwan</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">We should, in addition, avoid focusing excessive attention
                            on those areas where the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> and the
                                <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> continue to disagree</hi>. Such
                        a focus would detract from our objective of rebuilding a positive,
                        broad-based relationship. The immediate issue remains Taiwan. <hi
                            rend="italic">Despite the communique, the Chinese have told us directly
                            they do not consider this the end of the issue</hi>, and that they
                        reserve the right to scrutinize our future sales. Since our agreement to the
                        communique, we have continued to be pressured on this score. According to
                        the Chinese Foreign Ministry, the communique “only marks a beginning of the
                        settlement of this issue,” and a through resolution “is indispensable to the
                        maintenance and development of Sino-<gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                        relations.” We have been told privately that Beijing expects that reductions
                        in arms sales to Taiwan will not be “dollar-a-year,” but rather will be
                        rapid and will lead to an early termination. We are currently being pressed
                        for data on past sales levels, and it is clear that Beijing will attempt to
                        use language in paragraph 9 of the communique calling for “appropriate
                        consultations” to support their claim to a voice in our future arms
                        decisions. China has publicly rejected the fundamental linkage between our
                        willingness to reduce future sales and the <gloss target="#t_PRC_1"
                            >PRC</gloss>’s commitment to a peaceful resolution of the issue (<hi
                            rend="italic">Xinhua</hi>, August 29). Beijing has also continued to
                        heavily criticize the Taiwan Relations Act, suggesting it will remain a
                        specific target of Chinese policy. An authoritative editorial in the <hi
                            rend="italic">People’s Daily</hi> has predicted that the <pb facs="0521"
                            n="452" xml:id="pg_452"/>
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-China relationship will face a crisis
                        if <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> policymakers insist on adhering to
                        this “internal law.”<note n="6" xml:id="d118fn6">In telegram 11030 from
                            Beijing, August 18, the Embassy highlighted various aspects of the
                            editorial. (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File, Electronic
                            Telegrams, D820428–0525)</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">I do not believe these objections to <gloss
                                target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> policy are “pro forma</hi>.” Instead,
                        it seems clear that even if these statements are made to some extent for
                        internal consumption, they are no less indicative of the true Chinese
                        position. While some are hopeful that the communique will allow us to put
                        the Taiwan issue on the “back burner” for one or more years, if experience
                        is any indication our respite will be short. Under these circumstances, <hi
                            rend="italic">we must be prepared to be very firm in adhering to the
                            President’s desire to sell Taiwan the arms it needs for its legitimate
                            self-defense, and must strongly resist pressure from Beijing to
                            explicitly or implicitly accept a Chinese role in determining the pace
                            of our movement on this score</hi>. Such pressure should be met, I
                        suggest, not with discussion of the merits of proposed arms sales, but
                        rather should be deflected by general reassurances of our commitment to the
                        terms of the communique as we interpret it.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Implications</p>
                    <p>The analysis above suggests that the United States might move in a number of
                        directions.</p>
                    <p>(a) <hi rend="italic">Pursue a positive but low-keyed relationship</hi>. The
                            <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> can go forward with its
                        relationship with China on a reserved basis, based on the judgment that
                        current Chinese attitudes may restrain for the foreseeable future the extent
                        of Sino-American cooperation. Under this strategy, <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                            >U.S.</gloss> initiatives should be undertaken at a measured pace
                        related directly to the degree of reciprocity demonstrated by the Chinese.
                        Specific steps might include initial restraint in near-term high-level
                        visits (e.g., postponement of some high-level visits to Beijing until early
                        1983, or waiting for <persName corresp="#p_ZZ_1">Zhao Ziyang</persName> to
                        visit Washington before sending a delegation of comparable seniority), and
                        shifting the primary focus of the relationship, if this should be necessary,
                        in the direction of economic and <rs corresp="recajGOY1Llc8movd"
                            type="topic">commercial</rs> relations (e.g., enhanced technology
                        transfer and <rs corresp="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic">credit</rs>
                        extension).</p>
                    <p>(b) <hi rend="italic">Expand the relationship, if possible, as a means toward
                            achieving specific objectives</hi>. Pursue a more aggressive policy,
                        aimed at achieving concrete benefits. Under this approach, we would seek to
                        move the Chinese forward by offering up special incentives that may be of
                        interest. Should Beijing prove unwilling to offer concrete, reciprocal
                        benefits, we would need to fall back to a more restrained policy. Specific
                        inducements the United States could offer might include stepped up <pb
                            facs="0522" n="453" xml:id="pg_453"/>
                        <rs corresp="recIW1xgHEanEAKPW" type="topic">technology transfer</rs> and
                        the sale of selected defensive arms (consistent with the interests of
                        China’s non-communist neighbors). Specific objectives the United States
                        might hope to pursue (and concrete measures of Chinese interest in
                        constructive cooperation) could include Chinese support or <rs
                            corresp="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic">neutrality</rs> on third world
                        issues in which we have an interest, a forthcoming position on Southwest
                        Asian problems (such as support for Pakistan), aid to the non-communist
                        resistance in Kampuchea, <rs corresp="recD442AQ8Opa4Jcf" type="topic"
                            >access</rs> to military facilities in China, port calls for US naval
                        vessels, and restraint of Chinese criticism on Taiwan. Though far from
                        certain, this approach could have the added benefit of drawing the Chinese
                        closer to the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> strategic network.</p>
                    <p>In either event, <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> does not recommend an
                        immediate acceleration of the China relationship in the absence of more
                        clearly articulated planning for long-term strategy toward both China and
                        Taiwan.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
