<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>185. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d185</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">185</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1984-02-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1984-02-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec9aDoDi7sluDnsm" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="civil-rights"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026371"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil rights</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic crisis</term>
                    <term ref="rec7XCpI38AIhVpLJ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Regional security</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recvFVZiL6ijeo9Lc" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104428"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Political rights</term>
                    <term ref="recH8UKNUTXoDXkax" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044163"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Environment</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="reczhNQIs9rGlNS1M" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96008124"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Humanitarian assistance</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="sub-saharan-africa" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="sub-saharan-africa">Sub-Saharan Africa</term>
                    <term ref="reccdibbkraMVDFLb" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2020000630"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Humanitarian relief</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1984-02-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1984-02-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="185" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d185">
                <head>185. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>On February 15, 1984, Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">George
                        Shultz</persName> spoke before the Boston World Affairs Council. He began
                    his remarks by stating: “Many Americans have images of Africa that are
                    anachronistic, partial, and often inaccurate. The perception of Africa that most
                    of us grew up with—unknown lands somehow exotic and divorced from the rest of
                    the world—has unfortunately persisted in some quarters despite the last 25 years
                    of Africa’s independence and increasing presence <pb facs="0832" n="763"
                        xml:id="pg_763"/> on the world stage. It is a misperception that ignores
                    compelling realities. One out of every eight people in the world now lives in
                    Africa, and this proportion is growing. Africa, south of the Sahara—which is my
                    principal concern this evening—is taking on increasing importance in several
                    respects.</p>
                <p>“First, we have a significant geopolitical stake in the security of the continent
                    and the seas surrounding it. Off its shores lie important trade routes,
                    including those carrying most of the <rs corresp="recN222dd4YgVLuoR"
                        type="topic">energy</rs> resources needed by our European allies. We are
                    affected when Soviets, Cubans, and Libyans seek to expand their influence on the
                    continent by force, to the detriment of both African independence and Western
                    interests.</p>
                <p>“Second, Africa is part of the global economic system. If Africa’s economies are
                    in trouble, the reverberations are felt here. Our exports to Africa have dropped
                    by 50% in the last 3 years; American financial institutions have felt the pinch
                    of African inability to repay loans. And Africa is a major source of raw
                    materials crucial to the world economy.</p>
                <p>“Third, Africa is important to us politically because the nations of Africa are
                    now major players in world diplomacy. They comprise nearly one-third of the
                    membership of the United Nations, where they form the most cohesive voting bloc
                    in the General Assembly.</p>
                <p>“Finally, Africa is important to us, most of all, in human terms. Eleven percent
                    of America’s <rs corresp="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic">population</rs> traces
                    its roots to Africa; all of us live in a society profoundly influenced by this
                    human and cultural heritage. The revolution of Africa’s independence coincided
                    with the <rs corresp="rec9aDoDi7sluDnsm" type="topic">civil rights</rs>
                    revolution in this country. Perhaps it was not a coincidence. Both were among
                    the great moral events of this century: a rebirth of freedom, summoning all of
                    us to a recognition of our common humanity. Just as the continued progress of
                        <rs corresp="rec9aDoDi7sluDnsm" type="topic">civil rights</rs> is important
                    to the moral well-being of this country, so too the human drama of Africa—its
                    political and economic future—is important to the kind of world we want our <rs
                        corresp="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic">children</rs> and grandchildren to
                    inherit.”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> then outlined the economic crisis
                    facing African nations and the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> response to
                    the crisis before discussing regional security issues: “Tonight, I have focused
                    on the role we have to play in confronting Africa’s <rs
                        corresp="recfgV5j0WMmONcRO" type="topic">economic crisis</rs>. But I cannot
                    ignore the other concerns. Africa needs stability and an end to conflict to get
                    on with the important tasks of national development. Many African nations face
                    real security threats. New and fragile political institutions are particularly
                    vulnerable. Where economies falter and fail to provide the basics of existence
                    and hopes for a better future, political instability can result. It is difficult
                    for <rs corresp="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic">democracy</rs> to flourish;
                    authoritarian solutions may appear more attractive but often only serve to make
                    problems worse while circumscribing human and political rights.</p>
                <pb facs="0833" n="764" xml:id="pg_764"/>
                <p>“In this <rs corresp="recNBOveCHYDHbAqL" type="topic">environment</rs>, outside
                    powers are tempted to exploit instability. There is no excuse for some 35,000
                    Cuban troops in Africa—trained, equipped, financed, and transported by the <rs
                        corresp="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic">Soviet Union</rs>—inserting
                    themselves into local conflicts, and thereby internationalizing local problems.
                    This Soviet/Cuban meddling has no precedent; it distorts Africa’s nonalignment;
                    it injects an East-West dimension where none should be, making fair solutions
                    harder to achieve.</p>
                <p>“We do not view Africa through the prism of East-West rivalry. On the other hand,
                    Africa does not exist on some other planet. It is very much part of today’s
                    world. Africa helps to shape the global structure—through its economic expansion
                    or <rs corresp="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic">decline</rs>, by its weight in
                    international forums, through its expanding web of bilateral and multilateral
                    links with the major powers, and through its conflicts. At the same time, it is
                    shaped by the global structure—by the shifts in the global balance of power, by
                    the broader marketplace of ideas and technologies, and by the readiness of
                    predators and partners to contribute to or detract from its development. We, and
                    Africa, ignore these facts at our peril.</p>
                <p>“We are not the gendarmes of Africa. But to stand by and do nothing when friendly
                    states are threatened by our own adversaries would only erode our credibility as
                    a bulwark against aggression not only in Africa but elsewhere. Therefore, we
                    have been ready, together with others, to provide <rs
                        corresp="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic">training</rs> and arms to help our
                    friends defend themselves.</p>
                <p>“And we act rapidly when the situation demands. Last summer, when Chad was again
                    invaded by Libyan troops, we rushed military supplies to the legitimate
                    government there and helped halt the Libyan advance. Libya’s destabilization
                    efforts have come to be an unfortunate fact of African existence. It is an
                    unacceptable fact. We will continue to work with others to help African states
                    resist Qadhafi’s overt aggression and covert <rs corresp="recSIsJwyicghR7T3"
                        type="topic">subversion</rs>.</p>
                <p>“In West and Central Africa as well as in the Horn—that critically important area
                    which sits on Africa’s right shoulder along the Red Sea—we help our friends, and
                    we protect our own strategic interests. We encourage the regional parties to
                    seek their own peaceful solutions to local conflicts.</p>
                <p>“We continue to emphasize, as we should, economic and humanitarian assistance
                    over military aid. This year the ratio will continue at five to one. The
                    Soviets, of course, provide minimal economic assistance to sub-Saharan Africa
                    and rarely participate in <rs corresp="reccdibbkraMVDFLb" type="topic"
                        >humanitarian relief</rs>. They seek to buy their influence in Africa
                    through the provision of arms. In the past decade, Moscow has contributed less
                    than 1% of Africa’s foreign economic assistance but has sold or provided 75% of
                    its weapons.”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> devoted the remainder of his
                    address to a discussion of Southern Africa before concluding his remarks: “If I
                    may leave you <pb facs="0834" n="765" xml:id="pg_765"/> with one message, it
                    would be that America takes Africa and its problems seriously. We see a direct
                    relationship between Africa’s political and economic stability and the health of
                    the Western world. We are committed to working with our African friends, and
                    with the international community, to help Africa overcome its problems.”</p>
                <p>“It is in our self-interest that we do so. And it is morally right. It is in the
                    best tradition of America.” (Department of State <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bulletin</hi>, April 1984, pages 9–12)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
