<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1984-06-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1984-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="196" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d196">
                        <head>196. Note From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                                (<persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName>) to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d196fn1">Source: Department of State, A Files,
                                    <gloss target="#t_FAIM_1">FAIM</gloss>/IS Files, Miscellaneous
                                Papers Screened From the Subject Files of Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> and his Assistant <persName corresp="#p_HMC_1">Charles Hill</persName>, upon the Secretary’s
                                Resignation on January 20, 1989: Lot 89D250, Misc File 6/84. Secret.
                                The President initialed the top right-hand corner of the
                                note.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1984-06-10">June 10,
                                1984</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Mr. President:</p>
                        <p>While I share your superstition of planning for events (re election) that
                            may never happen, we do have a responsibility to be prepared both to
                            deal with existing problems next year and to lead in charting new
                            courses to assure more stable peace and prosperity.</p>
                        <p>Toward this end, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">George Shultz</persName>
                            and I are setting in motion a discreet but comprehensive review. It is
                            organized to deal with the following framework: <list>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>Identifying ideas “whose time has come.”</item>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>New initiatives to expand the Reagan legacy.</item>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>Identifying better ways to deal with long-term issues.</item>
                                <pb facs="0898" n="829" xml:id="pg_829"/>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>Examining the effectiveness of our existing management
                                    arrangements, e.g. <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> and
                                    foreign policy instruments (i.e. declining aid
                                    resources).</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>We would very much welcome your participation in the planning effort.
                            Attached is a paper which describes it. We will keep you advised in the
                            coming weeks and would welcome your thoughts, ideas, priorities and
                            guidance at any time.</p>
                        <p>You need not read this entire paper. I have highlighted some of its more
                            salient and provocative factors.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Bud McFarlane</hi>
                                </persName><note n="2" xml:id="d196fn2"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> signed “Bud” above his typed
                                    signature.</note>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline">
                                <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                            </note>
                            <head>Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                                Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName>) to
                                President <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName><note n="3" xml:id="d196fn3">Secret. Sent for information. Prepared by
                                    Fortier, <persName corresp="#p_RDM_1">Rosen</persName>, and
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SSR_1">Sestanovich</persName>.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> did not
                                    initial the memorandum. Fortier sent a copy of the memorandum to
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> under a
                                    June 8 memorandum, indicating that it had “gone through many
                                    revisions, and the more we revised, the longer the paper became.
                                    Given the magnitude of the subject, I believe the length is
                                    justified; but you may want to see us shorten it.” (Reagan
                                    Library, <persName corresp="#p_FDR_1">Donald Fortier</persName>
                                    Files, Subject File, Policy Planning (Second Term) I:
                                    [01/01/1984–06/12/1984])</note></head>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian">undated</date></dateline>
                            <list type="subject">
                                <head>SUBJECT</head>
                                <item>Planning Second-Term Foreign Policy</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>We have begun to think about the foreign policy problems and
                                opportunities ahead in your second term.<note n="4" xml:id="d196fn4"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> crossed
                                    out “your second term” and wrote “the years ahead” above
                                    it.</note> We need to review first-term accomplishments, assess
                                where we stand now, and have operational strategies ready for
                                January. This paper is by no means a finished plan. It is meant to
                                illustrate the kinds of choices you will face, and to help you think
                                about how you will want to spend your time and effort in the months
                                and years ahead.<note n="5" xml:id="d196fn5"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> added “if reelected”
                                    to the end of this sentence.</note></p>
                            <pb facs="0899" n="830" xml:id="pg_830"/>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">Global Context</p>
                            <p>During your first term, <hi rend="italic">we began regional and
                                    global programs to arrest the decline of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> power and influence</hi>, and to lay the
                                groundwork for actions that stabilize and expand the area of liberty
                                and prosperity in the world. The trends are now more favorable than
                                they were in 1981:<note n="6" xml:id="d196fn6"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted the
                                    majority of this paragraph, beginning with the “During” and
                                    ending with “favorable.”</note>
                                <list>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>The willingness of the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> to raise defense spending, coupled with
                                        prompt and effective use of force in Grenada, has already
                                        done much to erase the image of American decline.</item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>The Soviet tide of advance in the Third World is being met
                                        and now half of the insurgencies in the world are directed
                                        against Soviet clients.<note n="7" xml:id="d196fn7"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName>
                                            highlighted the portion of this point, beginning with
                                            “half” and ending with “clients.”</note></item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>Moscow’s control of Eastern Europe requires increasing
                                        attention and resources and the burden of sustaining Soviet
                                        clients like Cuba and Vietnam is becoming more
                                        onerous.</item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>The dynamism of our leadership and economic growth stands
                                        in vivid contrast to a succession-plagued Soviet leadership
                                        and a stagnating Soviet economy.</item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>The growth of Communist insurgency has been slowed in
                                        Central America and a free election has taken place in El
                                        Salvador.</item>
                                    <label>—</label>
                                    <item>Added to all this, the world economy has some major bright
                                        spots. Energy prices seem to have begun a long-term decline.
                                        The performance of the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                                        and some East Asian economies is good, and could help spur
                                        recovery elsewhere.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>There are other elements in this picture, of course. Although the
                                Soviet leadership appears to be preoccupied with internal affairs,
                                they still have the ability to probe weak points on the periphery of
                                the Soviet Union that are of vital importance to the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Soviets could confront us with simultaneous
                                    crises in the Middle East and Southwest Asia, for example, and
                                    reveal that there are still large parts of our global strategy
                                    that we are not yet strong enough to execute</hi>.<note n="8" xml:id="d196fn8"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted the portion of this
                                    sentence, beginning with “there” and ending with
                                    “execute.”</note> While our increased defense budgets and new
                                programs have improved our ability to deter Soviet moves, there
                                still remain large gaps between <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                                defense commitments and capabilities in critical parts of the
                                    world.<note n="9" xml:id="d196fn9"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted the portion of this
                                    sentence, beginning with “there” and ending with
                                “world.”</note></p>
                            <pb facs="0900" n="831" xml:id="pg_831"/>
                            <p>The vulnerability of one leg of our strategic triad has been kept
                                dangling. And although <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>
                                deployment in Europe has shown the Soviet Union that missile
                                rattling and “peace offensives” cannot divide the West, the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>-Warsaw Pact balance still
                                strongly favors the East and the solidity of the alliance <hi rend="italic">has</hi> been strained.</p>
                            <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> also suffered a clear but
                                limited defeat in Lebanon.<note n="10" xml:id="d196fn10"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted this
                                    sentence.</note> Countries of the region now see the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> as less able to influence Mid East
                                politics than before. A sustained, successful defense of the Persian
                                Gulf should help to offset this to an important extent, as will
                                continued development of strategic cooperation with Israel.<note n="11" xml:id="d196fn11"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted “A sustained, successful
                                    defense of the Persian Gulf should help to offset this.”</note>
                                Basic strengths of the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> position
                                remain, but building on them will take time, particularly in light
                                of the unresolved debate here at home about the use of force.</p>
                            <p>More generally, as we look around the world, we are struck by the
                                enormous political, economic, and technological changes that have
                                occurred since the 1950s, and by the fact that many of the key ideas
                                and institutions of American foreign policy have not changed, and
                                may, in fact, have reached dead-ends.<note n="12" xml:id="d196fn12"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName>
                                    highlighted “enormous political, economic, and technological
                                    changes that have occurred since the 1950s,” and “many of the
                                    key ideas and institutions of American foreign policy have not
                                    changed, and may, in fact, have reached dead-ends.”</note></p>
                            <p>In planning an agenda for you to consider for the second term, we
                                intend to keep the following central ideas in mind.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>We should <hi rend="italic">capitalize on <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> strengths</hi>
                                    (technological innovation, organizational flexibility, etc.) and
                                    Soviet weaknesses (inefficient economic structures, fear of
                                    subject peoples, etc.)</item>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>Strategic planning must <hi rend="italic">reflect the
                                        importance of timing</hi>. We must be ready for
                                    opportunities as they arise, and act to create opportunities for
                                    ourselves down the road.</item>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>We should <hi rend="italic">seek the maximum leverage for our
                                        efforts</hi>. This means identifying areas where, having
                                    laid the groundwork, we can reap the largest payoff for
                                    investments of time and resources. Where the payoff will be
                                    smaller, our effort should also be less.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">Looking Ahead</p>
                            <p>No re-elected President since <persName corresp="#p_EDD_1">Eisenhower</persName> (and no new President since Kennedy) has
                                had the kind of freedom of action with which you will probably begin
                                your second term.<note n="13" xml:id="d196fn13"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted this
                                    sentence and at the end drew a line to the margin above and
                                    wrote: “if reelected.”</note> Nevertheless <hi rend="italic">early action on <pb facs="0901" n="832" xml:id="pg_832"/> key
                                    issues will be essential</hi>, to use the leverage created by
                                your first term, to exploit your post-election authority at its
                                peak, and where possible to control the agenda.<note n="14" xml:id="d196fn14"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted “early action on key
                                    issues will be essential.”</note> The lessons of ’81 are
                                relevant here.</p>
                            <p>An early start was the key to obtaining larger defense budgets, one
                                of your prime national security successes. We must similarly begin
                                early in the areas that matter most to us, and not allow our time
                                and political capital to be used up in secondary or tactical
                                fights.</p>
                            <p>Your second-term agenda must obviously include issues that loomed
                                large in your first term—<gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet
                                relations, Central America, the Middle East, China, the state of
                                    <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>. All involve essential
                                    <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> interests. On most of them
                                there will also be considerable public and allied anticipation of
                                new initiatives, whether due to the intense controversy they have
                                already generated (e.g., Central America) or because (like <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet and Arab-Israeli talks)
                                they have been on hold for more than a year.</p>
                            <p>We want to approach all of these issues with care. Decisions on
                                timing and priorities will have effects throughout your term, and it
                                is critical that you not overcommit yourself at the outset to solve
                                problems where openings are extremely limited. <hi rend="italic">One
                                    of the main objectives of this planning exercise will therefore
                                    be to assess where forward movement is truly possible</hi>.<note n="15" xml:id="d196fn15"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted this sentence.</note>
                                Where it seems remote, we will have to devise more incremental
                                policies, while continuing to search for ways to increase our
                                leverage and build future opportunities.</p>
                            <p>Our initial (and very tentative) judgment is that most of the big
                                issues identified above will be just as knotty and intractable next
                                year. For this reason, the following discussion begins instead by
                                identifying issues where we see special opportunities. If these are
                                successfully addressed, they will increase our leverage across the
                                board and help us to deal with other openings as they arise.<note n="16" xml:id="d196fn16"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted the first three sentences
                                    of this paragraph.</note> At the same time, the legacy you could
                                leave to the world community in these large, knotty problem areas is
                                a vital consideration. Therefore, in certain areas, it may be
                                crucial to use the special period of a second term to at least begin
                                to define and tackle problems whose solution may not be quickly
                                achieved.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">Decisions for 1985</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">1. Resources Issues</p>
                            <p>Our leverage in all of the international issues we face will depend
                                on how well we use the resources available to us for national
                                security action. In a painfully tight fiscal process our military
                                and security assistance budgets will be the target of budget
                                cutters. We are most likely to <pb facs="0902" n="833" xml:id="pg_833"/> get support for adequate budgets if we can
                                show how they help us take the initiative and force the Soviets into
                                activities less threatening to peace. There are several ways to do
                                this. We will need to convince a skeptical Congress that we are not
                                simply throwing money at defense problems but we have a thoughtful
                                plan for handling the threats facing us, and that we are building
                                forces in accord with that plan.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">In thinking about the structure of our defense
                                    program in a resource-constrained second term, our effort should
                                    be on forcing the Soviets to behave in ways that are less
                                    threatening to peace</hi>. Our strategic cruise missiles, for
                                example, have already forced the Soviets to spend large sums of
                                money on air defenses, at relatively low cost to us. The money they
                                spend on air defenses is not available for other, more threatening
                                programs. Capitalizing more on existing Soviet vulnerabilities is
                                also important and a very good way to rectify the gap between <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> defense commitments and
                                capabilities that we mentioned in the global context. However, some
                                of these weapons and strategies could be in tension with the desire
                                for arms control. Non-nuclear cruise missiles, for example, will be
                                critical in dealing with Southwest Asian contingencies, but they
                                will also make it more difficult to count and control nuclear cruise
                                missiles. We must be careful that we do not deny ourselves valuable
                                instruments that help us meet our commitments within our budget
                                limits. <hi rend="italic">Our planning activities will examine ways
                                    of reducing this tension</hi>.</p>
                            <p>The pressures on our defense budget will mount during the campaign,
                                as well as in 1985, and we will hear calls for more simple, cheap
                                weapons. We will examine this issue, though it is important to
                                understand that a production battle to see who can make the most
                                simple weapons would play to Soviet strengths in mass production. We
                                have discovered from recent and highly sensitive sources that Soviet
                                military calculations give great importance to our high-tech
                                weapons. While we understand the limitations of <gloss target="#t_F15_1">F–15</gloss>s and other sophisticated systems,
                                the Soviets apparently give very great weight to weapons whose
                                high-tech features they cannot match.</p>
                            <p>Making effective use of our resources is most important in crises. In
                                particular, the effective use of power requires better crisis
                                management techniques and organization. We will devote particular
                                attention to this issue in the months ahead.</p>
                            <p>If cuts are made in the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> military
                                budget, we should work hard to obtain correspondingly large
                                increases in foreign and security assistance budgets. To do so, we
                                need to increase awareness of how much our ability to act abroad
                                depends on strengthening states that will act as partners. We have
                                made this point repeatedly but <hi rend="italic">our ability to make
                                    the foreign assistance budget a truly potent diplomatic
                                    instrument probably depends on a first-year initiative tied to
                                    some offsetting reductions in defense <pb facs="0903" n="834" xml:id="pg_834"/> spending</hi>.<note n="17" xml:id="d196fn17"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted the portion of this
                                    sentence beginning with “our” and ending with “spending.”</note>
                                This could be structured in a way that makes it appear a very
                                dramatic initiative—appealing to liberals and conservatives alike,
                                while keeping money that we would otherwise lose altogether in the
                                national security account.</p>
                            <p>Finally, we should focus on the ways in which Japanese economic
                                strength can be used to relieve some of the demands on <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> resources. Japan should not be
                                used to finance <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> security
                                projects, but we will be looking to identify areas where additional
                                Japanese activity would be in the interest of both countries.
                                Premier <persName corresp="#p_NY_1">Nakasone</persName> has
                                discussed some innovative defense measures for Japan, and we should
                                pursue them with him more vigorously.</p>
                            <p>If our discussions with the Japanese go well, we might decide to
                                devote considerably more time and effort to this issue. It could, in
                                fact, develop into what we call special opportunities in the next
                                section. This illustrates that our categories are not rigid.
                                Depending on the decisions you make, the timing and priority of our
                                work on various issues will be adjusted.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">2. Special Opportunities<note n="18" xml:id="d196fn18"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted this heading.</note></p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Our chances for success in the central areas of
                                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> national security
                                    policy will improve if we can shape circumstances and create
                                    opportunities for ourselves by winning some smaller victories
                                    first</hi>.<note n="19" xml:id="d196fn19"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted “winning
                                    some smaller victories first.”</note> It now appears that in
                                1985 we may be able to reverse some of the gains made by the Soviet
                                Union in the Third World.<note n="20" xml:id="d196fn20"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted “reverse
                                    some of the gains made by the Soviet Union in the Third
                                    Word.”</note> The position of their clients in Angola and
                                Ethiopia is not firm.<note n="21" xml:id="d196fn21"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted “Angola”
                                    and “Ethiopia.”</note> Libya has become more isolated
                                    diplomatically.<note n="22" xml:id="d196fn22"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted
                                    “Libya.”</note> With increased <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> assistance, the <hi rend="italic">mujahadeen</hi>
                                in Afghanistan could impose serious costs on the Soviet Union;
                                without it, they may face defeat.</p>
                            <p>Defeating Soviet clients in some of these countries will provide
                                important benefits.<note n="23" xml:id="d196fn23"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted
                                    “Defeating Soviet clients” and “will provide important
                                    benefits.”</note> First, it will help build the consensus in the
                                    <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> on the use of force.<note n="24" xml:id="d196fn24"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted “First.”</note><hi rend="italic"> </hi>Successful use of limited force without
                                direct confrontation with the Soviet Union can only help rebuild the
                                consensus <pb facs="0904" n="835" xml:id="pg_835"/> in favor of
                                    <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> action where it is needed
                                and can be effective.<note n="25" xml:id="d196fn25"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted the
                                    portion of the sentence beginning with “Successful” and ending
                                    with “needed.”</note> At the same time, it should reduce the
                                need for <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> intervention by
                                showing the Soviets that they can spend a lot of money to prop up a
                                client and still lose. Second it will show countries around the
                                world that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> is a good friend
                                to have, and can impose costs on those who attack us or our
                                    friends.<note n="26" xml:id="d196fn26"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted the
                                    portion of this sentence beginning with “Second” and ending with
                                    “have.”</note> Finally, it will meet the issue of
                                state-sponsored terrorism and low-level conflict head-on by
                                combatting it in the Third World.<note n="27" xml:id="d196fn27"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName>
                                    highlighted this sentence.</note></p>
                            <p>We will also be looking at possibilities for drawing important
                                countries closer together. On the basis of our outstanding relations
                                with Pakistan, and now our substantive dialogue with India, measures
                                to promote Indo-Pakistani detente are a logical next step; <persName corresp="#p_BGHW_1">George Bush</persName>’s recent trip
                                revealed major possibilities here.<note n="28" xml:id="d196fn28"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName>
                                    highlighted the portion of the sentence beginning with
                                    “measures” and ending with “here.” <persName corresp="#p_BGHW_1">Bush</persName> visited India, May 12–15, and Pakistan, May
                                    15–18, in the course of a trip to Japan, Indonesia, India,
                                    Pakistan, and Oman, May 8–20. Documentation on <persName corresp="#p_BGHW_1">Bush</persName>’s meetings with Gandhi
                                    and Zia are scheduled for publication in <ref target="frus1981-88v33"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. XXXIII, South
                                    Asia</ref>.</note> No progress is likely this year (they have
                                elections too) but we want to have a package of ideas ready by early
                                1985—including military confidence-building measures (border troop
                                withdrawals, military exchanges, a hot line, etc.) as well as
                                economic and cultural projects and cooperation on narcotics
                                problems. The Vice President is in an excellent position to
                                spearhead this after you launch the effort.<note n="29" xml:id="d196fn29"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted this sentence.</note></p>
                            <p>Korea may offer another opening. For now, finding the right
                                modalities looks very hard (the number and identity of other
                                participants is a problem) but the Chinese are plainly interested in
                                lowering tensions on the peninsula (especially as the Soviets court
                                the North) and may be able to help us.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">3. Key Choices</p>
                            <p>Arms control and our strategic nuclear weapons programs may be
                                approaching a turning point. If we can learn anything from the past,
                                it is that it is crucial to have a plan that relates our strategic
                                weapons programs and our arms control strategy <hi rend="italic">early</hi>: perhaps as early as this summer.</p>
                            <p>The arms control theories and agreements of the past are, to a very
                                large extent, also based on the technologies of the past. Controls
                                on new <pb facs="0905" n="836" xml:id="pg_836"/> weapons simply
                                cannot be verified with the same confidence as in the past.<note n="30" xml:id="d196fn30"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted this sentence.</note> At
                                the same time, new technologies could help us reduce our dependence
                                on vulnerable traditional strategic weapons, or even allow us to
                                scrap them in the interest of arms control.</p>
                            <p>The new technologies that make a truly mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> possible will deal with the
                                problem of vulnerability even better than the M–X can. At the same
                                time, the current log-jam in the strategic arms control arena and
                                the charge that you are indifferent to arms control might be handled
                                by accelerating our efforts on MIDGETMAN and cancelling the
                                M–X—particularly if the Congress insists on transforming our
                                well-constructed M–X proposal into a tiny absurdity.<note n="31" xml:id="d196fn31"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted “accelerating our efforts
                                    on MIDGETMAN and cancelling the M–X.”</note> If we were to do
                                this, it would have to be done <hi rend="italic">early</hi>, before
                                our friends on the <persName corresp="#p_HMC_1">Hill</persName> go
                                to bat for you for the M–X, and before Congressional action makes it
                                look as if you were being forced to cancel.</p>
                            <p>Although still at the canter of our foreign policy, <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> now faces problems that may
                                further reduce that institution’s vitality. The Soviet nuclear and
                                non-nuclear build-up has increased the military and political
                                pressures on West Europe at a time when the economies of West Europe
                                are in bad shape, and likely to remain so. The potential for a
                                visible, debilitating clash between the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> and West Europe exists.</p>
                            <p>Solving this problem will require a major effort. We might need
                                programs to strengthen the economies of West Europe—perhaps a
                                technological “Marshall Plan.”<note n="32" xml:id="d196fn32">See
                                        <ref target="#d177fn3">footnote 3, Document
                                    177</ref>.</note> In our planning activities, we will consider
                                the merits of painfully thrashing out new, more realistic doctrines
                                for the defense of West Europe, or new alliance arrangements. And we
                                will have to consider how to handle domestic critics who ask why we
                                should be doing all this with Europe when we have problems of our
                                own.</p>
                            <p>Treating <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> on a business as
                                usual basis would involve lower costs. The West Europeans are moving
                                slowly toward solutions for their economic problems, and are talking
                                about joint European defense projects. The Soviets are not likely to
                                invade or provoke a crisis. We could muddle through. But if the
                                Soviets do attack somewhere around the world, <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> could be shown up as an empty
                                shell.</p>
                            <p>Whichever course we end up following, we will investigate in the
                                coming months the potential value of new non-nuclear weapons for the
                                defense of Europe.<note n="33" xml:id="d196fn33"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted “the
                                    potential value of new non-nuclear weapons for the defense of
                                    Europe.”</note> Their military value appears to be real,
                                although <pb facs="0906" n="837" xml:id="pg_837"/> their economic
                                costs, and the ability of the Soviets to devise ways of beating the
                                new technologies need to be evaluated. More importantly, better
                                non-nuclear weapons offer a way to reduce our reliance on nuclear
                                weapons that frighten Europeans, very reasonably.<note n="34" xml:id="d196fn34"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted “better non-nuclear
                                    weapons offer a way to reduce our reliance on nuclear
                                    weapons.”</note> The desire to avoid nuclear war may allow us to
                                forge a consensus in favor of the new non-nuclear weapons, and in
                                favor of a strong <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>.</p>
                            <p>Like the new technologies, the flanks of <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>—Norway on the north, Turkey in the south—will
                                receive our close attention whatever our other decisions may be.
                                Those areas are so vital to <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                                strategic concerns—control of the seas in the north, control of
                                Southwest Asia in the south—and their current defenses are so weak,
                                that we simply must devise ways to improve their position.</p>
                            <p>In the Middle East, a new Labor government in Israel could provide us
                                with some diplomatic opportunities.<note n="35" xml:id="d196fn35"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName>
                                    highlighted the portion of the sentence beginning with “a” and
                                    ending with “opportunities.”</note> If the leaders of the Labor
                                party do what they now say they will do (a freeze on West Bank
                                settlements, confidence-building measures on the West Bank,
                                negotiate on the basis of the Reagan plan), King <persName corresp="#p_HTI_1">Hussein</persName> may find it more difficult
                                to explain why he cannot join the negotiations. While <persName corresp="#p_HTI_1">Hussein</persName> is not likely to find new
                                courage overnight, and run risks for peace, he knows that if the
                                Israelis are flexible, it will be more risky for him to refuse to
                                move forward. If he does not negotiate in those circumstances, his
                                relations with us would suffer, and some of his own people who are
                                linked by family to the West Bank would be angry. There is no
                                guarantee that there would be progress, but the potential is there.
                                Any effort to take advantage of that potential would require your
                                own involvement. If the Labor government were, with our help, to
                                successfully press such an initiative forward this summer, it would
                                have two important effects on our planning process: 1) partially
                                free up resources for initiatives outside the Middle East at the
                                beginning of the second term; and 2) create an environment of
                                success conducive to undertakings more ambitious than those now
                                imagined.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">4. Unavoidable Decisions</p>
                            <p>On some issues, even if real openings seem slight, we will face
                                considerable pressure next year (whether from Congress, public
                                opinion, allies, or action-forcing events) to prepare new
                                initiatives. This will probably be true of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet relations and Central America. Both will be
                                prominent campaign issues, and a November victory may put our
                                critics on the defensive, but not for long.</p>
                            <pb facs="0907" n="838" xml:id="pg_838"/>
                            <p>The Soviets’ own focus will probably continue to be inward; if so, we
                                may see less activism and confrontation, but also little basis for
                                major agreement. Despite this, Congress will probably interfere more
                                in our policy, above all by holding nuclear-weapon systems hostage
                                to arms control initiatives; the odds are also increasing that in
                                1985 Moscow will do more to encourage such efforts here and in
                                Europe, by appearing more responsive (even if only as a
                                    tactic).<note n="36" xml:id="d196fn36"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted
                                    “Congress will probably interfere more in our policy, above all
                                    by holding nuclear weapon-systems hostage to arms control
                                    initiatives.”</note></p>
                            <p>Considerable public and Allied anticipation is also likely on the
                                summit issue (particularly as more Allied leaders pick up the line
                                of circumventing <persName corresp="#p_GAA_2">Gromyko</persName>).<note n="37" xml:id="d196fn37"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted
                                    “summit.”</note> As we plan a probe of Soviet positions on a
                                number of issues, such a meeting may offer certain advantages.<note n="38" xml:id="d196fn38"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted this sentence.</note> Our
                                position on “results” as a precondition may therefore need review:
                                the start of a new term could allow a “clear-the-air” summit (no
                                major results) without loss of credibility—in fact, with extra
                                freedom to hang tough on issues of substance (such as
                                    verification).<note n="39" xml:id="d196fn39"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> highlighted “the
                                    start of a new term could allow a ‘clear-the-air’
                                    summit.”</note></p>
                            <p>Congressional interference will remain a continuing problem for
                                Central America policy as well. Yet if <persName corresp="#p_DFJN_1">Duarte</persName> strengthens himself in El Salvador, and the
                                    <hi rend="italic">contras</hi> escalate in Nicaragua, our
                                position vs. Managua may seem as strong as it’s ever likely to be
                                (especially if we can fund the <persName corresp="#p_JHM_1">Jackson</persName> Plan<note n="40" xml:id="d196fn40">See <ref target="#d192fn18">footnote 18, Document 192</ref>.</note>
                                next year and use it as a lure for Nicaraguan demobilization). As a
                                result, pressures for—and perhaps a true chance of—accommodation
                                will increase. We’ll need to balance two conflicting goals—showing
                                that we can decisively defeat threats in our own hemisphere, and
                                gaining flexibility on other issues by putting this “crisis” behind
                                us.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">Steady-state Management</p>
                            <p>In many issues, where our policy is basically on track, an
                                end-of-term review will do little more than survey some marginal
                                changes of direction. This usually reflects progress already made.
                                Policy toward China is now clearly in this category, along with our
                                efforts in southern Africa and our management of the international
                                debt crisis.</p>
                            <p>On these and other issues, despite a basically favorable outlook, we
                                have to be alert to new problems and opportunities that may arise. A
                                marked worsening of Sino-Soviet relations may, for example, increase
                                Chinese interest in accelerated cooperation with us. Similarly, <pb facs="0908" n="839" xml:id="pg_839"/> in managing debt issues we
                                should probably work harder to gain informal political payoffs from
                                the debt relief we provide.</p>
                            <p>Adjustments like these will be considered in this planning process,
                                but because they are highly tactical, we do not expect to do more
                                than establish general guidelines. Moreover, the possible benefits
                                of even small policy adjustments have to be carefully weighed
                                against likely costs.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>