<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1987-10-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1987-10-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="311" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d311">
                        <head>311. Paper Prepared in the Bureau of European and Canadian
                                Affairs<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d311fn1">Source: Reagan
                                Library, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">George Shultz</persName>
                                Papers, Executive Secretariat Sensitive (10/05/1987–10/22/1987);
                                NLR–775–17–9–6–8. Secret. Acting Assistant Secretary for European
                                and Canadian Affairs Charles Thomas sent the paper to <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>, under an October 6
                                information memorandum, indicating that the paper, which was drafted
                                by <persName corresp="#p_FD_1">Fried</persName> on October 5 and
                                cleared by <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Simons</persName> and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PRM_1">Perito</persName> “provided <gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss>’s thoughts on <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> policy toward Eastern Europe.” In
                                an October 8 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_WJC_1">Whitehead</persName> wrote: “This memo is on the right track.
                                Our objective should be to do what we can to loosen the bonds
                                between the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe. If <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> succeeds in making the
                                Soviet Union a more open place, we must make sure that the Eastern
                                Europeans don’t stand still; they should stay ahead of Moscow. It
                                would be good for us if countries like Hungary and Poland could
                                continue their experiments with free markets or the tolerance of
                                dissent using <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName>’s
                                Russia as a base line rather than <persName corresp="#p_BLI_1">Brezhnev</persName>’s.” (Ibid.) <persName corresp="#p_WJC_1">Whitehead</persName>’s memorandum is in <ref target="frus1981-88v10#d49"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. X, Eastern Europe, Document
                                    49</ref>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-editorial-annotation" calendar="gregorian" when="1987-10-05">undated</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center"><gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> POLICY TOWARD EASTERN
                            EUROPE: CONCEPTUAL FRAMEWORK</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Introduction</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>Since you gave Deputy Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WJC_1">Whitehead</persName> his special East European/Yugoslav mandate
                                last summer, <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> engagement with
                                the countries of the area has been activated across the board.
                                Highpoints <pb facs="1498" n="1429" xml:id="pg_1429"/> have been the
                                Deputy Secretary’s two trips and the Vice President’s visit to
                                Poland last week; the Deputy Secretary’s November visit to the
                                    <gloss target="#t_GDR_1">GDR</gloss> and three additional
                                countries will affirm our new activism.<note n="2" xml:id="d311fn2"><persName corresp="#p_WJC_1">Whitehead</persName> traveled
                                    to Hungary, Yugoslavia, and Romania, November 9–16, 1986, and
                                    Poland, Czechoslovakia, and Bulgaria, January 27–February 7,
                                    1987. <persName corresp="#p_BGHW_1">Bush</persName> visited
                                    Poland, September 26–29, as part of a larger trip to the Federal
                                    Republic of Germany, France, the United Kingdom, and Belgium,
                                    September 25–October 3. <persName corresp="#p_WJC_1">Whitehead</persName> was scheduled to travel to Hungary,
                                    the Soviet Union, Yugoslavia, and the German Democratic
                                    Republic, November 6–17.</note> Raimond’s and <persName corresp="#p_GHD_1">Genscher</persName>’s comments to you suggest
                                it is time to consider the overall policy situation after a year of
                                accomplishment.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">The sources of change</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>Eastern Europe entering period of significant change, most
                                profound since 1956 upheavals. Raimond told you Eastern Europe was
                                    <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>’s “main problem.” May be
                                right; socialist <hi rend="italic">ancien regime</hi> there in
                                <rs corresp="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic">decline</rs>: <list>
                                    <item>East European regimes never commanded full political
                                        legitimacy; now clear they do not function economically.
                                        Economic pressures a long-term fact: time lost repaying
                                        wastefully spent borrowed money will ensure region misses
                                        next generations of industrial innovation.</item>
                                    <item>Although situation varies by country, ruling elites
                                        increasingly demoralized, defensive. Ideological elan and
                                        corporate party identity, significant even in 1956, now
                                        largely dissipated. Pragmatic “technocratic” communist model
                                        of the 1970’s discredited. Leaderships are aging and tired,
                                        with exception of <persName corresp="#p_JW_1">Jaruzelski</persName>.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>Pressures for change are indigenous, driven by policy failures of
                                communist leadership and underlying non-legitimacy. In every country
                                he visited, <persName corresp="#p_WJC_1">John Whitehead</persName>
                                found elements of leadership sensitive to this pressure.</item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>As in 1956, however, Soviet developments can affect timing of
                                events. <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> dynamism
                                an unexpected new source of pressure on East European regimes: <list>
                                    <item>By denouncing <persName corresp="#p_BLI_1">Brezhnev</persName> “era of stagnation,” <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> has helped
                                        undercut local <persName corresp="#p_BLI_1">Brezhnev</persName>-era leaderships, <persName corresp="#p_JW_1">Jaruzelski</persName> excepted. Barely
                                        disguised, public <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> slaps at <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> earlier this year
                                        symptomatic.</item>
                                    <item><persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName>’s
                                        reformism from the top intended to inspire East European
                                        imitators and lay basis for economic momentum. But rapid
                                        reformism, ultimately containable in <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> where Party is strong,
                                        Russian people essentially patriotic, has potential for
                                        accelerating possibly explosive sequence of events in
                                        Eastern Europe.</item>
                                    <pb facs="1499" n="1430" xml:id="pg_1430"/>
                                    <item>Some East European reformist elites intrigued by <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName>, but West is not
                                        in competition with <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> for popular loyalties, affections.
                                        Eastern Europeans intensely identify with West, increasingly
                                        with <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss></item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>In short, situation may become relatively fluid. Communist regimes
                                will not collapse, but extensive economic and, in some cases,
                                political reform, rising to top of local agenda. Question is less
                                whether reform will occur than when and how far it will go, and what
                                consequences will be.</item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>West must be prepared to react in ways that advance our
                                interests.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Policy Implications</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>Must balance forward-looking approach with realism; avoid extremes
                                of excessive expectations or cynical disengagement that have
                                sometimes characterized past <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                                policies. <list>
                                    <item>Excessive objectives, e.g., “rollback,” proved
                                        embarrassingly empty when put to test in Hungary.</item>
                                    <item>But mistaken to assume <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> cannot influence events. Not possible in
                                        short or medium run to challenge Soviet domination directly,
                                        but can help alter realities on the ground—the internal
                                        context with which local communist regimes and the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> must contend. A
                                        favorable evolution would have long-term strategic
                                        implications.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>Situation calls for Western effort to respond to and channel
                                change: through a deliberately active approach, to press our
                                interests and put our policy agenda directly before East European
                                decision makers; to respond to express wishes and interests of East
                                Europeans themselves. <list>
                                    <item><persName corresp="#p_WJC_1">John Whitehead</persName>
                                        laid groundwork for moving forward through process beginning
                                        with deliberate though relatively modest bilateral steps.
                                        These would be tailored to fit our interests with individual
                                        East European countries.</item>
                                    <item>We would use our biggest lever—economic and financial
                                        relations—explicitly to press for <rs corresp="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic">economic reform</rs>. We would
                                        work mostly through <rs corresp="recBS0IqgpfGXNR4a" type="topic">international financial institutions</rs>,
                                        only sometimes bilaterally, and would support strict
                                        economic conditionality throughout.</item>
                                    <item>We would make clear that <rs corresp="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic">human rights</rs> and national
                                        reconciliation would be a crucial factor in our ability to
                                        proceed with relations across the board.</item>
                                    <item>The willingness and ability of individual EE countries to
                                        respond to such a framework would vary; our points of
                                        departure with each country could be consistent.
                                        Differentiation would develop naturally.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <pb facs="1500" n="1431" xml:id="pg_1431"/>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>This framework was not only keynote of <persName corresp="#p_WJC_1">Whitehead</persName>’s and Vice President’s
                                message to Poland, but of our overall approach to area: it sets
                                standards for improving relations which press regimes in our
                                direction in a form they can accept.</item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>An active <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> role in Eastern
                                Europe would be based on a conceptual balance of benefits, not a
                                give-away. But it would require some resources, particularly
                                diplomatic. <list>
                                    <item>We should be focused outward on the ground: that means
                                        maintaining our Embassies and our contacts with the
                                        developing situation, not cutting back.</item>
                                    <item>Our efforts to enhance security in the field should be
                                        constructed with our broad interests in mind, not in
                                        isolation.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>Purposeful <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> engagement with
                                Eastern Europe would also serve <rs corresp="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic">alliance</rs> interests, unity: <list>
                                    <item><persName corresp="#p_GHD_1">Genscher</persName> expressed
                                        concern to you about <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss>
                                        becoming isolated in the West as it reaches out to <gloss target="#t_GDR_1">GDR</gloss>. Raimond spoke of Soviets
                                        using the <gloss target="#t_GDR_1">GDR</gloss> as bait for
                                        Bonn. This could be mitigated by an active <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> role in Eastern
                                        Europe.</item>
                                    <item>West Europeans, moreover, are far greater economic actors
                                        than we in Eastern Europe. <rs corresp="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic">Alliance</rs> ability to act in
                                        concert, and <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> interests,
                                        will be enhanced if the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                                        is engaged actively in the process.</item>
                                    <item>Allied consultations would be useful as our policies
                                        develop, possibly at a <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> Ministerial next spring.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>In short, framework for meaningful <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> engagement is already in place: next steps are to
                                activate it with each country—<persName corresp="#p_WJC_1">Whitehead</persName>’s November trip will be important here—and
                                to make sure its conceptual premises are well understood and, to the
                                extent possible, accepted within the <rs corresp="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic">Alliance</rs>.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>