<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1981-07-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1981-07-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="56" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d56">
                        <head>56. Address by Secretary of State Haig<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d56fn1">Source: Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, August 1981, pp. 31–34. <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> spoke before the Foreign
                                Press Association. The question and answer session following the
                                address is ibid., September 1981, pp. 31–33. The Department
                                transmitted the text of the address to all diplomatic and consular
                                posts in telegram 183639, July 14. (Department of State, Central
                                Foreign Policy File, Electronic Telegrams,
                            D810327–0450)</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>New York</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1981-07-14">July 14,
                                1981</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">Arms Control for the 1980s: An American Policy</p>
                        <p>I do want to say I’m very, very pleased to have an opportunity to talk
                            again before the <rs corresp="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic">Foreign Policy</rs> Association. I’ve always believed that
                            an effective policy abroad must be the product of support for that
                            policy here at home. And this association and its activities have
                            clearly made a major contribution to that requirement here in America.
                            It has always sharpened the issues for the American people and enabled
                            them to decide for themselves on these fundamental issues. And it is
                            just such an issue that I would like to discuss today, and that is the
                            vitally important issue of the future of arms control in this decade of
                            the 1980s facing Americans. There is hardly a subject which enjoys or is
                            a focus of greater international attention, especially recently, among
                            our allies in Western Europe, and with good cause.</p>
                        <p>This is true because we are living in an age when man has conceived the
                            means of his own destruction. The supreme interest of the United States
                            has been to avoid the extremes of either nuclear catastrophe or <pb facs="0262" n="193" xml:id="pg_193"/> nuclear blackmail. Beginning
                            with the <rs corresp="recmAP2t62yiJVSBo" type="compound-subject">Baruch plan</rs>,<note n="2" xml:id="d56fn2">In 1946 Bernard Baruch,
                                then the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> Representative to the
                                    <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Atomic Energy Commission
                                    (<gloss target="#t_AEC_1">AEC</gloss>), proposed a plan for the
                                international control of atomic energy. Documentation on the
                                development of the <rs corresp="recmAP2t62yiJVSBo" type="compound-subject">Baruch plan</rs> is in <ref target="frus1946v01"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1946, vol. I, General;
                                    the United Nations</ref>.</note> every President has sought
                            international agreement to control <rs corresp="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic">nuclear weapons</rs> and to prevent their
                            proliferation. But each Chief Executive has also recognized that our
                            national security and the security of our allies depend on American
                            nuclear forces as well.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> stands in this
                            tradition. He understands the dangers of unchecked nuclear arms. He
                            shares the universal aspiration for a more secure and peaceful world.
                            But he also shares the universal disappointment that the arms control
                            process has delivered less than it has promised.</p>
                        <p>One of the President’s first acts was to order an intense review of arms
                            control policy, the better to learn the lessons of the past in the hope
                            of achieving more lasting progress for the future. Two fundamental
                            conclusions have emerged from this review.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">First</hi>, the search for sound arms control
                            agreements should be an essential element of our program for achieving
                            and maintaining peace.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Second</hi>, such agreements can be reached if
                            negotiations among adversaries about their <rs corresp="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic">national security interests</rs>
                            are not dominated by pious hopes and simplistic solutions.</p>
                        <p>The task of arms control is enormously complex. It must be related to the
                            nation’s security needs and perspectives. Above all, arms control policy
                            must be seen in the light of international realities. As Churchill put
                            it: “You must look at the facts because they look at you.” An American
                            arms control policy for this decade must take into account the facts
                            about our security and the lessons that we have learned about what
                            works—and what does not work—in arms control.</p>
                        <p>Despite the extraordinary efforts at arms control during the 1970s, the
                            world is a less secure place than it was 10 years ago. We began the
                            process with the expectation that it would help to secure the deterrent
                            forces of both the United States and the <rs corresp="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic">Soviet Union</rs>. But Moscow’s
                            strategic buildup has put at risk both our crucial land-based missiles
                            and our <rs corresp="recuUFhBncrUg6V07" type="topic">bombers</rs>. Simultaneously, the Soviets have continued a massive
                            buildup of conventional forces and have used them with increasing
                            boldness. Their armies and those of their surrogates have seized
                            positions that threaten resources and routes critical to Western
                            security.</p>
                        <p>We cannot blame our approach to arms control alone for our failure to
                            restrain the growth and use of Soviet power. The <rs corresp="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic">Soviet Union</rs> did not
                            feel compelled to agree to major limitations and adequate <pb facs="0263" n="194" xml:id="pg_194"/> verification in part because
                            the United States did not take steps needed to maintain its own
                            strategic and conventional capabilities. Nor did we respond vigorously
                            to the use of Soviet force. The turmoil of the 1960s, Vietnam, and
                            Watergate all contributed to this passivity. As a result, the basis for
                            arms control was undermined. We overestimated the extent to which the
                            <rs corresp="recAynYh8uzxYGQRH" type="topic">Strategic Arms</rs> Limitation Talks would help to ease other tensions. We
                            also underestimated the impact that such tensions would have on the arms
                            control process itself.</p>
                        <p>This experience teaches us that arms control can only be one element in a
                            comprehensive structure of defense and <rs corresp="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic">foreign policy</rs> designed to reduce
                            the risks of war. It cannot be the political centerpiece or the crucial
                            barometer of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet relationships,
                            burdening arms control with a crushing political weight. It can hardly
                            address such issues as the Soviet <rs corresp="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic">invasion</rs> of <rs corresp="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic">Afghanistan</rs>, the Iran-Iraq
                            war, the Vietnamese <rs corresp="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic">invasion</rs> of Kampuchea<note n="3" xml:id="d56fn3">See
                                    <ref target="#d53fn12">footnotes 12</ref> and <ref target="#d53fn13">13, Document 53</ref>.</note>—which is the
                            subject of our U.N. conference here this week—the Libyan <rs corresp="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic">invasion</rs> of
                            Chad, or Cuban intervention in Africa and Latin America. Instead, arms
                            control should be an element—a single element—in a full range of
                            political, economic, and military efforts to promote peace and
                            security.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Principles</p>
                        <p>The lessons of history and the facts of international life provide the
                            basis for a realistic set of principles to guide a more effective
                            approach to arms control. All of our principles are derived from a
                            recognition that the paramount aim of arms control must be to reduce the
                            risks of war. We owe it to ourselves and to our posterity to follow
                            principles wedded exclusively to that aim.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Our first principle is that our arms control efforts
                                will be an instrument of, not a replacement for, a coherent allied
                                <rs corresp="rec0QsshUhjiMmm5v" type="topic">security policy</rs></hi>. Arms control proposals should be designed in
                            the context of the security situation we face, our military needs, and
                            our defense strategy. Arms control should complement military programs
                            in meeting these needs. Close consultation with our allies is an
                            essential part of this process, both to protect their interests and to
                            strengthen the Western position in negotiations with the Soviet
                            Union.</p>
                        <p>If, conversely, we make our defense programs dependent on progress in
                            arms control, then we will give the Soviets a veto over our defenses and
                            remove their incentive to negotiate fair arrangements. Should we expect
                            Moscow to respect parity if we demonstrate that we are not prepared to
                            sacrifice to sustain it? Can we expect the Soviets to agree to
                            limitations if they realize that, in the absence of agreement, we shall
                            not match their efforts? In the crucial relationship between arms <pb facs="0264" n="195" xml:id="pg_195"/> and arms control, we must not
                            put the cart before the horse. There is little prospect of agreements
                            with the <rs corresp="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic">Soviet Union</rs> that will help solve such a basic security problem
                            as the vulnerability of our land-based missiles until we demonstrate
                            that we have the will and the capacity to solve them without arms
                            control, should that be necessary.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Our second principle is that we will seek arms control
                                agreements that truly enhance security</hi>. We will work for
                            agreements that make world peace more secure by reinforcing <rs corresp="recMrVNgNJpQ8DjcR" type="topic">deterrence</rs>.
                            On occasion it has been urged that we accept defective agreements in
                            order “to keep the arms control process alive.” But we are seeking much
                            more than agreements for their own sake. We will design our proposals
                            not simply in the interest of a speedy <rs corresp="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic">negotiation</rs> but so that they will
                            result in agreements which genuinely enhance the security of both
                            sides.</p>
                        <p>That is the greatest measure of the worth of arms control, not the money
                            saved nor the arms eliminated. Indeed, valuable agreements can be
                            envisioned that do not save money and that do not eliminate arms. The
                            vital task is to limit and to reduce arms in a way that renders the use
                            of the remaining arms less likely.</p>
                        <p>Just as arms control could not aim simply at reducing numbers, so it
                            should not try simply to restrict the advance of technology. Some
                            technological advances make everyone safer. Reconnaissance satellites,
                            for instance, discourage surprise attacks by increasing warning and make
                            verification of agreements possible. Submarines and other means of
                            giving <rs corresp="recJwYAJf2vdRiALq" type="topic">mobility</rs> to strategic systems enhance their <rs corresp="recWnMoFvE8rSByAg" type="topic">survivability</rs>, reduce
                            the advantage of preemptive strikes, and thus help to preserve the
                            peace. Our proposals will take account of both the positive and the
                            negative effects of advancing technology.</p>
                        <p>Whether a particular weapons system, and therefore a particular
                            agreement, undermines or supports <rs corresp="recMrVNgNJpQ8DjcR" type="topic">deterrence</rs> may change with the
                            development of other weapons systems. At one time, fixed
                            <rs corresp="reccap2GMokKh4v4P" type="topic">intercontinental ballistic missiles</rs> (<gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>s) were a highly stable form of strategic weapons
                            deployments, but technological change has altered that. We need to
                            design arms control treaties so that they can adapt flexibly to
                            long-term changes. A treaty that, for example, had the effect of locking
                            us into fixed <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> deployments would
                            actually detract from the objectives of arms control.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Our third principle is that we will seek arms control
                                bearing in mind the whole context of Soviet conduct worldwide</hi>.
                            Escalation of a crisis produced by Soviet aggression could lead to a
                            nuclear war, particularly if we allowed an imbalance of forces to
                            provide an incentive for a Soviet first strike. American <rs corresp="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic">foreign policy</rs>
                            and <rs corresp="recfDPXugH8GvkDjP" type="topic">defense policy</rs>, of which arms control is one element, must deter
                            aggression, contain crisis, reduce sources of conflict, and achieve a
                            more stable <rs corresp="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic">military balance</rs>—all for <pb facs="0265" n="196" xml:id="pg_196"/> the purpose of securing the peace. These tasks
                            cannot be undertaken successfully in isolation one from the other.</p>
                        <p>Soviet international conduct directly affects the prospects for success
                            in arms control. Recognition of this reality is essential for a healthy
                            arms control process in the long run. Such “linkage” is not the creation
                            of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> policy: It is a fact of life. A
                            policy of pretending that there is no linkage promotes reverse linkage.
                            It ends up by saying that in order to preserve arms control, we have to
                            tolerate Soviet aggression. This Administration will never accept such
                            an appalling conclusion.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Our fourth principle is that we will seek balanced arms
                                control agreements</hi>. Balanced agreements are necessary for a
                            relationship based on reciprocity and essential to maintaining the
                            security of both sides. The <rs corresp="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic">Soviet Union</rs> must be more willing in the
                            future to accept genuine parity for arms control to move ahead. Each
                            agreement must be balanced in itself and contribute to an overall
                            balance.</p>
                        <p>Quantitative parity is important, but balance is more than a matter of
                            numbers. One cannot always count different weapons systems as if they
                            were equivalent. What matters is the capacity of either side to make
                            decisive gains through <rs corresp="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic">military operations</rs> or threat of military
                            operations. Agreements that do not effectively reduce the incentives to
                            use force, especially in crisis situations, do nothing at all to enhance
                            security.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Our fifth principle is that we will seek arms controls
                                that include effective means of verification and mechanisms for
                                securing <rs corresp="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic">compliance</rs></hi>. Unverifiable agreements only increase
                            uncertainties, tensions, and risks. The critical obstacle in virtually
                            every area of arms control in the 1970s was Soviet unwillingness to
                            accept the verification measures needed for more ambitious limitations.
                            As much as any other single factor, whether the Soviets are forthcoming
                            on this question will determine the degree of progress in arms control
                            in the 1980s.</p>
                        <p>Failure of the entire arms control process in the long run can be avoided
                            only if <rs corresp="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic">compliance</rs> issues are clearly resolved. For example, there have
                            been extremely disturbing reports of the use of <rs corresp="rectadvRz4QZmc1z7" type="topic">chemical weapons</rs> by the
                            Soviets or their proxies in <rs corresp="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic">Afghanistan</rs> and in Southeast Asia. With full
                            Western support the United Nations is now investigating the issue of
                            <rs corresp="rectadvRz4QZmc1z7" type="topic">chemical weapons</rs>.<note n="4" xml:id="d56fn4">Reference is to
                                A/RES/35/144 C, “Chemical and Bacteriological (Biological) Weapons,”
                                adopted by the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> General Assembly
                                on December 12, 1980, which requested the Secretary-General to
                                investigate the alleged use of <rs corresp="rectadvRz4QZmc1z7" type="topic">chemical weapons</rs>.</note> Similarly,
                            in the spring of 1979, there was an extraordinary outbreak of anthrax in
                            the Soviet city of Sverdlovsk.<note n="5" xml:id="d56fn5">Reference is
                                to the accidental release of anthrax from a military research
                                facility in Sverdlovsk in April 1979. For additional information,
                                see <ref target="frus1977-80v06#d267"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. VI, <rs corresp="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic">Soviet Union</rs>, Documents
                                    267</ref>, <ref target="frus1977-80v06#d269">269</ref>, <ref target="frus1977-80v06#d270">270</ref>, <ref target="frus1977-80v06#d290">290</ref>, <ref target="frus1977-80v06#d294">294</ref>, <ref target="frus1977-80v06#d297">297</ref>, <ref target="frus1977-80v06#d304">304</ref>, and <ref target="frus1977-80v06#d306">306</ref>.</note> Despite continued
                            probing, we still await a serious Soviet <pb facs="0266" n="197" xml:id="pg_197"/> explanation as to whether it was linked to
                            activities prohibited under the biological weapons convention.<note n="6" xml:id="d56fn6">Reference is to the Convention on the
                                Prohibition of the Development, Production and Stockpiling of
                                Bacteriological (Biological) and Toxin Weapons and on their
                                Destruction (26 <gloss target="#t_UST_1">UST</gloss> 583), commonly
                                known as the Biological Weapons Convention, signed in London,
                                Washington, and Moscow on April 10, 1972, and entered into force on
                                March 26, 1975. For additional information, see <ref target="frus1969-76ve02#d256"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol. E–2, Documents on Arms
                                    Control and Nonproliferation, 1969–1972, Document
                                256</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Our sixth principle is that our strategy must consider
                                the totality of the various arms control processes and various
                                weapons systems, not only those that are being specifically
                                negotiated</hi>. Each <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> weapons
                            system must be understood not merely in connection with a corresponding
                            Soviet system, but in relation to our whole strategy for deterring the
                            Soviets from exploiting military force in general. In developing our
                            theater nuclear arms control proposals, for example, we should consider
                            the relationship of theater nuclear forces to <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>’s overall strategy for deterring war in Europe. We
                            cannot overlook the fact that our European strategy has always
                            compensated for shortfalls in conventional capability through a greater
                            reliance on theater and <rs corresp="recCx6QZi7AaiEP6y" type="topic">strategic nuclear forces</rs>. If we are to rely less
                            on the nuclear elements in the future, the conventional elements will
                            have to be strengthened.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Prospects</p>
                        <p>What then are the prospects for arms control in the 1980s? We could
                            achieve quick agreements and an appearance of progress if we pursued
                            <rs corresp="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic">negotiation</rs> for its own sake or for the political symbolism of
                            continuing the process. But we are committed to serious arms control
                            that truly strengthens international security. That is why our approach
                            must be prudent, paced, and measured.</p>
                        <p>With a clear sense of direction and a dedication to the serious
                            objectives of arms control, this Administration will strive to make arms
                            control succeed. We will put our principles into action. We will conduct
                            negotiations based on close consultation with our allies, guided by the
                            understanding that our objective is enhanced security for all of our
                            allies, not just for the United States. We will work with the Congress
                            to insure that our arms control proposals reflect the desires of our
                            people, and that, once agreements are negotiated, they will be ratified
                            and their implementation fully supported. We will comply with agreements
                            we make, and we will demand that others do likewise.</p>
                        <p>By the end of the year, the United States will be embarked upon a new
                            arms control endeavor of fundamental importance, one designed to reduce
                            the Soviet nuclear threat to our European allies. The impetus for these
                            negotiations dates back to the mid-1970s when the Soviets began
                            producing and deploying a whole new generation of nuclear <pb facs="0267" n="198" xml:id="pg_198"/> systems designed not to
                            threaten the United States—for their range was too short—but to threaten
                            our European allies. These new weapons, and in particular the nearly
                            3,000-mile-range <gloss target="#t_SS20_1">SS–20</gloss> missile, were
                            not just modernized replacements for older systems. Because of their
                            much greater range, their <rs corresp="recJwYAJf2vdRiALq" type="topic">mobility</rs>, and above all their multiplication
                            of <rs corresp="recfkRWjb8Vcm4Gga" type="topic">warheads</rs> on each missile, these new systems presented the <rs corresp="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic">alliance</rs>
                            with a threat of a new order of magnitude.</p>
                        <p>The pace of the Soviet buildup is increasing. Since the beginning of last
                            year, the Soviets have more than doubled their <gloss target="#t_SS20_1">SS–20</gloss> force. Already 750 <rs corresp="recfkRWjb8Vcm4Gga" type="topic">warheads</rs> have been deployed on
                                <gloss target="#t_SS20_1">SS–20</gloss> launchers. The <rs corresp="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic">Soviet Union</rs>
                            has continued to deploy the long-range <gloss target="#t_Backfire_1">Backfire</gloss> bomber and a whole array of new medium- and
                            short-range nuclear missiles and nuclear-capable <rs corresp="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic">aircraft</rs>. This
                            comprehensive Soviet arms buildup is in no sense a reaction to <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>’s defense program. Indeed, <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> did very little as this alarming
                            buildup progressed.</p>
                        <p>In December 1979 the <rs corresp="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic">alliance</rs> finally responded in two ways. First, it
                            agreed to deploy 464 new <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                            <rs corresp="recEYJpmEGRfvJpPc" type="topic">ground-launched cruise missiles</rs> in Europe and to replace 108
                            medium-range Pershing <rs corresp="recr08QgEMEm1Bk04" type="topic">ballistic missiles</rs> already located there with
                            modernized versions of greater range. Second, the <rs corresp="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic">alliance</rs> agreed that
                            the United States should pursue negotiated limits on <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> and Soviet systems in this
                            category.</p>
                        <p>This two-track decision represents explicit recognition that arms control
                            cannot succeed unless it is matched by a clear determination to take the
                            defense measures necessary to restore a secure balance. On taking
                            office, as one of its first <rs corresp="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic">foreign policy</rs> initiatives, this
                            Administration announced its commitment to both tracks of the <rs corresp="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic">alliance</rs>
                            decision—deployments and arms control. Last May, in Rome, we secured
                            unanimous <rs corresp="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic">alliance</rs> endorsement of our decision to move ahead on both
                            tracks and of our plan for doing so.<note n="7" xml:id="d56fn7">See <ref target="#d48fn3">footnotes 3</ref> and <ref target="#d48fn6">6,
                                    Document 48</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>Since then I have begun discussions in Washington with the Soviet
                            Ambassador on this issue.<note n="8" xml:id="d56fn8">In an undated
                                memorandum to the President, <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> indicated that <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> had delivered to him that day a letter from
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BLI_1">Brezhnev</persName> to Reagan,
                                dated May 27. <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> noted
                                that during their conversation, <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> had expressed the Soviet desire to get the
                                    <gloss target="#t_TNF_1">TNF</gloss> talks underway. <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> continued, “I told him that
                                the talks we will conduct between now and when <persName corresp="#p_GAA_2">Gromyko</persName> and I meet in September
                                will be restricted to the modalities. I explained that the US had to
                                engage in extensive consultations with its allies and prepare threat
                                and requirement assessments so that when we begin negotiations we
                                will know which systems will be involved. The <gloss target="#t_TNF_1">TNF</gloss> talks are not like the <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> talks where the US could act
                                largely unilaterally. I argued that both we and the Soviets will be
                                well served by these intensive preparations so that my discussions
                                with <persName corresp="#p_GAA_2">Gromyko</persName> in September
                                can be productive and businesslike.” For the text of the memorandum
                                and the text of <persName corresp="#p_BLI_1">Brezhnev</persName>’s
                                letter, see <ref target="frus1981-88v03#d59"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. III, <rs corresp="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic">Soviet Union</rs>,
                                    January 1981–January 1983, Document 59</ref>.</note> When I meet
                            with Soviet Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GAA_2">Gromyko</persName> at the United Nations this September, I will
                            seek agreement <pb facs="0268" n="199" xml:id="pg_199"/> to start the
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet negotiations on these
                            weapons systems by the end of this year.<note n="9" xml:id="d56fn9"><persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> met with <persName corresp="#p_GAA_2">Gromyko</persName> during the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> General Assembly (<persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName>’s speech is printed as
                                Document 63) on September 23 and September 28. On September 23, they
                                agreed that formal negotiations would begin in Geneva on November
                                30, with <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName> representing
                                the United States and U.A. Kvitsinsky representing the Soviet Union.
                                The memoranda of conversation are printed in <ref target="frus1981-88v03#d88"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. III, Soviet Union, January
                                    1981–January 1983, Documents 88</ref>–<ref target="frus1981-88v03#d91">91</ref>.</note> We would like to
                            see the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> and Soviet negotiators meet
                            to begin formal talks between mid-November and mid-December of this
                            year. We intend to appoint a senior <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                            official with the rank of Ambassador as our representative at these
                            talks.</p>
                        <p>Extensive preliminary preparations for this entirely new area of arms
                            control are already underway in Washington and in consultation with our
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> allies in Brussels. Senior
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> and European officials will
                            continue to consult after the beginning of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet exchanges. We and our allies recognize that
                            progress can only come through complex, extensive, and intensive
                            negotiations.</p>
                        <p>We approach these negotiations with a clear sense of purpose. We want
                            equal, verifiable limits on the lowest possible level on <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> and Soviet theater nuclear forces.
                            Such limits would reduce the threat to our allies and bring to Europe
                            the security undermined today by the Soviet buildup. We regard the
                            threat to our allies as a threat to ourselves, and we will, therefore,
                            spare no effort to succeed.</p>
                        <p>We are proceeding with these negotiations to limit the theater threat
                            within the framework of <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>—the
                            <rs corresp="recAynYh8uzxYGQRH" type="topic">Strategic Arms</rs> Limitation Talks designed to limit the nuclear threat to
                            the United States and the Soviet Union. In this area, too, we have
                            initiated intense preparations. These preparations must take into
                            account the decisions we will take shortly on modernizing our
                            <rs corresp="reccap2GMokKh4v4P" type="topic">intercontinental ballistic missiles</rs> and our strategic <rs corresp="recuUFhBncrUg6V07" type="topic">bombers</rs>.</p>
                        <p>In the course of 10 years of <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>
                            negotiations, conceptual questions have arisen which must be addressed.
                            For instance, how have improvements in monitoring capabilities, on the
                            one hand, and new possibilities for deception and concealment, on the
                            other, affected our ability to verify agreements and to improve
                            verification? Which systems are to be included in a <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> <rs corresp="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic">negotiation</rs>, and which should be
                            discussed in other forums? How can we compare and limit the diverse
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> and Soviet military arsenals in
                            the light of new systems and new technologies emerging on both
                            sides?</p>
                        <p>In each of these areas there are serious and pressing questions which
                            must be answered to insure the progress of <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> in the 1980s and beyond. Only in this way can <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> become again a dynamic process <pb facs="0269" n="200" xml:id="pg_200"/> that will promote greater
                            security in the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet
                            relationship. We are determined to solve these problems and to do
                            everything necessary to arrive at balanced reductions in strategic
                            arsenals on both sides.</p>
                        <p>We should be prepared to pursue innovative arms control ideas. For
                            example, negotiated <rs corresp="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic">confidence-building measures</rs> in Europe could provide
                            a valuable means to reduce uncertainty about the character and purpose
                            of the other side’s military activities. While measures of this sort
                            will not lessen the imperative of maintaining a <rs corresp="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic">military balance</rs> in
                            Europe, they can reduce the dangers of miscalculation and surprise.</p>
                        <p>We are eager to pursue such steps in the framework of a European
                            disarmament conference based on an important French proposal now being
                            considered at the Madrid meeting of the Conference on Security and
                            Cooperation in Europe.<note n="10" xml:id="d56fn10">Reference is to a
                                French proposal, introduced at the <gloss target="#t_CSCE_1">CSCE</gloss> Madrid review conference (see <ref target="#d48fn4">footnote 4, Document 48</ref>), which called
                                for a conference on disarmament in Europe to discuss confidence
                                building measures that would “apply to all of Europe from the
                                Atlantic to the Urals.” (Telegram 90145 to Moscow, Seoul, Tokyo,
                                    <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC_1">CINCPAC</gloss> Honolulu, and
                                    <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC_1">CINCUNC</gloss> Seoul, April 10;
                                Department of State, Central <rs corresp="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic">Foreign Policy</rs> File, Electronic
                                Telegrams, D810170–0334)</note> We call upon the Soviets to accept
                            this proposal, which could cover Soviet territory to the Urals. As we
                            proceed in Madrid, we will do so on the basis of a firm <rs corresp="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic">alliance</rs>
                            solidarity, which is the key to bringing the Soviets to accept serious
                            and effective arms control measures.</p>
                        <p>Our efforts to control existing nuclear arsenals will be accompanied by
                            new attempts to prevent the spread of <rs corresp="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic">nuclear weapons</rs>. The Reagan
                            Administration is developing more vigorous policies for inhibiting
                            nuclear proliferation.<note n="11" xml:id="d56fn11">On July 16, the
                                White House released the President’s statement on <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> nuclear nonproliferation policy.
                                In it, the President outlined the administration’s “policy
                                framework,” containing basic guidelines for the pursuit of its
                                policy, asserting: “We must reestablish this Nation as a predictable
                                and reliable partner for peaceful nuclear cooperation under adequate
                                safeguards. This is essential to our nonproliferation goals. If we
                                are not such a partner, other countries will tend to go their own
                                ways, and our influence will diminish. This would reduce our
                                effectiveness in gaining the support we need to deal with
                                proliferation problems.” He directed that <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName>, in concert with other
                                agencies, work to “reestablish a leadership role for the United
                                States in international nuclear affairs.” (<hi rend="italic">Public
                                    Papers: Reagan, 1981</hi>, pp. 630–631)</note> We expect the
                            help of others in this undertaking, and we intend to be a more
                            forthcoming partner to those who share responsibility for
                            nonproliferation practices. Proliferation complicates the task of arms
                            control: It increases the risk of preemptive and accidental war, it
                            detracts from the maintenance of a stable balance of conventional
                            forces, and it brings weapons of unparalleled destructiveness to
                            volatile and developing regions. No short-term gain in <rs corresp="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic">export</rs> revenue or
                            regional prestige can be worth such risks.</p>
                        <p>It may be argued that the “genie is out of the bottle,” that technology
                            is already out of control. But technology can also be tapped for the <pb facs="0270" n="201" xml:id="pg_201"/> answers. Our policies can
                            diminish the insecurities that motivate proliferation. Responsible
                            <rs corresp="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic">export</rs> practices can reduce dangers. And international norms can
                            increase the cost of nuclear violations. With effort we can help to
                            assure that nuclear plowshares are not transformed into nuclear
                            swords.</p>
                        <p>In sum, the United States has a broad agenda of specific arms control
                            efforts and negotiations already underway or soon to be launched. The
                            charge that we are not interested in arms control or that we have cut
                            off communications with the Soviets on these issues is simply not
                            true.</p>
                        <p>The approach I have discussed today stands in a long and distinguished
                            American tradition. We are confident that it is a serious and realistic
                            approach to the enduring problems of arms control. The United States
                            wants a more secure and a more peaceful world. And we know that
                            balanced, verifiable arms control can contribute to that objective.</p>
                        <p>We are also confident that the Soviet leaders will realize the
                            seriousness of our intent. They should soon tire of the proposals that
                            seek to freeze <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>’s modernization of
                            theater <rs corresp="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic">nuclear weapons</rs> before it has even begun, while reserving for
                            themselves the advantages of hundreds of <gloss target="#t_SS20_1">SS–20</gloss>s already deployed. They should see that the
                            <rs corresp="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic">propaganda</rs> campaign intended to intimidate our allies and frustrate
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>’s modernization program
                            cannot and must not succeed. Arms control requires confidence, but it
                            also requires patience.</p>
                        <p>Americans dream of a peaceful world, and we are willing to work long and
                            hard to create it. This Administration is confident that its stance of
                            patient optimism on arms control expresses the deepest hopes and the
                            clearest thoughts of the American people.</p>
                        <p>It is one of the paradoxes of our time that the prospects for arms
                            control depend upon the achievement of a balance of arms. We seek to
                            negotiate a balance at less dangerous levels but meanwhile we must
                            maintain our strength. Let us take to heart <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1">John F. Kennedy</persName>’s reminder that negotiations “are not a
                            substitute for strength—they are an instrument for the translation of
                            strength into survival and peace.”<note n="12" xml:id="d56fn12">Then-Senator Kennedy made these remarks during a speech delivered
                                in the Senate on June 14, 1960.</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>