<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-04-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="96" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d96">
                        <head>96. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs (Clark) to the Counselor to the President (<persName corresp="#p_ME_1">Meese</persName>), the White House Chief of Staff
                            and Assistant to the President (Baker), and the Deputy White House Chief
                            of Staff and Assistant to the President (<persName corresp="#p_DMK_1">Deaver</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d96fn1">Source:
                                Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_GDR_1">David Gergen</persName>
                                Files, Subject File, Nuclear [Freeze] (1 of 8). No classification
                                marking. A stamped notation in the top left-hand corner of the
                                memorandum reads: “URGENT.” A copy was sent to <persName corresp="#p_GDR_1">Gergen</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-04-22">April 22,
                                1982</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Policy Offensive on Arms Control and the Anti-Nuclear
                                Movement</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The movement to educate Americans on the effect of <rs corresp="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic">nuclear weapons</rs> is
                            gaining momentum, and this week enters a crucial phase.<note n="2" xml:id="d96fn2">Clark’s reference is to Ground Zero Week, April
                                18–25. <persName corresp="#p_MRC_2">Molander</persName>, a former
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> staff member during the
                                    <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> and Carter
                                administrations and current Executive Director of a non-partisan
                                nuclear war education project known as “Ground Zero,” and others
                                worked to organize the event, which consisted of a variety of
                                seminars and other activities taking place in cities and on
                                university campuses throughout the United States. (Robert G. Kaiser,
                                “Movement Against Nuclear Arms Is Mushrooming,” <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>, April 11, 1982, pp. A1, A4, and Judith
                                Miller, “New Look at Stopping Nuclear War,” <hi rend="italic">New
                                    York Times</hi>, April 17, 1982, p. 8)</note> Ground Zero
                            activities are pictured as educational by its national <pb facs="0416" n="347" xml:id="pg_347"/> organizers, who claim to want to arouse
                            the citizenry rather than propose specific solutions, such as a nuclear
                            freeze. But under the Ground Zero umbrella are a variety of policy
                            proposals that would be detrimental to the United States. The next phase
                            for the movement could be toward promotion of policy solutions, as its
                            leaders try to keep up momentum. In any event, Ground Zero educational
                            activities leave the movement open for exploitation by others of all
                            stripes.</p>
                        <p>Our effort should be directed toward convincing Americans whose anxieties
                            are heightened by this movement that <hi rend="italic">our</hi> policy
                            solutions best meet their desire that the United States do something to
                            lessen the prospect of a nuclear holocaust. The time for us to do
                            something is now, and I agree with Dave Gergen that the communications
                            effort must be pulled together by the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> and White House.</p>
                        <p>We have begun. I will personally chair an <rs corresp="reciyQtOOb7NA9qHF" type="topic">interagency meeting</rs>, probably
                            this week, with a specific agenda to deal with the issues.<note n="3" xml:id="d96fn3">In an April 26 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_WCW_1">Weinberger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_REV_1">Rostow</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_WCZ_1">Wick</persName>, Clark indicated that an <rs corresp="reciyQtOOb7NA9qHF" type="topic">interagency meeting</rs>
                                would take place on April 28. Attached to Clark’s memorandum are a
                                meeting agenda and an undated paper entitled “Fact Sheets and Q’s
                                and A’s.” (Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_GDR_1">David
                                    Gergen</persName> Files, Subject File, Nuclear [Freeze] (1 of
                                8)</note> I have no illusions about solving our problem by asking
                            the bureaucracy to produce fact sheets on a lot of esoteric issues.
                            That’s just the kind of activity that could give everyone a feeling of
                            accomplishment, while actually not moving the ball an inch. My purpose
                            is to sensitize all departments to our concern about the direction of
                            public and international opinion on arms control, and to emphasize our
                            desire to take the lead in the policy solution phase of the movement’s
                            activities. I want to involve all departments in a coordinated strategy,
                            bringing their talents to bear on specific aspects of the problem.</p>
                        <p>In no way do I wish to foster a “we/they” syndrome, wherein we become
                            antagonists with <persName corresp="#p_MRC_2">Roger Molander</persName>
                            of Ground Zero, or <persName corresp="#p_GB_3">Billy
                                Graham</persName>,<note n="4" xml:id="d96fn4"><persName corresp="#p_GB_3">Graham</persName> had announced that he would
                                address an international disarmament conference in Moscow in May;
                                see Kenneth A. Briggs, “Growing Role for Churches in Disarmament
                                Drive,” <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, April 10, 1982, p.
                                3.</note> or 40 Catholic Bishops,<note n="5" xml:id="d96fn5">Presumable reference to Pax Christi, a Catholic peace organization
                                whose members included approximately 40–50 bishops.</note> or the
                            Mayor of Pella, Iowa.<note n="6" xml:id="d96fn6">In an April 16 article,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Wall Street Journal</hi> reporter John J.
                                Fialka described the planning for Ground Zero week in Pella, noting
                                that “after a year of organizing effort” Ground Zero was “about to
                                hit the streets in an attempt to reach the nonactivists. More
                                specifically, on Sunday [April 18] it will hit the town square here
                                when a small group of people, including Mayor C.B. ‘Babe’ Caldwell,
                                will erect a large sign near Tulip Tower, an imposing red, white and
                                blue structure that is normally used for Tulip Time, Pella’s
                                springtime festival of flowers and Dutch folk activity. The sign
                                will say: ‘If This Were Ground Zero, a One Megaton Nuclear Explosion
                                Would Totally Destroy Virtually Everything Within Two Miles of This
                                Spot—Instantly.’” (John H. Fialka, “Ground Zero: Town of Pella,
                                Iowa, Talks of Little Other Than Nuclear Attack: Group Favoring Arms
                                Freeze Stresses Atomic Horrors, But Some Ears Are Deaf: Refugees
                                From Des Moines?” <hi rend="italic">Wall Street Journal</hi>, April
                                16, 1982, pp. 1, 22)</note> The <pb facs="0417" n="348" xml:id="pg_348"/> broad public is being awakened to the problem
                            specialists in and out of government have dealt with for years: they are
                            scared to <rs corresp="recwKPXCPUAmFQyJr" type="topic">death</rs> at the prospect of nuclear war.<note n="7" xml:id="d96fn7">An unknown hand placed a checkmark in the left-hand
                                margin next to this sentence.</note> We should welcome the public’s
                            concern about this issue, as it parallels our own. But we must convince
                            the public that <hi rend="italic">our</hi> policies are best for dealing
                            with their newfound concerns: that unilateral disarmament by the United
                            States would only endanger us more; that progress can be made only when
                            the Soviets (where is <hi rend="italic">their</hi> anti-nuclear
                            movement, we should ask) respond to our fears about the growth of their
                            conventional and nuclear armaments. We should go beyond a static
                            restatement of our policy to generate real enthusiasm for new
                            initiatives as we unfold them, especially our proposals for <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>. Clearly, as Dave Gergen says, we
                            should emphasize the President’s role as a peacemaker, but we must not
                            let the Russians off the hook. We must also focus on concrete policy and
                            new initiatives; otherwise, our “peace offensive” will be met with
                            cynicism, both at home and abroad.</p>
                        <p>A strategy for the next six months could include these activities:</p>
                        <p>a) <hi rend="italic">Immediate efforts to enhance communication of the
                                President’s philosophy on arms control.</hi> The <rs corresp="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic">radio</rs> talk Saturday
                            was a beautiful step in the right direction—perfectly timed to present
                            the President’s views at the beginning of Ground Zero week, rather than
                            in reaction to it.<note n="8" xml:id="d96fn8">The President delivered
                                his weekly <rs corresp="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic">radio</rs> address from Camp David on April 17 at 12:06 p.m.
                                In it, he stated: “Today, I know there are a great many people who
                                are pointing to the unimaginable horror of nuclear war. I welcome
                                that concern. Those who’ve governed America throughout the nuclear
                                age and we who govern it today have had to recognize that a nuclear
                                war cannot be won and must never be fought. So, to those who protest
                                against nuclear war, I can only say, ‘I’m with you.’ Like my
                                predecessors, it is now my responsibility to do my utmost to prevent
                                such a war. No one feels more than I the need for peace.” (<hi rend="italic">Public Papers: Reagan, 1982</hi>, Book I, p.
                                487)</note> We should hammer his theme in the immediate future, as
                            in Gene Rostow’s speech at the National Press Club (Monday, April
                                19),<note n="9" xml:id="d96fn9">According to the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, Rostow’s speech “was quietly cancelled”
                                due to low reservation numbers: “The cancellation prompted agency
                                aides to call reporters Friday [April 16] with quotes from the
                                speech Mr. Rostow would have given, which was critical of proposals
                                for a nuclear arms freeze.” (Francis X. Clines and Warren Weaver
                                Jr., “Washington Talk: Briefing,” <hi rend="italic">New York
                                    Times</hi>, April 20, 1982, p. A22)</note> in network <rs corresp="recAsWFxRUa5DhtTM" type="topic">television</rs>
                            opportunities involving Administration spokesmen and friends, and in
                            Senate testimony on the <persName corresp="#p_JHM_1">Jackson</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_WJW_1">Warner</persName>
                            Amendment later this month.<note n="10" xml:id="d96fn10">Senate Joint
                                    <gloss target="#t_Res_1">Res.</gloss> 177, which <persName corresp="#p_JHM_1">Jackson</persName> and Warner introduced on
                                March 30, called for a long-term, rather than immediate, nuclear
                                freeze. For the text, see <hi rend="italic">Nuclear Arms Reduction
                                    Proposals: Hearings Before the Committee on Foreign Relations,
                                    United States Senate, Ninety-Seventh Congress, Second Session on
                                    S.J. Res 163, 171, 177, 191; S. Res. 242, 323, 343, 370, 391; S.
                                    Ex. Res. 5, 6; and <gloss target="#t_SCR_1">S. Con. Res.</gloss>
                                    81, April 29, 30, May 11, 12, and 13, 1982</hi> (Washington:
                                Government Printing Office, 1982), pp. 8–10.</note> This will mean
                            passing the word to our own people and briefing outside organizations
                            and individuals on a priority basis, one of the things I will stress at
                            our initial <rs corresp="reciyQtOOb7NA9qHF" type="topic">interagency meeting</rs>.<note n="11" xml:id="d96fn11">An unknown
                                hand placed a checkmark in the left-hand margin next to this
                                sentence.</note> The themes <pb facs="0418" n="349" xml:id="pg_349"/> must be kept basic. Any cabinet member or political official may
                            expect to receive questions in public on this issue; while we do not
                            want every appointee to become our spokesman, each senior official
                            should know how to handle the issue when it comes up.<note n="12" xml:id="d96fn12">An unknown hand placed a checkmark in the left-hand
                                margin next to this sentence.</note> More important, we urgently
                            need a small, but readily available, stable of articulate people who can
                            address the issue and guide the public to support our policy solutions.
                            We should identify these people, and promptly formalize a system for
                            providing our spokesmen on request—or better yet, on our own
                            initiative—for public speeches, <rs corresp="recAsWFxRUa5DhtTM" type="topic">television</rs> appearances, editorial board
                            conferences, <rs corresp="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic">media</rs> interviews, and group meetings.</p>
                        <p>b) <hi rend="italic">Communications with the activists.</hi> The fact
                            that the activists have our attention should be kept secret. We want to
                            demonstrate that we, too, are activists—seeking resolution to the same
                            concerns. As we organize to deal with the problem more coherently, we
                            should make it known without fanfare that we are doing so, rather than
                            have the <rs corresp="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic">media</rs> leap on the inevitable leak to portray us as secretive
                            and defensive. Also, I see no reason to rule out high-level meetings
                            soon with people like the Physicians for Social Responsibility group,
                                <persName corresp="#p_MRC_2">Molander</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GB_3">Billy Graham</persName>, or Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM_1">Jackson</persName>—meetings designed to show the
                            public that we are paying attention to the national message of concern,
                            and that we have the best program to deal with those concerns.<note n="13" xml:id="d96fn13">An unknown hand placed a checkmark in the
                                left-hand margin next to this sentence.</note> These meetings could
                            hint at new initiatives and solicit views and recommendations. Even if
                            the meetings do not reassure or convert the participants, they should at
                            least help reassure the concerned public as to our good faith and
                            reasonableness. (I am not suggesting meetings with those who are intent
                            on political exploitation of the issue and would gain more from the
                            exposure than would we. Questions of who to meet with, where, when, who
                            should represent us, etc., need careful examination, but with
                            dispatch.)</p>
                        <p>c) <hi rend="italic">Address the arms control issue in the President’s
                                <rs corresp="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic">foreign policy</rs> speech in May and again on <rs corresp="recAsWFxRUa5DhtTM" type="topic">television</rs> prior to the
                                European trip</hi>. The President should restate his policy as a
                            major, but not central, part of his overall <rs corresp="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic">foreign policy</rs> speech,
                            foreshadowing a new initiative in connection with <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>. Then, in line with Dave Gergen’s
                            suggestion, he should go on prime time to present his arms control
                            proposals and propose a date for <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>.<note n="14" xml:id="d96fn14">An unknown hand placed
                                a vertical line in the left-hand margin next to this and the
                                previous two sentences and placed a checkmark to the left of the
                                line. It is unclear if Clark’s reference to the “<rs corresp="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic">foreign policy</rs>
                                speech” is to the President’s May 9 Eureka College commencement
                                address, printed as Document 99.</note> This appearance should come
                            as soon as feasible after <pb facs="0419" n="350" xml:id="pg_350"/> the
                            <rs corresp="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic">foreign policy</rs> speech, and should be designed to capture the initiative
                            by its boldness, to give the President genuine national (and perhaps
                            bipartisan) <rs corresp="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic">foreign policy</rs> support as he goes to Europe. <hi rend="italic">The <rs corresp="recAsWFxRUa5DhtTM" type="topic">television</rs> talk and our associated efforts could
                                be the key to gaining public support from June to November</hi>. The
                            talk should be accompanied by an all-out communications and policy
                            coordination effort.<note n="15" xml:id="d96fn15">An unknown hand placed
                                a checkmark in the left-hand margin next to this sentence and the
                                first clause of the following sentence.</note> The logic in doing
                            this before Europe and before his <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                            speech seems overwhelming to me; but so is the task of agreeing on
                            policy proposals, coordinating with allies overseas and here, and
                            undertaking the communications effort in the relatively short time
                                left.<note n="16" xml:id="d96fn16">Reagan was scheduled to address
                                the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Special Session on
                                Disarmament on June 17; his address is printed as Document
                                106.</note> Needless to say, the reaction of the Soviets, other
                            countries, and our public to the President’s presentation will be
                            factors in deciding how to proceed during the European trip and at the
                                <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>. The point is that we must go on
                            the offensive and stay on the offensive, rather than waiting and
                            reacting—a situation likely to give the Soviets and anti-government
                            forces in this country the upper hand.</p>
                        <p>Getting the job done:</p>
                        <p>This strategy calls for a special organizational approach. Ideally, one
                            individual—a Special Advisor reporting directly to the President and
                            working closely with the National Security Advisor—should manage this
                            issue as a sole responsibility. He or she should establish a
                            senior-level steering committee of principal members of the White House
                            staff and Deputies in other key departments. This Special Advisor should
                            keep policy issues moving, orchestrate our actions, take over and push
                            the communications effort I have initiated, act as principal articulator
                            of policy in public appearances, and develop and lead a team of
                            spokesmen. There are drawbacks to this approach: we’d need an individual
                            with the abilities and stature of a <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry
                                Kissinger</persName> to make it work best; staffing and obtaining
                            cooperation from all departments could be problems. However, the
                            management advantages are obvious: there would be full time top-level
                            attention to the problem; Presidential involvement and control would be
                            insured. <rs corresp="recSWpZOc8YpkYHHD" type="topic">Public affairs</rs> benefits would also accrue—we would have a
                            competent and authoritative spokesman and team leader; we’d be giving
                            evidence of the serious attention the Administration is placing on the
                            issue. Another obvious advantage: the Special Advisor assignment would
                            not last forever. It would stop, at latest, with <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>The alternative to a Special Advisor is for the President to designate
                            someone with functional responsibility—the Vice President, Secretary of
                            State, National Security Advisor, or Director of <gloss target="#t_ACDA_1">ACDA</gloss>—to take <pb facs="0420" n="351" xml:id="pg_351"/> the lead and devote the major part of his time and
                            effort to the project. That route presents many opportunities for
                            failure.</p>
                        <p>In conclusion, what I have outlined is a proposed grand strategy to deal
                            with what may be the most important national security opportunity and
                            challenge of this Administration. With some hard work, it can be done.
                            Success in the next six months is well within our grasp. There is no
                            need for panic, only for planning and action. We should be fully in
                            agreement on this strategy before proceeding. Could we talk about it
                            briefly at everyone’s earliest convenience.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>