<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>16. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-11-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-11-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="rect4tQQCzcqVqdpO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98003467"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democratization</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recbfb6dc62c599a48" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Tobacco</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec9FMZD7j350k99B" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recCltKCJUXlGAvwr" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general">Claims issue</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-11-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-11-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="16"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d16">
                <head>16. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d16fn0"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, 611.69/12–1062. Confidential.
                        Prepared by <persName corresp="#p_AE2">Anderson</persName> on December 10
                        during a visit to Washington for consultations. A notation on the source
                        text reads: “typed in the Department.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Sofia</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1962-11-28">November 28,
                            1962</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Conversation with Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Todor
                            Zhivkov</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>I paid a protocol call on Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Todor
                        Zhivkov</persName> on November 28, 1962, having requested an appointment
                    prior to my departure for consultations in Washington. The Prime Minister
                    received me very cordially, and our conversation was animated and extended,
                    lasting fifty minutes. Also present were Deputy Foreign Minister Angelov,
                    Foreign Ministry interpreter Gerasimov who did all the interpreting and Cultural
                    Officer Bloomfield.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName> began by thanking me for my
                    visit and apologizing for his lack of diplomatic experience. He said that his
                    background had been entirely political, and that since this is his first
                    government post<note n="1" xml:id="d16fn1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName> was elected Prime Minister by
                        the Bulgarian National Assembly on November 19.</note> he has little
                    knowledge of diplomacy and protocol. He added that inasmuch as my background is
                    also mainly political we should be able to understand each other.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister referred to his visit to the US in 1960,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d16fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName> was a member of the Bulgarian
                        Delegation to the 15th session of the U.N. General Assembly in New York
                        September–December 1960.</note> saying that he had enjoyed it greatly and
                    that the State Department had been most helpful to him. He said that he had
                    become good friends with the policemen who had protected him (of whom he had
                    seen more than anyone else). He had been grateful for his tour of various
                    industrial plants, cities, etc. in the US. He said he had been able to see
                    everything he wanted.</p>
                <p>There were other preliminary niceties, while a waiter served us with Slivova and
                    Turkish coffee. The Prime Minister told a rather indelicate story about a
                    peasant from his home village, and I noted that the Foreign Office interpreter
                    hesitated slightly before repeating a somewhat vulgar “peasant” remark.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Bulgarian Government Shakeup</hi>
                </p>
                <p>After the usual toasts, I asked the Prime Minister to interpret for me the
                    sweeping changes in the Bulgarian Government which had just occurred.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="28" xml:id="pg_28"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName> began by saying that all these
                    changes had been fully reported and explained in the press, and that the meaning
                    of events was precisely that which had been publicized. (I am inclined to think
                    that the fact that <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName> stressed that
                    “all” had been published means the opposite.) He said that Prime Minister Yugov
                    and Tsankov had been ousted because of (1) Crimes against the State. (2)
                    Undermining Central Committee policies. (3) Hindering democratization of the
                    Country. (4) Yugov pursuing “careerist” tendencies. <persName corresp="#p_ZT1"
                        >Zhivkov</persName> maintained that these were the only reasons for Yugov’s
                    ouster. I felt that he stressed this a little too much, and was overly anxious
                    for me to believe that there were no other factors behind Yugov’s dismissal. He
                    said that Yugov had failed to carry out the directives of the Party, and
                    therefore he had to go, just the same as he, <persName corresp="#p_ZT1"
                        >Zhivkov</persName>, would have to take his hat and go if he failed to carry
                    out the Party’s orders. However, he added laughingly that he did not wish to
                    leave the office he had just assumed and therefore he intended to carry out the
                    Party’s directives.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName> went on to say that the many
                    other changes in the Government were necessitated not because of political
                    factors, but because of the need to bring new, young blood into the Government
                    and also to carry out the Party plans for more scientific and technical
                    development. The Prime Minister noted the presence of several academicians in
                    the new Government, and remarked also that the Party’s new plans require that
                    experts be placed in charge. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName>
                    pointed particularly to new Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_BK1"
                        >Bashev</persName>, stating that he is well qualified with a background in
                    ideological training and that he speaks four languages. He said that Former
                    Foreign Minister Lukanov and also the former Minister of Transport Dimitrov, for
                    example, were not dismissed because of any failures or wrongdoings (such as
                    Yugov’s and Tsankov’s) but only because of poor health and overly-long tenure.
                    He added that most of the former officials would be retained in the Government,
                    but given lesser jobs.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister stressed the need for Governmental reorganization, and
                    mentioned in particular that the Foreign Office will be reorganized.</p>
                <p>Since he had emphasized Governmental plans, I asked him if this meant that the
                    Government would assume a greater role than the Party in directing the affairs
                    of the country. He said not at all, simply that the Government will have to
                    carry out the policies and plans of the Party. He repeated that if he, as Prime
                    Minister, did not carry out Party orders then he would be thrown out, the same
                    as Yugov had been. (I believe that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ZT1"
                        >Zhivkov</persName> repeated this idea at least three times which makes me
                    think that he is somewhat uneasy over the way in which he has reached the
                    Premiership. Perhaps it is also a case of “uneasy is the head that <pb
                        facs="0051" n="29" xml:id="pg_29"/> wears the crown”.) Yesterday it was
                    Yugov, today it is <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName>, and
                    tomorrow—?</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Bulgarian Internal and Foreign Policy</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I then asked the Prime Minister what would be the principal changes one could
                    expect in the internal and external policies of the new government. His reply as
                    regards internal policies followed the same lines he had already mentioned,
                    greater scientific and technical development carrying out the 20-year Plan etc.
                    He was not specific, and did not mention agriculture. He referred briefly to the
                    need to develop transportation and industry, but dwelt mostly on generalities
                    about carrying out the Party’s directives and the 20-year Plan which had all
                    been published, he said.</p>
                <p>Then Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName> turned to the question of
                    foreign policy which, he said, would continue to follow the same lines of
                    peaceful coexistence and friendship with all nations. He said: “We are even
                    trying to improve relations with Turkey, which is an ally of the US. While the
                    Ottoman Turkey oppressed Bulgaria for 500 years, we do not hold this against the
                    present Turkish Government, with which we want good relations.” Although Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName> spoke for several minutes
                    about Bulgaria’s continuing to adhere to “peaceful coexistence” policies, he did
                    not mention the Soviet Union (or Yugoslavia) at this point, nor indeed
                    throughout the entire conversation.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Relations with the United States</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I asked the Prime Minister how the new Government’s foreign policy might affect
                    Bulgaria’s relations with the United States. He began by replying emphatically
                    that he wants to improve relations with the US, in particular in the economic
                    and political spheres.</p>
                <p>As for political relations with the US, the Prime Minister said that the first
                    problem is that Bulgaria is a small, poor nation and the US is a great, rich
                    one. He said that Bulgaria is sensitive about being ignored or treated as if it
                    were not important. He said that Bulgaria has felt that the US had not regarded
                    Bulgaria with the principle of equality which even small nations deserve. He
                    declared that in spite of our ideological differences the US had nothing to fear
                    from Bulgaria, and that Bulgaria is not going to try to bolshevize the US. He
                    added that neither is Bulgaria afraid of the US and it does not feel that we
                    will be able to exert much influence on it. He said that I had been in this
                    country several months now and must be aware of the feelings of the people.
                    (This was apparently a veiled reference to Bulgarian-Soviet attachments,
                    implying that the people heartily support the Soviet Union.)</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName> then went on to say that economic
                    relations are the most important of all, and that up until now there has been
                    practically no <pb facs="0052" n="30" xml:id="pg_30"/> trade with the US. He
                    said that Bulgaria’s export potentialities to the US would be, at best, “but a
                    drop in the sea” to a big country like the US, and he could not understand why
                    there could not be more trade between the two countries.</p>
                <p>I replied that this would be difficult to develop, but not impossible. I pointed
                    out that the U.S. produces great surpluses of tobacco and foods, which might be
                    the very things Bulgaria would like to sell to us. His response was almost
                    pleading, “But it surely should be possible for Bulgaria to sell some canned
                    foods and attar of roses oil!”</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister then introduced the subject of the financial claims
                    negotiations which he said he understands have been an obstacle in improving
                    relations with the U.S. He declared that this problem must be settled now, and
                    that so far as Bulgaria is concerned this should not be difficult. No amount of
                    money is too great to pay for the improvement of relations between the U.S. and
                    Bulgaria, he said, whether it is $350,000 or $10 million! Even for Bulgaria,
                    which is a poor country, no amount is too great for improving our relations. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName> looked directly at Minister
                    Angelov, laughed and said, “Perhaps I will get into trouble with the Foreign
                    Office diplomats, but this is what I think! The next time you and I meet to
                    discuss these questions, we should not have any Foreign Office official present,
                    only our interpreters.”</p>
                <p>Later on he again said, “You can go to the Protocol Section for the routine
                    things, but when you really want to discuss something serious and worthwhile and
                    of some importance, then come directly to me. We can talk it over. If you want
                    to talk to me as a friend on any kind of subject, then I will be only too happy
                    to see you any time and we will be able to reach a decision.”</p>
                <p>Finally the Prime Minister mentioned that cultural relations should be improved
                    too but that he does not view them as of the same importance as economic and
                    political. He made a reference to Bulgaria’s inability to finance an American
                    “ensemble” in exchange for the Kutev Ensemble’s forthcoming tour of the U.S.,
                    adding that the “principle of reciprocity” must be observed. (Apparently Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName> was not well informed on this
                    question.) He clearly does not attach much importance to cultural relations.</p>
                <p>In my response to the Prime Minister’s various points I emphasized my belief that
                    the development of relations between the U.S. and Bulgaria must proceed in all 3
                    areas—political, economic and cultural—which are interrelated. I referred to our
                    country’s traditional and firm belief in the sovereignty and independence of
                    small nations, whose rights we would continue to respect. I said that it was
                    true that relations had not been good between Bulgaria and the U.S., but that
                    this was due first of all to world political factors beyond his control or mine.
                    I also pointed out that geographically Bulgaria is remote from the U.S. and <pb
                        facs="0053" n="31" xml:id="pg_31"/> that people in the U.S. simply have not
                    known much about Bulgaria. Now the possibilities for communications are
                    improving, I said, and we should take advantage of this period.</p>
                <p>As for the financial claims issue, I said I heartily agree with him that this
                    problem should be settled forthwith, and that I was delighted to hear him say
                    that it should not be difficult to conclude an agreement. I said that it had
                    seemed most unfortunate that U.S.-Bulgarian relations had been static, simply
                    because of a difference of a few hundred thousand dollars. I hoped that we could
                    settle this issue at once and move on to more constructive relations.</p>
                <p>I stated my belief that cultural relations are important and have a bearing on
                    political and economic development, since people must get to know each other
                    better if trade and political understanding are to increase.</p>
                <p>Just before concluding our discussion, I asked the Prime Minister whether a new
                    Bulgarian Minister to the U.S. has been chosen yet. He replied that due to the
                    pressures of the Party Congress there had not been time to select a new
                    candidate, but he assured me there will be a good man named soon.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister asked me to convey his greetings to President <persName
                        corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>, for whom he expressed high regard and
                    respect, and to inform President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>
                    of Bulgaria’s desire for better economic and political relations with the
                    U.S.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName> also asked me to visit him upon
                    my return from the U.S. and added that he would always be at my disposal. He
                    expressed the hope that we could settle many problems, and work together to
                    improve relations between Bulgaria and the U.S.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Personal Observations and Comments</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName> has an unassuming manner, at
                    first impressing one as a quiet man. However, he is also talkative and laughs
                    robustly and often. He may affect a <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchevian</persName> style in his deliberate attempt to be hearty, and
                    at times play the buffoon. He wagged his finger at me to emphasize a point, a
                    mannerism to which I believe <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                    is given.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName> spoke proudly of his peasant
                    origins and his native village, which is famous for slivova and
                    slivova-drinking. His manners are a bit crude, although he was courteous and
                    most cordial to me.</p>
                <p>I believe that a certain rapport was established between us. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName>’s personality is quite different than
                    Yugov’s, who impressed me as a hard, cruel, cold and ruthless man. <persName
                        corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName>, by contrast, is capable of acting in an
                    affable, flexible manner. He does not convey an impression of great strength or
                    intelligence. One would judge him to be a “follower” rather than a “leader”,
                    which may be significant in view of his devotion to <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> and the Soviet line.</p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="32" xml:id="pg_32"/>
                <p>I was struck by <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName>’s frequent
                    references to his own inexperience, “poor abilities” and “incapable qualities”.
                    Either he must have deep feelings of inferiority, or else the opposite belief in
                    his superiority which he tries to conceal by frequent self-denigrations.
                    Whatever the case, his manner and bearings are those of a modest man.</p>
                <p>Whether <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName>’s emphatic assertions of
                    his willingness to settle the claims issue now at whatever the cost represent a
                    genuine determination on his part, I cannot be sure. He appeared to mean what he
                    said, but only time will tell. I believe that we should soon test his
                    intentions.</p>
                <p>I also believe that <persName corresp="#p_ZT1">Zhivkov</persName>’s emphasis on
                    Bulgaria’s sensitivity and desire to be treated “as an equal” and not to be
                    ignored, offer some possibilities for the U.S. which I hope to exploit.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AE2">
                            <hi rend="strong">Eugenie Anderson</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="3" xml:id="d16fn3">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">American Minister</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
