<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>160. Telegram From Secretary of State Rusk to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d160</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">160</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-05-05T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-05-05T03:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recSkg5rdjWW1fsS7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Spare parts</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Detente</term>
                    <term ref="rec5leqjXNtlx0kjy" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="outer-space"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85096156"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Outer space</term>
                    <term ref="recujbZvPfRFtp7HU" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general">Nuclear test
                        ban</term>
                    <term ref="recHEnRX74raOryAY" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044893"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Espionage</term>
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="western-hemisphere" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Western Hemisphere</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-05-05T03:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-05-05T03:00:00-05:00" n="160"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d160">
                <head>160. Telegram From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD1" type="from"
                        >Rusk</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d160fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, ORG 7 <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>. Confidential; Priority.
                        Repeated to Zagreb. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>
                        visited Yugoslavia May 4–5 on his return from a trip to South Asia.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Belgrade</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-05-05T09:00:00+01:00">May 5, 1963, 9 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_SECTO1">Secto</gloss> 44. At 1700 Secretary met Foreign
                    Minister <persName corresp="#p_PK1">Popovic</persName>. Also present were Under
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_NM1">Nikezic</persName>, Assistant Secretary
                    Lekic and Director Petric. Meeting lasted one hour and half.</p>
                <p>After agreement discuss bilateral and then broader international issues,
                    Secretary began by stating US Government had serious desire steadily improve our
                    relations with Yugoslav Government. While recognizing there are and will
                    continue to be differences in points of view some questions, it was our hope
                    that each side would work toward resolving them. Immediate problem of <gloss
                        target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> was before Congress and it was our hope that
                    discussion there would help clarify our relations. Secretary said he could not
                    give any clear assurances at this time what Congress would do but President and
                    he had talked with congressional leaders and there was reason to expect that
                    some who had been unhelpful in past might be silent this year. He pointed out we
                    had not carried out the provision in the Trade Act Law withdrawing <gloss
                        target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> and would not as long as Congress has the
                    matter under consideration. Secretary said it would assist us in handling matter
                    on Washington scene if matter of public statements and exchanges between
                    governments could be avoided.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PK1">Popovic</persName> replied he did not have much
                    comment now; history of matter well known; Yugoslavs regarded it as an important
                    problem not because of economic substance but because it was a political problem
                    which until solved threatens the whole fabric of our relations. He knew it was
                    not an act by US Government and recognized difficulties in correcting matter.
                    Yugoslavs were encouraged by information they had received that difficulties
                    might be less than before, which they attributed to efforts of most
                    authoritative members US Government. Expressed optimism that matter was on way
                    to be solved. Pointed out that Yugoslavs had refrained from too negatively
                    presenting matter before Yugoslav public opinion. They had congressional problem
                    much in mind and would continue to show restraint in hope problem can be
                    solved.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PK1">Popovic</persName> then raised question of Yugoslav
                    emigre activities in US noting that US had already taken some measure to
                    ameliorate situation. Yugoslavs were not asking for an unreal maximum and
                    recognized that under American law the US restricted as to what could be done.
                    However, Yugoslavs hope that most extreme actions can be discouraged in <pb
                        facs="0373" n="351" xml:id="pg_351"/> order that relations not be affected
                    in a negative manner. Solution of this problem could only help both sides.</p>
                <p>Secretary commented he aware of incidents in past for which we had expressed
                    regrets. We would continue carefully follow this matter but there was limit to
                    what we can do not only because of constitutional provisions but because US was
                    nation of emigres. Within range of free speech and freedom of press, we will
                    take action to prevent anything harmful to Yugoslav officials or property or
                    which could injure relations between two countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PK1">Popovic</persName> then raised question sales
                    military spare parts. Pointed out there had already been failure to meet certain
                    contractual obligations and this created difficulty for normal function Yugoslav
                    Army. Secretary replied he was familiar with this problem and hoped a solution
                    can be found. Pointed out that this solution for US has two points: the
                    technical legal point under the law of certain findings which the President must
                    make but it was also a political matter as we must consult with congressional
                    leaders and thus it has some political connection with problem <gloss
                        target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss>. Promised to take up question when he returned
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>Discussion then turned to international issue with Secretary remarking that we
                    were trying to reach agreement on one of two points with Soviet Union though we
                    don’t see any possibility of a broad detente. Secretary cited outer space,
                    recent message to <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> from
                    Macmillan and President on nuclear test ban, non proliferation and Berlin.<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d160fn1">Dated April 15; for text, see <ref
                            target="frus1961-63v06#d93">vol. VI, Document 93</ref>.</note> With
                    regard to nuclear test ban expressed belief that number of inspections should
                    not be allowed to stand in way of achieving agreement. Until we could obtain
                    agreement on character of inspections it relatively meaningless to discuss
                    number. Believed this could be worked out so that espionage would not come into
                    question. Described dangers of armaments race and thought agreement on ban still
                    in national interest of three countries. Secretary stated we had been
                    disappointed that temperature of <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName>’s interest in nuclear test ban seemed to have fallen
                    since last December.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PK1">Popovic</persName> noted Yugoslavs were not so well
                    qualified to talk about this question. Said they were not enough acquainted with
                    latest proposal to have definite opinion. Yugoslavs appreciated dangers in sense
                    Secretary spoke about arms race and danger of other nations arming themselves
                    with nuclear weapons. Yugoslavs had impression that Western side insisted too
                    much on inspection and USSR too much on espionage.</p>
                <p>They were hopeful two sides could find basis for agreement but had impression
                    both sides seemed to be more rigid than warranted. Yugoslavs <pb facs="0374"
                        n="352" xml:id="pg_352"/> unable judge Secretary’s estimate Soviets had
                    cooled off on test ban treaty.</p>
                <p>After brief general discussion disarmament Secretary brought up question of Cuba
                    pointing out potential dangers as long as Soviet forces present on island.
                    Observed there were two non-negotiable points, i.e., military and political
                    connection of Cuba with Moscow, and illegal intrusion of Cuba into affairs of
                    other LA countries. Reviewed history of Castro movement and commented Castro
                    appeared to have abandoned his original commitments and turned revolution into
                    something else. We did not oppose Castro just for historical reasons but problem
                    related to present security needs. So long as Soviet troops are there Cuba will
                    continue to be a difficult question.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PK1">Popovic</persName> expressed recognition importance
                    US attached to Cuban question and as unresolved question it constituted threat
                    to peace not only in that region but to world. Yugoslavs considered real social
                    revolution had taken place in Cuba and that the regime there represents basic
                    aspirations of Cuban people. Recognized this viewpoint different from
                    Secretary’s. Pointed out that even before Soviet troops or arms were introduced
                    into Cuba differences between US and Cuba were great. Asked if modus vivendi
                    could not be found which might then eventually lead to a solution.</p>
                <p>Secretary replied though we did not know too much about attitude and thinking
                    present Cuban regime, we knew that there were those who believed Cuba should
                    have close ties with Soviet Union while others believed that ties should be with
                    Peiping. What US did not find were those who want reconciliation with the other
                    LA countries. Hence the Secretary was not hopeful of a solution particularly in
                    the light of two non-negotiable points he had mentioned.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KGF1">Kennan</persName> pointed out US had never
                    made an issue of nationalized properties in Cuba and that it was not question of
                    social revolution but rather a question of Cuban attitude toward the US and
                    toward their responsibilities to other countries in Western hemisphere.
                    Secretary noted 1959 Castro visit to US and our attempt to establish good
                    relations. However, by May 1960 it was evident Castro rejected all overtures and
                    a great many of Castro’s old associates in revolutionary movement had abandoned
                    him. Cuba was a highly exposed nerve to the American people and the Yugoslavs
                    should know that last October was a unique moment on two counts, i.e., for the
                    first time US and Soviet forces confronted each other and for the first time
                    their leaders faced the possibility of general nuclear war. Emphasized this
                    could not help but affect all our relationships until problem was solved.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PK1">Popovic</persName> said Yugos properly appraised
                    dangers in this situation. Noted that US making efforts calm situation which had
                    not been accepted by “certain circles” in US. Secretary replied it was true
                    President <pb facs="0375" n="353" xml:id="pg_353"/> was trying to keep country
                    calm and realistic on these matters but this was not easy on issue which struck
                    so deep in American opinion. Emphasized that Yugoslavs should understand depth
                    of feeling in US on Cuban question.</p>
                <p>Discussion ended with the brief description at request of <persName
                        corresp="#p_PK1">Popovic</persName> of Secretary’s impressions his visit to
                    Pakistan and India in particular in regard to Kashmir problem.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
