<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-11-20T22:07:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-11-20T22:07:00-05:00" n="199" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d199">
                        <head>199. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Finland</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d199fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 660E.61/11–2061. Secret; <gloss target="#t_NIACT1">Niact</gloss>; Limit Distribution; Verbatim Text. Drafted by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BWC1">Burdett</persName> and cleared by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName>. Repeated to London and
                                Moscow.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-11-20T22:07:00-05:00">November 20, 1961, 10:07 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>167. Ambassador requested deliver message below from President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_KU1">Kekkonen</persName> soonest. Message should be
                            conveyed orally and written communication not left. Approach should be
                            made inconspicuously. We wish to avoid public knowledge that American
                            Ambassador saw President immediately before his departure to meet
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>. Should press
                            learn of your meeting suggest you say only that you called to obtain
                            President <persName corresp="#p_KU1">Kekkonen</persName>’s views. You
                            should agree with <persName corresp="#p_KU1">Kekkonen</persName>
                            beforehand on this line to be followed with press in case of queries or
                            leaks.</p>
                        <p>“On the eve of your departure for Novosibirsk I am sending you this
                            private message so that you may not be in doubt of the position of <pb facs="0442" n="420" xml:id="pg_420"/> the United States. It will
                            receive no publicity whatever in my country, for I am mindful of your
                            desire not to be embarrassed by public comments from others which might
                            be misconstrued as infringements on Finnish neutrality.</p>
                        <p>In our joint communique of October 16 in Washington I expressed American
                            understanding for Finland’s policy of neutrality, our firm intention
                            scrupulously to respect that chosen course, and the necessity for all
                            nations to avoid interference in the affairs of Finland. This remains
                            the basis of the relations between the United States and your
                            country.</p>
                        <p>You will appreciate that our concern in this matter derives not alone
                            from our great interest in the welfare of your country. My Government,
                            and other Western Governments, have accepted Finnish neutrality in all
                            good faith. We have placed on ourselves a solemn obligation to respect
                            that neutrality at all times and in all ways. In our own national
                            interest we have to expect that in turn Finland will in fact be truly
                            neutral.</p>
                        <p>I realize the doubts and anxieties which you and the Finnish people are
                            now suffering as the memories of 1939 return to you. However, today
                            peace prevails and we have in the United Nations a forum where the
                            strength of world opinion is brought to bear against the employment of
                            force. Furthermore given the close interrelationship of all elements in
                            the present world situation, the overwhelming deterrent power of the
                            Free World, of which the Soviet Union is well aware, provides all
                            nations assurance against resort to arms.</p>
                        <p>I want to assure you of the readiness of my country to give Finland our
                            political and economic support. We stand ready to extend commercial and
                            economic assistance in the event of economic pressure against Finland
                            designed to secure political compliance. We are prepared, when
                            opportune, to speak out firmly in behalf of Finland’s security and
                            independence. We would be willing to carry to the United Nations actions
                            seeming to threaten your country’s independence, depriving you of the
                            right to follow your chosen course of neutrality.</p>
                        <p>I am sure that the unity of all patriotic Finns, irrespective of party,
                            when their country is threatened is a great source of strength
                            underlying Finland’s resolve to determine its own destiny.”</p>
                        <p>Report date, hour of delivery. Further instructions follow on US
                            policy.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RD1"><hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>