<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-12-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-12-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="28" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                        <head>28. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d28fn0">Source: Department of State, Central Files, POL
                                Hung-US. Confidential. Drafted by Squire and approved in <gloss target="#t_M1">M</gloss> on December 20.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1963-12-14">December 14, 1963</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>US-Hungarian Relations</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">United States</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>,
                                        Under Secretary for Political Affairs</item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_VH1">Harold C.
                                            Vedeler</persName>, Director, Office of EE
                                        Affairs</item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName>Frederick M. Chapin</persName>, Office of
                                        the Under Secretary for Political Affairs</item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName>Christopher A. Squire</persName>, OIC
                                        Hungarian Affairs</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Hungary</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item><persName corresp="#p_MP1">Peter Mod</persName>, First
                                        Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs</item>
                                    <item><persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Janos Radvanyi</persName>,
                                        Charge d’Affaires a.i., Hungarian Legation</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>At his own request, Hungarian First Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs
                                <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Peter Mod</persName>, accompanied by
                            Charge <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Janos Radvanyi</persName>, called on
                            Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> on
                            December 14. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> is returning
                            to Hungary on December 17 at the close of the 18th <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> session, where he has been head of
                            the Hungarian Delegation to the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>. He
                            stated that he wished to take advantage of a “courtesy call” before his
                            departure to continue discussions that had begun with Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> at the time of President
                                <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>’s funeral but which
                            had been interrupted when <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> had
                            to return to New York.<note n="1" xml:id="d28fn1">No record of these
                                discussions has been found.</note></p>
                        <p>After initial amenities, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName>
                            said that he would like to take the opportunity, now that he was in
                            Washington, to talk further with Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> about relations between Hungary and the United
                            States. Although he did not know in detail the daily matters of concern
                            between the two countries, he knew the general feeling in the Foreign
                            Ministry. Relations between Hungary and the US, he continued, had
                            recently developed in a good way. The relation of the two countries’ UN
                            delegations were more normal. During the recent visit to the US of the
                            Hungarian First Deputy Minister of Agriculture, <persName>Janos
                                Hont</persName>, Hungary saw with some satisfaction the good will
                            towards that visit on the part of the US Administration and its helpful
                            attitude. In the matter of the wheat and corn purchases, the US
                            Government also gave evidence of helpfulness and good will.</p>
                        <p>On Hungary’s part, continued Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName>, there had also been signs of improvement. Travel
                            restrictions had been abolished in Hungary. He <pb facs="0081" n="59" xml:id="pg_59"/> had recently noted with pleasure that the US Charge
                            had called on the Hungarian Foreign Minister in Budapest.<note n="2" xml:id="d28fn2">On December 5, Jones delivered a message stating
                                President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>’s intention
                                to follow the policies of the <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> administration. Jones reported on the
                                meeting in telegram 351 from Budapest, December 5. (Department of
                                State, Central Files, POL 15–1 US-<persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>)</note> The atmosphere, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> felt, in regard to US-Hungarian
                            relations was better than at any time in the last few years, and it was
                            his personal feeling that this atmosphere now made it appropriate to
                            talk about the development of US-Hungarian relations.</p>
                        <p>Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> noted that the
                            US Charge in Budapest had been talking over, with the Hungarian Foreign
                            Office, various matters which the US thought would assist in the
                            improvement of US-Hungarian relations. Certain useful steps had already
                            been taken, Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>
                            continued, but other further steps remain to be taken. These steps,
                            which the US Charge was authorized to discuss with the Hungarian Foreign
                            Office, were the same ones outlined to <persName>Charge
                                Radvanyi</persName> in Washington on October 20, 1962<note n="3" xml:id="d28fn3">See <ref target="#d15">Document 15</ref>.</note> by
                            Deputy Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DR1">Davis</persName>.
                            The subjects include the problem of dual nationals, the separation of
                            families, and the ability of American citizens to see their families in
                            Hungary. While there had been a decided improvement in travel to and
                            from Hungary recently, certain members of the families of American
                            citizens still remain in Hungary separated from their relatives. There
                            was also the question of the size of the US mission in Budapest and the
                            restrictions on its personnel. Other problems were the claims relating
                            to US Government property in Budapest, as well as the post-war claims of
                            private American citizens which have already been settled in most
                            Eastern European countries.</p>
                        <p>Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> added that he
                            had told Mr. <persName>Kadar</persName> in Moscow<note n="4" xml:id="d28fn4"><persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>’s
                                July 15–25 visit to the Soviet Union concluded with an agreement on
                                the text of the Nuclear Test Ban Treaty. No record of this
                                conversation has been found.</note> that, although it was not
                            directly a bilateral issue, the question of Cardinal Mindszenty would be
                            an important one in the improvement of US-Hungarian relations. A problem
                            that the Hungarian Government wanted settled, on the other hand, related
                            to Hungary’s desire to sell meat to the US so that Hungary might expand
                            its trade. This involved inspection procedures to satisfy US sanitary
                            standards. The US had rather strict rules on the standards of meat
                            production, which applied all over the world, not just to Hungary. The
                            US had worked this problem out with Poland, and some progress, Governor
                                <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> understood, had been
                            made in this matter with Hungary. The major point was that certain steps
                            should be taken: the specific steps should be discussed in Budapest with
                            the US charge.</p>
                        <pb facs="0082" n="60" xml:id="pg_60"/>
                        <p>The subject of claims, said Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>, had not yet been under active discussion
                            between the US and Hungary. The US had property in Hungary which it
                            wanted to rehabilitate, but first the Hungarian squatters who presently
                            occupied the premises must be moved out. To make these properties
                            available to the US the cooperation of the Hungarian authorities was
                            necessary. The US felt that these foregoing points were very important
                            and action should be taken on them if relations between the two
                            countries were to make progress. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> agreed that certain points were very important.</p>
                        <p>The US, continued Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>, had watched and was watching with interest
                            various liberalization steps that Hungary had taken, including the
                            general amnesty of March 1963. This was encouraging to the US. The US
                            was of course interested in the development of US-Hungarian relations,
                            and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> could repeat to his
                            Ministry in Budapest that the American charge in Budapest was fully
                            authorized to discuss these matters. Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> concluded that the question of
                            Cardinal Mindszenty had come up quite informally in Moscow in his
                            discussions with Premier Kadar (during the negotiating and signing of
                            the Partial Test Ban Agreement).</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> said that as in Governor
                                <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>’s discussions with
                            Premier Kadar, the position of the Hungarian Government with regard to
                            Cardinal Mindszenty was clear. The problem of Cardinal Mindszenty, as
                            well as other Church-State matters, was the subject of negotiations
                            between Hungary and the Vatican. These negotiations were proceeding in a
                            good atmosphere, and he thought that some time in the near future the
                            problem of the Cardinal, as well as the other Church-State problems,
                            would be settled.</p>
                        <p>As to the normalization of relations between the US and Hungary, Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> continued, the questions
                            connected with the person of the Cardinal could be settled. All pending
                            questions could be settled by direct negotiations, even the question of
                            claims, if approached within the framework of the general problem of
                            commercial and economic relations between the US and Hungary. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> said he felt it necessary
                            for the US and Hungary to sit down and talk over the claims problem. As
                            to diplomatic relations, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName>
                            noted that the US must surely be aware that all its allies in Western
                            Europe were raising their missions in Budapest to the level of
                            embassies. It seemed to him, said Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName>, that the US was not in accord with the general
                            diplomatic situation in Budapest, because the diplomatic establishment
                            maintained by the US was of third rank, being headed not by an
                            Ambassador or Minister but by a charge. In conclusion, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> doubted that this situation was very
                            satisfactory even for the US.</p>
                        <pb facs="0083" n="61" xml:id="pg_61"/>
                        <p>Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> pointed out that
                            the US had its own special problems with Hungary, some of which he had
                            just mentioned. Additionally, in its relations with Hungary the US had
                            historically been influenced by the especially friendly feelings of the
                            American people for the Hungarian people. So many Hungarians had
                            emigrated to the US, there was perhaps a more personal feeling for the
                            welfare of the Hungarian people in the US than in other Western
                            countries for historical and other reasons. The first problem that had
                            to be solved, Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>
                            said, was the normalization of US-Hungarian relations. The raising of
                            the US Legation in Budapest to an Embassy must remain a matter for
                            future developments. Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> pointed out that the US had legations in
                            Bulgaria and Rumania, and embassies in Poland and Czechoslovakia. US
                            relations with Poland had improved steadily, and the US has done a great
                            deal for Poland, particularly with regard to supplying food. It was
                            necessary only to refer to the case of Poland to understand how
                            relations between the other Eastern European governments could be
                            developed with the US, if those countries were of a mind to do so. To
                            develop such a relationship required give, as well as take, on the part
                            of the Hungarian Government. The US was glad to note the prog-ress that
                            Hungary had made, continued Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>, but further steps still needed to be taken by
                            that Government. The US was certainly interested in contributing to the
                            improvement of US-Hungarian relations, and Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> added that he was very glad
                            for the opportunity to talk over the matter of relations with Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName>. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> added that Hungary, too, was
                            interested in better relations and was prepared to discuss the
                            subject.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_VH1">Vedeler</persName> said that the basic
                            points on which the US feels improvement of relations with Hungary
                            depends were still those outlined to charge <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Radvanyi</persName> on October 20, 1962 by Deputy Assistant
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DR1">Davis</persName>. Both in Budapest
                            and Washington, discussions between the two Governments on this subject
                            had followed the outlines of the October 20 discussion. These points
                            were embodied in a “talking paper”, a copy of which was informally
                            provided Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Radvanyi</persName> at the time
                            of that discussion.</p>
                        <p>Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> asked Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> if there had been anything
                            in the recent <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> Session which had
                            seemed of special importance to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> at the time. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> answered that the most important fact was the
                            absence of the Hungarian question from the agenda of the 18th <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> session. Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> said that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> had undoubtedly noticed the US
                            position on that question, and the fact that the US has decided to move
                            ahead. He added that he thought Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> should tell the Foreign Ministry why the US asked
                            more of Hungary. The American people had strong feelings for the
                            Hungarian people. America was made up of people from all countries in
                            East and West Europe. As Ambassador <pb facs="0084" n="62" xml:id="pg_62"/> to Moscow during World War II, Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> said he had addressed himself
                            more to the subject of the future status of Poland than to any other
                            subject: Poland was a symbol to the American people. The US also had
                            special feelings for the people of Hungary, which reflected the way the
                            US people felt towards US relations with Eastern Europe.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> said that the Hungarian
                            Government knew the obstacles in the way of bettering relations, and he
                            thought that these obstacles were now largely removed.</p>
                        <p>Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> mentioned that
                            US relations with Yugoslavia were of a special nature, a fact stemming
                            basically from Yugoslavia’s independence of outside domination. Ever
                            since the time of President Wilson, the US had been particularly strong
                            for the self-determination and independence of peoples from outside
                            domination. It appeared to be a policy on the part of the Kremlin to
                            favor more self-determination in Eastern Europe. On this question
                            Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> had recently
                            said that when the child grows, he becomes harder to control. President
                                <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> in his speech at
                            American University on June 10, 1963,<note n="5" xml:id="d28fn5">For
                                text, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the
                                    United States: <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">John F.
                                        Kennedy</persName>, 1963</hi>, pp. 459–464.</note> had very
                            important things to say on this subject. Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> has called it the best
                            speech since the time of President Roosevelt. The speech had been very
                            fundamental, and very frank, and Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> hoped that we would go down the road to which
                            President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> had pointed at
                            that time. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> said he was
                            convinced that this speech had been understood correctly all over the
                            world, and that what he was talking about, namely the improvement of
                            US-Hungarian relations, was in line with that speech.</p>
                        <p>The meeting then closed. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName>
                            agreed to Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>’s
                            proposal that the press be informed merely that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mod</persName> had paid a courtesy call, and
                            discussions of mutual interest which had been broached at the time of
                            President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>’s funeral were
                            continued during this second meeting.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>