<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>69. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d69</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">69</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-12-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-12-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                    <term ref="receYZXmZSuptfeyg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">PL 480</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="recGiqhGF0E6qdj5q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2019102796"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Boycott</term>
                    <term ref="recILGIop3TL1t3vh" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85045811"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Common Market</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recDNr3fFoY74D9ro" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HqULsC7KBoXeW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-12-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-12-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="69"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d69">
                <head>69. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d69fn0"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, 411.4841/12–662. Confidential.
                        Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_KJ1">Katz</persName> and approved in <gloss
                            target="#t_U1">U</gloss> on January 3, 1963.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1962-12-06">December 6,
                            1962</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Call of the Polish Ambassador Regarding US-Polish Economic
                        Relations</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The Polish Ambassador, <persName corresp="#p_DE1">Edward
                            Drozniak</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName>Marian Dobrosielski</persName>, Counselor, Polish
                        Embassy</item>
                    <pb facs="0164" n="142" xml:id="pg_142"/>
                    <item>The Under Secretary</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KJ1">Julius L. Katz</persName>, EE</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Ambassador expressed satisfaction that after so many months of delay the PL
                    480 negotiations had finally begun. He wished to raise some general problems
                    connected with our bilateral relations, rather than the negotiations per se, but
                    he hoped his point of view would be taken into account before the negotiations
                    were finalized. The past months, he said, were full of expectation, promises and
                    disappointments. (He noted parenthetically that “some officials” of the State
                    Department said they had a right to be disappointed.) He realized, of course,
                    that US-Polish relations were affected by the international situation, and that
                    the Administration was not always able to do what it wished. Nevertheless, facts
                    were facts and the Polish Government could not depend upon intentions and
                    attitudes. The Ambassador said that he wished to call attention to these facts: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Despite a promise last December that there would be a further
                            agreement in the early Spring, and a further promise to begin
                            negotiations in June, nothing had happened until now. The promises of
                            last December and June had figured in Polish planning for animal
                            husbandry. When the U.S. did not provide grain Poland had to buy grain
                            at great cost in order to maintain the hog population. The result was a
                            grave deterioration in the Polish balance of payments.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Despite the Administration’s attitude, the Congress had voted to
                            withdraw <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> from Poland. This, together
                            with the boycott campaign against goods of Polish origin, was producing
                            a serious effect on Polish exports to the U.S.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Poland had expected to see a further development in bilateral
                            relations with the U.S., i.e., it expected a change in the Battle Act.
                            Today one hears nothing about this. The Ambassador noted in this
                            connection that he came here 18 months ago to work for improved
                            relations; now he has to work hard to maintain the status quo.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>To the problems with the U.S. must be added problems with Western
                            Europe, particularly the Common Market. Some 40% of Poland’s trade was
                            with the West, but because of trade difficulties and discrimination,
                                <persName corresp="#p_GW1">Gomulka</persName> had recently pointed
                            out that Poland’s dependence on trade with the West would have to be
                            reconsidered. In the past five years, Poland had lost $450 million
                            through a working of the terms of trade. This produced a terrible strain
                            on Poland’s balance of payments.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Poland’s agricultural situation this year was very bad. Grain
                            production was 2 million tons less than last year, potatoes were lower
                            by 7.5 million tons, and the vegetable and fruit crops were very bad.
                            Poland had to import between 2.7 and 2.9 million tons of grain this
                            year.</item>
                        <pb facs="0165" n="143" xml:id="pg_143"/>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>In these circumstances, Poland expected to receive a proposal from the
                            U.S. which would recognize Poland’s present situation and reflect the
                            traditional generosity of the U.S. The U.S. offer, however, was only $37
                            million. Without wishing to enter into details, the Ambassador wished to
                            point out that Poland had requested 1.5 million tons of grain. The U.S.
                            offered 400,000 tons of wheat. Yugoslavia, he noted, had recently
                            received 1.2 million tons of wheat. Similarly with respect to cotton,
                            Poland had requested 40,000 tons to cover its deficit. The U.S. offered
                            4,000 tons.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Summing up, the Ambassador said that in one of Poland’s most difficult years the
                    U.S. made its smallest proposal and had proposed conditions (cash purchase
                    commitments) which were beyond Poland’s capacity at the present time. On the
                    assumption that the U.S. shared Poland’s desire to advance our relations, he
                    requested: <list>
                        <label>1)</label>
                        <item>A public statement by the U.S. Government indicating the intention to
                            maintain the status quo regarding most-favored-nation treatment. This
                            would assure American firms who were uncertain about the future of trade
                            with Poland.</item>
                        <label>2)</label>
                        <item>A public statement, preferably by the President, opposing the boycott
                            campaign. The efforts of the Department in the form of letters and
                            interviews were appreciated but this was not enough.</item>
                        <label>3)</label>
                        <item>Efforts in the new Congress to amend the Battle Act.</item>
                        <label>4)</label>
                        <item>Review by the Under Secretary of the U.S. position in the PL 480
                            negotiations. The Ambassador hoped that the U.S. could examine the
                            situation not merely from a statistical point of view but from the
                            viewpoint of the Ambassador’s presentation.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The Under Secretary thanked the Ambassador for his clear and frank presentation
                    and assured him that we wished to have good relations with Poland. There were,
                    however, forces beyond control which limited the full possibilities. With regard
                    to the points made by the Ambassador, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1"
                        >Ball</persName> commented: <list>
                        <label>1)</label>
                        <item>The President had indicated in a speech in Buffalo his intention to
                            seek a change in the <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> provision of
                            the Trade Expansion Act.<note n="1" xml:id="d69fn1">For text of the
                                October 14 statement, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the
                                    Presidents of the United States: <persName corresp="#p_KJF1"
                                        >John F. Kennedy</persName>, 1962</hi>, pp. 782–783.</note>
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> noted that he personally
                            had done everything in his power to prevent the passage of this
                            provision.</item>
                        <label>2)</label>
                        <item>With regard to the boycott campaign, it was difficult to control the
                            attitudes of individuals. He was not sure that an official statement
                            would provide the answer to this problem, but said he would consider
                            this matter further.</item>
                        <pb facs="0166" n="144" xml:id="pg_144"/>
                        <label>3)</label>
                        <item>Regarding the PL 480 negotiations, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1"
                                >Ball</persName> recalled the difficult period in the Congress on
                            the Foreign Assistance Act which made it uncertain whether PL 480 could
                            continue. In the circumstances we could not move faster. He indicated
                            that he was aware of the general considerations in the negotiation but
                            was not familiar with the details. He stated that he would review our
                            position with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KJ1">Katz</persName> in the
                            light of the Ambassador’s remarks.</item>
                        <label>4)</label>
                        <item>With regard to the Battle Act problem Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1"
                                >Ball</persName> noted that we tried to get an amendment, had
                            succeeded in the Senate, but not in the House. It was pointed out that
                            the worsening of the international situation, notably in Berlin and
                            Cuba, was largely responsible for the failure to obtain passage of the
                            amendment.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Invited by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> to add any further
                    comments, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KJ1">Katz</persName> observed that the
                    Ambassador’s first fact was based upon a misapprehension, i.e., that we had
                    “promised” that there would be a further agreement for grain in the early
                    Spring. In fact we had agreed to consider further sales of wheat. We had
                    considered this and concluded that we were not in a position to offer additional
                    wheat and so informed the Ambassador at the time we signed a supplemental
                    agreement for cotton and rice. The current negotiations were a new round,
                    unrelated to last year’s negotiations.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> concluded the conversation
                    reiterating that he would review our position in the negotiations.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
