<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>73. Telegram From the Embassy in Poland to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d73</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">73</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-01-11T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-01-11T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recORcNZq5ClDOVNg" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046356"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exhibit</term>
                    <term ref="reccAEF3WTG3YVwaX" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85065851"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Industrial development</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-01-11T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-01-11T09:00:00-05:00" n="73"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d73">
                <head>73. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Poland</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d73fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 411.4841/1–1163. Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Warsaw</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-01-11T15:00:00+01:00">January 11, 1963, 3 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1071. Personal for Secretary from Ambassador. In view personal interest you have
                    shown in PL–480 negotiations with Poles I am taking liberty of setting forth my
                    views regarding them.</p>
                <p>I am disturbed by increase in our new PL–480 proposals to Poles from 37.1 million
                    dollars to 51.6 million together with lessened purchase requirements in view of
                    absence of adequate quid pro quo. I do not think that US-Polish relations have
                    improved in past year. In some respects such as <gloss target="#t_MFN1"
                        >MFN</gloss> this has been our fault but for most part this has been
                    deliberate choice of Polish Government, i.e., repeatedly expressed Polish
                    position on Berlin, <persName corresp="#p_RA1">Rapacki</persName> visit to Cuba,
                    refusal to accept Glenn capsule and Medicine-<gloss target="#t_USA1">USA</gloss>
                    exhibit et cetera.<note n="1" xml:id="d73fn1">The Polish Government had delayed
                        granting permission for the display of the Glenn capsule, and the United
                        States withdrew its offer. During the exhibition, U.S. officials repeatedly
                        protested against police surveillance and harassment of U.S. delegation
                        members.</note> On record we have certainly no reason to reward Poles for
                    any cooperation they have given us.</p>
                <p>We must bear in mind that any PL–480 sales are ipso facto help given to member of
                    Soviet bloc and must therefore be justified by other positive considerations. We
                    recognize that PL–480 can be properly and effectively used to increase sales of
                    agricultural products. Although agricultural surpluses mean relatively little to
                    United States, their receipt is vital to Poland and its plans for industrial
                    development. I do not believe we should accept Polish view that criterion should
                    be Poland’s commodity needs but should rather think in terms of how we can best
                    further our policy objectives in our relations with Poland. Unless we keep Poles
                    on short leash we lose leverage which PL–480 sales provide us.</p>
                <p>I do not understand how Poland can undertake to repay us for additional $50
                    million worth of commodities if it is frankly unable to assume responsibility
                    for paying a lesser sum of defaulted bonds. I am concerned that there is no end
                    in sight to process of providing Poland with PL–480 commodities and this might
                    ultimately lead to default.</p>
                <p>It is possible Poles are so short of foreign exchange that they cannot buy grain
                    they need, but it is to be remembered that they have been buying from other
                    markets on relatively short credit terms. If they must purchase grain they can
                    probably secure exchange for it by curtailing plans for industrial development.
                    I believe the Poles are in more urgent need <pb facs="0172" n="150"
                        xml:id="pg_150"/> of grain imports now than they have been for past several
                    years and will accept best terms they can get. I have distinct impression that
                    Poles feel confident that we are so wedded to our “special Polish policy” that
                    we can always be pressured into meeting their needs despite lack of Polish
                    cooperation in furthering bilateral relations or Polish willingness to grant
                    adequate quid pro quo in negotiations.</p>
                <p>I have from time to time and most recently in Embassy telegram 988 of December
                        18<note n="2" xml:id="d73fn2">See <ref target="#d70fn2">footnote 2, Document
                            70</ref>.</note> suggested other quid pro quos which we might request.
                    (Incidentally, Department apparently has mistaken impression free market grain
                    purchase discussed in Embassy telegram 988 is insignificant whereas fact is
                    substantial quantities are purchased by the state on the free market.) Since
                    offer described in Department telegram 766<note n="3" xml:id="d73fn3">Telegram
                        766, January 3, outlined U.S. proposals for further discussions of a P.L.
                        480 agreement. (Department of State, Central Files, 611.4841/1–363)</note>
                    has been made, it cannot of course be withdrawn. If not accepted within
                    reasonable time, however, I see no impropriety in making alternative offers
                    involving other benefits to United States objectives.</p>
                <p>I am anxious to know policy considerations under which it was decided to increase
                    our original offer by almost 40 percent since I am concerned lest we use too
                    much carrot and not enough stick. However, whatever misgivings I may have it is
                    obviously essential that any discussions with Polish officials here be closely
                    attuned to those in Washington and I should therefore be grateful for any policy
                    guidance you may wish to send me.</p>
                <p>In conversation with <persName corresp="#p_WJ1">Winiewicz</persName> today I
                    referred to very favorable offer we had made. He was noncommittal.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Cabot</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
