<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-08-02T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-08-02T12:00:00-05:00" n="113" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d113">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/8–250: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                                </gloss>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-08-02T18:00:00+01:00">August 2,
                                    1950—6 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>720. For the Secretary and Perkins. Re <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 648<note n="1" xml:id="d113fn1">See footnote 2, <ref target="frus1949v03#pg_174">p. 174</ref>.</note> and <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss>s 579 and 580.</p>
                        <pb facs="0200" n="178" xml:id="pg_178"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>I have no question whatsoever about the policy of utilizing German
                                industrial capacity for the purpose of providing non-military items
                                necessary for military equipment, including primary commodities such
                                as steel, aluminum, et cetera. I have been recommending this for
                                longtime.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>I think, however, we are completely deluding ourselves and will be
                                guilty of deceiving our allies if we indicate to them that it does
                                not contemplate any modifications of <gloss target="#t_PLI1">PLI</gloss>, about which I personally know a great deal, for I
                                negotiated the <gloss target="#t_PLI1">PLI</gloss> agreement,<note n="2" xml:id="d113fn2">Documentation on review of the Prohibited
                                    and Limited Industries Agreement of 1949 by the Intergovernment
                                    Study Group on Germany is scheduled for publication in volume
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>.</note> As matter of inexorable
                                logic it is impossible, in my view, to follow the policy which is
                                indicated in reference cables, and with which I agree
                                enthusiastically, without modifying the <gloss target="#t_PLI1">PLI</gloss> agreements.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The British Government has today been notified of our policy in
                                the matter in accordance with the instructions but again I repeat
                                this will entail, in my opinion, necessarily modification of the
                                restrictions on the production of certain primary
                                commodities.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_PLI1">PLI</gloss>, as matter of fact, as you know,
                                is on the calendar of <gloss target="#t_ISGG1">ISG</gloss> and will
                                be discussed when <gloss target="#t_ISGG1">ISG</gloss> meets on 15
                                August.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>I suggest very urgently that in view of the political implications
                                here and in Europe, whatever the Secretary’s evidence may be,
                                discussion of the matter in <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NAT</gloss>
                                should not receive any publicity on this side of the water or at
                                home. I make this recommendation with great urgency.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>It seems to me that all we need at the moment to implement the
                                policy is the right to indulge in off-shore procurement. When this
                                right has been obtained we can then in an orderly manner put the
                                policy into effect and suggest that other <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NAT</gloss> countries do likewise. We can then, too, arrange
                                for the adjustments that will necessarily be entailed in Germany
                                itself.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>The lapse of month before putting this policy into effect other
                                than by off-shore procurement, cannot influence rearmament to any
                                appreciable degree. On the other hand, to give it publicity before
                                the harvests are in may be taking risk which it is not necessary for
                                us to take. (I do not place much stock in the theory that the Soviet
                                can be provoked, but I do not see the sense of putting this theory
                                to the test unless there is commensurate gain to us.)</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>The primary question on the continent is to determine whether the
                                French have the real will to fight. We have to make certain
                                commitments in order that the French instinctive will to fight will
                                be encouraged by the consciousness of reasonable possibility of
                                winning. But to plunge Germany into this matter too soon, before we
                                have made <pb facs="0201" n="179" xml:id="pg_179"/> our commitments
                                and the French will to fight has been substantially encouraged, is
                                hazardous business.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Douglas</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>