<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Department of State Member of the National Security Council
                    Staff ( (Bishop) ) to the Ambassador at Large ( (Jessup))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d263</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">263</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="263"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d263">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">S/S–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files: Lot
                    63 D 351: <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 82 Series</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Department of State Member of the National
                        Security Council Staff</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bishop</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Ambassador at Large</hi> (<persName
                        type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Jessup</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-11-15">November 15,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: U.S. Contribution to the Defense of Western Europe</p>
                <p>At the Senior Staff meeting<note n="1" xml:id="d263fn1">The Ambassador at Large
                        was the Department of State member of the National Security Council Senior
                        Staff Group, a group composed of high-ranking representatives of the Council
                        membership and separate from the regular Council Staff. At the meeting under
                        reference here, Policy Planning Staff Director Nitze apparently substituted
                        for Jessup.</note> yesterday, November 14, Mr. Finletter<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d263fn2">Secretary of the Air Force Thomas K. Finletter.</note>
                    raised what seems to me an extremely important point. He said that he felt it
                    might be desirable for the Senior Staff to consider and make <pb facs="0480"
                        n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/> recommendations to the Council regarding the basic
                    principles upon which determination should be made of the extent to which the
                    United States will contribute to the defense of Western Europe. Mr. Finletter
                    went on to point out that certain decisions are being made now in the Department
                    of Defense regarding the contribution which the United States will make to the
                    defense of Western Europe. At the same time, however, not only has there been no
                    discussion of these decisions by the Senior Staff or by the Council itself, but
                    also there has been no discussion by the Senior Staff or formulation by the
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> of the basic principles upon which to
                    make such decisions. He added that he felt it was not necessary or appropriate
                    for the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> to go into the military question of
                    the various force strengths but he did feel strongly that the contribution to be
                    made to the defense of Western Europe by each of the various interested
                    countries is a politico-military question. For example, in considering the
                    extent to which the United States would contribute, we must also consider such
                    matters as “Germany and Spain”. We must also go into the problem of the economic
                    drain on the United States and determine whether this is a matter to be taken
                    into account or whether it is controlling or only partially so.</p>
                <p>Mr. Nitze suggested that the eight questions which the President had answered
                    before the New York meetings<note n="3" xml:id="d263fn3">The reference here is
                        to the joint communication of September 8 from the Secretary of State and
                        the Secretary of Defense to President Truman, p. 273.</note> pretty well
                    answered the policy problem involved. Mr. Finletter did not agree with this and
                    asserted that, for example, we have not faced up to the question whether the
                    United States will make its contribution to the defense of Western Europe even
                    though this contribution would cut into the amount of protection which the
                    United States can give to its sea and air lanes. He repeated that he felt that
                    we must determine the principles governing us in deciding upon the U.S.
                    contribution. He also pointed out that budget ceilings arbitrarily imposed might
                    actually throw out our present calculations. Mr. Finletter suggested that we
                    might have to spell out “the really top priorities in our foreign policies.”</p>
                <p>There was considerable discussion of a document approved by the Defense Ministers
                    in their recent meeting (<gloss target="#t_DC1">DC</gloss> 28<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d263fn4">Defense Committee Document on Medium Term Plan Force
                        Requirements, dated October 28, 1950, not found in Department of State
                        files. The paper was a combination of studies by the <gloss
                            target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> regional planning groups on the forces
                        needed from the various <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> participants
                        to defend the North Atlantic Treaty Area.</note>). I shall endeavor to get a
                    copy for you.</p>
                <p>There was also some discussion of tentative war plans and troop strengths. I was
                    a little disturbed and I am sure Admiral Wooldridge<note n="5" xml:id="d263fn5"
                        >Rear Admiral E. T. Wooldridge was the member of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> Senior Staff representing the Joint Chiefs of Staff; he was
                        also Deputy Director, Joint Staff, for Politico-Military Affairs.</note>
                    <pb facs="0481" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/> was vastly more disturbed that they
                    came so close to a discussion of actual war plans in the effort to give examples
                    of the need for decision on politico-military principles. I do feel, however,
                    that Mr. Finletter has raised an extremely important matter and I am confident
                    that you will want to discuss it further in the Senior Staff.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Max</hi> W. <hi rend="smallcaps">Bishop</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
