<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in France ( (Bohlen) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d435</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">435</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-10-10T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-10-10T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-10-10T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-10-10T12:00:00-05:00" n="435"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d435">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">640.521/10–1050: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bohlen</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-10-10T18:00:00+01:00"
                            >October 10, 1950—6 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1900. <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> surprised to find press reports
                    correct that in speech at Bremen October 8, Francois-Poncet had declared it
                    desirable that Spain enter Council of Europe. Does not yet have text of speech
                    so unable say whether he mentioned any conditions, but in any case declares High
                    Commissioner was expressing only personal opinion in matter, in no way spokesman
                    for government on Spanish policy.<note n="1" xml:id="d435fn1">
                        <p>In telegram 1904 to the Embassy in France dated October 12, 1950, the
                            Department asked for copies of Francois-Poncet’s remarks “re
                            desirability Spain membership Council of Europe.” The Embassy in France
                            responded in despatch 1150 of November 10, 1950, enclosing
                            Francois-Poncet’s speech with the added comment that “As the Department
                            will at once recognize, the mention of Spain is so incidental that
                            reference to Franco Spain is by no means certain.” The Embassy further
                            noted that “an informal note from a [French] Foreign Office official
                            enclosing the relevant excerpts from the French text of
                            Francois-Poncet’s speech points out that he was not speaking even as
                            French High Commissioner” and that he had opened his speech with the
                            disclaimer “that he was speaking in any official capacity.”
                            (740.00/10–1250 and 740.00/11–1050)</p>
                        <p>Nonetheless, there was an attempt made during the November 18–24, 1950,
                            session of the Consultative Assembly of the Council of Europe to propose
                            a resolution supporting the entry of Spain into the Council. This
                            initiative was under the direction of the French Liberal Republican
                            Delegate, André Mutter. However, according to Consul in Strasbourg
                            George D. Andrews (despatch 211, December 1, 1950) so little support
                            developed for such a proposal that the informal Spanish observers at the
                            Assembly Session urged its sponsors to abandon it, which was done
                            (740.00/12–150).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Sent Department 1900; repeated info Madrid 32, Frankfort 211, pouched
                    Strasbourg.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bohlen</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
