<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-09-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-09-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="561" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d561">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">
                                <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Files: Lot M–88: Box 152: <gloss target="#t_SFM1">SFM</gloss> Documents 1–40</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Paper Prepared by the Tripartite Drafting Group of
                                    the Preliminary Conversations of the United States, United
                                    Kingdom, and France</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d561fn1">Attached to
                                    the source text was a cover sheet, not printed, which indicated
                                    that this paper had been prepared in the preliminary talks for
                                    submission to the Foreign Ministers. It is a revision of
                                    Document 6 [D–7], dated August 31, the text of which is
                                    indicated in the following footnotes. (<gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Files: Lot M–88: Box 152: <gloss target="#t_SFM1">SFM</gloss> Documents 1–40)</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-09-01">September 1,
                                        1950</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Document 10 [D–7<hi rend="italic">a</hi>]</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Security of Greece and Turkey</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The security of the Near and Middle East and therefore the security
                                of the West would be endangered if the Soviet Union obtained control
                                of either Greece or Turkey.</p>
                            <pb facs="1204" n="1180" xml:id="pg_1180"/>
                            <p>The United Kingdom and French Governments have a treaty of alliance
                                with Turkey. The United States and United Kingdom Governments have
                                publicly stated and demonstrated in practice their deep interest in
                                the integrity of Greece and Turkey.</p>
                            <p>The Soviet Union, therefore, has every reason to believe that a
                                direct Soviet attack on Greece or Turkey would lead to general war,
                                and that a satellite attack on either country might involve a
                                similar risk.</p>
                            <p>The three Foreign Ministers should discuss the problem posed by the
                                Turkish request for inclusion in the North Atlantic Treaty
                                Organization in an endeavor to reach an agreement among themselves
                                prior to its consideration in the <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NAT</gloss> Council. Recommendations on this point will, if
                                possible, be submitted to the Ministers prior to their meeting.<note n="2" xml:id="d561fn2">The last sentence of the paragraph was
                                    not present in Document 6 [D–7].</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>It is believed, however, that the Ministers should also consider the
                                broader question of Near Eastern security, of which the Turkish
                                application is but one facet.</p>
                            <p>Other means of dealing with this problem might include the following: <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item>The establishment of a new regional pact covering some or
                                        all of the countries in this area and to which the United
                                        Kingdom, Franca and the United States might lend their
                                        support;</item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item>The admission of Turkey and Greece to North Atlantic
                                        Treaty discussions on a consultative basis rather than as a
                                        full member;</item>
                                    <label>(3)</label>
                                    <item>New unilateral declarations by the three governments
                                        concerning the security of certain Near Eastern
                                        states.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Some of the considerations affecting the decision as to the inclusion
                                of Turkey in the <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NAT</gloss> would also
                                apply to certain of these alternatives.<note n="3" xml:id="d561fn3">
                                    <p>In Document 6 [D–7], the preceding two paragraphs starting
                                        with “It is believed” read as follows:</p>
                                    <p>“Among the considerations involved in this decision, over and
                                        above the <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NAT</gloss> considerations
                                        would be the following: <list>
                                            <item>“(1) Would the adherence of Turkey to the <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NAT</gloss> give substance to the
                                                Soviet Government’s claim that the USSR is being
                                                encircled by the West?</item>
                                            <item>“(2) Would refusal of the application without some
                                                alternative form of reassurance cause the Soviet
                                                Union to believe that Western interest in Turkey had
                                                decreased?</item>
                                            <item>“(3) Would inclusion in the Pact deter aggression
                                                more effectively than the existing commitments and
                                                the expressions of interest already given?</item>
                                            <item>“(4) Would the psychological effect on Turkey of
                                                the rejection of its application, in the absence of
                                                an acceptable alternative, be serious?</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>“Possible alternatives to the inclusion of Turkey in the
                                            <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NAT</gloss> might be: <list>
                                            <item>“(1) The establishment of a new regional pact to
                                                which the United Kingdom, France and the United
                                                States might lend their support;</item>
                                            <item>“(2) The admission of Turkey to North Atlantic
                                                Treaty discussions on a consultative basis rather
                                                than as a full member;</item>
                                            <item>“(3) New unilateral declarations by the three
                                                governments concerning the security of Turkey. Some
                                                of the objections to the inclusion of Turkey in the
                                                  <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NAT</gloss> would also
                                                apply to certain of these alternatives.”</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </p>
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <p>The admission of Turkey to the <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NAT</gloss>
                                would probably involve the admission of Greece also. If Turkey and
                                Greece were admitted to the <pb facs="1205" n="1181" xml:id="pg_1181"/>
                                <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NAT</gloss> some form of reassurance might
                                be required for Iran. If some alternative form of reassurance were
                                adopted for Greece and Turkey, very careful consideration would have
                                to be given to extending this reassurance to Iran, in the light of
                                the association of this country with Greece and Turkey in public
                                statements, and to the possible extension of this reassurance to
                                other Middle Eastern countries also.</p>
                            <p>Irrespective of the decisions taken on the broad security problems
                                discussed above<note n="4" xml:id="d561fn4">In Document 6 [D–7] the
                                    first 12 words of this paragraph were not present.</note> the
                                importance of continuing and, wherever feasible, expanding the
                                present program of the supply of military equipment to Greece and
                                Turkey should be borne in mind. Urgent study should be given to the
                                question of what military equipment, over and above that comprised
                                in present programs, could and should be supplied to Greece and
                                Turkey in case of an attack by satellite forces without overt Soviet
                                participation.</p>
                            <p>Similarly,<note n="5" xml:id="d561fn5">The first word of this
                                    paragraph was not present in Document 6 [D–7].</note> as a
                                further measure of protection to Greece, and in the light of the
                                possibility of the renewal of guerrilla warfare, the French, United
                                Kingdom and United States Delegations to the United Nations General
                                Assembly should be instructed to support the continuation of <gloss target="#t_UNSCOB1">UNSCOB</gloss> in its present form.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>