<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>United States Minutes, Private Meeting of the Foreign Ministers, New York,
                    September 12, 1950</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d569</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">569</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-09-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-09-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec_korean_war" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="korean-war" subject="korean-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073119" lcsh-match="exact">Korean War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-09-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-09-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="569"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d569">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Files: Lot M–88: Box 152: File—<gloss
                        target="#t_SFM1">SFM</gloss> Meeting Minutes</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">United States Minutes, Private Meeting of the Foreign
                        Ministers, New York, September 12, 1950</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d569fn1">This private meeting was held during an adjournment
                        in the first meeting of the Foreign Ministers on September 12; for the
                        minutes of that meeting, see <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>. The minutes
                        printed here were prepared by Special Assistant Battle.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1950-09-12">September 12, 1950</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Present:</p>
                <table cols="3" rows="3">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Mr. Bevin</cell>
                        <cell>Mr. Schuman</cell>
                        <cell>Mr. Acheson</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Mr. Barclay</cell>
                        <cell>Mr. Bourbon-Busset</cell>
                        <cell>Mr. Battle</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>US Interpreter</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Mr. Acheson opened the meeting by saying the United States had been working very
                    hard since last August on the French memorandum and messages from Mr. Bevin on
                    the same subjects.<note n="2" xml:id="d569fn2">For the text of the French
                        memorandum of August 17 and the Bevin messages under reference here, see
                            <ref target="#pg_220">pp. 220</ref> ff.</note> He said we had been
                    trying to get coordinated US Governmental views on the questions raised by the
                    French and the British. He said we had come to decisions on the principal points
                    except for the financial ones.</p>
                <p>Mr. Acheson said that the President had agreed to an increase in forces in being
                    on the continent of Europe. He said this had been carefully considered and was
                    based on the assumption we could work out an effective plan for defense of the
                    European continent. He said the Korean war might have some effect on the dates
                    that further US troops would be available, but that we expected to move as
                    rapidly as possible.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said we had considered how we draw the western forces together and
                    had concluded that we should create an international staff and eventually
                    appoint a Supreme Commander when the staff had begun to function effectively and
                    there was in being something for a Supreme Commander to command. He said that we
                    hoped the staff would serve under a chief of staff and would have some delegated
                    authority and would not be confined to mere planning functions. He said the
                    Supreme Commander would be an outgrowth of this and its powers would have to be
                    worked out. He said that the chief of staff would not necessarily become the
                    Supreme Commander, in our opinion, but this might be a development if the powers
                    were satisfied with the functioning of the Chief of Staff.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said we had also considered the supply and production problems and
                    that we thought the French memorandum was right <pb facs="1223" n="1199"
                        xml:id="pg_1199"/> in suggesting that there be more central direction of the
                    supply effort. He said that we proposed that the military production and supply
                    board become a full time body with executive functions and would coordinate
                    production in Europe.</p>
                <p>In the field of finance, the Secretary said that we had not progressed this far.
                    He said that as we saw it, there are three general stages: First, we should get
                    the high priority production program going with as much speed as possible.
                    Second, we should consider the long range problem of eventual arrangements for
                    dealing with financial matters. We do not want study of this problem to delay us
                    on our consideration of the immediate problem. Thirdly, the more immediate
                    problem is to get together the representatives of the US, UK and France and see
                    what problems we will face for the next two or three years and particularly in
                    1951. After we had gone into this, US officials could then get together for such
                    help and authority as was needed. The Secretary said we had asked Mr. Mtze to
                    meet with the designated representatives of the French and British and that he
                    hoped we would know by tomorrow a little more about how we proceed. He then said
                    that we would get the necessary people from Washington to come here to discuss
                    the problem.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that in trying to determine what was necessary for the defense
                    of Western Europe we come to the troublesome problem of Germany. If Germany were
                    not defended, the USSR would gain a tremendous advantage. If it were defended,
                    we wondered if it could be done without German help. The Secretary said that it
                    seemed unreasonable to us to defend all of Germany without getting assistance
                    from Germany. He said that our preference was for German units to serve in a
                    European defense force rather than to create a German police force. He said that
                    consideration of this problem was necessary.</p>
                <p>Mr. Acheson said that we had US Government agreement on the broad programs he had
                    discussed and had wide public support for them.</p>
                <p>Mr. Schuman expressed pleasure at the US agreement on most points of the French
                    memorandum and particularly in regard to the increase of US forces and the
                    creation of the collective authority command staff, combined command, etc. He
                    said that he was in favor of reorganizing bodies of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> and particularly the military production and supply board. Mr.
                    Schuman said that two points must be carefully considered: The high priority
                    production program <pb facs="1224" n="1200" xml:id="pg_1200"/> must be begun as
                    soon as possible, but we must not wait too long to discuss a final system for
                    the financial arrangements. He said that both were extremely urgent. Mr. Schuman
                    then pointed to the French proposal contained in the French memorandum for what
                    he called an early solution to the point of a long range solution. He said he
                    realized there would be alternate proposals and he would be glad to discuss any
                    others. Regarding the participation of Germany in the defense effort, Mr.
                    Schuman said it would seem illogical for us to defend Western Europe, including
                    Germany, without contributions from Germany. He said that there was a serious
                    psychological problem in France, however, and that it would create serious
                    difficulties if we force the French to take a position too early. He said that
                    the French felt that there were limited resources available for common defense.
                    In their opinion, these resources must be distributed between the <gloss
                        target="#t_NAT1">NAT</gloss> countries. Only when a minimum level is reached
                    in these countries would it be easy for the French to take a definite position
                    on the matter. When the combined staff and the Supreme Commander has been
                    created the difficulty will be much lessened for the French and the Government
                    might be in a position to consider the German matter on a different basis.</p>
                <p>Mr. Schuman urged that the other Foreign Ministers be patient on this matter.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bevin said that he thought care should be used in the phraseology of some of
                    our proposals. He said that he did not like the use of the word “European” in
                    regard to our defense force plan. He pointed out that the United States and
                    Canada would be participating. He said that what we are trying to do is defend
                    the free world in Europe rather than merely defending Europe. He suggested a
                    broad concept and as comprehensive terminology as possible.</p>
                <p>Regarding the combined command, Mr. Bevin said he was ready to discuss any plan
                    the Combined Chiefs put up. He said that he was anxious to develop organization
                    at the top. He also said he thought we should move toward the organization as
                    soon as possible.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bevin said the main concern of the UK was production and that the UK was
                    somewhat uneasy at the way this problem was moving. He said the financial side
                    must be settled or we would check the momentum of the production effort. He
                    pointed out that troops could not be trained without equipment.</p>
                <p>In regard to the financial problems, he said that many of the problems could be
                    solved by bilateral discussion. He then indicated general concurrence with
                    Secretary Acheson’s proposal for getting UK, <pb facs="1225" n="1201"
                        xml:id="pg_1201"/> French and US representatives to go to work on the
                    general outline of the problem.</p>
                <p>Mr. Acheson related to the other Foreign Ministers that all we could do would be
                    to work out a program which satisfied the Executive Branch and then go to the
                    Congress with it. We could not, of course, assure what Congress would do.</p>
                <p>Regarding the German problem, Mr. Bevin said that the UK took the view that we
                    must be careful not to put the Germans in a bargaining position, which would
                    make the situation very difficult. He said that he thought we should get the
                    High Commissioners to give us their estimates of the reactions of the Germans if
                    we should approach them and ask for German units for a defense force. He said
                    that he doubted: that the Germans would go along, and thought a refusal on their
                    part would make the Western powers look foolish. He said he had great doubt as
                    to the response the proposal would get in Germany and said the UK favored a more
                    cautious course of supporting the German police.<note n="3" xml:id="d569fn3"
                        >Documentation on proposals for a German Federal police force is scheduled
                        for publication in volume <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>.</note> He said the
                    UK thought it preferable to give the Germans what they asked for rather than ask
                    them for something. Mr. Bevin said further that he believed we should approach
                    the problem with regard to the broader problem of Germany rather than looking at
                    it from a strictly military standpoint. He mentioned again the fear in the UK of
                    a German resurgence to power. He said that the UK was willing to examine the
                    matter with the best people available to determine how best to proceed to decide
                    how Germany should be brought in. He said that he did not think we should let it
                    interfere with our own defense effort. Mr. Bevin mentioned that internal
                    disorders would be a serious factor militarily and that this supported the UK
                    position in favor of increasing the police force. He suggested also that we must
                    remember that we want to work out an arrangement for Germany to become
                    permanently associated with the community of nations and not simply approach the
                    problem from the standpoint of the present emergency. He also asked if it would
                    not be well to take the Benelux countries into confidence on what was decided on
                    the problem. He mentioned their great concern as close neighbors of
                        Germany.<note n="4" xml:id="d569fn4">Secretary Acheson had met individually
                        with Schuman and Bevin, accompanied by Franks, at 10:45 a. m. and 12:15 p.
                        m., respectively, before the first meeting. In addition to discussing <gloss
                            target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> with each of them along the lines,
                        indicated in this tripartite meeting, Secretary Acheson had briefly examined
                        Indochina with Schuman and the United Kingdom’s financial position with
                        Bevin. For memoranda of these conversations, see <ref target="#pg_293">pp.
                            293</ref> and <ref target="#pg_285">285</ref>, respectively.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
