<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-05-15T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-05-15T17:00:00-05:00" n="69" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d69">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">396.1 LO/5–1550: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-05-15T23:00:00+01:00">May 15,
                                    1950—11 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 267. As result three weeks
                            negotiations conducted during past week on daily basis, Bevin, Schuman
                            and Acheson tentatively agreed tonight on following text of resolution
                            on strengthening <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NAT</gloss> Council
                                organization.<note n="1" xml:id="d69fn1">This text was the third
                                revision of the resolution. The first was Annex A to Foreign
                                Ministers Document <gloss target="#t_Min1">MIN</gloss>/TRI/P/28,
                                    <ref target="#pg_1103">p. 1103</ref>. The second was <gloss target="#t_Min1">MIN</gloss>/TRI/P/29 dated May 13, not printed,
                                which was the same in substance as this text.</note> Will be
                            distributed tonight as UK proposal. Appreciate any comments.<note n="2" xml:id="d69fn2">In telegram <gloss target="#t_Tosec1">Tosec</gloss>
                                213 to London, May 16, the Acting Secretary of State transmitted a
                                State–Defense message approving the text of this resolution with
                                suggestions for two minor changes in wording and a request by the
                                Department of Defense that it be given an “opportunity to comment on
                                any new specific details in connection therewith that may have
                                military implications, before acceptance by North Atlantic Council.”
                                    <gloss target="#t_Tosec1">Tosec</gloss> 213 not printed; 396.1
                                LO/5–1650.</note> Have coordinated with Defense representative
                            here.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Begin text:</hi> The North Atlantic Council,
                            established in accordance with Article 9 of the treaty, has so far only
                            met twice at the ministerial level and on two other occasions when the
                            Foreign Ministers, members of the council, have been represented by
                            their governments’ diplomatic representatives in Washington.</p>
                        <p>But under article 9, the council is the supreme body of the <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NAT</gloss>. It is, therefore, the paramount duty
                            of the council to put itself in a position to exercise its full role as
                            the central and most important of the <pb facs="0124" n="104" xml:id="pg_104"/> various organs of the treaty by taking the most
                            effective steps to keep public informed of all matters which fall within
                            its competence, by taking the necessary decisions and by ensuring the
                            execution of such decisions.</p>
                        <p>A year’s experience has shown that on the political side the meetings of
                            the council have been too infrequent to permit a sufficient exchange of
                            views on matters of common interest within the scope of the treaty. On
                            the military side, the strategic concept of the treaty has been adopted
                            and a defense plan drawn up, and the corresponding estimate of the
                            necessary forces is being established. The next step is to put these
                            plans into effect by taking further measures in the direction of common
                            defense, the division of finance responsibilities and the adaptation and
                            development of the necessary forces.</p>
                        <p>In view of this situation, the council will in particular undertake the
                            following tasks: <list>
                                <label>A.</label>
                                <item>Studying interrelationship of the various programs to support
                                    the plans for the defense of the North Atlantic area and ensure
                                    coordination of the work of the defense committee, the <gloss target="#t_DFEC1">DFEC</gloss>, and all other bodies
                                    established under the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>;</item>
                                <label>B.</label>
                                <item>Recommend to governments the steps necessary to ensure that
                                    effect is given to the coordinated plans prepared for the
                                    defense of the North Atlantic area;</item>
                                <label>C.</label>
                                <item>Exchange views on political matters of common interest within
                                    the scope of the treaty;</item>
                                <label>D.</label>
                                <item>Promote and coordinate public information in furtherance of
                                    the objectives of the treaty, while leaving responsibility for
                                    national programs to each country;</item>
                                <label>E.</label>
                                <item>Consider what further action should be taken under article 2
                                    of the treaty.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>To enable the council effectively to carry out these responsibilities and
                            to exercise them continuously, each government shall appoint a deputy to
                            its council representative. Each deputy shall be in a position to give
                            whatever time may be necessary to ensure that the responsibilities of
                            the council are carried out effectively. In the intervals between
                            meetings of Ministers, the deputies shall be responsible, on behalf of,
                            and in the name of, the council, for carrying out its policies and for
                            formulating issues requiring decisions by the member governments. They
                            shall have the same responsibilities and powers as the council.</p>
                        <p>To assist the deputies in fulfilling their responsibilities, they shall
                            establish a suitable fulltime organization composed of highly qualified
                            persons contributed by member governments. In setting up the
                            organization, provision shall be made for vigorous leadership
                            thereof.</p>
                        <p>Member governments will appoint their deputies with the least possible
                            delay in order that agreement may be reached by them, acting on behalf
                            of their governments, on the type of organization required and the
                            qualified persons required. It is contemplated that the deputies,
                            assisted by the organization to be created, should begin functioning
                            [in] the very near future in order that tangible results may be achieved
                            before the next meeting of the Ministers, when the progress made will be
                            reviewed. First priority in the work of the deputies and <pb facs="0125" n="105" xml:id="pg_105"/> the organization should be given to points
                            A and B above. The deputies will meet in blank. [End text.]<note n="3" xml:id="d69fn3">The last three paragraphs of this proposal were
                                revised in <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 298, May 17, as
                                follows: In the first of these paragraphs, sentence 1, the words
                                “these” and “shall” were changed to “its” and “will,” respectively.
                                In the last paragraph, first sentence, the first use of “their” and
                                the word “them” were changed to “its” and “the deputies,”
                                respectively. Also, the first use of the word “required” was
                                deleted. In the following sentence, the word “Ministers” was changed
                                to “Council,” and, in the last sentence, the word “blank” was
                                changed to “London.” (<gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 296,
                                not printed; 396.1 LO/5–1750)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Sent Department <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 267, repeated
                            Paris information 854. Pass to Secretary Defense.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>