<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Deputy Representative on the North Atlantic Council (
                    (Spofford) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d97</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">97</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-07-27T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-07-27T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recJWMonWClUHgnN6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Common fund</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-07-27T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-07-27T19:00:00-05:00" n="97"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d97">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/7–2850: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Deputy Representative on the North Atlantic
                        Council</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Spofford</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-07-28T01:00:00+01:00"
                            >July 28, 1950—1 a. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 18. No distribution except as directed
                    by Secretary’s office. Alphand called on me this morning<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d97fn1">July 27.</note> at his request and, referring to Ambassador
                    Bruce’s communication of the US Government’s proposal last week,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d97fn2">Circular telegram, July 22, <ref target="#pg_138">p.
                            138</ref>.</note> stated that Prime Minister Pleven had instructed him
                    to communicate to me the French Government’s attitude as to certain important
                    principles relevant to the present situation.</p>
                <p>He began by referring to our commonly agreed objective of building strength to
                    prevent war and added that in the event of war we were united to win.</p>
                <p>He stated that it was the French Government’s conviction that it was essential to
                    agree on what is to be defended. Was it to be Elbe? Was it to be area between
                    Elbe and Rhine? Was it to be a beachhead in Brittany, defense of Spain and North
                    Africa or defense of British Isles? French Government was clear that defense
                    must be as far east as possible. French Government found it necessary to insist
                    all agree where line of defense should be drawn. He thought that this question
                    had perhaps not been presented to US in this manner before.</p>
                <p>Western Europe itself must be defended and under this principle French Government
                    felt it necessary that actions be taken now to insure initial defense would be
                    successful. This meant additional American and British forces must be sent to
                    Germany to be available along with additional French forces which would be
                    raised. Defense of Western Europe could not be effected unless American and
                    British troops were actually there to help meet initial shock. It would be to no
                    avail if these forces were to be sent after initial attack, because there would
                    be nothing to defend. And, of course, forces in being and on spot would have to
                    be reinforced in order successfully to win the battle.</p>
                <p>Lesson of Korea was clear in minds of all Frenchmen and Prime Minister felt it
                    absolutely essential he be able give assurances to French people with regard to
                    aforementioned basic principles, if he <pb facs="0171" n="149" xml:id="pg_149"/>
                    was to be justified in calling for the additional effort and sacrifices that
                    would be necessary.</p>
                <p>Alphand referred to Council’s resolution adopted in May (Council resolution
                        4/8)<note n="3" xml:id="d97fn3">Not printed, but see footnote 2, <ref
                            target="#pg_109">p. 109</ref>.</note> and said French Government was
                    convinced of necessity for listing equipment which had to be produced, for
                    allocating production of this equipment and for dividing cost of its production.
                    He stated it was essential to abandon perfection and take steps immediately to
                    increase defense strength. His government proposed that initial list be made and
                    quantities determined of those essential items of armament which had to be
                    produced right away. Anything produced now would fall within confines of
                    whatever plans were developed. Work must be undertaken immediately to produce
                    essential armaments necessary to conduct initial defense. This must not be
                    delayed because of unfinished plans as to what forces would use equipment or
                    because of not yet clearly defined methods of financing production. His
                    government thought that urgent items of equipment produced could be put into
                    something of a pool and then apportioned to proper forces as they were developed
                    and trained. But at any rate equipment must be got on spot with no delay.</p>
                <p>When I pointed out that in lunching with Moch, Shinwell, Montgomery and Delattre
                    I received impression latter two felt that having equipment was not the answer
                    unless forces were in being and trained to use it, Alphand modified his
                    statement to agree that two must come together.</p>
                <p>Emphasizing necessity for preparing list and quantities of vital armaments to be
                    produced immediately, Alphand referred to President Roosevelt’s list of 1942
                    setting forth requirements for “60,000 planes” et cetera.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d97fn4">For the text of President Roosevelt’s annual message to the
                        Congress, January 6, 1942, see Department of State <hi rend="italic"
                            >Bulletin</hi>, January 10, 1942, p. 39.</note> A similar list was what
                    was needed now.</p>
                <p>With regard to production of this equipment, each nation must undertake
                    immediately what it can without waiting for perfected plans to be devised as to
                    allocation. Effort initially would not be so great as to be outside bounds of
                    whatever plans were eventually developed.</p>
                <p>In regard to financing, French Government intended to proposer common fund be
                    instituted, that US make initial contribution thereto, that other nations
                    contribute as soon as possible and details be agreed later as to rules of fund,
                    apportionment of costs, et cetera, moneys contributed immediately to be used to
                    let contracts for producing urgently needed armaments referred to above. French
                    Treasury officials were now working on proposals regarding common fund and he
                    would be ready to discuss those with me shortly.</p>
                <p>Alphand said Prime Minister felt matters which he had presented were so important
                    and that the necessity for deciding them soon was <pb facs="0172" n="150"
                        xml:id="pg_150"/> so great that it might require a meeting of the heads of
                    governments or Foreign Ministers, even before the September meeting of the
                    Council. He thought such meeting would be most beneficial, not only because it
                    would produce the necessary agreements but because of impression it would make
                    on all peoples. He was prepared to go to Washington to discuss this and other
                    matters raised.</p>
                <p>He stated further French Government’s belief meeting referred to above should
                    consider the possibility of establishing something in nature of an international
                    war cabinet and executive body, which would be composed of representatives of
                    US, UK and France, and perhaps two other nations and which would be responsible
                    for direction of defense effort.</p>
                <p>Turning to Indochina, Alphand said that this situation was draining life blood
                    from France and could not be dealt with by France’s resources alone. French Army
                    now in Indochina must be replaced to large extent with native forces who must be
                    equipped and trained, and French officers and non-coms brought back to France to
                    help build new French Army. This would require financial resources which, when
                    considered from French point of view, were staggering. Since 1945 France had
                    spent 800 billion francs in Indochina. They must have help if situation were to
                    be maintained. Prime Minister had instructed him to inform me French Government
                    requested financial aid for Indochina in amount of 200 billion francs for next
                    two years. This was essential if efforts referred to above were to be carried
                    through.</p>
                <p>I assured Alphand substance of his statement would be reported immediately and I
                    would let him know instructions received.<note n="5" xml:id="d97fn5">For
                        documentation on U.S. policy relating to Indochina, see <ref
                            target="frus1950v06#pg_690">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, pp.
                            690</ref> ff.</note>
                </p>
                <p>When I inquired as to status of French Government’s deliberations on our
                    proposals as to increased level of defense effort, Alphand said he hoped be able
                    give me their answer first part next week.</p>
                <p>Sent Department <gloss target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 18, repeated info Paris
                    150 (eyes only Ambassador).</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Spofford</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
