<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-10-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="234" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d234">
                    <head>234. Letter From the Deputy Director for Intelligence, Central
                        Intelligence Agency (<persName type="from">Cline</persName>) to the Director
                        of the Arms Control and Disarmament Agency (<persName corresp="#p_FWC2" type="to">Foster</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d234fn0">Source: Central Intelligence Agency, <gloss target="#t_DCI1">DCI</gloss>, ER Subject Files. Secret.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-10-01">October 1,
                            1962</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC2">Foster</persName></hi>: Thank you for sending us a copy of your
                        September 26 letter to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, which requested the comments of the Department of
                        Defense and the Joint Chiefs on the current draft proposal for a nuclear
                        non-diffusion agreement.<note n="1" xml:id="d234fn1"><persName corresp="#p_FWC2">Foster</persName>’s September 26 letter to
                                <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> summarized
                            developments regarding a possible international agreement on
                            non-diffusion of nuclear weapons and provided <gloss target="#t_ACDA1">ACDA</gloss>’s recommendations on such an agreement. (Department of
                            State, Central Files, 397.5611-GE/9-2762) See the Supplement.</note></p>
                    <p>I understand that General Carter has already made known our reservations
                        about parts of the September 18 draft letters to President <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> and Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName>.<note n="2" xml:id="d234fn2">The
                            comments of Lieutenant General Marshall S. Carter, Deputy Director of
                            Central Intelligence, have not been found. Undated draft letters from
                            the President to <persName corresp="#p_MHS2">Macmillan</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> were transmitted under cover of
                            a memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_FWC2">Foster</persName> to the
                            Committee of Principals, September 18. (Washington National Records
                            Center, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 383, <gloss target="#t_ACDADD1">ACDA/DD</gloss> Files: <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 77 A 17, Committee of Principals Jan-Dec 1962)</note>
                        It occurred to me that further comments might be useful to you.</p>
                    <p>As you know, we believe that the material transmitted to the Committee of
                        Principals on September 18 exaggerated both the imminence and the probable
                        scale of nuclear diffusion.<note n="3" xml:id="d234fn3">In addition to the
                            draft letters cited in <ref target="#d235fn3">footnote 3</ref> above,
                            the material included an undated draft memorandum from the Secretary of
                            State to the President and an undated draft declaration on
                            non-diffusion. The draft memorandum, somewhat revised, was sent to the
                            President on September 21; see <ref target="#d230">Document
                            230</ref>.</note> In addition to the considerations discussed in <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 4-3-61,<note n="4" xml:id="d234fn4"><gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 4-3-61, “Nuclear Weapons and Delivery
                            Capabilities of Free World Countries Other than the US and <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>,” September 21, 1961, is scheduled for
                            publication in <ref target="frus1961-63v08">volume VIII</ref>.</note>
                        with which you are familiar, I should like to add that we also consider the
                        cost of acquiring a nuclear weapons capability still to be an important
                        deterrent. It is true that costs are in general declining as uranium becomes
                        easier to obtain, as plutonium becomes more widely available and as
                        information on weapons technology increases. Nonetheless, the minimum cost
                        is still on the order of two hundred million dollars merely to acquire a
                        single crude nuclear weapon. This does not allow anything for an effective
                        modern delivery system. The French spent one billion dollars before their
                        first test shot in 1960 and will probably be spending this much each year by
                        1968 on weapons alone. To this must be added the cost of acquiring
                        appropriate delivery vehicles. The French will need at least fifty Mirage IV
                        light jet <pb facs="0609" n="583" xml:id="pg_583"/> bombers for a real
                        strike force, and these would cost between 200-250 million dollars. Some
                        seven hundred million dollars more would be required for an intermediate
                        range ballistic missile now under development in France.</p>
                    <p>A second point we would like to make concerns the feasibility of keeping
                        Communist China from acquiring nuclear weapons. The September 18 draft
                        letter to the President stated that “… the possibility of obtaining the
                        adherence of Communist China to such an agreement is very remote unless the
                        appeal can be put as a joint effort by the three Western nuclear powers.” We
                        would go considerably farther than this statement. We believe that the
                        Communist Chinese are determined to go ahead with their nuclear weapons
                        program and that the Soviets do not have (and are not likely to acquire) the
                        leverage to produce a change in this decision. In July, Chinese Communist
                        Foreign Minister Chen-yi stated in a speech that the Chinese were going
                        ahead with their program and would achieve success soon. Early in September,
                        the Peiping <hi rend="italic">People’s Daily</hi> charged that the real
                        purpose of US disarmament proposals was to tie China’s hands in developing
                        nuclear weapons. We suspect that the Chinese are well aware of what is in
                        the wind and that these remarks and their timing are not coincidental. Thus
                        we should be very cautious in assuming that it is feasible to keep nuclear
                        weapons out of the hands of the Chinese Communists or that other nations
                        (including the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>) will find this one of
                        the practical benefits of a nuclear non-diffusion agreement.</p>
                    <p>With the hope that these observations will be helpful to you,</p>
                    <p>Sincerely,</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Ray S. Cline</hi></persName><note n="5" xml:id="d234fn5">Printed from a copy that indicates
                                    <persName>Cline</persName> signed the
                        original.</note></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>