<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-12-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-01-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="239" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d239">
                    <head>239. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>In the last weeks of October 1962, President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> and Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> exchanged several messages in their efforts to
                        negotiate a peaceful resolution of the Cuban missile crisis. Once <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> agreed to the prompt dismantling
                        and withdrawal of the missiles from Cuba and other concessions, the two
                        leaders began to consider other outstanding issues between the two nations.
                        Concerning disarmament, <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName>
                        wrote in his message to President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> on October 28: “We should like to continue the
                        exchange of views on the prohibition of atomic and thermonuclear weapons,
                        general disarmament, and other problems relating to the relaxation of
                        international tensions.” (<hi rend="italic">Documents on Disarmament,
                            1962</hi>, volume II, page 997; the letter is also printed in <ref target="frus1961-63v06#d67">volume VI, Document 67</ref>)</p>
                    <p>President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> immediately
                        responded with a message to <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> on October 28. In the final paragraph of this
                        message, the President wrote:</p>
                    <p>“I agree with you that we must devote urgent attention to the problem of
                        disarmament, as it relates to the whole world and also to critical areas.
                        Perhaps now, as we step back from danger, we can together make real progress
                        in this vital field. I think we should give priority to questions relating
                        to the proliferation of nuclear weapons, on earth and in outer space, and to
                        the great effort for a nuclear test ban. But we should also work hard to see
                        if wider measures of disarmament can be agreed and put into operation at an
                        early date. The United States government will be prepared to discuss these
                        questions urgently, and in a constructive spirit, at Geneva or elsewhere.”
                            (<hi rend="italic">Documents on Disarmament, 1962</hi>, volume II, page
                        1001; the letter is also printed in <ref target="frus1961-63v06#d68">volume
                            VI, Document 68</ref>)</p>
                    <p>Extensive documentation on the Cuban missile crisis is printed in <ref target="frus1961-63v11">volume XI</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>