<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-12-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-01-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="242" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d242">
                    <head>242. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>In early November 1962, the <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> General
                        Assembly considered resolutions calling for the suspension of nuclear
                        testing. On November 5, Committee One debated and voted on a two-part
                        resolution. Section A was a 37-nation proposal, which was revised and
                        approved in Committee One. Section B, introduced by the United Kingdom and
                        the United States, urged, among other things, the Eighteen-Nation
                        Disarmament Committee “to seek the conclusion of a treaty with effective and
                        prompt international verification which prohibits nuclear weapon tests in
                        all environments for all time.” A summary of the proceedings and voting on
                        these resolutions in Committee One is in a memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_CH4">Harlan Cleveland</persName> to Secretary of State
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>, November 5. (Department of
                        State, Central Files, 700.5611/11-562)</p>
                    <p>On November 6, the <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> General Assembly voted
                        separately on the preamble and on each of the seven paragraphs of Section A.
                        The preamble and all but two paragraphs were adopted unanimously, although
                        many nations abstained on several of the votes. The United Kingdom and the
                        United States were among 10 nations voting against paragraph 2, which asked
                        that all nuclear tests “should cease immediately and not later than 1
                        January 1963.” The Soviet bloc constituted the 10 nations voting against
                        paragraph 6, which recommended that in the absence of a test ban agreement
                        by January 1, 1963, the nuclear weapons states should agree immediately to
                        prohibit testing in the atmosphere, outer space, and under water,
                        accompanied by an “interim arrangement” suspending all underground tests,
                        “such interim agreement to include adequate assurances for effective
                        detection and identification of seismic events by an international
                        scientific commission.” Section A as a whole was adopted by a vote of 75-0,
                        with 21 abstentions. The General Assembly adopted Section B by a 51-10 vote,
                        with 40 abstentions. The Soviet bloc constituted the 10 negative votes.</p>
                    <p>For text of Resolution 1762 (XVII) and additional details on the voting on
                        each section in Committee One and the General Assembly, see <hi rend="italic">Documents on Disarmament, 1962</hi>, volume II, pages
                        1029-1033; and <hi rend="italic">Yearbook of the United Nations, 1962</hi>,
                        pages 9-13 and 20-26.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>