<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>272. Memorandum by Director of Central Intelligence McCone</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d272</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">272</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-04-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-04-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reclbsHvbXLer8sMP" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">On-site inspections</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recpqcSvEFyuxPc7E" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134146"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Testing</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military balance</term>
                    <term ref="recCP2IC3LozXMzXn" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2022004495"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Surveillance</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recbcbcHDEt9ge9nZ" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110610"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fissionable material</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-04-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-04-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="272"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d272">
                <head>272. Memorandum by Director of Central Intelligence <persName
                        corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d272fn0">Source: Central Intelligence Agency,
                            <gloss target="#t_DCI1">DCI</gloss>, ER Subject Files, White
                        Papers-Nuclear Test Ban 3/1/63-1/2/64. Secret. Circulated to <persName
                            corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-04-08">April 8, 1963</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>With respect to the test ban treaty, I have not gone over the last draft.<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d272fn1">Reference is to a March 23 draft comprehensive test
                        ban treaty. (Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_RG1"
                            >RG</gloss> 383, <gloss target="#t_ACDA1">ACDA</gloss>/CRSC Files:
                            <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 77 A 59, Basic Policy, Pol 3-3,
                        Proposals to President)</note> However, it is my understanding that the
                    present negotiating position provides for seven on-site inspections, seven black
                    boxes within the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, and an inspection area
                    of 500 square kilometers, and that the treaty deals with all the other issues
                    which have been developed through the years. Some consideration is being given
                    to reducing the seven on-site inspections to six, or even to five. There is also
                    a difference of opinion as to the value of the black boxes.</p>
                <p>One would have to make a penetrating study of the results of the Vela experiments
                    to make a final judgment as to the adequacy of the verification provisions of
                    the treaty. However, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC2">Foster</persName>, at a
                    recent Executive Committee meeting,<note n="2" xml:id="d272fn2">Not identified;
                        the test ban was not discussed in the Executive Committee of the National
                        Security Council during 1963.</note> stated that the threshold is on the
                    order of one kiloton in granite, two kilotons in tuff, and 10 to 20 kilotons
                    (and possibly 30 kilotons) in alluvium. He added that this was the threshold for
                    a single test. Based on a theory of probabilities, he further concluded that a
                    series of tests which included a meaningful number of underground shots in a
                    single location would, with a small number of inspections, undoubtedly be
                    detected and identified as nuclear rather than natural.</p>
                <p>On the basis of these threshold figures, I have expressed the view to Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_FWC2">Foster</persName> and to the President<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d272fn3">In a memorandum for the record, April 4, <persName
                            corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> wrote he had told the President
                        that day that former President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                            >Eisenhower</persName> had expressed opposition to the present draft
                        treaty “because of inadequate verification, the threshold, etc.,” and that
                        he, <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName>, agreed with this
                        position and also opposed it because “the Russians could no longer handle
                        the Chinese situation and we and the British could no longer handle the
                            <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> situation, and hence
                        the proliferation problem. The President seemed to agree, and restated that
                        he did not think we were going to get a treaty anyway.” (Central
                        Intelligence Agency, Meetings with President, 4/1/63-6/30/63) <persName
                            corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName>’s memorandum of April 4 of a
                        meeting held with <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> on March
                        30 is ibid.</note> that the degree of verification is not sufficient, as it
                    cannot prove adherence to a suspension of testing in an important area of
                    yields. Of greater importance, however, is the fact that under present political
                    circumstances a test ban between the U.S., <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                    >USSR</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> would not, in the final
                    analysis, answer the “proliferation” problem because the Soviets cannot handle
                    the Chinese Communists and we and the British cannot handle the French.</p>
                <pb facs="0695" n="669" xml:id="pg_669"/>
                <p>As for the advantages to the United States of further testing, doing so would
                    yield a continuing improvement in our technology through the further development
                    of small weapons, improvement of weight/yield ratios and increased knowledge of
                    weapons effects. With respect to the first two of these items, improvements are
                    important. Our failure to pursue them while the Soviets do so (clandestinely)
                    would probably deprive us of our superior nuclear position. However, this would
                    not necessarily affect the military balance as the improvements are expected to
                    be evolutionary rather than revolutionary, although important information would
                    be provided. With respect to effects of testing, more study would be necessary
                    before I would have an opinion.</p>
                <p>There is a great danger of engaging in a treaty, living under it for a number of
                    years, and permitting our laboratories to go downhill (which they undoubtedly
                    would do) while the Soviets covertly pursue developments in their laboratories.
                    The Soviets could then abrogate the treaty for some reason they claim
                    provocative, and confront us with a situation under which they had made a
                    significant forward step in their technology. This, as will be recalled, was
                    exactly what they did in 1961. I do not see how we can avoid this risk if we
                    engage in a treaty unless the treaty is subscribed to by all world powers and
                    contains substantial penalties for such abrogation.</p>
                <p>The Plowshare problem must be considered. Meaningful Plowshare experiments
                    involve our most advanced weapons technology and, if the inspection arrangements
                    outlined in the treaty are undertaken, it would mean exposing to the Soviets our
                    most advanced weapons technology. This might mean abandoning Plowshare and
                    therefore one must consider whether Plowshare is important to our national
                    interest.</p>
                <p>Intelligence will make some contribution to the verification of a test ban. Some
                    indicators which have been meaningful in the past are now lost to us, some
                    useful indicators are still available but they, too, could be lost. Aerial
                    surveillance might help in some circumstances, and clandestine penetrations
                    might also help. Soviet fear of the latter might also serve as a deterrent. No
                    useful figure can be placed on the contribution of intelligence.</p>
                <p>It seems to me that there has been an overemphasis on the importance of the test
                    ban treaty and the whole issue of testing for many years, and most particularly,
                    during the last two or three years. The issue at first centered around fallout.
                    The most responsible scientific judgment seems to indicate that the effects of
                    fallout were vastly overemphasized by the test ban advocates. I feel the whole
                    issue should be brought into proper perspective and question whether much is to
                    be gained by an agreement to stop testing so long as the United States, Soviet
                    Union, and the British continue the production of fissionable material, nuclear
                    weapons, and delivery systems at a high rate, and in addition, the French and
                    the Chinese <pb facs="0696" n="670" xml:id="pg_670"/> Communists pursue an
                    independent and uncontrolled program, and rumor has it that the Israelis are now
                    doing likewise. Hence, stopping testing does not slow down the arms race, does
                    not remove the dangers of a nuclear holocaust, and does not end the
                    proliferation problem.</p>
                <p>One important consideration is that if we reach an agreement with the Soviets, we
                    have “broken through” in our effort to negotiate with the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> on an issue of disarmament, and this might
                    lead to other more meaningful agreements. This consideration is important and we
                    could sacrifice a great deal to accomplish such a “break through”. However, this
                    consideration is of value only if the test suspension agreement provides
                    reasonable means of verification and reasonable guarantee for conformance with
                    all treaty terms, including some protection against unilateral revocation or
                    abrogation of the treaty. If, however, we are reckless on the question of
                    verification, then the “break through” will be a decided disservice to the
                    United States’ security interests because it will establish a precedent for
                    further steps in disarmament without adequate means of verification.</p>
                <p>I have not personally studied the most recent developments in detection and
                    identification techniques and cannot render a judgment on the proposed treaty.
                    However, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC2">Foster</persName>’s disclosure of the
                    threshold set forth in the second paragraph of this memorandum represents a
                    drastic departure from US policy so often stated, i.e. we will only agree to a
                    suspension of tests which can, in the opinion of responsible and informed
                    people, be verified with reasonable assurance.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
