<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>290. Memorandum for the Record</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d290</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">290</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-06-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec5Yy9hoP1ve9DPX" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124537"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Atmospheric</term>
                    <term ref="recpqcSvEFyuxPc7E" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134146"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Testing</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-06-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="290"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d290">
                <head>290. Memorandum for the Record<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d290fn0"
                        >Source: National Defense University, <persName corresp="#p_TMD1"
                            >Taylor</persName> Papers, <gloss target="#t_CJCS1">CJCS</gloss>
                        Memoranda. Confidential. Drafted on June 27 by Chief Warrant Officer Proctor
                        of <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName>’s personal staff.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-06-08">June 8, 1963</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Telephone Conversation with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KC2"
                            >Kaysen</persName> on 8 June</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KC2">Kaysen</persName>, working at Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BMG2">McGeorge Bundy</persName>’s desk in the White House,
                        called <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">General Taylor</persName> on 8 June. He
                        wanted to give <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">General Taylor</persName> a piece
                        of information, which was that the President was, at the moment (i.e., 8
                        June), planning on Monday (10 June) in his commencement speech at the
                        American University to announce that he does not intend to be the first to
                        resume atmospheric testing.<note n="1" xml:id="d290fn1">For text of the
                            speech, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the
                                United States: <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">John F.
                                    Kennedy</persName>
                            </hi>, 1963, pp. 459-464.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KC2"
                            >Kaysen</persName> said that the President may think about this
                        again—that it was very much a personal view of his (the President’s)—that
                        the President had discussed it with almost no one, only discussion was in
                        writing the speech.<note n="2" xml:id="d290fn2">In his memorandum for the
                            record of the White House daily staff meeting held the morning of June
                            10, Legere stated that it was not clear whether <persName
                                corresp="#p_KC2">Kaysen</persName> had written the original draft of
                            the speech, but that it was “clear that he worked and reworked it over
                            the weekend. <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName> noted that
                            this projected speech is unusual in that there has been absolutely no
                            leak of its content to the press.” (National Defense University,
                                <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName> Papers, Chairman’s
                            Staff Group, June 1963, T-223-69)</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KC2"
                            >Kaysen</persName> said that the people who knew about this were the
                        Secretary and <pb facs="0737" n="711" xml:id="pg_711"/> Under Secretary of
                        State, <persName>Bill Foster</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                            >McNamara</persName> (<persName corresp="#p_KC2">Kaysen</persName>, at
                        this time, had placed a call to “Bob” but had not yet talked to him).<note
                            n="3" xml:id="d290fn3">No record of this telephone call has been
                            found.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KC2">Kaysen</persName> said that
                        if <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">General Taylor</persName> had a reaction to
                        transmit to the President that he would be glad to transmit it.<note n="4"
                            xml:id="d290fn4">The President left Washington the morning of June 5 for
                            a trip to the Southwest, California, and Hawaii. He arrived back in
                            Washington around 9 a.m. on June 10.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">General Taylor</persName> asked if this was
                        atmospheric testing—no implication of a ban on underground testing.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KC2">Kaysen</persName> said they were; the
                        United States does not now propose to conduct testing in the atmosphere as
                        long as someone else does not do so, the United States will not be the
                        first.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">General Taylor</persName> said that he would
                        suspect that “his corporation”<note n="5" xml:id="d290fn5">The Joint Chiefs
                            of Staff.</note> would feel that any unilateral abstination [abstention]
                        is bad; that his personal reaction is not particularly that way unless it
                        should indeed be a deterrent to underground testing.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KC2">Kaysen</persName> said the President’s
                        speech went on to say what efforts we are making to conclude a treaty. He
                        (the President) just feels very strongly on it, and that the President had
                        decided that this is a good time to do this. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KC2"
                            >Kaysen</persName> had learned this for the first time yesterday (7
                        June).</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">General Taylor</persName> said that he did not
                        think he should rush in and advise the President on this, but he would like
                        to plant the thought that this is likely to be a psychological deterrent to
                        underground testing. <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">General Taylor</persName>
                        asked if he could mention this to <persName corresp="#p_GRL1"
                            >Gilpatric</persName>.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KC2">Kaysen</persName> said he would rather call
                            <persName corresp="#p_GRL1">Gilpatric</persName>—although there was no
                        problem in talking to him if <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">General
                            Taylor</persName> wanted to—but he wanted to call him.<note n="6"
                            xml:id="d290fn6">No record of either telephone call has been
                            found.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KC2">Kaysen</persName> mentioned
                        that this was “secret” until the President made his speech.<note n="7"
                            xml:id="d290fn7">In a conversation held on June 11, French Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_AH9">Herve Alphand</persName> asked <persName
                                corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> if the timing of the speech was
                            “tactical or fundamental.” <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>
                            replied that there was no information from the Soviets pointing toward a
                            detente or a change in their position on nuclear testing, but that “the
                            timing was somewhat influenced by the forthcoming Soviet-Chinese
                            meetings.” If <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName>
                            attempted to “close the gap” with the Chinese by adopting unreasonable
                            positions on East-West issues such as Laos, the record would show that
                            the West had been reasonable. (Memorandum by Johannes V. Imhof;
                            Department of State, Secretary’s Memoranda of Conversation: Lot 65 D
                            330)</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <hi rend="strong">CWO Proctor</hi>
                    <note n="8" xml:id="d290fn8">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                        signature.</note>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
