<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-07-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-07-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="317" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d317">
                    <head>317. Letter From Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK3" type="from">Adenauer</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2" type="to">Kennedy</persName><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d317fn0">Source:
                            Department of State, Presidential Correspondence: Lot 66 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 204, Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName>’s Correspondence with Presidents <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> &amp; <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>, 1963-1964, Vol. II. Secret.
                            The source text is an unofficial translation apparently provided by the
                            German Embassy.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-07-09">July 9,
                            1963</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: Thank you very much for your
                        letter of July 4,<note n="1" xml:id="d317fn1">See <ref target="#d310">Document 310</ref>.</note> and for the confidence you have thus
                        shown me. I have gained, I believe, useful impulses for our policy from your
                        visit to the Federal Republic and to West Berlin as from the talks with you,
                        I am particularly grateful for your statement that you will get in personal
                        contact with me if there is any new development.</p>
                    <p>I have for the moment stopped my steps towards a contact which I had
                        mentioned to you,<note n="2" xml:id="d317fn2">See <ref target="#d310fn4">footnote 4, Document 310</ref>.</note> because I deem it suitable
                        for the time being to await the outcome of the negotiations between the
                        Soviet Union and Red China. I shall continue to inform you as soon as
                        something happens.</p>
                    <pb facs="0804" n="778" xml:id="pg_778"/>
                    <p>In the meanwhile, President <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName>
                        was here. The talks with him —the confidential talks as well as the other
                        talks—took a good course. <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi> as well
                        as BBC-London and anti-de Gaullist papers in Paris are publishing inaccurate
                        reports. I have confidentially spoken to President <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> in downright earnest about the
                        community of interests of all Allies vis-à-vis the Soviet Union, telling him
                        in particular that, whatever I do, I always ask myself: is hereby Moscow’s
                        hope of a split in the West to be strengthened or not. I suppose, President
                            <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> deems fair such a
                        question with respect to every Ally. I have not gained the impression that
                        he is in any way biassed vis-à-vis the United States of America.<note n="3" xml:id="d317fn3">On July 8, <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> replied to <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>’s July 3 letter (see <ref target="#d311">Document
                                311</ref>), stating that a potential non-aggression pact must not
                            have the effect of further stabilizing the status quo, including the
                            division of Germany and Berlin, and should be considered only in
                            connection with measures leading to an improvement of the German and
                            Berlin situation. <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> agreed
                            that it “would be useful to explore thoroughly the Soviet position in
                            the forthcoming talks.” (Unofficial translation supplied by the German
                            Embassy attached to German text; Department of State, Presidential
                            Correspondence: Lot 66 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 204, German
                            Officials’ Correspondence with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>, 1961-1964) An amplification of <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName>’s letter is contained in a
                            note from the German Embassy, July 9, attached to a memorandum of
                            conversation held July 8 between <persName corresp="#p_TWR2">Tyler</persName> and Georg von Lilienfeld, Minister of Embassy, by
                            F.E. Cash of BTF. (Department of State, Central Files, POL 28
                            Berlin)</note></p>
                    <p>With sincere regards</p>
                    <p>Yours</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_AK3"><hi rend="strong">K.
                                Adenauer</hi></persName><note n="4" xml:id="d317fn4">Printed from a
                                copy that indicates <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName>
                                signed the original.</note></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>