<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>319. Instructions for the Under Secretary of State for Political Affairs
                    (Harriman))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d319</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">319</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-07-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-07-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recujbZvPfRFtp7HU" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general">Nuclear test
                        ban</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recTNMFmPG15mKxJQ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">European security</term>
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recFKwbJC7hOq07wX" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation">Comprehensive Test Ban</term>
                    <term ref="recpqcSvEFyuxPc7E" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134146"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Testing</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft treaty</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec5leqjXNtlx0kjy" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="outer-space"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85096156"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Outer space</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec2qYX3T6ktEaSsg" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85087216"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Moratorium</term>
                    <term ref="recF2jh59vGhjZ2KX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="recCx6QZi7AaiEP6y" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general">Strategic
                        nuclear forces</term>
                    <term ref="recLwZnf8LnfqGD3M" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96004190"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Weapons of mass destruction</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="rec5e761bcdc7fa693" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation">Nuclear free zones</term>
                    <term ref="recNBOveCHYDHbAqL" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044163"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Environment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-07-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-07-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="319"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d319">
                <head>319. Instructions for the Under Secretary of State for Political Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_HWA2">Harriman</persName>)<note n="0" type="source"
                        xml:id="d319fn0">Source: <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName>
                        Library, National Security Files, Meetings and Memoranda Series, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Meetings, Nos. 515-517. Secret. Another
                        copy is attached to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 2468,
                        July 9, which states that the President approved the revised text after the
                        9:30 a.m. meeting; see <ref target="#d320">Document 320</ref>. (Department
                        of State, <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> (Miscellaneous) Files: Lot 66 <gloss target="#t_D1"
                            >D</gloss> 95, Records of Action by the National Security Council)
                        Regarding earlier drafts of the instructions, see <ref target="#d318fn1"
                            >footnote 1, Document 318</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-07-10">July 10, 1963</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">INSTRUCTIONS FOR HONORABLE <persName corresp="#p_HWA2">W. AVERELL
                        HARRIMAN</persName>
                </p>
                <p>Your mission involves both negotiating and exploratory aspects.</p>
                <p>On the negotiating side, you should seek to negotiate the most comprehensive
                    nuclear test ban treaty possible in accordance with existing guidelines.</p>
                <p>On the exploratory side, you should canvass, in so far as appears practical, the
                    range of issues involving peace and security which divide us from the Soviets.
                    You should give especial attention to two points: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>What other acceptable measures of disarmament the Soviets are
                            interested in undertaking;</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>What are Soviet intentions in dealing with the problems related to
                            European security, as raised in <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                                >Khrushchev</persName>’s speech of July 2.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">I. Test Ban</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Our judgment that a test ban treaty is in the national interest rests on
                        two grounds. First, it may be a significant first step toward the halting
                            <pb facs="0812" n="786" xml:id="pg_786"/> of the arms race and thus
                        reduce international tensions. Second, and more important, it is an
                        indispensable first step toward the limitation of the further diffusion of
                        nuclear weapons. The prospects of a further increase in the number of powers
                        possessing nuclear weapons poses a potentially serious threat to our
                        security and to world stability and peace. Therefore, a test ban treaty must
                        be viewed in relation to the problem of checking the further diffusion of
                        nuclear weapons.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Accordingly, the achievement of a comprehensive test ban treaty outlawing
                        testing in all environments remains our objective. However, Chairman
                            <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName>’s speech makes it
                        unlikely that we can reach agreement with the Soviets on a comprehensive
                        treaty at this time. Therefore, we should seek an agreement banning testing
                        in three environments along the lines of the August 27, 1962, draft treaty
                        banning nuclear weapons tests in atmosphere, outer space and underwater,
                        presented to the 18-Nation Committee on Disarmament in Geneva. You are
                        authorized to carry such negotiations as far as you can.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The achievement of such an agreement should be viewed as a first step
                        toward the achievement of a comprehensive test ban treaty. If the Soviets
                        show an interest in pursuing the topic, you should initiate technical
                        discussions with the Soviet Union which may resolve the present
                        disagreements between the Soviet Union on the one hand, and ourselves and
                        the United Kingdom on the other, on the need for inspections in any
                        comprehensive test ban treaty. The Soviets may, in one way or another, raise
                        the issue of a moratorium on underground tests. If the Soviets do this, you
                        may explore the usefulness of responding to such an initiative by means of a
                        limited quota of underground tests in addition to the total prohibition of
                        testing in other environments, but without discussing specific numbers,
                        unless on further instructions.<note n="1" xml:id="d319fn1">The part of this
                            sentence beginning with “but” is new.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">II. Non-Dissemination</p>
                <p>1. You should continue to emphasize the relation between the nuclear test ban
                    treaty and our desire to control the diffusion of nuclear weapons. In pursuing
                    this subject, you should be guided by the talks on non-dissemination of nuclear
                    weapons between Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> and
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>. You may indicate
                    that the United States will endeavor to secure adherence to or observation of
                    any non-dissemination agreement by those powers associated with it, if the
                    Soviet Union is willing to undertake a parallel responsibility for those powers
                    associated with it.<note n="2" xml:id="d319fn2">In the July 9 draft this
                        sentence reads: “You may indicate that the U.S. is willing to take some
                        responsibility in respect to non-dissemination with relation to those powers
                        associated with it, if the Soviet Union is willing to take a corresponding
                        obligation for the powers with which it is associated.”</note> In this
                    connection, you should maintain our position that the <pb facs="0813" n="787"
                        xml:id="pg_787"/>
                    <gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss> proposals now under discussion are not
                    inconsistent with the goal of a non-dissemination agreement.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d319fn3">This sentence is new.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">III. Other Measures of Disarmament</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Our talks on general and complete disarmament in the 18-Nation Disarmament
                        Conference in Geneva have made little progress. Recently Foreign Minister
                            <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> made a proposal which at
                        least raises the question of whether or not the Soviets are willing to
                        consider serious first-stage disarmament measures not tied to an agreement
                        to proceed rapidly to complete and general disarmament on terms which we
                        have always found unacceptable. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                            >Gromyko</persName>’s proposal still presents serious problems,
                        including the question of the extent of reduction of strategic nuclear
                        forces in relation to the reduction of other forces. Nonetheless, you should
                        explore the possibility that the <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                            >Gromyko</persName> proposal is intended to open a serious discussion of
                        separable first stages, on terms to which we can respond.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>In addition, you should attempt to discover Soviet interest in other
                        measures previously authorized as separable measures. These include, but
                        need not be limited to: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>An agreement not to put weapons of mass destruction in orbit. This
                                is a matter of particular interest to the United States.<note n="4"
                                    xml:id="d319fn4">This subparagraph is new.</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>A halt to the production of fissionable materials, under
                                appropriate safeguards, and in combination with the transfer from
                                military stockpiles of agreed quantities of fissionable materials to
                                peaceful uses. In this connection, you should be prepared to discuss
                                an arrangement in which we transfer more fissionable materials than
                                the Soviets.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>An agreement to establish nuclear free zones in areas where
                                nuclear weapons do not form an integral part of the security
                                arrangements upon which the countries in the areas rely. (This
                                refers to Latin America and Africa.)<note n="5" xml:id="d319fn5">The
                                    parenthetical sentence is new.</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>The scrapping on a one-for-one basis of B-47’s and Badgers at a
                                rate to be agreed.</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>Measures on the reduction of risk of war through accident,
                                miscalculation or failure of communication.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">IV. Other Measures</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName>, in his speech,
                        stated a connection between the test ban treaty and a non-aggression pact
                        between the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and Warsaw Pacts. Neither
                        the degree of this connection nor the nature of the proposals to which
                        Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> referred are
                        clear. In exploring Soviet intentions in this respect, you should be guided
                        by the following objectives: <pb facs="0814" n="788" xml:id="pg_788"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>If possible, we should separate the non-aggression
                                    arrangements<note n="6" xml:id="d319fn6">“Arrangements” replaces
                                    “pact.”</note> from the test ban treaty and other disarmament
                                matters. We should press the discussions on these, and defer to a
                                later date the further discussions of non-aggression arrangements.
                                We would prefer to go as far as possible in discussing the three
                                environment test ban treaty first, and then explore other measures
                                of disarmament, as well as the Soviet proposals for non-aggression
                                    arrangements.<note n="7" xml:id="d319fn7">The phrase “go as far
                                    as possible in discussing” replaces “conclude.”</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Even if it proves impossible to agree on this procedure it is
                                useful to explore Soviet purposes. The phrase, “non-aggression
                                pact”, has been loosely used to cover a wide variety of possible
                                arrangements about the way in which relations between Eastern
                                European Communist states and Soviet Russia on the one hand, and the
                                    <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> allies on the other, are
                                conducted. In discussing these arrangements, we must continue to
                                make clear that we can accept no arrangement which formally
                                recognizes the East German regime or which is inconsistent with the
                                ultimate reunification of Germany as a policy goal.<note n="8"
                                    xml:id="d319fn8">In the July 9 draft, the latter part of this
                                    sentence reads: “or which renounces the ultimate reunification
                                    of Germany as a policy goal.”</note> Further, we can make no
                                arrangements which do not insure the present Western position in
                                Berlin. In all these matters we must take into account the interests
                                of our allies. Within these constraints a non-aggression arrangement
                                could be advantageous to the West by reducing the possibility of
                                further Berlin crises. Accordingly, you should explore Soviet
                                purposes in advancing this suggestion, and the possible modes which,
                                in the Soviet view, would meet these purposes.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>You should also be prepared to explore any other matters which the Soviets
                        wish to raise under the general heading of improving relations<note n="9"
                            xml:id="d319fn9">“Improving relations” replaces “reducing
                            tensions.”</note> between the Soviet Bloc and <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                            >NATO</gloss>; or between the United States and the Soviet Union. In the
                        context of such a discussion, you may wish to raise the problem of enforcing
                        the Geneva Agreements in Laos.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
