<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>185. Memorandum of a Conversation, Secretary Dulles’ Residence, Washington,
                    March 3, 1957, 6:40 p.m.’ Residence, Washington, March 3, 1957, 6:40
                    p.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d185</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">185</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-03-03T18:40:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-03-03T18:40:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recENG9eU9z7Tfb9L" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recZobsyHhwdJPklD" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085246"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Occupied territory</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-03-03T18:40:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-03-03T18:40:00-05:00" n="185"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d185">
                <head>185. Memorandum of a Conversation, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1"
                        >Dulles</persName>’ Residence, Washington, March 3, 1957, 6:40 p.m.<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d185fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 674.84A/3–357. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RWM1"
                            >Rountree</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1957-03-03T18:40:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 3, 1957, 6:40 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Israeli Withdrawal</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Abba Eban</persName>, Israeli
                        Ambassador</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Reuven Shiloah</persName>, Israeli
                        Minister</item>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_U1">U</gloss>—<persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Christian A.
                            Herter</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>—<persName corresp="#p_RWM1">William M.
                            Rountree</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> said he could describe the
                    position of his Government more definitively than yesterday. The Prime Minister
                    would like tomorrow to complete the arrangements for withdrawal. He planned to
                    carry the matter through the Government and Parliament in the morning, to
                    arrange a meeting between the Israeli Chief of Staff and General <persName
                        corresp="#p_BMGELM1">Burns</persName> “to finalize everything” during the
                    early part of the day, and to be prepared for the Israeli representatives to
                    make an announcement in the General Assembly during the afternoon, New York
                    time. The Prime Minister had asked whether, on this basis, the United States
                    would be willing to help in one more respect. Carrying the program through the
                    Government and Parliament would be very difficult. The Prime Minister would,
                    however, be able to overcome these difficulties if he had an “inner-conviction”
                    regarding the American attitude in certain respects. He wanted to know, in order
                    to facilitate his efforts, whether we understood each other fully with respect
                    to Gaza. If Egypt, while in a state of war with Israel, were to return to Gaza
                    and thus recreate conditions set forth in Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_MG1"
                        >Meir</persName>’s statement, Israel would be prepared to act in defense of
                    its rights. The Ambassador hoped that we would be able to understand this
                    position. This would not involve a public statement on our part. The Secretary
                    had indicated last night that if the Ambassador wrote a letter setting forth
                    Israel’s position regarding its intentions to act under Article 51 to defend its
                    right of transit of the Straits, he would consider replying to the letter.
                    Perhaps, the Ambassador said, a similar arrangement could be made with the
                    United States taking full cognizance of what the Israelis said with respect to
                    Gaza. In her speech Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Meir</persName> had said, on
                    the basis of the arrangements worked out with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PC1"
                        >Pineau</persName> and the Secretary, that Israel reserved its right to act
                    under Article 51 if conditions in Gaza should impose a threat. The problem was
                    whether we understood each other regarding the circumstances in which Israel <pb
                        facs="0384" n="352" xml:id="pg_352"/> would act. His Government believed
                    that such a situation calling for Israeli action would be created if the United
                    Nations abandoned Gaza and Egypt should return. His Government would like to say
                    to us that in such a case of a premature breakdown of the United Nations in
                    Gaza, and a return of a belligerent Egypt, Israel would be justified in
                    considering that rights of defense would become operative. He did not know how
                    exactly Israel would protect its rights, but it would expect to be able to act
                    effectively. This matter had been discussed with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MG2"
                        >Mollet</persName> in Canada by the Israeli Ambassador there. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MG2">Mollet</persName> had suggested a text which in his opinion
                    would be consistent with the original suggestion discussed in Washington.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador showed the Secretary the text of the <persName corresp="#p_MG2"
                        >Mollet</persName> proposal. He said it is not intended that the statement
                    be public and that it would not necessarily be formally submitted, but a similar
                    statement from the United States on an informal and personal basis would give
                    the Prime Minister the feeling that we had not misunderstood each other.</p>
                <p>As to the form, the Ambassador said he might address himself to the Secretary
                    concerning the statements made by Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_MG1"
                        >Meir</persName> and state the determination of the Israeli Government to
                    protect its rights regarding shipping through the Straits of Aqaba. He might go
                    on with regard to Gaza and spell out that the occupation by Egypt of Gaza would
                    place into operation Israel’s rights to act. He would request the United States
                    to take cognizance of that policy declaration. The basis of the proposal was
                    that there was not a feeling, especially after the Friday General Assembly
                    session, that Israel was producing a situation in which Egypt would not move
                    back, and the Israeli Government would like to make it clear that in fact such a
                    situation preventing the Egyptian return had been created. The Prime Minister’s
                    feeling was that the Aqaba problem was of greater importance to Israel in the
                    future, and he believed that the arrangements made with respect to Aqaba were
                    adequate. On the other hand, although the Gaza problem was of less importance in
                    the long run, it evoked much stronger feelings particularly among the people in
                    the general area. It was therefore urgent to obtain some recognition of Israeli
                    rights of self-defense in the Gaza, even though this might be on a confidential
                    basis. His Government hoped that it would be possible to effect a speedy
                    withdrawal. If things went well it was the expectation that arrangements would
                    be completed before the Monday General Assembly meeting.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d185fn2">March 4.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary observed that the United Nations already had assumed that the
                    departure would be prompt, based upon what Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_MG1"
                        >Meir</persName> said on Friday. Unless there were a concrete move, the
                    situation <pb facs="0385" n="353" xml:id="pg_353"/> would deteriorate very
                    rapidly. Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Meir</persName> had stated her
                    Government proposed that a meeting be held immediately with the United Nations
                    Commander with regard to withdrawals from both Aqaba and Gaza.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador said that four members of the Cabinet had voted against the plan,
                    which had created a considerable problem. If the parties which they represented
                    took a strong position in the Parliament, a real difficulty might be involved,
                    and that could bring about new elections.</p>
                <p>The Secretary observed that if he understood the Ambassador clearly he was
                    suggesting that we acquiesce at least in the Israeli position that termination
                    of the United Nations’ exclusive control in Gaza, both civil and military, would
                    in itself be a cause for action by Israel. The Ambassador interposed that this
                    would be true only if it were at a time, as at present, when Egypt considered
                    itself to be at war with Israel. Continuing, the Secretary said that while it
                    might be said that if Egypt should return that would involve threats to Israel
                    such as those which existed before, he did not think we would from a juridical
                    standpoint be entitled to make such an assumption. What Mrs. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MG1">Meir</persName> had said was that if conditions were
                    created which would threaten Israel, then Israel would be entitled to act. It
                    would not be our view that Israel would have such rights merely because Egypt
                    occupied territory which under the Armistice Agreement Egypt was entitled to
                    occupy. One might consider that to be a threat, but he did not as a legal
                    proposition agree that the mere fact of occupation would give rise to a claim
                    that Israel was threatened to the extent that it was entitled to take action. We
                    of course did not want Egypt to exercise its legal rights and move back in the
                    Gaza. We had said that we would try to obtain a continuation of a situation in
                    which the United Nations would carry responsibility for the administration of
                    Gaza. We had some influence in the matter, and there were various ways in which
                    that influence might be exerted. We did not think, however, that our influence
                    would be effective if we should maintain that merely because Egypt exercised
                    certain rights it has under the agreement that would give rise to the use of
                    force to oust Egypt. This, the Secretary said, involved a difficult problem of
                    determining how long Israel would have to wait after the return of Egypt, and of
                    how imminent the danger must be, before there was the right of defense. Israel
                    took the view that any Egyptian participation in Gaza would carry a threat. On
                    the basis of past experience that was not surprising, but it was not a
                    conclusion to which we would come.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Shiloah</persName> said the Secretary had
                    previously stated that Egypt, for various reasons, was not keen on returning to
                    Gaza. For all practical purposes they might not be keen, although there were
                    perhaps political and prestige reasons why they might feel that they should go
                    back. If they did make an effort to restore their position in Gaza, he <pb
                        facs="0386" n="354" xml:id="pg_354"/> would assume that their motives would
                    be evil. The Secretary responded that while they might be evil, they probably
                    would be motivated first by questions of national prestige, which any of us were
                    prone to be.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador said perhaps a new formulation could be agreed. He asked whether
                    the Secretary would regard the Israeli safeguards as coming into effect not only
                    upon the return of Egypt but upon the recreation of conditions which would
                    threaten Israel’s security, using the words in Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_MG1"
                        >Meir</persName>’s statement. The Secretary said that even that would be an
                    over-simplification. There were many variations, and it would be difficult to
                    say exactly what our position would be in the many contingencies which might
                    arise. It might be, for example, that an Egyptian return to Gaza would be
                    accompanied by so many bellicose statements that Israel might feel justified in
                    acting without waiting to be struck first. We would not want to set ourselves up
                    as arbiters to say how long Israel should wait before taking action. On the
                    other hand if the Egyptian return were merely for prestige reasons, and involved
                    no large numbers of Egyptians, clearly there would be no such rights on the part
                    of Israel. This situation simply did not lend itself to an expression of opinion
                    in advance. He thought that Israel would be much better off to let the matter
                    stand as at present. He thought it essential to the integrity of the United
                    States position that we be able to state that we had not given any secret
                    assurances or guarantees to Israel. We could honestly state that now, and must
                    keep it that way. He did not think that any public statement which we could make
                    would make it easier for Israel to withdraw, and perhaps with the qualifications
                    which we have to impose it would make it more difficult. The United States could
                    not assume the position of being the guardian of Israel’s rights and he did not
                    think Israel wished to put us in that position. Any statement which we made
                    would lack any binding effect and would serve to confuse rather than clarify the
                    situation. The matter should be left to stand as it was. If, after completion of
                    the withdrawal, Israel wished to ask us questions about any such matters, we
                    would consider making replies, although even then we would not want to work too
                    much on a hypothetical basis. We knew what the Israelis wanted and they knew
                    what we wanted. Surely we both understood that there was no guarantee that
                    things would happen as we would like. We would try, but if the situation should
                    not develop according to our wishes and Israel should feel itself threatened,
                    Israel had unilaterally reserved its freedom of action. He did not think that
                    Israel could be any better off than that in the circumstances.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador said he would of course have to accept the Secretary’s position.
                    He wondered whether the situation might be looked at in this broader context:
                    The Israeli representative had made a statement in the General Assembly; the
                    American representative <pb facs="0387" n="355" xml:id="pg_355"/> said he had
                    taken note and commented that the Israeli hopes and expectations were not
                    unreasonable. The Ambassador wondered whether he could address a letter to the
                    Secretary saying that he attached great importance to two specified aspects of
                    Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Meir</persName>’s statement, which would be
                    quoted along with parts of Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1"
                        >Lodge</persName>’s statement. The Secretary would reply that he had taken
                    note of what Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Meir</persName> had said in this
                    specific regard.</p>
                <p>In response to the Secretary’s question as to what he thought about the
                    suggestion, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> said he was
                    concerned with the implications of a further exchange along these lines. The
                    fact that part of the statements made by Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_MG1"
                        >Meir</persName> and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1"
                        >Lodge</persName> had been extracted from their total context and were the
                    subject of a special exchange between the Israeli and United States Governments
                    would undoubtedly lead to widespread speculation as to their import.</p>
                <p>The Secretary told Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> that he
                    would consider the matter. He felt that no time should be lost in this respect,
                    however. He was afraid that if the withdrawal was not well underway before the
                    General Assembly met on Monday, Arab representatives would make statements to
                    the effect that the Israeli assumptions were unjustified and unacceptable. If
                    that should happen, the Israeli position would be much weaker than if they
                    proceeded with the withdrawal program under the assumptions which had not been
                    knocked down. The Israeli position would be stronger if they could proceed on
                    the basis of the statements made and which up to the time of the announced
                    withdrawal had not been denounced.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that the Ambassador would immediately prepare the text of the
                    letter which he would like to send to the Secretary asking that the United
                    States take note of the specific statements made by Mrs. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MG1">Meir</persName>. He would then consider whether he felt it
                    would be possible or useful to reply along the lines requested. The Ambassador
                    said he would return to the Embassy and send back a draft promptly for the
                    Secretary’s consideration.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
