<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>262. Telegram From the Embassy in Egypt to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d262</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">262</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-04-01T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-04-01T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recWpOYNUONIWKYCh" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85109354"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Explosion</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-04-01T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-04-01T18:00:00-05:00" n="262"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d262">
                <head>262. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Egypt</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d262fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 974.7301/4–257. Secret; Priority. Received at 4:19 p.m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Cairo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-04-02T01:00:00+02:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 2, 1957—1 a.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3093. Embassy telegram 3083.<note n="2" xml:id="d262fn2">At 11:30 a.m., March 31,
                        in Cairo, <persName corresp="#p_HRA1">Hare</persName> delivered to <persName
                            corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName> a third-person Note setting forth the
                        comments of the U.S. Government on the Egyptian memorandum of March 26 (see
                        telegram 3253, <ref target="#d258">Document 258</ref>) and, as an enclosure
                        to the Note, the revised text of the Egyptian memorandum as cabled to Cairo
                        in telegram 3238, <ref target="#d255">Document 255</ref>. At the same time,
                            <persName corresp="#p_HRA1">Hare</persName> presented orally the
                        comments suggested in telegram 3253. (Telegram 3081 from Cairo, March 31,
                        and despatch 734 from Cairo, April 1; Department of State, Central Files,
                        974.7301/3–3157 and 974.7301/4–157, respectively)<p>Telegram 3083 from
                            Cairo, March 31, transmitted <persName corresp="#p_FM1"
                            >Fawzi</persName>’s preliminary comments at the time the documents were
                            presented. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 974.7301/3–3157)</p>
                    </note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> gave me following fill-in last
                    night following his final talks with <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName>:</p>
                <p>Talk with <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> centered primarily
                    around his reactions to our comments on Egypt second draft<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d262fn3">Reference is presumably to the Egyptian draft memorandum of
                        March 26; see telegram 3032, <ref target="#d250">Document 250</ref>.</note>
                    and on memo of personal suggestions which <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1"
                        >McCloy</persName> had prepared at request of <persName corresp="#p_FM1"
                        >Fawzi</persName>.<note n="4" xml:id="d262fn4">
                        <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName>’s memorandum was transmitted
                        to the Department of State in telegram 3094 from Cairo, April 2, not
                        printed. (Department of State, Central Files, 974.7301/4–257)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Reference proposed revision of draft <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1"
                        >McCloy</persName> led off by urging forthright action by <gloss
                        target="#t_GOE1">GOE</gloss> in order create atmosphere of confidence and
                    even suggested <gloss target="#t_GOE1">GOE</gloss> go further and voluntarily
                    increase Development Fund from 25 to 30 percent as evidence of Egypt
                    constructive intention. In so doing he followed general line of our
                    representations. (<persName corresp="#p_BRJ1">Bunche</persName> later told me he
                    did so with great vigor). <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> began
                    response by rather disarming acknowledgment of understanding if implications of
                    situation and admission of doubt Egypt able run Canal effectively without
                    foreign help. However, when conversation turned specifically to United States
                    suggestions he reverted to characteristic suspicion and said seemed clear our
                    proposals primarily made “to make case for Israel”; this could be read between
                    lines our entire draft. As particular evidence of this he pointed to adherence
                    provision of which, he maintained, Israel would be one of first to take
                    advantage and to follow up by citing six points in order put Egypt on spot. He
                    seemed fully convinced this was our principal motive.</p>
                <p>Another point to which he took exception was provision regarding Development Fund
                    which he convinced intended put in escrow. <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1"
                        >McCloy</persName> pointed out provision did not so read. <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> was only half-convinced. <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> also objected to restriction placed on
                    raising tolls <pb facs="0533" n="501" xml:id="pg_501"/> even within one percent
                    limit proposed by <gloss target="#t_GOE1">GOE</gloss>, and to setting up an
                    outside board. Why couldn’t Canal Authority have its own board as had old Canal
                    Company?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>’s objections to mention of six
                    points were especially strong. Not only were they subject to varying
                    interpretation but they had been product of negotiations with British and French
                    who now known to have been dealing in bad faith. To be sure they remain on books
                    but he just didn’t want to talk about them any more. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> said his strongest arguments didn’t
                    seem shake <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> in this regard.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> then read to <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> personal and informal memo which he
                    had noted down at <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName>’s request in
                    attempt move ahead (text in immediate following telegram). <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> seemed interested and asked to retain
                    copy. <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> agreed but emphasized
                    tentative character and said not at all sure would be approved in his United
                    Nations capacity. <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>’s reactions to
                    specific points were as follows: 1) he was fairly receptive to idea of
                    increasing Development Fund to 30 percent.<note n="5" xml:id="d262fn5">In his
                        memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> suggested raising
                        the amount of the proposed Suez Canal Capital and Development Fund to 30
                        percent of the Canal’s gross revenues, as a means of emphasizing Egypt’s
                        good intent without any cost to Egypt.</note> 2) Regarding board of
                    consultants he questioned desirability of bringing United Nations in picture
                    but, after <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName>’s explanations, he
                    seemed not to exclude idea.<note n="6" xml:id="d262fn6">
                        <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> recommended the establishment
                        of a board of consultants appointed by the U.N. Secretary-General to be
                        composed of: (1) representatives of the private interests whose products and
                        materials pass through the Canal; (2) representatives of the shipping and
                        passenger interests who use the Canal; and (3) a certain number of
                        individuals of high standing and experience who could be said to represent
                        the public interest at large.</note> He also questioned desirability of
                    mentioning board in declaration since would perpetuate “for eternity”. 3)
                    Regarding suggested reference in announcement to World Bank.<note n="7"
                        xml:id="d262fn7">
                        <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> also proposed that
                        coincidentally with the publication of the Declaration the Egyptian
                        Government should announce that it was requesting the World Bank to study
                        immediately, in conjunction with its preliminary plans and methods of
                        financing, the radical rehabilitation and improvement of the Canal as a
                        modern waterway fully designed to meet future trade needs.</note> He did not
                    object in principle but said dubious about making announcement to that effect
                    now because of his recent unhappy experience with that institution. Said he
                    would like have <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName>’s views.</p>
                <p>Regard repayment of advances by surcharge,<note n="8" xml:id="d262fn8">According
                        to <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName>’s memorandum, Egypt should
                        also announce its acceptance of the principle that the advances voluntarily
                        made by contributing nations toward clearing the Suez Canal should be repaid
                        and that as a matter of equity Egypt was prepared to impose a surcharge on
                        the existing tolls designed to liquidate such advances as promptly as
                        possible, the surcharge not to exceed 10 percent of existing toll
                        charges.</note>. <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> said only
                    that United Nations should be repaid for its help but he wondered what attitude
                    of various countries would be. Russians and Indians had already said they did
                    not intend participate in defraying clearance costs.</p>
                <pb facs="0534" n="502" xml:id="pg_502"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> spoke highly of Wheeler and said
                    wanted show appreciation in some way. He also repeated usual story that matter
                    Israeli passage through Canal not only legal question but practical security
                    problem. As matters stand would have to deploy half of army along Canal to
                    assure safe passage of single Israeli ship.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> said conversation with <persName
                        corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName> had covered series subjects from Israel to
                    world scene. Re American draft, <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName> said
                    useful and would use as much as possible. He also felt <persName
                        corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName>’s draft would be helpful and hoped to
                    be able weave in some ideas.</p>
                <p>When <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> noted there had as yet been
                    no strong reaction from British or French, <persName corresp="#p_FM1"
                        >Fawzi</persName> suggested might be result of domestic troubles of effect
                    of consultation with US but he then hinted that might be in anticipation of
                    early “explosion”. When <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> asked
                    what he meant, <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName> said <gloss
                        target="#t_GOE1">GOE</gloss> has reports of unusual movements of French
                    fleet which would seem unrelated to Algerian situation and also has had
                    disquieting intelligence reports from Israel. He emphasized that this
                    information was very confidential.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> said that in conversations with
                    both <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>, he had suggested possibility of
                    improved American-Egyptian relations if certain pending difficulties could be
                    surmounted but that neither had sought pursue subject.</p>
                <p>In conclusion, <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> said he felt that
                    his endeavors may have helped some in promoting receptivity to American
                    suggestions and he thought he had probably been particularly helpful in
                    strengthening hand of <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName>. However, he
                    was not overly sanguine.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> is returning direct to New York
                    without stopping in either Paris or London.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HRA1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Hare</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
