<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-04-11T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-04-11T15:00:00-05:00" n="281" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d281">
                            <head>281. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Egypt</gloss>
                                to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d281fn1">Source: Department of State,
                                    Central Files, 974.7301/4–1157. Secret; Priority. Received at
                                    8:07 p.m.</note></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Cairo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-04-11T22:00:00+02:00"><hi rend="italic">April 11,
                                            1957—10 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                            <p>3204. Re <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 3190.<note n="2" xml:id="d281fn2">See <ref target="#d280fn2">footnote 2, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi></ref>.</note> This is more
                                detailed account of meeting with <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName>:</p>
                            <p>I began by tracing course of conversations, covered points in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 3341<note n="3" xml:id="d281fn3"><ref target="#d276">Document 276</ref>.</note>
                                and suggested that discussion be directed to three main points, i.e.
                                six principles, user representation and adherence, concerning which
                                I outlined our position.</p>
                            <p>Regarding six principles, <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> took very strong line. His reason, he said,
                                was historical. Six principles had been product of <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> meeting in which British and French
                                had participated at time when, speaking in terms of peaceful
                                solution, they were planning forceful seizure of canal. Furthermore,
                                real thinking of British and French had been clearly revealed in
                                vetoed part of October 13 resolution and unfortunately US had been
                                “more or less on their side”. Against this background he saw
                                insistence on inclusion six principles as a trap of West which would
                                result in his being hailed before <gloss target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss> “every day” on one pretext or another. What was it
                                we really wanted anyway? Did we have something up our sleeve? Was it
                                some trick? I replied that, if it were, I naturally would not tell
                                him (uproarious laughter by <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> at this point) but it so happened that I was
                                fully acquainted with background of matter and could assure him
                                there was no double-dealing involved. <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> had said he had suspicions arising out of
                                history of case; we also felt we had good grounds have some serious
                                doubts as I had explained to him exactly one week before (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 3112).<note n="4" xml:id="d281fn4"><ref target="#d270">Document 270</ref>.</note>
                                Inclusion of six points would be important step in restoring this
                                shaken confidence.</p>
                            <p>After this little dust-up, <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> settled down to serious discussion and said
                                just could not see way clear to including something in declaration
                                which not understandable because subject to various interpretations.
                                Actually <gloss target="#t_GOE1">GOE</gloss> had six points in mind
                                in drafting declaration and had included number of points designed
                                meet its interpretation of them. If this was not sufficient and
                                further safeguards were desired, then he would be glad incorporate
                                in declaration provided they were specific and not unreasonable. It
                                was not further guarantees that he was opposing but guarantees which
                                he could not understand. He would not even object to putting in
                                something about insulation from <pb facs="0569" n="537" xml:id="pg_537"/> politics if term could be clearly and
                                reasonably defined. He, too, believed in insulation from
                                politics—from international politics—and only natural there should
                                be reciprocal guarantee from Egyptian politics. Was not this
                                reasonable?</p>
                            <p>I replied interested in <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>’s suggestions for finding solution this
                                problem but had some doubts re practicability. Very often necessary
                                to state objectives in general terms owing fact application would be
                                too complicated to cover in detail; would be question of
                                feasibility. However, would report.</p>
                            <p>He next discussed representation of users and <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> put on another emotional
                                act. He would never consent to anything that would allow outside
                                management and control. He had even become allergic to word “users”
                                with either small or capital “U”. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> had submitted a plan for consultative body of
                                users last October and he had turned it down. He believed in
                                international cooperation; that only natural if Canal to be run
                                effectively; but he would not submit to international control.</p>
                            <p>I asked if it to be understood then what <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> opposed deal with any user
                                group, even on purely consultative basis. At first <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> replied in affirmative
                                but, on second thought, he explained what he was really opposed to
                                was governmental user representation. However, he saw no reason why
                                there should not be some organization of business interests with
                                which <gloss target="#t_GOE1">GOE</gloss> could deal on consultative
                                basis and also in connection paragraph 4 (B) re tolls and paragraph
                                7, both of which had been significantly amended.</p>
                            <p>Discussion on the question of form of declaration was brief.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> said could not
                                accept suggestion re adherences of which Israelis could take
                                advantage at this time. If we could suggest way in which adherences
                                could be provided for and Israel excluded, he had no objection.
                                Otherwise, he could not accept. However, advice available to <gloss target="#t_GOE1">GOE</gloss> is that declaration would be
                                legally binding by registration with <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and acknowledgment of type <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Hammarskjöld</persName> had proposed.</p>
                            <p>We then discussed various points of lesser importance in declaration,
                                noting areas of agreement and disagreement but nothing of interest
                                developed to supplement discussion earlier in day with <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName> (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 3185).<note n="5" xml:id="d281fn5">Dated April
                                    10, not printed. (Department of State, Central Files,
                                    974.7301/4–1057)</note></p>
                            <p>Concluding part of talk re degree of coincidence of views covered in
                                reference telegram.</p>
                            <p>Have learned today that probable reason for <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>’s rather unusual behavior
                                last night was that he was suffering from case of “gyppy tummy”
                                which, combined with observance of Ramadan, had <pb facs="0570" n="538" xml:id="pg_538"/> caused him so much discomfort that he
                                had thought of postponing meeting but had not done so for fear of
                                giving impression procrastinating.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HRA1"><hi rend="strong">Hare</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>