<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-09-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-09-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="376" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d376">
                        <head>376. Memorandum From the Under Secretary of State’s Special Assistant
                                (<persName type="from">Villard</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d376fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                                320.51/7–257. Secret. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_WWNJ1">Walmsley</persName> concurred in the memorandum which was sent
                                through <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> and the
                                Executive Secretariat. The memorandum is item No. 5 of “Palestine
                                Refugee Problem, Villard Study, 1957–58”.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-09-30"><hi rend="italic">September 30,
                                    1957</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Palestine Refugee Problem</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi></p>
                        <p>Since the preparation of the <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> memorandum of July 2 and mine of August
                            6 on the Palestine refugee problem (Tab l),<note n="2" xml:id="d376fn2">Not attached to the source text. See <ref target="#d349">Documents
                                    349</ref> and <ref target="#d360">360</ref>.</note> which were
                            discussed with you on August 7, developments in the Near East have cast
                            a shadow over the possibility of constructive action regarding the
                            refugees at this time.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> study and recommendations were made on two basic
                                assumptions: (1) that it is an overriding political necessity to
                                have some solution prior to <gloss target="#t_UNRWA1">UNRWA</gloss>’s expiration date in 1960, and (2) that conditions in
                                the area are somewhat more favorable today for an initiative by the
                                United States on the refugee problem. With the first of these
                                assumptions I am still in general agreement. But events in Syria
                                have so changed the climate in the area that whatever encouragement
                                we may have had two or three months ago to believe that conditions
                                were more favorable seems now to have been offset by the disturbing
                                effect of Syria’s pro-Soviet trend, the deteriorating security
                                situation in Lebanon, and the prevailing political uncertainty in
                                Jordan and other neighboring countries.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>At a meeting on September 17, attended by officers of <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>, it was agreed that in view of the Syrian situation,
                                conditions in the area were not ripe for a fresh attempt, on United
                                States or other initiative, to solve the long-standing problem of
                                the Palestine refugees. It was felt, however, that as a preliminary
                                step in this direction it would be well if I conferred with the
                                Secretary-General of the United Nations in regard to his memorandum
                                of June 17, 1957<note n="3" xml:id="d376fn3">Not printed, but see
                                    the brief summary of it in <ref target="#d349">Document
                                        349</ref>. Later in August, <persName corresp="#p_CAW1">Cordier</persName> delivered to the Department of State an
                                    aide-mémoire by <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Hammarskjöld</persName>, dated August 16, which contained a
                                    summary of developments subsequent to the June 17 memorandum. A
                                    copy is in Department of State, Wilcox Files: Lot 60 D 113,
                                    Refugees.</note> and outlined to him the plan of approach which
                                had been under tentative consideration here. It was further agreed
                                that I should explain, on a personal <pb facs="0774" n="742" xml:id="pg_742"/> basis and as reflecting the views of the
                                political officers concerned with the area, that it would be
                                inadvisable to start to carry out any plan for the refugees until
                                circumstances were more favorable than at present.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>I accordingly went to New York and conferred in the strictest
                                confidence with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Hammarskjold</persName> on September 19. A copy of my
                                memorandum of conversation with him is attached. (Tab 2)<note n="4" xml:id="d376fn4">Not attached to the source text. A copy is item
                                    No. 4 of the Villard Study. The original memorandum of
                                    conversation is in Department of State, Central Files,
                                    884.411/9–1957. A memorandum, dated September 18 and drafted by
                                    Villard, which contained a discussion of the points which
                                    Villard intended to make to <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Hammarskjöld</persName>, is <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>,
                                    320.51/9–1857.</note> The Secretary-General agreed completely
                                that this was not the moment to launch an attack on the refugee
                                problem, especially as neither side appeared anxious to disturb the
                                status quo of the Palestine question during the current General
                                Assembly. He thought, however, that he had had sufficient
                                encouragement in the past from Egyptian Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName> to explore the Palestine issue
                                with him as soon as <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName>
                                arrived at the United Nations. <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName>’s reaction might serve as a guide to the next
                                step. I have the impression that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Hammarskjold</persName> himself would like to serve in some way
                                on the refugee problem, as far as Cairo is concerned, and that he
                                believes he has a good deal of personal influence there which might
                                be helpful. From past experience, however, I would not expect too
                                much from the forthcoming talks between <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName> and the Secretary-General.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>I have also talked with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JEA1">Eric
                                    Johnston</persName>, who continues to believe that we should
                                push the Jordan River plan as a vital element to the solution of the
                                refugee question as well as a necessity to the existence of Jordan
                                as a viable state. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JEA1">Johnston</persName> did not seem impressed by the political
                                problems created by developments in Syria, pointing out that Syria’s
                                pro-Soviet tendencies have been known for some time. He felt that we
                                should put pressure on Israel to agree to the principle of
                                repatriation, and that this could best be done by an approach to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BGD1">Ben-Gurion</persName>, with the
                                President’s backing, and by an effort to enlist the support of
                                responsible Jews in this country who were neither Zionist extremists
                                nor non-Zionists. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JEA1">Johnston</persName> suggested this was a job which he would be
                                willing to tackle personally.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>It may be said that no time has ever yet been opportune to press
                                for a solution to the refugee question, nor is it ever likely to be
                                completely so in the future. There is, of course, a certain urgency
                                to the matter, if any move is to be made before <gloss target="#t_UNRWA1">UNRWA</gloss> goes out of existence in 1960.
                                Moreover Israel is anxious to obtain financial assistance from us at
                                this time and has shown a desire to orientate its foreign policy
                                with ours in some respects. Other considerations aside, presentation
                                of <pb facs="0775" n="743" xml:id="pg_743"/> a concrete proposal by
                                the United States regarding the refugee question might reveal a more
                                cooperative attitude on the part of Israel than in the past.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>If for no other reason, we are under an obligation to move in the
                                direction of a solution because the Congress, in appropriating funds
                                for <gloss target="#t_UNRWA1">UNRWA</gloss> in the fiscal year 1958,
                                attached this condition: “In determining whether or not to continue
                                furnishing assistance for Palestine refugees in the Near East, the
                                President shall take into account whether Israel and the Arab host
                                governments are taking steps toward the resettlement and
                                repatriation of such refugees.”<note n="5" xml:id="d376fn5">Additional amendments to the Mutual Security Act of 1954 were
                                    signed into law on August 14, 1957. See 71 Stat. 361.</note> The
                                presumption is that in the absence of any such steps there may be a
                                cessation of United States contributions for the remainder of <gloss target="#t_UNRWA1">UNRWA</gloss>’s life. If this prospect were
                                brought home to the Arab host governments, they might see some merit
                                in an early solution of the problem.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Nevertheless, we must recognize the fact that however divided the
                                Arab countries may be on other issues, they continue to preserve a
                                remarkably united front on the question of Palestine. No one of them
                                is likely to take the lead in accepting a refugee solution; and by
                                injecting the refugee problem into the political situation at this
                                time there is a danger that the attention of the Arabs would be
                                distracted from the Communist threat in the area and again
                                concentrated on a highly sensitive segment of the Arab-Israeli
                                dispute. Taking into consideration the realities of the situation,
                                it would appear that the best we can hope to do at the present time
                                is not to initiate an all-out effort to break the back of the
                                refugee problem, but to continue working on a plan which might have
                                a reasonable chance of acceptance under more favorable
                                circumstances.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>We should postpone action on the steps suggested in the <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>
                                memorandum of July 2, at least until the Syrian situation is more
                                clearly resolved.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>We should continue to devote careful study to the refugee problem
                                and to the proposed plans for its solution so as to be in a position
                                to move ahead promptly whenever circumstances warrant.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>If developments justify, and particularly if Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Hammarskjold</persName> should encourage
                                further discussion, I should take advantage of the General Assembly
                                in New York to study the situation at firsthand and possibly lay the
                                groundwork for whatever steps may be practicable in the direction of
                                a settlement at the proper time.<note n="6" xml:id="d376fn6"><persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> initialed his
                                    approval of all the recommendations on the source
                                text.</note></item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>