<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>63. Memorandum of Discussion at the 312th Meeting of the National Security
                    Council, Washington, February 7, 1957, 9 a.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d63</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">63</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-02-07T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-02-07T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recXuFW8WO1tqBrVK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recd7021a58b486ded" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="suez-canal" subject="suez-canal">Suez Canal</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-02-07T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-02-07T09:00:00-05:00" n="63"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d63">
                <head>63. Memorandum of Discussion at the 312th Meeting of the National Security
                    Council, Washington, February 7, 1957, 9 a.m.<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d63fn1">Source: Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Records. Top Secret; Eyes Only. Drafted by
                            <persName corresp="#p_GSE1">Gleason</persName> on February 8. The time
                        of the meeting is from the record of the President’s Daily Appointments.
                            (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1957-02-07T09:00:00-05:00"
                            >February 7, 1957, 9 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follow a paragraph listing the participants at the meeting and agenda item
                    1.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">2. Significant World Developments Affecting U.S. Security</hi>
                </p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of unrelated subjects.]</p>
                <p>Mr. [<persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen</persName>] <persName corresp="#p_DAW1"
                        >Dulles</persName> pointed out that clearance of the Suez Canal was
                    continuing at a very rapid pace, and limited transit for vessels with not more
                    than a 25-foot draft was possible right now. Unlimited transit could be expected
                    in early March. Meanwhile, there was not very much evidence to suggest that
                        <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> has changed his position of
                    insisting on all payments for the transit of the Canal be made to Egypt.</p>
                <pb facs="0132" n="100" xml:id="pg_100"/>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> observed that we had
                    proposed yesterday to <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Hammarskjöld</persName> that he
                    try to get Egyptian agreement to the payment of all tolls to the International
                    Bank. Half of these payments would immediately go to Egypt; the other half would
                    remain with the Bank pending the achievement of a solution of the Canal
                    problem.</p>
                <p>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Radford</persName> pointed out that three or
                    four Soviet merchant vessels were at this moment approaching the entrance to the
                    Canal. He thought it quite likely that they would pass through the Canal on
                    Sunday. They would ostentatiously pay their tolls to the Egyptian Government,
                    and thus make a great propaganda play. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HGM1"
                        >Humphrey</persName> commented that every single minute was important to us.
                    If a large number of ships start rushing through the Canal as soon as it opens
                    and pay their tolls to <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>, we will
                    be confronted with an accomplished fact. <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName> would have secured complete control of the Canal, and the
                    only thing left for us to do would be to station battleships at both ends of the
                    Canal and prevent the transit of any ships. This was hardly a welcome course of
                    action.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> pointed out the
                    difficulty that all of this was in a certain sense <persName corresp="#p_HD1"
                        >Hammarskjöld</persName>’s responsibility, and he already has too much to
                    do. Nevertheless, we are pressing him hard on this matter. Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_HGM1">Humphrey</persName> closed the discussion with a statement
                    that the moment Soviet vessels go through the Canal, that will mark the end of
                    all negotiations with <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> for a
                    reasonable settlement.</p>
                <p>[Here follow discussion of unrelated subjects and agenda item 3.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">4. The Suez Canal Situation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Cutler</persName> said that Admiral <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1"
                        >Radford</persName> wished to bring the problem of the Suez Canal situation
                    before the Council. Admiral <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Radford</persName>
                    explained the fear of the Joint Chiefs of Staff that once ships begin to transit
                    the Suez Canal paying their tolls to <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName>, control of the Canal would again revert completely to
                        <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>. The only possible ray of
                    hope that the Chiefs could perceive was that the Israelis would prove themselves
                    smart, would obey the injunctions of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>,
                    bring their own ships to the entrance to the Canal, and thus clearly pose the
                    issue of the right of Israeli ships to transit the Canal. If the Egyptians
                    forcibly prevented the passage of Israeli vessels, they would place themselves
                    clearly in the wrong and we and the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> would be
                    in a position to impose sanctions on <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName>.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> pointed out that, after
                    all, the United States was not anxious to get into a war in the Middle East in
                    place of the British and the French. He indicated that the United States had
                    applied about every sanction it possessed against Egypt except the ultimate one
                    of military force. In reply to a criticism of <persName corresp="#p_HD1"
                        >Hammarskjöld</persName>’s handling of this issue by Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_HGM1">Humphrey</persName>, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DAW1"
                        >Dulles</persName> defended <persName corresp="#p_HD1"
                        >Hammarskjöld</persName>
                    <pb facs="0133" n="101" xml:id="pg_101"/>as having done a very good job, at
                    least up to now. We need not necessarily assume that <persName corresp="#p_HD1"
                        >Hammarskjöld</persName> will fail on the last and most important phase of
                    the Suez Canal problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The National Security Council:</hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d63fn2">The paragraph that follows constitutes <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 1668, approved by the President
                        on February 8. (Department of State, <gloss target="#t_SS1"
                            >S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> (Miscellaneous) Files:
                        Lot 66 D 95, Records of Action by the National Security Council,
                        1957)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Discussed the subject in the light of the views of the Joint Chiefs of Staff as
                    presented orally at the meeting by the Chairman, <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                        >JCS</gloss>.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GSE1">
                            <hi rend="strong">S. Everett Gleason</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
