<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-02-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="66" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d66">
                            <head>66. Memorandum for the Record by the Assistant Secretary of State
                                for Near Eastern, South Asian, and African Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d66fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                                    784A.5622/2–757. Top Secret; Eyes Only.</note></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-02-07"><hi rend="italic">February 7,
                                        1957</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p>General Fox called to see me on February 7 on instructions from Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GG1">Gray</persName>. He said the Joint
                                Chiefs of Staff had recommended that “Operation Stockpile” as it
                                relates to 24 F–86’s for possible future delivery to Israel should
                                be cancelled unless the Department of State felt that this would be
                                unwise in present circumstances. He said the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> wished to release the equipment for other priority
                                needs.</p>
                            <p>I recalled that part of the operation relating to a shipload of
                                military equipment for possible use of Egypt had already been
                                cancelled. I said that while I believed in present circumstances the
                                Department would agree with the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>’
                                recommendation, I wished to confirm this with the Secretary in view
                                of the latter’s personal interest in the matter.</p>
                            <pb facs="0138" n="106" xml:id="pg_106"/>
                            <p>Later, on February 7, I talked personally with the Secretary who
                                agreed that the operation might be cancelled. I have conveyed this
                                information to General Fox. The matter will be confirmed in an
                                exchange of letters between Defense and State.<note n="2" xml:id="d66fn2">In a letter to General Fox dated February 19,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> confirmed
                                    that the Department of State had no objection to the termination
                                    of “Operation Stockpile”. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName>’s letter also noted that the supplies
                                    and equipment assembled to support the plan were urgently needed
                                    to fulfill other requirements. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>,
                                    700.56/2–857)</note></p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>