<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>67. Telegram From the Mission at the United Nations to the to the Department
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d67</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">67</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-02-07T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-02-07T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQFlapfZuYOQASo" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042795"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nationalization</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-02-07T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-02-07T20:00:00-05:00" n="67"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d67">
                <head>67. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Mission at the United Nations</gloss>
                    to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d67fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 974.7301/2–757. Confidential; Priority. Received at 12:18 a.m.,
                        February 8. Repeated to London.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-02-07T20:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 7, 1957—8 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 685. London for <persName>James W.
                        Swihart</persName>.<note n="2" xml:id="d67fn2">First Secretary of the
                        Embassy in London.</note> Verbatim text. Re Suez Canal. We conveyed to
                        <persName corresp="#p_CAW1">Cordier</persName> Department’s views regarding
                    interim arrangements Thursday morning for Suez Canal as contained in <gloss
                        target="#t_Gadel1">Gadel</gloss> 133.<note n="3" xml:id="d67fn3">
                        <ref target="#d61">Document 61</ref>.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CAW1">Cordier</persName> said he and <gloss
                        target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> would study them carefully and take them into
                    account since they are anxious to keep as close to US views on this as is
                    possible. During course day, Ramsbotham (<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>)
                    informed <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss> that <gloss target="#t_UK1"
                        >UK</gloss> Embassy had been in contact with Dept and that we here were to
                    be asked to set forth views in support “Neutral Agency and Fifty-Fifty” scheme.
                    We confirmed such approach made to <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Late Thursday afternoon <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Hammarskjold</persName> via
                    letter to <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> sent us working paper
                    given below. It is also being given to <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, France
                    and Norway for their reactions. <persName corresp="#p_CAW1">Cordier</persName>
                    says it is a working paper on which <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> wants
                    our views. Paper is for internal Secretariat use only and its purpose is to
                    clarify certain points at issue.</p>
                <p>Would appreciate Department’s views urgently.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">“Working Paper—7 February 1957</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>An early arrangement of a provisional character for the collection of all
                        payments for transit through the Suez Canal seems essential in order to
                        avoid a possible conflict when traffic through the Canal is resumed. The
                        arrangement should be such as to avoid any prejudging of the forthcoming
                        negotiations on the general settlement. It should <pb facs="0139" n="107"
                            xml:id="pg_107"/> further take into account the situation established in
                        the course of previous negotiations which have been accepted by the main
                        parties as a starting point for new negotiations.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The situation after the London Conference in August was summed up by Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_MRG1">Menzies</persName> in the following terms:
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>‘From the outset, you will have observed that the eighteen nations
                                have not attempted to arrive at any joint opinion as to the validity
                                or otherwise of Egypt’s nationalization decree. The London
                                conference felt that to have a debate on this point would be
                                fruitless, since the conference possessed no authority to make any
                                judicial determination.</p>
                            <p>‘It was therefore considered much more practical to work out
                                constructive proposals which assumed that the act of nationalization
                                had occurred and that the problem of the payment of compensation to
                                the Suez Canal Company would be properly dealt with, with provisions
                                for arbitration in the event of difference, and that what was needed
                                was the establishment of principles and methods for the future.’</p>
                        </quote>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>It is of interest to note further that Foreign Minister <persName
                            corresp="#p_PC1">Pineau</persName> expressed himself at the London
                        Conference as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>‘Il y a des points sur lesquels nous considerons que l’accord doit
                                etre facilement acquis, encore qu’il comporte pour certains, dont
                                nous sommes, des sacrifices evidents. Ces points sont les suivants: <list>
                                    <label>‘a)</label>
                                    <item>la propriete du Canal et de ses installations est reconnue
                                        a l’Egypte, ce qui entraine en faveur de celle-ci le
                                        principe une relevance adequate.</item>
                                    <label>‘b)</label>
                                    <item>la Compagnie Universelle devra etre convenablement
                                        indemnisee et elle pourra devenir par exemple une sorte de
                                        holding gerant son propre portefeuille.’</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The Security Council’s decision, 13 October, stated in point 6: ‘in case
                        of dispute, unresolved affairs between the Suez Canal Company and the
                        Egyptian Government should be settled by arbitration with suitable terms of
                        reference and suitable provisions for the payments of the sums found to be
                        due.’ In the 4th point the Security Council stated that ‘the manner of
                        fixing tolls and charges, should be decided by agreement between Egypt and
                        the users.’ These points make it clear that also the Security Council worked
                        on the basis of the assumption that Egypt’s ownership of the Canal would be
                        respected (an assumption correlated with the Council’s own decision, as
                        endorsed by Egypt, that the Company would get full compensation).</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>If a proposal for provisional arrangements is to be put forward by the
                        Secretary General, it seems necessary for him to base his proposals on the
                        assumption referred to above, as another stand would involve a retreat from
                        the starting point for previous negotiations and the working hypothesis
                        maintained all through the ‘progress so far made’.</item>
                    <pb facs="0140" n="108" xml:id="pg_108"/>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>It follows that a provisional arrangement should meet the three following
                        objectives: <list>
                            <label>a)</label>
                            <item>It should eliminate the risks for a collision by being acceptable
                                to the users as well as to Egypt;</item>
                            <label>b)</label>
                            <item>It should not prejudge the position of any one party on
                                operational, institutional or general financial questions (beyond
                                the extent to which this may be considered as having resulted, in a
                                provisional way, from previous negotiations);</item>
                            <label>c)</label>
                            <item>It should be based on the working hypothesis implicit in those
                                negotiations, from London and onwards, that Egypt is owner of the
                                Canal.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>The preceding argument indicates that payments should be made to an
                        account held in the name of Egypt, but that the disposal over such an
                        account, might be qualified either (a) by an agreement between the parties,
                        or (b) by reserves made in connection with payments to the account. A
                        general provision for the account would be that no one, by paying to the
                        account, has committed himself to any specific stand on those questions
                        which were covered by the Security Council and in the exchange of letters
                        between the Secretary General and the Foreign Minister of Egypt based on the
                        resolution of the Security Council.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>The immediate question is, on the basis of this argument, what rules for
                        disbursement from the account might be considered acceptable by Egypt and by
                        the users. The simplest solution would be that all disbursements, except
                        those necessary for current expenditures, would be suspended pending a
                        settlement of outstanding questions. Other formulae are, however,
                        possible.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>A special question refers to administrative arrangements for the account
                        and for the collecting of tolls and charges. Where should the account be
                        held? Through what agents should payments to the account be made?”</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Lodge</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
