<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-06-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="173" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d173">
                        <head>173. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Japan</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d173fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 794.00/6–1060. Confidential; <gloss target="#t_niact1">Niact</gloss>. Also sent to the White House. No time of
                                transmission is on the source text; it was received at the
                                Department of State at 9:25 a.m.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Tokyo</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-06-10">June 10,
                                1960</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>4127. From Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName>
                            to General <persName corresp="#p_GGAJ1">Goodpaster</persName>. For
                            transmittal to the President and Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HCAJ1">Herter</persName> at an appropriate time. When I met <persName corresp="#p_HJC3">Hagerty</persName> and Stephens at Haneda airport
                            this afternoon we were of the unanimous opinion that despite fact there
                            were demonstrators along road to Tokyo we should proceed as planned in
                            my car rather <pb facs="0362" n="332" xml:id="pg_332"/> than sneak out
                            of airport by helicopter. For if the leftists were going to resort to
                            force and violence it was better for Japanese and US to know now rather
                            than when President arrives. Furthermore I felt that if force and
                            violence were used against us, there would be a deep feeling of
                            revulsion on part of the great majority of Japanese which would
                            seriously blunt the pro-Communist offensive here.</p>
                        <p>As we approached exit of airport grounds a mob spearheaded by Zengakuren
                            students closed in on us stoning the car, shattering the windows,
                            cutting the tires and trying to turn us over.<note n="1" xml:id="d173fn1">According to the Air Attaché’s message 100820Z,
                                June 10, the stoning occurred at about 3:15 p.m. local time, and the
                                American Embassy went into “a condition II, standby to destroy
                                situation.” (Department of State, Central Files, 711.11–EI/6–1060)
                                See Supplement.</note> Our situation was fairly uncomfortable for
                            about fifteen minutes until police reached us. Since it was quite
                            impossible to proceed further by car the police eventually cleared a
                            path for helicopter to pick us up and we arrived at Embassy without
                            further adventure and with none of the party suffering any real damage
                            although unfortunately the helicopter was damaged.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HJC3">Hagerty</persName> and Stephens were superb
                            throughout this trying experience.</p>
                        <p>The Prime Minister, Foreign Minister, Minister of Education and other
                            Japanese leaders have sent messages expressing their profound regret and
                            sympathy at the treatment which was accorded us by these organized
                            leftist groups.</p>
                        <p>While it is of course too early to assess impact of this incident on
                            Japanese political and public opinion I believe that it will have most
                            salutory and helpful result here. I am informed that Prime Minister and
                            Foreign Minister will have special radio-TV broadcast tonight and since
                            there were number of photographers in the melee around car I am sure
                            action shots will be quite graphic. I personally feel that Japanese
                            press, intellectuals, business leaders and Conservative Party have long
                            needed some real shock to shake them out of their passive acceptance of
                            use of force, violence and illegal action by a militant pro-Communist
                            minority which is trying to paralyze parliamentary Govt and democracy in
                            Japan. I am hoping that Japanese reaction to this incident will be
                            similar to Japanese reaction to the violence on May Day 1952 and that
                            net result will be a major setback for Communist cause in Japan.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong"><persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>