<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>265. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d265</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">265</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-01-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-01-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-01-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-01-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="265"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d265">
                <head>265. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d265fn0"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, 795A.00/1–1959. Confidential;
                        Limit Distribution. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_PHJ1">Howard
                            Parsons</persName> and approved by <persName corresp="#p_RWS1"
                            >Robertson</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1959-01-19">January 19,
                            1959</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Political Situation in the Republic of Korea</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName>Walter</persName>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DWC1">Dowling</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Walter S. Robertson</persName>, Assistant
                        Secretary</item>
                    <item>Mr. Howard L. Parsons, Director, Northeast Asian Affairs</item>
                </list>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DWC1">Dowling</persName> described briefly the
                    current political situation in the Republic of Korea. He indicated that members
                    of the Liberal Party (President <persName>Rhee</persName>’s party) apparently
                    have decided that they can not stand to have another election as free and open
                    as that in May 1958. These individuals are divided into two groups: (1) those
                    who want to retain their power at any cost and (2) those who are sincerely
                    convinced that the country can not be run by the opposition party. He explained
                    that the Liberal Party did well in 1957, with economic stabilization, a large
                    crop and other favorable factors. They also did well in the May 1958 elections,
                    when they succeeded in electing a clear majority in the National Assembly even
                    though the Democratic Party more than doubled the number of seats it held.
                    However, in recent weeks the Liberal Party has lost heavily in terms of public
                    opinion. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DWC1">Dowling</persName> concluded his
                    evaluation by saying that he is convinced that the United States must take
                    actions to deflect the Liberal Party from pursuing the course which it started
                    on December 24, 1958 (the date of enactment of the National Security Law).</p>
                <p>The Secretary asked whether the problem in Korea was similar to that appearing
                    throughout the world in many of the new countries, where the people seem not to
                    be ready, in terms of education particularly, to operate under the very fine
                    constitutions which had been written for the countries in question. In several
                    countries in the last few months military dictators had taken over as a result
                    of lack of popular support of the government in power.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DWC1">Dowling</persName> responded that, except
                    for the Japanese, the Koreans are among the most literate of all Asian peoples.
                    In addition, democracy was working well in Korea until the recent excesses. He
                    explained further that the situation can best be described as one in which the
                    party in power wants to retain its power and is willing to go to considerable
                        <pb facs="0563" n="533" xml:id="pg_533"/> lengths to serve that end.
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DWC1">Dowling</persName> explained that
                    analyses of the election in May showed those Assemblymen who had the reputation
                    for serving their constituents well won reelection almost without exception.
                    However, if the immoderate elements of the Liberal Party are permitted to
                    continue a course which enables them to retain their position in government
                    without regard to the type of actions which must be taken to accomplish such
                    purpose, the Korean people will become so disillusioned that they will become
                    susceptible to extreme solutions. He explained that in spite of President
                        <persName>Rhee</persName>’s assertions that the Democratic Party is a
                    communist party, in fact it is probably less infiltrated than is the Liberal
                    Party. However, President <persName>Rhee</persName> has obviously been convinced
                    by individuals wishing to retain power that the Democratic Party does have
                    communists in it.</p>
                <p>The Secretary asked whether the opposition members in Korea were afraid for their
                    lives.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DWC1">Dowling</persName> indicated that the
                    leaders were; in fact, at one time there had been an attempt made on the Vice
                    President’s life. In addition, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CPCP1">Cho
                        Pung-ok</persName>, leader of the Democratic Party, is in a position of
                    possible danger to his life. Those members of the Democratic Party who do not
                    stand to lose their lives stand to lose hope. Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_DWC1">Dowling</persName> reinforced his conclusion that the
                    Koreans were capable of operating a democracy by referring to the devotion and
                    earnestness of the Korean youth. He added, however, that these are the
                    individuals who can be most affected by a continued deterioration of the
                    democratic processes in Korea and they are the group that could quickly turn to
                    violence. The Ambassador concluded by referring to his personal conviction that
                    if we are determined it is possible to deflect the Liberal Party from its
                    present course. However, we must be prepared to use all the resources at our
                    disposal if necessary.</p>
                <p>The Secretary asked whether Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DWC1"
                        >Dowling</persName> had a program. When answered in the affirmative, he
                    asked to see it.<note n="1" xml:id="d265fn1">See <ref target="#d266">Document
                            266</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> pointed out that the absence
                    of a normal relationship among the various agencies in Korea was an obstacle to
                    efficient and effective operation of the United States Government in Korea and
                    to any effective implementation of a program to cope with the current and
                    prospective political situation in Korea if it is decided to take such action.
                    He further commented that had we had a normal relationship in Korea <pb
                        facs="0564" n="534" xml:id="pg_534"/> the alleged irregularities in the
                        <gloss target="#t_GAO1">GAO</gloss> report<note n="2" xml:id="d265fn2">on
                        January 8, the General Accounting Office presented a report on the Korean
                        Military Assistance Program to the House Subcommittee on Review of the
                        Mutual Security Program. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Walter
                            Robertson</persName> summarized the report in a January 18 memorandum to
                        the Secretary, noting that the report had been characterized by a member of
                        the subcommittee as the most damaging on any program he had ever seen. The
                        report revealed serious deficiencies in <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>
                        planning, programming, and deliveries, and highlighted problems of diversion
                        and pilferage of <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> matériel, and lack of
                        control over the use of local currency provided from U.S. economic
                        assistance for support of the Korean military budget. (Department of State,
                        Central Files, 795B.5–MSP/1–1859) See Supplement.</note> could have been
                    dealt with before now. He indicated that it is highly desirable to get this
                    problem straightened out with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MENH1"
                        >McElroy</persName> during Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DWC1"
                        >Dowling</persName>’s consultation.<note n="3" xml:id="d265fn3">On March 20
                        President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> reestablished a
                        normal Country Team relationship in Korea by endorsing an agreement
                        developed through extensive negotiations between the Departments of State
                        and Defense that restored control over economic assistance programs to the
                        Ambassador while leaving the Commander-in-Chief of the United Nations
                        Command with the authority to deal directly with the Korean Government on
                        military programs. (Memorandum for the President from the Secretaries of
                        State and Defense, and attached Memorandum of Agreement, March 10;
                        Department of State, Central Files, 795B.5/3–2059) See Supplement.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
