<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>27. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs
                    (Robertson) to Secretary of State ) to Secretary of State Dulles</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-09-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-09-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft treaty</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85115805"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rule of law</term>
                    <term ref="recjP7nK0m2r7YYXK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International relations</term>
                    <term ref="recAPhAIrM8XS4R2T" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="recNuUP5FwVBYX7g7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic policies</term>
                    <term ref="recSta4gcC4EmYjyi" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="recAWJwqRIM3ZNS4f" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-09-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-09-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="27"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d27">
                <head>27. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_RWS1" type="from">Robertson</persName>) to Secretary
                    of State <persName corresp="#p_DJF1" type="to">Dulles</persName>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d27fn0">Source: Department of State,
                        Conference Files: Lot 64 D 559, CF 1584. Secret. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_PHFJ1">Pfeiffer</persName>; cleared with <gloss
                            target="#t_G1">G</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_WMSC1">W/MSC</gloss>, <gloss
                            target="#t_C1">C</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_L1">L</gloss>, <gloss
                            target="#t_H1">H</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>, and with
                        Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName> and Assistant
                        Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_SMD1">Sprague</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1958-09-12">September 12, 1958</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Circular 175:<note n="1" xml:id="d27fn1">Department Circular No. 175,
                            December 13, 1955, outlined procedures for the exercise of the
                            treaty-making and executive agreement-making process of the United
                            States. (Department of State Library)</note> Request for Authorization
                        to Enter into Negotiations for new “Treaty of Mutual Cooperation and
                        Security between Japan and the United States”</item>
                </list>
                <p>Pursuant to your discussions with the Japanese Foreign Minister on September 11
                    regarding the conclusion of a new mutual security treaty <pb facs="0115" n="85"
                        xml:id="pg_85"/> between the United States and Japan, it is recommended that
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName> be authorized to
                    enter into negotiations with the Japanese Government on the following basis: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>As soon as we have completed necessary Senate consultation, introduce
                            and seek Japanese agreement on the draft text of the new mutual security
                            treaty which has been prepared (Tab A).<note n="2" xml:id="d27fn2">No
                                attachments were found with this memorandum. Tabs A and B were
                                attached to another copy of this memorandum. Tab C, Peace Treaty
                                with Japan, September 8, 1951, is in 3 <gloss target="#t_UST1"
                                    >UST</gloss> (pt. 3) 3169.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>At an appropriate point, introduce and seek agreement to a formula
                            (Tab B) to meet Japanese requests with regard to consultation on the use
                            and equipment of United States forces in Japan.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Make clear to Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_KN1"
                                >Kishi</persName> that the exchange of notes between Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_ADG2">Acheson</persName> and Prime Minister
                                <persName corresp="#p_YS2">Yoshida</persName> of September 8, 1951
                            (by which Japan agreed to permit and facilitate the support in and about
                            Japan of United Nations forces engaged in any United Nations action in
                            the Far East) will not be affected by the new security treaty. (Tab
                            C)</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>It will be noted that under Article IX of the draft text of the new agreement
                    (Tab A) it is envisaged that the present Administrative Agreement under Article
                    III of the Security Treaty will continue in force except insofar as it may be
                    subsequently modified.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi>:<note n="3" xml:id="d27fn3">Approved by
                            <persName>Dulles</persName> on September 29.</note>
                </p>
                <p>That you authorize Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName>
                    to enter into negotiations with the Japanese Government along the lines outlined
                    above.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="strong">Tab A</hi>
                        <note n="4" type="source" xml:id="d27fn4">Source: Department of State,
                                <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> Files: Lot 60 D 90, Japan.
                            Secret.</note>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">DRAFT TREATY OF MUTUAL COOPERATION AND SECURITY BETWEEN JAPAN
                        AND THE UNITED STATES</p>
                    <p rend="center">Preamble</p>
                    <p>Japan and the United States of America,</p>
                    <p>Desiring to strengthen the bonds of peace and friendship traditionally
                        existing between them, and uphold the principles of democracy, individual
                        liberty, and the rule of law, <pb facs="0116" n="86" xml:id="pg_86"/>
                        Desiring further to encourage closer economic cooperation between them and
                        to promote conditions of stability and economic well being in their
                        countries and in the Pacific area,</p>
                    <p>Reaffirming their faith in the purposes and principles of the Charter of the
                        United Nations, and their desire to live in peace with all peoples and all
                        governments,</p>
                    <p>Recognizing their inherent right of individual or collective self defense as
                        affirmed in the Charter of the United Nations,</p>
                    <p>Having resolved to conclude a treaty of mutual cooperation and security,</p>
                    <p>Therefore agree as follows:</p>
                    <p rend="center">Article I</p>
                    <p>The Parties undertake, as set forth in the Charter of the United Nations, to
                        settle any international disputes in which they may be involved by peaceful
                        means in such a manner that international peace and security and justice are
                        not endangered and to refrain in their international relations from the
                        threat or use of force against the territorial integrity or political
                        independence of any state or in any other manner inconsistent with the
                        purposes of the United Nations.</p>
                    <p rend="center">Article II</p>
                    <p>The Parties will contribute toward the further development of peaceful and
                        friendly international relations by strengthening their free institutions,
                        by bringing about a better understanding of the principles upon which these
                        institutions are founded, and by promoting conditions of stability and well
                        being. They will seek to eliminate conflict in their international economic
                        policies and will encourage economic collaboration between them, including
                        economic cooperation with other friendly and like-minded countries in the
                        Pacific area.</p>
                    <p rend="center">Article III</p>
                    <p>In order more effectively to achieve the objectives of this Treaty, the
                        Parties, separately and jointly, by means of continuous and effective
                        self-help and mutual aid will maintain and develop their individual and
                        collective capacity to resist armed attack and to prevent and counter
                        subversive activities directed from without against their territorial
                        integrity and political stability.</p>
                    <p rend="center">Article IV</p>
                    <p>The Parties will consult together regarding the implementation of this Treaty
                        and whenever in the opinion of either of them the territorial integrity,
                        political independence, or security of either of them is threatened in the
                        Pacific.</p>
                    <pb facs="0117" n="87" xml:id="pg_87"/>
                    <p rend="center">Article V</p>
                    <p>Each Party recognizes that an armed attack in the Pacific directed against
                        the territories or areas under the administrative control of the other Party
                        would be dangerous to its own peace and safety and declares that it would
                        act to meet the common danger in accordance with its constitutional
                        processes. Any such armed attack and all measures taken as a result thereof
                        shall be immediately reported to the Security Council of the United Nations.
                        Such measures shall be terminated when the Security Council has taken the
                        measures necessary to restore and maintain international peace and
                        security.</p>
                    <p rend="center">Article VI</p>
                    <p>The conditions under which the United States land, air, and naval forces may
                        be stationed in and about the territories or areas under the administrative
                        control of Japan will be determined by the Administrative Agreement.</p>
                    <p rend="center">Article VII</p>
                    <p>This Treaty does not affect and shall not be interpreted as affecting in any
                        way the rights and obligations of the Parties under the Charter of the
                        United Nations or the responsibility of the United Nations for the
                        maintenance of international peace and security.</p>
                    <p rend="center">Article VIII</p>
                    <p>This Treaty shall be ratified by the United States of America and Japan in
                        accordance with their respective constitutional processes and will enter
                        into force when the instruments of ratification thereof have been exchanged
                        by them in Tokyo.</p>
                    <p rend="center">Article IX</p>
                    <p>The Security Treaty between Japan and the United States shall expire upon the
                        entering into force of this Treaty. However, the Administrative Agreement
                        between the United States of America and Japan signed at Tokyo on February
                        28, 1952 under Article III of the Security Treaty shall continue in
                        force.</p>
                    <p rend="center">Article X</p>
                    <p>This Treaty shall remain in force indefinitely. However, after the Treaty has
                        been in force for 10 years either Party may terminate it one year after
                        notice has been given to the other Party.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0118" n="88" xml:id="pg_88"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Tab B<note n="5" type="source" xml:id="d27fn5">Source: Department of
                            State, <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> Files: Lot 60 D 90, Japan.
                            Confidential.</note>
                    </head>
                    <table cols="2" rows="2">
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>United Kingdom</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Joint Communiqué by President Truman and Prime Minister Churchill
                                January 9, 1952</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Pertinent Language of Agreement</hi> “Under
                                arrangements made for the common defense, the United States has the
                                use of certain bases in the United Kingdom. We reaffirm the
                                understanding that the use of these bases in an emergency would be a
                                matter for joint decision by His Majesty’s Government and the United
                                States Government in the light of the circumstances prevailing at
                                the time.”</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Proposed Formula to Deal With Japanese Request</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Under arrangements made for the common defense, the United States has the use
                        of certain bases in Japan. The deployment of United States forces and their
                        equipment into bases in Japan and the operational use of these bases in an
                        emergency would be a matter for joint consultation by the Japanese
                        Government and the United States Government in the light of circumstances
                        prevailing at the time.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
