<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-09-29T20:59:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-09-29T20:59:00-05:00" n="28" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                        <head>28. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Japan</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d28fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 794.5/9–2958. Secret; <gloss target="#t_niact1">Niact</gloss>. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_MJVJ1">Martin</persName> and cleared with <gloss target="#t_L1">L</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss>. Repeated to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-09-29T21:59:00-04:00">September 29, 1958, 9:59 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>474. Joint State–Defense message. You are authorized enter into
                            negotiations with <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> following
                            basis:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item><p>Introduce and seek Japanese agreement on our draft text of new
                                    mutual security treaty. Note following changes in our draft.</p>
                                <p>Article VI–Substitute “In furtherance of the objectives of this
                                    Treaty, the US has the use of certain bases in Japan. With
                                    respect to the <pb facs="0119" n="89" xml:id="pg_89"/> use of
                                    these bases and the status of US forces in Japan, the
                                    Administrative Agreement signed at Tokyo on February 28, 1952,
                                    as amended, shall continue in force.”</p>
                                <p>Article IX will consist of only the first sentence which reads
                                    “The Security Treaty between Japan and the US shall expire upon
                                    the entering into force of this Treaty.”</p>
                                <p>Article X based on modification Articles 13 <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Treaty now reads “This treaty
                                    shall remain in force indefinitely. However, after the treaty
                                    has been in force for 10 years either party may terminate it one
                                    year after notice has been given to the other party.”<note n="1" xml:id="d28fn1">The draft printed as Tab A, <ref target="#d27">Document 27</ref>, already incorporates
                                        this change.</note></p></item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item><p>Note that Article VI of draft mutual security treaty states
                                    that present Administrative Agreement will continue in force. Of
                                    course Administrative Agreement still subject to subsequent
                                    amendment under its own Article XXVIII.</p>
                                <p>If the subject of revising the Administrative Agreement should be
                                    raised, you may assure <persName corresp="#p_KN1">Kishi</persName> that necessary technical steps will be
                                    taken to cure references to the present security treaty. Any
                                    attempts to renegotiate the Administrative Agreement should be
                                    forestalled until we have had an opportunity to review whether
                                    this would be in our interest. Our tentative thinking is to
                                    leave agreement intact, with side agreement reciting that
                                    present references in Administrative Agreement should henceforth
                                    be read as references to Mutual Cooperation and Security Treaty.
                                    If further changes are in your opinion necessary, please advise
                                    soonest as any revision of Administrative Agreement should be
                                    concluded contemporaneously with treaty and available for
                                    possible Congressional scrutiny.</p></item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item><p>At an appropriate point introduce and seek agreement to our
                                    formula to meet Japanese requests with regard to consultation on
                                    the deployment of US forces and their equipment in Japan. [<hi rend="italic">5 lines of source text not
                                    declassified</hi>]</p>
                                <p>Defense desires you raise with <persName corresp="#p_KN1">Kishi</persName> personally the importance that we attach
                                    to the use of the facilities in Japan in the event of Communist
                                    aggression directed against another free Asian nation wherein
                                    Japan’s safety is threatened. Please report <persName corresp="#p_KN1">Kishi</persName>’s reaction and any
                                    recommendations as to how some understanding with Japanese might
                                    be reached to accomplish this objective.</p></item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>Make clear to <persName corresp="#p_KN1">Kishi</persName> that
                                exchange of notes between Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ADG2">Acheson</persName> and Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_YS2">Yoshida</persName> of September 8, 1951 (by
                                which Japan agreed to permit and facilitate support in and about
                                Japan of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> forces engaged in any
                                    <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> action in Far East) will not
                                be affected by new security treaty.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong"><persName>Dulles</persName></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>