<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-07-03T00:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-07-03T00:30:00-05:00" n="324" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d324">
                        <head>324. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Korea</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d324fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 795B.00/7–360. Secret; Priority; Limit Distribution.
                                Transmitted in two sections.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Seoul</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-07-03T15:00:00+09:30">July 3,
                                    1960, 3 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>8. For Assistant Secretary <persName>Parsons</persName>. Re Deptels
                                1160,<note n="1" xml:id="d324fn1"><ref target="#d321">Document
                                    321</ref>.</note> 1317.<note n="2" xml:id="d324fn2">See <ref target="#d321fn1">footnote 1, Document 321</ref>.</note> With
                            passage Constitutional Amendment, transition “of Korea from April
                            “Democratic Revolution” to new political era begins. Even over
                            short-run, political prospects contain large element uncertainty, and
                            possibilities indicated <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1317
                            certainly cannot be discounted. At present however Embassy believes
                            following are most likely prospects for period immediately following
                            elections: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>In all probability <gloss target="#t_DP1">DP</gloss> will win
                                    narrow majority in lower house elections possible 120 of 233
                                    seats. If party does not split in two its ability form
                                    government and constitute effective working majority in Assembly
                                    will depend in part on support obtained from independents
                                    (including ex-liberals), who may hold as many as 70–80 seats.
                                    Remaining lower house seats will be divided among various
                                    “Reformist” parties; in such circumstances, non-conservative
                                    (“Progressive”) element not likely be in position wield balance
                                    power.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Ability <gloss target="#t_DP1">DP</gloss> to constitute basis
                                    of moderately oriented and working majority (<gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1160) likely be seriously
                                    limited by factionalism which again has approached critical
                                    point. If both factions emerge from elections relatively equal
                                    in strength, there will be greater incentive for compromise than
                                    in case one faction being appreciably stronger. Emergence
                                    stronger non-conservative block than now anticipated similarly
                                    might reduce likelihood major break in <gloss target="#t_DP1">DP</gloss> ranks.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>In any event organization new government will require
                                    compromise between two factions <gloss target="#t_DP1">DP</gloss> each attempting draw support from independent
                                    and minor party ranks. Successful compromise in all likelihood
                                    would divide Presidency and Prime Ministership between two
                                    factions with roughly equal representation in Cabinet and
                                    Assembly leadership. (See <persName corresp="#p_CMJMC1">Chang
                                        Myon</persName>’s views this point <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 3.)<note n="3" xml:id="d324fn3">Telegram 3 from Seoul, July 1, reported on
                                        a conversation that day with <persName corresp="#p_CMJMC1">Chang Myon</persName> in which he expressed concern
                                        about the danger of factional strife within the Democratic
                                        Party and indicated that he would prefer the position of
                                        president should his party win the election. (Department of
                                        State, Central Files, 795B.00/7–160)</note></item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item><p>At least over short-run government almost certainly will be
                                        handicapped by lack strong leadership at top level. Embassy
                                        inclined <pb facs="0704" n="674" xml:id="pg_674"/> agree
                                        with view <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1160
                                        that <persName corresp="#p_CMJMC1">Chang Myon</persName>
                                        better suited for Presidency. (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 3 also indicates
                                            <persName>Chang</persName> may be inclining this
                                        direction.) <persName>Chang</persName> not only better
                                        qualified for this post by reason temperament and talent but
                                        removed from partisan politics he might be able provide
                                        necessary national symbol stability and sense direction.
                                        Additionally Chang’s departure from active participation
                                            <gloss target="#t_DP1">DP</gloss> probably would reduce
                                        severity factional struggle which now encouraged not only by
                                        fact old faction has been at disadvantage since death
                                            <persName corresp="#p_CPCP1">Cho Pyong-ok</persName> but
                                        by <persName>Chang</persName>’s personal inability rise
                                        above pretty factionalism as well as his unacceptability to
                                        old faction as leader entire party.</p>
                                    <p>On other hand it should be recognized that apart from
                                            <persName>Chang</persName>, no individual comes readily
                                        to mind who, among leadership ranks either faction, is
                                        qualified by experience and age to fill Prime Ministership.
                                        Even <persName>Chang</persName>’s availability this post not
                                        assured since he will encounter stiff opposition in campaign
                                        for Assembly seat. Such leadership as suggested <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>s may develop over
                                        time, given reasonably stable political situation. Until
                                        such leadership available, however, direction government and
                                        party politics likely depend more on emergence of working
                                        team of younger leaders than upon any single
                                    individual.</p></item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>It difficult foresee probable effects formation upper house on
                                    polit situation. In view limited powers upper house and fact
                                    that with few exceptions, membership likely be undistinguished,
                                    effect this development in immediate situation likely be
                                    marginal, other than in election of president.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Embassy entirely agrees with views indicated <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1160 as to polit situation most likely contribute to
                            development stable and effective democratic govt, as well as with
                            analysis <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1317 of pitfalls
                            which threaten such development. In Embassy view however extent our
                            ability influence directly emergence certain individuals to particular
                            positions responsibility or affect configurations power within and
                            between polit parties is decidedly marginal. Moreover extent to which we
                            would be required inject ourselves into active polit situation in order
                            exert even this limited influence, presents serious dangers not only of
                            evoking adverse criticism of our interference but encouraging polit
                            leadership shift or evade responsibility.</p>
                        <p>Further our experience in Korea suggests that however much particular
                            individuals and groups may appear to understand requirements and basic
                            values of effective representative democracy, they function within a
                            total situation which is uncongenial to their realization. Longer-range
                            polit stability within democratic framework therefore depends
                            essentially upon changes in such aspects of total situation as
                            psychological climate, patterns and values polit behavior, and economic
                            situation as will encourage: A) development of experienced and
                            responsible leadership in Govt and polit parties; B) greater concern for
                            translating realizable <pb facs="0705" n="675" xml:id="pg_675"/> popular
                            aspirations into sound national policies together with higher standards
                            probity and efficiency in administration Govt and management party
                            affairs; and C) achievement measurable progress toward self-supporting
                            economy.</p>
                        <p>In Embassy view therefore it essential US influence be brought bear more
                            effectively in direction encouraging such changes in total situation. In
                            this an important objective should be to lend support to those many
                            Koreans particularly younger citizens and Govt officials including
                            educators who are fired by genuine desire set country’s polity and
                            economy in order and whose views given effective expression can
                            condition policies and actions polit leadership.</p>
                        <p>All these questions currently under informal consideration by members
                            Country Team and it hoped to develop in near future concrete activities
                            and programs to this end. Sound beginning already being made in
                            administration economic aid along lines indicated <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 871,<note n="4" xml:id="d324fn4">See <ref target="#d297fn5">footnote 5, Document 297</ref>.</note>
                            to encourage imaginative and responsible leadership and constructive
                            policy planning free from corruption and polit favoritism. Among other
                            possibilities being considered are: 1) assistance to Hoover
                            commission-type public study of specific problems facing development
                            effective representative govt; 2) adult citizenship education program;
                            3) Fulbright exchanges directed to close examination problems Korean
                            politics and development practical understanding functioning democratic
                            institutions in Korean context.</p>
                        <p>Embassy would appreciate <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss>’s comments
                            and suggestions re this approach. We of course appreciate importance our
                            continued encouragement those politically active individuals and groups
                            who can contribute most to realization stable democratic Govt Korea, but
                            we believe our major effort must perforce be directed on broader and
                            more fundamental plane if effects such individuals and groups to have
                            any realistic hope for fulfillment.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong"><persName corresp="#p_MCWPJ1">McConaughy</persName></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>