<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-12-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="169" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d169">
                    <head>169. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>On January 28, 1971, Assistant to the President <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> met Soviet Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> in the Map Room at the White House from 12:05 to
                        1:15 p.m. for a discussion of several issues, including the Berlin
                        negotiations. (Record of Schedule; Library of Congress, Manuscript Division,
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box 438,
                        Miscellany, 1968–76) According to the memorandum of conversation, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> requested the meeting “to give
                            <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> the answers to our
                        discussions of the previous week [January 23].” The memorandum records the
                        conversation on Berlin:</p>
                    <p>“I told <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> that the President
                        was prepared to proceed along the line that we had discussed; that is to
                        say, that <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> and I would
                        discuss the outstanding issues, and after some agreement in principle, move
                        our conclusions into the Four-Power discussions on Berlin. I also told
                            <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> that I planned to speak
                        to <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bahr</persName> on an early occasion, and that
                        we were also bringing Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RK1">Rush</persName>
                        back to make certain that he would be in on these arrangements.</p>
                    <p>“I reiterated the need for total secrecy of this channel, and that if the
                        channel became public or was leaked to people other than those authorized to
                        know, we would simply break it off. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said they had always respected the privacy of this
                        channel; moreover, it was very much in their interest to preserve its
                        secrecy, and I could therefore be sure. He said that <persName corresp="#p_FVM1">Falin</persName> had told <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bahr</persName> that there might be a separate channel, but had not
                        told him its nature and, except for that, no other person had been told.
                            <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said that he thought
                        this information would be well received in Moscow, and that he was hoping
                        that some significant progress could be made in the next few months.”</p>
                    <p>After discussion of the Strategic Arms Limitation Talks and negotiations in
                        the Middle East, the conversation on Berlin continued:</p>
                    <p>“<persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> returned to the Berlin issue
                        and said that the Soviet Union had attentively studied my suggestion that
                        there had to be some guarantees. He then handed me the attached piece of
                        paper (Tab A) which represents the strongest statement so far that the
                        Soviet Union has made for assuming some responsibility for the outcome of an
                        eventual West German-East German agreement. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> told me that <persName corresp="#p_RK1">Rush</persName>’s inflexibility had presented a peculiar problem for
                        Abrasimov.</p>
                    <p>“Abrasimov actually has instructions to go further than he did on access
                        procedures; however, since <persName corresp="#p_RK1">Rush</persName> was
                        absolutely unyielding, he could not present them. He did not want to be in a
                        position of seeming to keep making concessions. He therefore wondered
                        whether <persName corresp="#p_RK1">Rush</persName> could offer anything at
                        the February 9th meeting to show some move on our part to which, in turn,
                        Abrasimov could then respond.”</p>
                    <p>At the end of the meeting, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                        and <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> agreed to meet again
                        after <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> had “prepared the
                        ground with <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bahr</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RK1">Rush</persName>.” <pb facs="0533" n="502" xml:id="pg_502"/>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> would then “let <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> know what the procedure would be.”
                            <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> also said he would
                        “check in Moscow.” (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 490, President’s Trip Files, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, 1971, Vol. 4 [Part 2])</p>
                    <p>The text of the Soviet note on Berlin (Tab A) that <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> gave <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> during the meeting reads as follows:</p>
                    <p>“It goes without saying that the arrangement reached between the four powers
                        on questions related to the status of West Berlin, as well as the agreements
                        between the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> and respectively the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> and the Senate of West Berlin on questions
                        of civil transit to West Berlin and therefrom, and on access for persons
                        from West Berlin to the territory of the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>, including its capital, are to be strictly implemented.
                        Implementation of the arrangement on each question presupposes
                        implementation of the arrangement on other questions.</p>
                    <p>“In those cases if facts of violation of the arrangement in this or that part
                        thereof would take place, each of the four powers would have the right to
                        call the attention of the other participants in the arrangement to the
                        principles of the present settlement with the view of holding within the
                        framework of their competence proper consultations aimed at removing the
                        violations that took place and at bringing the situation in compliance with
                        the arrangement.” (Ibid.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> forwarded the memorandum of
                        conversation, including the attached Soviet note, to the President on
                        February 1. (Ibid.) Both are scheduled for publication in <ref target="frus1969-76v13">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume
                        XIII</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>