<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>265. Message From the Ambassador to Germany (Rush) to the President’s
                    Assistant for National Security Affairs () to the President’s Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v40</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d265</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">265</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="265"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d265">
                <head>265. Message From the Ambassador to Germany (<persName corresp="#p_RK1"
                        type="from">Rush</persName>) to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to"
                        >Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d265fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                        Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 59, Country
                        Files, Europe, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RK1">Rush</persName>,
                        Berlin, Vol. 1. Top Secret; Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes Only. A copy was
                        sent to <persName corresp="#p_HC1">Haig</persName>. The message was sent
                        through the special Navy channel in Frankfurt. No time of transmission is on
                        the message; a handwritten note indicates that it was received in Washington
                        on July 1 at 0110Z.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Bonn</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-06-30"
                            >June 30, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Yesterday’s meeting went off well, <persName corresp="#p_FVM1">Falin</persName>
                    being in his usual relaxed friendly un-Russian mood. The principal developments
                    were as follows:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>We completed the section and accompanying annex on visits by West
                            Berliners to East Berlin and the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>.
                            The big issue is how to describe the area so as to bypass the question
                            as to whether East Berlin is or is not a part of the <gloss
                                target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>. Until our meeting yesterday the
                            Russians had insisted on wording such as “Berlin (East) and other areas
                            of the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>.” However, after long
                            discussion he yesterday accepted, subject to Moscow approval, the
                            wording, “communications with areas contiguous to the Western sectors of
                            Berlin as well as with areas not contiguous to those sectors.”</p>
                        <p>Another issue has been our attempt to have the western end of the Teltow
                            Canal opened to navigation. The canal is largely in East Berlin and the
                            acrimonious post war history of the canal has caused a hardening of
                            attitudes and given the issue an undue symbolic importance. The <pb
                                facs="0800" n="769" xml:id="pg_769"/> Russians have adamantly
                            refused to open the western end of the canal, but yesterday <persName
                                corresp="#p_FVM1">Falin</persName> finally agreed that it “can be
                            opened to navigation.”</p>
                        <p>The text of the tentatively agreed upon provisions is attached.<note
                                n="2" xml:id="d265fn2">Attached but not printed.</note>
                        </p>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>We were also to discuss yesterday the final protocol, to which the French
                        give such importance. In order to help meet your timetable however, I
                        postponed that discussion on the basis that we had to do much more work with
                        the French first.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Particularly in view of the Kvitsinskiy–Dean episode, I think that in
                        order to allay suspicion and prevent disruption, we should continue the
                        normal pattern of advisors meetings and thus deviate somewhat from the plan
                        you and I outlined to <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>. We
                        can give the advisors plenty to do usefully, and, by careful coordination
                        through <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bahr</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_FVM1">Falin</persName> and me, prevent these talks from
                        adversely affecting our plans for getting the agreement as secretly
                        finalized through the Four Power Ambassadorial talks. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BE1">Bahr</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_FVM1"
                            >Falin</persName> agreed with this reasoning, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_FVM1">Falin</persName> is taking the word back to
                        Moscow.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Our next meeting is on Tuesday 6 July following <persName
                            corresp="#p_FVM1">Falin</persName>’s return from Moscow. I think it will
                        take some time for him to work out an acceptable posture on Federal
                        presence, but if instead he returns with one, we may have a small problem of
                        avoiding embarrasment with the Germans as we carry out your time schedule.
                        However I think it can be done by delaying consideration and final agreement
                        on the issues of representation abroad and Soviet interests in West Berlin
                        and by other means.<note n="3" xml:id="d265fn3">
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> replied by special
                            channel on July 2: “Thanks for your messages. They were greatly
                            appreciated. Could you not use my Asia trip to bring about a delay by
                            claiming difficulty in getting instructions? At any rate, keep things
                            fluid until I am back from my trip and various things have fallen into
                            place.” (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                            Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files,
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files,
                            Country Files, Europe, Box 59, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RK1"
                                >Rush</persName>, Berlin, Vol. 1) <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                                >Kissinger</persName> had already left Washington on July 1 for a
                            2-week tour of Asia, including stops in Saigon, Bangkok, New Delhi, and
                            Islamabad; on July 9, he secretly arrived in Beijing, the “real
                            destination” of his trip. (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                                >Kissinger</persName>, <hi rend="italic">White House Years</hi>, pp.
                            736–741) In <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s absence,
                                <persName corresp="#p_HC1">Haig</persName> sent the following
                            message to <persName corresp="#p_RK1">Rush</persName> on July 6: “Due to
                            circumstances which will be explained subsequently, Dr. <persName
                                corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> has asked me to flash to you
                            the essentiality of going as slowly as possible during any meetings
                            which may be already arranged. He also asks that you avoid, on some
                            pretext, any new meetings to which you are not already committed until
                            he returns from his trip on or about July 12. Best regards.” (Department
                            of State, Bonn Post Files: Lot 72 F 81, Berlin Files—Amb.
                                <persName>Kenneth Rush</persName>) In a conversation that morning,
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> told <persName
                                corresp="#p_HC1">Haig</persName> to “tighten up on Berlin” to
                            counter a “crude and obvious attempt” by the Soviets to delay a decision
                            on the summit. <persName corresp="#p_HC1">Haig</persName>: “Well, I just
                            sent a message to <persName corresp="#p_RK1">Rush</persName> and told
                            him to delay everything, not to accept any new meetings on the subject
                            and just to hold up. That’s why I’m a little—That’s what they really
                            want. They’re pressing to get that thing locked into shape.” <persName
                                corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: “Hmhmm. Can we still stop them?”
                            Haig: “It’s still manageable, sir. It’s going to take a little gasping
                            because of the German side, they’re Goddamn panting on this thing.”
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: “Sure.” <persName
                                corresp="#p_HC1">Haig</persName>: “But we can make it very
                            difficult.” (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                                >Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, White House Tapes,
                            Recording of Conversation Between <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                                >Nixon</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HC1">Haig</persName>,
                            July 6, 1971, 9:10–9:25 a.m., Oval Office, Conversation 538–4) The
                            editor transcribed the portion of the conversation printed here
                            specifically for this volume.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
