<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>284. Memorandum From Arthur Downey of the National Security Council Staff to
                    the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the National
                    Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v40</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d284</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">284</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-08-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-08-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec6XfF2Oe1IjakB2" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="recAZ6vp0KaSfYUeW" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018002867"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Demilitarization</term>
                    <term ref="rechQxXfPBmLXmMRi" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067357"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">International organizations</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-08-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-08-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="284"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d284">
                <head>284. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_DAT1" type="from">Arthur
                        Downey</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the President’s
                    Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to"
                        >Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d284fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                        Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 692, Country
                        Files, Europe, Germany (Berlin), Vol. IV. Secret. Urgent; Sent for
                        information. <persName corresp="#p_HC1">Haig</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> both initialed the memorandum,
                        indicating that they had seen it; according to an attached form, the
                        memorandum was “noted by <gloss target="#t_HAK1">HAK</gloss>” on August
                        17.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1971-08-11">August 11, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Berlin Negotiations—the August 10 Session</item>
                </list>
                <p>The first day of the marathon negotiating session produced both a constructive
                    atmosphere and visible improvements. The following is a brief summary (the
                    reporting cables<note n="2" xml:id="d284fn2">On August 11 the Mission reported
                        the highlights of the August 10 session in telegram 1580 and the details in
                        telegrams 1586, 1587, 1588, 1589, and 1590. (All ibid., RG 59, Central Files
                        1970–73, POL 28 GER B)</note> run over sixty pages):</p>
                <p>The Ambassadors decided on the <hi rend="italic">order of consideration</hi> of
                    the various issues, beginning with the focus on Bonn/Berlin relationships, then
                    representation abroad, access, entry into East Berlin, and finally Soviet
                    interests in West Berlin. In this first meeting, the concentration was on
                    Bonn/Berlin relationships and representation abroad.</p>
                <pb facs="0853" n="822" xml:id="pg_822"/>
                <p>Abrasimov offered a fairly tough paper on <hi rend="italic">Bonn/Berlin
                        relations</hi>.<note n="3" xml:id="d284fn3">The text of the Soviet paper was
                        transmitted on August 11 in telegram 1581 from Berlin. (Ibid.)</note> In
                    presenting it, he indicated that even this was on the condition that, outside
                    the framework of the Agreement, but in connection with it, the Four Powers reach
                    an understanding on banning the <gloss target="#t_NPD1">NPD</gloss> and on
                    demilitarization. As they hinted at in the last session, the Soviet paper was in
                    the “short form.” As a result, the Three Ambassadors made clear that agreement
                    to this brief format would depend on Soviet agreement to adding a supplementary
                    letter or an agreed minute setting forth clarifications and interpretations of
                    the laconic language.</p>
                <p>The critical “constitutional” formulation describing the Bonn/Berlin relationship
                    in the Soviet draft contained the statement that the Western Sectors “are not a
                    part of the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>, do not belong to it and cannot
                    be governed by it.” In a <hi rend="italic">major breakthrough</hi>, Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_RK1">Rush</persName> succeeded in securing Abrasimov’s
                    agreement to drop the “does not belong” language, and altering the last phase to
                    provide that West Berlin “continues not to be governed” by the <gloss
                        target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>.</p>
                <p>The consideration of Berlin’s <hi rend="italic">representation abroad</hi> was
                    also fruitful. Both sides offered texts of an exchange of letters, and the
                    Western side finally agreed to treat this subject separately and not merely as
                    one aspect of the Bonn/Berlin relationship. There are few significant
                    differences in the two texts. Essentially, both provide that the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> will not object to provision of consular
                    services by the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>, extension of treaties,
                    representation in international organizations and conferences and inclusion in
                    exchanges and exhibitions. The Soviet text, of course, highlights particularly
                    that these forms of <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> representation are
                    tolerable only to the extent that matters of security and status are not
                    affected (it is not clear, for example, exactly how Berlin’s representation at
                    the Security Council will be handled).</p>
                <p>The major difference on this issue remains the question of <gloss
                        target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>
                    <hi rend="italic">passports</hi>. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RK1"
                        >Rush</persName> pressed hard for Soviet acceptance, noting that this was a
                    very important aspect for the acceptance of the agreement as a whole. Abrasimov
                    said he did not reject the right of a West Berliner to have an <gloss
                        target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> passport in his pocket, but only that he could
                    not use this document while traveling to the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Abrasimov immediately linked this issue with the question of a Soviet Consulate
                    General. At various stages during the session, Abrasimov said that unless there
                    was agreement on a Consulate General, there would be no section on
                    representation abroad, and even no agreement at all. He finally made clear that
                    he was going to raise the Consulate General in connection with every issue to be
                    discussed. Ambassador <pb facs="0854" n="823" xml:id="pg_823"/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_RK1">Rush</persName> pointed out that it would be a
                    serious matter for the Allies to grant the Consulate General and not to be able
                    to obtain the right for West Berliners to use <gloss target="#t_FRG1"
                        >FRG</gloss> passports.</p>
                <p>In a brief cable this morning, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RK1"
                        >Rush</persName> said that the question of the Consulate General would be up
                    for discussion this afternoon,<note n="4" xml:id="d284fn4">In telegram 1594 from
                        Berlin, August 11, <persName corresp="#p_RK1">Rush</persName> sent the
                        following personal message for <persName corresp="#p_RWP1"
                        >Rogers</persName>: “Negotiations are moving at a faster pace than we
                        anticipated. Subject of Soviet interests, and particularly Consulate General
                        up for discussion still this afternoon. I would therefore appreciate
                        earliest possible instruction.” (Ibid., POL 38–6)</note> and he requested
                    instructions. The <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>
                    <note n="5" xml:id="d284fn5">
                        <ref target="#d285">Document 285</ref>.</note> of this morning has been sent
                    by flash cable.<note n="6" xml:id="d284fn6">Telegram 146328 to Berlin, August
                        11. (National Archives, RG 59, Central Files 1970–73, POL 38–6)</note>
                </p>
                <p>With respect to timing of the negotiations, the four Ambassadors agreed that, if
                    necessary, a meeting after the August 12 session would take place on Monday, the
                    16th. All agreed not to meet on August 13— the tenth anniversary of the Wall. In
                    that context, <persName corresp="#p_RK1">Rush</persName> told Abrasimov that he
                    had gone to great lengths to tone down Western publicity on the 13th. Abrasimov
                    responded that there would be no military parades on the 13th in East Berlin,
                    but “only” a march of workers’ brigades before a reviewing stand.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
