<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-08-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-08-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="285" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d285">
                    <head>285. National Security Decision Memorandum 125<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d285fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59, <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>/CE Files: Lot 91 D 341, <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> &amp; <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>. Secret;<gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>.
                            Copies were sent to <persName corresp="#p_MATH1">Moorer</persName> and
                            Helms. According to another copy, <persName corresp="#p_DAT1">Downey</persName> drafted the <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>
                            on August 7. (National Security Council, <gloss target="#t_SRG1">SRG</gloss> Files, <gloss target="#t_SRG1">SRG</gloss> Meetings
                            8–6–71, Berlin Negotiations (<gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 136))
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> then revised the
                            text; the changes are noted in the footnotes below. The Department
                            forwarded the final text to the Mission in Berlin on August 11 in
                            telegram 146328 to Berlin. (National Archives, RG 59, Central Files
                            1970–73, POL 38–6)</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-08-11">August 11, 1971</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="to">
                        <head>TO</head>
                        <item>The Secretary of State</item>
                        <item>The Secretary of Defense</item>
                    </list>
                    <pb facs="0855" n="824" xml:id="pg_824"/>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>The Berlin Negotiations: The Issue of a Soviet Consulate
                            General</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>After considering the Senior Review Group’s memorandum of August 7,<note n="2" xml:id="d285fn2">See <ref target="#d283">Document
                            283</ref>.</note> the President has directed that the following
                        guidelines shall be used as the basis for our conduct of the remainder of
                        the Berlin negotiations: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The general requirements for a satisfactory Agreement defined in
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> 106<note n="3" xml:id="d285fn3">
                                    <ref target="#d225">Document 225</ref>.</note> are maintained.
                                In addition, the following specific requirements are defined: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item><note n="4" xml:id="d285fn4">At this point, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> removed the
                                            following phrase from the draft: “No reference to the
                                                <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> should appear in
                                            the provision of the Agreement which defines Soviet
                                            responsibility for unimpeded access, and.” (National
                                            Security Council, <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>
                                            Files, <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> 125)</note>
                                        The concept of unimpeded access should not be diluted
                                        through reference to international practice or rules.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>There should be no provision for <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> spot checks of the contents of sealed
                                        conveyances, and no <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>
                                        inspection of baggage on through trains and buses.<note n="5" xml:id="d285fn5">
                                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                                            eliminated the following provision in the draft: “The
                                            Agreement must provide that the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> cannot obstruct unimpeded access by
                                            arbitrary denial of visas, and the Agreement must make
                                            clear that the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>
                                            cannot arrest access travelers for crimes or other
                                            activities which allegedly took place previously.”
                                            (Ibid.)</note>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>Soviet acceptance of the utilization by West Berliners of
                                        Federal passports should be a requirement if the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> desires. Formulations
                                        relating to <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>-Berlin ties
                                        should be precisely worded so as to minimize the likelihood
                                        of future disputes.</item>
                                    <label>d.</label>
                                    <item>It should be established that the Agreement is not limited
                                        to West Berlin, and this may be accomplished by referring to
                                        “Berlin” in the Preamble. Similarly, there should be no
                                        implication of a Western acknowledgment of the division of
                                        Berlin, as the phrase “taking into account the existing
                                        situation” implies.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>If an Agreement obtaining most<note n="6" xml:id="d285fn6">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> inserted the
                                    word “most” to replace “all” in the draft. (Ibid.)</note> of the
                                above requirements can be obtained <hi rend="italic">only if</hi>
                                the Western side concurs in the establishment of a Consulate General
                                in West Berlin, then authorization is granted on the condition that
                                the Soviets accept in binding form the following restrictions on the
                                Consulate General: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>The Consulate General must be accredited to the Western
                                        Commandants.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>The Consulate General will not perform any functions
                                        deriving from the rights and responsibilities of the Four
                                        Powers for Berlin and Germany as a whole; its activities
                                        will be limited to consular functions, and it will not
                                        perform political functions.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0856" n="825" xml:id="pg_825"/>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>The consul general, and all Soviet staff members, must be
                                        acceptable to the Western Commandants who must be given
                                        prior notification of their designation; and the number of
                                        Soviet staff will be established at a figure not to exceed
                                        twenty.</item>
                                    <label>d.</label>
                                    <item>The consul general and its personnel must abide by all
                                        applicable Allied laws and regulations, and any pertinent
                                        German legislation.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The prohibition in <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> 106
                                (paragraph 6 a (2)) with respect to an official Soviet
                                representation in West Berlin is deleted.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">
                                <hi rend="strong">Henry A. Kissinger</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>