<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>316. Briefing Memorandum From the Acting Assistant Secretary of State for
                    European Affairs (Fessenden) and the Acting Legal Advisor () and the Acting
                    Legal Advisor (Brower) to Secretary of State ) to Secretary of State
                    Rogers</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v40</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d316</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">316</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-08-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-08-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recydYSQ1GmGAh8yu" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">European security</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-08-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-08-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="316"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d316">
                <head>316. Briefing Memorandum From the Acting Assistant Secretary of State for
                    European Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_FR1" type="from">Fessenden</persName>)
                    and the Acting Legal Advisor (<persName corresp="#p_BCN1">Brower</persName>) to
                    Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RWP1" type="to">Rogers</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d316fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                            <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>/CE Files: Lot 80 D 225, Aug 23,
                        1971, Memos to the Secretary. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SJS1"
                            >Sutterlin</persName> on August 22.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1971-08-23">August 23, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">BERLIN QUADRIPARTITE AGREEMENT</p>
                <p>The Western objective in the Berlin negotiations has been to obtain pragmatic
                    improvements in the situation which would facilitate the life of the Berliners
                    and lessen the likelihood of confrontation with the Soviets or the East Germans.
                    The text agreed to by the Four Ambassadors for consideration by governments
                    substantially accomplishes the pragmatic improvements we had in mind. Access
                    should, as a result, be visibly facilitated, communication between West Berlin
                    and the surrounding areas improved and Berlin’s representation in the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and Eastern Europe by the <gloss
                        target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> on matters not affecting status and security
                    assured. This is a significant accomplishment, going beyond what we thought
                    possible when the negotiations began.</p>
                <p>We intended to utilize two factors to obtain Soviet concessions:</p>
                <p>(1) a reduction in the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>’s political presence
                    in West Berlin and (2) the possibility of a Conference on European Security. As
                    negotiation progressed we added the prospect of ratification of the <gloss
                        target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>’s Moscow treaty and an enhanced Soviet presence
                    in the Western sectors. Thus the bargain has been broadened on both sides.</p>
                <p>A basic principle underlying the Western approach to negotiations was that the
                    status of Berlin as reflected in Four Power agreements should not be altered.
                    The Soviets have shown the contrary objective of establishing that West Berlin
                    and only West Berlin is the subject of <pb facs="0924" n="893" xml:id="pg_893"/>
                    Four Power negotiations and is a separate political entity where Four Power
                    agreements on Berlin as a whole continue to be valid. It is in this area that
                    the major problems arise in the text agreed to by the Ambassadors. These are
                    discussed in the following paragraphs. The full text as agreed by the
                    Ambassadors is at Tab A.<note n="2" xml:id="d316fn2">Attached but not
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Status of Berlin</hi>
                </p>
                <p>No individual sentence in the text as it now stands can be cited as altering the
                    status of Berlin. However, despite references to the effect that Four Power
                    rights and responsibilities remain unchanged and legal positions are not
                    prejudiced, the following aspects of the text in combination could be
                    interpreted as Allied acknowledgment of a separate Four Power status for West
                    Berlin:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>(1)</label>
                    <item>There is no mention in the text of Berlin as the subject of
                        negotiations.</item>
                    <label>(2)</label>
                    <item>All of the operative provisions of the text have to do with the Western
                        sectors or travel to and from them.</item>
                    <label>(3)</label>
                    <item>The text (the Preamble) includes the phrase “taking into account the
                        existing situation in the relevant area,” which suggests acceptance of the
                        division of the city.</item>
                    <label>(4)</label>
                    <item>The text (Part I, para 4) also refers to “the situation which has
                        developed in the area, and as it is defined in this agreement as well as in
                        other agreements,” thus implying that the present agreement does, in fact,
                        define a new “situation” in the city.</item>
                    <label>(5)</label>
                    <item>The stipulation that this situation “shall not be changed unilaterally”
                        indicates that the Allies may not have an entirely free hand in West
                        Berlin.</item>
                    <label>(6)</label>
                    <item>The provision, in the agreement, for the establishment of a Soviet
                        consulate general in West Berlin, without any increase in the Western
                        presence in East Berlin, tends also to increase the impression that a
                        separate status is being established for the Western sectors.</item>
                    <label>(7)</label>
                    <item>The provisions for limited representation of the Western sectors by the
                            <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> in the Soviet Union and issuance of
                        Federal passports to West Berlin residents for travel to the Soviet Union
                        and other countries are cast in a form suggesting that the Soviets share
                        with the Three Western Powers certain functions limited to the Western
                        sectors.</item>
                </list>
                <p>It is evident that not all of these aspects of the draft agreement can be
                    changed, nor do we consider this absolutely necessary. The extent to which one
                    or more might be altered, however, could materially affect the overall
                    implications of the text insofar as Berlin’s status is concerned.</p>
                <pb facs="0925" n="894" xml:id="pg_894"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Soviet Commitment</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Soviet commitment to see to it that the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>
                    lives up to agreements reached with the Federal Republic and the Senat is weak.
                    To the extent that it exists it derives from the wording of paragraph 4 of the
                    final quadripartite protocol (page 16 of the text at Tab A). It could be
                    materially strengthened by the addition of a few words as the Department
                    suggested during the final stage of the negotiations.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Soviet Presence</hi>
                </p>
                <p>An increased Soviet presence in West Berlin is part of the bargain and must be
                    accepted as such. In accepting such a presence, however, we have considered it
                    important to maintain Western freedom to deal with Soviet installations in West
                    Berlin in accordance with Soviet behavior both in West and East Berlin. Thus if
                    the Soviets should close East Berlin to Allied access we should be in a position
                    to expel Soviet representatives in the Western sectors. For this reason, among
                    others, it was decided that provision for an enhanced Soviet presence should not
                    be included in the quadripartite agreement itself since we would thus be unable
                    to change the nature of the Soviet presence without placing in question the
                    continued validity of the agreement as a whole.</p>
                <p>The Western Ambassadors were unable to persuade the Soviets to handle the
                    question outside the agreement and this battle has presumably been lost. The
                    agreed Minute on Soviet activities in the Western sectors (page 21 of the draft)
                    contains wording, however, which could intensify the problem. The Minute states
                    “this authorization will be extended indefinitely, subject to compliance with
                    the provisions outlined herein.” The conditions outlined have to do only with
                    the operations of the Soviet offices to be located in the Western sectors. If
                    taken literally, this provision would prevent us from taking measures against
                    the Soviet offices because of Soviet actions in East Berlin or unacceptable
                    Soviet comportment in the Western sectors.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Balance</hi>
                </p>
                <p>At Tabs B and C<note n="3" xml:id="d316fn3">Both attached but not printed. The
                        paper at Tab B presented a detailed tabulation of Soviet and Allied
                        concessions in the draft agreement. The paper at Tab C argued that the
                        agreement left the United States vulnerable to domestic criticism on several
                        fronts, including the implied change of status for both West Berlin and East
                        Germany and the lack of balance between Soviet presence in West Berlin and
                        Allied presence in East Berlin. “The unhappiness of the <gloss
                            target="#t_CDU1">CDU</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_CSU1">CSU</gloss>
                        opposition in the Federal Republic with these provisions,” the paper
                        concluded, “may be reflected in the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>,
                        particularly by American leaders who have been directly involved with
                        Germany and Berlin in past years.”</note> you will find analyses of the
                    concessions made by both sides in reaching the draft text and of the points on
                    which the United States Government may be vulnerable to criticism because of
                    omissions <pb facs="0926" n="895" xml:id="pg_895"/> and commissions. In summary,
                    the Soviets have made significant concessions—more, in concrete terms, than the
                    Western side. If this were not the case, there could hardly be a satisfactory
                    agreement, since the “pragmatic improvements” largely consist of revisions of
                    arbitrary restrictions imposed unilaterally by the Soviets and East Germans in
                    the past. There will be critics who claim that the agreement amounts to Western
                    acceptance of a separate West Berlin, in which the Soviet Union will have
                    increased influence, if not control. Questions will be asked as to why the
                    Western side gained nothing in East Berlin.</p>
                <p>On the whole, however, the pragmatic improvements resulting from the agreement
                    should more than balance the effect of such criticism. Chancellor <persName
                        corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> and Foreign Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_SW1">Scheel</persName> have both welcomed the agreement without
                    reservations as a major achievement. Moreover, if a Berlin agreement opens the
                    way for changes in central Europe, including general recognition of the <gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>, the status of Berlin is likely to be affected.
                    At that point, any ambiguities in the present Berlin agreement could lose their
                    importance.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>We should view the draft developed by the Four Ambassadors as an important
                    achievement which essentially meets Western objectives in the Berlin
                    negotiations. A few substantive changes could result in a sounder text which
                    would be less vulnerable to criticism and less susceptible to varied
                    interpretations in the future. There is, however, serious reason to doubt
                    whether these changes can now be achieved. Both Chancellor <persName
                        corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> and Foreign Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_SW1">Scheel</persName> believe that the text should be accepted
                    as it now stands. The British Foreign Office has also approved it and it seems
                    likely that the French will follow suit. Thus, in pursuing changes, we will have
                    the double task of first persuading our Allies and then tackling the Soviets.
                    There is also the danger that in reopening the text we would afford the Soviets
                    an opportunity to withdraw some of the concessions which they have made.</p>
                <p>In view of the great importance of the agreement, and the critical scrutiny to
                    which it is bound to be subjected we believe that, on balance, it would be
                    worthwhile to make a final effort to achieve a few changes which could
                    materially improve the text. With this in mind, telegrams are at Tabs D and
                        E<note n="4" xml:id="d316fn4">Attached but not printed. Neither telegram was
                        sent.</note> providing appropriate instructions to the field. These
                    telegrams can provide a focus for discussion with Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_RK1">Rush</persName> during your meeting on August 25. You will
                    no doubt wish to take into account his views before reaching a decision on their
                    despatch. Should we decide not to take the initiative in seeking <pb facs="0927"
                        n="896" xml:id="pg_896"/> changes, the telegrams could be redrafted as
                    contingency guidance in the event the Soviets reopen the text.</p>
                <p>White House clearance will be required if the telegrams are sent since, even if
                    the changes we are suggesting are made, the resultant text would not comply with
                    all of the requirements of <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> 106 and <gloss
                        target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> 125.<note n="5" xml:id="d316fn5">
                        <ref target="#d225">Documents 225</ref> and <ref target="#d285"
                        >285</ref>.</note> The same would be true if the decision is made to send a
                    telegram authorizing signature of the text as it now stands.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
