<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-09-10T10:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-09-10T10:15:00-05:00" n="372" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d372">
                    <head>372. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d372fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                            Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files,
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box
                            24, <gloss target="#t_HAK1">HAK</gloss> Trip Files, <gloss target="#t_HAK1">HAK</gloss> European Trip Sept. 1972, <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_Memcon1">Memcon</gloss>s <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>
                            (Originals), Eyes Alone. Confidential; Eyes Only. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, an avid soccer fan, was in
                            Munich to attend the Olympic Games. The meeting was held at the
                            Arabaella House.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Munich</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1972-09-10T16:15:00+01:00" to="1972-09-10T16:45:00+01:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">September 10, 1972, 4:15–4:45
                                p.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item>Minister of State <persName>Franz Heubl</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Franz Josef Strauss</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SH2">Helmut Sonnenfeldt</persName>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: I want to ask you first of
                        all about the <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: It is probably inevitable
                        some time next year.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: Are you sure it is
                        inevitable?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: We did not favor it but
                        all our allies do; the French do, the British do and your government
                        does.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: Well, we do not and we will
                        go slow once we are elected. You have to realize that with these socialists
                        there is nothing but concessions.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Why do you say that?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: My dear
                            <persName>Henry</persName>, because socialism is synonymous with
                        concessions. They can’t help themselves. And we are really faced with a
                        socialist belt now. First there are the Scandinavians and we all know about
                        them. Then there is Austria, although [Chancellor
                        <persName>Bruno</persName>] Kreisky is trying to follow his own policy. In
                        Italy by sheer luck there isn’t a socialist government yet but who can tell
                        in that country how long the present setup will last. And in France you have
                            Mitterand,<note n="2" xml:id="d372fn2">François Mitterand, First
                            Secretary of the French Socialist Party.</note> who is already in bed
                        with the Communists. <persName corresp="#p_PG1">Pompidou</persName>, who is
                        a good man, <pb facs="1085" n="1054" xml:id="pg_1054"/> will probably win in
                        the elections next year but don’t discount Mitterand and the socialists. And
                        then our socialists. Well, the chances are you will have this socialist belt
                        from the North Cape to the Mediterranean.</p>
                    <p>Heubl: There has been a story, just in the last few days, that the Chinese
                        will somehow want to participate in the <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I cannot believe that Mao
                        will die unfulfilled if there is never a conference. For obvious reasons,
                        this is not a favorite idea of the Chinese. They are the best members of
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> these days. You mentioned the
                        election. What do you think the outcome will be?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: It looks as though we will
                        win it. The Olympics have probably hurt <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName>.<note n="3" xml:id="d372fn3">On September 5 eight
                            Arab terrorists of the Black September organization stormed the quarters
                            of the Isareli athletic team at the Olympic village in Munich, killing
                            two and taking nine hostage. In a gun battle with German security forces
                            that night at a nearby military airport, five of the terrorists were
                            killed but not before killing all of the hostages.</note> There also was
                        the <persName corresp="#p_SK1">Schiller</persName> affair and the Quick
                            affair<note n="4" xml:id="d372fn4">
                            <hi rend="italic">Quick</hi>, a popular illustrated magazine, published
                                <persName corresp="#p_SK1">Schiller</persName>’s private letter of
                            resignation on July 26; the magazine had also published without
                            permission the “<persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bahr</persName> Paper” in
                            June/July 1970 and several drafts of the quadripartite agreement on
                            Berlin in July 1971. On August 29 two state secretaries resigned from
                            the Federal Government after a police raid on the Quick offices in
                            Munich and Hamburg revealed that they had received consulting contracts
                            from a publishing company associated with the magazine.</note>—the
                        practice of persecuting journalists for minutia. You are laughing. But I am
                        not sensitive when I say this because I think there is a difference between
                        printing a letter of resignation of a minister and the nuclear target list
                        of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.<note n="5" xml:id="d372fn5">In
                            November 1962 Strauss, then Minister of Defense, was forced to resign
                            due to his role in the so-called <hi rend="italic">Spiegel</hi> affair
                            in which his concern for national security, the unauthorized disclosure
                            in <hi rend="italic">Der Spiegel</hi> of a <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> exercise on nuclear war, led to the controversial
                            arrest of several representatives of the German newsmagazine.</note> So
                        I am not sensitive. You should know there is an underground attack against
                        our system. Communists and anarchists pervade the youth organizations of the
                            <gloss target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss> and even the Free Democrats. And of
                        course the Russians support the Government and have a mammoth propaganda
                        machinery against us. This could result in a close election.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: What is the best time for
                        you?</p>
                    <p>Heubl: December 3 is optimal, after that is is unpredictable.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: There is a story that
                            <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> in the next two weeks will
                        send a letter to the President of the Bundestag and ask him to pose the
                        confidence question. <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> does not
                        want to pose it himself. But under our constitutional system that would be a
                        very questionable procedure.</p>
                    <p>Heubl: I had not heard of this.</p>
                    <pb facs="1086" n="1055" xml:id="pg_1055"/>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: I heard about it just in the
                        last few days. I don’t know what von Hassel will do. But I think it is
                        impossible.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: What will be the effect of
                        the completion of the treaty with East Germany?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: Well they could have that;
                        and <persName corresp="#p_SW1">Scheel</persName> will go to China; and there
                        could be an agreement on <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss>; and the
                        Poles could agree to repatriate Germans from their Western territories. But
                        I think people are not so much concerned about foreign policy as they are
                        about security (“Sicherheit”).</p>
                    <p>Heubl: Anyway, it could be close. But if <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> ends up with just a onevote majority, the legislative
                        period will not last four years.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SH2">Sonnenfeldt</persName>: What if you end up with
                        onevote [majority]?</p>
                    <p>Heubl: Then we have to govern; there would be no alternative.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: Of course we will have to
                        keep <persName corresp="#p_BR1">Barzel</persName> tied down.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: But you supported him.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: What was the alternative?
                        But he would have to go if he does not perform after the election.</p>
                    <p>Heubl: But with <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Franz</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Josef</persName> running economics and finances and
                        Schroeder foreign policy it should be possible to keep <persName corresp="#p_BR1">Barzel</persName> in line.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: <persName corresp="#p_BR1">Barzel</persName> lost a lot because of his wavering on the Eastern
                        treaties. But if he does not perform, he will have to go.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: We are talking completely
                        privately? No press leaks?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: None whatsoever.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Not even hints or
                        statements attributed to me by implication?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: Nothing traceable to you.
                        That is how it should be between old friends.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Who would be the
                        alternatives to <persName corresp="#p_BR1">Barzel</persName>?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: Well—Schroeder or <persName corresp="#p_SG2">Stoltenberg</persName>.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Do you think the evolution
                        would have been the same if the small coalition had continued in 1966?</p>
                    <p>Heubl: I don’t think so.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: It is very hard to say; it
                        is speculative.</p>
                    <p>Heubl: I know your time is short. I want to ask you three questions. One,
                        what do you think will be the reaction in Moscow if there is a <gloss target="#t_CSU1">CSU</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_CDU1">CDU</gloss>
                        Government? Two, what are the prospects for <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> troop cuts in Europe? (<persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: Application of the <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> doctrine to Europe.) Three, how do you see the
                        developments in the Middle East and will this come up in your talks in
                        Moscow?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: Yes, and then there have
                        recently been many stories, especially from the French that say you and the
                        Russians will get together <pb facs="1087" n="1056" xml:id="pg_1056"/> on a
                        combined attack on the <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss>. Of course, the
                        French have a reason for saying this. <persName corresp="#p_PG1">Pompidou</persName> is an intelligent man but the French use this to
                        argue against any derogation of sovereignty in Europe.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: (Asks for repetition of
                        first question.) Let me tell you about our experience. We were warned that
                        when President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> became
                        President, the Russians would see him as a cold warrior and things would be
                        rough. Everyone was making proposals to us: that we should go to the summit
                        immediately; that we should start <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>;
                        that we should make concessions; that we should move quickly on trade. The
                            <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> and other papers were full of
                        this. Well, we did nothing like that. We took our time. The Russians tried
                        to build a submarine base in Cuba and we reacted tough; they tried to inject
                        themselves in the Middle East and we reacted. Then things began to change.
                        Now we are prepared to move on trade and we will do many things because we
                        have gotten some political things. We moved very coldly and concretely and
                        deliberately. That is what the Russians respect because they also calculate
                        coldly.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: That is exactly my
                        approach.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: You may have a similar
                        experience. Lots of threats beforehand. And maybe some kind of crisis after
                        you are elected. But then they may be ready to do business. In any case, we
                        won’t permit a crisis to happen.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: I find this very
                        interesting. There actually are some signs already of their trying to
                        communicate with us. But this is very interesting.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: The Russians have no use
                        for sentimental people.</p>
                    <p>Heubl: Well, <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Franz-Josef</persName> is not
                        sentimental.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Now on the second
                        question. We will use <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> to reduce troops
                        as slowly as possible—not more than 10–15% over five years and then only
                        reciprocally. But of course the Europeans have to do their share.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: Burden-sharing. A <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> doctrine modified for Europe. I have
                        advocated it for eight years.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Yes, burden-sharing. The
                        Europeans have to stop using our troops for their détente policies.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: I hope you have said this to
                            <persName corresp="#p_SH1">Helmut Schmidt</persName>.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: If you are defense
                        oriented, we won’t reduce. Of course, I can’t guarantee some small number
                        like 20,000. But…</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: I have always said that if
                        the Americans reduce in Europe, mutatis mutandis have to make up the
                        difference.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I agree. You simply cannot
                        expect the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> to defend an economic
                        competitor. I mean there will be competition; but it has to be within
                        bounds. You simply cannot expect this to go on indefinitely.</p>
                    <pb facs="1088" n="1057" xml:id="pg_1057"/>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: Well, I agree with that.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Now on the Middle East.
                        Well—this is really too complicated and I don’t really want to say anything
                        about it now. It is very dangerous and there has recently been a substantial
                            <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> success because of the removal of the
                        Russian troops.<note n="6" xml:id="d372fn6">On July 18 Egyptian President
                            Sadat announced his order for the immediate withdrawal of Soviet
                            military personnel from Egypt.</note> But we do need a united Western
                        policy on energy sources. We can’t let them—cites example of Libya—play us
                        off one against the other. So we really should do what we can to get a
                        united policy on that.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: Well, I agree with you on
                        that, too.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Now about the <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss>. It is absolutely essential—and I have said
                        this to the members of the Government with whom I have spoken—that after we
                        have had our elections that we have a fundamental review of our relations,
                        the relationship between the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>— America—and
                        Western Europe. I think this is absolutely essential or we will find
                        ourselves fighting about individual issues year after year. And after a
                        while the economic problems will make it impossible to maintain the security
                        relationship. You should be aware that if it were not for <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Richard Nixon</persName>—this extraordinary political
                        phenomenon who does not come from the American political establishment—if it
                        were not for him we would already be in the midst of a major fight with
                        Europe. You could very well get this. I wouldn’t say that there will be a
                        joint <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>-Soviet attack. But there will be
                        real pressures against Europe. So we need to get our relations fundamentally
                        looked at. I don’t mean that you would agree with us in every detail.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: Obviously, that would not be
                        the case. But I completely agree with you. We are exactly in agreement on
                        this. But I doubt that the other party, the present majority party, is.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Well, as soon as the
                        elections are over, we must get in touch. I may send somebody over. All this
                        is of course on the premise that the President will be elected. I remember
                        the advice you gave me once that after defense one should turn to economics.
                        Maybe this is what I should do.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: I hope you will do nothing
                        that can be used by the Government as being your blessing of its eastern
                        policy. I mean the sort of thing the Secretary of State said, though he
                        hasn’t recently.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: There is no reason to say
                        anything. But we will do nothing like that.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: Well, we really hope so
                        because it gets used in the debates with us constantly.</p>
                    <pb facs="1089" n="1058" xml:id="pg_1058"/>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Well, I am afraid the time
                        is running out. I have to get to Moscow to see <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>. I hope we can stay in touch. We are old
                        friends.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: I tried to get in touch in
                        April—about those statements that the Secretary of State was making. But you
                        were away.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Yes, I think I was out of
                        town. But let me know when you come so we can talk.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SFJ1">Strauss</persName>: Well, I don’t like to trade
                        on old personal friendship. But we will stay in touch.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>