<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>78. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Kissinger) to President ) to President Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v40</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d78</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">78</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-04-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4kNZ3bN6ephN7u" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027420"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Coalition government</term>
                    <term ref="recieOBiY284bnHpv" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances">Western alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recILGIop3TL1t3vh" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85045811"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Common Market</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations">Ostpolitik</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="recydYSQ1GmGAh8yu" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">European security</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Domestic politics</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-04-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="78"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d78">
                <head>78. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>) to President
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d78fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 917, <gloss target="#t_VIP1"
                            >VIP</gloss> Visits, Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_BW1"
                            >Brandt</persName> Visit, April 10–11, 1970 [1 of 3]. Secret; Sensitive;
                        Nodis. Sent for information. No drafting information appears on the
                        memorandum.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-04-09">April 9, 1970</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Your Meetings with Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_BW1"
                        >Brandt</persName>, April 10–11, 1970</item>
                </list>
                <p>You are scheduled to meet with the Chancellor immediately after the arrival
                    ceremony on Friday, beginning about 10:30 a.m. until a little after noon. (He
                    then has a commitment at the National Press Club.) You will then have a final
                    meeting on Saturday from 9:30 a.m. until about 10:15 when he is to leave for the
                    Apollo 13 launch at Cape Kennedy. You will also see him at the White Tie dinner
                    on Friday night.</p>
                <pb facs="0240" n="209" xml:id="pg_209"/>
                <p>Points for your arrival statement and your dinner toast will be sent to you
                    separately.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Background and Setting</hi>
                </p>
                <p>You twice saw <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> last year when he was
                    Foreign Minister in the <persName corresp="#p_KKG1">Kiesinger</persName>
                    coalition government—when you visited Bonn and when he was here for the <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> meeting in April 1969. You had originally
                    invited him to come here shortly after he became Chancellor but he preferred to
                    wait several months. The delay was undoubtedly related to his desire to
                    establish himself fully as head of government and not appear to be “running to
                    Washington.”</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, he has successfully managed the first party switchover in the
                    Chancellorship since the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> was founded in
                    1949. This was a substantial political and psychological achievement given the
                    fact that the <gloss target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss> remains a minority party and
                    that, with the <gloss target="#t_FDP1">FDP</gloss>, he has only a tiny majority
                    in the Bundestag. This majority is still under threat if the small <gloss
                        target="#t_FDP1">FDP</gloss> should fall apart.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, also, <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> has set in train a
                    series of interrelated policies toward both the East and West; his political
                    life depends in important measure (though not exclusively) on his ability to
                    manage these complex policies.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> maintains that he is solidly
                    anchored in the Western alliance and the Common Market and that what he seeks in
                    the East is only “normalization” and not some basic reorientation in German
                    alignment. Nevertheless, his Eastern Policy (“Ostpolitik”) has drawn most
                    attention, caused the toughest opposition at home—though there is currently a
                    substantial popular majority in his favor—and raised the most suspicion among
                    his allies, especially the French. Few people, either inside Germany or abroad,
                    see <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> as selling out to the East;
                    what worries people is whether he can control what he has started.</p>
                <p>For <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> his <gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >US</gloss> trip and meetings with you are important because they will
                    establish him in the same league as previous Chancellors and as such Western
                    leaders as <persName corresp="#p_WH2">Wilson</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_PG1">Pompidou</persName>. Beyond that, however, <persName
                        corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> sees his relationship with the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and our policies as crucial elements determining
                    his own success or failure.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> has several concerns or fears about
                    the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. His main current worry is that we will
                    reduce our troops in Europe. He sees these troops as vital to the strength of
                    the Alliance which in turn is the basis on which he wants to conduct his Eastern
                    policy. He fears that if the Soviets see the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                    as withdrawing and the Alliance as disintegrating, the Soviets will simply sit
                    back and not negotiate seriously with the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>
                    about the kind of normalization which <persName corresp="#p_BW1"
                        >Brandt</persName> thinks will mitigate the division of Germany.</p>
                <pb facs="0241" n="210" xml:id="pg_210"/>
                <p>Related to his concern about our troop levels is his fear that we will demand
                    heavy German financial support as the price for keeping our troops in Europe.
                    This worries him not only because the German budget is taut but because such an
                    arrangement would look like he was paying us money so that he can conduct his
                    Ostpolitik.</p>
                <p>Again, stemming from his worry about our troops, <persName corresp="#p_BW1"
                        >Brandt</persName> is eager that we agree to enter negotiations with the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> on mutual troop reductions in Central
                    Europe. He believes—as do many people in Washington—that such an offer would
                    take the wind out of Senator <persName corresp="#p_MM1">Mansfield</persName>’s
                    sails (although, in fact, the Senator wants our troops reduced whether or not
                    the Soviets cut theirs). He also wants to have the Soviets believe that there
                    will be no unilateral <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> reductions but only
                    agreed and reciprocal ones.<note n="2" xml:id="d78fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined most of this
                        sentence.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> also feels that such a proposal
                    would be a constructive response to Eastern pressure for a European Security
                    conference.</p>
                <p>Part of <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName>’s worry list has to do with
                    Berlin. He recognizes that the success of his Ostpolitik will be measured
                    importantly in terms of what it accomplishes for West Berlin’s viability. For
                    this reason the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> has been in the forefront of
                    those pressing for the recently begun talks between the three Western powers and
                    the Soviets. While wanting to maintain fully the four-power status of Berlin,
                    the Germans want the four powers to provide an umbrella for <gloss
                        target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> talks on
                    improving access to and movements within the city.</p>
                <p>While pressing ahead with his normalization policies toward the East, <persName
                        corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> has also been active in the West,
                    pressing for enlargement of the Common Market and for improvements within
                        it.<note n="3" xml:id="d78fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined most of this
                        sentence.</note> He has been worried about friction between the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and the Common Market— again, in part, because he
                    feels this undermines his strength in dealing with the East—and favors a <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss>-Common Market commission<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d78fn4">
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined the phrase “<gloss
                            target="#t_US1">US</gloss>-Common Market commission.”</note> to iron out
                    issues that have arisen (mostly having to do with the Communities’ preferential
                    trade agreements and its internal agricultural policies).</p>
                <p>Altogether, therefore, <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> has a heavy
                    budget of issues on which he seeks reassurance, together with others—such as
                        <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>, Vietnam, the Middle East and,
                    currently, the murder of the German Ambassador to Guatemala—which he wishes to
                    discuss with you. Rightly or wrongly, the Germans see the <persName
                        corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> visit as a, if not the, major event in
                        <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName>’s tenure as Chancellor thus far
                    because to them Washington is the key to almost everything the Germans are
                    attempting to do in the international arena.</p>
                <pb facs="0242" n="211" xml:id="pg_211"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Your Objectives</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In this situation your purpose will be</p>
                <list>
                    <item>—to allow a far-ranging discussion of the issues that concern <persName
                            corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName>;</item>
                    <item>—to affirm that a solid and frank working relationship exists between the
                        two governments;</item>
                    <item>—to provide <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> with general
                        reassurance of your understanding and support (for, in the end, the Germans
                        remain fundamentally uncertain and insecure and, regardless of who is in
                        power in Bonn, need a sense of understanding with Washington);</item>
                    <item>—at the same time, to avoid identification with specific elements of
                        German Eastern policy so that we do not end up in the crossfire of German
                        domestic politics;</item>
                    <item>—to encourage <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> in pursuing his
                        Western policy.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Particular Points to Emphasize or be Alert to</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Detailed talking points, incorporating recommendations by Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>, are at Tab A.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d78fn5">Attached at Tab A but not printed is an April 3 memorandum
                        from <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> to the President
                        providing “perspectives” on the <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName>
                        visit and including an enclosed set of talking points. Another copy is in
                        the National Archives, RG 59, Central Files 1970–73, POL 7 GER <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWP1">W. Rogers</persName> suggested that “our principal
                        objective for the visit will be to leave no doubt in <persName
                            corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName>’s mind that an intimate, forthright
                        relationship between our two governments has equal importance for the United
                        States.” Among the specific objectives, <persName corresp="#p_RWP1"
                            >Rogers</persName> recommended that the administration “demonstrate that
                        we are working as closely and as successfully with the <gloss
                            target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss>-led government, as we did with its <gloss
                            target="#t_CDU1">CDU</gloss> predecessors” and “reaffirm American
                        support for the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>’s efforts to strengthen
                        and enlarge the European community in the West and to reduce tension through
                        patient negotiations in the East.”</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">1. <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Troops in Europe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Germans are almost convinced that sooner or later there will be a reduction
                    of <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> forces in Europe. They acknowledge that you
                    have made no decision to reduce but they have interpreted our statements that we
                    will maintain our forces intact until mid-1971 as meaning that we intend to cut
                    them thereafter. You may wish to stress that</p>
                <list>
                    <item>—we are serious in wanting the future of <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                            >NATO</gloss> strategy and forces examined within the Alliance and have
                        no intention to confront the Europeans with an accomplished fact;</item>
                    <item>—we should then decide together whether, within an agreed strategic
                        concept, the contributions of the several Allies are in the right
                        proportion;</item>
                    <item>—the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> is still conducting its own
                        internal studies.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">2. Offset and Budget Support</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Germans recognize the need for offsetting the balance of payment outflows
                    produced by the stationing of our forces in Germany, but they have begun to say
                    that it will be much harder for them to <pb facs="0243" n="212" xml:id="pg_212"
                    /> purchase <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> arms in the seventies because
                    their need for such arms is declining. They are more concerned about
                    intimations, including by Senator Percy, that we will ask for budgetary support.
                        <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> has indicated some willingness
                    to consider this but the idea is highly controversial in Germany. You may wish
                    to make the point that</p>
                <list>
                    <item>—you have no intention to pressure <persName corresp="#p_BW1"
                            >Brandt</persName> for decisions now;</item>
                    <item>—that both of us should look at the financial problems without publicity
                        and fanfare over the next several months;</item>
                    <item>—that in the fall we should perhaps begin considering the issues;</item>
                    <item>—but that in any case financial arrangements should be related to the
                        Review of Strategy and Forces to be undertaken within <gloss
                            target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> later this year.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">3. Mutual and Balanced Force Reductions (“<gloss
                            target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>”)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>As noted above, <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> will seek your
                    agreement to a more explicit Western proposal to the East that there be
                    negotiations on reciprocal force reductions in Central Europe.<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d78fn6">
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined the phrase
                        “reciprocal force reductions in Central Europe.”</note> No one believes
                    there is much prospect of success; the topic is in some ways more complex than
                        <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> because of the major asymmetries
                    between the two sides (e.g., the fact that we would withdraw back to the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss> while the Soviets would only pull back some
                    hundreds of miles; or that Soviet forces in Eastern Europe are partly there for
                    internal security reasons). But <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName>
                    feels that a <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> commitment to mutual reductions
                    with the East will reduce the danger of unilateral <gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >US</gloss> cuts.<note n="7" xml:id="d78fn7">
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined most of this
                        sentence.</note> You may wish to say that</p>
                <list>
                    <item>—you understand <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName>’s
                        arguments;</item>
                    <item>—that the subject is extremely complex and that we should make sure that
                        before entering negotiations we know where we are headed;</item>
                    <item>—but that you will consider supporting a more explicit “signal” to the
                        East of our interest in talks on this subject.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">4. Ostpolitik</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> will wish to give you an account of
                    what has happened so far and what his objectives and expectations are. He has
                    said to others that he has no great hopes for progress. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> will seek your endorsement of his policy
                    in part to use it politically against those in the <gloss target="#t_CDU1"
                        >CDU</gloss> who oppose it. You may wish to</p>
                <list>
                    <item>—give him the opportunity to set forth his views;</item>
                    <item>—generally endorse the objective of more normal relations between the
                            <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> and the East;<note n="8"
                            xml:id="d78fn8">
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined this
                            point.</note>
                    </item>
                    <item>—express appreciation for <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName>’s
                        keeping us and the other Allies informed;</item>
                    <item>—express confidence that <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> will
                        move cautiously.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0244" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">5. A New <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>-Western
                        Agreement</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Germans have advanced a proposal to the Soviets that any agreement between
                    the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss> would not affect the treaties that each of them may have with
                    third parties. The intent is to leave four power rights and responsibilities for
                    Germany as a whole and for Berlin intact and to deny the Soviets any legal right
                    to challenge the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>’s treaties with the Western
                    powers. <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> may suggest that
                    simultaneously with any <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>-Soviet agreement or
                    renunciation of force, the Western powers and the <gloss target="#t_FRG1"
                        >FRG</gloss> issue a joint declaration reaffirming the validity of past
                    treaties between them.<note n="9" xml:id="d78fn9">
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined most of this
                        sentence.</note> This proposal will have to be examined by legal experts:
                        <hi rend="italic">you may want to say, if <persName corresp="#p_BW1"
                            >Brandt</persName> raises the subject that</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <item>—the Germans should raise the idea formally with the Allies when the time
                        is ripe;</item>
                    <item>—we will meanwhile be prepared to examine it.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">6. Berlin</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> wishes the Western powers to get an
                    agreement with the Soviets that the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> and
                        <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> should work out ways of improving
                    access. <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> is willing to reduce the
                        <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>’s political presence in West Berlin
                    provided the Soviets accept a substantial <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>
                    link to the city. (The French want to maintain sole four power responsibility
                    which they feel would be weakened by <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>–<gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> dealings.) <hi rend="italic">You may want to
                        note that</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <item>—as you noted when you were in Berlin, you favor getting improvements in
                        the situation there;</item>
                    <item>—you understand the German position and will seek to meet it as far as
                        possible;</item>
                    <item>—basically, you are not too optimistic that the Soviets and East Germans
                        will be very forthcoming.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">7. Common Market</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> has advanced the idea of <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss>-Common Market Commission to work out problems.
                    This stems partly from German concern with some recent speeches by <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss> officials who were critical of the Common
                    Market’s preferential commercial agreements with nonmembers.<note n="10"
                        xml:id="d78fn10">
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined the phrase “critical
                        of the Common Market’s preferential commercial agreements with
                        nonmembers.”</note>
                    <hi rend="italic">You may simply want to note that</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <item>—these speeches do not reflect your own views;</item>
                    <item>—that the idea of a Commission to deal with points of friction is
                        interesting and will be examined.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0245" n="214" xml:id="pg_214"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">8. Murder of German Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SKG1">Von
                            Spreti</persName> in Guatemala</hi>
                </p>
                <p>You may wish to express personally your condolences over the murder of Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_SKG1">von Spreti</persName> by Guatemalan terrorists,
                    your condemnation of such crimes and your concern over the growing problem of
                    political kidnapping and its international consequences and security
                    implications. You may also add that we are studying what can be done in
                    international fora, such as the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> and the
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, as well as in assisting nations
                    bilaterally to improve their internal security capability (<persName
                        corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> may himself suggest international
                    cooperation).</p>
                <p>Should <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName> express his concern that the
                        <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> did not pressure the Guatemalans to do
                    more, <hi rend="italic">you may wish to say that</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <item>—we did all we felt we could at the time;</item>
                    <item>—the Guatemalan Government was adamant that it could not yield completely
                        to the kidnappers;</item>
                    <item>—and there was, in our judgment, no more pressure which we could
                        practically and properly exert which would have changed their minds or which
                        they would have accepted.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">9. Other Points</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In addition to the foregoing matters, most of which <persName corresp="#p_BW1"
                        >Brandt</persName> will certainly raise if you do not, you may want to give
                        <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Brandt</persName>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <item>—your impressions of President <persName corresp="#p_PG1"
                            >Pompidou</persName>;</item>
                    <item>—your basic approach to <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> (this will
                        be treated in greater detail through <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss>);</item>
                    <item>—your current assessment of the Vietnam/Laos/Cambodia situation;</item>
                    <item>—your assessment of the Middle East, including your hope that there can be
                        some stabilization in the Western Mediterranean through the cooperation of
                        the countries of that area. (You may in this connection stress the
                        desirability of finding ways to associate Spain with <gloss
                            target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.)</item>
                </list>
                <p>You may also find an opportunity to urge <persName corresp="#p_BW1"
                        >Brandt</persName> to support replenishment of the International Development
                    Association (IDA) at the level of $1 billion annually. This is crucial to the
                    new foreign assistance effort. The Germans have preferred a lower replenishment
                    level.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
