<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-02-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="111" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d111">
                    <head>111. Remarks by President <persName corresp="#p_CJE2_1">Carter</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d111fn1">Source: <hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_CJE2_1">Carter</persName>, 1979,</hi> Book I, pp. 300–306. All brackets
                            are in the original. The President spoke at a special convocation, which
                            took place at 12:30 p.m. in Alexander Memorial Coliseum at the Georgia
                            Institute of Technology. In his diary entry for February 20, the
                            President commented: “I made a foreign affairs speech at Georgia Tech
                            and got the first honorary degree they’ve ever given. They had to pass a
                            special rule by the Board of Regents that an honorary degree could be
                            given by a college in the university system only to an alumnus of the
                            college who had become president of the United States.” (<hi rend="italic">White House Diary,</hi> p. 295) The President had
                            attended Georgia Tech before he received a commission to the U.S. Naval
                            Academy.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Atlanta, Georgia</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1979-02-20">February 20, 1979</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <opener>
                        <salute>
                            <hi rend="italic">Chairman Milton Jones, Chancellor George Simpson, Dr.
                                Joe Pettit, Mr. Kroll,</hi><note n="2" xml:id="d111fn2">Reference is
                                to the Chairman of the Board of Regents of the University System of
                                Georgia Milton Jones, Chancellor of the University System George
                                Simpson, Jr., President of the Georgia Institute of Technology
                                Joseph Pettit, and President of the Georgia Institute of Technology
                                National Alumni Association Bernard Kroll.</note>
                            <hi rend="italic">honored guests, fellow Tech students and alumni,
                                ladies and gentlemen:</hi>
                        </salute>
                    </opener>
                    <p>I have always been proud that I attended Georgia Tech, and I’ve always been
                        grateful for what I learned here.</p>
                    <p>I have attended as a full-time student four different colleges in my life.
                        Georgia Tech is by far the most difficult—[<hi rend="italic">laughter</hi>]—and a number of years ago I decided that my being elected
                        President was the only way that I would ever have a chance to get a degree
                        from Georgia Tech. [<hi rend="italic">Laughter</hi>] This has made it
                        worthwhile. [<hi rend="italic">Laughter</hi>]</p>
                    <p>I remember when I first came to Tech, the entire world was at war. Our Nation
                        was under attack on two fronts and was desperately gearing up for a total
                        war effort that we had not known since we fought each other in the
                        1860’s.</p>
                    <p>In 1942, 1943, it was not yet a time for victories for the United States nor
                        for our allies, and many people feared that Western democracies might be
                        overwhelmed. We now face a very different world from the world in which I
                        came of age. The old empires are gone, and the maps are covered with new and
                        developing nations with names that we had then never heard.</p>
                    <p>But one thing has not changed as much as I had hoped. It’s still a world of
                        danger, a world in which democracy and freedom are still challenged, a world
                        in which peace must be rewon day by day. Too many people still lack the
                        simplest necessities of life, and too many are deprived of the most basic
                        human rights. As the events of recent days</p>
                    <pb facs="0594" n="553" xml:id="pg_553"/>
                    <p>have shown, peace remains a fragile thing, vulnerable to assaults from all
                        sides.</p>
                    <p>Disturbances in Iran, the Western Indian Ocean, and Southeast Asia, are a
                        challenge to our determination and our leadership. They underscore the
                        importance of strength in our national defenses, wisdom in our diplomacy,
                        and steadfastness in the pursuit of arms control and peace.</p>
                    <p>I want to speak to you today about America’s role and America’s purpose in
                        this world of change and turbulence.</p>
                    <p>Ever since the end of the Second World War, the United States has been the
                        leader in moving our world closer to a stable peace and genuine security. We
                        have the world’s strongest economy; we have the world’s strongest military
                        forces; and we share burdens of mutual defense with friends abroad whose
                        security and prosperity are as vital to us as to themselves.</p>
                    <p>With our strong allies, we have succeeded in preventing a global war for more
                        than one-third of a century—the longest period of general peace in modern
                        times. And as President of the United States, I am determined to keep our
                        Nation at peace.</p>
                    <p>We help to sustain a world trading and monetary system that has brought
                        greater prosperity to more of the world’s people than ever before in
                        history. We are working to resolve conflicts among other nations so that
                        each can develop its own future in independence and peace. And we’ve helped
                        to maintain the conditions in which more than 100 new nations have come into
                        being, and in which human hope—and its fulfillment—has taken a revolutionary
                        leap forward.</p>
                    <p>In short, we in the United States provide the bedrock of global security and
                        economic advance in a world of unprecedented change and conflict.</p>
                    <p>In such a world America has four fundamental security responsibilities: to
                        provide for our own Nation’s strength and safety; to stand by our allies and
                        our friends; to support national independence and integrity of other
                        nations; and to work diligently for peace.</p>
                    <p>We do not oppose change. Many of the political currents sweeping the world
                        express a desire that we share—the desire for a world in which the
                        legitimate aspirations of nations and individuals have a greater chance for
                        fulfillment.</p>
                    <p>The United States cannot control events within other nations. A few years
                        ago, we tried this and we failed. But we recognized as inevitable that the
                        uncertainty and the turmoil that come with change can have its darker side
                        as well. We saw this in a senseless act of violence last week in
                        Afghanistan, when a brave and good man—Ambassador <pb facs="0595" n="554" xml:id="pg_554"/>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Adolph Dubs</persName>—gave his life in the
                        performance of his duty as a representative of the United States.<note n="3" xml:id="d111fn3">
                            <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dubs</persName> was kidnapped in Kabul on
                            February 14 and was killed during an attempt to free him. For the
                            President’s and <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>’s comments
                            at a February 18 ceremony honoring <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dubs</persName>, which took place at Andrews Air Force Base, see
                                <hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_CJE2_1">Carter</persName>, 1979,</hi> Book I, pp. 295–296.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>As we meet here today at Georgia Tech—enjoying the blessings of freedom and
                        peace—we must remember that we are indebted for those blessings to the
                        sacrifice of men and women like <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Spike
                            Dubs</persName>.</p>
                    <p>We also see the darker side of change when countries in turbulence provide
                        opportunities for exploitation by outsiders who seek not to advance human
                        aims, but rather to extend their own power and their own position at the
                        expense of others.</p>
                    <p>As I speak to you today, the country of Iran—with which we have had close
                        relations for the last 30 years—is in revolution.<note n="4" xml:id="d111fn4">Documentation on the Iranian Revolution is scheduled
                            for publication in <ref target="frus1977-80v10">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. X, Iran:
                                Revolution, January 1977–November 1979</ref>.</note> It’s been our
                        hope that Iran could modernize without deep internal conflicts, and we
                        sought to encourage that effort by supporting its government, by urging
                        internal change toward progress and democracy, and by helping to provide a
                        background of regional stability.</p>
                    <p>The revolution in Iran is a product of deep social, political, religious, and
                        economic factors growing out of the history of Iran itself. Those who argue
                        that the United States should or could intervene directly to thwart these
                        events are wrong about the realities of Iran. So, too, are those who spout
                        propaganda that protecting our own citizens is tantamount to direct
                        intervention.</p>
                    <p>We have not and we will not intervene in Iran, yet the future of Iran
                        continues to be of deep concern to us and to our friends and allies. It’s an
                        important nation in a critical part of the world, an immediate neighbor of
                        the Soviet Union, a major oil producer that also sits beside the principal
                        artery for most of the world’s trade in oil. And it is still a significant
                        potential force for stability and progress in the region.</p>
                    <p>Iran is a proud nation with a long history—more than 2,000 years—of struggle
                        to establish and to guarantee its own freedom. The independence of Iran is
                        also in our own vital interest and in the interest of our closest allies—and
                        we will support the independence of Iran.</p>
                    <p>Out of today’s turmoil, it is our hope that these troubled people will create
                        a stable government which can meet the needs of the Iranian people and which
                        can enable that great nation not only to remain independent but to regain
                        its internal strength and balance.</p>
                    <pb facs="0596" n="555" xml:id="pg_555"/>
                    <p>We are prepared to support that effort as appropriate and to work with the
                        Iranian Government and the people as a nation which shares common interests
                        and common aspirations with us.</p>
                    <p>But just as we respect Iran’s independence and integrity, other nations must
                        do so as well. If others interfere, directly or indirectly, they are on
                        notice that this will have serious consequences and will affect our broader
                        relationships with them.</p>
                    <p>At the same time, we are intensifying our efforts to promote stability
                        throughout the Middle East so that the security and the independence of the
                        nations of that part of the world will be maintained.</p>
                    <p>At my direction, the Secretary of Defense recently carried out comprehensive
                        consultations in Israel, Egypt, Jordan, and Saudi Arabia, concerning the
                        security of that region.<note n="5" xml:id="d111fn5">Documentation on
                                <persName corresp="#p_BH_1">Brown</persName>’s consultations is in
                                <ref target="frus1977-80v09">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1977–1980, vol. IX,
                                Arab-Israeli Dispute, August 1978–December 1980</ref> and <ref target="frus1977-80v18">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1977–1980, vol. XVIII,
                                Middle East Regional; Arabian Peninsula</ref>.</note> We are
                        determined to work with these nations and with others to put the peaceful
                        development of the region on a sound and a lasting foundation.</p>
                    <p>Recent disturbances in the region have underlined the need to work even more
                        urgently towards peace between Israel and its Arab neighbors. To this end,
                        Israeli and Egyptian negotiators, the Foreign Ministers of both countries,
                        will return to Camp David tonight at the invitation of the United
                            States.<note n="6" xml:id="d111fn6">Documentation on the meetings is in
                                <ref target="frus1977-80v09Ed2">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1977–1980, vol. IX,
                                Arab-Israeli Dispute, August 1978–December 1980</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>They will be meeting with Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Cyrus Vance</persName>. And I myself will do whatever I can to promote
                        the success of the Camp David negotiations. And if it should be necessary,
                        and the parties show adequate flexibility, I will call another summit
                        conference to work for peace.</p>
                    <p>I urge all leaders throughout the Middle East to recognize the vital
                        importance for their region for these talks to succeed.</p>
                    <p>For us in the United States, any crisis in the Middle East has the most
                        immediate and serious consequences. But we are also deeply concerned by what
                        is happening now in Southeast Asia. The same principles of American policy
                        apply: We support the independence and integrity of the regional nations; we
                        will stand by our friends; and we will continue as a nation to work for
                        peace.</p>
                    <p>Just in the last few weeks we’ve seen a Vietnamese invasion of Cambodia<note n="7" xml:id="d111fn7">See <ref target="#d108fn17">footnote 17, Document
                                108</ref>.</note> and, as a result, a Chinese frontier penetration
                        into Viet<pb facs="0597" n="556" xml:id="pg_556"/>nam.<note n="8" xml:id="d111fn8">See <ref target="frus1977-80v13#d205">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1977–1980, vol. XIII,
                                China, Documents 205</ref>–<ref target="frus1977-80v13#d207">207</ref>, <ref target="frus1977-80v13#d212">212</ref>, <ref target="frus1977-80v13#d214">214</ref>–<ref target="frus1977-80v13#d220">220</ref>.</note> Both actions threaten
                        the stability of one of the world’s most important and promising
                        regions—Southeast Asia.</p>
                    <p>We have opposed both military actions. Let me outline very briefly the
                        principles that govern our conduct.</p>
                    <p>First, we will not get involved in conflict between Asian Communist nations.
                        Our national interests are not directly threatened, although we are
                        concerned, of course, at the wider implications of what might happen in the
                        future and what has been happening in the past.</p>
                    <p>We are using whatever diplomatic and political means are available to
                        encourage restraint on all parties and to seek to prevent a wider war. While
                        our influence is limited, because our involvement is limited, we remain the
                        one great power in all the world which can have direct and frank discussions
                        with all the parties concerned. For this reason, we have a useful and
                        important role to play in the restoration of stability. We will continue our
                        efforts, both directly with the countries involved and through the United
                        Nations, to secure an end to the fighting in the region, to bring about a
                        withdrawal of Vietnam forces from Cambodia, and of Chinese forces from
                        Vietnam, and to gain the restoration of the independence and integrity of
                        all nations involved.</p>
                    <p>At the same time, we are continuing to express our deep concern that this
                        conflict may widen still further—with unforeseen and grave consequences for
                        nations in the region and also beyond.</p>
                    <p>In any event, the United States is fully prepared to protect the vital
                        interests of our people wherever they may be challenged. We are in close
                        consultation with our friends and allies in the region, especially the
                        members of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations, the <gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss> nations. Their continued stability and
                        prosperity are of great importance to us.</p>
                    <p>The normalization of relations between the United States and the People’s
                        Republic of China is already an accomplished fact and will not be reversed.
                        This was the simple, long overdue recognition of the reality of the
                        government in Peking.</p>
                    <p>In the last few days, we’ve consulted directly with leaders around the
                        world—and with our own congressional leaders, as well—about events both in
                        the Middle East and Southeast Asia. The responsibilities that we face are
                        serious, and they are shared by the administration and the Congress, by our
                        Nation, and our allies—and our common understanding and our adherence to a
                        common cause are vital.</p>
                    <p>All of us know that the internal affairs of Iran or combat even among
                        Communist nations are of concern to us. Many nations are trou<pb facs="0598" n="557" xml:id="pg_557"/>bled, even threatened by the turmoil in
                        Southeast Asia and in the Middle East. To stand by our friends and to help
                        meet their security needs in these difficult times, I will consult with the
                        Congress to determine what additional military assistance will be required.
                        This added measure of support is crucial for stability throughout the Indian
                        Ocean area.</p>
                    <p>And let me repeat, in the Middle East, in Southeast Asia, and elsewhere in
                        the world, we will stand by our friends. We will honor our commitments. And
                        we will protect the vital interests of the United States, and you can depend
                        on it.</p>
                    <p>As we face this immediate series of crises, we also look constantly to the
                        broader needs of security. If we are to meet our responsibilities, we must
                        continue to maintain the military forces we need for our defense and to
                        contribute to the defense of our allies.</p>
                    <p>This year, I have proposed a substantial real increase in the defense
                            budget.<note n="9" xml:id="d111fn9">See <ref target="#d109fn3">footnote
                                3, Document 109</ref>.</note> The events of recent weeks underscore
                        the responsibility of the Congress to appropriate these funds in full. There
                        must be no doubt that the people of the United States are fully prepared to
                        meet our commitments and to back up those commitments with military
                        strength.</p>
                    <p>Turmoil and crisis also underscore the vital needs to work wherever possible
                        to stabilize and to reduce competition in strategic nuclear weapons. This
                        effort has the same ultimate goals as does our strong defense—the goals of
                        security, stability, and peace. In pursuit of these goals, our Nation faces
                        no more important task this year than the successful conclusion of a
                        strategic arms limitation agreement.</p>
                    <p>Just as we work to support national independence and to aid our friends and
                        allies in times of trial, we must work to regulate nuclear arms capable of
                        threatening life throughout this planet. For a <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> agreement is a fundamental element of strategic and
                        political stability in a turbulent world—stability which can provide the
                        necessary political basis for us to contain the kinds of crises that we face
                        today, and to prevent their growing into a terrible nuclear
                        confrontation.</p>
                    <p>After more than 6 years of negotiations—conducted by three different
                        Presidents—agreement has now been reached on most of the major components of
                        a sound and verifiable <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II treaty.</p>
                    <p>The emerging agreement will establish for the first time equal numbers of
                        strategic arms for both sides. It will thus reverse the Soviet’s numerical
                        advantage which was temporarily established in the <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> I treaty of 1972, when they had about a 40-percent
                        built-in negotiated advantage.</p>
                    <pb facs="0599" n="558" xml:id="pg_558"/>
                    <p>To reach these new levels, the Soviets will be required to reduce their
                        overall number of strategic arms. Over 250 Soviet missiles or bombers—about
                        10 percent of their strategic forces—will have to be destroyed or
                        dismantled. At the same time, because we are now well below the agreed
                        ceiling, we could substantially increase our own operational strategic
                        forces.</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II agreement will also provide
                        negotiated limits on building new types of weapons and limits on the
                        improvement of existing ones—the so-called qualitative arms race can be
                        controlled.</p>
                    <p>
                        <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II will limit the size of land-based
                        missiles and the number of warheads that can be placed on them. Without
                        these limits, the Soviets could vastly increase the number of warheads on
                        their large land-based missiles—with grave implications to the strategic
                        balance. <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II will therefore contribute
                        to our ability to deal with the growing vulnerability of our land-based
                        missiles. Without it, the Soviet Union could continue to increase the number
                        of their warheads, tending to nullify our effort to protect our
                        missiles.</p>
                    <p>The agreement will also permit us and our allies to pursue all the defense
                        programs that we believe might eventually be needed—the <gloss target="#t_MX_1">M–X</gloss> missile; the Trident submarine and its
                        missiles; air, ground, and sea-launched cruise missiles; cruise missile
                        carrier aircraft; and a new penetrating bomber. These would be
                        permitted.</p>
                    <p>Thus <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II would allow our own prudent
                        programs to move ahead and also will place important limits on what the
                        Soviets might otherwise do. And this <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>
                        II agreement will be a basis for further negotiations for additional
                        substantial cuts in the level of nuclear armaments.</p>
                    <p>Without the <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II agreement, the Soviet
                        Union could have nearly one-third more strategic forces by 1985 than with
                            <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II. We would, of necessity, as a
                        nation, match such a buildup. The costs would be enormous, the risks
                        self-evident. And both nations would wind up less secure.</p>
                    <p>The stakes in <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> are too high to rely on
                        trust. Any <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II treaty that I sign will
                        be adequately verifiable, using our own independent means of guaranteeing
                        Soviet compliance with terms of the agreement.</p>
                    <p>
                        <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II will specifically forbid any
                        interference that would impede our ability to verify compliance with the
                        treaty. Any effort on the part of the Soviet Union to interfere with our
                        verification activities would be a detectable violation of the agreement
                        itself, and an early signal of any possible cheating.</p>
                    <p>Finally, let me put this agreement in the context of our overall relations
                        with the Soviet Union and the turbulence that exists in many parts of the
                        world. The question is not whether <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>
                        can be divorced from <pb facs="0600" n="559" xml:id="pg_559"/> this
                        complicated context. It cannot. As I have often said, our relationship with
                        the Soviet Union is a mixture of cooperation and competition. And as
                        President of the United States, I have no more difficult and delicate task
                        than to balance these two. I cannot and I will not let the pressures of
                        inevitable competition overwhelm possibilities for cooperation, any more
                        than I will let cooperation blind us to the realities of competition, which
                        we are fully prepared to meet.</p>
                    <p>Because this carefully negotiated and responsible arms control agreement will
                        make the world safer and more secure, it is in our national interest to
                        pursue it, even as we continue competition with the Soviet Union elsewhere
                        in the world. Therefore, I will seek both to conclude this new <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> agreement and to respond to any Soviet
                        behavior which adversely affects our interests.</p>
                    <p>To reject <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II would mean that the
                        inevitable competition in strategic nuclear arms would grow even more
                        dangerous. Each crisis, each confrontation, each point of friction—as
                        serious as it may be in its own right—would take on an added measure of
                        significance and an added dimension of danger. For it would occur in an
                        atmosphere of unbridled strategic competition and deteriorating strategic
                        stability. It is precisely because we have fundamental differences with the
                        Soviet Union that we are determined to bring this dangerous dimension of our
                        military competition under control.</p>
                    <p>In today’s world, it is vital to match the pursuit of ideals with the
                        responsible use of force and of power. The United States is a source of
                        both, ideals and power. Our ideals have inspired the world for more than two
                        centuries; and for three generations, since World War II, our power has
                        helped other nations to realize their own ideals.</p>
                    <p>The determination and strength of purpose of the American people are crucial
                        for stability in a turbulent world. If we stand together in maintaining a
                        steady course, America can protect its principles and interests and also be
                        a force for peace.</p>
                    <p>Americans have always accepted the challenge of leadership. And I am
                        confident that we will do so now.</p>
                    <p>Thank you very much.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>