<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>34. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Brzezinski) to President ) to President Carter</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d34</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">34</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-04-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-04-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">Development aid</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-04-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-04-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="34"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d34">
                <head>34. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>) to President <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJE2_1">Carter</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d34fn1">Source: Carter Library, National
                        Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Brzezinski Office File, Subject Chron
                        File, Box 125, Weekly National Security Report: 2–4/77. Top Secret;
                        Sensitive; Contains Codeword. <persName corresp="#p_CJE2_1"
                            >Carter</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MWF_1">Mondale</persName>
                        both initialed the memorandum.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-04-16">April 16, 1977</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Weekly National Security Report #9</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">1.</hi> Opinion</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Human Rights: For a Broader Interpretation.</p>
                <p>As I signaled to you, some elements in Congress are seizing on human rights as an
                    excuse for blocking constructive initiatives in the area of development aid or
                    at least as an opportunity for attaching all sorts of restrictive conditions on
                    such aid.<note n="2" xml:id="d34fn2">Presumable reference to bills and
                        amendments requiring U.S. representatives to the international financial
                        institutions (<gloss target="#t_IFIs_1">IFIs</gloss>) to vote against loans
                        to countries designated as human rights violators. See <ref
                            target="frus1977-80v02#d33">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1977–1980, vol. II, Human
                            Rights and Humanitarian Affairs, Documents 33</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1977-80v02#d35">35</ref>–<ref target="frus1977-80v02#d37"
                            >37</ref>.</note> Abroad, some see our concern as excessively rigid and
                    moralistic.</p>
                <p>Despite this, I believe that our affirmative commitment to human rights is not
                    only morally justified but is in keeping with historical trends, thereby giving
                    American foreign policy additional influence and associating America as a
                    society with a vital human concern. Otherwise, America runs the risk of being
                    perceived only as a consumption-oriented society, making us the focus both of
                    envy and of resentment.</p>
                <p>However, the point to stress is that human rights is <hi rend="italic">a broad
                        concept.</hi> These two words should mean much more than just political
                    liberty, the right to vote, and protection against arbitrary governmental
                    action. Human rights, and this we should stress, means also certain basic
                    minimum standards of social and economic existence. In effect, human rights
                    refers to all three (political, social, and economic) and this is why these
                    words have such universal appeal.</p>
                <p>Such a broader, and more flexible definition would have several advantages: it
                    would retain for us the desirable identification with a human cause whose time
                    has come, and yet it would avoid some of the rigidities that are potential in
                    the narrower political definition. It would give us the freedom to point at the
                    most glaring abuses (e.g., political suppression in some countries, or total
                    social indifference in others), <pb facs="0184" n="143" xml:id="pg_143"/> though
                    leaving us the necessary margin of flexibility in dealing with most governments.
                    In general, we should stress that achieving human rights <hi rend="italic">is a
                        process</hi> and that we are watching carefully progress toward greater
                    respect for human rights, realizing that there is no single standard for all the
                    countries of the world.</p>
                <p>I believe that all of the foregoing is implicit in what you have been saying, but
                    making some of these points more explicit may make it more difficult for your
                    critics to attack your position and for others to distort it into excessively
                    rigid and politically confining meanings.</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is information unrelated to foreign policy opinions.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
