<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-06-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-06-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="90" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d90">
                    <head>90. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                        Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>) to President
                            <persName corresp="#p_CJE2_1">Carter</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d90fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                            Brzezinski Material, Subject File, Box 26, Foreign Policy: 12/77–12/78.
                            Secret. The President initialed the top right-hand corner of the
                            memorandum. <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> sent the
                            memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_CJE2_1">Carter</persName> under a
                            June 19 note, indicating that 70 members of Congress would attend the
                            meeting and inquiring as to whether or not <persName corresp="#p_YAJ_1">Young</persName> should attend. According to the President’s Daily
                            Diary, the meeting took place in the East Room of the White House on
                            June 20 from 7:07 to 10:12 p.m. (Carter Library, Presidential Materials)
                            Although no record of the meeting has been found, an article in the <hi rend="italic">Chicago Tribune</hi> contains assessments of the
                            meeting from three participants: <persName corresp="#p_UMK_1">Udall</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_FDB_1">Fascell</persName>,
                            and <persName corresp="#p_SSJ_1">Solarz</persName>. (“<persName corresp="#p_CJE2_1">Carter</persName> displays united foreign policy
                            front,” June 21, 1978, p. 6) Attached but not printed is a list of
                            participants.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-06-19">June 19, 1978</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Congressional Foreign Policy Discussion</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                        <hi rend="roman">I.</hi> Your Conduct of the Meeting</p>
                    <p>1. Since this is clearly a meeting with the President, you should set the
                        tone for it through an opening statement, and then ask for only brief (5–10
                        minutes) supplementary comments by Cy, <persName corresp="#p_BH_1">Harold</persName>, and myself. I would urge you to <hi rend="italic">impose strict time constraints</hi> on your supporting cast. Otherwise
                        the Congressmen will feel “talked at” instead of being “talked with.”</p>
                    <p>2. Cy will be prepared to comment on the state of our key negotiations
                            (<gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>, Middle East, Southern Africa);
                            <persName corresp="#p_BH_1">Harold</persName> on our defense posture
                            (<gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>, and, if needed, <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>); I on the China trip or more generally
                        on broad global changes.</p>
                    <pb facs="0473" n="432" xml:id="pg_432"/>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                        <hi rend="roman">II.</hi> Your Overview</p>
                    <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Basic Message:</hi> Your basic commitment is to the
                        shaping of a more just and equitable international system for a world that
                        has now become more politically awakened (and you might mention the
                        emotional outpouring of the Panamanians as an example)<note n="2" xml:id="d90fn2">Presumable reference to the reception the President
                            received in Panama. <persName corresp="#p_CJE2_1">Carter</persName>
                            traveled to Panama June 16–17 in order to sign the protocol confirming
                            the exchange of documents ratifying the Panama Canal treaties.</note>
                        and that thus cannot be confined to a system dominated exclusively by the
                        developed countries. The world now includes more than 150 nation-states, and
                        their aspirations as well as participation require a wider framework. Unlike
                        the years 1945–1950, when America played a creative role in shaping the
                        post-World War II international system, this calls not for a predominantly
                        American response but for more subtle inspiration and cooperative leadership
                        on a broader front.</p>
                    <p>In effect, we are seeking to shape a cooperative global community, while
                        attempting to dampen the more traditional East-West conflicts and to resolve
                        the novel global and North-South issues.</p>
                    <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Your Ten Key Goals—and Our Performance</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Early in 1977 you set yourself ten key goals as a way of achieving a more
                        equitable international system.<note n="3" xml:id="d90fn3">See <ref target="#d36">Document 36</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2">
                        <row>
                            <cell>Your Key Goals</cell>
                            <cell>Response</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1. To engage Western Europe, Japan, and other advanced democracies
                                in closer political cooperation, thereby also providing wider
                                macroeconomic coordination among them.</cell>
                            <cell>The first Summit was quite useful; the second is about to be
                                    held;<note n="4" xml:id="d90fn4">See <ref target="#d92">Document
                                        92</ref>.</note> more frequent and more direct personal
                                top-level contacts and consultations than ever before (including
                                phone calls).</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>2. To weave a worldwide web of bilateral, political, and economic
                                cooperation with the new emerging regional powers, thereby extending
                                our earlier reliance on Atlanticism to include such newly
                                influential countries as Venezuela, Brazil, Nigeria, Saudi Arabia,
                                Iran, India, Indonesia in a wider pattern of international
                                cooperation.</cell>
                            <cell>Your two trips were designed to advance that goal;<note n="5" xml:id="d90fn5">See <ref target="#d60">Document 60</ref> and
                                        <ref target="#d60">footnote 4</ref>, <ref target="#d74fn4">Document 74</ref>.</note> the Vice President has recently
                                been to Indonesia; U.S. has better relations with all of those
                                mentioned than at any previous point.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="0474" n="433" xml:id="pg_433"/>
                        <row>
                            <cell>3. To exploit the foregoing in the development of more
                                accommodating North-South relations, both political and economic,
                                thereby reducing the hostility toward the United States that in
                                recent years has developed within the Third World.</cell>
                            <cell>We have made excellent progress politically; here especially
                                noteworthy is the breakthrough in Panama and the formulation of a
                                new policy towards Latin America, a policy no longer based on a
                                single slogan but one which recognizes both the importance of
                                bilateral relations with individual Latin American countries and the
                                global character of many of their concerns. However, so far we have
                                not done enough to formulate an economic policy dealing with
                                North-South problems.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>4. To push U.S.-Soviet strategic arms limitation talks into
                                strategic arms reduction talks, to widen the scope of
                                American-Soviet collaboration by engaging the Soviet Union in a
                                wider pattern of negotiating relationships, thereby making detente
                                both more comprehensive and reciprocal.</cell>
                            <cell>We have made progress on a wide range of bilateral issues and are
                                pressing to get <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>. At the same
                                time, we have finally made the Soviets aware that we are concerned
                                over their lack of restraint in the use of military proxies in
                                Africa. We do not expect the cold war to revive and we are prepared
                                both to compete and to cooperate simultaneously. At the same time,
                                we have developed more extensive relations with East European
                                states—both those externally independent and those internally more
                                liberal.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>5. To normalize U.S.-Chinese relations in order to preserve the
                                U.S.-Chinese relationship as a major stabilizing factor in the
                                global power balance.</cell>
                            <cell>We remain committed to such normalization; in the meantime we are
                                broadening the scope of our bilateral relations and have recently
                                held mutually useful global consultations.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>6. To seek a comprehensive Middle Eastern settlement, without
                                which the further radicalization of the Arab world and <pb facs="0475" n="434" xml:id="pg_434"/> the reentry of the Soviet
                                Union into the Middle East would be difficult to avoid.</cell>
                            <cell>The last year has been one of remarkable progress. We are
                                disappointed with the most recent Israeli answer, but will continue
                                to press for negotiations.<note n="6" xml:id="d90fn6">Presumable
                                    reference to the Israeli Cabinet’s decision on the occupied
                                    territories of the Gaza Strip and the West Bank. See Bernard
                                    Gwertzman, “U.S. Criticizes Israel but Plans to Press for
                                    Renewed Talks,” and William E. Farrell, “<persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> Says He Is Still
                                    ‘Optimistic’ On Peace Despite Israeli Response,” both <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, June 21, 1978, pp.
                                    A–1, A–4.</note> In the meantime, we are continuing our efforts
                                to draw the moderate Arabs into closer ties with the West.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>7. To set in motion a progressive and peaceful transformation of
                                South Africa and to forge closer cooperation with the moderate black
                                African countries.</cell>
                            <cell>We have made progress on Namibia and Rhodesia. Moreover, we have
                                established more positive relations with a larger number of African
                                countries. At the same time, we are concerned that the Soviet/Cuban
                                intrusion into Africa will interfere with our efforts to obtain
                                peaceful accommodation; moreover, African governments remain quite
                                vulnerable to such significant external military presence.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8. To restrict the level of global armaments and to inhibit
                                nuclear proliferation through international agreements as well as
                                unilateral U.S. acts.</cell>
                            <cell>We have now developed a policy of U.S. restraint on the sale of
                                    arms,<note n="7" xml:id="d90fn7">Presumable reference to <gloss target="#t_PD_1">PD</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>–13; see <ref target="#d40fn5">footnote 5,
                                        Document 40</ref>.</note> while the <gloss target="#t_INFCE_1">INFCE</gloss> program<note n="8" xml:id="d90fn8">See <ref target="#d56fn3">footnote 3, Document
                                        56</ref>.</note> is a very tangible response to what is now
                                increasingly recognized to be a genuine global problem.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>9. To enhance global sensitivity to human rights through pertinent
                                U.S. actions, comments, and example, thereby also seizing the
                                ideological initiative.</cell>
                            <cell>While progress has been uneven, there is not a continent which is
                                unaware of U.S. concerns; moreover, tangible progress has been made
                                in a number of Latin American and Asian countries. </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>10. To renovate the U.S. and <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> defense posture in</cell>
                            <cell>The recent <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> Summit reflects
                                tangible progress;<note n="9" xml:id="d90fn9">See <ref target="#d83">Document 83</ref>.</note> the</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="0476" n="435" xml:id="pg_435"/>
                        <row>
                            <cell>keeping with the requirements posed by the Soviet arms
                                buildup.</cell>
                            <cell>Long-Term Defense Program<note n="10" xml:id="d90fn10">
                                    <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> members attending the
                                    North Atlantic Alliance Washington summit (see footnote 9 above)
                                    agreed to a 15-year plan designed to modernize and improve
                                    military forces. (Kenneth H. Bacon, “<gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> Members Agree on Defense Plan, Differ on
                                    Approach to African Situation,” <hi rend="italic">The Wall
                                        Street Journal,</hi> June 1, 1978, p. 5)</note> is a
                                tangible expression, as is the reinforcement of the U.S.
                                commitment.</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                        <hi rend="roman">III.</hi> Four Likely Problem Areas</p>
                    <p>The legislators are likely to be most concerned with the state of U.S.-Soviet
                        relations; our African policy; the Middle East; and perhaps China.</p>
                    <p>I would suggest the following comments:</p>
                    <p>1. <hi rend="italic">U.S.-Soviet relations:</hi> Our long-term objective
                        remains constant: to prevent the spread of Soviet influence, to reduce the
                        risk of nuclear confrontation with the Soviet Union, and to increasingly
                        assimilate the Soviet Union in wider international cooperation. The recent
                        public exchanges were necessary to convince the Soviets that we are serious
                        about our concerns, namely that the Soviet Union is overly inclined to use
                        its growing military power to exert political pressure and particularly to
                        exploit Third World turbulence, thereby preventing moderate solutions to
                        international problems. We have repeatedly tried through private
                        correspondence to convince Brezhnev that we are serious. Your speech
                        reaffirmed our commitment to a detente based increasingly on mutual
                        restraint and on reciprocity.<note n="11" xml:id="d90fn11">See <ref target="#d87">Document 87</ref>.</note> We want to draw the Soviet
                        Union into a wider fabric of international cooperation.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Africa:</hi> Our central objective is the creation of
                        majority rule governments and elimination of racial oppression. At the same
                        time, we want to avoid a situation in which East-West and North-South
                        conflicts intersect. This is precisely why we object so strongly to the
                        Soviet/Cuban intrusion. It makes moderate solutions more difficult to
                        achieve and it runs the risk of transforming difficult regional problems
                        into graver international conflicts. We would like the Africans,
                        particularly acting through the <gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss>, to
                        resolve African problems themselves.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Middle East:</hi> You might express cautiously your
                        disappointment at the recent Israeli response. Any peaceful solution must be
                        based on the complete application of <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                        Resolution 242. I would suggest you simply ask the legislators for their
                        advice, without being too specific on what we might do next.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">China:</hi> You might make the point that we remain
                        committed to normalization, and that in the meantime it is in our mutual
                        benefit to <pb facs="0477" n="436" xml:id="pg_436"/> widen the scope of our
                        global cooperation. You might mention that I specifically told Chairman
                            <persName corresp="#p_HG_2">Hua</persName> on your behalf that we seek
                        closer relations with China for long-term strategic reasons and not because
                        of any tactical expediency. How fast we move on normalization depends on our
                        ability to negotiate successfully some of the outstanding issues; it also
                        depends on Congressional attitudes, and here asking for their advice may
                        also be the best way to deal with the issue.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>