<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-01-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-01-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="130" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d130">
                        <head>130. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d130fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                                Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 78,
                                Country Files, Europe, <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>. Top Secret; Sensitive. The
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff extracted this
                                discussion of <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> from a
                                memorandum of conversation of the entire meeting, which covered a
                                range of topics. The memorandum of conversation, which was sent to
                                Nixon under a January 28 memorandum, is printed in <ref target="frus1969-76v13#d105">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume
                                    XIII, Soviet Union, October 1970–September 1971, Document
                                    105</ref>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1971-01-28">January
                                    28, 1971</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Anatoliy F. Dobrynin</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I told <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> that we had not
                            really had a formal reply to our proposition,<note n="2" xml:id="d130fn2">See <ref target="#d124">Document 124</ref>.</note>
                            and yet it was quite important that we have one. We had to make
                            Congressional presentations on <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> and
                            the <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> and we had to prepare for the
                            next meeting in Vienna. It was therefore quite important that we know
                            Soviet intentions.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said, speaking off the
                            record, it was important for me to understand that <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> presented the Soviets with tough
                            bureaucratic problems. It was very hard for them to handle it since they
                            have no lateral clearances in their bureaucracy. He therefore thought it
                            would be helpful if I would formulate the proposition in the form of an
                            unsigned Note Verbale which he could transmit to Moscow in order to
                            elicit a response. I said to <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> that, for a response to be helpful to us, it
                            should be forthcoming in the next week or two. He said he would transmit
                            the question to Moscow.</p>
                        <p>Next <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said that he had,
                            however, a number of other questions of some interest. He said if he had
                            understood me correctly, I was <pb facs="0434" n="399" xml:id="pg_399"/>
                            proposing a freeze on offensive deployments—specifically, land-based
                            missiles—in return for a formal <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss>
                            agreement. I said that was correct. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> then said that this might present some problem
                            with respect to silos that had already been started but had not yet been
                            completed. Would the Soviet Union be permitted to complete the silos
                            that were started? It would be hard for the Soviet bureaucracy to accept
                            the losses of resources involved in an unfinished silo. I said I could
                            not give him a clear answer, but I was certain that this would be
                            considered a reasonable question to which we would try to find some
                            response. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said it had
                            occurred to him that one way of handling the problem would be to put the
                            date at which no further construction could take place at some point in
                            the future—say, January 1st of next year. If that were done, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said, this would enable them
                            to finish; they would simply have to pay the price for those that were
                            not finished by then. I said as soon as he was authorized to discuss
                            these issues concretely I would be prepared on my side with a formal
                            position.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> then asked me how we
                            were going to conclude the <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>
                            arrangement if he and I talked. I said if he and I could agree in
                            principle to proceed along the lines that we had discussed,—that is to
                            say, a formal <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> agreement coupled with
                            an offensive freeze—then I would suggest that the President make a
                            speech early in March in which he puts forward this as an idea and the
                            Soviet Union could respond to it positively. Vienna would then implement
                            the agreement. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> asked
                            whether we would, together with the speech, plan a formal démarche to
                            the Soviet Government. I said we had really not thought the matter
                            through, and we would be very receptive to their suggestion. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said that, given the way the
                            Soviet bureaucracy worked, it would be helpful to have a formal record
                            in addition to whatever the President might say publicly, and to have
                            that formal material part of the record before the speech was made. I
                            said I did not believe this would present an insuperable obstacle.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>