<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>98. Memorandum for the Record</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-07-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-07-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recr08QgEMEm1Bk04" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-07-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-07-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="98"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d98">
                <head>98. Memorandum for the Record<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d98fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> Files, Box 879, <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>,
                            <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> talks (Vienna), Vol. XII, July
                        20–September 1970. Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-07-24">July 24, 1970</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Report for the President’s file on his meeting with Senators <persName
                            corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> and Tower on Thursday, July 23 at
                        4:00 p.m.</item>
                </list>
                <p>The President met with Senators Tower and <persName corresp="#p_JHM1"
                        >Jackson</persName> to discuss Safeguard vote count and strategy.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d98fn2">From July 8 through August 6 the Senate debated the
                        administration’s request for a $759.1 million authorization to begin
                        deployment and continue research on the Safeguard system. On August 6 the
                        Senate approved the request by roll-call votes of 50–51 and 49–51. (<hi
                            rend="italic">Congress and the Nation</hi>, Vol. III, 1969–1972, p.
                        197)</note> Present, in addition to the President, were Senators <persName
                        corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> and Tower, Secretary of Defense
                        <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Mel Laird</persName>, Chuck Colson and <persName
                        corresp="#p_BK1">Ken BeLieu</persName>.</p>
                <p>After a brief discussion of Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM1"
                        >Jackson</persName>’s campaign in Washington, the President began by giving
                    a background on the <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> program, the increased
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> missile threat, what the Soviet
                    buildup means and the importance of the <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> vote
                    to <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>.</p>
                <p>The various anti-<gloss target="#t_MIRV1">MIRV</gloss> amendments were also
                    discussed. The President pointed out that it is interesting to note that the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> won’t discuss this subject at the
                        <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>.</p>
                <p>The President said those of us sitting here in the White House, at this time,
                    have a very momentous responsibility because if we don’t act with vigilance and
                    strength we may see the United States become a second-rate power. <persName
                        corresp="#p_JHM1">Scoop Jackson</persName> said second-rate isn’t good
                    enough in today’s world.</p>
                <p>The President said, “Let’s get down to the vote count.” It was agreed that we had
                    approximately 50 votes against 48 in the opposition depending whether Margaret
                        <persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName> was present to vote. Several
                    potential soft votes were discussed. Cotton being one and <persName
                        corresp="#p_AGW1">Anderson</persName> another.<note n="3" xml:id="d98fn3"
                        >Senators Margaret Chase <persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName>
                        (R–ME), Norris Cotton (R–NH), and <persName>Clinton Anderson</persName>
                        (D–NM).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Consensus was that it would be helpful if the President called Cotton. He said,
                    “Oh, I’d just as soon have him down.” I pointed out that Cotton was in New
                    Hampshire and the President said he would call him from California and also have
                    him down later perhaps. (Chuck Colson has sent to San Clemente a telephone
                    recommendation to the President reminding him of the call to Cotton.)</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Scoop Jackson</persName> said <persName
                        corresp="#p_AGW1">Anderson</persName>’s physical situation was such that we
                    couldn’t depend on his memory. He thought the President didn’t <pb facs="0358"
                        n="323" xml:id="pg_323"/> have to ask <persName corresp="#p_AGW1"
                        >Anderson</persName> to the White House; but that a phone call from
                    California would be sufficient. <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Scoop
                        Jackson</persName> will talk to <persName corresp="#p_AGW1"
                        >Anderson</persName> first and let us know when he thinks the President
                    should call him. (<persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> says today,
                    July 28 that he has talked with <persName corresp="#p_AGW1">Anderson</persName>
                    and that the President should not call him until just before the vote.)<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d98fn4">The statements in parentheses at the end of some of
                        the paragraphs, which describe subsequent actions, were apparently added at
                        a later date.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Tower said we have to check with the two Jordan’s. <persName corresp="#p_JHM1"
                        >Scoop</persName> will check with B. Everett Jordan of North Carolina and
                    Tower will check Len Jordan of Idaho. The President said, “I could call them if
                    you want me to.” And Tower said, “Well, let us check first and we’ll see.”</p>
                <p>The possibility of pairing Senator Mundt<note n="5" xml:id="d98fn5">Karl Mundt
                        (R–SD).</note> was discussed and considered to be most desirable in order to
                    secure an additional insurance. The most likely possibility would be to pair
                    Mundt with <persName corresp="#p_PC2">Percy</persName> (or perhaps Pearson).
                    Tower is going to pursue this and <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Scoop</persName>
                    is going to talk with <persName corresp="#p_PC2">Percy</persName> on <gloss
                        target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>. (<persName corresp="#p_PC2">Percy</persName>
                    has already approached <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Scoop</persName> on the
                    subject of <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>.)</p>
                <p>The President suggested that it would be desirable to have <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWP1">Bill Rogers</persName> also talk to <persName
                        corresp="#p_PC2">Percy</persName> on the idea of pairing with Mundt. (Dave
                    Abshire has been given this info.)</p>
                <p>Both <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> and Tower said that they
                    would make sure that we had 48 hour notice before the final vote on Safeguard in
                    order to insure Tom Dodd and <persName>Dick Russell</persName>’s<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d98fn6">
                        <persName>Thomas Dodd</persName> (D–CT) and <persName>Richard
                            Russell</persName> (D–GA).</note> presence. <persName corresp="#p_LMR1"
                        >Mel Laird</persName> agreed we’d need to send an aircraft for them if
                    necessary.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Scoop Jackson</persName> brought up the possibility
                    of an executive session and Tower said we might need an executive session in
                    order to use the classified <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> information
                    available within <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Scoop Jackson</persName>’s
                    Subcommittee. The President suggested that maybe the <persName corresp="#p_SGC1"
                        >Gerry Smith</persName> memorandum on <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss>
                    could be used and would have an impact on <persName corresp="#p_PC2"
                        >Percy</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Scoop</persName> said, “I
                    think the information in my Committee is probably stronger than <persName
                        corresp="#p_SGC1">Gerry</persName>’s but in any event if we go to executive
                    session, I think we can emphasize to some of the doubting Thomases the
                    importance of the Safeguard vote on <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>.”</p>
                <p>The President asked, “Why is it so difficult to convince some of these Senators
                    of the facts that are so obvious to us?” <persName corresp="#p_JHM1"
                        >Scoop</persName> responded that some of the opponents are just so
                    pro-Russian that they are actually disappointed and feel that Russia let them
                    down by building more missiles. One had come to him and said, “It just can’t be
                    true that the Russians continued building <gloss target="#t_SS91">SS 9</gloss>’s
                    and <gloss target="#t_SS111">SS 11</gloss>’s.”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Scoop</persName> further said that Russian personnel
                    from the Embassy in Washington were all over the Hill probing Senators and
                    Senator’s <pb facs="0359" n="324" xml:id="pg_324"/> staffs—not looking for
                    information on hardware but trying to ascertain the state of the Senate’s
                    mind.</p>
                <p>Tower pointed out that certain Senate Staffers were in a daily contact with
                    Russian Embassy people and socializing with them.</p>
                <p>One of the Senators suggested it would be good if the FBI could take a good look
                    at this. (Chuck Colson to discuss w/<persName corresp="#p_HHR1"
                        >Haldeman</persName>.)</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> pointed out that it was not easy to
                    understand why Defense personnel were challenged when they went on the Hill to
                    explain Defense programs and yet no one challenged the Russian Embassy personnel
                    when they lobbied for a foreign power on the Hill. For example, two Defense
                    officers were recently called upon because they had tried to sell Defense
                    programs on the Hill. <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> said, “Why
                    don’t some of our Senators demand the resignation of Soviet individuals who are
                    lobbying on the Hill?”</p>
                <p>In discussing <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Scoop</persName>’s staff, Dorothy
                    Fosdick’s strong and staunch support to the President’s program came up. And the
                    President said to Chuck Colson, “Make certain that she gets invited to a social
                    evening at the White House.”</p>
                <p>The President emphasized that winning the <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss>
                    vote will not only have a salutary effect on <gloss target="#t_SALT1"
                        >SALT</gloss> but also on the Middle East situation. He said it isn’t a
                    question of being belligerent with Russia, it’s just the fact that the Russians,
                    simply and only, understand strength and conviction. We have to show this.</p>
                <p>There was discussion of when the <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> vote should
                    come up and <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> pointed out that it
                    would be good to have it over with before the argument started on
                        McGovern–Hatfield.<note n="7" xml:id="d98fn7">The amendment proposed by
                        Senators <persName>George McGovern</persName> (D–SD) and Mark Hatfield
                        (R–OR) required the termination of military operations and the complete
                        withdrawal of <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S</gloss>. forces from Vietnam by
                        December 31, 1971. On September 21, 1970, the <gloss target="#t_US1"
                            >U.S</gloss>. Senate rejected the amendment by a vote of 55–39. (H.R.
                        17123)</note> All agreed to this however Tower pointed out that the
                    Democrats control the schedule and we’d have to play it by ear.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> described his Committee amendment
                    on the Mideast (see copy attached)<note n="8" xml:id="d98fn8">Attached but not
                        printed is Sec. 501, which stated in part that “in order to restore and
                        maintain the military balance in the Middle East,” the President was
                        authorized to transfer aircraft to counteract military assistance provided
                        by the Soviet Union to countries in the Middle East.</note> and it was
                    agreed that we should get it voted up or down—and on the record.</p>
                <p>The President said this kind of a vote at this particular time would be helpful
                    in the negotiations.</p>
                <p>He also strongly emphasized that it would be folly, as some recommend,
                    unilaterally to agree to limit <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> without an
                    agreement on <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss>’s and other strategic
                    systems.</p>
                <pb facs="0360" n="325" xml:id="pg_325"/>
                <p>There was general discussion on what part the Israeli Ambassador might play.
                        <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Scoop</persName> will talk to the Israeli
                    Ambassador and tell him informally, not for attribution, of <persName
                        corresp="#p_JHM1">Scoop</persName>’s amendment and the importance of the
                        <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> vote. He will impress on the Ambassador
                    the fact that the credibility of the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S</gloss>.
                    world-wide military posture is in itself a deterrent and has a major impact on
                    the Mideast situation.</p>
                <p>The meeting adjourned at 5:05 p.m.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BK1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Kenneth E. BeLieu</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Deputy Assistant to the President</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
