<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>107. Telegram From the Embassy in Algeria to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d107</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">107</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1981-06-17T13:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1981-06-17T13:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwtK4pWGzcpfduJ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">USCINCEUR</term>
                    <term ref="recfDPXugH8GvkDjP" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085264"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Defense policy</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">C–130</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Strategic balance</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119735"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Self-determination</term>
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Logistics</term>
                    <term ref="rec7XCpI38AIhVpLJ" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Regional issues</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Detente</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recaCPsAUbblCdB8K" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092233"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Non-alignment</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="arms-transfers"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91001417"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arms sales</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="rec9ptkWICFUk7Mvu" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="arms-transfers">Arms
                        Transfer Policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1981-06-17T13:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1981-06-17T13:30:00-05:00" n="107"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d107">
                <head>107. Telegram From the Embassy in Algeria to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d107fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Foreign Policy File, Electronic Telegrams, D810284–0872. Secret; Immediate;
                        Exdis. Sent for information to Cairo, Moscow, Lagos, Nouakchott, Rabat, and
                        Paris. Sent for information Immediate to Tunis.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">2309.</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Algiers</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1981-06-17T18:30:00+00:00">June 17, 1981, 1830Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Department please pass <gloss target="#t_SECDEF_1">SecDef</gloss> and <gloss
                        target="#t_USCINCEUR_1">USCINCEUR</gloss>. Tunis also for DepSecDef
                        <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName>. Subject: Deputy
                    Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName> Visits
                    Algeria.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>(<gloss target="#t_C_1">C</gloss>—Entire text.)</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Summary. DepSecDef <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName>
                        visited Algiers June 16–17 for discussions with the Algerian Government. At
                        both the <gloss target="#t_MOD_1">MOD</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_MFA_1"
                            >MFA</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName>
                        briefed senior officials on U.S. defense policy and its regional
                        implications and described U.S. concern over Libyan activities. His <gloss
                            target="#t_MOD_1">MOD</gloss> interlocutor avoided a substantive
                        response on these <pb facs="0274" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"/> issues, but
                        raised instead his hopes for further sales of AMC trucks and his expectation
                        that the end-use assurances the U.S. is awaiting regarding <gloss
                            target="#t_C130_1">C–130</gloss> aircraft will soon be transmitted.
                            <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName>’s <gloss
                            target="#t_MFA_1">MFA</gloss> interlocutor indicated Algerian
                        understanding of the need for strategic balance, stressed Algeria’s desire
                        for good relations with the U.S., criticized U.S. sales of arms to Morocco
                        without restrictions, and called for an end to the Western Sahara conflict
                        through negotiations and self-determination. On Libya, he described the
                        threat it poses to the region as overestimated, dismissing such operations
                        as the Gafsa affair<note n="2" xml:id="d107fn2">Reference is to the January
                            26–27, 1980, commando raid by Libyans and Tunisian rebels on Tunisian
                            Government installations in Gafsa. See <ref
                                target="frus1977-80v17p3#d204fn2">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. XVII, Part
                                3, North Africa, footnote 2, Document 204</ref>.</note> as worthy of
                        a cheap detective novel. Libyan assistance to the Polisario, he said, was
                        fully under Algeria’s control. However, Libya’s arsenal was indeed a matter
                        for concern, as was the possibility of union between Chad and Libya. For
                        this reason, Algeria was collaborating with Nigeria to find a formula for
                        the departure of Libyan troops. We found <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1"
                            >Carlucci</persName>’s visit valuable as a demonstration of U.S.
                        interests in high-level dialogue, as an opportunity for the U.S. to set
                        forth its defense policies, and as an occasion for the <gloss
                            target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> to reiterate its desire for a cautious
                        expansion of ties and acknowledge certain aspects of the Libyan danger. End
                        summary.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Deputy Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1"
                            >Carlucci</persName> visited Algiers June 16–17 to continue the
                        administration’s political and military dialogue with Algeria. In the
                        absence of Foreign Minister Benyahia and <gloss target="#t_MFA_1"
                            >MFA</gloss> Secretary-General Dembri in France and of <gloss
                            target="#t_MOD_1">MOD</gloss> Secretary-General Belloucif in the U.S.,
                        the visit and program were approved at the very last minute, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName> was received by middle-level
                        officials of the Ministries of Defense and Foreign Affairs in their
                        capacities as Acting Secretaries-General. Although President <persName
                            corresp="#p_BC_1">Bendjedid</persName> was purported to be out of town
                        and did not receive <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName>, and
                        although the <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> was unable to provide any
                        formal hospitality, both of the meetings held were extremely cordial, and
                            <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName>’s interlocutors
                        apologized repeatedly for the absence of their principals.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>In a 40-minute meeting with Acting <gloss target="#t_MOD_1">MOD</gloss>
                        Secretary-General and Director of Logistics <gloss target="#t_COL_1"
                            >Col.</gloss> Abdelmalek Guenaizia and in a 90-minute meeting with
                        Acting <gloss target="#t_MFA_1">MFA</gloss> Secretary-General and Director
                        of Western European and North American Affairs <persName corresp="#p_BS_2"
                            >Saadeddine Benouniche</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1"
                            >Carlucci</persName> reviewed U.S. defense policy, emphasizing the
                        commitment of the <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName>
                        administration to strengthening national defense in the face of an erosion
                        of the strategic balance and a change in Soviet military policies and the
                        resulting need for the U.S. to build up its capacity for flexible response
                        through, among other things, cooperation with like-minded governments.
                            <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName> stressed that the
                            <pb facs="0275" n="236" xml:id="pg_236"/> forces and capabilities
                        developed in the process were not meant for intervention in the internal
                        affairs of other states or in purely regional disputes. Specifically, the
                        development of further collaboration with Morocco was taking place in the
                        context of U.S. global strategy, not in response to any regional or local
                        dispute. <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName> took the
                        occasion of both meetings to describe heightened U.S. concern for Libyan
                        adverturism. Although he indicated he had no formula to propose for dealing
                        with this disturbing phenomenon, he invited Algerian views on the
                        subject.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>At the <gloss target="#t_MOD_1">MOD</gloss>, Guenaizia (who was clearly
                        not authorized to address broad issues of foreign or military policy and
                        kept glancing at a major introduced as the new Director of External
                        Relations for reassurance) limited himself to a review of the two pending
                        issues in military sales—AMC trucks and <gloss target="#t_C130_1"
                            >C–130</gloss> aircraft. On the truck sale, Guenaizia said the <gloss
                            target="#t_MOD_1">MOD</gloss> was extremely satisfied with the
                        negotiations and U.S. approval and indicated the first purchase of 1,300
                        units was likely to be merely a beginning. On <gloss target="#t_C130_1"
                            >C–130</gloss> aircraft, Guenaizia said the end-use restrictions being
                        discussed in Washington posed no problems to the <gloss target="#t_GOA_1"
                            >GOA</gloss>, and the assurances the U.S. desired would be forthcoming
                        “very soon”. On broader political and military issues, Guenaizia made no
                        substantive response, although he kept nodding understandingly throughout
                            <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName>’s presentation. He
                        limited his response on Libya to several nods and a broad smile. (Comment:
                        This is the first time a <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> official has
                        initiated a discussion of the <gloss target="#t_C130_1">C–130</gloss> sale
                        in Algiers. That this should occur so soon after President <persName
                            corresp="#p_BC_1">Bendjedid</persName>’s visit to Moscow demonstrates
                        the seriousness with which the <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> is
                        approaching this sale.)</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>At the <gloss target="#t_MFA_1">MFA</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_BS_2"
                            >Benouniche</persName> responded to <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1"
                            >Carlucci</persName>’s remarks with a well organized and well reasoned
                        presentation of Algeria’s view of world and regional issues. Although he
                        broke no new ground except on Libya, the following points of his
                        presentation were noteworthy: <list>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>Algeria is fully aware that the continued independence to which it
                                and other small states aspire requires detente and the absence of
                                superpower confrontation. This in turn requires a strategic balance
                                between the two superpowers which it is not appropriate for Algeria
                                to pass judgement on. (Comment: Nowhere did <persName
                                    corresp="#p_BS_2">Benouniche</persName> take issue with U.S.
                                efforts to restore military equilibrium vis a vis the Soviet Union;
                                indeed, in an airport discussion with the Charge after <persName
                                    corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName>’s departure, he went
                                so far as to say Algeria understands the reasons for U.S. actions in
                                this field.)</item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>The genuine non-alignment to which Algeria aspires requires good
                                relations with the U.S., and Algeria is heartened whenever new areas
                                of collaboration are found.</item>
                            <pb facs="0276" n="237" xml:id="pg_237"/>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>Algeria understands fully the traditional good relations that
                                exist between the U.S. and Morocco. What it cannot understand is the
                                change in U.S arms sales policy that took place in November 1979 and
                                by which Morocco was furnished weapons specifically for use against
                                the Polisario outside its internationally recognized
                                boundaries.</item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>Algeria seeks proper decolonization of the Western Sahara through
                                negotiations between the warring parties and through the
                                internationally-sanctioned method of self-determination. To do
                                otherwise sets a bad precedent for Africa by bringing inherited
                                borders into question. Algeria fears the continuation of the
                                conflict for two reasons: (a) under certain circumstances, it could
                                escalate into a wider conflict; (b) it threatens the stability of
                                Morocco, and Algeria is keenly aware of the need for stability
                                there.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>On Libya, <persName corresp="#p_BS_2">Benouniche</persName> went somewhat
                        further than <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> interlocutors have gone in
                        the past. He began by excluding Libya’s intervention in Chad<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d107fn3">Reference is to Libya’s December 1980 invasion and
                            current occupation of northern Chad.</note> as a special case and went
                        on to minimize the gravity of the Libyan threat in its other manifestations,
                        expressing the view that the destabilizing threat Libya poses to the region
                        has been overestimated. As an example of the absence of danger or serious
                        purpose to be found in Libyan adventures, he cited the Gafsa raid, whose
                        scenario (an armed attack by 40 men on a city of 200,000 some 600 kilometers
                        from the capital in the expectation that this would lead to a wide-scale
                        revolution) he described as worthy of a cheap detective novel.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Libya’s role in the Western Sahara conflict, <persName corresp="#p_BS_2"
                            >Benouniche</persName> affirmed, is not an independent one. While it
                        supports the Polisario, it can go no further. To do so would be to challenge
                        Algeria, and this it cannot do. Morocco may try to exploit Libya’s present
                        unsavory image to obscure these facts, but this is simply a maneuver to
                        relegate Morocco’s own intervention in Mauritania into the background.
                        Algeria does not believe Libya has the capacity to get the upper hand in the
                        Western Sahara issue to change the substance of the problem.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Chad, he said, is a different problem. The absence of any state structure
                        had helped give the impression that the Libyan intervention had been a
                        massive, effective operation, but this was not as true as it seemed. In any
                        case, no one in Africa had really found the Libyan intervention at the
                        request of the Lagos Accord, which Algeria continues to support, a really
                        dramatic development.<note n="4" xml:id="d107fn4">Reference is to the August
                            21, 1979, peace agreement between the warring factions in the Chadian
                            Civil War, which created the Gouvernement d’Union Nationale de
                            Transition (<gloss target="#t_GUNT_1">GUNT</gloss>), or Transitional
                            Government of National Unity.</note> The announcement of Chadian-Libyan
                        union was an entirely different matter, one on which <pb facs="0277" n="238"
                            xml:id="pg_238"/> Algeria had taken a clear position. Unions cannot be
                        achieved in this manner; they must be authentic expressions of the wishes of
                        each country. When they take place in the presence of military forces, this
                        is annexation. Algeria has been working and continues to work with Nigeria
                        to find a solution based on a formula leading to the departure of Libyan
                        troops from Chad. Since, in Algeria’s view, Libya intervened for its own
                        motives, not on behalf of “other parties”, a solution can be found in a
                        regional setting.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>In give-and-take following <persName corresp="#p_BS_2"
                            >Benouniche</persName>’s remarks, <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1"
                            >Carlucci</persName> indicated that the <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1"
                            >Reagan</persName> administration indeed has revised U.S. arms transfer
                        policy to make it responsive to overall U.S. interests in the national
                        security field,<note n="5" xml:id="d107fn5">In telegram 84780 to all
                            diplomatic posts, April 3, the Department informed the posts that “the
                            administration is in the process of revising U.S. conventional arms
                            transfer policy to make it more responsive to the new security
                            challenges we face and more supportive of our military, political and
                            economic interests.” (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File,
                            Electronic Telegrams, D810157–1195)</note> but stressed that in
                        Morocco’s case this did not mean a change in policy on the issue of the
                        Western Sahara. The U.S. continues to urge a peaceful solution on its
                        Moroccan friends. While the Moroccan military now appears to have greater
                        confidence in itself and in its role, the Moroccan Government also appears
                        to be more willing to negotiate on the Western Sahara issue. However, it is
                        not appropriate for outside powers like the U.S. to make value judgements on
                        the basis of such impressions. It is to be hoped that the Nairobi summit
                        conference of the <gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> will start the
                        parties on the road to a peaceful solution.<note n="6" xml:id="d107fn6"
                            >Reference to the Organization of African Unity meeting held in Nairobi
                            in June.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName> also reiterated U.S.
                        concern over the size and continuing growth of Libya’s arsenal, again
                        indicating he had no formula to propose to deal with this troubling trend.
                            <persName corresp="#p_BS_2">Benouniche</persName> responded that indeed
                        Libya’s sizeable arsenal could pose a problem. Algeria had noted U.S.
                        concern over this arsenal as expressed during the visit of General <persName
                            corresp="#p_WVAD_1">Walters</persName> in April, and, when it shared
                        with the U.S. its view that Libya was not a worrisome factor, it limited
                        this evaluation to Libya’s activities, not its arsenal.<note n="7"
                            xml:id="d107fn7">See <ref target="#d105">Document 105</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>When a member of <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName>’s
                        delegation raised the existence of some difficult-to-verify reports that
                        Libya’s support for the Polisario was growing rapidly and might prove an
                        obstacle to a peaceful solution, <persName corresp="#p_BS_2"
                            >Benouniche</persName> responded that Libya did not have the logistical
                        capability to move in this direction. Only two routes were possible—the
                        existing trans-Algerian route and a theoretical Niger-Mali-Mauritania route.
                        Algeria was firmly in control of the first, while the second was
                        impractical.</item>
                    <pb facs="0278" n="239" xml:id="pg_239"/>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>Comment: The <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> appears to have taken a
                        calculated risk in approving this visit in the full knowledge that top
                        leadership would be absent. It had to balance its desire to avoid giving a
                        negative signal against the danger of leaving its visitors with the
                        impression they were not getting their due. In spite of the absence of
                            <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> principals, however, the visit was
                        valuable as a demonstration of U.S. interest in continued high-level
                        dialogue, as an opportunity for the U.S. to set forth its defense policies
                        and their regional implications, and as an occasion for the <gloss
                            target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> to reiterate its desire for a cautious
                        expansion of ties, notably in the military field, and acknowledge for the
                        first time (albeit guardedly) the dangers that Libya presents. It is an
                        interesting coincidence that Algeria nominated its first defense attaché in
                        Washington on the very day of <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1"
                            >Carlucci</persName>’s visit.</item>
                    <label>14.</label>
                    <item>We are not certain why President <persName corresp="#p_BC_1"
                            >Bendjedid</persName> did not receive <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1"
                            >Carlucci</persName>. It may be that he did not wish to see him because
                        he is a principal of the Department of Defense and such a meeting would have
                        made too much too soon of Algerian-American military relations. It may,
                        however, simply be that the <gloss target="#t_MFA_1">MFA</gloss> failed to
                        coordinate preparations for the visit adequately. We had several indications
                        large and small that it had failed to do anything until the very last
                        minute, and a Presidential call may have proven impossible to arrange on
                        that basis.</item>
                    <label>15.</label>
                    <item>In the absence of ministerial or presidential calls, the Algerian press
                        was extremely restrained in announcing the visit June 16. A small front-page
                        item in “El Moudjahid” simply noted that “in the framework of an orientation
                        trip (tournee d’information) in the Mediterranean region, U.S. Deputy
                        Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Frank
                            Carlucci</persName> is visiting Algeria from June 16 to 17. During his
                        visit, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName> will have
                        discussions with Algerian officials.” This short item has already caused
                        foreign journalists in Algiers to call us for more details, but we have
                        limited ourselves to saying that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1"
                            >Carlucci</persName> is visiting a number of countries in the
                        Mediterranean region for discussions on issues of mutual interest on the
                        bilateral, regional, and world scene. We suspect the Soviet Embassy would
                        gladly give us several cases of vodka for a fuller report.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RCWS_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Ross</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
