<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>239. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern
                    and South Asian Affairs (Murphy) to Secretary of State ) to Secretary of State
                    Shultz</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d239</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">239</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1985-05-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1985-05-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1985-05-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1985-05-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="239"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d239">
                <head>239. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern
                    and South Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MRWD_1">Murphy</persName>) to
                    Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d239fn1">Source: Reagan Library, <persName
                            corresp="#p_SGP_1">George Shultz</persName> Papers, Official Memoranda
                        (05/02/1985–05/06/1985). Secret. Sent through <persName corresp="#p_AMH_1"
                            >Armacost</persName>. Drafted on April 30 by Robert Barrett (<gloss
                            target="#t_NEAAFN_1">NEA/AFN</gloss>); cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_ZD_1">Zweifel</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_NT_1"
                            >Nassif</persName>, and in substance by Loustanou (<gloss
                            target="#t_DOC_1">DOC</gloss>) and Savitt (<gloss target="#t_DOD_1"
                            >DOD</gloss>). Neither <persName corresp="#p_MRWD_1">Murphy</persName>
                        nor <persName corresp="#p_AMH_1">Armacost</persName> initialed the
                        memorandum. A stamped notation at the top of the memorandum reads: “GPS.”
                            <persName corresp="#p_MKB_1">McKinley</persName> also initialed the
                        memorandum and wrote: “3 May.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1985-05-03">May 3, 1985</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Morocco—Suggested Letter From You to King Hassan</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">ISSUE FOR DECISION</hi>: Whether you should send a letter to
                    King Hassan following his request for postponement of the Joint Economic and
                    Military Commission meetings.<note n="2" xml:id="d239fn2">In telegram 3946 from
                        Rabat, April 26, <persName corresp="#p_RJV_1">Reed</persName> reported that
                        King Hassan had decided to postpone the <gloss target="#t_JMC_1">JMC</gloss>
                        and <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> meeting scheduled to take place May
                        7–10, which reflected his “fears that Commission meetings without tangible
                        results would aggravate growing problems of perception in the bilateral
                        relationship.” (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File, Electronic
                        Telegrams, D850292–0342)</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">DISCUSSION</hi>: Among the steps Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_RJV_1">Reed</persName> recommended to deal with present strains
                    in our relationship with Morocco is a letter from you to the King, acknowledging
                    and expressing understanding for his decision to request postponement of the
                    Joint Economic and Military Commission meetings, which were to have taken place
                    in Washington May 7–10. We agree with the Ambassador that such a letter is in
                    order. Attached is a draft for your consideration (TAB 1). It contains a few
                    changes from Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RJV_1">Reed</persName>’s suggested
                    draft, made to remove any encouragement for Hassan to involve himself in the
                    Middle East peace process, (which we consider might be counterproductive), or
                    any commitment by you to participate in or meet with the Joint Commissions when
                    they eventually convene.</p>
                <p>For your information, Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1"
                        >Weinberger</persName> has already sent a message to Hassan.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d239fn3">No record of <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1"
                            >Weinberger</persName>’s message has been found.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">RECOMMENDATION</hi>: That you approve the cable message and
                    sign the original (to be pouched to Rabat) at TAB 1.<note n="4" xml:id="d239fn4"
                        >Below this recommendation, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>
                        wrote: “OK G.” A stamped notation next to this reads: “May 6 1985.”</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0538" n="499" xml:id="pg_499"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Tab 1</hi>
                    </note>
                    <head>Telegram From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1"
                            >Shultz</persName> to the Embassy in Morocco<note n="5" xml:id="d239fn5"
                            >Secret; Immediate; Exdis. Drafted by Barrett; cleared by [illegible]
                            and Hill; approved by <persName corresp="#p_MKB_1">McKinley</persName>.
                            Sent for information to the Department. <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1"
                                >Shultz</persName> was in Bonn for the Economic Summit and to
                            accompany <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> on his state
                            visit to the Federal Republic of Germany.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <gloss target="#t_SECTO_1">Secto</gloss> 9016.</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Bonn</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1985-05-06T01:17:00+00:00">May 6, 1985, 0117Z</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Message From Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>
                            to King Hassan.</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="references">
                        <head>Ref:</head>
                        <item>Rabat 4002.<note n="6" xml:id="d239fn6">In telegram 4002 from Rabat,
                                April 29, <persName corresp="#p_RJV_1">Reed</persName> stated “I
                                strongly recommend that you acknowledge and express understanding
                                for King Hassan’s recent decision to postpone the Joint Economic and
                                Joint Military Commission meetings in Washington for several months”
                                and proposed a draft message from <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1"
                                    >Shultz</persName> to Hassan. (Department of State, Central
                                Foreign Policy File, Electronic Telegrams, D850297–0715)</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>1. Secret—Entire text</p>
                    <p>2. Please deliver following message from Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> to King Hassan. Signed original
                        being pouched.</p>
                    <p>3. Begin text:</p>
                    <p>Your Majesty:</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RJV_1">Reed</persName> has conveyed to me
                        your decision to postpone for several months the meetings of the
                        U.S.-Moroccan Joint Economic and Joint Military Commissions which were
                        scheduled to be held in Washington from May 7–10.</p>
                    <p>The postponement of these meetings should, in no case, detract from the
                        considerable importance which we continue to attach to the Joint Military
                        and Economic Commissions as valuable catalysts for strengthening bilateral
                        cooperation in these areas between our two countries. We will continue to
                        address this issue in the light of the close relationship which exists
                        between our two countries and the value we place upon our association.</p>
                    <p>We look forward to receiving your government’s suggestions regarding
                        appropriate new dates for the holding of these meetings, and I am confident
                        a mutually agreeable schedule can be established.</p>
                    <p>Please accept, Your Majesty, the assurance of my highest respect for your
                        leadership and for the historic friendship and bonds which unite Morocco and
                        the United States. Sincerely yours, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">George P.
                            Shultz</persName>.</p>
                    <p>His Majesty</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HII_1">Hassan II</persName>,</p>
                    <p>King of Morocco,</p>
                    <p>Rabat. End text.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">
                                <hi rend="strong">Shultz</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
