<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1987-02-19T13:22:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1987-02-19T13:22:00-05:00" n="266" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d266">
                        <head>266. Telegram From the Embassy in Morocco to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d266fn1">Source: Department
                                of State, Executive Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss>
                                Records, 1987 Nodis Telegrams: Lot 95D26, Rabat 1987 Nodis. Secret;
                                Nodis.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">1745.</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Rabat</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1987-02-19T18:22:00+00:00">February 19, 1987, 1822Z</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Dept pass White House and <gloss target="#t_SECDEF_1">SecDef</gloss>. For
                            the Secretary and <gloss target="#t_NEA_1">NEA</gloss> Asst Secy
                                <persName corresp="#p_MRWD_1">Murphy</persName> from Ambassador.
                                <gloss target="#t_SECDEF_1">SecDef</gloss> for <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1">Weinberger</persName> from Ambassador. White
                            House for <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> from Ambassador. Subject:
                            Renewed Offer for U.S. Air Base in Morocco.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>(<gloss target="#t_S_1">S</gloss>—Entire text).</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In a meeting with the Foreign Minister to discuss U.S.
                                representation for the Fête du Trone.<note n="2" xml:id="d266fn2">Reference is to Morocco’s Feast of the Throne, which celebrates
                                    the day of the enthronement of the King in 1933 in defiance of
                                    French colonial rule. During King Hassan’s reign (1969–1999),
                                    the Fête occurred on March 3.</note> I advised that Treasury
                                Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BJAIII_1">Baker</persName> would be
                                head of delegation. After explaining arrival and departure dates. I
                                asked the Foreign Minister to give us some idea of what plans the
                                King has for the delegation. He advised that he would speak with the
                                King and try and give us a notional schedule.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>He then asked me how our negotiations with the Spanish were going
                                and why it was important to keep the 401st in Madrid.<note n="3" xml:id="d266fn3">In telegram 1514 from Madrid, February 5, the
                                    Embassy summarized the most recent round of negotiations between
                                    the United States and Spain over basing and military aid, which
                                    took place in Madrid February 3–4. (Department of State, Central
                                    Foreign Policy File, Electronic Telegrams, D870425–0247,
                                    D870090–0295) Documentation is scheduled for publication in <ref target="frus1981-88v08"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. VIII, Western Europe,
                                        1985–1988</ref>.</note> I explained that there had been hard
                                bargaining and an insistence by the Spanish that the U.S. presence
                                be reduced due to the commitments made by Gonzales in the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> referendum.<note n="4" xml:id="d266fn4">Reference is to the national referendum held on
                                    March 13, 1986, on whether or not Spain should remain in <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>. Spanish citizens voted to
                                    remain in <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>.</note>
                                <persName corresp="#p_FA_1">Filali</persName> then asked why we
                                didn’t just move the base to Morocco. He reiterated conversation
                                between Hassan and Defense Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1">Weinberger</persName>.<note n="5" xml:id="d266fn5">See Tab A,
                                    Document 265.</note> I asked the Minister whether King Hassan
                                was prepared to make a firm commitment to basing the 401st in
                                Morocco subject to negotiations should a decision be made to leave
                                Spain and come to Morocco. His answer was a firm yes. I explained
                                that our obvious strong preference was to keep the 401st in Madrid
                                and that if that was not possible we would consider other locations
                                in Europe and elsewhere, including the possible return to the
                                U.S.</item>
                            <pb facs="0592" n="553" xml:id="pg_553"/>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>I mentioned Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BM_1">Bargach</persName>’s discussions with <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss><note n="6" xml:id="d266fn6">No record of these
                                    discussions has been found.</note> as a follow-up to Hassan’s
                                statement to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1">Weinberger</persName> that Morocco was interested in an oil
                                barter deal for F–16’s. He told me he knew of no present Arab source
                                of funding.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The Minister mentioned that he understood President <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> would be visiting Italy in
                                May or June for a State visit. I told him that I understood that it
                                was in connection with the economic summit.<note n="7" xml:id="d266fn7">Reference is to the 1987 G–7summit scheduled to
                                    take place in Venice in early June.</note> While he did not
                                press me further, the implication was that it may be a good time for
                                the President to pass through Morocco for a brief stop. I did not,
                                however, suggest that possibility.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_FA_1">Filali</persName> remarked that the
                                invitation to the King for a visit in 1987 had not yet been
                                extended. I explained that we were considering a convenient date and
                                remarked that this summer was a possibility. I told the Foreign
                                Minister that since Hassan would be going to London July 14–17 it
                                might make sense for him to thereafter go to Washington in time to
                                celebrate the bicentennial anniversary.<note n="8" xml:id="d266fn8">Reference is to the ceremony marking the bicentennial of the
                                    U.S.-Moroccan Treaty of Peace and Friendship.</note> I also
                                explained that I did not have an indication that those dates were
                                open for an official working visit but if he thought that was a good
                                idea I would pursue it. The Foreign Minister wholeheartedly
                                supported that suggestion and said he would feel out Hassan on the
                                question.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Comment: It appears clear that Hassan’s offer to <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1">Weinberger</persName> on basing in Morocco
                                was not made lightly. The Moroccans see many advantages inuring to
                                their benefit by both the offer of a base in Morocco and the
                                possible acceptance of that offer by the United States.<lb/>It is
                                also clear that the Moroccans are becoming somewhat sensitive that
                                in the year of the bicentennial the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> has neither extended the invitation to the King nor
                                offered a major celebration of that anniversary in the U.S. I
                                strongly urge that Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BJAIII_1">Baker</persName> have in hand an invitation from the President
                                to make an official working visit the week of July 20, 1987. I also
                                urge that if there are any new programs or additional aid
                                contemplated for Morocco, that the Secretary announce them during
                                his visit.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>End comment.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_NT_1"><hi rend="strong">Nassif</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>