<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-04-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-04-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="294" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d294">
                        <head>294. Intelligence Memorandum Prepared in the Central Intelligence
                                Agency<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d294fn1">Source: Central
                                Intelligence Agency, Office of the Director of Central Intelligence,
                                Job 83M00035R, Box 17, C–384, Tunisia. Secret; [<hi rend="italic">handling restrictions not declassified</hi>]. Prepared in the
                                Maghreb Branch, Arab-Israeli Division, Office of Near East/South
                                Asia Analysis, Central Intelligence Agency, using information
                                available as of April 23.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">NESA M#82–10152</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-04-23">April 23, 1982</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">TUNISIAN PRESIDENTIAL SUCCESSION [<hi rend="italic">portion
                                marking not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p rend="center">Summary</p>
                        <p>Tunisia’s aging President <persName corresp="#p_BH_4">Habib
                                Bourguiba</persName> is spending less time directing policy,
                            although he continues to dominate it. <persName corresp="#p_BH_4">Bourguiba</persName>’s wife Wassila and various ministers,
                            including <persName corresp="#p_BH_4">Habib Bourguiba</persName>, Jr.,
                            will continue to compete with Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MM_2">Mzali</persName> for power and influence in the period preceding
                                <persName corresp="#p_BH_4">Bourguiba</persName>’s departure.<note n="2" xml:id="d294fn2">In telegram 2752 from Tunis, April 8, the
                                Embassy reported: “Although the Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MM_2">Mohamed Mzali</persName> has had his ups and
                                downs, the regime is probably stronger now than when he took office
                                two years ago. He has been the prime force behind Tunisia’s process
                                of political liberalization.” The Embassy continued: “Despite their
                                somewhat ambivalent relationship, <persName corresp="#p_MM_2">Mzali</persName> retains <persName corresp="#p_BH_4">Bourguiba</persName>’s support as the best qualified Tunisian
                                to lead the country once <persName corresp="#p_BH_4">Bourguiba</persName>’s rule ends.” (Department of State,
                                Central Foreign Policy File, Electronic Telegrams,
                                D820186–0124)</note> Although these individuals exert varying
                            degrees of influence, [<hi rend="italic">3 lines not declassified</hi>].
                            The resulting inconsistencies have encouraged a government of sycophants
                            and have alienated labor and political opposition groups seeking reform.
                                [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] the
                            slogans of the ruling Destourian Socialist Party are seen as
                            increasingly irrelevant by Tunisia’s youthful population. [<hi rend="italic">portion marking not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>When <persName corresp="#p_BH_4">Bourguiba</persName> departs the scene,
                            the Prime Minister, currently <persName corresp="#p_MM_2">Mohamed
                                Mzali</persName>, is the constitutionally designated successor for
                            the remainder of the current National Assembly term which runs to
                            November 1986. The timing of the succession will be a crucial factor in
                                <persName corresp="#p_MM_2">Mzali</persName>’s ability to
                            consolidate his position and to win his first presidential election.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MM_2">Mzali</persName>’s success in gaining
                            support and respect from the ruling party, labor, and opposition groups
                            will determine the duration of his time in office. [<hi rend="italic">portion marking not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>Although Tunisia’s military expenditures are increasing, the military
                            remains small and apolitical. It will probably be loyal to any legal
                            successor. Widespread popular revolt is also unlikely. [<hi rend="italic">portion marking not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <pb facs="0650" n="611" xml:id="pg_611"/>
                        <p>Tunisian foreign relations under <persName corresp="#p_MM_2">Mzali</persName> would emphasize the country’s nonaligned and
                            pro-Arab status. Neither <persName corresp="#p_MM_2">Mzali</persName>
                            nor other presidential contenders would align Tunisia with the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. Tunisia almost certainly will
                            continue to look to the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and Western
                            Europe for military support and economic investment. [<hi rend="italic">portion marking not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is the body of the memorandum.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>