<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>98. Telegram From the Embassy in Algeria to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1981-01-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1981-01-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMNSn3ulaoClE2c" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86002124"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Hostage</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001519"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recaCPsAUbblCdB8K" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092233"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Non-alignment</term>
                    <term ref="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134112"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Terrorism</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recmuOYE0cUMJaVom" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">North-South dialogue</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">C–130</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Cultural exchanges</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="disability-rights" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="disability-rights">handicapped</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1981-01-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1981-01-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="98"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d98">
                <head>98. Telegram From the Embassy in Algeria to the Department of State<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d98fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Foreign
                        Policy File, Electronic Telegrams, D810038–0924. Secret; Immediate;
                        Exdis.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">399.</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Algiers</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1981-01-26"
                            >January 26, 1981, 1840Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>The Implications of the Hostage Agreement for U.S.-Algerian
                        Relations.</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>(Secret—entire text.)</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Summary. The <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> probably accepted the
                        role of intermediary in the hostage crisis primarily to protect “the Iranian
                        revolution”, to enhance Algeria’s role as a peacemaker, to strengthen the
                        international position of Algerian diplomacy and the domestic position of
                            <persName corresp="#p_BC_1">Bendjedid</persName> and Benyahia, and to
                        change Algeria’s image in the U.S. and in the <persName corresp="#p_WFJB_1"
                            >West</persName>, bilateral issues were probably of secondary concern,
                        although the <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> undoubtedly hopes that its
                        new image will yield it benefits over time. In discharging what is
                        essentially a moral obligation, the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> may
                        wish to consider a number of steps: renewal of <persName corresp="#p_BC_1"
                            >Bendjedid</persName>’s invitation to visit the U.S., a rapid resumption
                        of <gloss target="#t_LNG_1">LNG</gloss> negotiations, action on military
                        training proposals, and a number of other initiatives, some easy, some not.
                        End summary.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>In discussing their efforts in the hostage crisis with us, Algerian
                        officials have stressed humanitarian aspects, and we understand <gloss
                            target="#t_MFA_1">MFA</gloss> officials have been told not to respond to
                        questions about Algeria’s mediation except with general statements about its
                        humanitarian concerns. However, the <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss>
                        probably undertook the role of intermediary in the hostage crisis for a
                        number of reasons, among which we see: <pb facs="0252" n="213"
                            xml:id="pg_213"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>(A)</label>
                            <item>A strong commitment to protect and support “the Iranian
                                revolution” which Algerians see as similar in many ways to their own
                                struggle for independence. In this context, the <gloss
                                    target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> probably saw the continuing
                                hostage crisis as dangerous because it (1) invited renewed U.S.
                                military action in Iran, (2) could have led the U.S. toward support
                                for Iraq, (3) hampered the emergence of strong domestic political
                                institutions in Iran, and (4) tempted the Soviet Union to continue
                                exploiting Iranian weakness and the possibility of U.S. military
                                action.</item>
                            <label>(B)</label>
                            <item>A commitment of principle to the resolution of regional disputes
                                of a strongly destabilizing nature. Since the Soviet invasion of
                                Afghanistan, the <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> has been
                                sensitive to the destabilization of the Gulf/Indian Ocean region,
                                and it probably saw the hostage mediation as contributing to
                                stability and opening the way to the resolution of other conflicts,
                                particularly the Iran-Iraq conflict.</item>
                            <label>(C)</label>
                            <item>A strong desire to re-establish the importance of Algerian
                                diplomacy, in the world at large and in the Third World in
                                particular. Since the death of <persName corresp="#p_BH_3"
                                    >Boumédiène</persName>
                                <note n="2" xml:id="d98fn2">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BH_3">Houari Boumédiène</persName>, the
                                    second President of Algeria, a proponent of Western Saharan
                                    self-determination and of non-alignment in foreign policy, died
                                    in 1978.</note> and the appointment of Benyahia as Foreign
                                Minister, Algerian diplomacy has achieved some modest success on the
                                Western Sahara issue and on relations with France, but there has
                                been no initiative or success spectacular enough to give the
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BC_1">Bendjedid</persName> regime and its
                                Foreign Minister their own place in the sun. Now, <persName
                                    corresp="#p_BC_1">Bendjedid</persName> and Benyahia are clearly
                                established on the world scene, and the Boumédiène/Bouteflika<note
                                    n="3" xml:id="d98fn3">Abdelaziz Bouteflika, Algerian Minister of
                                    Foreign Affairs from 1965 to 1978.</note> legacy has been
                                clearly relegated to the past. <persName corresp="#p_BC_1"
                                    >Bendjedid</persName> has been strengthened as President, and
                                Benyahia has been strengthened as Foreign Minister. With the
                                exception of the pro-Moscow Marxists, all elements of the Algerian
                                body politic have probably seen something in Algeria’s role to
                                praise. “Progressive” leftists such as Yahiaoui probably saw this
                                role as supportive of Iran. “Liberals” such as Algeria’s technocrats
                                probably saw it as a natural opening to the <persName
                                    corresp="#p_WFJB_1">West</persName>. The middle-of-the road
                                nationalist majority, including most of the military, probably saw
                                it as a healthy reaffirmation of Algeria’s place in the world and of
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BC_1">Bendjedid</persName>’s place in
                                Algeria.</item>
                            <label>(D)</label>
                            <item>A desire to change Algeria’s image in the <persName
                                    corresp="#p_WFJB_1">West</persName> in general and the U.S. in
                                particular. The <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> has been
                                working hard to make its policy of non-alignment a truly genuine
                                one, and is convinced that the only way to do this is to enjoy good
                                relations with both superpowers. In this context, it has been
                                hampered by its outdated image as a “radical” state that always
                                supported the Eastern bloc and lost no opportunity to attack the
                                    <persName corresp="#p_WFJB_1">West</persName>, even to the
                                extent of supporting certain forms of international terrorism.
                                Without changing its rhetoric, the <gloss target="#t_GOA_1"
                                    >GOA</gloss> has gradually taken specific policy actions to
                                alter its course and its image. <pb facs="0253" n="214"
                                    xml:id="pg_214"/> Its mediation effort is the latest of these
                                actions, and perhaps the most eloquent.</item>
                            <label>(E)</label>
                            <item>A growing commitment of the rules of international diplomacy and
                                genuine shock and embarrassment at the actions of the “Iranian
                                revolution” in this domain.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> probably does not expect anything
                        directly from the U.S. as a result of its mediatory role, and it is not
                        likely to make any specific request linked to the hostage agreement. It
                        knows that, now that the hostages have been released, it has little leverage
                        on us beyond that conferred by our intangible moral debt. It is not going to
                        come to us and say “stop selling weapons to Morocco” or “pay more for <gloss
                            target="#t_LNG_1">LNG</gloss>” instead, it will hope that its improved
                        image in the U.S. will make it possible for U.S. policymakers to respond
                        positively as it tries to strengthen its non-alignment and to respond with
                        understanding as it pursues its national interests in the region and in the
                        world.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The obvious terrain on which the <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> will
                        hope to elicit more cooperation from U.S. policymakers is military. The
                            <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> has standing requests for training
                        and equipment which it has justified explicitly in terms of lessening its
                        dependence on the Soviet Union. It undoubtedly hopes that its new image will
                        make it possible for U.S. policymakers to respond positively in spite of
                        continuing disagreement on some areas of bilateral and regional
                        affairs.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> will also hope to elicit a more
                        truly neutral U.S. policy on the Western Sahara. In recent months, it has
                        increasingly come to fear that the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>
                        would support King Hassan in anything he did because of the idealized
                        reputation he enjoys as America’s friend. Now, the <gloss target="#t_GOA_1"
                            >GOA</gloss> will hope that it too will be seen as ready to collaborate
                        with the U.S. on certain (but by no means all) issues and will thus also
                        have a claim on America’s friendship. Such friendship would, in the <gloss
                            target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss>’s view, argue for the U.S. to find ways to
                        support King Hassan short of espousing his claims to the Western Sahara in
                        theory or in practice.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Other issues such as the Middle East crisis and the North-South dialogue,
                        while important to Algeria, are not current issues of burning concern in
                        Algerian-American bilateral relations, and in any case the <gloss
                            target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> certainly understands that American policy
                        on such fundamental questions cannot be guided by considerations related to
                        U.S. relations with Algeria.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Against the background, we believe it would be in the U.S. interest to
                        demonstrate our gratitude and our desire to improve relations by taking
                        several of the following actions, some of which should not be difficult
                        provided we do not renounce the accords through which the hostages were
                        freed: <pb facs="0254" n="215" xml:id="pg_215"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>A)</label>
                            <item>Renew the invitation issued to President <persName
                                    corresp="#p_BC_1">Bendjedid</persName> by President <persName
                                    corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> to visit the United
                                    States.<note n="4" xml:id="d98fn4">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> extended the
                                    invitation to <persName corresp="#p_BC_1">Bendjedid</persName>
                                    in a February 9, 1979, letter. For text of the letter, see <ref
                                        target="frus1977-80v17p3#d71">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol.
                                        XVII, Part 3, North Africa, Document 71</ref>.</note> Such a
                                gesture would not only demonstrate our gratitude over Algeria’s role
                                in the hostage crisis, but would also show that the new
                                administration is interested in the Third World and would encourage
                                the trend toward more moderation by a key non-aligned leader. This
                                would be particularly important given reported plans for <persName
                                    corresp="#p_BC_1">Bendjedid</persName> to visit the Soviet Union
                                as early as this March.</item>
                            <label>B)</label>
                            <item>Promptly put forward a new proposal in the <gloss
                                    target="#t_LNG_1">LNG</gloss> price negotiations,<note n="5"
                                    xml:id="d98fn5">See <ref target="#d99">Document 99</ref>.</note>
                                one which would be as forthcoming as possible but consistent with
                                our fundamental criteria based on market factors. The most recent
                                round of talks in Washington appeared to show such a new U.S.
                                proposal is possible.</item>
                            <label>C)</label>
                            <item>Authorize cash sale of some military training, thus improving our
                                ties to the dominant element in the Algerian political system. This
                                proposal has already been considered with some care within the
                                Department of State, but no decision has been taken.</item>
                            <label>D)</label>
                            <item>Consider the sale of <gloss target="#t_C130_1">C–130</gloss>
                                aircraft to Algeria, as the <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> has
                                previously requested and we had previously shelved.<note n="6"
                                    xml:id="d98fn6">In telegram 327 from Algiers, January 29, 1980,
                                    the Embassy informed the Department about Algeria’s request to
                                    purchase <gloss target="#t_C130_1">C–130</gloss> aircraft.
                                    (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File, Electronic
                                    Telegrams, D800051–0664) In telegram 56446 to Algiers, March 1,
                                    1980, the Department informed the Embassy that “time is not rpt
                                    not propitious for <gloss target="#t_C130_1">C–130</gloss>
                                    sale.” (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                    Electronic Telegrams, D800108–0312)</note> This would admittedly
                                be a difficult policy decision.</item>
                            <label>E)</label>
                            <item>Promptly act to facilitate <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss>
                                rental of purchase of a much-needed larger Chancery in Washington.
                                We have held up such action pending resolution of a property dispute
                                in Algiers, but could now go ahead in Washington and trust the
                                    <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> to arrive at a fair
                                settlement of our claim in Algiers. This gesture would be especially
                                pleasing to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MR_1">Malek</persName>,
                                one of the three Algerian negotiators.</item>
                            <label>F)</label>
                            <item>Expand educational and cultural exchanges particularly by offering
                                additional Fulbright scholars and facilitating an exhibition of
                                Algerian arts and crafts in the U.S.</item>
                            <label>G)</label>
                            <item>Review our decision not to participate in the 1981 Algiers
                                International Fair (i.e., institute the biennial cycle of attendance
                                agreed informally with the Department of Commerce in 1981 instead of
                                1982).</item>
                            <label>H)</label>
                            <item>Invite Minister of Planning Brahimi and his senior subordinates to
                                Washington for a symposium organized by the Department of Commerce
                                on business opportunities in Algeria following approval of <pb
                                    facs="0255" n="216" xml:id="pg_216"/> the new five-year plan
                                (Brahimi and his colleagues participated in such a symposium in
                                London following Queen Elizabeth’s visit to Algeria).</item>
                            <label>I)</label>
                            <item>Consider participation in the reconstruction of the El Asnam
                                region through grant aid to private voluntary agencies such as
                                Catholic Relief Services for assistance to the handicapped and the
                                orphaned.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>The above are preliminary ideas. We will be happy to elaborate on any of
                        them at the Department’s request.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Haynes</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
