<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-11-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-11-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="279" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d279">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Japan)/11–1346</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Assistant Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hilldring</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director of the Civil Affairs Division, War
                                Department</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Echols</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-11-23">November 23, 1946</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear General Echols</hi>: There is enclosed a
                            draft message to the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers summarizing
                            a statement by the Soviet Representative on the Far Eastern Commission
                            with reference to the question of the execution of the purge directive
                            of January 4, 1946.<note n="47" xml:id="d279fn1"><gloss target="#t_Scapin1">Scapin</gloss>–550, <hi rend="italic">Political Reorientation of Japan</hi>, p. 482.</note></p>
                        <p>In view of the fact that this matter is now under discussion in the Far
                            Eastern Commission and an urgent reply is desired, it is requested that
                            the enclosed draft message be transmitted by the War Department to the
                            Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers by cable.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed>J. H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Hilldring</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Draft Telegram for General of the Army Douglas
                                    MacArthur</hi></head>
                            <p>On November 4, 1946, the Soviet representative on the <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> submitted a statement with regard
                                to the question of the execution of the purge directive of January
                                4, 1946. Basing his comments on a summary of the purge prepared by
                                the <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> of State and circulated to
                                the <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss>, the Soviet representative
                                stated that the Soviet group did not feel that up to the present the
                                Japanese Govt had fully carried out the directive of the Supreme
                                Commander in spite of the fact that the directive was to be
                                fulfilled six months from January 4, 1946.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>I.</label>
                                <item>The Soviets stated that the U.S. report “admitted that ‘as of
                                    29 July 1946 remained to be screened about 1000 officials of 165
                                    corporations, in various fields.’ These corporations, as it was
                                    further pointed <pb facs="0378" n="366" xml:id="pg_366"/> out,
                                    are to be purged ‘because their largest stockholders are
                                    national policy companies.’” [It should be noted that the U.S.
                                    report reads as follows and gives a different impression than
                                    when read out of context: “As of 29 July 1946 there remained to
                                    be screened about 1000 officials of 165 corporations in various
                                    fields. These corporations are not Government-owned or
                                    controlled, but under a more rigorous application than
                                    originally employed they have been added to the list because
                                    their largest stockholders are national policy companies. This
                                    group represents an addendum to rather than a residue of the
                                    original program.”]<note n="48" xml:id="d279fn2">Statement in
                                        brackets in the original draft.</note></item>
                                <label>II.</label>
                                <item>The Soviets pointed to the following statement in the U.S.
                                    report as evidence of incompleteness of purge: “In the
                                    Demobilization Board (formerly the First and Second
                                    Demobilization Ministries) are about 4000 officials who have not
                                    been screened. These are all former Army and Navy officers
                                    subject to mandatory removal under Category ‘B’ of Appendix ‘A’
                                    but are listed in formal requests of the Japanese Govt to
                                    continue their employment as provided in paragraph 8 of <gloss target="#t_Scapin1">SCAPIN</gloss> 550 in order to carry out
                                    the repatriation, demobilization and re-absorption into civilian
                                    life of the approximately 1,500,000 Japanese military personnel
                                    who are still overseas.”</item>
                                <label>III.</label>
                                <item>The Soviets stated that they were in possession of some data
                                    that there were still in the House of Representatives 18 members
                                    who were elected through bribery and other violations of the law
                                    and that the results of the “inquests” of these Diet members
                                    were still unknown. Among them are the following members of the
                                    Liberal Party: Ida Tomohei, Arafune Seijiro, Makino Kansaku,
                                    Hiroaka Ryozo; Progressive Party: Sekine Kyuzo, Abe Shungo; non
                                    party: Zushi Yasumasa and others.</item>
                                <label>IV.</label>
                                <item>The Soviets stated that there were certain members of the
                                    House of Representatives who had compromised themselves due to
                                    their association with the militarists and their activity in the
                                    Imperial Rule Assistance Association during the war. As
                                    described by the Soviets they are:<list>
                                        <item>Matsuda Shoichi—former adviser to the Imperial Rule
                                            Assistance Association and in 1942 elected to the Diet
                                            on the recommendations of the IRAA;</item>
                                        <item>Inukai Ken—former economic adviser to the Wang
                                                Ching-wei<note n="49" xml:id="d279fn3">Chinese head
                                                of Japanese-sponsored regime in occupied China
                                                during World War II.</note> Government and one of
                                            the leaders of the “House for Development of
                                            Asia”;</item>
                                        <item>Tahara Haruji—Administrator of New Guinea during the
                                            war; chief of the second section of the Department of
                                            South Seas in the Navy Department; in 1942 recommended
                                            by the Imperial Rule Political <pb facs="0379" n="367" xml:id="pg_367"/> Association to Diet; and follower
                                            of ideology for alliance of the Axis powers and for the
                                            undermining of the relations with the Allied
                                            Powers.</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <label>V.</label>
                                <item>In view of this statement the Soviet delegation has proposed
                                    that the following policy decision be presented to the <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> for its consideration: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <list>
                                            <item>“1. To consider the fulfillment of the <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>’s purge directive
                                                of January 4, 1946, by the Japanese Government as
                                                unsatisfactory.</item>
                                            <item>“2. To formulate a policy decision according to
                                                which the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers
                                                could issue a directive to the Japanese Government
                                                to accelerate the complete fulfillment of the purge
                                                directive in the nearest future.</item>
                                            <item>“3. To recommend that the Supreme Commander for
                                                the Allied Powers delete paragraph 8 of his
                                                directive 550 of January 4, which permits the
                                                Japanese Government under the pretext of
                                                ‘irreplaceability’ to keep in public office persons
                                                which who fall undoubtedly under the purge directive
                                                of January 4.”</item>
                                        </list></quote></item>
                                <label/>
                                <item>The Supreme Commander is requested to comment, particularly on
                                    paragraphs I to IV and reply as soon as feasible.</item>
                            </list>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>