<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Max W. Bishop, of the Office of the Political Adviser in Japan, to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d333</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">333</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-03-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-03-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recfstIIL5scNKk3A" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                    <term ref="recQt10IdeXz66A6d" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="personnel-foreign-service"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005831"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign Service</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-03-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-03-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="333"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d333">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.94/3–2646</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Max W. Bishop</persName>, of the
                        Office of the Political Adviser in Japan, to the <gloss type="to">Secretary
                            of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 325</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-03-26">March 26,
                            1946</date>.<lb/>[Received April 2.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to this Office’s
                    despatch no. 98, December 13, 1945, enclosing memorandum of conversation with
                    Prince Konoye <pb facs="0434" n="422" xml:id="pg_422"/> on November 7,
                        1945,<note n="59" xml:id="d333fn1">Despatch No. 98 not printed; for
                        memorandum, see <ref target="frus1945v06#pg_955">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 955</ref>.</note> during the course of
                    which Konoye offered the following description of developments leading up to the
                    fall of his Cabinet in October 1941: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Through informal but entirely reliable information the Prime Minister
                            (Prince Konoye) learned that the Japanese Navy was far from confident of
                            Japanese ability to wage a successful war against the United States and
                            that the real desire of the most important leaders in the Japanese Navy
                            was to avoid war. The Army and General Tojo were also informed of this
                            basic attitude on the part of the Navy. On October 13 or 14, 1941, the
                                <hi rend="italic">Gummu Kyoku Cho</hi> (Chief of the Military
                            Affairs Bureau) of the Army went to the Chief Secretary of the Cabinet
                            and told the latter that the Army would not give up its idea of
                            preparing for war immediately against the United States if such were
                            merely the wish of the Prime Minister. However, the Army would consent
                            to give up this program if the Navy were formally to express its opinion
                            that the Japanese Navy was not prepared for war against the United
                            States. The Army therefore asked the Chief Secretary of the Cabinet to
                            obtain formally the official views of the Navy Ministry. Consequently
                            the Chief Secretary called upon the Chief of the Military Affairs Bureau
                            of the Navy and asked him to present formally the official views of the
                            Navy. The Naval Chief of Military Affairs refused to consent to this
                            proposal and stated that the Navy, officially and formally, would go no
                            further than to agree to leave the entire matter in the hands of the
                            Prime Minister and to support whatever decision the Prime Minister
                            should reach. The Army continued to oppose the views of the Prime
                            Minister and the Cabinet was forced to resign.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>While this account of events has since been confirmed from several sources, the
                    first authoritative explanation of the Navy’s position as above reported to come
                    directly to the attention of this Office was provided by Admiral Toyoda Teijiro,
                    Foreign Minister in the third Konoye Cabinet, in conversation with a member of
                    the staff of this Office at the Admiral’s home on March 22. Admiral Toyoda
                    stated that but for a last minute change of plans he would have been Navy
                    Minister instead of Foreign Minister in the last Konoye Cabinet, and that in
                    that post he would have officially advised Konoye and the Emperor of the Navy’s
                    active opposition to and incapacity for war with the United States. He pointed
                    out, however, that the Navy was in a very difficult position, because the advice
                    which he would have been ready to give would have been followed by question from
                    the Army as to just why Japan had gone to the trouble and expense of building a
                    Navy if when the crisis came it was unwilling or unable to fight the very Power
                    which had always been regarded as its most probable opponent. He said that the
                    Navy leaders, while desiring peace, being far from sanguine of Japan’s chances
                    of ultimate victory, could not summon courage to face this charge.</p>
                <pb facs="0435" n="423" xml:id="pg_423"/>
                <p>The Army extremists, the Admiral’s statement clarifies, clearly were in an
                    advantageous position. If the Navy had declared itself unwilling to fight the
                    United States, the Army could have proceeded with the liquidation of the China
                    War while placing the major portion of the blame for its mistakes and failures
                    of the past ten years on the Navy, which, it could then have said, had failed it
                    in the supreme effort before victory. If, on the other hand, the Navy refused to
                    be made a scapegoat, the war which these extremists in greater or lesser degree
                    desired would follow. An express Imperial Command, issued on the advice of the
                    Prime Minister even though he were not formally supported by the Navy, that war
                    with the United States should be avoided, might have provided them with a
                    similar face-saving opportunity. While Prince Konoye states that the Army would
                    not give up its idea of preparing for war immediately against the United States
                    merely on his say-so, there is reason to believe (reference despatch no. 124,
                    December 26, 1945<note n="60" xml:id="d333fn2">Not printed.</note>) that if the
                    Prince had formally advised the Emperor to declare for peace the Emperor would
                    have done so and the Army would have obeyed.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Max</hi> W. <hi rend="smallcaps">Bishop</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Service Officer</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
