<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Mr. Willard L. Thorp, Deputy
                        to the Assistant Secretary of State for Economic Affairs (
                        Clayton
                    ), to Mr. Martin T.
                            Bennett, of Ambassador Pauley’s Staff</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d366</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">366</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-04-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-04-02T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-04-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-04-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="366" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d366">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 PW/3–2346</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Willard L. Thorp</persName>, Deputy
                        to the Assistant Secretary of State for Economic Affairs</hi> (<persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Clayton</hi>
                    </persName>), <hi rend="italic">to Mr. <persName type="to">Martin T.
                            Bennett</persName>, of Ambassador Pauley’s Staff</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-04-02">April 2,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Bennett</hi>: In Mr. Pauley’s absence, I am
                    writing you to acknowledge receipt of his letter of March 23 enclosing a copy of
                    his report to the President on Japanese reparations,<note n="92" xml:id="d366fn1">For Ambassador Pauley’s <hi rend="italic">Report on
                            Japanese Reparations to the President of the United States, November
                            1945 to April 1946</hi>, see Department of State Publication 3174, Far
                        Eastern Series 25, released July 28, 1948.</note> and to express our
                    appreciation for the work of the Mission.</p>
                <pb facs="0498" n="486" xml:id="pg_486"/>
                <p>I am referring the report to Mr. Edwin M. Martin, Chief of the Division of
                    Japanese Economic Affairs, and U.S. member of the Reparations Committee of the
                    Far Eastern Commission, requesting that he review the conclusions with you in
                    the near future. Such preliminary discussion may aid in clarifying those aspects
                    of the report on which it may be desirable to secure further information as
                    suggested by Mr. Pauley.</p>
                <p>Mr. Martin and his staff will endeavor to keep in close touch with you and Mr.
                        DuBois<note n="93" xml:id="d366fn2">Josiah DuBois, member of Ambassador
                        Pauley’s Staff.</note> in order to have the full benefit of your assistance
                    in arriving at final recommendations for U. S. reparations policy. Such study
                    and discussion may require a period of two or three months as we and the other
                    Departments represented on <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss> will want to
                    examine closely the implications of your proposals from a number of standpoints
                    before the final recommendations of this government are transmitted to the Far
                    Eastern Commission. The latter body has yet to act on an interim reparations
                    program so that its final reparaions decisions are not likely to be made for
                    several months.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Willard</hi> L. <hi rend="smallcaps">Thorp</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
