<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Political Adviser in Korea (
                        Benninghoff
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d462</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">462</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-01-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-01-22T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="terrorism" subject="terrorism" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134112" lcsh-match="exact">Terrorism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-01-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-01-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="462" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d462">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Korea)/1–2246: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Political Adviser in Korea</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Benninghoff</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Seoul</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-01-22">January 22,
                            1946</date>.<lb/>[Received January 25—4:05 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>From General Hodge. The Commanding General of the U. S. Forces in Korea wishes to
                    express his appreciation to the State Department for having received from them,
                    prior to its broadcast,<note n="21" xml:id="d462fn1">For radio broadcast on
                        Korea, January 19, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                        January 27, 1946, p. 104.</note> the summary of the State Department message
                    regarding Korea. He feels that, generally speaking, such a policy will aid in
                    our contacts with both the Koreans and the Russians. (We have not yet received a
                    confirmation copy of the message.) He expresses the hope that advance copies
                    will be sent in the future. Under some circumstances it might be advisable to
                    make arrangements for releases to be made simultaneously. The two following
                    points are raised with regard to the broadcast.</p>
                <pb facs="0626" n="614" xml:id="pg_614"/>
                <p>Your reference that Japanese technicians might possibly be employed is not
                    understood by us. Presently the Koreans are much opposed to the continuance in
                    service of any <gloss target="#t_Jap1">Jap</gloss> and almost all previously
                    employed <gloss target="#t_Jap1">Jap</gloss>s are no longer in the service of
                    the Government. There are a few yet in the service of the Military Government
                    but we do not advertise the fact and have intentions of removing them as soon as
                    it is feasible. Even though the people of Korea are aware that assistance is
                    needed, they will not take it from the Japanese.</p>
                <p>When referring to the People’s Party of Korea the State Department obviously
                    thinks it is representative of the Liberals and not of the Communists. Such a
                    state of affairs no longer exists as the Communists are stronger in this Party
                    than the Liberals. This situation is elaborated upon in my November 24th [<hi rend="italic">25th</hi>], Tfcgc 159.<note n="22" xml:id="d462fn2">
                        <ref target="frus1945v06#pg_1133">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 1133</ref>.</note> A source close to
                    Lyuh Woon Hyung<note n="23" xml:id="d462fn3">Leader of the Korean “People’s
                        Republic”, September 1945, and of the People’s Party.</note> admits that Hun
                        Ho<note n="24" xml:id="d462fn4">Hu Hun, also a leader of the Korean
                        “People’s Republic”.</note> and he are no longer in control of the party as
                    the Communist Party has usurped power. Nonetheless, they are still leaders in
                    name and have made no open break with those actually in control of the party,
                    perhaps because they fear being removed completely from the present political
                    picture. We feel that at the present time the Communists (perhaps with the aid
                    of the Russians) are making use of the People’s Party, supposedly Liberal, to
                    conduct their activities, included in which is political terrorism. They have no
                    desire to get rid of Lyuh for this reason, and he does not wish to disappear
                    from the political scene of his own free will, as he is an opportunist who has
                    no backing outside the Party. [Hodge.]</p>
                <closer>[<signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Benninghoff</hi>
                    </signed>]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
