<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>General of the Army Douglas
                            MacArthur to the Joint Chiefs of
                            Staff
                    
                    Copy transmitted to the Department with letter of
                        March 18 from the Secretaries of War and Navy, Robert P. Patterson and James
                        V. Forrestal, not printed.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d473</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">473</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-02-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-02-02T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-02-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-02-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="473" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d473">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Korea)/3–1846</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">General of the Army <persName type="from">Douglas
                            MacArthur</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Joint Chiefs of
                            Staff</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="46" xml:id="d473fn1">Copy transmitted to the Department with letter of
                        March 18 from the Secretaries of War and Navy, Robert P. Patterson and James
                        V. Forrestal, not printed.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/> AG 091 (2 Feb 46) CC</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-02-02">2 February
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Radio from the Commanding General, U.S. Army Forces in
                    Korea, Tfgcg 272.</p>
                <p>Following radio from <gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_USAFIK1">USAFIK</gloss> is repeated for your information:</p>
                <p>“Reference is made to State Department radio Nr 90 DTG 271512 Z.<note n="47" xml:id="d473fn2">See footnote 34, <ref target="#pg_621">p. 621</ref>.</note>
                    Reference message contains and implies information that should have been passed
                    to this headquarters by the State Department several weeks ago for guidance in
                    planning, policies, and handling emergencies. It is in itself complete evidence
                    that the Department has paid little attention either to the information
                    painstakingly sent in from those actually on the grounds as to the psychology of
                    the Korean people or to the repeated urgent recommendations of the commander and
                    State Department political advisers. The verification of the full truth of the
                    Tass statement comes as real news to me, particularly in view of my urgent
                    recommendations beginning in October and the recent State Department attitude
                    and broadcasts which shy away <pb facs="0641" n="629" xml:id="pg_629"/> from the
                    trusteeship idea and hold out hope that possibly it may not be necessary. Just
                    after the quelling of the revolt and riots brought about by announcement of the
                    trusteeship, our position here was the strongest since our arrival. As the
                    significance of the Tass statement recently released here by General Shtikov
                    sinks in, the Korean people are feeling that the United States has again sold
                    ‘them down the river,’ this time to the Russians instead of the Japanese.
                    Without a denial by the United States nothing we can say or do locally will
                    clear the atmosphere of a newly growing distrust of the United States. The Tass
                    statement was very cleverly worded to make clear to the Koreans that the Soviets
                    tried to arrange for the Koreans at and prior to the Moscow Conference
                    everything Koreans had wanted, including full independence at an early date, but
                    had been thwarted in their benevolent wishes by the strong American pressure for
                    a 10-year trusteeship. Up to now the Koreans have hated and feared the Soviets
                    because of their actions within the northern zone and have looked to the United
                    States for salvation believing that the United States would give some
                    consideration to the wishes of freed Koreans. The Russians are improving
                    materially in behavior north of the 38th degrees and through clever propaganda
                    are beginning to rise in stature as the saviors of the ‘30,000,000 Korean
                    people.’ Communist activity, on the wane for almost a month up until January 15,
                    is locally again increasing materially both in boldness and effectiveness, while
                    thinking and educated Koreans are again becoming sure they will now have to
                    fight for their freedom and independence. It might be added that so far there is
                    nothing in the attitude of the Russians to indicate that they have any thought
                    of unifying the Korean nation while we keep forces here. So far all discussion
                    includes adjustment of flow of everything from mail to persons through control
                    posts along the boundary. My best guess now is that north and south will never
                    be really united until the Russians are sure that the whole will be soundly
                    communistic. Based on current trends, I question our ability to stem the
                    propaganda and controlled political maneuvering of the Soviets.</p>
                <p>“I do not know who have been the experts on Korea who have advised and guided the
                    State Department in their disregard of my recommendations. It may be the
                    educated Koreans in the United States. It certainly has not been anyone who has
                    seen and really knows Korea since the war. I hope that it can be impressed upon
                    the Department that here we are not dealing with wealthy U.S. educated Koreans,
                    but with early, [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] poorly trained, and poorly educated
                    Orientals strongly affected by 40 years of <gloss target="#t_Jap1">Jap</gloss>
                    control, who stubbornly and fanatically hold to what they like and dislike, who
                    are definitely influenced by direct propaganda and with whom it is almost <pb facs="0642" n="630" xml:id="pg_630"/> impossible to reason. We are opposed
                    by a strongly organized, ruthless political machinery designed to appeal to the
                    millions of this type.</p>
                <p>“I hope there is some way in which you can pass my ideas to the State Department
                    and get over to them the thought that we must be kept informed and that it might
                    be worth while to consider some of the information and recommendations we have
                    conscientiously sent in from Korean hotspot based on fact and not theory.”</p>
                <closer>For the Supreme Commander:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Harold Fair</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>for <signed>H. W. Allen</signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Colonel, AGD, Asst Adjutant General</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
