<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-02-28T06:41:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-02-25T10:00:00-05:00" n="482" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d482">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Korea)/2–2846:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Lieutenant General <persName type="from">John R.
                                    Hodge</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Seoul</hi></placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1946-02-28T06:41:00-05:00" notBefore="1946-02-26T00:00:00+09:00">undated</date>.<lb/>[Received February 28—6:41 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>From <gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_USAFIK1">USAFIK</gloss> to <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> No. Tfgcg 307 signed Hodge to War for action. Three
                            weeks have elapsed since agreements were signed with Soviets but no word
                            of approval or disapproval has been received from General Chistiakov. In
                            meantime reports from north indicate that Soviets are making
                            preparations to implement agreement concerning mails. I am today sending
                            letter to Chistiakov referring to such reports and inquiring as to his
                            intentions regarding all agreements, the Joint Commission should meet by
                            middle of next week. The Russians propose to open meeting before giving
                            any indication of intention regarding agreements reached by previous
                            conference, I shall, without refusing to have the Joint Commission
                            convene, assume the attitude that we should at least know the Soviet
                            intention regarding the former conference before it is possible to
                            discuss matters of substance.</p>
                        <p>I feel that this is important in view of the extreme desirability of
                            doing as much to open up the country as possible and removing the
                            “blackout” north of 38. When opportunity offers, I shall let it be known
                            through press conference or otherwise that I have approved the
                            agreements but the Russians have not in turn notified me of their
                            approval. Benninghoff concurs.</p>
                        <closer>[<signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hodge</hi></signed>]</closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>