<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Political Adviser in Korea (
                        Langdon
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d488</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">488</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-03-19T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="alliances" subject="alliance" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="propaganda" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443" lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415" lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="finance" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885" lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="transportation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994" lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recbqzzF4Eebaylpi" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="border-administration" subject="border-control" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006007505" lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Border control</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="food" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184" lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="fuel" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720" lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-03-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="488" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d488">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Korea)/3–1946: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Political Adviser in Korea</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Langdon</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Seoul</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-03-19">March 19,
                            1946</date>.<lb/>[Received March 21—12:39 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>37. “Summary of conditions in Korea February 15th through March 14th:</p>
                <p>“1. Internal situation.</p>
                <p>“Major political activity during period was characterized by intensified
                    maneuvering for position and effort at consolidation among Communist and
                    anti-Communist lines in anticipation of establishment of Joint Commission and
                    creation of Interim Korean Government. Little success has resulted from efforts
                    to bridge gap between two groups and to form united political front for South
                    Korea; in fact cleavage between these factions appears to be becoming sharper.
                    Some followers of the Chungking Provisional Government have endeavored to
                    capitalize on formation of Korean Representative Democratic Council of South
                    Korea as an advisory body to <gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_USAFIK1">USAFIK</gloss> by making it appear that this body is
                    merely a projection of Emergency National Assembly of original Kim Koo
                    Provisional Government. This Council now has quarters in Chang Kuk Palace, and
                    enjoys official recognition and support. Syngman Rhee is Chairman of Council,
                    Kim Kiusik,<note n="67" xml:id="d488fn1">Usually spelled Kimm (or Kim)
                        Kiusic.</note> Vice Chairman, and Kim Koo, Secretary <pb facs="0661" n="649" xml:id="pg_649"/> General. Communist controlled Korean People’s Republic,
                    People’s Party, Independence Alliance, and Communist Party are pinning their
                    hopes on Democratic People’s Front and continue to refuse participation in
                    Council despite continuing invitation to join up. A closer alignment between
                    Left Wing Parties in South Korea and newly-formed Communistic Central People’s
                    Government in north appears to be taking place, carrying with it implication of
                    support from these parties for future Soviet position in setting up Interim
                    Government under Joint Commission.</p>
                <p>“Local Communists and Communist-controlled Korean People’s Republic have
                    increased their propaganda against American Military Government. Democratic
                    People’s Front appears to be gaining in unity and strength under joint
                    leadership of four chairmen, leaders of four principal Leftist Parties in South
                    Korea, following series of meetings during February in which a 17-point platform
                    was adopted. There is some evidence that Kim Koo’s followers have gained an
                    increasing influence in the provinces at expense of People’s Committee of Korean
                    People’s Republic, to some degree attributable to the latter’s unpopular stand
                    in supporting trusteeship. Very few civil disturbances and a general reduction
                    of lawlessness among the Koreans marked period. This may have been due to
                    realization on part of political leaders that violence should be avoided as a
                    matter on [<hi rend="italic">of</hi>] policy and to increasing prestige and
                    effectiveness of Korean police.</p>
                <p>“Celebration of Korean Independence Day on March 1st was carried Right Wing Grp
                    numbering 200,000 persons participated in various ceremonies, without untoward
                    incident. Communist-controlled Left Wing factions held their own celebration, at
                    which an estimated 15,000 people were present. Soviet flags were in evidence and
                    a scheduled parade was cancelled, owing probably to poor attendance. Neither
                    Communist leader Pak<note n="68" xml:id="d488fn2">Pak Hon-yong, or Pak
                        Heun-yung.</note> nor Lyuh of People’s Republic were present.</p>
                <p>“Ordinance NR 55 was issued by Military Government on February 23rd, and, in
                    addition to other provisions, requires registration of all political parties, a
                    list of their members, and copies of their accounts. Communists were most
                    vociferous in condemning the ordinance, but opposition also came from other
                    quarters, feeling being voiced in press that ordinance was an unwarranted
                    restriction on political activity. First to register were the Communists.</p>
                <p>“Fears appeared to be gaining ground that division of Korea along 38 degrees
                    parallel may become permanent, and that country may develop into another
                    ‘Poland’. Considerable cynicism is being expressed in press that efforts of
                    forthcoming Joint Commission to achieve concrete results towards real economic
                    and political unity of <pb facs="0662" n="650" xml:id="pg_650"/> north and south
                    are foredoomed to failure. This sentiment appears to be based largely upon
                    alleged lack of success of initial Soviet-American conference and upon general
                    atmosphere of our present relations with Russia.</p>
                <p>“As of March 14th, 3,460 Japanese remained in South Korea and a total of
                    approximately 1,575,000 Koreans had been repatriated from abroad, including
                    11,533 from China.</p>
                <p>“2. Economic conditions.</p>
                <p>“Land program. On March 7th Military Government announced decision to sell former
                    Japanese-owned farms, urban residences, and small business properties to
                    Koreans. Ordinance soon to be issued authorized sale of 875,000 acres of former
                    Japanese-owned agricultural land to tenant and part-tenant farmers, who
                    themselves must operate the land they purchase. Payments will be made in kind on
                    a long term contract. At present farm households south of 38 degrees total about
                    2,000,000, including: 14 percent farm owner-operators; 33 percent part
                    owners-part tenants; 51 percent tenant farmers; 2 percent all others. Sale
                    Japanese land will enable about 300,000 tenant farmers to become
                    owner-operators.</p>
                <p>“Korean groups planning land reform programs applicable to large Korean-owned
                    agricultural holdings. Seoul newspapers report that according to <hi rend="italic">Ahovun Shinqmun</hi> (Korean Press) published in Pyongyang,
                    the Interim People’s Committee of North Korea drafted land ordinance on March
                    5th which provides for land seizure and distribution ‘without cost’ to farmers
                    in northern Korea of land formerly owned by the Japanese, by ‘national traitors’
                    and by those who fled south of 38 parallel. In addition, all farm tenants are to
                    be given the land they cultivate ‘without cost’. Churches and religious groups
                    will have all their land holdings above 12.5 acres seized and distributed. The
                    People’s Committee will administer this program, which is scheduled to be
                    completed by March 31. Of the approximately 1,000,000 farm households north of
                    38 degrees in 1943, 26 percent owned their farms, 31 percent were part
                    owners–part tenants, 42 percent were tenants, and 17 percent were in other
                    categories.</p>
                <p>“Rice collection and distribution program is considered to be making some
                    headway, although it is too early to forecast whether ultimate target figures
                    can be reached. A National Economic Board has been established in Military
                    Government, consisting of the American Directors of the Bureaus of Commerce,
                    Agriculture, Finance and Transportation, to study and coordinate economic policy
                    for Korea and to assist in complementing the various programs for industrial and
                    commercial rehabilitation.</p>
                <p>“3. External situation.</p>
                <pb facs="0663" n="651" xml:id="pg_651"/>
                <p>“On March 19th [?] party consisting of Colonel Booth, M. Benninghoff, and five
                    other Americans proceeded to Pyongyang at Russian invitation to complete
                    arrangements for initial meeting of Joint Commission; they returned with signed
                    copies of six basic agreements reached with Soviets as result of January joint
                    conference (myrad Tfgcg 316, March 6th). These final agreements represented some
                    recession from American desiderata as reflected in original provisional
                    agreement concluded at conference, particularly with respect to movement of
                    private persons and commercial traffic across 38 degree line.</p>
                <p>“Although Soviets originally suggested March 11th as opening date for Joint
                    Commission to meet in Seoul, tentative date has now been set by Soviets for
                    March 19th. Illness of General Shtikov, Head of Soviet delegation, is stated to
                    be reason for delay. An American liaison mission of three officers is now
                    stationed in Pyongyang and has direct telephone connection with Seoul.</p>
                <p>“Principal political activity in Russian Zone now appears concentrated upon
                    creation of a solid political front under Communist domination which would
                    provide strength for the Soviet position at meeting of Joint Commission.</p>
                <p>“Cho Man Sik, former leader of Democratic Party in North Korea, is now reported
                    to have disappeared; he was previously reported as being held in protective
                    custody. Reports indicate ever-increasing restrictions on civil liberties on
                    non-Communists in Russian Area and a further tightening of 38 degree border
                    control.</p>
                <p>“So-called ‘People’s Government’, under leadership of Kim Il Sawng,<note n="69" xml:id="d488fn3">Kim Il-sung (or Kim Il-song), who returned to Korea in 1945
                        from the Soviet Union as an officer in the Red Army, became head of cabinet
                        of provisional people’s committee for north Korea on February 9.</note>
                    continues to assume greater importance in the north and may be held out by
                    Soviets as an indigenous form of self-government, for purposes of invidious
                    comparison with American Military Government, since Soviets claim to stay aloof
                    from internal Korean politics. An armed Korean police organization known as
                    ‘Boan Dai’ is reported at disposition of People’s Government in carrying out
                    policies and suppressing opposition. Funds for this government are said to be
                    raised principally from forced ‘contributions’ levied on wealthy Koreans.
                    Popular resentment is understood to be arising against methods of Boan Dai and
                    Korean Communists.</p>
                <p>“March 1st Korean Independence Day was reported to have been marked by disorders
                    in Soviet area, including a bomb-throwing attempt of [<hi rend="italic">on</hi>]
                    life of Kim [Il] Sawng.</p>
                <p>“Scarcity of food, fuel, medicines, and transportation is reported to be serious
                    in Soviet Zone, while reports are received on continued stripping of industrial
                    machinery from northern factories. Reports <pb facs="0664" n="652" xml:id="pg_652"/> also persist that Soviets are shipping rice and other
                    foodstuffs out of North Korea. Their propaganda continues to allege that large
                    supplies of rice are being held in American Zone without distribution to
                    Koreans. Russians have requested payment in rice for approximately 220,000,000
                    kwh of electric power furnished to southern zone, under threat of turning off
                    power unless bill is paid. Our reply is that we will deduct cost of this power
                    from credits owing to Southern Korea.</p>
                <p>“Soviets have tentatively agreed to supply South Korea with 10 tons of chlorine
                    and 30,000 tons of fertilizer monthly provided a satisfactory basis for payment
                    in rice can be established. Final agreement would be subject to ratification by
                    Soviet Commander.</p>
                <p>“An increasing concentration of Soviet troops and material and construction of
                    defenses is reported in Southern AAOC [<hi rend="italic">area?</hi>] of Russian
                    Zone. Former Soviet Consul General at Seoul has been requested by <gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_USAFIK1">USAFIK</gloss> to withdraw from circulation in
                    American Zone certain Russian propaganda films and to refrain from all such
                    activities in future.”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Langdon</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
