<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in the Netherlands (
                        Hornbeck
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State
                    
                    Repeated by the Department as telegram 155, May 6,
                        to Batavia.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d610</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">610</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-05-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-05-03T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-05-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-05-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="610" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d610">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">856E.00/5–346: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Netherlands</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="71" xml:id="d610fn1">Repeated by the Department as telegram 155, May 6,
                        to Batavia.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">The Hague</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-05-03">May 3,
                            1946</date>.<lb/>[Received May 4—1:44 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>389. Minister Overseas Territories Logemann made report to Second Chamber evening
                    May 2 on progress Indonesian negotiations. Prime Minister and four other Cabinet
                    officers present in packed Chamber which received report in almost complete
                    silence. Debate on Indonesia scheduled to begin May [<hi rend="italic">next?</hi>].<note n="72" xml:id="d610fn2">In telegram 192, May 10, 10 p.m.,
                        from Batavia, Mr. Foote reported that the recent vote in the Second Chamber
                        was regarded as a mandate to proceed with negotiations with the Indonesians
                        (856E.00/5–1046).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Most salient points Logemann’s report follow: discussions have not yet reached
                    complete agreement but govt feels real progress has been made; basic principle
                    of Nationalists that Indonesian republic be recognized as sovereign state held
                    by govt incompatible with kingdom’s responsibilities; solution to threatening
                    deadlock appear[s] to be afforded along lines recent agreement between France
                    and former Annam Empire; applying same principle to solution NEI problem govt
                    reached conclusion Indonesian republic might be recognized as part of federal
                    Commonwealth of Indonesia which jointly with Netherlands, Surinam and Curacao
                    would become partners within <pb facs="0833" n="821" xml:id="pg_821"/> kingdom;
                    status of Indonesia would be that of federation of self-governing units in which
                    Netherlands Govt’s powers to assume final responsibility in respect of
                    fundamental rights, proper administration and sound finances would apply to
                    entire Commonwealth of Indonesia as well as to its constituent parts;
                    recognition of republic as one of these parts would not mean to imply that
                    Netherlands Kingdom would relinquish such powers as it needs for insuring
                    satisfactory functioning new administrative organization and would be compatible
                    with govt’s Feb 10 declaration; govt of opinion that group governing republic is
                    representative of national aim all Indonesians in Java and when cooperation is
                    resumed with Netherlands these leaders will be able overcome wanton acts
                    currently being committed undercover so-called warfare once Nationalist minds
                    are no longer dominated by presumption that freedom must be defended against
                    Netherlands aggression; obstacles remain to early satisfactory solution, namely,
                    republic in principle claims right to direct entire territory of Indonesia but
                    Sjahrir and his partisans are prepared reduce their claims to those areas where
                    republic exercises <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> authority; regarding outlying
                    islands including Sumatra, Netherlands Govt maintains view they will be free to
                    express their desires with regard to future status within Indonesia and should
                    they desire to join the Republic govt will not oppose; purpose discussions have
                    been to move Nationalists to lay down arms, to abandon revolt and to cooperate
                    in peaceful reform of kingdom; frank advice of Indonesian Delegates who
                    accompanied Van Mook to Hague strengthened govt in its convictions that
                    Nationalism is force uniting all educated Indonesians.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hornbeck</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
