<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chairman of the House Committee on Foreign
                    Affairs ( (Bloom))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d612</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">612</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-05-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-05-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="prisoners-of-war"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners of war</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recPjGjlVHIlHmzym" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112903"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Repatriation</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-05-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-05-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="612"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d612">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">856E.00/4–2046</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chairman of the House Committee on Foreign Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bloom</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-05-24">May 24,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Bloom</hi>: This is in response to your letter
                    of April 20, 1946,<note n="75" xml:id="d612fn1">Not printed.</note> receipt of
                    which I have previously acknowledged, in which you transmitted for the comment
                    of the Department of State copies of H. Res. 603, “Expressing the sense of the
                    House of Representatives to call upon the State Department to take steps
                    regarding the presence of Japanese troops in Indonesia, and other action in
                    support of the Indonesian Republic”.</p>
                <p>I am glad to have an opportunity to make a number of observations on questions of
                    fact raised by the proposed resolution. Furthermore, since the policies of this
                    Government with respect to the situation in the Netherlands East Indies have
                    frequently been misunderstood, if not actually misinterpreted, I welcome an
                    opportunity to set the record straight.</p>
                <p>The proposed resolution would call upon the Department of State to make the
                    necessary representation to the British and Netherlands Governments for the
                    complete and immediate withdrawal of their troops from Indonesia; it would also
                    have this Department call upon the United Nations to investigate the matter of
                    disarming and removing Japanese troops now in Indonesia.</p>
                <p>Regarding the withdrawal of Dutch forces, it is clearly inappropriate for this
                    Government to make such a representation to the Netherlands Government since the
                    United States recognizes the sovereignty of the Netherlands, which is an Allied
                    and friendly power, over the Netherlands East Indies.</p>
                <p>The withdrawal of British forces from the Netherlands East Indies is primarily a
                    matter between the British and Netherlands Governments and, consistent with the
                    responsibilities of the Southeast Asia Command, is to a great extent contingent,
                    the Department understands, upon the removal of Japanese troops from that area.
                    The return to Japan of Japanese forces in the entire Southeast Asia Theater,
                    including the Netherlands East Indies, is a British military responsibility
                    assigned on behalf of the Allies to the Southeast Asia Command <pb facs="0835"
                        n="823" xml:id="pg_823"/> under Admiral Mountbatten, although the arrival of
                    such troops in Japan is subject to the orders of General MacArthur. Thus the
                    Southeast Asia Command, apart from its other responsibilities towards Allied
                    prisoners of war and civilians, has been confronted with the tremendous task of
                    rounding up, disarming, interning and removing some 650,000 Japanese troops in
                    this area. Such troops are being removed, however, as rapidly as shipping and
                    other facilities permit. The order of priority of their repatriation from the
                    various regions of Southeast Asia is, of course, a military matter for decision
                    by Admiral Mountbatten in conjunction with General MacArthur. The Department is
                    informed that steps are now being taken which it is hoped will in the very near
                    future provide shipping for the evacuation of very large numbers of Japanese
                    from the Netherlands East Indies. At present, the task of preparing the Japanese
                    for removal is being carried forward by British and Netherlands troops in
                    cooperation with forces of the so-called “Indonesian Republic”.</p>
                <p>The resolution would also call upon this Department to take all steps appropriate
                    to withhold any further shipments of war material to Britain and the Netherlands
                    for use in Indonesia under any terms or agreement.</p>
                <p>Since the capitulation of Japan in August, 1945, no military lend-lease material
                    has been furnished the Netherlands by the United States. No arms or equipment
                    have been sold to the Netherlands for military use in the Netherlands East
                    Indies except, pursuant to a previous commitment, such as were necessary for the
                    equipment of a small unit of Netherlands Marines who were in training in this
                    country before <gloss target="#t_VJDay1">V–J Day</gloss>. Relative to the
                    Netherlands Marine contingent, may I call your attention to a letter from the
                    Secretary of the Navy dated January 4, 1946 and reproduced in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Congressional Record</hi> of January 14, 1946, page A–21.
                    Licenses for the export of arms and munitions from the United States to the
                    Netherlands East Indies are not being issued. Furthermore, it is contrary to the
                    policy of this Government to permit American flag vessels or aircraft to
                    transport troops of any nationality to or from the Netherlands East Indies
                    except for the evacuation of Japanese. It is also contrary to American policy to
                    permit the use of American flag vessels or aircraft to carry arms, ammunition,
                    or military equipment to this area.</p>
                <p>Finally, the resolution calls upon the Department of State to express through the
                    American delegates to the United Nations Security Council United States
                    disapproval of the manner in which present negotiations are being conducted
                    between the Netherlands and Indonesia. In this connection it is apparently felt
                    that the negotiations are prejudiced by the presence in the Netherlands East
                    Indies of three so-called “inter-ventionary armies”—British, Dutch and Japanese.
                    The reasons for <pb facs="0836" n="824" xml:id="pg_824"/> the continued presence
                    of these forces in the Netherlands East Indies are explained above. Meanwhile,
                    the Dutch-Indonesian negotiations, begun in February, have been carried forward
                    both in the Netherlands East Indies and in the Netherlands proper under
                    conditions of which the representatives of the Indonesian Republic themselves
                    have made no complaint, so far as the Department is aware.</p>
                <p>The proposed resolution claims that prior to the Japanese attack on the
                    Netherlands East Indies the Dutch administration refused to arm the Indonesians
                    in defense of their homeland. Actually, compulsory military service for both
                    Europeans and Indonesians was instituted in the Netherlands East Indies before
                    the war. Army and Navy forces designed wholly for the defense of the Indies were
                    made up of a majority of natives, particularly Amboinese and Menadoese, many of
                    them officered by Indonesians who even led some European units.</p>
                <p>The resolution also includes the statement that British troops in Indonesia have
                    used armed Japanese forces to destroy the Indonesian Republic and restore Dutch
                    imperial control in Indonesia. The Department is informed that in certain areas
                    of N.E.I, where no or insufficient British and Dutch forces were available,
                    Japanese forces have been used under Allied direction to keep open lines of
                    communication essential to effect the liberation of Allied prisoners of war and
                    civilian internees and to supply food and medical aid to such persons pending
                    their evacuation. The number of Japanese troops so employed is being reduced as
                    rapidly as conditions permit. In view of the fact that negotiations are going
                    on, it is clear that the Indonesian Republican administration is still in being
                    and that the conditions under which any Dutch sovereignty shall be exercised in
                    the N.E.I, are still being worked out between Republican leaders and the
                    Netherlands authorities.</p>
                <p>As early as October 18, 1945,<note n="76" xml:id="d612fn2">See memorandum by the
                        Director of the Office of Far Eastern Affairs, October 22, 1945, <ref
                            target="frus1945v06#pg_1167">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 1167</ref>.</note> an officer of the
                    Department stated that, while this Government does not question Netherlands
                    sovereignty in the East Indies, it is not our intention to assist or participate
                    in forceful measures for the imposition of control by the territorial sovereign.
                    Again, in a public statement of December 19, 1945, the Department called upon
                    both the Indonesian leaders and the Netherlands authorities to seek through
                    negotiation a peaceful settlement which would recognize alike the natural
                    aspirations of the Indonesian peoples and the legitimate rights and interests of
                    the Netherlands, and which would be in harmony with the principles and ideals of
                    the Charter of the United Nations organization.</p>
                <pb facs="0837" n="825" xml:id="pg_825"/>
                <p>On February 11, 1946, the United States delegate stated before the United Nations
                    Security Council in reference to the situation in the Netherlands East Indies
                    that the best hope for the settlement of this unhappy situation and for the
                    elimination of any possibility of a renewal of armed strife in that troubled
                    area lies in the successful and prompt completion of the negotiations between
                    the Netherlands Government and the Indonesian leaders. He added that he felt it
                    would be a serious responsibility for the Council to take any action which might
                    prejudice or retard the outcome of these negotiations and thereby increase the
                    chance of future bloodshed. It is the Department’s opinion that this reasoning
                    is still valid and is applicable to the possible passage at this time of such a
                    resolution as the one proposed.</p>
                <p>The Department has been informed by the Bureau of the Budget that there is no
                    objection to the submission of this report.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi> F. <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
