<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by the Secretary of
                            State to President Truman</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d653</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">653</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-01-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-01-28T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-01-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-01-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="653" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d653">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.11B31/1–1046</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                            State</gloss> to President <persName type="to">Truman</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-01-28">January 28,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Secretary Anderson’s Proposals with Respect to H. R.
                    4676, the Philippine Trade Bill</p>
                <p>I refer to your memorandum of January 10, 1946<note n="15" xml:id="d653fn1">See
                        footnote 2, <ref target="#pg_861">p. 861</ref>.</note> and to the attached
                    copy of Secretary Anderson’s letter of January 7, which deals with (1) the
                    problem of reconciling, particularly in the case of sugar, the differences in
                    our proposed treatment of Cuba and of the Philippines with respect to tariff
                    preferences, (2) the difficulties which this proposed difference of treatment
                    has caused in the negotiations for the purchase of Cuban sugar, and (3) the
                    question of the size of the Philippine and Cuban sugar quotas.</p>
                <p>As a solution to these problems, the Secretary of Agriculture has recommended
                    that: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>duties on our sugar imports within quotas established by sugar
                            legislation or international agreement with respect to sugar might be
                            entirely eliminated, and that</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>no commitments be made in H. R. 4676 which would have the effect of
                            tying the hands of this Government with respect to import quota
                            arrangements on sugar which may be developed in the future in connection
                            with domestic sugar legislation or international agreements.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0881" n="869" xml:id="pg_869"/>
                <p>With respect to the first recommendation of the Department of Agriculture, this
                    Department believes that it would be undesirable to propose, in connection with
                    the Philippine Trade Bill, the elimination of all sugar duties. The Department
                    believes that such a proposal would introduce a controversial political issue of
                    concern not only to the Philippines and Cuba but to all producers of sugar,
                    domestic as well as foreign, and that enactment of the Philippine Trade Bill
                    might be further delayed and Philippine rehabilitation retarded. The Department
                    believes that the question of sugar duties should be deferred until general
                    sugar legislation is considered in connection with the Sugar Act which expires
                    at the end of this year. This Department would appreciate an opportunity to
                    comment on any such legislation because of its important bearing on our foreign
                    economic relations.</p>
                <p>Secretary Anderson’s second proposal is consistent with the position that this
                    Department has already taken with respect to quota arrangements on sugar in H.
                    R. 4676. On December 11 I wrote to Mr. Robertson,<note n="16" xml:id="d653fn2">A. Willis Robertson, of Virginia, House of Representatives.</note> then
                    Acting Chairman of the Ways and Means Committee, that in the opinion of this
                        <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> the changing of the absolute quotas
                    provided in H. R. 4676 to tariff quotas, as had been suggested by this
                    Department, would not preclude the inclusion of Philippine sugar in any future
                    revision or extension of the Sugar Act of 1937. I added, moreover, that if there
                    should be any doubt as to this a proviso might be added to section 4 of the bill
                    stipulating that “nothing in this section shall affect any existing or future
                    legislation or international agreement imposing quantitative restrictions upon
                    the importation of sugar into the United States”.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi> F. <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
