<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in the Philippines (
                        McNutt
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d715</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">715</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-10-21T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMpPwlFJwREQmrz" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="cultural-and-educational-exchanges" lcsh-match="no_match">Cultural relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="715" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d715">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">896.01/10–2146</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Philippines</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">McNutt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 258</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Manila</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-10-21">October 21,
                            1946</date>.<lb/>[Received November 7.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to report that the text of
                    Moscow’s telegram No. 3816, of October 11,<note n="96" xml:id="d715fn1">Not
                        printed.</note> was shown to President Roxas, an abbreviated version of
                    which had already appeared in the Manila press. On October 21 President Roxas
                    issued the following press statement in comment on the article from <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi>, quoted in the Department’s telegram cited above:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“There has come to my attention an article from <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi>, the official organ of the Russian Communist Party in
                            Moscow, depreciating our independence and charging that the Philippines
                            are dominated by United States military and economic interests. A number
                                <pb facs="0936" n="924" xml:id="pg_924"/> of other charges are also
                            included in this rather lengthy dissertation on the Philippines,
                            including many of the same irresponsible accusations which have been
                            spread in uninformed circles in the United States by self-serving
                            interests here. All these charges are falsehoods, not one of them having
                            greater validity than the other. I am surprised that this great organ of
                            the Russian Communist Party, with all its world concerns today, should
                            devote so much space to our affairs, except, of course, I understand
                            that by making remarks derogatory to the Philippines, this newspaper
                            feels it is also placing the United States in some discredit.</p>
                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> states, for instance, that after
                            liberation the United States Government ‘reinstated the
                            collaborationists and destroyed the national liberation movement.’ This
                            meaningless statement is, of course, palpably untrue. I am accused of
                            having pursued ‘cruel persecution’ of the ‘partisan people’s army.’ It
                            is alleged that American tanks were used to disperse ‘united front
                            meetings’ and that American troops were used to determine the result of
                            the presidential election.</p>
                        <p>“All these statements fall of their own weight. I merely cite them in
                            order that the Filipino people may know the uses to which irresponsible
                            political charges made here are put on the international front. I should
                            also like the people of the world to know that we cherish our hard-won
                            independence; that we will protect it with all the means at our command;
                            and that we will resist any attempt by any nation to threaten or curtail
                            that independence.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Respectfully submitted,</p>
                <closer>For the Ambassador:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Julius C. C. Edelstein</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Acting Director of Information and Cultural Relations</hi>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>[For Department of State press release of November 4 on agreement by
                        Presidents Truman and Roxas to establish a joint American-Philippine
                        Financial Commission to study the financial and budgetary problems and needs
                        of the Philippines, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                        November 17, 1946, page 921.]</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
