<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-05-31T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-05-31T05:00:00-05:00" n="798" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d798">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">892.014/5–3146: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Siam</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Yost</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">most immediate</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Bangkok</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-05-31T17:00:00+07:00">May 31, 1946—5
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received June 5—1:55 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>585. Siamese Government has requested that Anglo-US observers be sent to
                            northeast border area to remain for week or two. British Minister, Gen.
                            Brunskill and I believe such visit would be useful as deterrent to
                            further armed action and are despatching observers shortly. Lt. Col.
                                Law<note n="75" xml:id="d798fn1">Assistant Military Attaché in
                                Siam.</note> will represent Legation. Observers will be
                                instructed<note n="76" xml:id="d798fn2">Instructions given to
                                Colonel Law by Mr. Yost were transmitted to the Department by
                                Bangkok in despatch 132, June 3, not printed.</note> not to
                            intervene in any way or support either side but they will be authorized
                            to assist, when requested, local authorities on both sides in coming to
                            common understanding and avoiding incidents.</p>
                        <p>We would appreciate being informed whether Department approves this step.
                            If it does, it may wish to instruct American Consul Saigon<note n="77" xml:id="d798fn3">Charles S. Reed, 2d.</note> to inform French
                                authorities.<note n="78" xml:id="d798fn4">In telegram 466, June 6, 4
                                p.m., to Bangkok, the Department approved the sending of an observer
                                and stated that Saigon was being notified (892.014/5–3146).</note>
                            In view their much more far-reaching proposal to Brunskill, (mytel 577
                            May 30) it is not believed they will object to this arrangement.</p>
                        <p>Foreign Minister told me this morning urgent instructions have been sent
                            to provincial governors along Mekong to prevent any crossing of river
                            from Siamese side while situation remains critical. It is unlikely of
                            course that these orders can be completely carried out. I took
                            opportunity to suggest that wildly exaggerated stories in Bangkok press
                            (reference penultimate paragraph mytel 577) are creating state of public
                            opinion which makes reasonable settlement difficult. Direk admitted
                            exaggerations and said he would endeavor to correct situation.</p>
                        <p>In view of statement of Secretary General of <gloss target="#t_UNO1">UNO</gloss> that he is not referring case to Security Council
                            because Siamese did not ask him to do so, Foreign Minister is now
                            considering formally invoking <pb facs="1022" n="1010" xml:id="pg_1010"/> Article 35 of Charter.<note n="79" xml:id="d798fn5">Paragraph 2 of
                                this Article reads: “A state which is not a Member of the United
                                Nations may bring to the attention of the Security Council or of the
                                General Assembly any dispute to which it is a party if it accepts in
                                advance, for the purposes of the dispute, the obligations of pacific
                                settlement provided in the present Charter.”</note> He has not yet
                            decided whether to submit to Council recent frontier incidents only or
                            whole question of disputed territories. I reiterated US policy on
                            disputed territories and expressed view that Siam would have more
                            sympathetic hearing by Council if she had previously restored disputed
                            territories to France or at least formally announced intention to do so.
                            Foreign Minister stated he feared such action at this time would produce
                            storm in Assembly but he would endeavor to work out formula which would
                            satisfy US and Britain.</p>
                        <p>Since this whole question seems likely to come to a head rapidly, we hope
                            British Foreign Office can be persuaded to proceed with joint
                            recommendations submitted in mytel 488 May 8.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Yost</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>