<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Sharp) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1917Supp02v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d198</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">198</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-07-24T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-07-24T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-07-24T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-07-24T10:00:00-05:00" n="198"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d198">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72/5971</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SWG1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sharp</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-07-24T16:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 24, 1917, 4 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received July 25, 3.05 a.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2321. Section 2. Next to the actual participation of the United States in the war
                    on the side of the Allies, certainly no other one thought has given so much
                    satisfaction to the French Government as that of the prospect of America
                    becoming an important factor in shaping the terms in the ultimate peace
                    convention. At the very time that Lord <persName corresp="#p_NVA1"
                        >Northcliffe</persName> was quoted as saying in substance, at a banquet in
                    London soon after our entrance into the war, that he could not look with
                    pleasure upon the United States taking part in such convention, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJ1">Cambon</persName> was telling me at the Foreign Office,
                    with unfeigned delight, of the satisfaction with which France hailed such a
                    participation.</p>
                <p>All the Allied lesser powers in Europe have voiced the same feeling, and with
                    scarcely a. single exception the representatives of those countries have at
                    different times expressed to me that view in the warmest terms.</p>
                <p>Particularly among these latter powers the coming conference has excited much
                    interest and some concern. Within the past few days the Minister for Foreign
                    Affairs of the Montenegrin Government came to ask if I would intercede to have
                    my Government represent his country at the conference as he had been told that
                    its desire for participation had not been favorably entertained. He expressed
                    the gravest concern over a future autonomy of Montenegro on account of the
                    ambitions of Servia. My reply that my own Government was not to be represented
                    at the confederation [<hi rend="italic">conference?</hi>] was a sufficient
                    answer to his request.</p>
                <p>The same day the Chinese Minister came to me to tell me that he looked with much
                    anxiety in regard to the future policy of Japan <pb facs="0221" n="147"
                        xml:id="pg_147"/> towards his country, though he expressed the conviction
                    that the recent rebellion in China was undoubtedly fomented by German intrigue.
                    He stated that its early suppression served the double purpose of not only
                    restoring stability to the country but prevented the Japanese Government from
                    sending over troops on the plea of protecting its interests in China.</p>
                <p>Later Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RG1">Roussos</persName>, the new Greek Minister
                    to the United States, who sails this week, came in to pay his respects and
                    during our brief conversation he told me that while matters looked now very
                    favorable for improved conditions in his country, yet there were some
                    differences existing between Greece and Italy growing out of the insistence of
                    the latter to control that section of Greece through which [pass] the railroads
                    for the movement of troops, <persName corresp="#p_VEK1">Venizelos</persName>
                    requesting that the civil Greek authorities be permitted to exercise control in
                    that territory, not, however, thereby preventing the free use of the railroads
                    to Italian troops.</p>
                <p>Yesterday Mr. <persName>Vesnitch</persName>, the Servian Minister, very highly
                    esteemed by his colleagues, came to my office to tell me that although his
                    Government and that of Roumania and Greece had been invited to attend the
                    conference in a consultative capacity, yet they had been given to understand
                    that it was not expected that they would have a vote or be permitted to take any
                    other action in effecting the decision of the conference. He had informed the
                    Foreign Office that it was his intention to offer a protest to such action and
                    was then awaiting the arrival of the Minister of the Foreign Office of the
                    Servian Government to consult him upon what action to take. He in turn expressed
                    to me much concern over the designs that Italy had toward his country. I know
                    from previous statements made by him on other occasions that he has strong
                    convictions as to the dangers and complications that may grow out of such
                    designs. He showed much pleasure recently in telling me that he had been
                    notified by his Government that it was planned to send a mission over to America
                    of which he would be the head.</p>
                <p>All my colleagues to whom I have referred, however, have with one common accord
                    manifested the greatest faith in the good intentions of France.</p>
                <p>I assume that the principal discussion at the conference itself—the object of
                    which has been stated to be the consideration of the Balkan question—will center
                    around the policy of maintaining the Allied forces at Salonica, concerning
                    wisdom of which there has been at different times a good deal of doubt and
                    dissatisfaction, chiefly growing out of the difficulties, I understand, of
                    meeting the burdens which it involves in the employment of a large tonnage of
                    ships.</p>
                <pb facs="0222" n="148" xml:id="pg_148"/>
                <p>It is my belief that France and England are now more in accord upon this matter
                    than at the beginning of the Salonica movement, though it has been a heavy
                    burden on England for the reason stated.</p>
                <p>Russia will be represented by the Chargé d’Affaires and several officials who
                    have been sent to Paris by the Provisional Government for that purpose. I am
                    informed on good authority, however, that they have been instructed to only
                    discuss Balkan affairs as they relate to maintaining the Salonica front.</p>
                <p>I have given this general outline of some of the issues which may be raised and
                    of the attitude of some of the participants in reference thereto in order to
                    enable the Department to get some appreciation of the conditions which exist
                    here on the eve of this conference, which is the first of the Allies to be held
                    since the advent of the United States into the war and the Russian
                    revolution.</p>
                <p>Personally I believe that its deliberations will be characterized by great wisdom
                    and harmony, for no matter what differences may exist among some of the powers,
                    or concern as to their own particular interests, they all recognize the great
                    necessity of presenting a united front with as little division as possible.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SWG1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sharp</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
