<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-11-21T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-11-21T05:00:00-05:00" n="487" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d487">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 102.1/405</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Delegate to the Inter-Allied Council</hi>
                                    (<persName corresp="#p_COT1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Crosby</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-11-21T10:00:00+00:00">
                                        <hi rend="italic">November 21, 1917, 10 a.m.</hi>
                                    </date>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received 1.34 p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>No. 8, for Secretary of the Treasury:</p>
                            <p>Referring yours November 15.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Referring Canadian purchases. Recommend that small and urgent
                                    purchases may be made without reference to council here but
                                    their general program should be submitted if only to determine
                                    place in priority scale and further because of highly probable
                                    relation <pb facs="0656" n="582" xml:id="pg_582"/> between
                                    Canadian and British finance. If, however, Canadians willing to
                                    accept foot of priority list see no great objection to letting
                                    them enter purchasing agreement without reference to
                                    council.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Referring to moneys reimbursed on account of shipping
                                    construction. Treasury here would like assurance that it may be
                                    all applied in one way or another to payment of their
                                    outstanding cash obligations including bills held by Du Ponts
                                    and other manufacturers. Have proposed that best disposition
                                    would be to apply to $94,000,000 notes maturing February which
                                    are scattered as previously indicated.
                                        <persName>Lamont</persName><note n="1" xml:id="d487fn1">
                                        <persName>Thomas W. Lamont</persName>, member of the firm of
                                        J. P. Morgan &amp; Co.</note> naturally expresses preference
                                    that all available cash should be applied to reduction of
                                    overdraft but I consider we must deal with British Government
                                    solely on this subject. There will be no difficulty in having
                                    subrogation to collateral held against obligations thus met.
                                    Please advise amount of money and probable time of payment to
                                    British Government by Shipping Board considering possible
                                    changes in situation of Italy and France whose requirements for
                                    next year still unknown, possibly very large. Recommend that if
                                    application of these funds to Morgan overdraft insisted upon
                                    they must be put on notice that February maturity cannot be met
                                    unless large reductions in other programs be
                                    accomplished.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Referring to Greek situation. Do not consider necessary to
                                    send special financial American agent to Greece. Information
                                    here that English and French experts are very capable master the
                                    situation; so urgent that probably no delay admissible such as
                                    would be invalued [<hi rend="italic">incurred?</hi>] in getting
                                    American special agent there. It would be well, however, to ask
                                    our Minister to be associated with the French and English
                                    experts in financial investigations. During an interview with
                                        <persName corresp="#p_VEK1">Venizelos</persName> yesterday
                                    he urged immediate help particularly in the way of food.
                                    Consider French and British absolutely bound to aid Greece whose
                                    situation very bad but do not believe we should make commitment
                                    for money until after conference in Paris with French
                                    authorities. <persName corresp="#p_VEK1">Venizelos</persName>
                                    will be there. It seems probable that 200,000 tons Indian wheat
                                    may be allocated to Greek consumption. This could be financed by
                                    Great Britain. Future military movements not yet decided.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_VEK1">Venizelos</persName> likely to
                                    be terribly disappointed, perhaps to the extent of complete
                                    discomfiture, if British and French troops are more or less
                                    withdrawn as is now anticipated but not known to him. This point
                                    entirely confidential.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>Concerning Japanese financial assistance. Treasury here
                                    considers not available nor particularly desirable. No war
                                    purchases being made by Allies in Japan save for Russia.
                                    Financial relations between Russia and Japan may present serious
                                    situations. No present action indicated.</item>
                                <pb facs="0657" n="583" xml:id="pg_583"/>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>Concerning Belgium. Think proposed increase justifiable but
                                    recommend that it be made now for not more than two months in
                                    order to require further Belgian demands to be coordinated with
                                    other demands upon the Treasury.</item>
                                <label>(6)</label>
                                <item>Referring to Serbia. Recommend application of Minister be
                                    granted.</item>
                                <label>(7)</label>
                                <item>Concerning Roumanian Minister. Understand he is awaiting my
                                    arrival in Paris.</item>
                                <label>(8)</label>
                                <item>Crespi, Italian Food Minister, just arrived. Thinks it
                                    necessary to get immediately large stores for Italy in order to
                                    prevent public excitement possibly reaching revolutionary
                                    crisis. This will be considered within next few days, possibly
                                    affecting amount of money immediately required. But slight
                                    prospect that program as to transportation of grain can be
                                    modified to meet his views.</item>
                                <label>(9)</label>
                                <item>Referring to nitrate agreement. Understand that State
                                    Department and purchasing commission have authorized negotiation
                                    by <persName corresp="#p_SRP1">Skinner</persName>. See nothing
                                    objectionable in financial side of contract which provides that
                                    each Government concerned shall finance its own purchases and
                                    provide its own shipping. Am asking British, French and Italian
                                    Governments to explain how they expect to finance their part
                                    merely because we must anticipate possibility of entire purchase
                                    price appearing in New York in the form of sterling
                                    bills.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>Please advise Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_COT1">Crosby</persName> that
                                Carraciolos stationed officially in Paris.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_COT1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Crosby</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>