<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-11-15T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-11-15T04:00:00-05:00" n="611" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d611">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72/7728</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_RPS1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Reinsch</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-11-15T17:00:00+08:00">
                                        <hi rend="italic">November 15, 1917, 5 p.m.</hi>
                                    </date>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received November 15, 4.25
                                    p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Both the Chinese Government and the French Legation eagerly awaiting
                                the decision of the American Government on the question submitted in
                                my telegram of November 4, 8 p.m. As to the safest method of
                                securing this important military support I have the honor to make
                                the following suggestion. In view of the fact that in the case of a
                                loan the Chinese Government naturally would desire to control the
                                expenditure, direct assumption by the United States in behalf of the
                                Allies of all the expense of the expedition would prove more
                                satisfactory. Under this arrangement China would contribute the men,
                                the United States would pay to the Chinese Government a lump sum to
                                defray the cost of getting the troops to the port of embarkation in
                                China and would thereafter directly provide in conjunction with the
                                Allies for transport, arming, provisioning and payment of the
                                troops. This arrangement would avoid all entanglements and possible
                                criticism connected with a loan for this purpose and would offer to
                                the Chinese a clean opportunity to do their part.</p>
                            <p>If concurrently financial assistance to be given by way of a loan for
                                national efficiency purposes a definite understanding as to the
                                application of the funds is most important.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RPS1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Reinsch</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>