<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-06-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-06-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="666" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d666">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72119/646</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Editor of the Chicago “Tribune”</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">McCormick</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Chicago</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-06-12">
                                    <hi rend="italic">June 12, 1917</hi></date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received June 14</hi>.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LR1">Lansing</persName></hi>: I enclose a cablegram from our
                            correspondent in Stockholm which I thought best not to print. I feel,
                            however, that the subject matter should come to your attention.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert R. McCormick</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Correspondent in
                                        Stockholm</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Editor of the
                                        Chicago “Tribune”</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-06-12">
                                        <hi rend="italic">June 12, 1917</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Socialist delegates here wholly cut from communication with American
                                Socialists, receiving no answers to cablegrams or letters nor any
                                answer to May 29 message in which <persName>Branting</persName> and
                                    <persName>Huysmans</persName> cabled <persName corresp="#p_WHR1">Wilson</persName> on behalf conference that hoped statement
                                Washington refused American delegates passports to Stockholm was
                                “only misunderstanding because conference was convened on principles
                                laid down in your Senate speech and definite refusal by American
                                Republic would not be understood in democratic countries.”</p>
                            <p>Lacking reply to this message and being unable receive word from
                                American Socialists, Stockholm delegates completely in dark
                                concerning possible bearings of conference on America. Comment
                                un-bitterly but wonderingly on this situation, saying: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>We here neither to play politics nor inflame world, but by
                                        interchange views to assuage cruel conditions afflicting
                                        world and lowering civilization. We convinced piling on
                                        unnecessary difficulties <pb facs="0817" n="743" xml:id="pg_743"/> hurt world more than hurt Socialists.
                                        We here to study, discuss and accumulate material for humane
                                        ends. Only if these difficulties from outside are made will
                                        conference be fruitless, otherwise timely.</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>To <hi rend="italic">Tribune’s</hi> question concerning what European
                                delegates thought would be effect of American participation in
                                conference, reply: “Very useful because we believe American
                                Socialist would take truly international views, thereby helping
                                clear situation.”</p>
                            <p>Undoubtedly been efforts certain section foreign correspondents to
                                belittle conference by ridicule and distortion of aims; your
                                correspondent was addressed these words: “What you think of joining
                                campaign to present these fellows as here on party funds and having
                                good time?” Though suggestion made half in levity, it personally
                                insulting and treasonable to humanity. Truth is preliminary
                                conferences doing more hard work daily than done in Stockholm
                                legations weekly. Members far from living in luxury, stay modest
                                hotels. One representative important foreign news service remarked
                                half dozen times last fortnight <hi rend="italic">à propos</hi>
                                tenor his dispatches on conference: “I think I have killed it.”
                                Meanwhile work goes on and conviction growing among many cautious
                                observers that in ultimate effect governmental anti-conference
                                policies will prove shortsighted and that governments may discover
                                they have forced peace by fighting peace.</p>
                            <p>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SP1">Scheidemann</persName> and German
                                Majority delegation confers with Dutch-Scandinavian Committee Monday
                                morning. German Minority delegation arrives Stockholm Monday.
                                Dutch-Scandinavian Committee says whether two delegations meet
                                depends wholly on their individual wishes.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>