<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-06-08T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-06-08T03:00:00-05:00" n="112" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d112">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/9070: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-06-08T16:00:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">June 8,
                                        1927—4 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received 7:13
                            p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>626. Your No. 243 and No. 244 of June 3.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The reply of the commander in chief to telegram No. 243 was
                                forwarded in my No. 623, June 7, 6 p.m.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>I have sought to keep in mind, in dealing with question of
                                possibly withdrawing Legation from Peking, not only the
                                responsibility with which your telegram 146 of April 12 charged me
                                in respect to determination of a state of facts, but in addition the
                                peculiar difficulties confronting you because of the trend of
                                opinion at home regarding China. As I understand it your problem is
                                to give American lives and property in China the fullest protection
                                without laying open our Government to the charge of taking
                                aggressive action in general against the Chinese people or perhaps
                                in particular against the so-called Nationalist movement.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Concerning the effect the withdrawing of our Legation from Peking
                                would have upon the Chinese, my conviction is that such a step would
                                have a stunning effect throughout China upon the generality of the
                                Chinese people, who would regard it as a calamity that in face of a
                                negligible amount of danger the Government of the United States
                                should at the most critical moment of their modern history withdraw
                                American representation from the crucial point of international
                                relationships. The Chinese could not but view our action with
                                feelings of disillusionment and even of suspicion perhaps that with
                                deliberate purpose we had left the field to the Japanese and the
                                British who have more realistic methods and larger interests. From a
                                Chinese point of view it would appear that we had renounced our
                                concern or interest in the readjustments which might be expected to
                                follow after the Nationalists take the capital. The Chinese would
                                recognize that our value would be heavily discounted as a factor in
                                China’s international situation if we were to withdraw now when
                                there is no reasonable apprehension of danger here to the lives and
                                property of foreigners and when others, the British and Japanese in
                                particular, are choosing to remain, and thereby negative our
                                influence in support of our own principles of the integrity of China
                                and the open door with all they imply, and for years to come debar
                                us from any effective participation in questions of international
                                import concerning China.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>In compliance with your wishes I am taking steps of a preliminary
                                character with a view to possible removal of this Legation; but <pb facs="0241" n="133" xml:id="pg_133"/> since any visible measures
                                would confirm reports already circulating and would in large measure
                                make operative at once the unfavorable consequences attending actual
                                removal, I am not taking any overt action to that end until either
                                some unexpected development has occurred which would warrant
                                changing the present estimate of the facts or else until you may
                                have instructed me to remove the Legation in any case.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">MacMurray</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>