<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-01-15T01:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-01-15T01:00:00-05:00" n="19" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d19">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/8061: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-01-15T14:00:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">January 15,
                                        1927—2 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received 3:37 p.m.<note n="40" xml:id="d19fn40">Telegram in three
                            sections.</note>]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>32. Your 9, January 11, 6 p.m.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>My answer to your third inquiry is affirmative, especially in view
                                of telegram from Hankow January 12, 4 p.m., transmitted in my
                                telegram 29, January 14, 1 p.m.<note n="41" xml:id="d19fn41"><hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_241">p.
                                    241</ref>.</note> Conditions are so inflammable in Shanghai that
                                there is certain to be an explosion if the Nationalists extend
                                control to that area unless the leaders of the Nationalists are
                                convinced definitely that the limit of tolerance has been reached by
                                the foreign powers and that the powers are prepared wholeheartedly
                                to unite on a stand for the protection of their nationals and
                                interests in Shanghai. The situation is one in which, it is my firm
                                belief, the only possible escape from the necessity to employ force
                                is an obvious readiness to employ it. With that in view there can be
                                no distinction, I think, between defending the International
                                Settlement and defending the lives and the property of residents.
                                The forces for the purpose must, in case of need arising, defend
                                what they are able to without differentiating among the nationals
                                involved and without regard to questions of boundary. To distinguish
                                between concerted attack by organized forces and mob violence would
                                prove to be equally impossible. Throughout their recent campaign the
                                characteristic tactics of the Nationalists have been to filter their
                                men into hostile territory where later they would assemble as an
                                organized and armed force. When in the midst of dealing with mob
                                violence within the Settlement it is altogether likely that foreign
                                forces would suddenly find themselves confronted with such
                                Nationalist units. Therefore scope of any defensive measures to be
                                taken to safeguard American and other foreign lives and property
                                ought to be left to discretionary judgment of the military
                                commanders.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In all probability the immediate situation of Americans who are in
                                the interior, particularly in the part of the Yangtze Valley now
                                under control, would be affected unfavorably if we joined other
                                powers in defending Shanghai. However, my opinion is that this
                                danger would in fact not be any greater than that which would be
                                produced by a failure on our part to participate in such defense,
                                which would inevitably carry with it a conviction that we are not
                                ready to look out for our own. On the other hand the probability <pb facs="0156" n="48" xml:id="pg_48"/> is that the situation of
                                Americans in the interior would be improved in the long run by
                                demonstrating resolution to protect our nationals.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Instructions have been issued by the British Government to its
                                consuls within the area controlled by the Nationalists to advise all
                                British subjects in interior places to concentrate at ports where
                                protection can be given them. I understand that heed is not very
                                generally given these warnings except in Szechuan and along the
                                middle Yangtze in those places which have been affected more
                                immediately by aggressive Nationalist action. I have given
                                discretion in the matter already to consuls within Nationalist
                                territory and now contemplate, whether it is decided to defend
                                Shanghai or not, giving warning to Americans resident in the river
                                region above Nanking that they should gather at places where their
                                protection is possible. However, in view of grave responsibility
                                which is involved in advising the abandonment of their institutions
                                and livelihood and of the doubt whether in removing to a river port
                                they would not expose themselves to an at least equal personal
                                danger, I believe that until the possibility of serious trouble at
                                Shanghai appears to be more imminent and certain it is premature to
                                give such advice.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>With regard to protective measures at Shanghai I understand that
                                the British Government has as yet not arrived at a decision on what
                                to do. This whole question has been discussed with me by my British
                                colleague with utmost frankness. … I for my part am firmly of the
                                opinion that the British, however reluctant they are to face the
                                issue, must eventually decide to defend Shanghai at all costs; this
                                not alone because of their enormous interests at Shanghai but also
                                because of political and economic consequences to them elsewhere
                                both in China and India if they surrendered their position at
                                Shanghai. I am informed by the Japanese Minister that he has
                                received no definite instructions in regard to the matter, but that
                                he himself believes his Government intends to send for the defense
                                of Shanghai at least as many men as the British or we do. He states
                                further that his Government has not indicated any tendency to
                                distinguish between maintaining the integrity of the Settlement and
                                protecting Japanese and other lives and property. The French
                                military attaché declares his Government is determined to defend its
                                Shanghai Concession at all costs and doubtless is acting
                                independently for that purpose, but unquestionably in the event of
                                actual trouble it would be necessary for the defense of the French
                                Concession and of the International Settlement to be coordinated.
                                The Italian Minister indicated to me that while his Government has
                                only a small landing force available it is prepared to join the
                                British, Japanese, and ourselves in any defensive measures that may
                                be undertaken.</item>
                            <pb facs="0157" n="49" xml:id="pg_49"/>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>I know you understand that an attempt to foresee the possible
                                developments at Shanghai cannot be more than a calculation of
                                eventualities which are likely to arise in a situation having
                                several indeterminable factors. My best surmise as to the
                                probabilities is all I can give you; and I may err perhaps on the
                                side of apprehension. However, in a case potentially involving the
                                lives of thousands of American nationals, I submit that we must face
                                deliberately the most serious contingencies and plan for the
                                possibility of the worst one that may eventuate. I am the more
                                disposed to take this view because I have a well assured conviction
                                that our best security for avoiding possibility of burning and
                                looting of a port which is one of the foremost in the world and the
                                massacre of a number of our nationals, with the various consequences
                                which might result, is to be found in our possible joining with
                                other interested powers in giving a resolute and wholehearted
                                cooperation to make what indeed would be the last ditch stand in
                                China as to foreign rights and foreign interests. We have our moral
                                and legal responsibilities for China jointly with British and other
                                nationalities participating in the International Settlement. So that
                                we may at once know where we stand, I cannot recommend too urgently
                                that the Department endeavor without delay to obtain assurances
                                concerning the attitudes of the British and the Japanese, the powers
                                principally involved. Unquestionably the hands of those responsible
                                for maintaining law and order in Shanghai would be strengthened if
                                you would let it be known generally, at the same time as inquiry is
                                made as to the attitudes of those Governments, that our Government
                                is ready to carry out its part in defending Shanghai in case use of
                                force against the safety and the interest of our people should
                                compel us to resort to force in order to protect them.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">MacMurray</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>