<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="372" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d372">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/8631: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-04-09T13:00:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">April 9,
                                        1927—1 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received—9:30
                            p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>390. Legation’s telegrams of April 7, number 366, 8 a.m., and April 8,
                            number 377, 9 a.m.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The sector held formally [<hi rend="italic">formerly?</hi>] by the
                                Russian Legation guard has constituted hiatus in the defense system
                                of the Legation quarter since the reoccupation of the Russian
                                property by the Soviet. As a result of the Chinese raid upon Russian
                                properties on April 6th it is disclosed that not only is this sector
                                undefended but it is occupied by a group that is actively
                                antagonistic to the foreign interests for which the quarter was
                                designed by the Boxer protocol<note n="45" xml:id="d372fn45">Art.
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>, <ref target="frus1901#pg_316"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1901,
                                        appendix (Affairs in China), p. 316</ref>.</note> to be a
                                defensible base.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>A recommendation to the diplomatic representatives of the protocol
                                powers was formulated at a meeting yesterday by the commandants of
                                the five Legation guards, to the effect that the portion of the
                                former Russian Legation which formed a part of the quarter’s system
                                of defense should be turned over to those who are responsible for
                                defense of the Legation quarter, in order that the proper defense
                                thereof might be provided for in the same manner as was done in the
                                cases of the German, Austrian and Dutch defense sectors upon the
                                withdrawal of their respective guards.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Yesterday evening the interested Ministers considered this
                                recommendation and all were in full agreement in regard to the
                                urgent military necessity of guarding the former Russian sector,
                                although it was felt by the British Minister, the Italian Chargé
                                d’Affaires, and me that we must request instructions in this
                                connection. All rights pursuant to the Boxer protocol having now
                                been professedly renounced by the Soviets, occupation of the former
                                Russian guard property is anomalous, and the interested Ministers
                                felt that no more of it should be occupied than is actually
                                necessary for the purpose of defending the quarter, the remainder of
                                the property being left free for the Russians to use.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>A discussion has been fixed for April 12th. For the purpose of
                                this discussion it is earnestly requested that you approve my
                                joining, in accordance with the following formula, in giving
                                authorization for action upon the recommendation of the guard
                                commandants: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“It is a general principle that the defense wall of the
                                        diplomatic quarter must, in case of emergency, be manned by
                                        the available forces of the several Legation guards. In
                                        accordance with this principle, it should be arranged that
                                        troops belonging to the other guards will <pb facs="0427" n="319" xml:id="pg_319"/> in the future occupy that
                                        portion of the wall formerly assigned to the Russian
                                        Legation guard.”</p>
                                </quote></item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The occupation of this property by the international guards
                                should, it is obviously desirable, be achieved by arrangement with
                                the Chinese who remain in possession, rather than by seizure (in the
                                case either of occupation prior to or during an actual attack upon
                                the quarter). In view of this desirability, until such time as this
                                question is decided, the Senior Minister is authorizing the Chinese,
                                day by day, to enter the quarter for further investigation.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">MacMurray</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>