<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-12-16T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-12-16T07:00:00-05:00" n="398" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d398">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.8007/37: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-12-16T20:00:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">December 16,
                                        1927—8 p.m.</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received December 16—8:30
                                    p.m.<note n="70" xml:id="d398fn70">Telegram in two
                                    sections.</note>]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>1106. Legation’s Number 1045, November 29, noon.</p>
                        <p>1. Following from Canton: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“December 16, noon. In reply to your telegram November 10,
                                        noon.<note n="71" xml:id="d398fn71">Not found in Department
                                        files.</note> Believe that the present moment is
                                    inauspicious time to present either joint or identic note on the
                                    subject of piracy. Present Cantonese military coterie in order
                                    to clear Kwangtung of Kwangsi troops are enlisting support of
                                    both bandits and pirates. I am convinced and such is testimony
                                    of many Chinese that prominent Cantonese general in this group
                                    is leader and under-cover man for various bands operating in the
                                    vicinity of Canton. Recent looted American cargo pirated within
                                    ten miles of Canton was sold in open market and also names of
                                    shops dealing in this pirated cargo were given to <pb facs="0448" n="340" xml:id="pg_340"/> Chinese authorities;
                                    no action was taken. Li Chai-sum<note n="72" xml:id="d398fn72">Also known as Li Chi-shen, military commander of Canton and
                                        supporter of Chiang Kai-shek in Kwangtung Province.</note>
                                    just previous to departure attempted without success to transfer
                                    this general to another theatre of operations.</p>
                                <p>Also present leaders were former Reds and within limits they are
                                    curbing radical laborers and showing a more friendly feeling
                                    towards foreigners. This is being done partly under the
                                    influence of the Foreign Commissioner Chu Chao-hsin, Chinese
                                    former representative at Geneva, who assumed the duties of
                                    office November 26th. If at the crisis of Cantonese attempt to
                                    clear the Province of Kwangsi troops the powers took action of
                                    the nature suggested, it might drive them towards the Russians
                                    again or have antiforeign repercussions.</p>
                                <p>Believe that offer of powers to cooperate in suppression of
                                    piracy would be ineffectual since British have not attained any
                                    success by similar offers in the past.</p>
                                <p>Another difficulty is that the Cantonese authorities at Canton
                                    may not exercise effective control over particular district in
                                    which any one band operates, the members of which may be working
                                    in collusion with local military forces hostile to political
                                    group in Canton.</p>
                                <p>Both Department and commander in chief appear to be under
                                    misapprehension regarding piracies of American ships in
                                    Kwangtung waters. Since July 1926 five Standard Oil Company
                                    boats have been pirated. Total losses amount to $53,000 Hong
                                    Kong currency. Three of these have occurred since August 1927 up
                                    shallow creeks where present Navy boats or those under
                                    construction cannot penetrate. All these five piracies occurred
                                    since practice of convoy was instituted and at times when
                                    company believed that [those?] districts in place [<hi rend="italic">particular?</hi>] were safe and convoy was not
                                    needed. If company had made continuous shipments as in past
                                    years without convoy at all times it is doubtful if a single
                                    shipment would have gone through unmolested.</p>
                                <p>Believe the commander in chief is in error regarding connection
                                    between boycott and piracies.</p>
                                <p>Believe that when local situation is slightly stabilized an
                                    opportunity will offer itself to make representations to local
                                    authorities by joint or similar note in concert with other
                                    powers, but feel that subsequent action if necessary should be
                                    taken only as the necessity arose either singly or in
                                    cooperation with the British at the discretion of the commander
                                    in chief and patrol commander after consulting consulate and
                                    Chinese authorities.</p>
                                <p>Am convinced that naval authorities cannot deal effectually with
                                    situation unless suggestion contained at the bottom of page 3 of
                                    my despatch number 661 of October 31st [<hi rend="italic">21st</hi>]<note n="73" xml:id="d398fn73">Not
                                        printed.</note> is carried out.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>2. The suggestion of American consul at Canton referred to in last
                            paragraph of his telegram is as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“I am of the opinion that the only way in which to cope with this
                                    menace is the stationing of two well-armed launches to act as
                                    auxiliaries to whatever gunboat is stationed in the harbor at
                                    the time. <pb facs="0449" n="341" xml:id="pg_341"/> These armed
                                    launches should be approximately 70 feet long by 16 feet broad,
                                    should have a horsepower of 200 to 250 and a speed of
                                    approximately 18 to 20 knots. They should be armed with 2
                                    quick-firing guns and about 4 to 8 machine guns. An officer with
                                    12 men would be a sufficient crew to man one of these auxiliary
                                    vessels. So far, the American naval authorities at Canton have
                                    been unable to follow these pirates up the shallow creeks and
                                    rivers where they usually take the pirated ship and cargo.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">MacMurray</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>