<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-01-25T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-01-25T07:00:00-05:00" n="403" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d403">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/8132: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Mayer</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-01-25T20:00:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">January 25,
                                        1927—8 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received January 25—3:55
                                p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>79. 1. Following from American consul general at Hankow: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“January 24, 6 p.m. Eugene Ch’en called me to his office late
                                    yesterday afternoon and handed me the statement which I
                                    telegraphed last night.<note n="87" xml:id="d403fn87"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note></p>
                                <p>Ch’en is greatly excited over the Belgian treaty negotiations and
                                    says that if the Belgians enter in [to] a new treaty with the
                                    Chinese regime at Peking, Belgians in the territory controlled
                                    by the Nationalists will find themselves in great disfavor and
                                    perhaps the object of retaliatory measures. He is even more
                                    concerned however lest the American Government should suddenly
                                    decide to negotiate a new treaty with China possibly as an
                                    outgrowth of the Porter resolution<note n="88" xml:id="d403fn88"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_341">p.
                                            341</ref>.</note> and he hinted that your return to
                                    Peking might have some connection with such an undertaking. He
                                    expressed the view quite emphatically that negotiations for new
                                    treaties between the foreign powers and the Chinese authorities
                                    at Peking at this juncture when the wave of nationalism gives
                                    promise of shortly spreading over the whole country, would be
                                    particularly inadvisable and would adversely affect the
                                    interests of the foreign perils [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] and
                                    the Chinese alike. His view is that if the powers do not yet
                                    feel warranted in dealing with Nationalist Government in the
                                    matter of new treaties they should at least hold aloof for the
                                    present and await developments. He emphasized, as he has once
                                    before, that he deplored any action which might lead to a
                                    division of the country—that is, a Northern and Southern
                                    government—and stated that such negotiations would tend to bring
                                    that about; that in any event new treaties negotiated now with
                                    the Peking regime would not be recognized by the Nationalists
                                    either here or in case the Cantonese should extend their power
                                    to Peking in due course.</p>
                                <p>As between the new treaty negotiations and the two and a half
                                    percent surtaxes soon to be levied by the Northern Government to
                                    which Ch’en is vigorously and persistently opposed, the Minister
                                    for Foreign Affairs is greatly disturbed, but seems to find
                                    satisfaction in the fact that Japan appears friendly to
                                    Nationalist aspirations. I venture to suggest that Saburi did
                                    some very effective work here from the point of view of
                                    cultivating a good understanding.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>2. Comment will follow in connection with reply to Department’s 22,
                            January 24, 11 a.m.,<note n="89" xml:id="d403fn89">Not printed.</note>
                            just to hand, which I have to despatch tomorrow morning (January
                                26th).<note n="89" xml:id="d403fn90">Not printed.</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Mayer</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>