<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-01-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-01-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="406" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d406">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/8285</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far
                                Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-01-28"><hi rend="italic">January 28,
                                1927</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary</hi>: I went to see the British
                            Ambassador as you suggested with reference to the Shanghai situation. I
                            told him that, in conversation with you, you had been led to understand
                            that the British Government would not be averse to discussions for a
                            change in the status of the International Settlement at Shanghai. I said
                            to him that we were contemplating sending an instruction to our Minister
                            at Peking, directing him to see what could be done toward taking the
                            question of the neutrality of the area of the International Settlement
                            at Shanghai up with the contending factions concerned. The Ambassador
                            stated that he thought this would be a good thing to do. I said that I
                            felt certain that to make such advances would bring a request for our
                            attitude with regard to the future status of the Settlement and I
                            wondered whether the British Government would be willing that we should
                            say that we were prepared to negotiate for a change in the status of the
                            Settlement. The Ambassador stated that he was not instructed on the
                            matter and he did not think the British Government was prepared to go
                            that far. He said, after all, the Settlement was not American. I said
                            no, that three Powers were immediately concerned—the Japanese, British
                            and ourselves. He said, of course, there were other Powers involved. I
                            assented to this. He stated that he thought that we could not go further
                            than to express our willingness to consult the Powers with a view to
                            discovering what their intentions would be in the matter.</p>
                        <closer><signed>N[<hi rend="smallcaps">elson</hi>] T. J[<hi rend="smallcaps">ohnson</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>