<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in China ( (MacMurray))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1927v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d433</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">433</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1927-02-15T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1927-02-15T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-02-15T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-02-15T16:00:00-05:00" n="433"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d433">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.512/542: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-02-15T16:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 15, 1927—4 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>61. Your 116, February 7, 9 a.m.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>For some time Department has realized the increasing difficulty of
                        obtaining complete recognition of the rights of United States nationals in
                        China conferred by the existing treaties between the United States and
                        China.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>It is not possible to use military and naval forces of the United States
                        to enforce the rights guaranteed under the existing treaties; therefore,
                        until the present treaties can be replaced by new and effective treaty
                        relations Department is of the opinion that a policy of patience and
                        watchfulness is the only path that can be followed.</item>
                    <pb facs="0491" n="383" xml:id="pg_383"/>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>With reference to taxes and imposts levied on American goods imported into
                        China and goods purchased in China by American citizens for export, the
                        Department is of the opinion that the Legation and the American Consulates
                        should carefully watch the situation and report in detail on all such taxes,
                        the methods used in their collection and the authorities by whom they are
                        established. While the Department is disposed to agree with you that
                        protests against the imposition of such taxes in direct violation of strict
                        treaty provisions are likely to be futile and in general should not be made
                        henceforth, it believes, nevertheless, that the Legation and the Consulates
                        should be on the alert to take up with the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi>
                        authorities any case where an American citizen or interest can show that he
                        or it has been subjected to discriminatory treatment. In replying to the
                        telegram of February 10, 10 a.m., from Foochow you will instruct the Consul
                        in this sense.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The Department would like to have your comment by mail despatch on some
                        general policy throughout China with regard to the payment of local
                        municipal taxes by American citizens. By municipal taxes the Department has
                        in mind police, fire protection, street maintenance and similar taxes. In
                        this connection see Department’s written instruction No. 405 of May 22,
                            1923.<note n="34" xml:id="d433fn34">
                            <ref target="frus1923v01#pg_582">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1923, vol. <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 582</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Department is of the opinion that a general instruction should be issued
                        by the Legation to the Consuls in China directing them to encourage American
                        citizens to make use of such facilities as may be offered by the modern
                        Chinese courts (Shen Pan Ting) in cases against Chinese. Department believes
                        that the facilities of the modern courts should be given a fair test. You
                        will instruct the American Consul General at Hankow in this sense when
                        replying to his telegram of February 10, 3 p.m.<note n="35"
                            xml:id="d433fn35">See telegram No. 133, Feb. 11, from the Minister in
                            China, <ref target="#pg_466">p. 466</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Department desires that the Legation study the question of the provisions
                        which should be written into a new treaty to take the place of existing
                        treaties between the United States and China and that you report by mail
                        your suggestions in this connection.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kellogg</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
