<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-06-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-06-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="440" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d440">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.512/573</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-06-02"><hi rend="italic">June 2,
                                1927</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 546</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department has received your despatch
                            No. 963, of March 16, 1927, transmitting your comments on a general
                            policy throughout China with regard to the payment by American citizens
                            of local municipal taxes.</p>
                        <p>The Department notes your segregation of the different types of Chinese
                            municipalities into more or less distinct categories and approves your
                            suggestion that the policy to be followed should be adapted to the
                            different circumstances encountered.</p>
                        <p>It seems necessary to observe, in regard to the taxation of American
                            citizens residing either in foreign concessions or in areas that were
                            formerly foreign concessions but are now controlled by Chinese
                            authorities, that American consular officials should be careful to avoid
                            entering into any commitment as to the enforcibility of municipal
                            regulations and taxes in the consular courts. Since this is a question
                            of legal interpretation, it can be answered only by a judicial ruling in
                            an appropriate case. (See in this connection the Department’s telegram
                            No. 131 of May 25, 1922, concerning the Kuling Estate).<note n="44" xml:id="d440fn44">Not printed.</note> The Department expects,
                            nevertheless, to be given the opportunity to express an opinion, if it
                            desires to do so, regarding municipal regulations designed to be
                            applicable to American citizens, in order that it may ascertain whether
                            the rights properly enjoyed by such citizens are infringed upon.</p>
                        <p>In regard to Chinese municipalities other than those embraced within the
                            categories already mentioned, the Department concurs in your view that
                            it would be desirable to instruct American citizens, when demands are
                            made by the Chinese authorities for the payment of municipal taxes, that
                            the American Government advises them to pay, as a voluntary
                            contribution, the rates levied on Chinese and other foreign citizens,
                            when such rates are, in the opinion of the Legation, reasonable and when
                            appropriate municipal services are rendered in return.</p>
                        <p>It is desired that you issue a circular instruction to American consular
                            officials in China in this sense, or special instructions as the
                            necessity therefor may arise, as you deem most appropriate. The
                            Department desires that the Legation should keep it fully informed in
                            regard to developments in these matters.</p>
                        <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph
                                    C. Grew</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>