<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-10-07T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-10-07T08:00:00-05:00" n="482" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d482">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.512/690: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Mayer</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-10-07T21:00:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">October 7,
                                        1927—9 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received October 7—4:27
                                p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>914. 1. Following from American consul general, Canton,<note n="63" xml:id="d482fn63">Jay C. Huston, consul in charge, in absence of
                                Consul General Douglas Jenkins.</note> which was not repeated to
                            Department awaiting clarification not yet received.</p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“September 30, 4 p.m. Local authorities have announced the collection
                                of ten percent of the surtaxes of two and a half percent which were
                                originally assessed to pay off Canton Hong Kong strikers. The
                                original two and a half surtax was abolished but it would appear
                                that the strikers have not received the proceeds. The usual formal
                                protest which I am making will be uneffective unless the Legation is
                                prepared to take other measures such as the releasing of seized
                                cargoes by our Navy. Suggest Legation consult British Legation at
                                Peking.”</p>
                        </quote>
                        <p>2. This morning Japanese Minister called meeting consisting of himself,
                            British and French Ministers and myself to consider situation. <pb facs="0528" n="420" xml:id="pg_420"/> Inquiry was made of me whether
                            American Government would be willing, should necessity arise, to put
                            into effect at Canton consular clearance procedure adopted at Shanghai.
                            I stated that I could not give definite answer and that anyway I felt
                            position at Canton was not similar to that at Shanghai; that without
                            serious consideration and further information from American consul at
                            Canton I was not prepared recommend adoption there of consular clearance
                            procedure unless it was prepared for eventual force protective measures
                            which my instructions clearly did not endeavor visage [<hi rend="italic">envisage?</hi>].</p>
                        <p>3. I was forced to leave meeting at this juncture owing previous
                            engagement. After my departure three Ministers concerned decided on the
                            following action.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>Telegraphic instructions to their respective consuls general at
                                Canton to proceed together to see the local authorities and make
                                representations in strong terms, warning them that the import tariff
                                must not be arbitrarily altered without the prior consent of the
                                powers. The consuls general to use such terms as, after consultation
                                with one another, they consider best.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>To inform their respective Governments of the action taken and to
                                recommend that if unsuccessful they should fall back on the
                                procedure adopted at Shanghai.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>4. I was asked if I could join in above telegraphic instructions. In view
                            of your 304, August 2, 1 p.m.,<note n="64" xml:id="d482fn64"><hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_446">p.
                                446</ref>.</note> and similar directions, I did not feel I could as
                            I was apprehensive that they might convey impression that they authorize
                            adoption of threatening attitude with implication of use of force
                            particularly in respect of the last sentence. British Minister with whom
                            I have just discussed the matter assures me to the contrary but in order
                            to be entirely safe I decided to instruct American consul at Canton as
                            follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“October 7, 6 p.m. Your September 30, 4 p.m.</p>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Paragraph number 1. You may join with your consular
                                        colleagues concerned in protesting against any arbitrary
                                        alternation [<hi rend="italic">alteration?</hi>] of the
                                        present import tariff without the consent of the powers. You
                                        should not in any circumstances however join in any
                                        representations which would threaten or imply the use of
                                        force by the United States in support of treaty
                                        rights.</item>
                                    <item>Paragraph number 2. Please telegraph me at once in full
                                        your comment on the feasibility of adopting at Canton the
                                        procedure now in force at Shanghai in respect of consular
                                        clearances in the event your protest [is?]
                                        unsuccessful.”</item>
                                </list>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>5. I trust this is in line with your desire to maintain cooperation with
                            other interested powers while at the same time not involving <pb facs="0529" n="421" xml:id="pg_421"/> United States in use of force
                            for protection of our treaty rights or conveying any such threat.</p>
                        <p>6. I shall telegraph further concerning feasibility of adoption at Canton
                            of Shanghai procedure after receiving Huston’s report in this.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Mayer</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>