<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in China ( (MacMurray) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1927v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d8</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">8</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1927-06-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1927-06-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-06-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-06-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="8"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d8">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/9291</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-06-22">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 22, 1927</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received August 8.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1099</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Adverting to the Department’s instruction No. 78,
                    of October 9th, 1925,<note n="18" xml:id="d8fn18">Not printed.</note> I have the
                    honor to transmit herewith enclosed a summary of events and conditions in China
                    during the month of May, 1927.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">J. V. A. MacMurray</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Extracts]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Summary of Events and Conditions in China During May
                            1927</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The month of May, which witnessed a well coordinated advance on the part of
                        the various army groups opposing the Ankuochun and <pb facs="0120" n="12"
                            xml:id="pg_12"/> its allies, and a resultant increase in the tenseness
                        of the situation in North China, was also characterized by a revival of
                        military activity and politico-military maneuvering of a confusing and
                        frequently abortive character, there seldom having been a time since the
                        establishment of the republic when it was so difficult to determine exactly
                        what was happening in various parts of China and what the prospects were of
                        any military faction overcoming its rivals. Press despatches and reports
                        from other sources reaching Peking from day to day during the month were
                        often contradictory in their accounts of the situation in the several
                        centers and it was not an infrequent occurrence, especially at the outset of
                        the Southern offensive, for both sides in an encounter, and sometimes even a
                        third party, simultaneously to claim victory or deny defeat.</p>
                    <p>At least nine separate factions were engaged during May in the fight for the
                        military control of China. Under the leadership of Chang Tso-lin three
                        principal groups made up the Ankuochun. They were the Fengtien, or Mukden
                        party; the Chihli-Shantung forces under Chang Tsung-chang; and Sun
                        Chuan-fang’s reorganized forces along the Grand Canal north of the Yangtze.
                        The other six main elements were: Chiang Kai-shek at Nanking and Shanghai;
                        the radical Hankow remainder of the original Canton Government whose armies
                        are under T’ang Sheng-chih; the Kuominchun under Feng Yu-hsiang in Shensi
                        and western Honan; Chin Yun-ao, a lone General attacking the Fengtien troops
                        in Honan; a Hupeh group of two generals, Yang Sen and Hsia Tao-yin, who have
                        declared war on the Hankow Government; and finally the famous General Yen
                        Hsi-shan, <hi rend="italic">Tupan</hi> of Shansi, who had not, during May,
                        declared himself for or against any faction.</p>
                    <p>Instead of having been able to take advantage of the diplomatic gains made
                        during the Washington Conference, China now finds itself in a period when
                        foreign men and women dare not dwell in the interior of the country, when
                        property is nowhere safe and when loosely organized bands of soldiers and
                        bandits roam over disorganized and often devastated provinces.</p>
                    <p>One of the major causes of disturbed conditions in the country, has been
                        Soviet influence within the Kuomintang. The communists, foreign and Chinese
                        alike, seized the opportunity afforded them to put their political and
                        economic theories into execution and met at first with considerable success.
                        Lately Soviet influence has been waning to the extent that the
                        impracticability of their theories, under the present organization of
                        Chinese society, is being demonstrated. Since the results attained during
                        the past year have been stupendous the communistic elements bid fair,
                        however, to take down with them to defeat, if this takes place as seemed
                        probable during May, the Kuomintang as that party was originally organized.
                        As foreshadowing <pb facs="0121" n="13" xml:id="pg_13"/> eventual
                        dissolution Mr. Jenkins reported early in May from Canton, the party’s
                        original headquarters, that the Kuomintang was thought already to have
                        ceased to exist as a political entity and that there was grave likelihood of
                        a disintegration into a number of provincial military governments similar to
                        those prevailing previous to 1925.</p>
                    <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Military Affairs</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>In regard to military activity a practical deadlock existed, during the first
                        two weeks of the month, among the various groups engaged in the civil war in
                        China which was broken, during the last fifteen days of May, in a
                        coordinated offensive all along the North China front by the armies of
                        Chiang Kai-shek, in Kiangsu and Anhwei; of T’ang Sheng-chih in Honan; and of
                        the Kuominchun under Feng Yu-hsiang in the West. Coordination was achieved
                        in the face of a multitude of internal jealousies and distrusts, in spite of
                        the apparent split between the Nanking and Hankow factions of the
                        Kuomintang, and in spite of a certain individualism on the part of Feng
                        Yu-hsiang. In this relation the Legation’s Military Attaché pointed out that
                        the mere synchronization of the movements of three individual army groups
                        over five hundred miles of front, at a time when communications were in a
                        most defective state, was a clear indication of the excellence of the
                        Russian staff-work involved.</p>
                    <p>T’ang Sheng-chih left Hankow on May 1st, to lead the northern expedition, all
                        traffic except military being suspended at that end of the Hankow-Peking
                        line. There seemed to be an evident desire on the part of the Hankow faction
                        to lead the advance against the Mukden forces, rather than leave that task
                        to Chiang Kai-shek, and the first days of May found the 3rd, 4th and 11th
                        armies on the move northward. The Hankow Government, well known to be in
                        serious financial difficulties, was apparently staking everything on the
                        outcome of their northern expedition. On May 7th it was estimated that about
                        30,000 troops had been sent up the railway line since the drive began, only
                        a few remaining in Hankow, there being no visible signs of conflict between
                        the radical faction there and the Nanking elements.</p>
                    <p>However, in spite of the determination displayed by Hankow, Chiang Kai-shek’s
                        offensive up the Tientsin-Pukow railway would seem to have been the first to
                        develop. On the 11th reports from Nanking indicated that the bulk of Chiang
                        Kai-shek’s armies were endeavoring to cross the Yangtze at three points;
                        near Wuhu, 10 miles above Nanking, and near Chinkiang, with a general
                        flanking attack against the northern forces along the Tientsin-Pukow line to
                        commence on the 15th of the month.</p>
                    <pb facs="0122" n="14" xml:id="pg_14"/>
                    <p>On May 18th, in consequence of the increasing gravity of the situation in
                        North China, the Military Attaches of the American, British, French, Italian
                        and Japanese Legations submitted a confidential statement outlining the
                        following three circumstances which were to be considered emergencies
                        warranting a reenforcement of the contingents of their respective countries
                        in North China: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Any decisive defeat or large-scale disaffection of the Northern
                                forces south of the Lunghai Railway.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The withdrawal of the Northern forces from any part of the Lunghai
                                Railway.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>In the event of a Southern (Nationalist) advance against the
                                Northern Government, any invasion, insurrection and/or <hi
                                    rend="italic">coup d’etat</hi> north of the Lunghai
                                Railway.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Southern forces continued their successful advance and on May 31st, at
                        the end of the period covered by this report, the Fengtien army completed a
                        withdrawal across the Yellow River in good order on the Kaifeng-Kunghsien
                        front and occupied a position extending from the Yellow River to the army’s
                        main concentration line which was in the vicinity of Shihkiachwang. Sun
                        Chuan-fang and the Shantung forces under Chang Tsung-chang were at that time
                        organizing a general line on Haichow-Taierchwang and Hanchwang, 30 miles
                        north of Suchow junction and were covered by Chu Yu-pu just south of Suchow.
                        All the Northern troops were badly disorganized and the subordinate officers
                        were undependable but the Southern forces were not pressing further and were
                        in need of reorganization.</p>
                    <p>On May 30th the American, British, French and Italian Ministers were informed
                        by the Japanese Minister of his Government’s despatch of 2,000 troops to
                        Tsingtao from Dairen, a further contingent of 2,000 to be sent to the
                        Peking-Tientsin area should the situation seem to require it. It was
                        emphasized that the troops were sent for protective purposes only and that
                        they were to be withdrawn as soon as conditions warranted. An avowal, in so
                        definite a manner, of the determination of the Japanese Government to
                        provide protection for its nationals did much to lessen the potential
                        gravity of the situation prevailing in North China at the end of May.</p>
                    <p>While it was felt that the Legation Quarter might yet become the object of
                        mob violence during an interregnum, or conceivably be attacked in a
                        desultory fashion by outgoing Northerners or incoming Southerners, the
                        American Legation felt that the degree to which the Japanese had permitted
                        themselves to become engaged constituted an important factor in causing the
                        question of the contemplated withdrawal of the Legation from Peking, in
                        order to prevent a repetition of the Boxer siege, to be removed from
                        immediate consideration.</p>
                    <p>In regard to the general question of the reenforcement of foreign contingents
                        in North China the Military Attaché ascertained that by <pb facs="0123"
                            n="15" xml:id="pg_15"/> the middle of June the following approximate
                        increases in strength would have been accomplished: <list>
                            <item>British at Tientsin from 750 to 1250; at Peking from 167 to 350,
                                with possible further reenforcements up to 4,000 depending on
                                developments in June.</item>
                            <item>Japanese at Tientsin from 1,000 to 2,500, plus a brigade
                                headquarters, artillery and an aviation unit; at Peking from 307 to
                                800.</item>
                            <item>French at Tientsin from 1,850 to 2,400; at Peking from 228 to
                                478.</item>
                            <item>Italians at Peking from 146 to 246.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>In the matter of American reenforcements, the breaking of the Lunghai line,
                        constituting as it did one of the emergencies envisaged in the statement of
                        the Military Attaches, made it seem advisable to cause the 1,700 marines
                        available at Shanghai to be despatched to Tientsin for the protection of
                        American lives and property in North China, and a telegram requesting that
                        that be done was accordingly despatched, by the Legation, to the
                        Commander-in-Chief of the United States Asiatic Fleet, through the Consulate
                        General at Shanghai, on May 31st.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
