<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-05-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-05-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="187" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d187">
                        <head>187. Conversation Between President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and his Assistant for National Security Affairs
                                (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d187fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, White
                                House Tapes, Oval Office, Conversation No. 718–9. No classification
                                marking. According to his Daily Diary, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> met with <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> in the Oval Office from 10:59 to 12:11
                                p.m. The editors transcribed the portion of the conversation printed
                                here specifically for this volume.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-05-03">May 3, 1972</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>[Omitted here is a discussion between the President and <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> regarding what they perceived
                            as Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>’
                            efforts to get credit for <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>,
                            especially his effort to assert that there was a freeze on nuclear
                            submarines. Both participants assessed that <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> was trying possibly to derail the negotiations.
                            Regarding the talks with the <pb facs="0725" n="696" xml:id="pg_696"/>
                            North Vietnamese, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                            recommended to the President a walkout in protest. He contended that the
                            North Vietnamese had given him a weak proposal in Paris the day before
                            in order to prolong the negotiating process. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> noted that he had told them to stop playing
                            games and asserted the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> Government’s
                            right to defend its position. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> concluded that continuing with the plenary
                            meetings would be interpreted as “a very weak move.”]</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Let me analyze this thing
                            on the summit, and so forth, and particularly in view of the <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> thing. You’re absolutely right
                            that anything less than walking out is a weak move. What I would like to
                            see is and we can say, which does not indicate the total breakdown and
                            thereby lack of hope on the negotiating front. Now, you and I know
                            there’s no hope at all for tomorrow.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s right.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: On the other hand, we have
                            a hell of a lot of people being used on this particular point. You’ve
                            made this point often.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is further discussion where <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> noted that such a walkout would be met with great
                            enthusiasm by the hawks, but would turn loose critics in the Senate and
                            other matters.]</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Now, what we have to
                            realize is that in terms of the domestic front, that this kind of a
                            move, and I want to put it in the context of the bombing and the summit
                            thing, this kind of a move can have a good short-range effect—the
                            walkout. In the long-range, we have to consider it in the context with
                            what our plans are and what effect it’ll have. Now let’s look at the
                            summit. As I see the summit, and of course I’m the strongest proponent
                            of not making the summit hostage to Vietnam or Vietnam to the summit,
                            anyway, the cancellation of the summit, and incidentally, there can’t be
                            any halfway. We can say that we are going to postpone or that we aren’t
                            going to go at this time or that we’ll be glad to go at a later time
                            when the offensive is stopped, or this, that, or the other thing, and so
                            forth—I’m just trying to think of all of the language that we could work
                            up. First, analyzing it from the foreign standpoint, it will have a
                            beneficial impact, as you pointed out last night on Thieu. It will have
                            a—certainly some shock effect on Hanoi. It will have some effect on the
                            Russians, and more on that in a moment.</p>
                        <p>The question arises, what effect does it have here? The initial effect
                            would be, in my opinion, extremely favorable. The greatest President
                            puts everything on the line, stands up to the Russians, and so forth.
                            However, in getting the domestic thing out of the way first, because it
                            does have some bearing, we have to realize, that once we have canceled
                            the summit, that then we will unleash without any question, not simply
                            to cause, but we will unleash again particularly our attacks on Senators
                            and Congressmen who are presently off-balance; one, <pb facs="0726" n="697" xml:id="pg_697"/> because the summit is coming, and two,
                            because they think that something is going on, which you and I know is
                            poppycock. And you are correct, certainly, in your suggestion to the
                            Soviets, [that] if we cancel the summit, then we get turned around.
                            Their reaction could be one of two things. It could present a problem.
                            Their reaction, however, might be to say, “Well, the conference got
                            thrown down, something was lost, in spite of the fact that the President
                            said we’ll negotiate on bilateral issues and so forth.” That could come
                            at a later time. They could unleash their rather massive propaganda
                            efforts abroad and here in this country. And so, what would happen is
                            that over a period of time, the time that this action were taken, that
                            the immediate—I’m speaking now of the effect at home—the immediate
                            effect at home would very substantially erode. It would be favorable,
                            very favorable, at the beginning, and then it would erode, and it would
                            erode for a variety of reasons. It would erode because of course the
                            attack on our enemies which we must expect, which would be unleashed
                            [unclear] would be off balance. It would erode because the hopes for,
                            you know, peace and so forth, would be knocked down. And it would erode
                            also because there would be—we would have to participate in massive
                            attack [unclear] on the ground on the idea that the so-called <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> foreign policy had collapsed and
                            collapsed because of our insistence on seeing the Vietnam war through to
                            an honorable conclusion. That would be the argument that they would
                            make. And, we on our side, that of course it would be argued
                            tremendously that what they were doing, as I found out last night, that
                            we have to put them right into the arms of the Soviets, the Soviets
                            responsible for this war, who continues to supply them arms and supplies
                            at the present time.</p>
                        <p>Now, let’s come to the other point. At the heart of the matter is what
                            effect the cancellation of the summit would have on the outcome of the
                            war itself. If the cancellation of the summit very substantially
                            improves a chance for a favorable outcome in Vietnam, that is a decisive
                            factor. If, on the other hand, the cancellation of the summit has only a
                            marginal effect in that respect, and would of course [mean] the bombing
                            has a marginal effect, then we have to look at it another way, and that
                            way would be along this line. If we are looking at a situation here
                            where over a period of three years we have built in a masterful way a
                            new foreign policy. The China game, the Soviet game, its a very big
                            game. You and I both know that it’s a very difficult operation. The
                            Soviets have been liars and bastards and thugs, and so forth and so on.
                            We also know that at the present time we’ve got some American public
                            opinion developing along that line.</p>
                        <p>However, if we put it in perspective, I think we have to realize that if
                            we’re looking at the effect, the effect on the Democratic Convention
                            coming up July, and we’re looking at the election coming up in November,
                            at the effect on the election, I think that cold-bloodedly <pb facs="0727" n="698" xml:id="pg_698"/> we have to say this. First,
                            the heart of the matter is Vietnam and how it comes out. If Vietnam
                            comes out badly, the election is very seriously jeopardized anyway.
                            However, if Vietnam comes out badly, then we also cancel the summit. In
                            other words, if we cancel the summit and if it still comes out badly,
                            the election would certainly be down the tube, something which <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> and yourself would say would be a
                            very tragic thing. Because it would mean we would not live to fight
                            another day. God knows it, we need to, there’s so much that needs to be
                            done. You hear this military briefing and you realize that our military
                            has let us down—and that’s just one. But you need a new foreign policy,
                            and you need a new military policy, and so forth, and it’s not going to
                            be done by any successor, but so much for that.</p>
                        <p>If, on the other hand, canceling the summit is the only and critical
                            factor, which may save the situation in Vietnam [unclear], because if
                            the situation in Vietnam is saved, then canceling the summit will look
                            good. I mean, [unclear] even though we will after our first [unclear]
                            and then our erosion will come back up again. Now, there’s one other
                            equation to throw into this. If canceling of the summit, now if we see
                            that the South Vietnamese situation is—if our cold-blooded analysis is,
                            and we cannot make that now, I realize that you use the term “50–50”,
                            that’s my guess. I mean it’s half and half, maybe a little better than
                            that, that they’ll survive, because I think they’re suffering a hell of
                            a lot more than we have any reason to believe, but we shall see. If the
                            South Vietnamese survive, then—I mean do not survive—then having the
                            summit, even under very difficult circumstances, but having it where we
                            say Vietnam will be at the top of the agenda, will have a bad
                            effect.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That is not a
                            possibility to put Vietnam on the top of the agenda. I mean, there’ll be
                            many issues we’ll have to juggle.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: All right. But having a
                            summit without Vietnam at least as a marginal, is a marginal plus,
                            instead of being a very substantial thing in the long run. That’s what
                            we’ll have to face—I’m speaking now of the domestic side. So that brings
                            me back to the other option. The other option is to react as we had
                            originally planned, with our 2-day strike, and see whether the Russians
                            go forward, whether they stress—they may move to cancel, which they
                            might. The 2-day strike thing certainly would have at first great
                            support in this country. Again, it would give some encouragement to the
                            South Vietnamese, give some pause to the Russians, and some pause to
                            Hanoi. The argument you made last night is a very strong one, to the
                            effect that, well, it would look like an act of desperation, to the
                            effect that Hue is being threatened, and so forth and so on. Well, maybe
                            so, maybe the first strike will look that way too. But we all know at
                            the present time the public temper will support that kind of a strike we
                            want to look at. So we have to weigh that. So it really comes down to
                            this. Whether we really honestly feel that canceling the summit could
                            have—could be—a decisive factor or even <pb facs="0728" n="699" xml:id="pg_699"/> a substantial factor in resolving the situation in
                            Vietnam. On that point, I have grave doubts. And if that is true, then
                            the case for it isn’t as strong as we thought it was last night. As far
                            as the strike in the North is concerned, I have serious doubts whether
                            that will have great effect on the situation in Vietnam. It will have
                            some. But we all know that we know it’s a choice between one of two
                            things: either we hit the North for 2 days or we cancel the summit. We
                            have no other options. [unclear exchange]</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: And hitting the
                            [unclear] of the North for 2 days may cancel the summit.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Oh, I understand that.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: And they may cancel
                            it.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: I know, I know.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: And then all of the
                            crap that you mentioned, maybe even more—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Right.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Coming against you. I
                            mean every argument that you made on canceling the summit wouldn’t fly
                            then even more because it would tie Vietnam even more intricately to it,
                            and you wouldn’t be able to get your story out.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: It’s a risk, it’s a
                            risk.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s right. And I
                            think there’d be a slightly better than 50–50 chance that they would
                            cancel the summit, which is why I moved to the point that we should
                            postpone it now. Nobody can present any of these positions to you with
                            the argument that they will save the situation in South Vietnam, because
                            I can’t say that they will. Nothing may. Canceling the summit may not,
                            certainly may not. But in this situation, I’m thinking of the
                            Presidency, thinking of your position in history, and of the position of
                            the country in the long-term. If you go to Moscow without having done
                            anything, it will be a total disaster. We can make it look good, we can
                            put on an act, but all the things that will be needed to be put on, that
                            the Russians will then despise us. We will have lost all
                            credibility.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Not doing anything.
                            Will—[unclear]</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: No, I know. I just
                            keep going up the ladder.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Yeah. Fine. So that’s out
                            of the question?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That I don’t see how
                            we can do. And the cramming of all that machinery, after reading them
                            your dispatches. But even without it—secondly, for the United States, I
                            mean, what the Russians have done systematically since last October is
                            put it to us. And they’ve said you can have your summit, and at the same
                            time we’re going to screw you. Now we go in on great principles of
                            coexistence. And I think the feeling of uneasiness among—I’m not even
                            worried now about Vietnam, <pb facs="0729" n="700" xml:id="pg_700"/> the
                            fact that Russian arms have run us out of Vietnam and the President goes
                            to Moscow and signs principles of coexistence, gives them credit, and
                            agrees with them to screw one of his allies in the Middle East. Now, you
                            know that I’m in favor, hell, we’ve got the principles all negotiated,
                            and the trade is all done, and the Middle East one we can do, and in
                            fact we’re prepared to do that too. But suppose you do all these three
                            things after India–Pakistan and Southeast Asia, and the fact that the
                            bastards have not done one goddamn thing for us ever.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: They have not.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: And I must say
                            objectively that this is a sign of great weakness, which will encourage
                            them. Your great strength in foreign policy is your toughness. And your
                            great standing abroad is due to the fact that you’ve gone your way. Now
                            you could say you could go to the summit, go through with it, don’t sign
                            these principles, don’t give them credit, and don’t make a deal on the
                            Middle East. Well, then, we’ll have a pretty lousy summit. Now to get
                            out of the summit what you want, you have to come back and be able to
                            talk about peace. And about having made tremendous strides towards
                            peace, in other words, you give the Soviets a certificate of good
                            conduct. Now, if we can limit South Vietnam while doing all of this that
                            would be great. That’d be the best of all the worlds.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: But that you can’t
                            unfortunately know in time.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Well if you are in
                            Russia miles away and everything is integrated, there’s just no way of
                            making it look good.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Correct. Our problem, of
                            course. I just wanted to be sure you considered all those.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I, Mr. President,
                            I—God, we suffered and anguished to get to this point. So they may give
                            us an answer that enables us to do it.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Are you going to get an
                            answer?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Oh, yeah, there’ll be
                            an answer. But they may give us a very threatening answer because in a
                            way they’re cornered too. This letter is couched in terms that suggests
                            we’re going to attack North Vietnam but there’s no threat to the Soviet
                            summit involved here. But they may figure that since that what we may do
                            they may pre-empt us and cancel it.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Okay. If we cancel the
                            summit, then follow with massive attacks on the North occur.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Yeah.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Am I right?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That would be my view.
                            And we’d have to go right to the country and we’d have to put it to the
                            presses.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is discussion of press reaction and <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s media contacts and
                            briefings.]</p>
                        <pb facs="0730" n="701" xml:id="pg_701"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: As between whether we
                            postpone the summit or do the 2-day strike, we don’t have to decide
                            that.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Well, can we, I mean, have
                            we got 24 hours for them to come back?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Oh, yes. We have more
                            than that.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Oh, that much? Oh, yes,
                            yes. They won’t pull the 2-day strike off until Saturday.<note n="2" xml:id="d187fn2">May 6</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I don’t think—I have
                            never had the same sense of urgency about the 2-day strike that others
                            have had because Hanoi and Haiphong aren’t going to go away. You—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Then, in other words, we
                            shouldn’t do it over the weekend anyway.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Well, I think we
                            should do it fairly soon if we’re going to do it. There’s something to
                            be said for not doing it on Saturday, so that it doesn’t catch the
                            weekly news magazines. But we can do it Sunday, Sunday and Monday.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Why don’t you analyze for
                            me what you think of it so that I get—just take a minute as to what you
                            think, we’ve gone through the summit thing, what the 2-day strike thing
                            does. First, I don’t need to go in—I know, for instance the Soviets
                            canceling the summit. Fine. Let’s get that out of the way. What does it
                            do in terms of the war? It has some benefits.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Well, the 2-day strike
                            has a number of military benefits. They’re not in themselves decisive
                            but when a country, especially as thin as they are now, anything can
                            impede—they have, for example, changed their whole pattern of unloading
                            gasoline in Haiphong as a result of the other strikes. Secondly, it
                            helps Hanoi that you may just go crazy and press too hard. Thirdly, it
                            really puts it to the Russians in the sense that you are saying all
                            right, you cancel the summit if you want to and leave the choice up to
                            them. Now there’s a certain—so, in other words, you shouldn’t leave the
                            decision of canceling the summit to them, which isn’t easy for them. We
                            had an intercept of a <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>
                            conversation with Gus Hall in which he praises to Hall that he admires
                            you very much and in fact gives a pretty objective account of—but, I
                            repeat how eager they are for the summit; that they are under a lot of
                            pressure from other Communist parties to cancel it. Now they’d love
                            to—the closer to your arrival in Moscow that you do the 2-day strike the
                            tougher it is for them. And, you see, the thing that worries me so much
                            about the visit is for you to give them credit while their trucks and
                            guns—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Never.</p>
                        <pb facs="0731" n="702" xml:id="pg_702"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: But if you don’t give
                            them credit—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: [unclear] the summit.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: they’re going to
                            go—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: And also let’s face it,
                            even signing the <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> agreement is
                            goddamn tough in the light of this—or any agreement with them of—I don’t
                            understand it. I’m the one who had grave doubts about the summit—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: And to sign the common
                            principles—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: That’s right.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: God. You know it’s a
                            tragedy. We had a tremendous breakthrough all along this front. We
                            worked 3 years to get it. And next to you, I’m the one most reluctant to
                            give it up. And to give us a month of relative peace and quiet. But—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Which it would—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Yeah.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: —add to the summit.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: No question. Would do
                            what—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: While we’re there, and for
                            a week afterwards or 2 weeks afterwards. And also it would calm me. I
                            have to realize the end of the summit comes at a time when the fighting
                            in South Vietnam, one way or another, it’s going to be escalating. I
                            mean weather or a lot of other factors. Well, can we take our 24 hours
                            now?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That we can, but we
                            don’t have to make a decision.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is discussion relating to Vietnam and measures to
                            counteract enemy offensive, as well as wording for a speech on Vietnam,
                            summit cancellation and strikes in North Vietnam.]</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: See, these principles,
                            and trade, and Middle East, from a strong President will be—China was
                            great, because no one questioned that you were tough and strong.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Correct.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: But you weren’t
                            getting run out of Vietnam at that time. And not by Chinese
                            equipment.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Yeah. The other thing I
                            was going to say. Look, Henry, that argument has sold me a thousand
                            percent. I’m just trying to think of—I’m trying to think of this. I’m
                            trying to think also that really the argument that is made that
                            [unclear] the canceling of the summit in and of itself would be a good
                            thing clearly apart from its effect on Vietnam. So, basically, what we
                            have to realize is if we get run out of Vietnam, we’re down the tubes.
                            Let’s face it. You understand?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: With or without the
                            summit?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: A chance to save it if we
                            have the summit. A little marginal, but it’s so marginal it doesn’t make
                            any difference to me. But my <pb facs="0732" n="703" xml:id="pg_703"/>
                            point is, though, that the—with the summit, by canceling the summit, you
                            could [unclear] effect on keeping the morale in Vietnam, which I gather
                            you don’t think it really has. Don’t know it. But I think the main
                            point—what you’re really getting to—is that the summit in-and-of itself
                            now isn’t a good idea in view of the situation in Vietnam.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s right. I think
                            it’s very dangerous.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: That’s the point. That’s
                            the thing that’s worried me. Like I’ve said, the tipping of glasses and
                            that sort of thing, at this point, with Russian tanks in there.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: It’s not a strong
                            sign, tipping of glasses, and I look at this hall, and all this while
                            Russian tanks are running around in Vietnam. I would say that—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Well, let’s take a minute
                            before you [unclear]. So the scenario goes like this. We cancel the
                            summit. And then, Henry, we do these bombings on Hanoi and Haiphong.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Oh, yeah. That we do
                            anyway.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Right. And then Thieu
                            still loses, and what happens? Well, it’s just one of those things,
                            isn’t it?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: we’ll then we take it
                            the other way. Supposing you bomb Hanoi and Haiphong and they cancel the
                            summit.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Right.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Then at least you’ve
                            maintained your position and you just keep going anti-Communist and
                            accuse your opponents of first having screwed up the peace talks.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Yeah, I set that in motion
                            with the [leadership] today. I said that the responsibility—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: And they made it
                            inevitable that the thing collapsed and now they want to sell out to the
                            Russians. I mean, you’ll probably lose—you may well lose the election
                            then.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: But I might not.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: But you might not.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Well, I just think we have
                            to see what we’re up to. So you get back to Vietnam, again, don’t you,
                            and their—could I ask one other thing? The situation in the
                            South—generally speaking, there is not a very substantial opposition to
                            Thieu and [unclear]. <persName corresp="#p_MTH1">Moorer</persName> says,
                            said something about Big Minh.<note n="3" xml:id="d187fn3">Duong Van
                                Minh, retired <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> General and
                                former South Vietnamese leader.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Oh, yeah, Big Minh is
                            trying to organize and get himself into a reserve position. And they’ll
                            all begin to do it if the situation gets worse.</p>
                        <pb facs="0733" n="704" xml:id="pg_704"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: What does that do to us?
                            Well—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Well, I consider—I
                            tell you, if they had made any sort of proposition yesterday, I don’t—I
                            consider Thieu expendable.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: I agree.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That isn’t the
                            problem.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: No, what they’re asking
                            for is to—is to not just replace him. They want to impose conditions
                            that would lead to a Communist government.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s right.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: I don’t know.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s the game plan
                            they’re playing.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: That’s right.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: They want to—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Can I ask this question on
                            the timing of the cancellation of the summit. Is it worth considering
                            risk taking and all that—to have him do this then have the bombing go
                            forward—no, no, not have the bombing to go forward; I mean, I think it’s
                            contingent to fight the battle in the South, and we’re very best to—and
                            to have the summit cancellation at the end of next week rather than at
                            the beginning. Just think of that.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: What’s the advantage
                            of that?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: The advantage of it is it
                            gives us more time to assess whether Vietnam might survive. Maybe we
                            won’t know any more then than now. You see my point? I am greatly
                            affected by—if we have some feelers.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: The other problem
                            though is supposing Hue has fallen by the end of next week, then it will
                            look like especially a reaction to a defeat.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: I think it’s going to look
                            that way anyway. I mean, they have played the [unclear] so heavily,
                            Henry, that I mean we didn’t have any illusions about the perpetual
                            reaction to a defeat. So, the fall of Hue I don’t think is going to make
                            much difference. Would you not agree?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I think, you know, it
                            doesn’t have to be Monday. It can be Tuesday. I think that if we’re
                            going to cancel that we better do it early rather than late. And we
                            won’t know a hell of a lot.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Well, that’s the answer
                            then. We won’t know a hell of a lot.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: We know we’ll lose
                            Kontum. See, supposing it gets all unstuck, I don’t see how you can go
                            to Russia then, in my view. But I—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: I couldn’t agree more.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: But, you know, the
                            other argument you could use it to divert attention from the defeat.</p>
                        <pb facs="0734" n="705" xml:id="pg_705"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: You go to Russia then,
                            what the hell can you agree on? That’s the point. You can’t agree to
                            give credits; you can’t agree to—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: See, the whole idea,
                            see, of agreeing, of having you sign health agreements, science
                            agreements—what do the Russians want at the summit? They want to show
                            that you and <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> are
                            ordering the world. Now, when you do it as equals, it’s risky enough
                            because it’s going to hurt us enormously in Europe, it’s going to hurt
                            us with the Chinese. But the risk is worth taking under the assumption
                            that you can recover from it in the next election—after the next
                            election.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: By turning hard.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: By turning hard. And
                            that’s how I’d justify it. But basically <persName corresp="#p_SFJJ1">Shakespeare</persName> isn’t wrong in his assessment of what this
                            détente is doing to our allies. Now, there’s strong sentiment that
                            somebody to whom you can say look how you stood in all these crises. But
                            its somebody who’s been humiliated or at least can be challenged in
                            South Asia by the Russians, and then the most vital area where we have
                            50,000—I mean vital from the point of view of national sensitivities,
                            not about strategic interest—and he still does it.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: That’s right. That’s
                            it.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s something I
                            think, Mr. President, that’s going to be hard to recover from.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: That’s right.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: And who is then going
                            to be left to respect you? I mean, I shouldn’t talk this way, but I
                            mean, the hawks?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Not likely.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: The doves?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Nah.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: A strong President—the
                            reason—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: The real heart of the
                            question, and it’s good to talk it out this way, the real heart of the
                            question is what I’m getting at really isn’t about Vietnam, because if
                            it were, we’d have to realize—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: It’s about what you
                            said at the end. It’s about the Presidency.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: That’s right. The real
                            point here is that the canceling of the summit or the bombing—neither
                            may prove to have too much of an effect on the outcome of Vietnam. So
                            scrub both of those things. The real reason we have to cancel the
                            summit, if we do cancel the summit, is that we cannot go to the summit
                            while Russian tanks and guns are kicking the shit out of us in
                            Vietnam.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s right.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: We cannot make an
                            agreement with people that are doing that. We don’t meet with a bunch of
                            outlaws. It’s like when <persName corresp="#p_RNA1">Rockefeller</persName>
                            <pb facs="0735" n="706" xml:id="pg_706"/> going to the prison at Attica
                            to meet with those goddamn people.<note n="4" xml:id="d187fn4">A
                                reference to Attica State Prison in New York State where a hostage
                                stand-off and riot occurred in 1969.</note> Right?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s my sense, Mr.
                            President, with great reluctance, and knowing how we may get a turn in
                            the situation; we may get an answer from <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> that we can live with. I doubt it.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Well, our answer—our
                            decision on the speech, and so forth, should be made, it seems to
                            me.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: You don’t have to make
                            it before Friday or Saturday.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: The decision to go
                            on—let’s get the speech ready.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I’ll get the speech
                            done.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: You get the speech ready,
                            and I’ll work on it, and I can make a decision as to whether to give it
                            or not Monday, and then give it Monday night or Tuesday night.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Yeah. There’s no—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: And have in mind the
                            fact—and then we can have the strike, in the case I don’t make the
                            speech, we can have the strike go Tuesday or Wednesday or Thursday of
                            next week.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s right.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: See my point?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: There’s no
                            incentive</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: I think in any event that
                            we should tell <persName corresp="#p_AGCWJ1">Abrams</persName>—see this
                            fits into the other point, that you can have these assets.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Don’t worry about this
                                <persName corresp="#p_AGCWJ1">Abrams</persName> baloney. I talked to
                                <persName corresp="#p_MTH1">Moorer</persName>. We can wait for that
                            ‘til tomorrow morning. He has got his execute order.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Okay. What I’m getting at
                            is this. I don’t think we should do it over the weekend. Let’s make the
                            final decision with regard to canceling the summit really Monday.<note n="5" xml:id="d187fn5">May 8.</note> I want the speech, however. I’m
                            going to prepare the speech, because getting the speech and writing it
                            will help me get my own thinking and the right kind of thing.<note n="6" xml:id="d187fn6">Later, the President and <persName corresp="#p_HHR1">Haldeman</persName> discussed the possible
                                cancellation of the Soviet trip. The President noted that he could
                                not “go to Moscow when Russian tanks were in the streets of Hue.” He
                                also added that the American people admired his courage on
                                initiatives like the recent trip to China, and therefore he did not
                                want to fail and appear to be helpless like his predecessor. “Keep
                                in mind <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> is still a pretty damn
                                strong country,” he proclaimed. But the President added that
                                cancellation was “almost a sure way to lose the election.” However,
                                he contended that even if canceling the summit had a marginal impact
                                on the war in Vietnam, then it would have been worth it. <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> had <persName corresp="#p_HHR1">Haldeman</persName> call <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> during this meeting, and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HHR1">Haldeman</persName> reported on
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s comments.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> noted his
                                opposition against “cancellation outright” and instead argued for
                                “postponement.” <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                                added that the President could not go to Russia under these
                                circumstances, and thus was in a position where options were
                                lacking. <persName corresp="#p_HHR1">Haldeman</persName> noted that
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> had not wanted
                                to bomb the Hanoi–Haiphong area before the Paris meeting. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> also believed that the
                                President could bomb and still retain a “50% chance of having the
                                Summit.” <persName corresp="#p_HHR1">Haldeman</persName> described
                                postponement as “rather intriguing.” <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> added, “I am convinced that the President
                                will not cancel the Summit.” <persName corresp="#p_HHR1">Haldeman</persName> told the President that he had to order the
                                bombing, and that <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                                said it would be over by June. However, the worst possible thing to
                                happen would be if the Soviets canceled the summit first. If
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> canceled it prior
                                to that point, then it would put the blame on the Soviets for the
                                Summit’s failure to convene. (Conversation between <persName corresp="#p_HHR1">Haldeman</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, May 3, 1972; National
                                Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                                Materials, White House Tapes, May 3, 1972, 2:50–3:35 p.m., Executive
                                Office Building, Conversation No. 335–17)</note> So I want the
                            speech, a copy of it by—well, can they—when can they have it, Henry?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Tomorrow noon.</p>
                        <pb facs="0736" n="707" xml:id="pg_707"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: But that’s too much for
                            them.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Well, I think they can
                            do it by tomorrow noon.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Well, let’s say, let’s
                            say, could we have a copy of the speech rather than tomorrow noon, could
                            we have it tomorrow say, after dinner, 7 o’clock? That gives all day
                            tomorrow. Fair enough?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Good.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: And you just put it there
                            and we’ll [unclear]. I’ll say really one thing, [unclear] that the
                            speech will be a real shocker, won’t it? It will be one of the real
                            surprises. Incidentally, there will be absolutely no agreement.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: It will make you look
                            very strong.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: For a moment. For a while.
                            Grandstanding with a temper.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: But—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: But on the other hand, on
                            the other hand, we will definitely say, and frankly, that’s the only
                            choice that we have. See that’s the way you have to look at it. If we
                            had a better choice we’d make it, wouldn’t we?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Well, you can do the
                            2-day strike. I think that if we wait for that too long—if we wait
                            they’ll think we’re blinking. I mean, we can’t—</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: A 2-day strike could still
                            go. It could land by Tuesday. We wouldn’t be waiting too long, would
                            it?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: No, but, no, but
                            that’s the problem. By Tuesday we’ve got to go one way or the other</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: That’s what I meant. So
                            that’s why we’ve got to decide. We’ve got to decide to go on this
                            thing.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: If you cancel the
                            summit, you can do without the 2-day strike for awhile.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Well, why hold back?</p>
                        <pb facs="0737" n="708" xml:id="pg_708"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Okay, I’ll get that
                            done. But in my view, you can hold up the decision until we get the
                            thing.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: All right.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>