<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-05-24T05:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-05-24T03:40:00-05:00" n="265" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d265">
                        <head>265. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d265fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 487, President’s
                                Trip Files, The President’s Conversations in Salzburg, Moscow,
                                Tehran, and Warsaw, May 1972, Part 1. Top Secret; Sensitive;
                                Exclusively Eyes Only. The meeting was held in St. Catherine’s Hall,
                                Grand Kremlin Palace. According to the President’s Daily Diary, the
                                meeting was from 11:34 a.m. to 1:31 p.m. (Ibid., White House Central
                                Files)</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1972-05-24T11:40:00+03:00" to="1972-05-24T13:30:00+03:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">May 24, 1972, 11:40
                                    a.m.–1:30 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Leonid I. Brezhnev</persName>, General
                                Secretary of the Central Committee of the <gloss target="#t_CPSU1">CPSU</gloss>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_PNV1">Nikolai V. Podgorny</persName>, Chairman
                                of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Aleksei N. Kosygin</persName>, Chairman
                                of the Council of Ministers of the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Andrei A. Gromyko</persName>, Minister
                                of Foreign Affairs</item>
                            <item>Anatoli F. Dobrynin, Ambassador to the USA</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_AAAM1">Andrei M.
                                    Aleksandrov-Agentov</persName>, Assistant to the General
                                Secretary</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SVM1">Viktor M. Sukhodrev</persName>,
                                Interpreter</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_ZLM1">Leonid Zamyatin</persName>, Director of
                                    <gloss target="#t_TASS1">TASS</gloss>
                            </item>
                            <item>The President</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">William P. Rogers</persName>, Secretary
                                of State</item>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>,
                                Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_HMJA1">Martin Hillenbrand</persName>,
                                Assistant Secretary of State for European Affairs</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SHH1">Helmut Sonnenfeldt</persName>, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Senior Staff Member</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_LW2">Winston Lord</persName>, Special
                                Assistant to Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECTS</head>
                            <item>Economic Relations; Europe</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>[In informal conversation before the meeting began, the Soviet leaders,
                            in particular <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>, emphasized
                            the importance of Most-Favored-Nation treatment for the Soviet Union,
                            citing the very high <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> tariff rates
                            for many Soviet products. The President essentially listened without
                            committing himself.</p>
                        <p>[The Soviet side then said that the meeting would take up European
                            issues. The <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> side had thought that
                                <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> would be the principal item,
                            and when he heard that Europe would be discussed the President said that
                            he wanted Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> and
                            Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HMJA1">Hillenbrand</persName>
                            present. He pointed out to the Soviet leaders that Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> would have to describe the
                            discussions to the European countries and at home. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> left the room to call
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>.]<note n="2" xml:id="d265fn2">All brackets in the source text.</note>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="1053" n="1024" xml:id="pg_1024"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Economic Relations</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The President: I was talking to Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName> on <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss>. As I told the General Secretary yesterday, I will
                            handle that. I already indicated this to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> at Camp David. I have to get
                            this through the Congress. I have already discussed it with the leaders;
                            if we can get Congressional agreement I will take responsibility.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: That would be a
                            very good thing. I can see that then we will really have a solid basis
                            for the development of our economic ties, because otherwise there can be
                            nothing but talk on this subject and nothing concrete. In fact, we can
                            sell commodities 40% dearer in European markets. So why should we sell
                            to the United States if we can get 40% more in Europe?</p>
                        <p>The President: That makes sense.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: While we are
                            waiting I can give you some comparable examples: all sorts of heavy
                            equipment, like machine tools and parts of metal cutting machines, power
                            stations, diesels, in short most of the products of the engineering
                            industry that we could sell to the United States would be taxed up to
                            40%.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_PNV1">Podgorny</persName>: There are some
                            that are even higher.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: Compared to that
                            the general tax [tariff] on goods in other nations is 5% or 7% compared
                            to that of 40% in the United States. There are other examples. On
                            optical equipment, for example, the tax is 50%. On electrical measuring
                            devices and instruments it goes as high as 90%. Can anyone do trade on
                            that sort of basis?</p>
                        <p>For example, with Canada recently we had a sale of turbines and
                            generators and it was a normal situation where the delegation came over
                            and crossed Siberia and saw our equipment at work and bought very
                            important machinery in the electrical power field, and the tax rates
                            were quite normal.</p>
                        <p>The President: On the whole economic matter, <persName corresp="#p_PNS1">Patolichev</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_FPM1">Flanigan</persName> had discussions yesterday. We have no problem
                            so far as Export-Import Bank credits are concerned. I can do that
                            unilaterally as President. On <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> I have
                            to go to Congress.<note n="3" xml:id="d265fn3">On May 23 <persName corresp="#p_FPM1">Peter Flanigan</persName> sent the President a
                                memorandum reporting on this meeting and saying that he and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> had clarified the
                                    <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> position on the various
                                possible commercial agreements. He noted that Soviet eligibility for
                                    <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> export credits and the
                                granting of <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> depended on
                                agreement on lend-lease, and that the only unsettled lend-lease item
                                was the amount, with the Soviets offering $300 million and the
                                United States asking for $800 million. Agreement on this could be
                                reached eventually, parallel to the work of the Joint <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                                Commercial Commission—the establishment of which was to be announced
                                that week—unless the President and Secretary wanted to make a major
                                step by compromising the amount and terms during the summit.
                                (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                                Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files,
                                Box 73, Country Files, Europe, <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, 1972 Summit, Economic Commission)</note>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="1054" n="1025" xml:id="pg_1025"/>
                        <p>It would be helpful, Mr. General Secretary, if whomever you designate,
                            perhaps Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>,
                            could talk to <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> about this
                            so he can sell it to Congress when he gets there. Don’t you agree, Mr.
                            Ambassador (<persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>)?</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>: [gestures to
                                <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>]</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: Very
                            well.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: Well, of course,
                            the solution of the question of Export-Import Bank credits will provide
                            the opportunity to achieve some progress, but ways must be found to get
                            over the <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> problem and seek ways to
                            increase trade.</p>
                        <p>I have already put this to some American representatives. When we really
                            get trade going it will be quite useful for us to have a bank of our own
                            in the United States, as we do in various countries, such as France,
                            Great Britain, Iran and Turkey, like in many parts of the world. We
                            should either have a bank of our own, or it could take the form of a
                            joint <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet venture.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: One
                            specific matter. I think on two occasions an important delegation of
                            American businessmen visited this country. Among the questions discussed
                            was a possible large scale agreement on a joint venture in gas, building
                            in the northern areas of our country special liquid gas plants. This
                            could be a very important project for <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet cooperation. Are you familiar with this, Mr.
                            President, and if so how do you view this matter? Because this would be
                            a question involving both vast quantities and also it would be on a long
                            term basis.</p>
                        <p>[Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> and Assistant
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HMJA1">Hillenbrand</persName>
                            arrived.]</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: The situation
                            right now is this. The representatives of American business circles are
                            suggesting where some of these could be built. We reached preliminary
                            agreement on a gas pipeline in Siberia from Tyumen. The initial duration
                            will be for a period of twenty years and the cost would be somewhere
                            close to $5 billion. The Americans who came here were quite confident
                            that they had almost agreed on this matter with their authorities in the
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> I don’t know if it has come to
                            your attention. They are quite sure that the total amounts of gas
                            involved would be 25 billion cubic meters, or liquid gas would be 25
                            million tons. They gave us preliminary projections, a preliminary plan
                            of action which they elaborated for our experts. I made a suggestion to
                            have not just one pipeline but two parallel pipes. Then they made their
                            own additional suggestions. They seemed quite sure a bargain could be
                            struck.</p>
                        <p>To sum up, I am quite sure there is a basis to study this matter. We are
                            also quite sure that there are enough gas deposits in this area to
                            arrange for a business deal. There is a very important project that
                            could be carried into effect. On account of the credit that would be
                            extended by the American side to us to carry the project into effect, we
                                <pb facs="1055" n="1026" xml:id="pg_1026"/> could place very
                            significant orders, for example for 3 million tons of sheet steel and
                            important orders in the field of compressors. We would thereby,
                            contribute to a fuller scale of operations important to American
                            industry. We would contribute to a lower American unemployment rate. If
                            correctly presented to the Congress it would be welcomed.</p>
                        <p>The President: [to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>] Would you say a word on the gas project?</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>: This is a very
                            large project, and we have to consider carefully its feasibility. We as
                            a government have not taken a position as yet. We recognize the point
                            that Premier <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName> has made. We
                            talked to private parties, and we indicated that we would want to
                            consider any proposals that they make. Up to this time we haven’t taken
                            a position as a government on it.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: That is exactly
                            what the American businessmen said. But they are interested and
                            confirmed what you said, that the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                            Government has not taken a position yet.</p>
                        <p>The President: [to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>] Before you came I said that I thought it would
                            be helpful if you could meet with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName> and discuss the specifics on this. They also
                            raised the points of <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> which I said we
                            were prepared to move on with the Congress. Would you like to say a word
                            about that?</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>: I would be happy
                            to meet with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName> and Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_FPM1">Flanigan</persName> at your convenience.
                            As you know, Mr. President, this involves huge amounts of credits and we
                            have to consider it carefully. Concerning natural gas, actually if we
                            were to extend that amount of credit, we would have to work out the
                            lend-lease settlement. Natural gas involves a very substantial amount of
                            credit, about one-third of what the Export-Import Bank has
                            available.</p>
                        <p>The President: It also involves <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss>?</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>: Credit.</p>
                        <p>The President: That doesn’t mean that it isn’t possible.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: But this is not
                            just something in our interest alone. It is something of a mutual
                            advantage to both sides.</p>
                        <p>The President: Oh no.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: This should
                            reflect a mutual desire on our part to develop a cooperation in this
                            field; it is not something that is unilaterally to our advantage.</p>
                        <p>The President: We would like to work it out altogether, including lend
                            lease, the resolution of that problem. I can move on Export-Import Bank
                            matters, but in regard to <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> I have to
                            go back to the Congress on that. I believe that <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> discussions would be useful because we get the
                            side of the businessmen, and I would like to hear directly what you have
                            in mind.</p>
                        <pb facs="1056" n="1027" xml:id="pg_1027"/>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>: I have talked to
                            the businessmen. I will be very happy to talk to Premier <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: Well, just
                            adding to what has been said now, we have large agreements on the sale
                            of gas with Austria and the Federal Republic of Germany and all the
                            Socialist countries and Italy. In short, we have almost potential
                            consumers of our gas than we need. This should be in the nature of a
                            serious business deal between our two countries.</p>
                        <p>On the question of lend lease, we think we should set aside a time to
                            discuss that so we know where we are. We should not just float in air so
                            that we can come to a concrete solution on the basis of your proposal
                            and the ones that we have. Certainly that issue is long overdue.</p>
                        <p>The President: That certainly would help the political climate that we
                            need to get Most-Favored-Nation.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: And here, of
                            course, we must both take a really realistic view of things and remember
                            that after all more than 25 years have passed since the end of the war.
                            None of us can expect very great figures or sums to be involved in
                            solving this matter. On the other hand many in this world want to
                            exploit this matter in their own selfish interest.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>: The President
                            suggested I say a word about <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss>. If we
                            have a satisfactory outcome of the lend lease negotiations and the
                            general relations between the Soviet Union and the United States improve
                            as a result of this visit, and the President supports <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss>, then Congress, I think, will follow
                            the President’s lead. It is not an easy matter, but I think whatever the
                            President recommends to the Congress under these circumstances, I think
                            that they should do.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: Shall
                            we now turn to the subject that has been suggested we discuss this
                            morning, Europe? If you have no objections, I would like to make a few
                            opening remarks on that question. A discussion of the problems relating
                            to Europe is a very important one indeed, and I believe the reasons for
                            that are understood perfectly well on both sides. Europe is indeed an
                            area which is one of the most densely populated ones in the world. It is
                            an area of enormous economic potential; an area of ancient culture and
                            science. All of these are important matters.</p>
                        <p>On the other hand, it is also an area where in the past many large-scale
                            wars originated. I need only to mention two world wars and especially
                            the last one which the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> was dragged
                            into also. And those wars, particularly the last one, involved very much
                            human suffering and sacrifice. It had a very bad aftermath and had a
                            long term effect on the situation in Europe generally.</p>
                        <pb facs="1057" n="1028" xml:id="pg_1028"/>
                        <p>The question therefore is how to make this area an area of peace and
                            tranquility so that all the peoples of Europe can live in conditions of
                            security, so that we too, and both of us, can be confident that the
                            situation in Europe would not deteriorate. This is certainly not an easy
                            thing to achieve, but it is something that should be the focus of our
                            attention.</p>
                        <p>In Europe, we have sufficient and quite rich experience of cooperation on
                            various matters. There has been the fighting cooperation of our two
                            nations during the Second World War. There was the fruitful cooperation
                            at the time of the Potsdam Agreement. There has been comparable
                            experience in the post-war period. We regard particularly highly the
                            cooperation of our two nations in the talks on the Berlin agreement and
                            in the matters of the Soviet Union–Federal Republic of Germany and
                            Poland–Federal Republic of Germany Treaties.</p>
                        <p>However much we value the cooperation in the past, we should not belittle
                            the importance of our role in ensuring the future of Europe, because
                            there are still in Europe the unresolved problems. Very much in the
                            policies of the United States and Soviet Union about Europe would favor
                            not only the interests of Europeans, but also the interests of your
                            country and ours. I should like to say quite frankly that if the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> is prepared to take measures to remove
                            the survivals of the past policies of the cold war, the outcome would be
                            an improvement of relations between the Soviet Union and the United
                            States. That, too, is a very important aspect of this problem.</p>
                        <p>And I would like at this point to emphasize again the significance of the
                            concerted policies we both pursued with regard to the problems of West
                            Berlin and the ratification of the treaty. At the same time I wish to
                            state firmly that our line with regard to the Federal Republic of
                            Germany would not be anti-American in character. This is something we
                            said in all frankness to Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_BWHF1">Brandt</persName>, and this is something we will abide by very
                            strictly. And as a practical step let me say that on May 31 our Supreme
                            Soviet will be ratifying the treaty with the Federal Republic of
                            Germany. As we pointed out in the past, immediately after that we will
                            sign the final protocol on West Berlin so that can be put into effect
                            too. In our view that will not only serve to improve the legal relations
                            between the Federal Republic of Germany, the German Democratic Republic
                            and Poland. It will also have a beneficial effect on the general
                            atmosphere in Europe.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>: I suggested to
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> that we make the
                            signing on June 3.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: I
                            think that seems to be a very acceptable date. We have promised to sign
                            it immediately after ratifying; that is something expected by the
                            Federal Republic of Germany.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>: There is some
                            suggestion that we delay until June 16, but June 3 is better for us.</p>
                        <pb facs="1058" n="1029" xml:id="pg_1029"/>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: We
                            feel the sooner the better. We promised they would come into force at
                            the same time, so it seems logical to do it on June 3.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>: We will try to
                            work it out with the others.</p>
                        <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>: Good,
                            the British and the French.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: That
                            would be a very good thing indeed. In our common policy in Europe it
                            will also be most important to continue to pursue a firm line and not
                            even conceive of the possibility of the violation of boundaries of
                            Europe as they have taken shape in the post-war period. That also is one
                            of the paramount tasks of current foreign policies.</p>
                        <p>And I would now like to tell you frankly, Mr. President, there have been
                            erroneous, fallacious interpretations of our policy with respect to
                            Europe. Sometimes this is a lack of true knowledge, but more frequently
                            it is deliberate rumors spread to the effect that the goal of our
                            policies is to break the ties that the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> has developed with European states. We wish to state
                            in these negotiations that this is very far from the truth. The
                            initiatives that we are taking in Europe, and particularly on the
                            question of European security, pursue a goal that is totally different.
                            We pursue our objective in the interest of not only the European states;
                            we pursue it also with the goal of maintaining and protecting the
                            interest of the Soviet Union and the United States in Europe, if of
                            course, like ourselves, the United States seeks to make Europe tranquil
                            and secure.</p>
                        <p>In confirmation with what I have said with regard to the goal of the
                            Soviet policy in Europe, we will take into account the role played by
                            the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet cooperation both during World War II and the
                            post-war period, particularly in the earlier talks on the problem of
                            West Berlin and the matter of the ratification of the treaties. We
                            believe it quite normal that in all matters relating to the European
                            Conference and the solution of all serious problems relating to Europe,
                            the United States should participate on an equal footing, even though
                            the United States is not an European nation. This review is confirmation
                            of our views and attitude to the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> and
                            to the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> being able to defend its own
                            interests in Europe.</p>
                        <p>Another question to which we attach great importance is the question of
                            preparing and convening an all-European Security Conference. The reasons
                            why we attach importance to this is as follows: We do not see the
                            Conference as an aim in itself. We regard it as one of the possible
                            means that can help bring to fruition the turn that has been discernible
                            toward the normalization of the situation and strengthening of the
                            prospects of securing lasting peace in the continent.</p>
                        <p>I should like to add the following. Despite the different approaches
                            taken by the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> and the Soviet Union to
                            several matters affecting <pb facs="1059" n="1030" xml:id="pg_1030"/>
                            European politics, the strengthening of security in Europe does in our
                            view correspond to the long-term interests of both the Soviet Union and
                            the United States. And if we both act in that direction—in a direction
                            of building up the guarantee of security of European states—that will
                            insure that there will be no more nuclear war and there will be
                            tranquility in Europe to a far greater extent than attempts to insure
                            that tranquility through the use or threat of nuclear weapons.</p>
                        <p>We believe that a turn for the better has become discernible in Europe
                            today, and it will be in our view useful if we could take advantage of
                            that fact in order to strengthen that feeling of security and begin a
                            joint effort to prepare for the convening of a European Security
                            Conference. We should therefore endeavor to begin preliminary bilateral
                            consultations on those matters and in a preliminary way we might say a
                            few words about that at this meeting. And we are counting on the
                            positive attitude of the United States toward this matter. We have
                            expressed our views publicly on this question on many occasions and so
                            have quite a few other European states.</p>
                        <p>As you know, we have spoken in favor of convening this conference even as
                            early as the end of this year. It is quite clear that in one blow it may
                            certainly not prove possible to resolve all the complex problems of
                            Europe, but the important thing is to launch the conference, to get the
                            conference going. It might prove expedient to prolong its work. The
                            important thing is to begin the work, to begin the preparations for the
                            conference.</p>
                        <p>As in any question such preparations can assume a different form, but as
                            a first suggestion perhaps we could discuss the following: we first
                            begin multilateral consultations in Helsinki. Then, in the first stage
                            of the conference itself the Foreign Ministers of the European states
                            and the United States and Canada could meet to work out an agenda of the
                            conference, to create the necessary bodies, commissions, secretariat and
                            so forth. And then those bodies could get to work in order to elaborate
                            and submit various specific proposals for the consideration of the
                            governments of the European states and the United States and Canada.</p>
                        <p>Certainly this is not the one and only possible form of addressing
                            ourselves to this problem. Other forms can also be discussed. We are
                            just submitting our own view. This form has in it nothing that can be
                            construed as running against any participants in the conference.
                            Whatever conversations we have on this topic, we should certainly like
                            to emphasize the significance for future developments of our two sides
                            publicly saying something in principle on the problem relating to the
                            European Conference at the conclusion of our meeting here. And you have
                            in principle given your consent to that first meeting. I wish to
                            emphasize that it would be very important indeed to say something at <pb facs="1060" n="1031" xml:id="pg_1031"/> the conclusion on these
                            subjects because if we don’t there might be all sorts of wrong opinions
                            and misunderstandings in Europe. People would start saying that the
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> or the Soviet Union was changing
                            their policy. Even if so, by making public reference we would be doing a
                            very good thing and therefore justify the hopes the people in Europe
                            have placed in these talks and in the people of our countries.</p>
                        <p>And now we have through joint cooperation settled the matter of the
                            ratification of the treaties and the question of West Berlin, another
                            important matter arises and that is a simultaneous admission of the two
                            German states, the Federal Republic of Germany and the German Democratic
                            Republic, to the United Nations. The possible solution to this question
                            would certainly remove much tension in Europe and the sources of
                            friction between us on those grounds. This is a major issue, and we feel
                            we should be entitled to count on the positive attitude of your part on
                            this also.</p>
                        <p>Although it is an international problem, it also relates to bilateral
                            relations between our two countries. It would help to create a better
                            climate for the relations between us. And that is something to which you
                            made frequent reference during this visit, Mr. President.</p>
                        <p>Another major issue which concerns not only improving the general climate
                            and relations between our two countries and the relations of our two
                            countries with the states of Europe, but also in line with the interest
                            of generally improving the situation in the world, is the question of
                            the military/political groupings in Europe. You are, I trust, familiar
                            with our position on these matters. We are prepared, together with our
                            allies, to disband military/political groupings in Europe towards a
                            first step to really disbanding military organizations, and we are
                            prepared to initiate consultations with you on this subject.</p>
                        <p>Those, Mr. President, are in our view just the basic issues we could
                            discuss and talk about with relation to Europe.</p>
                        <p>The President: Mr. General Secretary, you correctly pointed out our
                            position of agreeing in principle to a European Security Conference, or
                            a European Security and Cooperation Conference. As you know, we have,
                            and you have, the problem of not deciding at this meeting the future of
                            Europe. It is very important, while we agree in principle, that we
                            consult with our allies, you with yours and we with ours. Therefore it
                            is very important that whatever we state here, we will follow through
                            with consultations with our allies.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: That’s
                            quite natural.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: Do you think the
                            time will come when there are no allies on your part or on ours, that we
                            are common allies?</p>
                        <p>The President: Surely. It will take time.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: That’s what we
                            want to achieve. As long as you have your allies and we ours, we are at
                            loggerheads.</p>
                        <pb facs="1061" n="1032" xml:id="pg_1032"/>
                        <p>The President: It is very important we recognize that smaller nations are
                            very sensitive about the relations between the two great powers. Small
                            nations object to having their fate decided by larger ones.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: It
                            should not offend them.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: That in fact is
                            why we are so categorically opposed to allegations, these Chinese
                            allegations, about the two superpowers combining to settle all the
                            questions of the world, the affairs of smaller countries. We, for our
                            part, have the immutable position that we respect other countries. And
                            that is our attitude.</p>
                        <p>[There was a brief discussion about <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName> and a Deputy Prime Minister for Science.]</p>
                        <p>The President: He is making a private deal with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>. As the first nation to send a
                            manned mission to Mars, I will go along.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: I can stand it,
                            can you?</p>
                        <p>The President: It will take nine months. We will get to know each other
                            very well.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: We will take
                            cognac.</p>
                        <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>: How
                            could you go without the Foreign Ministers?</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_PNV1">Podgorny</persName>: This is not a
                            private deal. We have to give honest thought to who flies.</p>
                        <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>: Perhaps
                            first there should be a preliminary flight of foreign ministers.</p>
                        <p>The President: If the foreign ministers don’t come back, we won’t go.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: We
                            call Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> to order—keep
                            him away from submarines.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: If we don’t come
                            back, everything will be clear.</p>
                        <p>The President: Getting to the practical points, as I know the General
                            Secretary likes to do, stated frankly, I see these problems. First to
                            have a meeting this year, 1972, the first meeting of the European
                            Security Conference, would not be possible. It poses for us rather
                            considerable problems. We have elections and the aftermath, and it also
                            poses the problem of participation. We can talk in terms of a meeting in
                            1973. We can have preliminary discussions take place in the fall of this
                            year. That is realistic. One of the reasons that this meeting we are
                            having now is producing such solid results is because it was well
                            prepared. In a meeting involving all the countries of Europe, the
                            preparations, of course, would be very important. Whereas we two might
                            agree on an agenda, smaller nations have various ideas, and it will take
                            time. 1973 is the time for the meeting to aim for rather than trying to
                            compress it and get it done in 1972.</p>
                        <pb facs="1062" n="1033" xml:id="pg_1033"/>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>: Our allies agree
                            with this. Some of them have elections this fall, like Canada.</p>
                        <p>The President: You have to know whether you are dealing with a government
                            that will survive or one that’s gone. Preliminary discussions at the
                            proper level, the exploratory discussions, could go forward at the times
                            the European nations and all of us agree.</p>
                        <p>It’s your thought that these should take place at Helsinki?</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: That’s
                            where the idea of a conference came to life. Some work has already
                            begun. Since Finland was the initiator we feel that Helsinki should be
                            the city. That seems the general trend of public opinion, that it should
                            be held in Helsinki.</p>
                        <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>: In fact
                            practically all the countries concerned have indicated their preference
                            for Helsinki, and the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> has not in
                            fact registered a negative attitude.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>: We are talking
                            about preliminary talks, not the conference itself.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: That’s
                            exactly our understanding.</p>
                        <p>The President: The second point, with regard to <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> representation of East Germany, this is a problem where
                            we, of course, will have to be guided by the attitude of the Federal
                            Republic. And when the Federal Republic has discussed this matter and
                            indicated it is ready to move forward, we will, of course, cooperate. We
                            will be prepared to discuss it with the British and the French. There is
                            the very sensitive problem of four-power rights that might be affected
                            by this action.</p>
                        <p>The situation with regard to what the General Secretary was referring to
                            concerning military forces and military blocs is of course much more
                            difficult and is going to require a great deal of time. As the General
                            Secretary and all the representatives here of the Soviet Government are
                            aware, there have been considerable discussions in the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> community in regard to the
                            possibility of mutual balanced force reductions. This is naturally a
                            matter that cannot be decided in a large conference involving a number
                            of nations that do not have forces. That is why we are suggesting, I
                            know this is a matter of previous discussion. …</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: Of
                            course, there are such states as Luxembourg, with 90 policemen.</p>
                        <p>The President: … we have suggested that there should be parallel
                            discussions on the problem of force reductions, parallel discussions at
                            the time going forward with discussions on the European Conference.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: Well,
                            how do you visualize that in practice? Let us assume that we have the
                            procedure on the conference that I have suggested, the Foreign
                            Ministers’ meeting in Helsinki to discuss matters on the agenda, working
                            bodies, the secretariat, etc. In your view they would also discuss the
                            question of force reductions in parallel? Is that your thinking
                            generally?</p>
                        <pb facs="1063" n="1034" xml:id="pg_1034"/>
                        <p>The President: No. That was the point I was making. We thought that is
                            too large a body for that. Let the countries involved, with forces
                            involved, have discussions; that is the point Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> made in discussions with the
                            General Secretary before.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: But they should
                            proceed in parallel.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: In
                            parallel, but different bodies discussing the two different
                            subjects.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>: We might have
                            the subjects on the agenda and agree to discuss maybe simultaneously,
                            maybe shortly thereafter.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: Or
                            perhaps we really need not have them in parallel, perhaps first agree to
                            getting the question of the European Conference out of the way, and then
                            force reductions. But if we discuss the two very important matters of
                            the European Security Conference and force reductions in parallel,
                            perhaps they would get in the way of each other.</p>
                        <p>The President: If we wait until a multilateral conference, we may never
                            get to parallel discussions.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: That
                            matter could be dealt with in parallel but different bodies altogether.
                            We support the earliest possible discussion of that but without hinging
                            these questions together. The crux lies in not tying up these two
                            problems as far as substance is concerned.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>: I think that as
                            a matter of logic if you are going to have a conference dealing with
                            security certainly one of the most important aspects is forces.
                            Certainly any conference that didn’t cover forces would be lacking
                            something.</p>
                        <p>The President: Let me suggest, Mr. General Secretary, a procedure for
                            your consideration. I would like to do some thinking on how we do this
                            tactically, the date and so forth. If we could have <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> have a discussion also and then report back to
                            us, maybe Friday, and by Friday then we can consider this question. They
                            could give us some options.</p>
                        <p>[General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> stands
                            up.]</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>/General Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: Okay.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: Because indeed
                            it would be a very good thing if Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> could work on this for our consideration, a kind
                            of program for both of us working toward a European Conference. This
                            would indeed help us remove many questions that otherwise would take
                            months of time.</p>
                        <p>The President: This is too big a group for technical matters.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: Although
                            certainly there are many people in Europe who live under the impression,
                            perhaps false, that we are holding back preparations for the Conference.
                            If we come to an agreement on this, it would be very useful to remove
                            this impression.</p>
                        <pb facs="1064" n="1035" xml:id="pg_1035"/>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: Many
                            people in Europe think you oppose the Conference.</p>
                        <p>The President: Let me emphasize again that although we come to agreement,
                            we must be careful not to irritate our friends—all our friends, we
                            consider all Europe our friends. For example, we wouldn’t want to anger
                            Albania. (laughter) We don’t want to anger them.</p>
                        <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>: That is
                            a very noble intention.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>: We don’t want to
                            make Luxembourg mad.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: We heed the
                            words of Luxembourg too.</p>
                        <p>If, for example, we tell Albania that you regard them as best friend,
                            they will be very glad.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_PNV1">Podgorny</persName>: We are prepared
                            to heed the voice of Luxembourg but Albania takes a different view.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: No exceptions.
                            If they don’t want to take part, what can we do?</p>
                        <p>The President: Take a country like Austria. It is very important. It is
                            small but in the heart of Europe. We should heed its voice.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: The
                            voice of every country should be heeded.</p>
                        <p>I think we can accept as a basis the view by the President to make
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> and Comrade
                                <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> get to work, perhaps
                            throughout the night. While we enjoy our sleep they will do work. We
                            have to cherish our time.</p>
                        <p>The President: They will not see the ballet.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: I am
                            sure he’s seen “Swan Lake.”</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>: Not here. I am
                            looking forward to it.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: Well,
                            Mr. President, that I feel completes the discussion.</p>
                        <p>The President: I think we have a direction set. Also on the trade side
                            there will be further discussions with <persName corresp="#p_FPM1">Flanigan</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>.</p>
                        <p>General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>: At
                            nighttime too.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>: How shall we
                            divide it? Half the time for me and half the time for <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>?</p>
                        <p>[The Soviet side then suggested that an announcement for both sides be
                            made concerning this meeting. It contained the facts of the date of the
                            meeting, the participants, the atmosphere and that there were signatures
                            of the space and science and technology agreements. President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> suggested that the topic for
                            discussion for the meeting be termed “European matters” rather than
                            “European security.” The Soviet side accepted this, and the text of the
                            announcement was agreed to. The meeting then concluded.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>