<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>62. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d62</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">62</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1972-03-17T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1972-03-17T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="south-and-central-asia" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="south-and-central-asia">South Asia</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recP1TxBSuFrpDZ2S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Interim agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recAZ6vp0KaSfYUeW" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018002867"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Demilitarization</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">military
                        presence</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-03-17T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-03-17T13:00:00-05:00" n="62"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d62">
                <head>62. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d62fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 493,
                        President’s Trip Files, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                            >Dobrynin</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>,
                        1972, Vol. 10. Top Secret; Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes Only. The meeting was
                        held in the Map Room at the White House. A notation on the memorandum
                        indicates the President saw it. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> sent a March 28 summary memorandum of this meeting
                        to <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>. (Ibid.) <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s Record of Schedule gives the
                        time of the meeting from 1:10 to 3:10 p.m. (Library of Congress, Manuscript
                        Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box 438,
                        Miscellany, 1968–1976)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1972-03-17T13:00:00-05:00"
                            >March 17, 1972, 1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The President (at beginning)</item>
                    <item>Soviet Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Anatoliy F.
                            Dobrynin</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Summit</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The President joined us at the beginning of the meeting. The President made two
                    points: he said he was going to Moscow in order to do serious business. There
                    were some places to go for drinks and toasts, and there were other places to do
                    business. Moscow was the place where he wanted to do business.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d62fn2">In his memoirs <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> noted that “on March 17 <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> dropped in on one of my meetings with
                            <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> and told him that I was
                        to supervise all major summit preparations. Technical negotiations on
                        economic relations or scientific or cultural exchanges were turned over to
                        the Cabinet departments, with the State Department playing the lead role,
                        but the key policy issues were to be handled in the channel.” (<hi
                            rend="italic">White House Years</hi>, p. 1128)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Secondly, the President wanted to make sure <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> understood the arrangements for preparing the visit.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> was in complete charge of
                    the summit. We would parcel out specific assignments to specific individuals in
                    the bureaucracy, but this would be done at <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName>’s initiative and <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> should take his guidance from me. He hoped that
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> would cooperate in this
                    effort. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said <pb facs="0239"
                        n="210" xml:id="pg_210"/> that he understood that the big issues such as
                    South Asia, Southeast Asia, Middle East, and <gloss target="#t_SALT1"
                        >SALT</gloss> would be handled in the meetings with me and that others might
                    go to the bureaucracy. The President said that was correct, but he should take
                    the general instructions from me.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> then said, “Our friend <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry</persName> is very modest. Is he or is he not coming
                    to Moscow?” The President replied that a visit was impossible before the summit.
                    One, I had gone to Peking because there was no Chinese <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> in Washington, and two, it would break
                    too much china in our bureaucracy. However, he would be glad to have me go to
                    Moscow <hi rend="italic">after</hi> the summit. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> said this could be settled either at the summit or
                    shortly after.</p>
                <p>At this point, the President left. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> and I continued the conversation.</p>
                <p>I told <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> that I had a complaint
                    about the March 16 joint announcement<note n="3" xml:id="d62fn3">See <ref
                            target="#d59">Document 59</ref>.</note> of the date of the President’s
                    visit. I showed him the text which I thought we had agreed upon and the text
                        <gloss target="#t_TASS1">TASS</gloss> published (attached at Tab A).<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d62fn4">Attached but not printed.</note> I said I simply did
                    not understand Soviet procedures. Here I had checked every word with him, giving
                    him four different drafts, and finally when the announcement was published it
                    turned out to be exactly what the Soviets had proposed to begin with. It
                    corresponded in no way to the text we had been discussing. This was all the more
                    remarkable because there were no disagreements as to substance. Was it really
                    worth undermining confidence in this manner? <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> replied that if there was any fault, it was entirely
                    his. He had thought that the Soviet text was generally acceptable and that we
                    had asked for an alternative formulation only to improve the English. He had
                    checked our text for its consistency with the Russian, not to produce an
                    identical text. I said I hoped that we would once agree on a joint text; we have
                    made four unsuccessful attempts. That would, of course, affect our estimate of
                    how we could cooperate on the communiqué. We could not possibly afford two
                    different versions. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> agreed.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Trade</hi>
                </p>
                <p>We then turned to substantive matters. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> said that the trade situation seemed to be in hand.
                    After his conversation with <persName corresp="#p_PPG1"
                        >Peterson</persName>,<note n="5" xml:id="d62fn5">
                        <persName corresp="#p_PPG1">Peterson</persName> reported on his March 16
                        discussion with <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> in a March
                        17 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and
                            <persName corresp="#p_FPM1">Flanigan</persName>. (National Archives,
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 493, President’s Trip
                        Files, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>/<persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, 1972, Vol. 10) In a March 13
                        memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> entitled
                        “Soviet Economic Negotiating Strategy—Some Preliminary Thoughts,” <persName
                            corresp="#p_PPG1">Peterson</persName> offered the following caution: “If
                        major asymmetry is likely, and I have detailed projections through the end
                        of this decade to validate it, we could find ourselves in a kind of
                        ‘reverse–linkage’ situation. The Russians, knowing our vulnerability, could
                        then threaten us with non–payment and perhaps turn our generosity into both
                        their short–term economic and longer–term political advantage.” (Ibid., Box
                        992, <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> Chronological Files, March
                        7–15, 1972)</note> he had come to the view that it might be better for
                        <persName corresp="#p_PNS1">Patolichev</persName> to come over here in
                    April. He did not see much sense in having second–level people conduct
                    negotiations that were better conducted at a higher level. I told him this was,
                    of course, agreeable to us.</p>
                <pb facs="0240" n="211" xml:id="pg_211"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Middle East</hi>
                </p>
                <p>He then asked, “What about the major items? Let’s talk about the Middle East. You
                    told me you would have some proposition to make.” I said that the first question
                    that I wanted to raise was: could they give me some expression of how they
                    propose to inform the Egyptians if some agreement were reached between the
                    President and <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>? It seemed to me
                    extremely dangerous to inform the Egyptians at all since they were bound to be
                    penetrated by the Israelis. For us it was a matter of the gravest importance.
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> grew somewhat restless. He
                    said delivering the Egyptians was their problem and they could not be
                    accountable on that. I said that was not the issue; the issue was whether the
                    process of notification would create substantive difficulties that would affect
                    our situation and the possibility of carrying through with any understanding
                    that might be reached. For example, I said,<note n="6" xml:id="d62fn6">
                        <persName>Donald Bergus</persName>, principal officer, <gloss
                            target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> Interests Section, Cairo.</note> the
                    interim agreement we were discussing was worse than what Bergus had offered them
                    in the bilateral discussions. If they were going to be asked by the Soviets to
                    accept a worse interim agreement, there had to be some argument that would make
                    this plausible. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> again said that
                    I seem to be producing one red herring after another to avoid facing concrete
                    issues. I said this was not the case, and I insisted that they produce some
                    expression from Moscow of how they would deal with the implementation of any
                    agreement.</p>
                <p>Turning to the substance of the settlement, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> asked whether I had formulated any ideas. I told him
                    that it seemed to me that the irreducible Israeli position was for the airfield
                    just east of Eilat, control over Sharm el Sheikh, and a land connection with
                    Sharm el Sheikh. This perhaps could be wrapped up in some riparian arrangement
                    of the states along the Gulf of Aqaba, which perhaps might provide a fig leaf
                    for Israeli presence in Sharm el Sheikh. (Attached at Tab B is a memorandum
                    explaining this.)<note n="7" xml:id="d62fn7">Not attached.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> asked my view of
                    demilitarization. I said in my view demilitarization would have to take place at
                    least to the western edge of the passes. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> said that in effect I was giving him the Israeli
                    position. I said that if he talked to the Israeli Ambassador, he would not get
                    that idea; this would be next to impossible to sell to the Israelis. <pb
                        facs="0241" n="212" xml:id="pg_212"/> What I was trying to do was to get a
                    position which the Israelis might accept with some considerable pressure but
                    short of actions that would lead them to conclude that they were better off
                    going to war. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said that in
                    effect we were returning to the old position in which all the sacrifices had to
                    be made in Egypt. I said that the pity was that <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> could never seem to understand that these were
                    negotiating arguments that we had already heard in New York and Washington. If
                    he was talking to me, he should face the substance of the problem, and the
                    substance was that we were prepared to use our good offices with the Israelis
                    but only within a framework that we thought would not drive them to acts of
                    total desperation.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> asked why the demilitarized zone
                    had to be entirely on the Egyptian side. I said it was because equivalent
                    demilitarized zones would drive the Israelis back to Jerusalem. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> asked whether we would consider
                    proportional demilitarized zones. I said it seemed to me extremely improbable,
                    but if he wanted to make a proposal this was of course open to him.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> indicated that he did not think
                    we were making much progress. He said the difficulty was that we did not take
                    the Soviet proposals sufficiently seriously. The Soviet Union had offered to
                    withdraw all its forces from Egypt, except a number roughly equivalent to what
                    we had in Iran, not to establish bases elsewhere, and to accept limitations on
                    its arms shipments. This responded exactly to what we had said publicly in July
                    1969 we wanted. Now we were haggling about a few miles of territory.</p>
                <p>I responded that <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> always had the
                    great ability to present his position in the form of enormous concessions,
                    without ever looking at what we were doing on our side. For example, the Soviet
                    proposal was a way for the Soviets of extricating themselves from a difficult
                    situation. Their client could not win a war with the Israelis. Therefore, a
                    continuation of the situation would lead to one of two situations: either a
                    conviction on the part of the Arabs that their alliance with the Soviet Union
                    was not adequate to produce a settlement, or a war by the Egyptians which would
                    face the Soviet Union with a decision of military support and a risk out of
                    proportion to anything that could be achieved.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> answered that this was partially
                    true, but there was a third possibility that the Soviet Union had to consider.
                    The Soviet Union was now at a watershed; its next move would be a considerable
                    increase of its military presence in Egypt and other Arab states. He could
                    assure me they were deluged with offers, for example, to provide air protection
                    to other Arab countries. The Soviet Union had requests for a massive influx of
                    arms which then could be given with the argument that the Soviet Union would
                    stay there until the local people were in a position to defeat the Israelis
                    militarily. [Note: This seems confirmed by <pb facs="0242" n="213"
                        xml:id="pg_213"/> Israeli intelligence.]<note n="8" xml:id="d62fn8">Brackets
                        in the source text.</note> Also the Soviet Union was well aware of the fact
                    that its proposal really opened up the field for us to compete with them much
                    more effectively in the Arab world than is now the case. In short, it was a
                    major policy act by the Soviet Union, and if we did not pick it up, the
                    consequences might be quite serious. However, he would transmit my suggestions
                    to Moscow and he would give me their reaction.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <gloss target="#t_SALT1">
                        <hi rend="italic">SALT</hi>
                    </gloss>
                </p>
                <p>We then turned to <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> asked how serious we were about <gloss
                        target="#t_SLBM1">SLBM</gloss>s. I repeated once more that we were extremely
                    serious, and that indeed I doubted that an agreement was possible that did not
                    include <gloss target="#t_SLBM1">SLBM</gloss>s. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> said he would transmit this to Moscow. He asked me for
                    our <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> position. I hinted at movement in the
                    direction of two–for–two, but put it in form of thinking out loud with no
                    definite prospect of a final decision.<note n="9" xml:id="d62fn9">Following
                        extensive discussion at the Verification Panel meeting of March 8, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> noted that on the <gloss
                            target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> issue: “There are two basic decisions: 1)
                        whether to grant the Soviets any <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss>
                        defense, and 2) whether we should make any modification in our proposal. If
                        the President decides these two issues, we can make a technical decision on
                        the other aspects.” As to “the question of inclusion of <gloss
                            target="#t_SLBM1">SLBM</gloss>s,” <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> continued, “There are two issues: 1) whether or
                        not they <hi rend="italic">must</hi> be included; we are all agreed that we
                        want them included if we can get them, but the question is how essential is
                        it that they be included; and 2) what modifications could we make in our
                        proposal that would make their inclusion more probable?” <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> later added: “I have a horror of
                        the President’s getting into technical details in Moscow.” (National
                        Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                        Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Institutional Files (H–Files), Box H–107,
                        Verification Panel Minutes, Originals) At the <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> meeting on March 17, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                            >Nixon</persName> noted: “We don’t have to have an agreement because we
                        are going to Moscow. We do it in the context of the national interest—they
                        are moving in the arms race and we are not. We are beginning on both sides
                        to halt the escalation in a race that neither side can be allowed to win. We
                        can’t let them go to massive superiority—but its more difficult for us to
                        match them.” (Memorandum for the record, March 17; ibid., Box H–110, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Minutes, Originals)</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Communiqué</hi>
                </p>
                <p>At the end of the meeting I handed him a draft of an agreed statement of
                    principles and outline of the joint communiqué (attached at Tab C).<note n="10"
                        xml:id="d62fn10">Tab C was attached but is not printed. In a March 16
                        memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_SHH1">Sonnenfeldt</persName> described the draft joint
                        communiqué: “You will note that this draft finesses who the President will
                        meet and in what circumstances; it also leaves open what bilateral
                        negotiations will be completed; it keeps the economic part vague; it merely
                        lists a section on <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> without any text.”
                        (Ibid., <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box
                        67, Country Files, Europe, <gloss target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_SHH1">Sonnenfeldt</persName> Papers [2 of 2]) In
                        discussing <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> issues during a telephone
                        discussion with <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>, March 18,
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> stated: “We can do them
                        like we did some other things. Also we want to leave something open to be
                        settled at the summit. You and I can agree but we should leave something to
                        be settled at Helsinki.” (Transcript of telephone conversation between
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>, March 18, 10:40 a.m.; Library of
                        Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box 371, Telephone Conversations,
                        Chronological File)</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> expressed great appreciation and
                    indicated that it was a step forward to have something to work on. We then
                    discussed the dates for further meetings, and settled on March 30.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
