<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>74. Memorandum From Helmut Sonnenfeldt of the National Security Council Staff
                    to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the National
                    Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d74</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">74</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1972-03-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1972-03-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">military
                        presence</term>
                    <term ref="rectLhSs11Y4ZQ6zE" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015466"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bombers</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7Bwbos1G7X7n" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2013002394"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">MIG</term>
                    <term ref="recr08QgEMEm1Bk04" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="recu3GH1ojKcJBA1c" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85111861"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Reconnaissance aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recUatc2rZ79DXSzf" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-03-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-03-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="74"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d74">
                <head>74. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_SHH1" type="from">Helmut
                        Sonnenfeldt</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                    President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d74fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 67, Country
                        Files, Europe, <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_SHH1">Sonnenfeldt</persName> Papers [2 of 2]. Secret;
                        Outside System. Sent for information.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1972-03-30">March 30, 1972</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>The Soviets and the Middle East Dilemma</item>
                </list>
                <p>On several recent occasions, Soviet diplomats, including <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>, have made it clear that the Middle
                    East will be a “major item” on the Summit agenda. And they may be holding out to
                        <persName corresp="#p_SAMAAS1">Sadat</persName> and possibly other Arabs the
                    hope of significant movement toward a peace settlement resulting from the
                    Summit. As long ago as November, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>
                    speculated to <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> that an agreement on
                    a set of “principles” ought to come out of the summit,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d74fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                            >Dobrynin</persName> discussed the Soviet proposal for a set of
                        “principles” on the Middle East during a meeting on November 1; see <ref
                            target="#d10fn2">footnote 2, Document 10</ref>.</note> and in the last
                    weeks the Soviets have been actively probing what the <gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >US</gloss> might have in mind.</p>
                <p>There are some worrisome aspects in this situation. Some people, like the
                    Israelis, believe that the Soviets are preparing to set us up for a diplomatic
                    kill in Moscow by accepting the <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>’
                    Plan as a basis for an Arab–Israeli settlement. According to this theory, the
                    Soviets, knowing that the Egyptians would settle on this basis and that the
                    Israelis strongly oppose because of the provision for full withdrawal, would
                    attempt to draw the President out by endorsing our earlier position. This would
                    put us on the spot again because we could not produce the Israelis. If it
                    worked, the Soviets would be seen as favoring an American plan but they could
                    also pose as the champions of peace in the Middle East and demonstrate to their
                    Arab clients that they are doing something useful in the diplomatic realm.</p>
                <p>They may, of course, simply be interested in eliciting some sense of what could
                    be the basis for negotiation now rather than in seriously embarrassing us. This
                    would be more likely to be the case if they genuinely want (a) progress toward a
                    settlement and (b) to avoid a situation where they would have to commit
                    forces.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, the question arises, at least as a contingency in the Soviet view,
                    of what their alternatives would be should it become clear that diplomacy had
                    run its course. Could the Soviets contemplate military action; indeed, could
                    they stop it even if they insisted? The Egyptians <pb facs="0266" n="237"
                        xml:id="pg_237"/> seem generally to be waiting for the outcome of the summit
                    before deciding on next steps, and the reaction could be sharp if they are
                    disillusioned by its results. The Israelis, of course, hope that the Egyptians
                    and Soviets would then conclude that they have no recourse but to negotiate with
                    Israel. The Soviet–Arab alternative is to try to increase the threat of military
                    action another notch.</p>
                <p>Judging by the performance in the Indo–Pak confrontation, there comes a time when
                    the Soviets realize that if military action cannot be avoided, they must have
                    achieved some degree of influence over timing and tactics, and the outcome. In
                    contrast to their political role at the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> in the
                    Indian crisis, in the Middle East, their military presence almost ensures some
                    direct involvement of their own personnel, at least in Egypt. If it is true that
                    the present balance would guarantee a defeat for the Egyptians, then one line of
                    Soviet action would be to use their own forces to redress the balance and
                    guarantee at least a standoff, or possibly some limited Egyptian gains. This, of
                    course, would run a very high risk that we would enter into picture to “right
                    the balance” in favor of the Israelis. Against this background, it is worth
                    noting the rather extensive Soviet diplomatic activity in the past two
                    months.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Egypt.</hi> The Soviets have long held the view (as we
                            have) that Egypt’s basic military problem is not the quality and
                            quantity of its equipment but the morale, technical capabilities and
                            proficiency of its military personnel. Yet despite the fact that more
                            advanced weaponry at this point only brings marginal improvement, the
                            Soviets, in response to Egyptian pleas, keep introducing it. Thus when
                                <persName corresp="#p_SAMAAS1">Sadat</persName> went to Moscow in
                                February<note n="3" xml:id="d74fn3">See <ref target="#d43">Document
                                    43</ref>.</note> and made a strong pitch for more advanced
                            equipment, they promised TU–22 supersonic bombers, more advanced
                            versions of the MIG–21 and T–62 tanks. This followed the provision of a
                            squadron of missile carrying T–16 bombers and several high–altitude
                            FOXBAT reconnaissance aircraft with Soviet pilots and a training program
                            as a result of Sadat’s visit to Moscow last October.<note n="4"
                                xml:id="d74fn4">See <ref target="#d5">Document 5</ref>.</note> The
                            point is that in Egyptian hands this equipment will not significantly
                            improve their offensive capability, although it will give them at least
                            a temporary psychological boost and will maintain Soviet influence in
                            Cairo.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_GMAA1">Marshal Grechko</persName> visited Cairo
                            soon after Sadat’s mission to Moscow,<note n="5" xml:id="d74fn5">
                                <persName corresp="#p_GMAA1">Grechko</persName> visited Egypt from
                                February 18 to 21, 1972. For a summary both of the visit and of the
                                joint communiqué, see <hi rend="italic">Current Digest of the Soviet
                                    Press</hi>, vol. XXIV, No. 8, March 22, 1972, p. 22.</note> and
                            brought with him a very high level military delegation, including the
                            commander of the Soviet Air Force and the first deputy <pb facs="0267"
                                n="238" xml:id="pg_238"/> commanders of the Soviet Navy and Air
                            Defense and a first deputy Chief–of–Staff. The result was a cryptic
                            announcement of an “exchange of views” on strengthening Egypt’s “defense
                            capacity” but the Soviets must be reviewing their own military
                            position.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Iraq.</hi> While <persName corresp="#p_GMAA1"
                                >Grechko</persName> was in Egypt, the Iraqi leader, <persName
                                corresp="#p_HS4">Saddam Husayn</persName>, led a delegation to
                            Moscow, apparently at Iraqi initiative.<note n="6" xml:id="d74fn6">
                                <persName corresp="#p_HS4">Hussein</persName> visited the Soviet
                                Union February 11–17. For a summary of the visit and a condensed
                                text of the joint communiqué, see ibid., vol. XXIV, No. 7, March 15,
                                1972, pp. 7–8, 32.</note> He made a speech about the need to develop
                            relations to the level of a “firm strategic alliance.”</p>
                        <p>The final communiqué (February 17) referred to a “study of measures” that
                            could be taken “in the near future” to consolidate relations in
                            “treaties.” On March 12, Moscow radio predicted a new treaty. This is
                            not a purely Arab–Israeli development, since Soviet interests in Iraq
                            also relate to their ambitions in the Persian Gulf.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Syria.</hi> Almost immediately after the Iraqis departed
                        from Moscow, a Soviet delegation, led by Politburo member Kiril Mazurov,
                        arrived in Damascus.<note n="7" xml:id="d74fn7">Mazurov visited Syria from
                            February 21 to 26, 1972. For a condensed text of the joint communiqué,
                            see ibid., vol. XXIV, No. 8, pp. 20–21.</note> The first result was a
                        “cooperation agreement” between the Baath party and the <gloss
                            target="#t_CPSU1">CPSU</gloss>. A party–to–party agreement is something
                        of an achievement in terms of Soviet efforts to exert influence in the Arab
                        world through ruling parties, and to steer them toward national fronts that
                        include the communists. The visit, however, had military aspects. The
                        communiqué indicated that “possible” steps for promoting Syria “defense
                        capability” had been discussed. And Mazurov in a speech referred to a
                        “document” having been signed on this subject. There is also speculation
                        that the question of a Soviet–Syrian treaty was discussed. It is also
                        noteworthy, though not necessarily directly related, that the Syrians
                        shortly after the visit publicly accepted Security Council Resolution 242—as
                        interpreted by the Arabs—as a basis for a peace settlement.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Libya, Algeria, Cyprus.</hi> Despite the rather bitter
                        Libyan denunciation of Moscow during the Indo–Pak war, Jallud<note n="8"
                            xml:id="d74fn8">Major Abdul Salam Jalloud, member of the Libyan
                            Revolutionary Command Council and Minister of the Economy and
                            Industry.</note> came to Moscow in early March to discuss economic,
                        political, and military relations—and speculation is that he bartered Libyan
                        petroleum for Soviet military aid (which might be eventually destined for
                        Egypt). Soviet relations with Algeria also took a small turn for the better
                        as a result of Foreign Trade Minister <persName corresp="#p_PNS1"
                            >Patolichev</persName>’s negotiation in Algiers for a new trade
                        agreement.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0268" n="239" xml:id="pg_239"/>
                <p>Of course, the Soviets have been active in pressing their special claims in the
                    Eastern Mediterranean, through warning against interference in Cyprus, protests
                    against <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> homeporting in Greece, and in his
                    March 20 speech <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> characterized
                    Soviet–Arab relations as broadening in “defense cooperation.”<note n="9"
                        xml:id="d74fn9">See <ref target="#d65">Document 65</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The conventional wisdom is that the Soviets are hedging against a deterioration
                    of their relations with Egypt and, to this end, are consolidating their position
                    in the Arab world generally. Moreover, it is still the standard estimate, based
                    to some degree on Soviet reassurances, that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss> is a force for moderation and restraint or at least is not
                    willing to take actions which might risk a confrontation with us.</p>
                <p>This is reasonable, but looks mainly to the past record and present situation. It
                    is not inconceivable that the Soviets are toying with the notion of a deeper
                    military involvement or at least trying to create the impression of a greater
                    military threat to Israel. Certainly, signing treaties with the erratic regimes
                    in Damascus and Baghdad would be a step toward a greater identification of
                    Soviet power and prestige with governments they cannot control.</p>
                <p>One can only wonder how the Soviets would honor whatever treaty obligations they
                    undertake toward Syria. One possibility would be to tentative station Soviet
                    forces there.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
