<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>85. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d85</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">85</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-10-12T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1972-05-29T22:20:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="rec6SOt1hMx6m4tne" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085495"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recl1U5J9GBlgvmjh" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89004334"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contingency plan</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-equipment" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military supplies</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-05-29T22:20:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-10-12T10:00:00-05:00" n="85" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d85">
                <head>85. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>On April 6, 1972, Assistant to the President <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry
                        Kissinger</persName> received memoranda from Secretary of Defense <persName
                        corresp="#p_LMR2">Laird</persName> and Deputy Assistant to the President
                        <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> on contingency plans for
                    military operations against North Vietnam. <persName corresp="#p_LMR2"
                        >Laird</persName> explained in his memorandum that the Chairman of the Joint
                    Chiefs of Staff, Admiral <persName corresp="#p_MTH1">Thomas H.
                    Moorer</persName>, had developed “outlines” for two possible actions against
                    Haiphong: a one–time air strike against military targets in the area; and a
                    mining operation against shipping in the harbor. <persName corresp="#p_LMR2"
                        >Laird</persName> doubted, however, that either plan would lead to any
                    military advantage. Bombing would be largely ineffective, he argued, since North
                    Vietnam not only operated an intricate distribution system but also received
                    most of its military supplies from the Soviet Union and the People’s Republic of
                    China. Without an intensive air campaign, mining might also fail to interrupt
                    the shipment of military supplies. <persName corresp="#p_LMR2">Laird</persName>
                    did not believe that the proposal to mine the harbor merited “serious
                    consideration” at the time; he believed rather that political factors, both at
                    home and abroad, should determine the American response. <persName
                        corresp="#p_LMR2">Laird</persName> emphasized this point in a handwritten
                    postscript: “The political impact of these plans may be what is wanted by the
                    President—The military impact would be minor and <pb facs="0296" n="267"
                        xml:id="pg_267"/> the impact on present battle would be even less. If the
                    Russians want an excuse to stop their present major (80% supplies) contribution
                    to North Vietnam, mining might have that political impact but I would doubt it.”
                    (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                    Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 1079, Howe
                    Chronological File’s, Feb–Mar–April 1972)</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> dismissed the “negative attitude”
                    adopted by <persName corresp="#p_LMR2">Laird</persName> on the issue of bombing
                    and mining North Vietnam, noting that <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> was already considering “a directive for operations of
                    much greater scope.” (Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1"
                        >Haig</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, April
                    6; ibid.) In a separate, undated memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> proposed
                    “an intense no–holds barred air and naval campaign” to force Hanoi to retreat on
                    the battlefield and return to the negotiating table. The campaign consisted of
                    bombing every area in the country (except a buffer zone along the Chinese
                    border); bombarding the entire coastline; mining and blockading every port.
                        <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> further urged a political
                    campaign of psychological warfare against North Vietnam and diplomatic pressure
                    against its allies, including the Soviet Union. There was, however, a price to
                    be paid: “It is recognized that these actions may force cancellation of the
                    summit and it is assumed that the summit would be laid on the line as one of the
                    early diplomatic steps in the preparatory phase.” (Ibid.)</p>
                <p>Although he admitted ignorance of these contingency plans, <persName
                        corresp="#p_LW2">Winston Lord</persName> of the National Security Council
                    staff also addressed the impact of air operations against North Vietnam in an
                    April 8 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>.
                        <persName corresp="#p_LW2">Lord</persName> made a distinction between
                    “effective” and “harmful” bombing: the former, limited to the battle zone and
                    direct support areas, was already justified by provocation from Hanoi; the
                    latter, extended to the rear areas of North Vietnam, was likely to provoke an
                    outcry not only in Washington but also from Moscow and Beijing. <persName
                        corresp="#p_LW2">Lord</persName> assumed that <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> was actively considering punitive bombing on a short
                    term basis “to show Hanoi (and Moscow and Peking) that we are capable of going
                    bananas.” The result of such action, however, would be “the worst of all
                    worlds,” doing more damage to <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> policy than to
                    the North Vietnamese military. “I agree that this is a decisive test for our
                    Vietnam policy and for our global policy,” <persName corresp="#p_LW2"
                        >Lord</persName> concluded. “I also believe we may pass the test with the
                    help of effective bombing. More spectacular bombing cannot rescue us and indeed
                    could wreck the chance we do have.” (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss>
                    59, <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss> Files: Lot 77 <gloss target="#t_D1"
                        >D</gloss> 112, Box 335, [<persName corresp="#p_LW2">Lord</persName>–Chron],
                    April ′72)</p>
                <p>In spite of the reservations expressed by <persName corresp="#p_LW2"
                        >Lord</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_LMR2">Laird</persName>, President
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> decided that the contingency
                    plan outlined by <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> would be
                    implemented by May 8 if the South Vietnamese army proved unable to withstand the
                    North Vietnamese assault. (<persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName>, <hi
                        rend="italic">Inner Circles</hi>, page 282; <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName>, <hi rend="italic">White House Years</hi>, page
                    1116)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
