<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-04-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-04-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="91" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d91">
                        <head>91. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_SHH1" type="from">Helmut
                                Sonnenfeldt</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                            President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d91fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 67,
                                Country Files, Europe, <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SHH1">Sonnenfeldt</persName> Papers [1 of
                                2]. Secret; Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes Only. Sent for urgent
                                action. The memorandum was forwarded through <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName>, who initialed it. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> wrote “OK” on the top of
                                the first page. According to his memoirs, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> requested the memorandum.
                                “To keep up the pressure,” he explained, “I asked <persName corresp="#p_SHH1">Hal Sonnenfeldt</persName>, my principal
                                adviser on Soviet affairs, what negotiations with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> we could slow down that were of
                                substantial interest to the Kremlin leaders.” (<hi rend="italic">White House Years</hi>, p. 1118)</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-04-10">April 10, 1972</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>The Soviets and Vietnam—Our Signals</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>If the situation in Vietnam should deteriorate and assuming we want to
                            signal more explicitly to the Soviets, we need to select a set of
                            actions that convey our meaning without prematurely jeopardizing the
                            summit. This means either slowing down or freezing in discussions or
                            contacts that are of substantial interest to the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>As always in these situations, these things do not come free of charge
                            since we—or important segments of our society—also have an interest in
                            what is being done with the Soviets. The main object, however, would be
                            to signal that we will not “do business as usual.” Consistency alone
                            would seem to dictate some action comparable to what we did in the
                            India–Pakistan crisis, the 1970 Middle East crisis and the 1970 Cuban
                            fracas. Except possibly for the last, none of these involved Soviet
                            actions—acts of commission and omission—quite as directly damaging to us
                            as what is happening in Vietnam. I don’t mean to draw simple analogies:
                            there are many important differences cutting in different directions. In
                            South Asia, the Middle East and Cuba there was a potential for direct
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>–Soviet confrontation. Soviet
                            capacity to influence what was happening was considerable—in Cuba the
                            Soviets could actually control events. In Vietnam, the Soviets’
                            involvement is indirect (unless we moved against Haiphong) and their
                            influence is more conjectural; yet Soviet support through matériel and
                            advice is a crucially important asset to the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>. It is killing Americans, could unhinge the
                            Administration’s whole policy line in Southeast Asia and could injure
                            the President domestically.</p>
                        <p>I think we should operate on the broad hypothesis that whatever the
                            precise Soviet motive and role in Vietnam, in the end the present <pb facs="0316" n="287" xml:id="pg_287"/> Soviet leaders probably have
                            at least as large a stake as the President in not having the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>–Soviet relationship degenerate.
                            Consequently, the type of moves listed below should have the effect of
                            inducing the Soviets to exert some pressure on Hanoi. Even if this
                            judgment is wrong it is important to structure the situation in a way
                            that brings home to <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> that
                            he, too, will have to bear some of the cost of what is happening in
                            Vietnam; and that we are sufficiently serious and confident that we are
                            prepared to pay a price ourselves in <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>–Soviet relations.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Actions</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>(<hi rend="italic">Note:</hi> 1. Public statements a la <persName corresp="#p_LMR2">Laird</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MCRJ1">McCloskey</persName><note n="2" xml:id="d91fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_LMR2">Laird</persName> declared in a news
                                conference on April 7 that the Soviet Union was “a major
                                contributor” to the North Vietnamese offensive by failing to limit
                                the use of its equipment to defensive purposes. (<hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, April 8, 1972, pp. 1, 11) For
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MCRJ1">McCloskey</persName>’s remarks on
                                April 4, see <ref target="#d81">Document 81</ref>.</note> should be
                            stopped for now.</p>
                        <p>2. You should background selected journalists on the meaning of the
                            President’s statement at the <gloss target="#t_BW1">BW</gloss>
                                ceremony;<note n="3" xml:id="d91fn3">See <ref target="#d89">Document
                                    89</ref>.</note> also <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>.)</p>
                        <p>The <hi rend="italic">grain sales talks</hi> are underway; the key issue
                            is credit. This is perhaps the area that we would be most vulnerable to
                            charges of cynicism—extending credit to the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> to buy grain while they ship heavy equipment to Hanoi.
                            Unfortunately, it is also the area where we stand to make a commercial
                            gain. Since no agreement is likely without credits, this should become
                            for now our sticking point. In other words, <hi rend="italic">this
                                affair should not reach agreement in the Moscow session</hi> (see
                            draft message to <persName corresp="#p_BEL1">Butz</persName>, Tab
                                A).<note n="4" xml:id="d91fn4">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> approved the
                                attached backchannel message, which was sent to <persName corresp="#p_BEL1">Butz</persName> in Moscow on April 12. The
                                text of the message reads: “<persName corresp="#p_FPM1">Peter
                                    Flanigan</persName> has already told you of the President’s wish
                                not to have your current grain negotiations completed in Moscow. The
                                President wishes to reinforce this directive in light of the Vietnam
                                situation. Until that situation and Soviet role with respect to it
                                are clarified the President must fully retain option not to proceed
                                with the type of agreement you are negotiating. Tactical judgement
                                as to which issues in your negotiation should be left unresolved is
                                left to you and Palmby. In social and other contacts and
                                particularly in any public statements you should avoid all
                                optimistic language concerning overall <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>–Soviet relations. You should be aware that the
                                President is deeply concerned about Vietnam and Soviet role relating
                                thereto.” (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 718, Country Files,
                                Europe, <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, Vol. XXI) The White
                                House received a reply that afternoon, however, reporting that
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BEL1">Butz</persName> had left Moscow
                                before the message could be delivered to him. (Ibid.)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The <hi rend="italic">maritime talks</hi> open on April 17; we will have
                            a rather high level delegation in Moscow (<persName corresp="#p_SND1">Samuels</persName>, <persName>Gibson</persName>, <persName>Dick
                                Davies</persName>, <persName>Eagleburger</persName>).<note n="5" xml:id="d91fn5">
                                <persName corresp="#p_SND1">Nathaniel Samuels</persName>, Deputy
                                Under Secretary of State for Economic Affairs; <persName corresp="#p_SND1">Samuels</persName>, Andrew E. Gibson,
                                Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Maritime Affairs; <persName corresp="#p_DRT1">Richard T. Davies</persName>, Deputy Assistant
                                Secretary of State for European Affairs; and Lawrence S.
                                Eagleburger, Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for Policy Plans
                                and National Security Council Affairs.</note> The unfortunate aspect
                            will be the visibility—banquet toasts, <pb facs="0317" n="288" xml:id="pg_288"/> etc. There is also the angle easing regulations
                            for Soviet ships to enter our ports, which evokes images of Soviet
                            shipping to North Vietnam. Because of the protocol sensitivities of
                            Gibson and State, it may be difficult to change the composition of the
                            delegation. But we can ensure that the talks do not yield agreements in
                            this round, or we could postpone them by a week. At least, we should
                            tell <persName corresp="#p_SND1">Samuels</persName> to avoid comraderie
                            and we could tell him like <persName corresp="#p_BEL1">Butz</persName>,
                            not to permit matters to reach completion.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Incidents at sea</hi> is still awaiting a Soviet
                            response to beginning a second round. The Soviets will not agree to the
                            first round understandings in any case, until there has been another
                            round. Whenever they reply with a date we can decide at that time
                            whether to let the timetable slide. High–level discussions with Soviet
                            Admirals would be rather unseemly while we charge the Soviets with
                            supporting the North Vietnamese offensive.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Health, Science, Environmental and Space
                                Cooperation</hi> do not lend themselves very well to linkage or
                            slowdowns since our rationale is that we and the Soviets benefit about
                            equally and these are more or less in the interest of “mankind.”</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Lend–Lease</hi> is clearly in our interest and useful
                            in linkage to the other economic questions. The talks start this week
                            and we already have a tough, probably non–negotiable position.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Exchanges Agreement</hi> will be signed on April
                            11. There is little purpose in stopping it, but we could get word to
                                <persName corresp="#p_BJD1">Beam</persName> to keep the rhetoric
                            down.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <persName corresp="#p_PNS1">Patolichev</persName>
                                Visit</hi> is the most highly visible project in the immediate
                            future (April 27). He will receive considerable publicity as will the
                            general topic of Soviet–American economic relations. <hi rend="italic">To call it off would be a strong signal, but should be considered
                                if the situation in Vietnam continues</hi>. If he does come, you
                            might consider telling him that Vietnam could well set back economic
                            relations since our public would not understand our moving on such
                            things as credit under present circumstances.</p>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_SALT1">
                                <hi rend="italic">SALT</hi></gloss>. A freeze in <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> would be a strong signal, of course,
                            though this begs the question of who has the greatest interest in the
                            agreement. These talks have remained fairly well insulated from other
                            events, despite <persName>Smith</persName>’s blunder in telling Semyonov
                            of your message on India-Pakistan.<note n="6" xml:id="d91fn6">See <ref target="#d28">Document 28</ref>.</note> Since the negotiations
                            are now so tangled that a signal might not even get through, the best
                            source is probably to continue without change for a week or two. By
                            standing on our <gloss target="#t_SLBM1">SLBM</gloss> position, and our
                                <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> proposals we, in effect, convey
                            at least some firmness.</p>
                        <pb facs="0318" n="289" xml:id="pg_289"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Cuba.</hi> The Soviets still have a guided missile
                            cruiser and an F–Class attack submarine in Cienfuegos. They have been at
                            sea exercising with the Cubans. <hi rend="italic">If</hi> we want to
                            signal, then some more intensive surveillance and even harassment could
                            be laid on. It has some merit in its own right since the prolonged stay
                            of some Soviet naval vessels seems to be a violation, at least in
                            spirit, of the “understanding.”</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">High–Level Diplomacy.</hi> You will recall that at the
                            end of <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>’s last
                                letter<note n="7" xml:id="d91fn7">
                                <ref target="#d72">Document 72</ref>.</note> he referred to the
                            bombing. He brought it up in his March 20 speech,<note n="8" xml:id="d91fn8">See <ref target="#d65">Document 65</ref>.</note> but
                            this particular passage was censored out of the printed version. It is a
                            peg for a Presidential message, but I would think that this should come
                            later in the scenario. If we intended to engage the Soviets over North
                            Vietnam directly at the Presidential level then we should have a clear
                            message in mind. Do we want to tax the Soviets with their supplies? Do
                            we want to threaten some action? Or are we going to press them to use
                            their influence for negotiations? (If you wish, I could begin working on
                            a draft.)<note n="9" xml:id="d91fn9">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> wrote “Yes” in the
                                margin near the end of this paragraph.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Summit.</hi> Whatever we decide on sending small
                            signals or escalating our diplomacy, we have to consider that in the
                            next two weeks or so the summit in its broadest outline and in some
                            detail will be set (the advance Party arrives April 19). If we are
                            concerned that by May 22 we may be in a difficult situation vis–à–vis
                            bombing and the situation in the South, we might consider cutting back
                            on the visit. For example, shortening it by a day or so, dropping off
                            the third stop in Baku. This does not mean much but it might be prudent
                            to begin thinking of what the visit would be like if the situation
                            worsens.</p>
                        <p>We might consider dropping off the Polish visit, since it is marginal in
                            any case. After all Poland does participate in the three power
                            commission for Indochina, though retaliation against Warsaw is a rather
                            cloudy signal.</p>
                        <p>We may of course find ourselves confronted by a Soviet decision to call
                            off the summit or a threat to do so; and I note that for unexplained
                            reasons the Poles have still not reacted to our acceptance of their
                            invitation. For the moment, it would be imprudent for us to escalate the
                            situation by tinkering with summit plans. That complex of decisions is
                            at least as tough for the Soviets as it is for us and the best course
                            for now is to wait. But we should <hi rend="italic">not</hi> for now
                            have <persName corresp="#p_ZRL1">Ziegler</persName> say anything on the
                            itinerary, whatever the leaks.</p>
                        <pb facs="0319" n="290" xml:id="pg_290"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">In sum, here is a modest game plan for
                                gradualism:</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>—Ensure that the grain sales talks yield no results for now
                                    (message to <persName corresp="#p_BEL1">Butz</persName> at Tab
                                        A).<note n="10" xml:id="d91fn10">
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> initialed
                                        his approval of this recommendation.</note>
                                </item>
                                <item>—Keep the maritime talks in low key and avoid final agreement;
                                    tell <persName corresp="#p_SND1">Samuels</persName> and
                                        Gibson.<note n="11" xml:id="d91fn11">
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> initialed
                                        his approval of this recommendation and issued the following
                                        handwritten instruction: “Avoid excessively friendly toasts.
                                        Want to delay a week.”</note>
                                </item>
                                <item>—Hold off agreeing to date when Soviets propose one for the
                                    second round of incidents at sea.<note n="12" xml:id="d91fn12">
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> wrote “want
                                        to think” next to this recommendation.</note>
                                </item>
                                <item>—Stay tough on lend–lease.<note n="13" xml:id="d91fn13">
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> initialed
                                        his approval of this recommendation.</note>
                                </item>
                                <item>—Leave other bilaterals alone for now, but tell <persName corresp="#p_BJD1">Beam</persName> to keep rhetoric low when
                                    Exchanges Agreement is signed April 11.<note n="14" xml:id="d91fn14">
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> initialed
                                        his approval of this recommendation.</note>
                                </item>
                                <item>—Harassment of Soviet ships in Cuba.<note n="15" xml:id="d91fn15">
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> wrote “no”
                                        next to this recommendation.</note>
                                </item>
                                <item>—Use <persName corresp="#p_PNS1">Patolichev</persName> visit
                                    to take tough line, but <hi rend="italic">not</hi> involve the
                                    President. Cancel, if situation deteriorates.<note n="16" xml:id="d91fn16">
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> initialed
                                        his approval of this recommendation.</note>
                                </item>
                                <item>—Letter to <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>
                                    later this week.<note n="17" xml:id="d91fn17">
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> did not
                                        indicate a decision on this recommendation.</note>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Could you let me know which, if any of these, you wish pursued, and how.
                            The message to <persName corresp="#p_BEL1">Butz</persName> for your
                            approval is at Tab A.<note n="18" xml:id="d91fn18">Attached but not
                                printed.</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>