<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Steinhardt) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d117</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">117</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-01-06T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-01-06T08:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-01-06T08:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-01-06T08:00:00-05:00" n="117"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d117">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">761.94/1253: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Steinhardt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract]<note n="1" xml:id="d117fn1">The first two
                            paragraphs of this telegram are printed in <ref
                                target="frus1941v04#pg_905">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p.
                                905</ref>.</note>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-01-06T16:00:00+03:00"
                            >January 6, 1941—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 7:47 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>14.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>The halt in the Soviet-German negotiations appears to have been occasioned by
                    considerably more than Schnurre’s casual reference in a conversation with me 3
                    days ago to “endless detail and Russian exactions in respect of unimportant
                    matters.” The Soviets have been insistent in seeking a final adjustment of the
                    problems affecting German interests which have arisen out of the seizure of the
                    Baltic States<note n="2" xml:id="d117fn2">For correspondence concerning the
                        forcible occupation of the Baltic States and their incorporation into the
                        Soviet Union, see <ref target="frus1940v01#pg_357">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1940, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 357</ref> ff.</note> by the Soviets
                    (see my 13, January 5, 1 p.m.), and that while this <pb facs="0130" n="118"
                        xml:id="pg_118"/> subject will probably be amicably disposed of it has
                    caused the present delay. I am also inclined to the view that the recent <hi
                        rend="italic">démarches</hi> by the Soviet Government to the United States
                    and Great Britain with respect to the Baltic gold [and] ships constitute an
                    attempt to offset German pressure with respect to German interests in the Baltic
                    States, the Soviets entertaining the hope that concessions by the United States
                    or Great Britain, or both, could be used to their advantage in dealing with the
                    German demands. This view is supported by the Soviet endeavors to extract
                    concessions from the United States and Great Britain by holding out the hope
                    that such concessions will result in driving a wedge between the Soviet Union
                    and Germany without any real intention at the present time on the part of the
                    Soviet Government to depart from its policy of cooperation with Germany.
                    Apparently the Soviet Government hopes by these means to gain concessions from
                    the United States and Great Britain without giving anything in return other than
                    the encouragement of wishful thinking.<note n="3" xml:id="d117fn3">For
                        correspondence regarding discussions of difficulties affecting relations
                        between the United States and the Soviet Union, see <ref target="#pg_667"
                            >pp. 667</ref> ff.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The halt in the Soviet-Rumanian negotiations<note n="4" xml:id="d117fn4">For
                        correspondence on the interest shown by the United States in German and
                        Soviet activities in the Balkan States, see <ref target="#pg_272">pp.
                            272</ref> ff.</note> appears to have been occasioned by an unwillingness
                    of the Soviet Government to conclude these negotiations until its agreement with
                    Germany has become effective, while at the same time giving evidence to the
                    Rumanian Government of its displeasure with German domination of Rumania and for
                    the further purpose of having the question of control of the mouths of the
                    Danube determined according to the Soviet desire that they be exclusively under
                    joint Soviet-Rumanian supervision.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Steinhardt</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
