<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-01-17T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-01-17T06:00:00-05:00" n="123" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">761.62/854: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Steinhardt</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-01-17T14:00:00+03:00">January 17, 1941—2 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received January 17—11:48 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>104. <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> this morning publishes a brief
                                    Tass<note n="22" xml:id="d123fn22">Telegraph Agency of the
                                    Soviet Union, official communication agency of the Soviet
                                    Government.</note> item from Berlin quoting the German DNB<note n="23" xml:id="d123fn23">Deutsches Nachrichtenbüro, German News
                                    Agency.</note> agency as stating that in connection with the
                                conclusion of the Soviet-German agreement of January 10, 1941,
                                regarding the resettlement of German nationals from the Baltic
                                States (see my 51, January 11) 45,000 Germans living in Lithuania
                                and 12,000 Germans who remained in Estonia and Latvia after the
                                resettlement effected during the autumn of 1939 must now return to
                                    Germany.<note n="24" xml:id="d123fn24">The Chargé in Germany
                                    explained in despatch No. 4229, January 14, 1941, that these
                                    agreements completed “the final step in the exchange of
                                    populations between Germany and the Soviet Union” apparently
                                    made at the latter’s request “in order to prevent the creation
                                    in the territory acquired by the Soviet Union in the partition
                                    of Poland and by the annexation of the Baltic States of a German
                                    minority problem which might be manipulated at some later date
                                    by Berlin in the same manner that the minority question was used
                                    in bringing about the dismemberment of Czechoslovakia and
                                    Rumania, and the partition of Poland.” (761.62/862)</note>
                                Special delegates are stated to have been appointed to organize the
                                repatriation from Latvia and Estonia and will leave Berlin on
                                January 16. It is proposed that immigrants coming from Lithuania
                                shall proceed by rail and highway and those from Estonia and Latvia
                                by steamship.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Steinhardt</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>