<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Hungary ( (Pell) ) to President Roosevelt</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d338</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">338</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-06-23T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-06-23T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recDNr3fFoY74D9ro" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="recbHz5atbbO3GlrY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85063084"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Hunger</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Visas</term>
                    <term ref="rec9FMZD7j350k99B" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="food" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184" lcsh-match="exact">Foodstuffs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-06-23T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-06-23T12:00:00-05:00" n="338"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d338">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/15701</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Hungary</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to"
                            >Roosevelt</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Budapest</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-06-23T19:00:00+02:00"
                            >June 23, 1941—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: The war between Russia and Germany
                    broke out yesterday to the great joy of many Hungarians, who would like to see
                    them cut each others throats. They hope to see the Russians beaten and the
                    Germans bogged in and destroyed. It seems as likely a hope as any other. As the
                    Russians will almost certainly destroy all crops on their retreat and the
                    Germans will not hesitate to impound a great part of the foodstuffs of all the
                    neighboring countries, there is a very good prospect of considerable hunger
                    during the coming winter <pb facs="0330" n="318" xml:id="pg_318"/> in places
                    like Hungary. The prospect of the crops here is very bad; although this is
                    normally an exporting country, it will probably not produce as much as the
                    average domestic consumption. With the Germans helping themselves liberally
                    there will necessarily be a good deal of hardship.</p>
                <p>Most of the upper-class Hungarians, who hate the immediate menace, are frankly
                    delighted at the prospect of American aeroplanes being sent to England for the
                    bombing of Germany. Battleships not being able to get up the Danube, they have
                    no fear of British domination.</p>
                <p>It has been suggested that one of the causes of the war was the success of the
                    Russian propaganda in Germany during the short period of Nazi Bolshevik
                    friendship.</p>
                <p>I hope to get off on a tour of the country for a few days in the near future, as
                    I do not believe in a Minister spending all his time in the Capital and knowing
                    nothing of the outlying districts. It may be difficult to work this in, but I
                    shall try to do so.</p>
                <p>You are to be congratulated on the way you have handled the situation. I see no
                    reason why your course of armed neutrality should not continue. Although England
                    has not been beaten by the air attack, I believe that Germany would collapse if
                    as much pressure could be put on it as has been put on England.</p>
                <p>We are having a great deal of trouble with the American citizens anxious to
                    return to the United States. The Germans are making it most difficult to get
                    visas to cross Germany; apparently, partly from a planned desire to be offensive
                    and partly because of the inefficiency of an improperly coordinated government.
                    Even on the continent of Europe their diplomats know nothing of general
                    conditions. For example, when I left Lisbon the German Minister did not know
                    that I would be in any difficulty crossing Germany in a car. Here, they are the
                    same way.</p>
                <p>Our own great lack is of American news. Except what is passed through German
                    propaganda, we know nothing of what is happening in the United States until the
                    arrival of the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> from six to ten weeks late.
                    I think that we should be provided with a couple of competent radio men and
                    apparatus which could take down for us the news reports as they come from
                    America. This would not only be a personal pleasure, but would very much add to
                    the importance and the efficiency of the Legation here. For example, I have no
                    way of knowing the number and quality of aeroplanes sent to England, which is a
                    subject about which accurate information would be of the greatest value to us in
                    our efforts to encourage a large portion of the Hungarians, who value both their
                    independence and their skins.</p>
                <p>Please give our best to Mrs. Roosevelt and to your mother, and, should you see
                    him, to our old friend Ed Perkins, who admires you <pb facs="0331" n="319"
                        xml:id="pg_319"/> greatly. I think it would be worth while ringing him up
                    when you get to Hyde Park.</p>
                <p>I am</p>
                <p>Respectfully,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bertie Pell</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
