<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-10-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-10-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="431" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d431">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">340.1115A/2293</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Secretary
                                of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Long</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-10-14">October 14, 1941</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Italian Ambassador<note n="41a" xml:id="d431fn41a">Ascanio dei
                                principi Colonna.</note> came in this morning at his own request. He
                            said that he had communicated to his Government the proposal which had
                            been made to him in regard to the exchange of Italians in this country
                            to return to Italy and that his Government had agreed to accept the
                            proposal on the conditions that all of the Italians interned at
                                Missoula<note n="42" xml:id="d431fn42">Fort Missoula, Montana, Army
                                post and military reservation.</note> and those which were serving
                            jail sentences as a result of the prosecutions for sabotage on Italian
                            vessels be included.<note n="43" xml:id="d431fn43">See <ref target="#pg_451">pp. 451</ref> ff.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>I told the Ambassador that we had hoped that his Government would not
                            impose conditions; that it made it much more difficult to work out when
                            conditions were imposed; that it was my hope to exchange categories
                            irrespective of the numerical strength in each category; <pb facs="0440" n="428" xml:id="pg_428"/> and that I had not yet heard from the
                            German Government and would await a word from them.</p>
                        <p>I called the Ambassador’s attention to the fact that there were a great
                            many Italians and very few British and practically no Americans of
                            military age so that the conditions placed by his Government might not
                            be considered reasonable. I suggested that perhaps his Government would
                            recede from that extreme position and he said that he would, of course,
                            telegraph to his Government any proposal, even one which would be less
                            comprehensive than the maximum indicated by the Italian Government’s
                            response.</p>
                        <p>I told the Ambassador I would keep him advised of the developments.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>B[<hi rend="smallcaps">reckinridge</hi>] L[<hi rend="smallcaps">ong</hi>]</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>