<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-09-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-09-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="525" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d525">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">800.6354/295: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Winant</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-09-22">September 22,
                                        1941</date>.<lb/>[Received September 22—12:25
                                    p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>4439. Department’s 3855, September 17. Following are pertinent
                                extracts from communication received today from Colonial Office in
                                reply to Department’s inquiries: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“… you make three points. The first is ‘What articles if any
                                        are being considered for inclusion in the new agreement
                                        looking towards the protection of the interests of the
                                        consuming and importing countries?’ As you are no doubt
                                        aware, the 1937 Agreement contained the following article 6,
                                        headed ‘Consumers’ Representation’: ‘The Committee shall,
                                        within one month of the first meeting, invite a
                                        representative of tin consumers in each of the two largest
                                        tin consuming <pb facs="0537" n="525" xml:id="pg_525"/>
                                        countries to attend its meetings and to tender advice to the
                                        Committee regarding world stocks and consumption.’ This
                                        article is reproduced in the draft of the new agreement with
                                        the substitution for the words ‘each of the two largest tin
                                        consuming countries’ of the words ‘United States of America
                                        and a representative of other tin consumers.’ You will see,
                                        therefore, that so far as this matter is concerned there is
                                        no change in the situation.</p>
                                    <p>Your second point is that ‘Your Government feels confident
                                        that an adequate opportunity will be given for consultation
                                        in regard to any clauses formulated for safeguarding
                                        consumer interests before a final agreement is decided
                                        upon’. I am not clear what the words ‘for consultation’
                                        mean. In accordance with the instructions laid down in the
                                        1937 Agreement the Committee did invite tin consumers in the
                                        United States and in England to appoint representatives and
                                        in fact the present United States representative is Mr. Todd
                                        and the present United Kingdom representative is Mr. Lever.
                                        The latter is a fairly constant, though rather silent,
                                        attendant at the Committee’s proceedings and I think that it
                                        can fairly be said that if he had had any criticism to make
                                        of the present provisions on this subject he would have made
                                        them. For some reason, of which I am not aware, Mr. Todd has
                                        not thought fit to attend the Committee for a very long time
                                        past and I can only suppose that he too is quite content
                                        with the proposals.</p>
                                    <p>Your third point is ‘What arrangements, if any, are under
                                        consideration for the collection of reserves for buffer
                                        stocks to handle any shortage, emergency or unjustified
                                        price increases?’ It is not very easy to answer a question
                                        of this form without writing something like an essay on the
                                        subject. You are probably aware that two representatives of
                                        the International Tin Committee are in the United States
                                        negotiating with the Metals Reserve Corporation for a
                                        modification of the present arrangement by which that
                                        corporation are accumulating 75,000 tons of tin. The present
                                        proposal as I understand it, is that the quantity should be
                                        put up to 100,000 tons of tin, which must amount to well
                                        over 18 months’ supply of United States normal requirements.
                                        Part of the arrangement is that production shall be for
                                        practical purposes unrestricted until this stock is built
                                        up, and that, except for quantities required for immediate
                                        use by this country and our Allies and very small quantities
                                        for harmless neutrals, everything produced goes to the
                                        United States either for consumption or for addition to
                                        stocks. There can, therefore, be no question of building up
                                        a buffer stock of tin for the present; but the present
                                        buffer stock remains in the form of something over £2½
                                        million sterling in cash which is available to buy tin when
                                        the occasion arises; and, so far as the British Government
                                        at any rate are concerned, there is no proposal that the
                                        buffer stock agreement<note n="87" xml:id="d525fn87">Opened
                                            for signature at London, June 20, 1938, International
                                            Labour Office, <hi rend="italic">Intergovernmental
                                                Commodity Controls Agreements</hi> (Montreal, 1943),
                                            p. 90.</note> should be allowed to lapse if the
                                        International Tin Agreement is renewed. There is, however,
                                        one point which must be borne in mind, and that is that
                                        while the Agreement is an inter-governmental one, and is due
                                        to expire on 31st December 1941 unless it is renewed, the
                                        buffer stock tin which has now been converted into this
                                        money was put up not by the governments but by the producers
                                        themselves. It is their money and a difficult situation will
                                        arise if they say that while they have no objection to the
                                        buffer stock continuing <pb facs="0538" n="526" xml:id="pg_526"/> they want their own money back. I have
                                        an uncomfortable feeling that this letter may sound a little
                                        argumentative. Let me assure you that nothing of the sort is
                                        intended. It has quite genuinely caused a great deal of
                                        difficulty to the Tin Committee that the American
                                        representative has been so consistently absent, and it is,
                                        therefore, a little difficult to answer questions on
                                        subjects which it is really his business to watch and report
                                        upon to his constituents.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>