<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-06-25T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-06-25T11:00:00-05:00" n="56" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d56">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/12467:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Finland</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Schoenfeld</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Helsinki</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-06-25T18:00:00+02:00">June
                                        25, 1941—6 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received June 25—5:20 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>228. Ministry for Foreign Affairs informed me at 4:35 this afternoon
                                that up to 3 p.m. today some 16 Soviet aircraft had been shot down
                                in various parts of the country and one seaplane captured by a coast
                                guard vessel after a forced landing. Bombing had been widespread in
                                nearly all parts of the country with civilian casualties
                                considerable, Soviet forces having been used in some places
                                including groups of as many as 50 planes.</p>
                            <p>Minister said this seemed to be answer of Soviet Government to his
                                oral protest to Soviet Minister against incidents on June 22 and 23.
                                Finnish Chargé d’Affaires at Moscow had been informed by Soviet
                                Foreign Office yesterday that Finland’s “attack” on Soviet Union
                                would not be forgotten and would be avenged by 200,000,000 Russians
                                at some future date. The Minister did not tell me what the official
                                statement to be made by the Prime Minister in the Diet this evening
                                will contain but he greeted me with the words: “We are in the war
                                again.” He gave me to understand that the Swedish attitude
                                apparently remained one of aloofness.</p>
                            <p>I handed the Minister of Foreign Affairs a copy of Acting Secretary
                                Welles’ statement to the press on June 23,<note n="99" xml:id="d56fn99">For text, see telegram No. 836, June 23, to the
                                    Ambassador in the Soviet Union, <ref target="#pg_767">p.
                                        767</ref>.</note> which he took with him to a Cabinet
                                meeting immediately following our conversation but did not read
                                prior to my departure.</p>
                            <p>The Minister told me it was hoped air attacks on Helsinki would be
                                relatively ineffective by reason of greatly improved anti-aircraft
                                defense and that the Diplomatic Corps were not being advised to
                                leave. <pb facs="0055" n="43" xml:id="pg_43"/> He felt that present
                                trial would not be of long duration and gave me to understand that
                                the Germans had expressed themselves as very well satisfied with
                                their progress since hostilities began, claiming that they were
                                further advanced than they expected. Witting expressed thankfulness
                                that Finland did not this time stand alone, clearly implying
                                reliance upon German assistance. He intimated that according to
                                information available to him the Soviet authorities had already
                                issued instructions to attack Finland presumably by land as well as
                                by air.</p>
                            <p>I think Finnish Government feels that incidents which have thus far
                                taken place are clearly acts of war. In this relation the Minister
                                called my attention to the fact that Soviet aircraft have been shot
                                down in Finnish territory.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Schoenfeld</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>