<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d58</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">58</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-06-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-06-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="58"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d58">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/12920</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Secretary of
                        State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-06-28">June 28,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Minister of Finland called to see me this morning at his request. The
                    Minister left with me an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d58fn2">Not printed.</note> giving a detailed account <pb
                        facs="0056" n="44" xml:id="pg_44"/> of the hostile acts committed by Russia
                    within Finnish territory during the past few days.</p>
                <p>The Minister then read to me, by instruction of his Government, a statement of
                    the policy of the Finnish Government as already communicated by the Finnish
                    Minister in London<note n="3" xml:id="d58fn3">G. A. Gripenberg.</note> to the
                    British Government. The statement contained the following declaration: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Government of Finland desires to maintain unaltered its relations
                            with Great Britain. The Government of Finland is a co-belligerent with
                            Germany solely against Russia.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The Minister asked if I would make any statement as to the attitude of this
                    Government with regard to Finnish involvement in the war. I replied that I
                    should prefer to await developments for at least a few days before making any
                    such statement, but that the declaration as communicated to me by the Minister
                    would, of course, facilitate the determination which this Government would
                    reach.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >elles</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
