<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of State (
                    (Welles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d675</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">675</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-01-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmnRTtwUBtjR3ea" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-01-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="675"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d675">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">195.2/3822</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-01-21">January 21,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Soviet Ambassador called to see me today at his request.</p>
                <p>The question of the charter of tonnage for Soviet purchases was brought up in the
                    conversation. I stated that I had discussed this question fully with the
                    Maritime Commission and that the Commission had informed me that there had been
                    no change in policy whatever since I had given the Ambassador assurances on that
                    question some months ago. The present difficulties, I added, were due solely to
                    economic reasons relating to our own necessary defense. I said that the reason
                    why the Maritime Commission was not approving the charter of merchant steamships
                    to the Soviet Union for the transportation of products purchased in the United
                    States to Vladivostok was solely due to the fact that these vessels had to
                    return in ballast from Vladivostok since there appeared to be no cargo available
                    in Vladivostok for transportation to the United States. I further said that the
                    Maritime Commission had informed me that charters would be readily approved if
                    there were return cargo from Vladivostok, or from some other point in the Far
                    East where strategic materials could be obtained as cargo for the return
                    journey. The Ambassador said that he was glad to tell me that he had already
                    learned that this was <pb facs="0705" n="693" xml:id="pg_693"/> the fact and
                    that one vessel had now been chartered to the Soviet Union upon the
                    understanding that a return cargo would be found at some Indian port. He urged
                    that similar action be taken with regard to the steamship <hi rend="italic"
                        >Kentucky</hi>, which the Soviet Union desires to utilize in a voyage to
                    Vladivostok. I said that if the arrangements I had mentioned could be made, the
                    Maritime Commission I was certain would approve the charter.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador again brought up the desirability of excluding the port of
                    Murmansk from the combat area reaching around the northern tip of Norway. I said
                    that this question had been under consideration for some time and that I would
                    be glad to discuss the matter further with the Ambassador in the near
                    future.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >elles</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
