<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-08-21T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-08-21T08:00:00-05:00" n="71" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d71">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/14216:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Finland</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Schoenfeld</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Helsinki</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-08-21T15:00:00+02:00">August
                                        21, 1941—3 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received 10:25 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>376. My telegram 371, August 19.<note n="23" xml:id="d71fn23">Not
                                    printed.</note> I said to Minister for Foreign Affairs this
                                morning I had been disappointed by nature of Finnish press comment
                                which I felt would make bad impression in United States, on subject
                                of declaration issued after Roosevelt–Churchill meeting.<note n="24" xml:id="d71fn24">For correspondence on the Atlantic Conference
                                    meeting between President Roosevelt and Prime Minister
                                    Churchill, see <ref target="#pg_341">pp. 341</ref> ff.; for text
                                    of the Atlantic Charter, see <ref target="#pg_367">p.
                                    367</ref>.</note> I pointed out that comment overlooked fact
                                that declaration was consistent with established American policy of
                                non-recognition of territorial changes wrought by force. Minister
                                said he had not read Finnish press comment on declaration. Finland’s
                                position in present war remained unchanged; namely, that Finland was
                                seeking only security against threat of Bolshevik domination, and he
                                again mentioned numerous strategic railroads westward from Murmansk.
                                He said: I thought it was well understood in United States that
                                Finland was seeking safety against Russian domination as it had for
                                centuries whether Russian threat was in form of Czarism or
                                Bolshevism and that it seemed deplorable that Finnish press should
                                have deliberately ignored obvious purport of declaration while
                                accepting <pb facs="0071" n="59" xml:id="pg_59"/> without question
                                false German claim to be defending Europe against Bolshevism.</p>
                            <p>Minister repeated hope of Finnish Government to be able to withdraw
                                from participation in war upon achievement of its strategic aims,
                                but said that when this point was reached, presumably coinciding
                                with German occupation of Leningrad, it was expected that pending
                                general settlement Finland would have to maintain “armed peace” much
                                as it did between 1918 and 1921.</p>
                            <p>Witting, however, admitted uncertainty whether this program could be
                                carried out. There is apparently growing anxiety here lest Germans
                                prove unwilling to release Finland when Finnish war aims are
                                achieved. I did not gain impression that Germans have yet made new
                                demands for more extensive military or political cooperation.
                                Witting said that on economic side 75% of Finnish businessmen were
                                now convinced that Finnish economy would have to be adjusted to
                                German system for lack of foreign exchange and free capital. But he
                                expressed belief that Germans would make no attempt to force Nazi
                                social and political ideology upon Finnish people who he said had
                                five centuries of experience in free institutions and unlike German
                                people would not accept an essentially militarist system.</p>
                            <p>When during conversation I mentioned our full expectation that Nazi
                                regime would be destroyed, Minister expressed view that collapse of
                                German Government would open way for Bolshevism in heart of Europe.
                                I said we intended to forestall revolutionary disintegration of
                                Europe upon conclusion of war by preparations now being made to meet
                                urgent supply needs of European populations at that time.</p>
                            <p>I gained impression from today’s conversation with Witting that fear
                                of undue delay in concluding hostilities is also growing here and
                                that there is palpable desire to keep one foot in each opposing
                                camp.</p>
                            <p>Procopé appears to have reported to Witting that purposes in issuing
                                Roosevelt–Churchill declaration included checkmating any Hitler
                                peace move and possible Soviet-Nazi peace as well as serving warning
                                on Japan and assuring “Anglo-Saxon world domination” after war.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Schoenfeld</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>