<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Mr. Harry L. Hopkins, Personal Representative of President
                    Roosevelt</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d752</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">752</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-07-31T10:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-07-31T13:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recibBhfq1Nhuo5rk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="recuUFhBncrUg6V07" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015466"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bombers</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="reckO9szxNydLBID0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85003956"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Aluminum</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-07-31T13:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-07-31T10:30:00-05:00" n="752"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d752">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/15578</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Harry L. Hopkins, Personal Representative of
                        President Roosevelt</hi>
                    <note n="56" xml:id="d752fn56">Transmitted by President Roosevelt to Secretary
                        of State Hull, without date.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                        from="1941-07-31T18:30:00+03:00" to="1941-07-31T21:30:00+03:00">July 31,
                        1941, 6:30 p.m. to 9:30 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Conference Held on July</hi> 31, 1941, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >between Mr. Stalin, Mr. Hopkins, and the Interpreter Mr.
                        Litvinov</hi>,<note n="57" xml:id="d752fn57">Maxim Maximovich Litvinov,
                        formerly People’s Commissar for Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union, 1930 to
                        May 3, 1939.</note>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">at the Kremlin in Moscow</hi>—6:30 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >p.m. to</hi> 9:30 <hi rend="smallcaps">p.m.</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> I</p>
                <p>I told Mr. Stalin that the President was anxiotis to have
                    his—Stalin’s—appreciation and analysis of the war between Germany and Russia.
                    Mr. Stalin outlined the situation as follows:</p>
                <pb facs="0818" n="806" xml:id="pg_806"/>
                <p>He stated that in his opinion the German Army had 175 divisions on Russia’s
                    western front at the outbreak of the war, and that since the outbreak of the
                    war, this has been increased to 232 divisions; he believes that Germany can
                    mobilize 300 divisions.</p>
                <p>He stated that Russia had 180 divisions at the outbreak of the war, but many of
                    these were well back of the line of combat, and could not be quickly mobilized,
                    so that when the Germans struck it was impossible to offer adequate resistance.
                    The line which is now held is a far more propitious one than the more advanced
                    line which they might have taken Up had their divisions been prepared. Since war
                    began, however, divisions have been placed in their appropriate positions, and
                    at the present time he believes that Russia has a few more divisions than
                    Germany, and places the number of Russian divisions at 240 in the front, with 20
                    in reserve. Stalin said that about onethird of these divisions had not as yet
                    been under fire.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stalin stated that he can mobilize 350 divisions and will have that many
                    divisions under arms by the time the spring campaign begins in May 1942.</p>
                <p>He is anxious to have as many of his divisions as possible in contact with the
                    enemy, because then the troops learn that Germans can be killed and are not
                    supermen. This gives his divisions the same kind of confidence that a pilot gets
                    after his first combat in the air. Stalin said that “nothing in warfare can take
                    the place of actual combat”, and he wants to have as many seasoned troops as
                    possible for the great campaign which will come next Spring. He stated that the
                    German troops seemed to be tired, and the officers and men that they had
                    captured had indicated they are “sick of war”.</p>
                <p>The German reserves are as much as 400 kilometres back of the front, and the
                    communications between the reserves and the front line are extremely difficult.
                    These supply lines require many thousands of German troops to guard and protect
                    them from Russian raids.</p>
                <p>He said that in the battle now in progress, very many Russian and German troops
                    are fighting far forward from their respective lines because of the advances
                    made by both sides with their mechanized forces. Stalin said that his soldiers
                    did not consider the battle lost merely because the Germans at one point and
                    another broke through with their mechanized forces. The Russian mechanized
                    forces would attack at another point often moving many miles behind the German
                    line. Merely because German forces pierce the Russian line does not mean the
                    Russians are lost. They fight behind the Germans, are adept at the use of cover
                    and fight their way out in the night. He said, “Even the German tanks run out of
                    petrol.” This is merely a phase of modern warfare, and accounts for the fact
                    that there have been no mass surrenders of troops on either side. The Russians
                    therefore have <pb facs="0819" n="807" xml:id="pg_807"/> many “insurgent” troops
                    which operate behind Germany’s so-called front line. They constantly attack
                    German aerodromes and lines of communications. The Rusians are more familiar
                    with the terrain and know how to use the natural cover which nature has provided
                    better than the Germans. These “insurgent” troops are proving a great menace to
                    the German offensive.</p>
                <p>He believes that Germany underestimated the strength of the Russian Army, and
                    have not now enough troops on the whole front to carry on a successful offensive
                    war and at the same time guard their extended lines of communications. He
                    repeatedly emphasized the large number of men Germany was forced to use for this
                    purpose, and believes that the Germans will have to go on the defensive
                    themselves. There is considerable evidence that they are already doing this.
                    They are burying many of their large tanks in the ground for defensive purposes.
                    The Russians have already found 50 such defensive positions. Mr. Stalin stated
                    that in his opinion Hitler fears that he has too many men on the Russian front,
                    which may account for their preparing some defensive positions so that some of
                    their divisions might be returned to the German western areas of actual or
                    potential operation.</p>
                <p>He thinks the Germans have now on his front about 70 tank and motorized
                    divisions. He also states that the Russo-German war has already changed the
                    character of divisional organization; that the Germans had broken up their large
                    armoured divisions and dispersed this equipment through what Stalin called their
                    tank and motorized divisions. Stalin stated that the war has already shown that
                    infantry divisions must include a larger number of mechanized units. While
                    Russia had a large number of tank and motorized divisions—none of them were a
                    match for the German “Panzer” division, but were far stronger than other German
                    divisions. Hence the great pressure on the German infantry divisions which
                    caused the diversion of German armoured equipment all along the line.</p>
                <p>Stalin believes that Germany had 30,000 tanks at the outbreak of the Russian war.
                    Russia herself had 24,000 tanks and 60 tank divisions with about 350 to 400
                    tanks in each division. They have always had about 50 tanks in each infantry
                    division. Stalin believes that the large divisions are being broken up by the
                    German Staff and as the war progresses the number of men in the divisions will
                    be decreased in both armies.</p>
                <p>He stated that the pressure on his army in the last ten days had become
                    considerably less, and the only reason he could give for it was that he thought
                    Germany had been unable to supply their mechanized divisions and air forces with
                    adequate fuel. He stressed the great difficulty the German armies had
                    encountered in moving vast quantities <pb facs="0820" n="808" xml:id="pg_808"/>
                    of fuel to the front, and believes these difficulties are going to increase. He
                    does not think this is because Germany has any lack of fuel, but rather because
                    of transportation difficulties, the lack of good roads and more particularly the
                    effective interference of the Russians with the German communications.</p>
                <p>Stalin says that even though the war has been going on only six weeks, his troops
                    are meeting brand new divisions at the front, and some of the original divisions
                    seem to have been withdrawn. He believes that the morale of his own troops is
                    extremely high, and realizes that this is partly due to the fact that they are
                    fighting for their homes and in familiar territory. He said that Germany has
                    already found that “moving mechanized forces through Russia was very different
                    than moving them over the boulevards of Belgium and France”.</p>
                <p>Stalin said that the Russian Army had been confronted with a surprise attack; he
                    himself believed that Hitler would not strike but he took all precautions
                    possible to mobilize his army. Hitler made no demands on Russia, hence they were
                    forced to organize a defensive line of battle. Now the Russians were
                    counter-attacking at many points.</p>
                <p>He said the Russian Army had met few of the 70-ton German tanks but that this was
                    probably due to the inability of the Russian bridges to hold the tanks. He
                    believes the terrain too difficult to manoeuvre these giant tanks. Where the
                    70-ton tanks were encountered, they were pierced by the Russian 75 mm. guns. He
                    does not think that the very large German tank will play an important part in
                    the war in Russia, although there are parts of the southern front where these
                    tanks can manoeuvre. The roads are very bad for the big tanks to operate
                    over.</p>
                <p>He believes that his largest tanks are better than the other German tanks, and
                    that they have repeatedly shown their superiority in the war to date. He stated
                    that the two largest Russian tanks were of 48 and 52 tons respectively, with 75
                    mm. armour and 85 mm. guns. They have approximately 4,000 of these tanks at
                    present. The Russian medium tank of just over 30 tons has 45 mm. armour and 75
                    mm. guns. The infantry tank is 13 tons and has 37 mm. armour and 45 mm. guns.
                    They have approximately 8,000 medium (30-ton) tanks at present and 12,000 light
                    (13-ton) tanks. He stated their present production of tanks was 1,000 per month.
                    He stated that his production was equally divided between medium and heavy tanks
                    on the one hand, and light tanks on the other. He stated they would be short of
                    steel for tank manufacture and urged that orders for this steel be placed at
                    once. He later said it would be much better if his tanks could be manufactured
                    in the United States. He also wished to purchase as many of our tanks as
                    possible to be ready for the Spring campaign. <pb facs="0821" n="809"
                        xml:id="pg_809"/> Stalin said the all-important thing was the production of
                    tanks during the winter—the tank losses on both sides were very great but that
                    Germany could produce more tanks per month this winter than Russia. Hence the
                    aid of the United States in supplying steel and tanks is essential. He would
                    like to send a tank expert to the United States. He stated that he would give
                    the United States his tank designs.</p>
                <p>He emphasized the fact that Germany has a strong and powerful air force, and that
                    their present production of planes was probably 2,500 fighters and bombers per
                    month, but not more than 3,000 a month. Germany has more planes than the
                    Russians at the front at this time but the quality of many of the German planes
                    is not first-class—they are rough, plain machines, in which pilots fly without a
                    long training. Some pilots they have captured indicated that their training was
                    short and consisted of only a “practical course”. He realizes that Germany moved
                    to the Russian front a great many aircraft which types are no longer being built
                    in German factories. He thinks that Germany underrated the ability of the
                    Russian Air Force and thought that these second-rate planes could operate
                    successfully against them. The Russians have experienced no trouble in
                    destroying these planes. The Henkel plane was faster than the new Messerschmitt.
                    On the whole the most useful plane the Germans have against the Russians is the
                    Junkers 88, which is as good or better than anything of that type that the
                    Russians have.</p>
                <p>He stated that the Germans are putting 20 mm. cannon in their fighters; some have
                    12 mm. machine guns. Stalin said that all fighters must have cannon in modern
                    warfare. He has equipped all his fighters with cannon or heavy calibre machine
                    guns, and he stated the Russians proposed to have no fighters without cannon or
                    the heaviest calibre machine guns.</p>
                <p>The Russians put their old fighter planes on the front, and these have a speed of
                    only 440 kilometres per hour, but they have been very useful and successful
                    against many of the planes that the Germans put on Russia’s western front. They
                    have seven to eight thousand of these older type fighters.</p>
                <p>The new fighters are of three types. They have approximately 2,000 of these at
                    the front, and are producing 1,200 a month. The speediest of these newer
                    one-motor fighters is the M. I. G. 3, with heavy armour and cannon, and a speed
                    of 650 kilometres per hour. The second fighter is the L. A. G. 3, which carries
                    a cannon, has heavy machine guns and a speed of 590 k. p. h. The third is the J.
                    K. 1; this carries a cannon, and has a speed of 590 k. p. h.</p>
                <p>Stalin said the Russians have three new medium bomber types. First a single-motor
                    bomber, flying at 510 k. p. h., for close range <pb facs="0822" n="810"
                        xml:id="pg_810"/> bombing. Second, the 2-motor dive bomber, flying at 540 k.
                    p. h. with a flying range of 800 kilometres. The third bomber, which is only
                    just being produced in quantity, is a 2-motor dive bomber with a range of 2,200
                    kilometers and a speed of 610 k. p. h., and carries one ton of bombs on its full
                    flight range, but double that amount of bombs on more than half range. It has 7
                    heavy machine guns. Stalin spoke of it as “a very good bomber”.</p>
                <p>He said he has three types of long range bomber. One, a 2-motor bomber which is
                    quite slow, doing 440 k. p. h. with a range of 3,000 kilometres. Second, a
                    2-motor bomber, just in production, with a Diesel engine; range 5,000
                    kilometres, carrying one ton bomb load, 2 tons at 4,000 kilometres range; speed
                    500 k. p. h. Third, a 4-engine bomber, just now getting into production; range
                    3,500 kilometres, carrying 3 tons of bombs. He said they had at present about
                    600 heavy long range bombers.</p>
                <p>He said that his total production of planes at present was 1,800 per month; by
                    January 1st, this would increase to 2,500 per month. 60% of these would be
                    fighter planes, and 40% bombers. This was exclusive of training planes, now
                    being produced at 15 per day. The Russians have approximately 3,500 training
                    planes. Stalin said the training course for pilots was 8 months.</p>
                <p>He expressed considerable interest in training pilots in America and left me the
                    impression there would soon be a shortage of pilots. Stalin said the German
                    claims of Russian air losses were absurd. The Russians lost more planes than the
                    Germans at first, but he thinks the advantage is the other way now. He would not
                    indicate the number of losses other than there were a “good many on both
                    sides”.</p>
                <p>He stated there had been some damage to aircraft factories but that there had
                    been considerable dispersal of the machinery before the destruction took place.
                    (I saw two factories, which I was told by our Ambassador were aircraft
                    factories, just outside Moscow completely destroyed.)</p>
                <p>I asked Mr. Stalin about the location of his munitions plants. He did not reply
                    to this in detail but indicated that about 75% of the sum total of his munitions
                    plants, the percentage varying depending on the type of plant, were in the
                    general areas of which Leningrad, Moscow and Kiev were the centers.</p>
                <p>I gained the impression from him that if the German army could move some 150
                    miles east of each of these centers, they would destroy almost 75% of Russia’s
                    industrial capacity.</p>
                <p>Stalin said they had dispersed a good many of their larger factories and were
                    moving many machine tools eastward to escape the bombing attacks.</p>
                <p>Stalin repeatedly stated that he did not underrate the German Army. He stated
                    that their organization was of the very best and <pb facs="0823" n="811"
                        xml:id="pg_811"/> that he believed that they had large reserves of food,
                    men, supplies and fuel. He thinks that we may be underestimating Germany’s oil
                    supplies, and he bases this on the fact that under the two-year agreement they
                    had with Germany,<note n="58" xml:id="d752fn58">For illustrations of wartime
                        cooperation between Germany and the Soviet Union, including commercial
                        agreements, see <ref target="frus1940v01#pg_539">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1940, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 539</ref> ff.; and <hi rend="italic"
                            >ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_116">pp. 116</ref> ff.</note> the Germans
                    asked for less fuel than the agreement provided for during the year 1940–41. He
                    thought one weakness the British had was underrating their enemy; he did not
                    propose to do this. He, therefore, thinks that so far as men, supplies, food and
                    fuel are concerned, the German Army is capable of taking part in a winter
                    campaign in Russia. He thinks, however, that it would be difficult for the
                    Germans to operate offensively much after the first of September, when the heavy
                    rains will begin, and after October 1st the ground would be so bad that they
                    would have to go on the defensive. He expressed great confidence that the line
                    during the winter months would be in front of Moscow, Kiev and
                    Leningrad—probably not more than 100 kilometres away from where it is now. He
                    thinks that one of the great advantages the Russian Army has at the moment is
                    that the Germans “are tired” and have no stomach for an offensive. He realizes
                    that Germany can still bring up about 40 divisions, making 275 divisions in all
                    at the Russian front, but these divisions probably cannot get there before the
                    hard weather sets in.</p>
                <p>He told me that the first need of the Russian Army was light antiaircraft guns,
                    20 mm., 25 mm., 37 mm., and 50 mm., and that they need vast quantities of these
                    guns to give protection to their lines of communications against low flying
                    planes.</p>
                <p>His second great need was aluminum needed in the construction of airplanes.</p>
                <p>The third was machine guns of approximately 50 calibre, and the fourth rifles of
                    approximately 30 calibre. He stated that he needed large anti-aircraft guns for
                    the defense of cities. In his opinion the Russian supply of ammunition was
                    satisfactory. He stated the outcome of the war in Russia would largely depend on
                    the ability to enter the spring campaign with adequate equipment, particularly
                    in aircraft, tanks and anti-aircraft guns.</p>
                <p>He expressed an urgent desire that the British send large planes as soon as
                    possible to bomb the Rumanian oilfields, and made a point of urging that pilots
                    and crews be sent with the planes.</p>
                <p>He told me one of the great problems was to determine the ports of entry which
                    were to be used for supplies; and that Archangel was difficult but not
                    impossible; he was sure his icebreakers could keep the port free all winter. He
                    stated that Vladivostok was dangerous because it could be cut off by Japan at
                    any time, and he feared the <pb facs="0824" n="812" xml:id="pg_812"/> railroads
                    and roads in Persia were inadequate. But all would have to be used for the
                    present.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stalin expressed repeatedly his confidence that the Russian lines would hold
                    within 100 kilometres of their present position.</p>
                <p>No information given above was confirmed by any other source.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> II</p>
                <p>I told Mr. Stalin at this conference that our Government and the British
                    Government (Churchill having authorized me to say this) were willing to do
                    everything that they possibly could during the succeeding weeks to send matériel
                    to Russia. This matériel, however, must obviously be already manufactured and
                    that he—Stalin—must understand that even this matériel could in all probability
                    not reach his battle lines before the bad weather closes in.</p>
                <p>I told him that we believed that plans should be made for a long war; that so far
                    as the United States was concerned we had large supply commitments in relation
                    to our own Army, Navy and Merchant Marine, as well as very substantial
                    responsibilities for supplies to England, China and the Republics of South
                    America.</p>
                <p>I told him that the decisions relating to the long range supply problem could
                    only be resolved if our Government had complete knowledge, not only of the
                    military situation in Russia, but of type, number and quality of their military
                    weapons, as well as full knowledge of raw materials and factory capacity.</p>
                <p>I told him that I knew that our Government, and I believed the British
                    Government, would be unwilling to send any heavy munitions, such as tanks,
                    aircraft and anti-aircraft guns, to the Russian front unless and until a
                    conference had been held between our three Governments, at which the relative
                    strategic interests of each front, as well as the interests of our several
                    countries, was fully and jointly explored.</p>
                <p>I suggested that, in as much as he was so fully engaged with the immediate
                    prosecution of the battle now in hand, he could not give the time and attention
                    to such a conference until after this battle is over.</p>
                <p>Stalin had previously indicated that the front would be solidified not later than
                    October 1.</p>
                <p>I was mindful of the importance that no conference be held in Moscow until we
                    knew the outcome of the battle now in progress. I felt it very unwise to hold a
                    conference while this battle was in the balance. Hence my suggestion to him to
                    hold a conference at as late a date as was possible. Then we would know whether
                    or not there was to be a front and approximately the location of the front
                    during the coming winter months.</p>
                <p>Stalin said he would welcome such a conference and said that of course it would
                    be impossible for him to go to a conference anywhere <pb facs="0825" n="813"
                        xml:id="pg_813"/> other than in Moscow; that he would be glad to make
                    available to our Government all information which was required and he offered to
                    give us the Soviet designs of their airplanes, tanks and guns.</p>
                <p>I told him that I was not authorized to make this suggestion of a conference to
                    him officially.</p>
                <p>Stalin then stated that in case our Government wished to have such a conference
                    he would receive such a proposal sympathetically and would give the conference
                    his personal attention.</p>
                <p>Stalin has not given hitherto any information of any kind to any of the Embassies
                    or to any of the Military Attachés of foreign governments. The British Naval
                        Attaché<note n="59" xml:id="d752fn59">Capt. Henry Clanchy.</note> has been
                    given information confined to the Russian Navy because of certain joint
                    operations.</p>
                <p>There is literally no one in the whole Government who is willing to give any
                    important information other than Mr. Stalin himself. Therefore, it is essential
                    that such a conference be held with Mr. Stalin personally.</p>
                <p>I believe he would give this conference his personal attention.</p>
                <p>My suggestion is that the conference be not held prior to October 1, but not
                    later than October 15.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Harry</hi> L. <hi rend="smallcaps">Hopkins</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">For the President Only</hi>
                        <note n="60" xml:id="d752fn60">Photostatic copy obtained from the Franklin
                            D. Roosevelt Library, Hyde Park, N. Y. This part of the memorandum was
                            apparently not sent to Secretary of State Hull with the first two
                            parts.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> III</p>
                    <p>After Stalin had completed his review of the military situation, he expressed
                        to me his great thanks to the President for the interest he was showing in
                        their fight against Hitler. He stated that he wanted to give the President
                        the following personal message; that he had considered putting the message
                        in writing but believed it would be more desirable to have the message
                        delivered to the President by me.</p>
                    <p>Stalin said Hitler’s greatest weakness was found in the vast number of
                        oppressed people who hated Hitler and the immoral ways of his Government. He
                        believed these people and countless other millions in nations still
                        unconquered could receive the kind of encouragement and moral strength they
                        needed to resist Hitler from only one source, and that was the United
                        States. He stated that the world influence of the President and the
                        Government of the United States was enormous.</p>
                    <p>Contrariwise, he believed that the morale of the German army and the German
                        people, which he thinks is already pretty low, would be demoralized by an
                        announcement that the United States is going to join in the war against
                        Hitler.</p>
                    <pb facs="0826" n="814" xml:id="pg_814"/>
                    <p>Stalin said that he believed it was inevitable that we should finally come to
                        grips with Hitler on some battlefield. The might of Germany was so great
                        that, even though Russia might defend herself, it would be very difficult
                        for Britain and Russia combined to crush the German military machine. He
                        said that the one thing that could defeat Hitler, and perhaps without ever
                        firing a shot, would be the announcement that the United States was going to
                        war with Germany.</p>
                    <p>Stalin said that he believed, however, that the war would be bitter and
                        perhaps long; that if we did get in the war he believed the American people
                        would insist on their armies coming to grips with German soldiers; and he
                        wanted me to tell the President that he would welcome the American troops on
                        any part of the Russian front under the complete command of the American
                        Army.</p>
                    <p>I told Stalin that my mission related entirely to matters of supply and that
                        the matter of our joining in the war would be decided largely by Hitler
                        himself and his encroachment upon our fundamental interests. I told him that
                        I doubted that our Government, in event of war would want an American army
                        in Russia but that I would give his message to the President.</p>
                    <p>He repeatedly said that the President and the United States had more
                        influence with the common people of the world today than any other
                        force.</p>
                    <p>Finally, he asked me to tell the President that, while he was confident that
                        the Russian army could withstand the German army, the problem of supply by
                        next spring would be a serious one and that he needed our help.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
