<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d76</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">76</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-09-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-09-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="rec1ldfvh0EmC9PyC" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048697"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">High seas</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-09-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-09-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="76"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d76">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/14951: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-09-08">September 8,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Minister of Finland came in at my request. I said that, in the light of the
                    friendly relations that have always existed between this <pb facs="0074" n="62"
                        xml:id="pg_62"/> country and Finland and the extreme efforts this country
                    has always exerted to aid Finland when in trouble, or threatened with trouble, I
                    wished to express my gratification that Finland had regained possession of its
                    formerly held territory.</p>
                <p>I then said that I thought I had observed some reports to the effect that General
                    Mannerheim in a recent statement or address had indicated that Finland would
                    fight on until the end of the war between Germany and other countries, and that
                    naturally I felt justified in making inquiry regarding this in view of our
                    friendly relations and of our concern about the peace of the world, which is so
                    seriously threatened in a permanent way.</p>
                <p>The Minister proceeded to make general comment in a vague way about the fight of
                    the Finns to get back their territory, in the midst of which I inquired whether
                    and to what extent the Finns had advanced into Russian territory. The Minister
                    drew out his maps and showed that in one sector they had advanced quite a little
                    into Russian territory. In answer to a repeated question the Minister finally
                    expressed it as his personal opinion that the Finns were only occupying this
                    Russian territory for the purpose of safeguarding their own territory, and that
                    his Government did not intend to fight on through the war to its conclusion.</p>
                <p>The Minister made some reference to general conditions throughout the world and I
                    referred to Hitler’s plan of world conquest, both on land and sea. I said that
                    Hitler’s chief objective at present was to conquer Great Britain and get control
                    of the seas, which would be utterly disastrous to us and to all peaceful
                    nations. I referred to the tremendous efforts made by this country during the
                    early and middle 1930’s to preserve peace and to discourage war of any kind.
                    Despite all that we had done in this regard Berlin and Tokyo had deliberately
                    prepared for world-wide conquest. They had planned to use barbaric methods in
                    their dealing with all conquered peoples, and to set up a military despotism to
                    dominate the economic, political and other relations between Germany and
                    conquered or dominated countries. I proceeded further to say that the last thing
                    this country wanted was to get into trouble with any other country, but that
                    when it sees world peace increasingly undermined each day by Hitler operating
                    according to an avowed plan of conquest and destruction of everything
                    worthwhile, this country could not remain quiet from the standpoint of its own
                    self-defense.</p>
                <p>The Minister at this point interrupted and proceeded to advance a series of
                    relatively inconsequential and minor arguments against communism and Stalin, and
                    to indict Russia for many unjust acts against Finland during past years. Of an
                    emotional nature he could scarcely control himself while he excoriated Stalin,
                    and communism and their <pb facs="0075" n="63" xml:id="pg_63"/> injuries to
                    Finland. I finally interrupted him and said that we have a record of opposition
                    to communism with which we are pleased; that this record will always be
                    continued in the future; that Hitler instead of peacefully undertaking to
                    disseminate Hitlerism, which is very closely related to communism and Fascism,
                    proceeded for more than six years to assemble the greatest army and air force,
                    et cetera, that has ever been organized in history. He did not do this for the
                    purpose of defending himself, but for the avowed purpose of conquering peaceful
                    nations everywhere and securing control of the high seas, without geographical
                    limit. I emphasized that this danger from Hitler’s program and movements is real
                    and imminent, and that, of course, this country recognizes it and is proceeding
                    to act in self-defense against it. I stated that this country would not be
                    spending fifteen or twenty-five or forty billion dollars to resist Hitler in his
                    world march of conquest except to preserve the lives, the liberties and the free
                    institutions of our country and other peaceful countries, which are equally
                    destined, together with the conquered nations of Europe, to fall into the
                    clutches of Hitler. I then added that no desperado, individual or official, has
                    ever been known voluntarily to abandon his occupation, and that Hitler will not
                    stop until somebody stops him by force; that it is equally clear now to all
                    rational countries that when Hitler is stopped, and I firmly believe that he
                    will be stopped, some organized system involving the use of navies and aircraft,
                    et cetera, must be established to preserve the peace of the world against
                    uprisings or movements of conquest by international bandits and outlaws of the
                    one hundred percent stripe of Hitler. I went on to say that this long view is
                    the only view for peace-loving nations to adopt if the world is to offer
                    anything worthwhile to any country in the future; that this course of planning
                    to preserve the peace of the world following the present war is the only course
                    that will make life worthwhile in my country, in Finland and in all other
                    peacefully-inclined nations.</p>
                <p>I casually remarked at one appropriate point that if and when Hitler is stopped,
                    as I previously stated I firmly believe[d] he would be, this country may show a
                    far greater and more important interest in Finland than it has at any time in
                    the past.</p>
                <p>The Minister at one time inquired if we were going to war with Germany, to which
                    I replied that Hitler would like an answer to that question, and the Minister
                    said that that was true. I added that we have shown considerable interest in the
                    situation relating to resistance to Hitler, and if the Minister had any doubt
                    about that, Hitler would assure him, if he should so desire.</p>
                <p>The Minister showed absolutely no concern about anything except to reiterate his
                    hostility to Russia and after one of his excoriations <pb facs="0076" n="64"
                        xml:id="pg_64"/> of Russia he inquired what I would have Finland do. This
                    was after I had requested information as to her future course in the war, and
                    after I had made it clear that real and permanent peace could not be hoped for
                    except by stopping Hitler and establishing leadership and control by
                    peacefully-inclined nations such as the United States, Great Britain, Finland
                    and other countries. I replied to his question by stating that there was nothing
                    more in my mind than I had very definitely indicated.</p>
                <p>The Minister became very cordial near the end of the conversation, much of which
                    was repetition on his part and it was agreed that our countries were still
                    friends.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>C[<hi rend="smallcaps">ordell</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ull</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
