<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-10-04T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-10-04T16:00:00-05:00" n="84" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d84">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/15616a:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Minister in Finland</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Schoenfeld</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-10-04T16:00:00-05:00">October 4, 1941—4 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>201. Last week I asked Procopé to consult his Government with a view
                                to obtaining definite instructions on the basis of which he could
                                later inform me in detail with respect to the intention of his
                                Government to continue military operations against the Soviet Union
                                and the relation between Tanner’s statement of September 14 and the
                                action of his Government in continuing these military operations.
                                Pursuant to this request, the Minister called on me yesterday.<note n="47" xml:id="d84fn47">The following four paragraphs reproduce
                                    the memorandum of October 3 (not separately printed) which
                                    Secretary of State Hull wrote describing the conversation with
                                    the Finnish Minister on that day.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>I proceeded at once to say that it was unnecessary to go over the
                                pros and cons of the situation as the war relates to Finland and to
                                the United States, or to the likes and dislikes of either Government
                                with respect to Stalin and Hitler or their respective countries. I
                                said that as heretofore stated by me to the Minister, I am glad to
                                see Finland recover her lost territory. My Government, and country
                                and I have been loyal friends of Finland and would like very much to
                                see our fine relations continue, but even this consideration was
                                beside the governing question just now. That question, which is of
                                the greatest importance to my country without contemplating the
                                slightest injustice to Finland and her best interests relates to the
                                future safety of the United States and of all peaceful countries in
                                the world; that this Government profoundly convinced as it is, that
                                Hitler, practicing loathsome barbaric methods, is undertaking to
                                conquer the earth; that in these circumstances my country is
                                expending and is ready to expend 15 or 25 or 40 or 75 billions of
                                dollars to aid in resisting and suppressing Hitler and Hitlerism;
                                therefore, the one question uppermost in the mind of my Government
                                with respect to Finland is whether Finland is going to be content to
                                regain her lost territory and stop there, or whether she will
                                undertake to go further, if she has not already done so, so that the
                                logical effect of her course and action would be to project her on
                                the side of Hitler into the general war between Germany and Russia
                                and the other countries involved.</p>
                            <p>The Minister then undertook with maps to show that Finnish military
                                forces had only advanced certain distances beyond the outside limits
                                of their former borders; that the purpose in doing this was to
                                safeguard the legitimate territory and boundaries of Finland; and
                                that she has not participated in any attack on Leningrad. I replied
                                that without going into detail as to the location and numbers of
                                Finnish troops that have advanced into Russian territory, it is the
                                view of my Government that the Finnish troops have gone considerably
                                beyond the limits that would be legitimate for the mere protection
                                of the true <pb facs="0087" n="75" xml:id="pg_75"/> Finnish
                                boundaries and that, therefore, this action goes beyond the
                                reasonable interpretation and application of the Tanner statement of
                                some weeks ago. The Minister tried to make it appear that these
                                advances into Russia were necessary safeguards of Finnish territory.
                                I replied that this would signify exactly nothing at the peace table
                                and that it all depends on who wins the war. Having thus brushed
                                aside this contention, I said that if Finland persists in these
                                excesses then the Minister must understand clearly, and his
                                Government must understand definitely, that in the end this
                                Government is with Great Britain in every sense and that the
                                Minister must recognize instantly that there is no other course that
                                my Government could pursue except a suicidal one.</p>
                            <p>I further stated that before the British sent their recent statement
                                to Finland I had hoped that the Finnish Government on its own
                                initiative would announce that it did not plan to advance materially
                                beyond its own boundaries; that it had been fighting for the purpose
                                of regaining its lost territory and for no other purpose, and
                                especially that it had no purpose to get into the general war on the
                                side of Germany; and that the Finnish Government would not advance
                                beyond such legitimate distances. I said that unfortunately the
                                Finnish Government did not do this and instead it has been advancing
                                further and further into the interior of Russia, which is calculated
                                seriously to affect the situation of the Russians in the direction
                                of Murmansk and eastward and this amounted to material aid to
                                Germany. The Minister made no answer to this except to say that the
                                Germans would come in and occupy all of these areas or that the
                                Russians might come too near Finnish territory.</p>
                            <p>I left two propositions clear with the Minister, namely, that Finnish
                                troops have advanced entirely too far into Russia for compliance
                                with any legitimate plan merely to regain all lost Finnish
                                territory, and secondly, whether the Finns persisted in maintaining
                                this policy or extending it, his Government must understand that
                                this Government is with Great Britain.</p>
                            <p>You should be guided by the foregoing in your further conversations
                                with Finnish officials. You may also say to them that I am
                                considering making public this Government’s attitude toward Finland
                                as well as the details relating to the conversations which have been
                                going on between this Government and the Finnish Minister in our
                                desire to further a peaceful solution of Finnish-Soviet
                                    difficulties.<note n="48" xml:id="d84fn48">Most of the
                                    memorandum of August 18, by Under Secretary of State Welles of a
                                    conversation with the Finnish Minister (<hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_56">p. 56</ref>), and the
                                    “pertinent part” of the memorandum of October 3, by Secretary of
                                    State Hull of his conversation with the Finnish Minister (being
                                    the second paragraph of this telegram), were released to the
                                    press on November 7, and were published in the Department of
                                    State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, November 8, 1941, pp.
                                    362–363. See also telegram No. 226, November 3, to the Minister
                                    in Finland, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_88">p.
                                        88</ref>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <pb facs="0088" n="76" xml:id="pg_76"/>
                            <p>Please repeat to the Legation at Stockholm with my instructions to
                                apprise the Swedish Government for its information of this
                                Government’s attitude in regard to this matter.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>