<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-07-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-07-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="878" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d878">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.6131/621</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">C. Thayer
                                    White</persName> of the Division of Commercial Treaties and
                                Agreements to the Acting Chief of the Division of European
                                Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Atherton</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-07-03">July 3, 1941</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Atherton</hi>: Apparently it is considered
                            desirable on political grounds to provide for the extension beyond
                            August 5, 1941, of the commercial arrangement with the Soviet Union
                            despite the fact that under present conditions renewal of the
                            arrangement probably could not be justified on economic grounds.</p>
                        <p>The attached draft telegram<note n="83" xml:id="d878fn83">
                                <hi rend="italic">Infra.</hi>
                            </note> follows in general the suggestions contained in Eu’s<note n="84" xml:id="d878fn84">Division of European Affairs.</note> memorandum of
                            July 1.<note n="85" xml:id="d878fn85">Not printed.</note> It authorizes
                            our Embassy at Moscow, if approached by the Soviet Government, to
                            indicate that this Government would be agreeable to the renewal of the
                            1937 agreement,<note n="85a" xml:id="d878fn85a">For text of exchange of
                                notes signed August 4, 1937, see Department of State Executive
                                Agreement Series No. 105, or 50 Stat. 1619.</note> without the
                            related notes, for an indefinite period, i. e. subject to termination by
                            either party at any time on thirty days’ written notice. If political
                            considerations suggest that this Government should take the initiative,
                            the telegram can easily be changed to that end.</p>
                        <p>As indicated in the telegram, proclamation by the President of the
                            exchange of notes continuing in force the agreement of 1937, despite the
                            absence of the accompanying related notes, should continue to assure
                            exemption of Soviet coal from the import tax. Moreover, the inclusion of
                            a thirty-day termination provision should give the United States
                            adequate protection against the possibility that Soviet coal would be
                            imported at a rate substantially above the 400,000 tons for twelve
                            months specified in the present Soviet note limiting exports of coal to
                            the United States.<note n="86" xml:id="d878fn86">See telegrams No. 937,
                                July 31, 1940, and No. 978, August 6, 1940, from the Chargé in the
                                Soviet Union, <ref target="frus1940v03#pg_449">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1940, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 449</ref> and <ref target="frus1940v03#pg_456">456</ref>, respectively.</note>
                            Finally, it is believed that under existing circumstances a commitment
                            on the part of the Soviet Union to purchase in the course of a year
                            $40,000,000 or more of American goods would be meaningless, and that the
                            general commitment in the 1937 agreement by the Soviet Government to
                            increase substantially the amount of its purchases in the United States
                            should therefore not be made more specific by means of a related
                            note.</p>
                        <p>In the absence of a commitment to purchase a specified amount of American
                            goods in a twelve-month period, and the general character of the
                            commitment in the 1937 agreement, it is not anticipated that the Soviet
                            Government would desire a reservation to its promise to increase <pb facs="0934" n="922" xml:id="pg_922"/> its purchases in the United
                            States similar to the reservation included in the 1940 agreement.
                            However, if such a request should be made by the Soviet Government, a
                            safeguarding clause could be included.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>