<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in the Soviet Union ( (Thurston) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d973</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">973</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-11-27T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-11-27T03:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="prisoners-of-war"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners of war</term>
                    <term ref="recdlomV7plZIQUIj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136190"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Torture</term>
                    <term ref="recbWaHluS6u86H53" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038411"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diseases</term>
                    <term ref="recZPVvCSdB8G01JR" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recsJ9GxScV9mRtjF" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-assistance-and-sales" lcsh-match="no_match">Munitions</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-11-27T03:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-11-27T03:00:00-05:00" n="973"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d973">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00114 European War, 1939/1935: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Thurston</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Kuibyshev</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-11-27T12:00:00+04:00"
                            >November 27, 1941—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received December 4—3:48
                        a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1983. The Embassy has received a note<note n="61" xml:id="d973fn61">The Soviet
                        note was dated November 25, 1941.</note> from Molotov<note n="62"
                        xml:id="d973fn62">Vyacheslav Mikhailovich Molotov, People’s Commissar for
                        Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union.</note> (which also has been addressed
                    to all other diplomatic missions and published in the Soviet press) with respect
                    to the mistreatment of Soviet prisoners of war by the Germans.</p>
                <p>The note states that the Soviet Government is in possession of information
                    indicating that the German authorities are indulging in systematic cruel
                    treatment of Red army soldiers and officers, such as torture with hot irons; the
                    gouging out of eyes; the amputation of legs, arms, ears, noses, and fingers,
                    disemboweling; and quartering by tanks. It is alleged also that Soviet prisoners
                    are driven in front of attacking German columns; that sick and wounded Soviet
                    soldiers are refused medical attention and thus are doomed to death from typhus,
                    dysentery, and other diseases; that Soviet prisoners are being starved; and that
                    in violation of the Hague Convention of 1907, Red army prisoners are driven by
                    threats and beating to serve as wagon drivers, chauffeurs, and in other
                    capacities to carry munitions to the front and as porters carrying munitions to
                    firing positions. It is also <pb facs="1029" n="1017" xml:id="pg_1017"/> alleged
                    that the German Army, both officers and men, engage in wholesale pillage being
                    especially active in this respect in their search for warm clothing which leads
                    them to deprive wounded Russian soldiers of their clothing even to the extent of
                    removing warm clothing from wounded or dead women nurses.</p>
                <p>The note also alleges that the German authorities are endeavoring to bring about
                    the mass extermination of Soviet prisoners of war, in pursuance of which aim the
                    German Supreme Court command and the Ministry for Food and Agriculture have
                    issued a decree which provides that Soviet prisoners of war shall be given less
                    food than prisoners of other nationalities and that the food norms established
                    by this decree, namely 600 grams of bread and 400 grams of meat per person per
                    month, doom Soviet prisoners to a painful death from starvation. The note adds
                    that an inquiry on the subject by the Soviet Government through the Swedish
                    Government elicited the reply that information published in the foreign press
                    indicates that the facts are as alleged but that the text of the decree has not
                    been published and is therefore unobtainable.</p>
                <p>The note closes with the statement that “the Soviet Government indignantly
                    protests against the brutal treatment of captive Red army soldiers by the German
                    authorities who are violating the most elementary standards of human morality
                    and charges the criminal Hitlerite Government of Germany with full
                    responsibility for these inhuman acts of the German military and civil
                    authorities.”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Thurston</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
