<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>166. Memorandum From Robert H. Johnson of the National Security Council Staff
                    to the President’s Deputy Special Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of
                    the National Security Council Staff to the President’s Deputy Special Assistant
                    for National Security Affairs (Rostow))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d166</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">166</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-10-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-10-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="recAWJwqRIM3ZNS4f" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recHrSmzhfG78SwqX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HqULsC7KBoXeW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="receYZXmZSuptfeyg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">PL 480</term>
                    <term ref="recEmfen6T5wplQqD" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">Title II</term>
                    <term ref="recsJ9GxScV9mRtjF" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recqDYPNCT9Q6HQio" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85039557"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Drilling</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-10-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-10-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="166"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d166">
                <head>166. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_JR1" type="from">Robert H.
                        Johnson</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the President’s
                    Deputy Special Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName
                        corresp="#p_RWW1" type="to">Rostow</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d166fn1">Source: Kennedy Library, National Security Files, Viet-Nam
                        Country Series, 10/16/61-10/19/61. Top Secret. A copy was sent to
                        Bagley.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>. <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1961-10-14">October 14, 1961</date>
                        </hi>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Subjects for Exploration in Viet Nam</item>
                </list>
                <p>This memorandum contains a checklist of subjects that you may wish to explore
                    during your trip to Viet Nam. It does not pretend to be a comprehensive listing
                    of all of the questions that might be examined; I have eliminated many subjects
                    that will be on everyone’s minds and probably on everyone’s lists. In the
                    attachment to this memo, however, I have made a very brief listing of various
                    sorts of limited holding actions that have been considered at various times in
                    the course of work on <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss> Task Force papers.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">I. Military</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> Deployment</hi>. Is the <gloss
                            target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> really ninety percent committed to
                        counterinsurgency operations? At any given time, what percentage of the
                            <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> is engaged in patrolling
                        activities or offensive actions against the <gloss target="#t_VC1"
                            >VC</gloss>? (If you attempt to get figures which separate out <gloss
                            target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> casualties from those for the Civil Guard
                        and Self Defense Corps, you ought also to get a breakdown of <gloss
                            target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> casualties which indicates which were <gloss
                            target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss>-inflicted, which <gloss target="#t_CG1"
                            >CG</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss>-inflicted. The
                            <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> casualty figures alone, while
                        reflecting the fact that the <gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss> and <gloss
                            target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss> are more vulnerable and therefore more
                        often attacked, will not necessarily prove that the <gloss target="#t_ARVN1"
                            >ARVN</gloss> is passive.)</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Status of the Over-All Plan</hi>. While progress on
                        getting <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> approval of the over-all plan is
                        slow, the <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> Staff is said to have
                        approved over-all Corps-Area plans submitted by the corps commanders. Do
                        these fit together to provide an over-all scheme of action?</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Diem’s Attitudes Toward Military Planning and
                            Operations</hi>. Is it true, as I have heard alleged, that Diem is not
                        really interested in a major effort against the <gloss target="#t_VC1"
                            >VC</gloss> at this time; that he views this as a long-term problem
                        which can only be dealt with on a very long-term basis; that he therefore
                        prefers to concentrate on improvement of communications and to base his
                        military planning primarily on the gradual extension of <gloss
                            target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> control outward from Saigon?</item>
                    <pb facs="0391" n="369" xml:id="pg_369"/>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Identification of <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                            Concentrations</hi>. What can we do to identify with greater precision
                        the location of <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> units in areas such as
                            <gloss target="#t_ZoneD1">Zone D</gloss> where we know there are large
                        organized units? More photo recon? Send in small ranger units?</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Evaluation Center</hi>. Is full use being made of the
                        evaluations produced by the U.S. evaluation center in the embassy? Should
                        the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> be encouraged to develop its own war
                        room comparable to our evaluation center? What is the status of the <gloss
                            target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> Central Intelligence Organization? (We give
                        the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> information based upon our
                        evaluations, but do not give them access to the center, apparently because
                        some of our information is obtained from <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                        personnel through non-official channels.)</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">U.S. Advisory Personnel</hi>. Would it be desirable to get
                        U.S. advisory personnel down to platoon level and permit them to engage in
                        all military operations? (The Special Forces Officer whom I heard recommend
                        such action indicated that it would require 400 additional personnel.) In
                        order to increase the number of U.S. advisors in the field with combat
                        experience, should brevet rank be given to American <gloss target="#t_NCO1"
                            >NCO</gloss>’s?</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Special Forces Personnel</hi>. Could more U.S. Special
                        Forces Personnel be usefully employed? Is the supply of such personnel to
                        the field too erratic? (A Special Forces Officer indicated that at times he
                        was the only such officer in VietNam; this problem has allegedly since been
                        solved.)</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Self-Confidence and Offensive Spirit of the <gloss
                                target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss>
                        </hi>. Is there a real problem of increasing the self-confidence and
                        offensive spirit of the <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss>? If so, which
                        of the various R and D projects directed toward this problem show most
                        promise? (e.g., dogs, defoliation). <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>You recently expressed some skepticism on the subject of
                                defoliation. As I understood your argument, it was that defoliation
                                simply cleared the way for the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>.
                                But isn’t this a bit like the argument that one shouldn’t build
                                roads because they run in two directions? The question is not
                                whether defoliation may help the enemy as well as our side, it is
                                rather one of the net benefit. It seems to me that a guerrilla force
                                benefits more from forest cover than an anti-guerrilla force.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>The <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> proposes to use dogs on
                                static sentry duty; Godel’s concept was that they should be used
                                with patrols to help increase self-confidence by reducing prospects
                                for ambush. Isn’t use on patrols the better employment?</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Exotic Weapons</hi>. What is the current view of the R and
                        D test center of such items as the micro-jet, Tetrahedron and Lazy
                        Dog?</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Doctrine for Use of Helicopters and Helio-Couriers</hi>.
                        Does <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                            >GVN</gloss> have a clear military concept for use of helicopters and
                        Helio-Couriers? How many more could be usefully employed? (Maintenance of
                        helicopters has been a problem, but I believe that <pb facs="0392" n="370"
                            xml:id="pg_370"/> we are prepared to supply additional maintenance
                        personnel through Air America.)</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Radio Location Effort</hi>. In view of the continuous
                        increase in the number of <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> transmitters and
                        the inherent problems involved in location of them, does it make sense to
                        continue to devote resources and personnel to this effort? If it does, how
                        can the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> be made to take a more
                        cooperative attitude toward the effort?</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Deployment and Use of the 30,000 Man Increase</hi>. The
                        President’s approval of the 30,000 man increase in <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                            >GVN</gloss> armed forces (which will follow the 20,000 man increase now
                        going forward) was given with the understanding that there would be
                        agreement between the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> and the <gloss
                            target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> on the use to which these forces were put.
                        What are <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>’s plans? Do they make sense?
                        What is the status of <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> work on the
                        problem? Have we begun to think about whether a further increase beyond the
                        30,000 would be desirable, and about the use to which such forces might be
                        put? (You will recall that Diem asked for a total increase of
                        100,000.)</item>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Training and Use of the Civil Guard and Self Defense
                            Corps</hi>. Is training of the <gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss>
                        proceeding as rapidly as it could? Wouldn’t it be desirable to have the
                        training and equipping of the <gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss> and the
                            <gloss target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss> proceed simultaneously? (At present
                        the <gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss> is trained and equipped first and then
                        it trains the <gloss target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss>. The <gloss
                            target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss> has wholly inadequate weapons until it
                        completes its training.) Could more be done (perhaps with mobile training
                        teams) to train the <gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss> where they are
                        stationed rather than take them into special training camps? Do the concepts
                        for use of the <gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SDC1"
                            >SDC</gloss> developed by the <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> make
                        sense? (A training plan and concept of use was submitted by the <gloss
                            target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> to the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                            >GVN</gloss> in August and <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> comment
                        is awaited.) <gloss target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss> personnel are now often
                        deployed in a way that makes no military sense. Is the <gloss
                            target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss> deployed in areas with which the personnel
                        are generally familiar?</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">II. Economic</hi>
                </p>
                <p>(You will, of course, be exploring the current validity of the several programs
                    of emergency economic and social action contained in the Staley Report.<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d166fn2">See <ref target="#d93">Document 93</ref>.</note> I
                    have commented on those programs below on which I have some question.)</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Program Priorities</hi>. Are there U.S. projects now being
                        conducted in Viet Nam which interfere with the effort against the <gloss
                            target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> by absorbing the time of President Diem and
                        other top personnel and by diverting resources from essential military
                        tasks? On the other hand, to what extent are important economic programs
                        being cut back by the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> because of
                        concentration on the military threat or <pb facs="0393" n="371"
                            xml:id="pg_371"/> an unwillingness to mobilize necessary domestic
                        resources? (For example, it is said that agriculturists and nurses being
                        graduated from U.S.-supported schools are not being used on the grounds that
                            <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> resources must be concentrated on
                        the security problem. <gloss target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss> is presently
                        reviewing the Staley proposals and on-going programs with a view to
                        determining priorities. It is not easy for any <gloss target="#t_USOM1"
                            >USOM</gloss>, caught up in an existing program with every element of
                        the program supported by proponents within the <gloss target="#t_USOM1"
                            >USOM</gloss>, to re-orient its program. Outside advice could be most
                        useful.)</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Village Alarm System</hi>. What is the current status of
                        the village alarm system? I do not know the details on this, but I have the
                        impression that there may still be unresolved questions between <gloss
                            target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_MAAG1"
                            >MAAG</gloss> or the R and D center with respect to the kind of system
                        that should be installed. This is one of the most important economic
                        projects now going forward in VietNam.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Diem’s Road Program</hi>. Does Diem’s recently developed
                        road program make any sense? A member of the recently returned Army Civic
                        Action team indicated that it was grossly over-ambitious and that planning
                        and execution were not adequately related to real priorities. Can it be cut
                        down to essentials by agreement with the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                        on a first-stage program?</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Rural Dispensary System</hi>. Are there ways that the
                        existing rural dispensary system can be improved? For example, it has been
                        indicated that supplies of anti-biotics intended to meet some weeks of need
                        are exhausted within a couple of days of delivery while aspirin and other
                        less wanted items are in more than adequate supply. (Note that the Staley
                        Report’s recommendations on the rural medical program concentrated
                        exclusively on the care of the wounded. They thus reflected pre-occupation
                        with the security aspects of the medical problem. A much broader approach is
                        needed.)</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Rice Shortage</hi>. We shall be tackling the immediate
                        problem created by the flooding in the Delta area. But what is the over-all
                        rice situation? (Two months or so ago the embassy asked for some <gloss
                            target="#t_PL2">PL</gloss> 480 rice. Rice was offered, I believe under
                        Title II as a local currency sale. Partly because they were asked to pay for
                        it in piasters and partly because the situation seemed to ease, the <gloss
                            target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> turned down this proposal.)</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">III. Political-Social-Psychological</hi>
                </p>
                <p>(I have included in this category several items which are economic or military in
                    content or execution, but which have primarily social or psychological
                    purposes.)</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Attitudes of Troops and Local Officials</hi>. This is the
                    most important non-military element involved in obtaining the cooperation of the
                        <pb facs="0394" n="372" xml:id="pg_372"/> villagers. It is said that Diem
                    has disciplined and removed an increasing number of local officials guilty of
                    graft, excessive harshness and ineffectiveness. Is the progress significant or
                    only marginal? How can he be stimulated into further action?</p>
                <p>Troops are also said to treat the local populace very harshly. The Civic Action
                    Team is said to be recommending in its report that orders be issued to direct
                    that speed limits shall be enforced against military vehicles and to enforce
                    other criminal laws within the army. Will this be effective? Is the army’s
                    behavior in part related to low pay (e.g., as when a soldier pays an
                    exorbitantly low price for a chicken)? What can be done about the lack of
                    adequate provision for the dependents of armed forces personnel when they are
                    away from their homes? (Unlike the situation in most Asian countries, the
                    families do not live with the troops in the field and so do not benefit from the
                    soldier’s rice ration etc. I am not certain to what extent, if any, this problem
                    was created by the redeployments which we have insisted upon under the <gloss
                        target="#t_CIP1">CIP</gloss>.)</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Civic Action</hi>. The report of the U.S. Army Civic action
                        team<note n="3" xml:id="d166fn3">Not further identified.</note> will have
                    just been submitted to the <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>. You will want
                    to review it. One question that will need to be examined is whether adequate
                    provision is made for giving funds to the <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss>
                    for civic action purposes-to buy well-drilling equipment, simple brick-making
                    machines, etc. A small immediate amount was recommended and may have been
                    provided, but longer term needs will also require examination.</p>
                <p>There is an important limitation in existing <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss>
                    military directives on this subject. They apparently provide that civic action
                    may be conducted only to the extent that it does not interfere with military
                    operations. If strictly applied this rule could bar all civic action in <gloss
                        target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>. Obviously in a place like <gloss
                        target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> where programs of this kind could make a most
                    important contribution to the security effort, it is very short-sighted indeed
                    to view them simply as competitive with military operations.</p>
                <p>Would it facilitate <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> acceptance of civic
                    action if, instead of submitting our own report and waiting for months for the
                        <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> to react to it, we got together with
                    someone like General <persName corresp="#p_DVM1">Minh</persName> who has his own
                    program and, using that program as a base, worked our own ideas into it? This,
                    incidentally, is a technique that might be explored for more general
                    application. Our general approach has been to prepare a lengthy report on a
                    subject and submit to the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> for consideration.
                    That may be an excessively formal and not very effective way to get action on
                    military and non-military programs.</p>
                <pb facs="0395" n="373" xml:id="pg_373"/>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Montagnards</hi>. A U.S.-developed plan for assisting the
                        Montagnards<note n="4" xml:id="d166fn4">Not further identified.</note> has
                    recently been submitted to the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>. You may want
                    to examine it and determine what can be done to speed action.</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Agrarian Reform</hi>. The Washington Task Force received a
                    report some time ago that the agrarian reform program had about ground to a
                        halt.<note n="5" xml:id="d166fn5">Not further identified.</note> What, if
                    anything, in the way of U.S. assistance or otherwise can be done to revive
                    it?</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Radio and TV</hi>. I have attached copies of the memos
                        <persName corresp="#p_WD1">Donald Wilson</persName> left with us.<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d166fn6">Not found attached to the source text.</note> As I have
                    been given the picture, past delays on the radio program have been due partly to
                    arguments between ourselves and the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> over
                    objectives and partly to disagreements among the American technicians involved.
                    Disagreement over objectives has revolved primarily around Diem’s desire to have
                    sufficient power (100 <gloss target="#t_kw1">KW</gloss> or more) to reach into
                    North Viet-Nam and into other parts of Southeast Asia and our desire to
                    concentrate upon a system directed entirely toward the internal communications
                    problem. In August 1960 there was agreement with the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                        >GVN</gloss> on our concept.</p>
                <p>There are those who believe that much better cooperation could be obtained from
                    the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> if power were increased. (Diem has
                    indicated in the past that once we have the station built, he will himself
                    procure the equipment needed to increase the power.) The additional cost
                    involved is a relatively minor element. Greater power would require a higher
                    tower in Saigon which would have the additional advantage of providing the kind
                    of tower required if a TV program is undertaken. However, the Country team has
                    recently reviewed this power question and concluded that we should not reopen
                    it, but should proceed with the agreed program. You may want to determine what
                    continuing importance, if any, the power question has.</p>
                <p>Lack of progress since August 1960 is caused in part by lack of trained
                    personnel. We have never had more than two engineers in the field and have
                    relied upon inadequately qualified <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> personnel
                    to do much of the work. When the newly constructed radio tower in Hue fell to
                    the ground because of inadequate engineering the <gloss target="#t_USOM1"
                        >USOM</gloss> brought Chinese technicians from Hong Kong to supervise that
                    part of the undertaking. At present there is no radio engineer in the <gloss
                        target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_ICA1"
                    >ICA</gloss>/Washington is having great difficulty finding one. This is
                    primarily a Washington problem, but perhaps the <gloss target="#t_USOM1"
                        >USOM</gloss> could explore the possibility of bringing in Chinese or other
                    Asian engineers.</p>
                <pb facs="0396" n="374" xml:id="pg_374"/>
                <p>Non-project aid (commercial imports) are being used to provide some radio
                    receivers. This arrangement, however, provides very haphazard distribution. The
                        <gloss target="#t_ICA1">ICA</gloss> Desk officer has been working on a
                    proposal to procure receivers through project aid. This would permit the U.S. to
                    subsidize purchase by picking up the difference between the purchase price and a
                    lower selling price. It would also give us some control over distribution so
                    that they would get out to the villages instead of being concentrated wholly in
                    Saigon. This proposal has not yet been put to the field; you might want to
                    explore it. You might also want to explore the feasibility of Japanese aid in
                    this area.</p>
                <p>The principal problem foreseen on TV is the problem of servicing under conditions
                    where such skills are in very short supply and where security is very bad. A
                    plan developed by Togoland to deal with this problem has been, I believe, sent
                    to Saigon as a possible model. It is, I am told, a rather expensive and
                    elaborate program.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName>Robert H. Johnson</persName>
                        </hi>
                        <note n="7" xml:id="d166fn7">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">
                        <hi rend="strong">[Attachment]</hi>
                    </note>
                    <head>Memorandum Prepared by <persName corresp="#p_JR1">Robert H.
                            Johnson</persName> of the National Security Council Staff<note n="8"
                            xml:id="d166fn8">Top Secret.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <hi rend="italic">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                                    ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates"
                                    calendar="gregorian" when="1961-10-14">undated</date>
                            </hi>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Check List of Limited Holding Actions in Southeast Asia
                            From <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss> Task Force Papers</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Small Thai and <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> paramilitary units
                            in southern Laos.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Army engineer construction battalion to Thailand for training and work
                            on Bangkok by-pass.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Rotation of U.S. forces to Thailand for combined training, or
                            stationing of a brigade task force team there.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>U.S. aircraft and personnel for a defoliant spray program.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Expand naval capabilities by (a) expediting radios and motors for
                            junks; (b) use of U.S. ships and aircraft for interdiction; (c)
                            providing <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> more small boats under
                                <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Expedite encadrement of FAR.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>Resettle Meo to highland area of south Laos on Viet Nam border.</item>
                        <pb facs="0397" n="375" xml:id="pg_375"/>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>Expedite delivery of equipment to Thai border police.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>Help Thais establish Mekong River patrol.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>Strengthen suitable bases in southern Laos such as Savannekhet, Pakse,
                            Attopeu, and Saravane for operations by Thai, <gloss target="#t_VN1"
                                >VN</gloss> and Lao units. (Idea here, which has never been fully
                            developed in discussions, is to supplement paramilitary action referred
                            to in par. 1 above by creating strong bases in south Laos from which
                            probing actions could be mounted to keep enemy off balance.)</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
