<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>174. Telegram From the Embassy in Vietnam to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d174</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">174</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-10-17T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-10-17T23:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="recRywIrZWsI9yUJ7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2007010556"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Helicopter</term>
                    <term ref="recLVNRPFsjSN7TW4" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89004334"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contingency plan</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec636TkKuD4w6mkL" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97007802"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Flood</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-10-17T23:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-10-17T23:00:00-05:00" n="174"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d174">
                <head>174. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d174fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 120.1551K/10-1861. Secret; Priority. ReDeated to <gloss
                            target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> for PolAd, Bangkok. Vientiane. and
                        Phnom Penh.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1961-10-18T12:00:00+08:00">October 18, 1961, noon</date>.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>508. General <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CSJ1"
                        >Cottrell</persName> called on Diem together with local American officials
                    for initial discussion October 18. <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1"
                        >Taylor</persName> opened by explaining reasons for his mission, its
                    interest in all fields activity and its authority to make recommendations to
                    President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>, who will make
                    decisions.</p>
                <p>In response <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>’s request for
                    description situation in VietNam, Diem gave long historic account developments
                    here. Main point which emerged concerned lack sufficient number of <gloss
                        target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> troops. In addition insufficient armed forces
                    he stressed need for large number well equipped and trained Civil Guard and self
                    defense corps for protection of hamlets to prevent Viet Cong from feeding on
                    countryside. <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> asked whether
                    increase armed forces could not be stepped up. Diem and <persName
                        corresp="#p_NDT2">Thuan</persName> replied that shortage of cadres is main
                    bottleneck since additional officers and <gloss target="#t_NCO1">NCO</gloss>s
                    needed for all branches of security forces. Pointed to recent action doubling
                    officer trainee class at Thu Duc school.</p>
                <p>Since Diem’s description underlined need for large security forces for various
                    defensive purposes, <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> noted that
                    offensive warfare against guerrillas is less costly than defensive, and asked
                    whether greater offensive action, striking at Viet Cong bases and ambushing them
                    on infiltration trails could not be undertaken. Diem replied this being done in
                    part but many trails not known and Viet Cong find it easy to deviate past <gloss
                        target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> units on known trails.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> asked for Diem’s view on recent
                    step-up in Viet Cong campaign. Diem said that Viet Cong aim is to induce <gloss
                        target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> to withdraw troops from southern area (where
                    they have been more successful in recent months) to meet greater activity in
                    central VietNam, thus again giving Viet Cong opportunity for greater initiative
                    in southern area. Diem noted Viet Cong now often regroup into bigger units to
                    attack more important targets but added that Viet Cong are not yet trying to
                    engage in conventional warfare by holding on to places taken.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> said he understood there had been
                    recent discussions of introduction of American or <gloss target="#t_SEATO1"
                        >SEATO</gloss> forces into Viet-Nam and asked why change had occurred in
                    earlier <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> attitude. Diem succinctly replied
                    because of Laos situation. Noting it will take time to build up <gloss
                        target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> forces he pointed to enemy’s reinforcements
                    through infiltration <pb facs="0414" n="392" xml:id="pg_392"/> and increased
                    activities in central Viet-Nam and expressed belief that enemy is trying to
                    escalate proportionately to increase in <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                    forces so that CVN will not gain advantage. He asked specifically for tactical
                    aviation, helicopter companies, coastal patrol forces and logistic support
                    (ground transport).</p>
                <p>Diem indicated he thought there would be no particular adverse psychological
                    effect internally from introducing American forces since in his view Vietnamese
                    people regard Communist attack on Viet-Nam as international problem. <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName> inquired whether internal and external
                    political aspects such move could be helped if it were shown clearly to world
                    that this is international problem. Diem gave no direct comment on this
                    suggestion. He indicated two main aspects of this problem: (1) Vietnamese people
                    are worried about absence formal commitment by US to VietNam. They fear that if
                    situation deteriorates Viet-Nam might be abandoned by US. If troops are
                    introduced without a formal commitment they can be withdrawn at any time and
                    thus formal commitment is even more important in psychological sense. (2)
                    Contingency plan should be prepared re use American forces in Viet-Nam at any
                    time this may become necessary. In this connection Diem seemed to be talking
                    about combat forces. While it was not completely clear what Diem has in mind at
                    present time he seemed to be saying that he wants bilateral defense treaty and
                    preparation of plans for use American forces (whatever is appropriate) but under
                    questioning he did not repeat his earlier idea relayed to me by <persName
                        corresp="#p_NDT2">Thuan</persName> that he wanted combat forces.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> several times stressed importance
                    of overall plan-military, political, economic, psychological, etc.-for dealing
                    with guerrillas. Diem tended avoid clear response this suggestion but finally
                    indicated that he has new strategic plan of his own. Since it was not very clear
                    in spite efforts to draw him out what this plan is, <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1"
                        >Taylor</persName> asked him to let us have a copy in writing.</p>
                <p>I asked Diem about significance state of emergency decree just issued (our
                        504<note n="2" xml:id="d174fn2">Not printed. (Ibid.,
                    751K.00/10-1861)</note>). He said he took this action under conditions of
                    Constitution and has sent it to National Assembly for approval in 30 days as
                    required by Constitution. If Assembly approves establishment of state of
                    emergency he said that executive decrees could then be issued. I asked whether
                    this measure was taken because of security or flood conditions. He said both but
                    it was evident that security considerations were uppermost since he referred to
                    his mention of this proposed action in his October 2 National Assembly
                    speech.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NFE1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Nolting</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
