<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>269. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Special Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (Rostow) to the President) to the President</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d269</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">269</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-11-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-11-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="rec636TkKuD4w6mkL" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97007802"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Flood</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HqULsC7KBoXeW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recDNr3fFoY74D9ro" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="rectadvRz4QZmc1z7" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="chemical-and-bacteriological-warfare" subject="chemical-weapons" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007509" lcsh-match="exact">Chemical warfare</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-11-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-11-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="269"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d269">
                <head>269. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Special Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName>) to the
                        President<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d269fn1">Source: Kennedy Library,
                        National Security Files, Viet-Nam Country Series, Memos and Reports. Secret.
                        Initialed by <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1961-11-21">November 21, 1961</date>.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>VietNam Status Report</item>
                </list>
                <p>There is attached the first status report on recent decisions with respect to
                        VietNam.<note n="2" xml:id="d269fn2">Dated November 20, not printed.</note>
                    This memorandum is designed to supplement that status report by providing
                    additional clarifying information, covering subjects not covered in the report
                    and bringing it up to date where additional information has been received.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Military Situation</hi>. There has been continuing
                    deterioration, but no major change, in the military situation. The crisis
                    described in the Taylor Mission Report has not been reversed. There has been a
                    recent step-up of Viet Cong activity in the Delta and <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                        >GVN</gloss> analysis suggests that the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                    plans to broaden the area of <gloss target="#t_ZoneD1">Zone D</gloss> north of
                    Saigon. Though the Government has taken some military initiatives, its military
                    operations have produced no significant results. There is one bit of evidence
                    indicating that the Cambodians may have tightened their border somewhat and that
                    the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> are raiding Cambodian border villages in
                    retaliation.</p>
                <p>Casualty rates remain at the higher level inaugurated in September, when the
                        <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> stepped up their offensive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Flood Situation</hi>. Each new report on the flood
                    emphasizes the fact that its effects will not be so severe as had been feared
                    initially. However, estimates of rice requirements which have fluctuated up and
                    down have now been firmly estimated at the relatively high figure of 220,000
                    tons. Action to deal with this problem is reported in the status report.
                    Meanwhile, Diem has established his own flood <pb facs="0670" n="648"
                        xml:id="pg_648"/> relief and reconstruction organization under an official
                    who is well regarded by the American Embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">U.S. Economic Aid</hi>. AID in mid-October approved a level of
                    $140 million for non-project aid (commercial imports) for <gloss target="#t_FY1"
                        >FY</gloss> 1962. Because of the floods and General <persName
                        corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>’s visit, this figure was never given to
                    the Vietnamese. The Ambassador on November 16 requested that this level be
                    increased to $160 million on the basis of new requirements created by the flood,
                    particularly the need for rice.<note n="3" xml:id="d269fn3">
                        <gloss target="#t_Toaid1">Toaid</gloss> 69 from Saigon, November 16, not
                        found.</note> Today he has sent a new message to the personal attention of
                        <persName corresp="#p_HF1">Fowler Hamilton</persName>
                    <note n="4" xml:id="d269fn4">Telegram 680 from Saigon, November 20. (Department
                        of State, Central Files, 751K.00/11-2061)</note> requesting expedited action
                    on this request on the grounds that it would be of great help in his current
                    negotiations with Diem and is crucial to Vietnamese action to carry out exchange
                    reform and other measures which were agreed in connection with the Staley
                    Report. The request is receiving urgent consideration in State and AID.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Civil Guard and Self Defense Corps</hi>. The item on this
                    subject at the bottom of page 2 of the status report actually deals only with
                    the Civil Guard. We have not yet reached agreement with the Vietnamese
                    Government on a plan for the training of the Self Defense Corps. The Government
                    rejected a <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> proposal that members of the
                    Corps be trained in the Civil Guard training centers on the grounds that such
                    action would leave a security vacuum in the provinces. The <gloss
                        target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> proposed instead to bring 3 to 5 thousand
                    Nationalist Chinese military to Viet-Nam to provide “on-the-spot” training.<note
                        n="5" xml:id="d269fn5">On November 17, the Department of State’s Executive
                        Secretariat transmitted to <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge
                            Bundy</persName> a memorandum of the same date drafted by Warren A.
                        Silver of the Viet-Nam Task Force regarding Vietnamese requests for Chinese
                        Nationalist assistance as well as tables prepared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_SW1">Silver</persName> on U.S. economic and military
                        assistance to South Viet-Nam during the period October 18-November 17, 1961.
                        In a brief covering memorandum, Deputy Executive Secretary Melvin L. Manfull
                        told <persName>Bundy</persName> that the attached memorandum and tables
                        contained “the information you requested last night by phone for the
                        President’s use.” (Ibid., 751K.00/11-1761)</note> We are planning to make a
                    counter-proposal for training of the Corps at thirty provincial training
                    centers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Geneva Accords</hi>. As anticipated, we are already having
                    some difficulties dealing with questions from newsmen and others on the
                    relationship between our actions and the Geneva Accords. The problem has been
                    contained for the moment, but can be expected to become more difficult as
                    additional large items of military equipment are delivered.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">New Management of the Surete</hi>. The Embassy is seizing upon
                    the opportunities provided by change in leadership of the Surete. It is planning
                    to propose development of a “National Communist Party <pb facs="0671" n="649"
                        xml:id="pg_649"/> Penetration Service” … down to the provincial level and an
                    improved police program with the support of the <gloss target="#t_USOM1"
                        >USOM</gloss>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Organizational Questions</hi>. General <persName
                        corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> has been consulting with General
                        <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName> on the question of
                    organization of U.S. military activities in VietNam. The question of Washington
                    organization for implementation of the action program is under consideration
                    between State and Defense in consultation with General <persName
                        corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Weed Killer</hi>. You will be receiving papers from Defense
                    and State soon raising the question of whether we should support the use of a
                    weed killer to attack crops in the plateau area on which the <gloss
                        target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> feed and to clear jungle paths, notably for an
                    attack on <gloss target="#t_ZoneD1">Zone D</gloss>. Your decision is required
                    because this is a kind of chemical warfare.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
