<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>280. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    Vietnam</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d280</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">280</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-11-25T19:10:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-11-25T19:10:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-11-25T19:10:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-11-25T19:10:00-05:00" n="280"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d280">
                <head>280. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d280fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 751K.00/11-2561. Secret; Niact. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_WCB1">Wood</persName>; cleared with <persName
                            corresp="#p_CSJ1">Cottrell</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MCWP1"
                            >McConaughy</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">U. Alexis
                            Johnson</persName>, and the Office of the Secretary; initialed by
                        Pezzullo of the Executive Secretariat for the Secretary. Repeated to <gloss
                            target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> for PolAd.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1961-11-25T19:10:00-05:00">November 25, 1961, 7:10 p.m.</date>
                        </hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>684. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TVC1">Chuong</persName> called on Secretary
                    22nd and again 25th<note n="2" xml:id="d280fn2">Memoranda of these two
                        conversations are ibid., Secretary’s Memoranda of Conversation: Lot 65 D
                        330, November 1961.</note> in order clear up certain points raised by
                        <persName corresp="#p_TVC1">Chuong</persName>, who spoke under
                    instructions.</p>
                <p>Following principal points emerged from <persName corresp="#p_TVC1"
                        >Chuong</persName>’s somewhat opaque presentation:</p>
                <p>US should not rely on neutrals, particularly <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>
                    and RLG. Greatest threat to free world is in <gloss target="#t_SEA1"
                    >SEA</gloss>, not Berlin. Last year Communists waged war without danger to
                    themselves to take over Laos. This year it is VietNam. American military
                    assistance is best direct counter to Communists. It should not be spread too
                    thin; should be used not only as foreign aid, but as arm in a war.</p>
                <p>Secretary replied we not satisfied with attitude neutrals, but noted we have
                    explained situation to Indians and others. They increasingly concerned. <gloss
                        target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> may be helpful through <gloss target="#t_ICC1"
                        >ICC</gloss> and by its diplomatic efforts, but we should not expect too
                    much. Our total per <pb facs="0692" n="670" xml:id="pg_670"/> capita aid to
                    India for 12-year period has been $2.00. Our total per capita aid to Viet-Nam
                    for six years has been $100.</p>
                <p>Secretary agreed on dangers in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss> and emphasized
                    necessity joint effort. He asked repeatedly, “How do we win the battle?”
                    Ambassador did not reply directly, but several times in his presentation made
                    point US should be tougher with friends and foes alike.</p>
                <p>Secretary asked to what extent Thoi Bao editorial represented public expression
                    of <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>’s real attitude; said it appeared to be
                    most unhelpful prelude to Diem-<persName corresp="#p_NFE1">Nolting</persName>
                    talks. Emphasized US had no desire “run” <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>.
                    Our only aim to help <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> with its own war.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_TVC1">Chuong</persName> said <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                        >GVN</gloss> concerned lest impression be gained there was to be
                    “condominium” in VietNam, but, speaking personally, did not believe editorial
                    represented <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> opinion.</p>
                <p>Secretary said editorial (picked up in Washington Post today) could create
                    serious public opinion problem in US. Emphasized that in Greece and Korea when
                    the question was that of winning battle, problem of sovereignty did not
                    arise.</p>
                <p>Ambassador asked if US had suggested specific steps which might have caused
                    editorial and mentioned Diem sensitive on question bringing exiled political
                    elements into <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>. Secretary replied that we had
                    simply asked for <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> views on how it could get
                    broader support; perhaps there were elements in VietNam, now on sidelines, who
                    might throw themselves behind <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> in its
                    struggle.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_NFE1"
                        >Nolting</persName> may cite Secretary’s remarks as needed in conversations
                    with <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1"
                        >FYI</gloss>.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
