<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>295. Central Intelligence Agency Information Report</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d295</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">295</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-11-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-11-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="reccab053b473a4a56" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-i" subject="world-war-i" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148236" lcsh-match="exact">Councils</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-11-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-11-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="295"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d295">
                <head>295. Central Intelligence Agency Information Report<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d295fn1">Source: <gloss target="#t_USAMHI1">USAMHI</gloss>, Kraemer
                        Papers, <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> 61 63. Confidential,
                        Noforn/Continued Control.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1961-11-29">November 29, 1961</date>.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>… Subject: Views of President <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Ngo Dinh
                        Diem</persName>.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>On 27 November 1961, President <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Ngo Dinh
                            Diem</persName> said that the mission of General <persName
                            corresp="#p_TGMD1">Maxwell D. Taylor</persName> to South Viet-Nam was
                        somewhat similar to the mission of General Marshall to China. In the latter
                        case, General Marshall insisted that Chiang Kai-shek divide his power with
                        the Liberal Party, which had no authority and represented nothing but a few
                        intellectuals. The American position after the Taylor Mission was completed
                        bears similarities, as it apparently wishes to impose some sort of
                        liberalization or change upon the Government of Viet-Nam (<gloss
                            target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>) which is not suited to the present
                        situation or the Government’s structure. Diem said that he had been trying
                        for a long time to build the infra-structure of a democratic system in South
                        Viet-Nam but that he was faced with two major obstacles, the war being waged
                        by the Vietnamese Communists, and the difficulty of finding loyal and
                        efficient cadres for the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>President Diem stated that he was conscious of the demand that “emergency”
                        action be taken and this he had tried to accomplish. When discussing the
                        specifics of “emergency” actions with such political figures as Pham Huy
                        Quat, leader of the Front for National Unity, however, the President found
                        nothing but vague and irrelevant ideas about giving greater freedom
                        propounded. He found that such figures as Dr. <persName>Quat</persName>
                        actively refused to accept the real “emergency” actions necessary, such as
                        immediate and severe punishment of treason and cowardice in the face of the
                        enemy. He planned in the next few days to establish provincial councils, but
                        these would not be elected in the beginning but would be appointed from
                        non-party people in the area. A similar technique was used in forming the
                        National Economic Council which was nominated by various interest groups. It
                        was delayed by the difficulties of finding labor representatives who were
                        anything but Communist. Meanwhile oppositionists such as Pham Huy Quat were
                        currying favor with potential foreign sponsors instead of helping the
                        country to fight during this period.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Another drawback to the <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>
                        Report recommendations was the experience of the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                            >GVN</gloss> with the Staley Report, which was delivered with great
                        fanfare and indicated that all sorts of additional assistance would be
                        forthcoming. The promised increase in American <pb facs="0715" n="693"
                            xml:id="pg_693"/> support had not materialized to date. Diem stated that
                        he had taken steps to devaluate the recommendations.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The Vietnamese newspapers were commenting on the conditions stated in the
                            <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> Report, according to
                        Diem, and the press revealed the depth of the antagonism of thinking
                        Vietnamese to any conditions which they believed limited <gloss
                            target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> sovereignty. Diem knew that his advisers
                        and cabinet members would feel so strongly on this subject that he had not
                        exposed the specifics of the <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>
                        recommendations to more than one or two individuals. (Field comment.
                        Assistant Secretary of National Defense and Secretary of State at the
                        Presidency <persName corresp="#p_NDT2">Nguyen Dinh Thuan</persName> stated
                        on 27 November that President Diem’s attitude was appropriately described as
                        “frustrated” by the convergence of problems upon him, including what he
                        deemed the unreality of the <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>
                        conditions; the extreme difficulty in locating appropriate individuals to
                        whom power could be delegated and who would accept it; the pressures of the
                        war; and, the fact that he had carefully consulted his Cabinet, National
                        Assembly members, and other advisers on the desirability of receiving
                        American troops, and now faced a difficult problem in re-orienting
                        them.)</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>President Diem also expressed considerable fury and bafflement at how to
                        handle American press representatives. He realized the importance of the
                        American press influence, but insisted that it should assume responsibility
                        commensurate with its power, and should also realize that the backdrop to
                        the Vietnamese scene being reported is the Vietnamese Communist attack. He
                        complained that if he did not give an interview to a foreign newsman, the
                        latter criticized him for ignoring foreign newsmen, but that if he did give
                        the interview, the reporter used almost nothing told to him and criticized
                        the length of the interview. …</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>President Diem said that he intended to go ahead with extra financial
                        expenditures and has instructed <persName corresp="#p_NDT2">Thuan</persName>
                        to find the necessary 600 million plasters, of which 40 million would be for
                        Self Defense Corps equipment, 60 million would be to pay village notables,
                        etc.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
