<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-12-05T16:19:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-12-05T16:19:00-05:00" n="310" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d310">
                        <head>310. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d310fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 751K.00/11-1261. Secret; Niact. Drafted by Chapman (TF/VN) on
                                November 28; redrafted by <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">U. Alexis
                                    Johnson</persName> on December 4; cleared with <persName corresp="#p_CSJ1">Cottrell</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SCF1">Salans</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CRG1">Cleveland</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_ADV1">Anderson</persName>, and Cross (all <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>), <persName corresp="#p_MCWP1">McConaughy</persName>, <persName>Cleveland</persName> (<gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>), and the Secretary. Repeated to ten
                                posts.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-12-05T16:19:00-05:00">December 5, 1961, 4:19 p.m.</date></hi></dateline></opener>
                        <p>729. Re Embtels 684 and 720.<note n="2" xml:id="d310fn2">Telegram 684 is
                                printed as <ref target="#d268">Document 268</ref>. Telegram 720 is
                                not printed.</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Concur that our present policy re Geneva Accords increasingly
                                difficult to implement and should be further developed. Concur
                                specifically that arrival USS Core with two helicopter companies
                                will bring matter to a head. (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 720)</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>We fear that using rotation argument as you suggest will again
                                involve us in numbers game which frustrating, time-consuming and
                                fruitless in present context. It will stretch accords to point where
                                credibility of our legal theory and our good faith in advancing it
                                may be cast into serious doubt. It would impress no one and would
                                not redound to our credit, to suddenly raise “ceiling” from 888 to
                                3500 seven years after signing of Geneva Accords.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Instead, we consider <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> and we
                                have a good, legally sound position which we can take publicly in
                                response to questions and which would provide us with a firm
                                political base for whatever actions we would later judge necessary
                                including taking issue to <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. This
                                position would be presented in first instance by <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> to <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> along following lines: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p><gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> is committing acts of
                                        aggression in flagrant violation of Geneva Accords, and
                                            <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> has consequently
                                        requested US for additional support in men and materiel.
                                        These measures are being taken as requirements of legitimate
                                        self-defense necessitated by North Vietnamese breaches of
                                        Accords. As soon as North Vietnamese end their aggressive
                                        acts and resume their observance of Geneva Accords, these
                                        measures of support can be terminated, <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> is asking <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> increase its frontier
                                        patrols.</p>
                                </quote></item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>We would then state in response to queries that “US has acceded to
                                    <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>’s request for expanded aid
                                in men and materiel and is determined to help <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> preserve its independence. This is
                                sole objective of US. US will terminate these measures as soon as
                                    <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> ends its acts of
                                aggression.”</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_NFE1">Nolting</persName>
                                authorized take up this matter with <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> and seek persuade it to clarify its position with
                                    <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> along these lines.</item>
                            <pb facs="0741" n="719" xml:id="pg_719"/>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Department will discuss with British, Canadians and Indians upon
                                receipt word <persName corresp="#p_NFE1">Nolting</persName><gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> concurs this course action.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RD1"><hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>