<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-12-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-12-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="338" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d338">
                        <head>338. Telegram From the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                                (<persName corresp="#p_LGLL1" type="from">Lemnitzer</persName>) to
                            the Chief of the Military Assistance Advisory Group in Viet-Nam
                                (<persName corresp="#p_MGLGLC1" type="to">McGarr</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d338fn1">Source: National Defense
                                University, Lemnitzer Papers, L-21071. Top Secret; Priority. No
                                transmission time is given on the source text.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-12-23">December 23,
                                        1961.</date></hi></dateline></opener>
                        <p>[<gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 2027-61.] 1. The question of
                            proposed reorganization and ultimate command arrangements which you
                            raise in your Eyes Only message (<gloss target="#t_SGN1">SGN</gloss>
                                901)<note n="2" xml:id="d338fn2"><ref target="#d331">Document
                                    331</ref></note> and your letter of 18 December<note n="3" xml:id="d338fn3">Not found.</note> is one of <pb facs="0781" n="759" xml:id="pg_759"/> utmost importance and one to which I have been
                            devoting much personal attention here.</p>
                        <p>2. I had planned to have a few moments with you alone after the 16
                            December meeting to discuss the question with you, but as you know, our
                            party left almost immediately for take-off and there was no possibility
                            for such a get-together.</p>
                        <p>3. Although the subject was listed in our agenda for the 16 December
                            meeting, it was passed over without discussion because the Secretary of
                            Defense and the Secretary of State had already initiated joint
                            consideration of the problem here in Washington and had agreed that they
                            personally (and not their staffs) would work out a final recommendation
                            for submission to the President. Therefore, as you noted at the meeting,
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> simply
                            skipped the item when we came to it on the agenda. Near the end of the
                            meeting Amb Nolting handed me a note to pass to Secy <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> in which he said he would
                            like to discuss the subject personally with Sec Def after the meeting.
                            Sec Def agreed although it was his intention not to discuss it with
                            anyone at Honolulu. From what Sec Def told me I gather that they did in
                            fact have a brief discussion on the subject of proposed organizational
                            changes. I understand that Amb Nolting asked Sec <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> what his and other thinking
                            in Washington was in this regard and Sec Def gave him his general views.
                            From information available to me they did not have a meeting of minds on
                            the subject. (Note: Foregoing is for your eyes only and should not be
                            revealed to any other person.)</p>
                        <p>4. I would like to give some flavor of my personal thinking and of <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> views on this sensitive question. We
                            have been completely satisfied with the manner in which you have
                            discharged your duties out there and we have consistently made this
                            point in interdepartmental discussions here. With the decision not to
                            introduce combat troops into Viet-Nam we have had serious doubts about
                            the desirability of a fundamental change in the U.S. organization there.
                            In view of information we had regarding thinking at higher levels in
                            U.S. Govt, the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> response to a request
                            for recommendations for a new U.S. command structure in Viet-Nam is
                            qualified by the words “if it is decided to change the command structure
                            in Vietnam.” Nevertheless although final decision has not yet been made
                            by the President it now appears that a change in U.S. organization will
                            be made. The primary object of the change is to impress Diem that we are
                            entering a new era in U.S.-Vietnamese relationships in which the U.S.
                            will be giving him increased support and be expecting him to pay
                            increased heed to our advice and suggestions. Generally speaking, the
                            new terms of reference will provide for a U.S. military assistance
                            command, rather than an advisory group, and will insure that the senior
                            U.S. military representative in Viet-Nam has the <pb facs="0782" n="760" xml:id="pg_760"/> controlling voice, both on the U.S. side and with
                            Viet-Nam officials, on military matters. Another factor which is
                            involved is the possibility of broadening whatever organization is
                            decided for Viet-Nam into a U.S. military organization for all of SE
                            Asia, and possibly ultimately expanding into a <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> command if the situation continues to deteriorate in
                            Laos, Vietnam, Cambodia and Thailand.</p>
                        <p>5. Also, for the purpose of increasing the impact on Diem that the U.S.
                            looks to a new and increased counter-insurgency effort on his part, it
                            now appears that a four-star U.S. commander will be named to operate
                            under the new terms of reference and that you and your <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> will come under his over-all command.
                            I fully appreciate what your feelings may be if this proposal is
                            implemented. That is why I want personally to emphasize to you that the
                                <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> and I have complete confidence
                            in you and have been thoroughly satisfied with the results you have
                            achieved in the face of great handicaps, obstacles and frustrations.
                            From my conversations with Adm Felt I am convinced he feels the same
                            way. We recognize the burden of personal adjustment necessary to fit
                            into the new command structure, if and when it is created, but are
                            certain that you will take this in your stride, as you have so many
                            other difficulties during your fifteen months in Saigon. I know you’ll
                            appreciate that the new man will have to lean heavily on you and will
                            need every bit of help he can get from you.</p>
                        <p>6. I will keep you further informed as developments take place here. All
                            of this, I know, adds up to something less than a Christmas present for
                            you, but you are too good a soldier to let it bother you for long.
                            Therefore I’ll close with a personal expression of the Season’s
                            Greetings for you and the members of your command and the hope that the
                            New Year in Viet-Nam will see the results of some of the training and
                            planning you have so patiently and thoroughly accomplished during 1960
                            [1961].</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>