<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>97. Letter From Secretary of State for the Presidency Thuan to the Deputy
                    Director of the Viet-Nam Task Force ( to the Deputy Director of the Viet-Nam
                    Task Force (Wood))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d97</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">97</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-07-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recLVtmipNOLIF0A1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85122588"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Silver</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HqULsC7KBoXeW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rec7wEECiiCfq0TDz" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85123713"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Smuggling</term>
                    <term ref="recVanxJ0yM3HzUcM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037333"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Devaluation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-07-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="97"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d97">
                <head>97. Letter From Secretary of State for the Presidency <persName
                        corresp="#p_NDT1" type="from">Thuan</persName> to the Deputy Director of the
                    Viet-Nam Task Force (<persName corresp="#p_WCB1" type="to">Wood</persName>)<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d97fn1">Source: Washington National Records
                        Center, RG 84, Saigon Embassy Files ERC 66 <gloss target="#t_A1">A</gloss>
                        878, TF <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> 1961. Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1961-07-18">July 18, 1961</date>.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Ben</hi>: Since I returned from Washington to my paper
                    mill, quite a few things happened. So I want to write you a few words.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The financing problem for 20.000 additional men is solved as you know. May
                        I have to say how much do I appreciate your help?</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>The Staley group has completed their report. They took a few trips to get
                            a more precise idea of the Vietnamese context. On the spot they did
                            realize the difficulties and they did see that we are working and
                            fighting hard. Three major things have to be implemented right away:
                            increasing the force level, building up a wireless system for all
                            villages, and expanding as much as we can the agrovilles network. I get
                            the impression that the Ambassador agrees with me. He took quite a few
                            trips with President Diem and myself. He gets convinced now, I think,
                            that we must have more troops to occupy different areas, to protect
                            population and we have too to regroup them. If you don’t occupy
                            villages, the Commies get in and the population can’t resist.</p>
                        <p>The village level is the basis. Silver will report to you longer about
                            the trip we took yesterday in Kien Hoa Province. That’s a successful
                            test. The necessity is to act rapidly to create an impact right away.
                            Better to increase noticeably the Armed Forces now to get rid of
                            subversion in one or two years and to increase them afterwards than to
                            take half measures. So, if Cottrell and yourself can get the force level
                            of 200.000 approved for 1962 and the corresponding level of
                            commercialised (sic) aid, i.e., 170 millions US$, that would help a
                            lot.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>You know the victory our troops got over the Commies in the Plaine des
                        Joncs. The Communist unit knocked out is their best one. Objectively that’s
                        quite a hit. They lost 187 men and 10 prisoners. Weapons captured: 76. As
                        far as I remember, nothing like that happened before to the Commies in South
                        VietNam, even during Indochinese war. I ask Silver to bring back to the
                        Vietnamese Task Force a cane we got from the Commander of <gloss
                            target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> unit, namely Battalion 502. I would like that
                        you will show it to President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1"
                        >Kennedy</persName>. I have been in the front right away after the hit with
                        newsmen. I did see the arms captured, the bodies all over in rice fields. We
                        still have plenty of guts so don’t worry about (us).</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Our main difficulty: the rice situation. Many causes to that: <pb
                            facs="0253" n="231" xml:id="pg_231"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Estimate made by Department of Agriculture too different from
                                estimate made by provincial authorities about the rice production
                                this year. The latter is less optimistic.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Smuggling through Cambodian border. They play on the “change”
                                (exchange). Because of insecurity the black market rate of exchange
                                is like that: 1.6 <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> piaster for 1
                                riel. So people prefer to send rice to Cambodia to be exported and
                                to change afterwards the riels they get into <gloss target="#t_VN1"
                                    >VN</gloss> piasters at the “faux noir.”</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>Communists prevent population to sell their rice.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>Rumors about devaluation. Peasants prefer to keep rice than to get
                                piasters.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>I know that you are very busy Ben. I am too. So I stop here.</p>
                <p>My best to Cottrell the “dragon”. Mes homages a Madame et mes amities a votre
                    jeune fils de 14 ans.<note n="2" xml:id="d97fn2">On August 19, <persName
                            corresp="#p_WCB1">Wood</persName> sent a letter to <persName
                            corresp="#p_NFE1">Nolting</persName> enclosing a reply dated August 18
                        to <persName corresp="#p_NDT2">Thuan</persName>, and asked <persName
                            corresp="#p_NFE1">Nolting</persName> to transmit the reply to <persName
                            corresp="#p_NDT2">Thuan</persName>. In his letter <persName
                            corresp="#p_WCB1">Wood</persName> congratulated <persName
                            corresp="#p_NDT2">Thuan</persName> on recent military victories by the
                        Government of Vietnam, which he said “have been very encouraging to persons
                        in our Government at every level.” He also wrote that the questions raised
                        by <persName corresp="#p_NDT2">Thuan</persName> were ones that he worked on
                        every day and that while some had been answered, “the others keep us so busy
                        that I have postponed any plans of visiting Viet-Nam until early 1962.” In a
                        letter of August 28, <persName corresp="#p_NFE1">Nolting</persName> informed
                            <persName corresp="#p_WCB1">Wood</persName> that he had sent <persName
                            corresp="#p_WCB1">Wood</persName>’s letter to <persName
                            corresp="#p_NDT2">Thuan</persName> that day. All these letters are
                        ibid.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Truly yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NDT2">
                            <hi rend="strong">Nguyen dinh Thuan</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="3" xml:id="d97fn3">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
