<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-04-26T00:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-04-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="111" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d111">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">756D.94/28: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Bullitt</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-04-26T14:00:00+09:00">April 26,
                                1939—2 p.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received April 26—7:46 a.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>202. Our 190, April 20, 8 p.m.<note n="27" xml:id="d111fn27">Not
                            printed.</note>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The Secretary of the Netherlands Legation informs us that according to
                            the Netherlands Consul at Shanghai now visiting in Japan the Netherlands
                            Consul General at Shanghai received information from what he considered
                            to be a reliable source to the effect that the Japanese Fleet had
                            received orders to proceed “in the event of war in Europe” to the
                            Netherlands East Indies under the guise of carrying out routine
                            maneuvers following which certain demands would be presented to the
                            Netherlands East Indies Government; but that the orders did not
                            contemplate the immediate occupation of Netherlands territory.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>This statement differs in one important respect from the report
                            brought to the Department by the Netherlands Minister,<note n="27" xml:id="d111fn28">Not printed.</note> namely, the contingency of war
                            in Europe.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Without knowing the source of the Netherlands Consul General’s
                            information, we are not in a position to weigh the accuracy of such
                            information. However, in view of the secrecy which surrounds the
                            movements of Japanese naval vessels, we are inclined to believe that his
                            information is probably in the nature of a shrewd forecast of
                            developments in the contingency of a European war.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>