<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Adviser on Political Relations (
                    (Hornbeck))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d242</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">242</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-09-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-09-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-09-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-09-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="242"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d242">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.0146/723</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Adviser on Political
                        Relations</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-09-27">September 27,
                            1939</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The French Ambassador called this afternoon and began the conversation with an
                    inquiry: he supposed that I had seen the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                    which he had given the Secretary of State<note n="57" xml:id="d242fn57">Dated
                        September 20, <ref target="#pg_258">p. 258</ref>.</note> on the subject of
                    the armed forces in China; was I in position to tell him what was our reaction.
                    He said that he understood that the British Embassy had given us an <hi
                        rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                    <note n="58" xml:id="d242fn58">Dated September 19, <ref target="#pg_257">p.
                            257</ref>.</note> similar to that given by his Embassy.</p>
                <p>I replied that I had seen both <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>, that this
                    Government’s reply was ready, and that I was authorized to hand him an <hi
                        rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                    <note n="59" xml:id="d242fn59">
                        <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note> in reply to his <hi rend="italic"
                        >aide-mémoire</hi>.</p>
                <p>While the Ambassador was reading our <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>, I
                    pointed out that the substance of our reply was that this Government does not
                    expect to withdraw its forces from the points in China at which they are now
                    stationed. I said that this statement of our position was in terms of
                    expectation, that it represents a position taken in the light of existing
                    circumstances, and that it does not constitute a commitment but will be subject
                    to review from time to time as the situation develops. The Ambassador ejaculated
                    that he well understood that we could not and would not make a commitment; he
                    said that he had told his Government just that and that he had advised against
                    their asking us to do anything of that sort. He indicated that he regarded the
                    contents of our <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> as an adequate and
                    satisfactory reply. In fact, he seemed greatly pleased with our statement that
                    we do not expect to withdraw our forces from the points where they <pb
                        facs="0271" n="267" xml:id="pg_267"/> now are. He said that his Government
                    does not want to make withdrawals, but that the British Government inclines
                    toward withdrawal, and that both the French and the British Governments are
                    presented with difficult problems. I commented only to the effect that we well
                    realize that such is the case, and I added the observation that practically all
                    governments and peoples are today confronted with problems of extraordinary
                    difficulty.</p>
                <p>There followed a brief discussion of summer holidays and the present tense
                    situation in Europe.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stanley K. Hornbeck</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
