<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of Far Eastern
                    Affairs ( (Hamilton))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d273</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">273</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-10-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-10-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-10-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-10-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="273"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d273">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.0146/752</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of
                        Far Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hamilton</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-10-30">October 30,
                            1939</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Mallet, Counselor of the British Embassy, called at his request this
                    afternoon and left with me the attached <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                    bearing date October 30.<note n="98" xml:id="d273fn98">
                        <hi rend="italic">Infra.</hi>
                    </note> Mr. Mallet said that he hoped that the decision of the British
                    Government, as recorded in the attached <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>,
                    would be satisfactory to us. Mr. Mallet said that he understood that the
                    decision was in line with comments made by the Secretary and by Mr. Hornbeck in
                    conversations with the British Ambassador. I said that I could make no comment
                    in addition to the comment which had previously been made by the Secretary and
                    by Mr. Hornbeck. I added, however, that it was my recollection that the British
                    Ambassador had in his conversation with the Secretary made inquiry as to what
                    the Secretary thought of the British leaving a few guards at Peiping and at
                    Tientsin as a symbol, and that the Secretary had replied that this would in his
                    opinion operate to mitigate to some extent but not to avert loss of
                    prestige.</p>
                <p>I told Mr. Mallet that I would without delay bring the British Embassy’s <hi
                        rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> to the attention of the Secretary.</p>
                <p>Mr. Mallet commented that he understood that what the British were doing was
                    along the lines of action taken by this Government a number of months ago. I
                    then recounted to Mr. Mallet the action taken by this Government in withdrawing
                    its infantry forces from Tientsin and in replacing those infantry forces with
                    part of the marine guard forces on duty at Peiping.</p>
                <p>I assured Mr. Mallet again that I would bring the British Embassy’s communication
                    to the attention of the Secretary.</p>
                <p>Mr. Mallet said that the British Government desired that its decision in the
                    matter be regarded as strictly confidential.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>M[<hi rend="smallcaps">axwell</hi>] M. H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >amilton</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
