<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-09-13T00:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-09-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="447" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d447">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">393.115 Tung or Wood Oil/249:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-09-13T13:00:00+08:00">September
                                    13, 1939—1 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 1:50 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>816. Following is text of letter dated yesterday received this morning
                            from the Japanese Consul General at Shanghai: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of
                                    August 9th concerning the shipment of American owned wood oil
                                    which is now at Hankow.</p>
                                <p>This question, as I informed you at our conversation on the
                                    matter on the above date, had long been a matter of special and
                                    careful consideration by the Japanese authorities concerned.
                                    They have studied the possibility of allowing the American owned
                                    wood oil to be shipped down the Yangtze River without coming in
                                    contradiction with the present state of the navigation on the
                                    river.</p>
                                <p>Your letter above referred to was brought at once to the
                                    attention of my Government, and I now have the honor to state
                                    that I have been instructed to inform you that they have taken
                                    the matter up again and have come to the decision that the bulk
                                    of wood oil, as was ascertained as American owned in your letter
                                    dated September 6th, is to be given facilities to be shipped
                                    from Hankow.</p>
                                <p>I believe you will readily appreciate the difficulties placed in
                                    the way of this decision owing to the present restrictions for
                                    military necessities on the river navigation. Accordingly,
                                    several devices had to be worked out, viz: the wood oil in
                                    question is to be first purchased by the Japanese military
                                    authorities as a sort of military supply, to be <pb facs="0461" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/> repurchased by the American firms,
                                    the owners, upon clearance of the Yangtze River, for which
                                    purpose the transport had to be selected from among those
                                    vessels which have the accommodation for vegetable oils, which,
                                    on its down river voyage, is scheduled to cease to be the
                                    transport at the moment when the oil is repurchased by the
                                    American firms, to be shipped direct to the American coast.</p>
                                <p>Instructions have already been given to a Japanese shipping
                                    company along the above mentioned practical arrangement, who, on
                                    their part, will soon be ready to discuss the matter into [in?]
                                    detail with the American firms.</p>
                                <p>You would also appreciate that one of the suggestions put in your
                                    letter of August 14th contributed much towards this satisfactory
                                    decision, together with questions of favorable capacity
                                    available as military transport.</p>
                                <p>There are some more minor points to be adjusted in this
                                    arrangement before the wood oil is to be actually shipped at
                                    Hankow, probably at the end of this month, which may be left
                                    with the companies concerned. I am writing to you in order to
                                    inform you as soon as possible of the principle of our decision
                                    so far reached. Therefore, this communication might be
                                    supplemented later when deemed necessary.</p>
                                <p>I might add that the above decision is the outcome of what had
                                    long been considered by the Japanese authorities concerned and
                                    that, but for the unexpected abrogation of the commercial treaty
                                    of 1911, it would have been reached sooner and with less
                                    difficulty.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>While the foregoing communication refers only to the American-owned oil
                            we have subsequently been informed orally that it may be considered as
                            extended also to cover the oil under contract of sale. We are also
                            [informed] that the Japanese shipping company concerned is the Nippon
                            Yusen Kaisha and that the arrangements are to be made at Shanghai with
                            possible reference of any details to Hankow.</p>
                        <p>I am very much concerned regarding the “device” of purchase of the cargo
                            by the Japanese military and repurchase by the American owners. This
                            matter has been taken up informally with the Japanese Consulate General
                            who tell us that this was a point insisted upon by the Japanese
                            military. I have pointed out that even though it may be said that the
                            transfer of ownership is merely nominal, and aside from the fact that a
                            principle is involved, there is the practical consideration that a
                            transfer of title to the Japanese military would affect the ability of
                            the owners of the oil to obtain adequate insurance and there is also
                            involved the question of responsibility for any losses which might be
                            incurred during the transit of the oil from Hankow to Shanghai. I shall
                            report developments as soon as possible.</p>
                        <p>Repeated to Tokyo, Chungking and Peiping.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Gauss</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>