<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of State (
                    (Welles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d490</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">490</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-02-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-02-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="490"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d490">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/15197</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-02-03">February 3,
                            1939</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The British Chargé d’Affaires called to see me this morning. Mr. Mallet was
                    instructed by his Government to discuss with me the question of the possible
                    taking of retaliatory measures against Japan dealt with in Mr. Mallet’s <hi
                        rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of January 25. Mr. Mallet was instructed to
                    give me to read the telegram sent the British Foreign Office by Sir Robert
                    Craigie, the British Ambassador in Tokyo, in which the latter differed in some
                    of the considerations advanced to the United States Government by the British
                    Foreign Office. Upon reading the telegram which Mr. Mallet gave me I told him
                    that the contents of this telegram had already been communicated to the
                    Department by Ambassador Grew<note n="65" xml:id="d490fn65">See telegram No. 53,
                        January 31, 3 p.m., <hi rend="italic">supra.</hi>
                    </note> and that we were consequently familiar with the views expressed. Mr.
                    Mallet replied that his Foreign Office knew that Sir Robert Craigie had showed
                    this telegram to Mr. Grew but they had not been certain whether Mr. Grew had
                    reported the contents thereof fully to the Department.</p>
                <p>I told Mr. Mallet that he might inform his Government that very full
                    consideration had been given to this question by the Secretary of State himself
                    and that this Government had reached the conclusion that for the time being its
                    point of view was more or less that expressed by the British Government in its
                        <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of January 25.</p>
                <p>I said that this Government would not consider for the time being undertaking
                    retaliatory measures against Japan. I stated that if as the time passed we
                    desired to consider the matter further, we would inform the British Government
                    accordingly and discuss further with them some of the issues involved.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >elles</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
