<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-04-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-04-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="505" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d505">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/14951</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                                State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-04-15">April 15, 1939</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Chinese Ambassador<note n="92" xml:id="d505fn92">Hu Shin.</note>
                            called to see me this morning and handed me the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> attached to this memorandum.<note n="93" xml:id="d505fn93">
                                <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> The Ambassador said that he had
                            received the first part of this <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> from
                            his Government some days ago and that in order to assure himself that
                            the text and translation were similar to that used by his colleague in
                            London, he had cabled the latter and the latter part of the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> handed to me came from the Chinese
                            Ambassador in London.</p>
                        <p>After I had read the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> I said that, as
                            the Ambassador would understand, I could not at this time make any
                            comment upon it as I would first have to consult the Secretary of State.
                            I asked the Ambassador, however, if he would be good enough to explain
                            to me what was meant by the phrase “parallel action” in the first point
                            of the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>. The Ambassador said that his
                            interpretation of this phrase was that the Chinese Government did not
                            propose that the United States take any military action in conjunction
                            with China, Great Britain and France against Japan, but was intended to
                            imply the hope that should China, Great Britain and France engage in
                            military action against Japan, the United States would support such
                            action by economic or financial measures.</p>
                        <p>I told the Ambassador that I should be glad to see him next week after I
                            had consulted with the Secretary of State.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps">elles</hi>]</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>