<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Controls ( (Green))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d527</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">527</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-12-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-12-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recQZssarRbcJz7o2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil company</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-12-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-12-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="527"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d527">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">894.24/759</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Controls</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Green</hi>)<note n="32" xml:id="d527fn32">Copies transmitted
                        on December 19 to the companies listed in the second paragraph. For the
                        Department’s press release of December 20, see <ref
                            target="frus1931-41v02#pg_203">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 203</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1939-12-19">undated</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>It is considered that the national interest suggests that for the time being
                    there should be no further delivery to interests of certain countries of plans,
                    plants, manufacturing rights, or technical information required for the
                    production of high quality aviation gasoline.</p>
                <p>Accordingly, the Department has requested E. B. Badger and Sons Company, the M.
                    W. Kellogg Company, the Phillips Petroleum Company, the Shell Oil Company,
                    Incorporated, the Shell Union Oil Corporation, the Socony-Vacuum Oil Co.,
                    Incorporated, the Standard Oil Development Company, the Sun Oil Company, and the
                    Universal Oil Products Company to withhold any further sale or delivery of any
                    such plans, plants, manufacturing rights or technical information, or of related
                    patents, processes, or engineering assistance to representatives of or for use
                    in certain countries.</p>
                <p>In the event that the sale or delivery of such plans, plants, manufacturing
                    rights or technical information, or of related patents, processes, or
                    engineering assistance to certain other countries is contemplated, it is
                    understood that the Department will be informed.</p>
                <p>It is understood that, in case negotiations are broken off or the fulfillment of
                    commitments is suspended, the request of the Department may be given as a reason
                    for such action.</p>
                <p>Should any problems arise in connection with the carrying out of this program,
                    companies may communicate with the Division of Controls of the Department which
                    will be glad to take up any such problems at once.</p>
                <p>The Department recognizes that companies other than those represented in the
                    meeting held today will have an interest in this policy. It is understood that
                    the representatives of the companies listed above will take it upon themselves
                    to communicate with representatives of such companies.</p>
                <p>For the purpose of giving additional effectiveness to this policy, if necessary,
                    it is considered desirable that manufacturers and exporters of such blending
                    agents as tetra-ethyl lead, iso-octane, neo-hexane, and alkylates be requested
                    to furnish the Department with data as to recent shipments or contemplated
                    shipments of such blending agents to certain countries<note n="33"
                        xml:id="d527fn33">Countries referred to were Japan and the Soviet
                        Union.</note> to the end that the Department may be informed as to whether
                    large reserve stocks are being built up in that country. The Department is,
                    therefore, with a view to determining whether or not the sale for export of such
                    blending agents <pb facs="0554" n="550" xml:id="pg_550"/> requires further
                    discussion, requesting the companies listed below to furnish it currently with
                    such information: <list>
                        <item>Atlantic Refining Company</item>
                        <item>Cities Service Export Company</item>
                        <item>Ethyl Gasoline Corporation</item>
                        <item>Gulf Refining Company</item>
                        <item>Pan American Refining Company</item>
                        <item>Phillips Petroleum Company</item>
                        <item>Shell Union Oil Corporation</item>
                        <item>Sinclair Refining Company</item>
                        <item>Socony-Vacuum Oil Company, Inc.</item>
                        <item>Standard Oil Company of California</item>
                        <item>Standard Oil Company of Indiana</item>
                        <item>Standard Oil Company of New Jersey</item>
                        <item>The Texas Company</item>
                        <item>Tidewater Associated Oil Company</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph C. Green</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
