<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-01-04T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-01-04T10:00:00-05:00" n="598" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d598">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/14296: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-01-04T15:00:00+00:00">January 4,
                                    1939—3 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received January 4—2:15 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>12. The Chief of the Far Eastern Division of the Foreign Office<note n="60" xml:id="d598fn60">Reference is to Henri Hoppenot, who, on
                                October 24, 1938, was transferred from the Far Eastern to the
                                European Section as head of Section.</note> expressed the view to me
                            last night that Wang’s<note n="61" xml:id="d598fn61">Wang Ching-wei,
                                formerly Deputy Leader of the Kuomintang (Nationalist Party) at
                                Chungking.</note> defection has not weakened Chiang Kai Shek’s<note n="62" xml:id="d598fn62">Chairman of the Chinese Supreme National
                                Defense Council and Leader of the Kuomintang.</note> position and
                            that the latter is as determined as ever to see it through to the end.
                            His information is that the American credit and hopes of a British
                            credit have greatly encouraged the Chinese and that Chinese morale has
                            definitely improved in the last 2 or 3 months.</p>
                        <p>Hoppenot said that recently the Japanese Chargé d’Affaires inquired
                            whether France would grant a credit to China. He replied that he knew of
                            no such plan at present. He added to me that if anything of this nature
                            were done it would be through the Bank of Indo-China but that there was
                            nothing definite in mind at present.</p>
                        <p>He expressed the view that with the militarists on top in Japan as a
                            result of the Cabinet shake-up the army now would make a drive on Yunnan
                            in the hope of shutting off Chinese supplies by the Burma route which is
                            now operating fairly effectively.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>