<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan ( (Grew) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d795</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">795</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-01-01T22:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-01-01T22:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-01-01T22:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-01-01T22:00:00-05:00" n="795"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d795">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">693.002/802: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-01-02T12:00:00+09:00"
                            >January 2, 1939—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received January 2—8 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3. Embassy’s 788, December 17, 11 a.m., 1938,<note n="31" xml:id="d795fn31">Not
                        printed.</note> Canton Customs. My British colleague<note n="32"
                        xml:id="d795fn32">Sir Robert L. Craigie, British Ambassador in Japan.</note>
                    has just sent me the following letter: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“I have now received instructions to contest the argument, contained in
                            the Japanese Government’s reply to my note of the 24th November about
                            the Canton Customs, that since the Canton area is now under the
                            occupation of the Japanese forces the Japanese Government cannot accept
                            this protest.</p>
                        <pb facs="0805" n="801" xml:id="pg_801"/>
                        <p>I am to take the line that occupation of the area by the Japanese forces
                            affords no justification for taking over the customs. While the Customs
                            Administration is an organ of the Chinese Government, it is invested
                            with an international status both on the ground that it is the subject
                            of international agreements (e. g. the Peiping Protocol of 1901<note
                                n="33" xml:id="d795fn33">Signed at Peking, September 7, 1901, <ref
                                    target="frus1901#pg_312">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1901, Appendix
                                    (Affairs in China), p. 312</ref>.</note> to which Japan is a
                            party) and because of the important international interests which it was
                            designed to protect. Third powers have at all times been willing to
                            discuss customs questions with the Japanese Government and they have in
                            recent months frequently had occasion to point out the importance which
                            they attach to recognition of the international status of the
                            administration. The Japanese Government have on several occasions given
                            assurances that they do not intend to destroy its integrity, and their
                            present attitude is utterly at variance with their assurances. In these
                            circumstances I am to ask again for an assurance that control of the
                            Canton customs will be restored to the Inspector General of Customs.</p>
                        <p>Before addressing a note on the above lines to the Japanese Government, I
                            should be grateful if you would let me know whether you are intending to
                            reply to the similar note which the Japanese Government addressed to you
                            on the subject, and if so on what lines?”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Please instruct. Repeated to Chungking, Peiping, Canton.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
