<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in China ( (Peck) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d826</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">826</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-04-04T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-04-04T23:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-04-04T23:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-04-04T23:00:00-05:00" n="826"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d826">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">693.002/853: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Peck</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-04-05T11:00:00+07:00"
                            >April 5, 1939—11 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 1:38 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>239. Telegram 253, March 31, 2 p.m., from Shanghai to the Department regarding
                    Chinese customs. The British Diplomatic Mission supplied me last night with a
                    copy of a note sent by [<hi rend="italic">to?</hi>] the Chinese Minister for
                    Foreign Affairs on April 4 as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Your Excellency, I have the honor, on instructions from His Majesty’s
                            Ambassador in China, to inform Your Excellency that the Japanese
                            continue to exercise pressure on the Inspector General of Customs for
                            the appointment of additional Japanese to the senior posts in the
                            Customs Service, as well as for further Japanese to be appointed to
                            Kiungchow (Hainan). In the view of the Inspector General, the complete
                            rejection of these demands (in accordance with the categorical
                            instructions which he has received from Your Excellency) would result in
                            independent Japanese action which would jeopardize the integrity of the
                            service at an early date.</p>
                        <p>These instructions appear to place Sir Frederick Maze in an impossible
                            position. The policy which he has so far followed, namely, resistance to
                            the Japanese so long as may be practicable followed by concessions on a
                            minor scale, constitutes in the existing circumstances the only method
                            of preserving the integrity of the Customs Service regime permitting Sir
                            Frederick Maze to retain his nominal control.</p>
                        <p>Your Excellency is aware that in view of His Majesty’s Government in the
                            United Kingdom the maintenance of that integrity as long as may be
                            possible is in the interests of Great Britain and China alike; and I
                            have accordingly been instructed to urge upon Your Excellency the
                            acceptance of the views expressed by the Inspector General in his
                            telegram No. 30 of March 16th, transmitted to you by His Majesty’s
                            Consul General at Chungking.</p>
                        <p>I avail myself, et cetera.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Referring to despatch 2022, February 28 from Shanghai to the Department<note
                        n="70" xml:id="d826fn70">Not printed.</note> and especially to the telegram
                    from the Ministry of <pb facs="0833" n="829" xml:id="pg_829"/> Finance to the
                    Inspector General copied therein which states <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>
                    that the American Ambassador has requested of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs
                    that foreign employees of the customs shall be engaged on a broad international
                    basis, a search of the files of the Embassy for a year past fails to show the
                    American Ambassador has been instructed to make or has made any such
                    request.</p>
                <p>Repeated to Shanghai and Peiping. Latter please mail to Tokyo.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Peck</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
