<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-06-11T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-06-11T21:00:00-05:00" n="845" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d845">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/6915: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Counselor of Embassy in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Peck</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-06-12T09:00:00+07:00">June 12,
                                    1939—9 a.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received June 12—7 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>377. My 373, June 10, 11 a.m.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>This morning Arthur Young expressed to me great concern lest the
                                increasingly strained relations between Japan and Great Britain
                                should nullify British efforts to induce the Japanese to agree to
                                the arrangement for customs funds which he had been discussing with
                                the British Ambassador. He thought that the Japanese would receive
                                representations from American and French sources more favorably than
                                from British and he added that ample reason for such representations
                                seemed to exist in that immobilization of quota payments for the
                                service of obligations would protect the interests of foreign
                                bondholders while retention of the quota by the Japanese would
                                assist them [the Japanese] to frustrate attempts at support of
                                Chinese currency in the success of which attempts foreign interests
                                    <pb facs="0850" n="846" xml:id="pg_846"/> are so closely
                                involved. He regretted that he personally was so prominent in the
                                initiation of the strictly confidential discussions of this
                                proposal. He hoped the Department would realize that it was
                                necessary for some individual to take this initiative because there
                                were phases of the arrangement to which the Chinese Government could
                                not give more than the tacit approval that would be indicated by
                                refraining from interposing objections.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Does the Department desire that I repeat my 373 and this telegram
                                to Shanghai for Tokyo or to Peiping?</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Peck</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>