<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-09-30T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-09-30T15:00:00-05:00" n="867" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d867">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">693.002/931: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Chargé in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Dooman</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-09-30T15:00:00-05:00">September
                                    30, 1939—3 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>297. Reference Shanghai’s 847, September 22, 3 p.m., Chinese Maritime
                            Customs. Please consult your British and French colleagues and, if and
                            when they are prepared to take separate but substantially <pb facs="0866" n="862" xml:id="pg_862"/> similar action, make an
                            approach to the Japanese Foreign Office in such manner as you may deem
                            appropriate along lines as follows:<note n="19" xml:id="d867fn19">The
                                American, British, and French Embassies in Japan made similar
                                representations on October 26; for the American note, No. 1405, see
                                    <ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_750">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol.
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 750</ref>. For the Japanese
                                reply, see note No. 203, December 28, <ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_751">
                                    <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 751</ref>.</note>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>The Government of the United States has received information to
                                    the effect that a new regime sponsored by the Japanese forces in
                                    China may soon be established at Nanking; that it is planned
                                    that such new regime will offer to the Inspector General of the
                                    Chinese Maritime Customs a position similar to that which he now
                                    holds under appointment by the National Government of China; and
                                    that should he refuse to accept that offer he would be prevented
                                    from further exercise of his present functions as Inspector
                                    General in Chinese territory under the control of the new
                                    Japanese-sponsored regime.</p>
                                <p>It is the opinion of the Government of the United States that
                                    such action would constitute a serious disruption of the Chinese
                                    Maritime Customs. This Government has repeatedly expressed to
                                    the Japanese Government its rightful interest in the
                                    preservation of the administrative integrity of the Chinese
                                    Maritime Customs and it again earnestly requests that the
                                    Japanese Government refrain from action, either directly through
                                    its own agencies or indirectly through the agencies of any
                                    Japanese-sponsored regime in China, tending to destroy the
                                    administrative integrity of the Chinese Maritime Customs.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Sent to Tokyo via Shanghai. Repeated to Chungking and Peiping.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>