<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>133. Memorandum From the Director of Intelligence and Research (Cumming) to
                    the ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d133</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">133</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1960-11-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-11-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recu8CRwmmn30dF6G" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081635"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Martial law</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134112"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Terrorism</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-11-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-11-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="133"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d133">
                <head>133. Memorandum From the Director of Intelligence and Research (<persName
                        corresp="#p_CHSJ1" type="from">Cumming</persName>) to the <gloss type="to"
                        >Secretary of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d133fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 713.00/11–1460. Confidential. No drafting information appears on the
                        source text.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-11-14">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 14, 1960</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Intelligence Note: Revolutionary Outbreaks in Central America<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d133fn2">On November 17, Assistant Secretary <persName
                                corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> sent Under Secretary <persName
                                corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> a more extensive memorandum
                            covering the same subject. (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>.,
                            713.00/11–1760)</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The bloodless overthrow of the <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM1">Lemus</persName>
                    regime in El Salvador on October 26, and its replacement by a government which
                    is exhibiting an increasingly leftward trend, has been followed by attempts
                    against the Ydígoras and <persName>Somoza</persName> administrations,
                    respectively, in Guatemala and Nicaragua. The Guatemalan and Nicaraguan
                    Governments allege that <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> is
                    supporting the revolutionary movements. Disturbances related to the Nicaraguan
                    uprising have also taken place in Costa Rica. <pb facs="0492" n="452"
                        xml:id="pg_452"/> All of these developments, beginning with the deposing of
                        <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM1">Lemus</persName>, have had an unsettling
                    effect upon the somewhat unstable <persName corresp="#p_VMDJR1"
                        >Villeda</persName> regime in Honduras.</p>
                <p>Summaries of the situation in Guatemala, Nicaragua, and Costa Rica follow:</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Supported by the army and air force, the Ydígoras administration appears to have
                    placed insurgent forces, which staged uprisings in several parts of the country
                    on November 11, on the defensive. A state of siege—a modified form of martial
                    law—has been placed in effect. Order, never seriously disrupted, prevails in
                    Guatemala City, from which rebels fled after attacking at least one garrison.
                    Troops have been dispatched to reinforce Chiquimula, and are fighting rebels in
                    Zacapa and Puerto Barrios, where some troops in local garrisons are reported to
                    have defected. Led by several middle grade army officers, the revolutionary
                    movement has some support among anti-Ydígoras elements of various political
                    orientations, but principally moderate leftists. The clandestine Guatemalan
                    Labor (Communist) Party reportedly was unaware of plans for the movement,
                    although it and extreme leftists have been very active in their opposition to
                    Ydígoras.</p>
                <p>The elements undertaking the revolution are reported to have agreed upon a new
                    government composed of members ranging from extreme leftists to rightists. Thus
                    far, there does not appear to be widespread popular support for the insurgents
                    despite the fact that the Ydígoras regime is unpopular in many quarters. The
                    revolt appears to some extent to represent a coalescing of hitherto disparate
                    oppositionist elements seeking to take advantage of declining stability, and to
                    bring about pressure which would compel the military to replace Ydígoras with a
                    junta.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Nicaragua</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On November 11 predominantly leftist and pro-Communist opposition forces launched
                    a co-ordinated uprising from within and outside Nicaragua against the
                        <persName>Somoza</persName> regime. Severe fighting took place in Carazo
                    province, where barracks at Jinotepe and Diriamba were seized for a short time
                    by the rebels. Some acts of terrorism were reported to have taken place in
                    Managua. There were also reports that reinforcements and arms for the rebels had
                    been landed on the country’s Caribbean coast. Indications are that a
                    considerable number of the insurgents within Nicaragua have been killed or
                    captured, and the government, which has declared martial law, appears to be in
                    control of the situation.</p>
                <pb facs="0493" n="453" xml:id="pg_453"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Costa Rica</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On November 12 the <persName corresp="#p_EJM1">Echandi</persName> government
                    began attempts to contain Nicaraguan exiles and other revolutionaries, possibly
                    including Cubans, which were concentrated at the Nicaraguan border. This has
                    resulted in clashes between the Costa Rican Civil Guard and the rebels.
                    President <persName corresp="#p_EJM1">Echandi</persName> has declared a state of
                    siege and has called up the country’s reserves. Some reports indicate that the
                    rebels are well-armed and receiving reinforcements and supplies by air from Cuba
                    and Honduras.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Conclusions</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The almost simultaneous timing of these uprisings suggests the probability that
                    the whole is a co-ordinated undertaking. Both <persName>Somoza</persName> and
                    Ydígoras allege that the actions against their governments are Cuban inspired.
                    Ever since its inception, the <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>
                    regime has actively sought to further its interests in Central America through
                    the use of its diplomatic missions, special agents, financial assistance, and
                    propaganda. As a result, Guatemala severed diplomatic relations with Cuba, and
                    Honduras declared a Cuban ambassador <hi rend="italic">persona non grata.</hi>
                    In all of the Central American republics, <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                        >Castro</persName>’s efforts have been abetted by local Communists and
                    extreme leftist sympathizers. While direct evidence of Cuban participation in
                    the most recent uprisings as yet is lacking, their occurrence, together with
                    developments in El Salvador, creates an unsettled atmosphere favorable for
                    exploitation by <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
