<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-04-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-04-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="179" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d179">
                        <head>179. Memorandum of a Conversation, President <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName>’s Residence, Olivos, April 29,
                                1959<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d179fn1">Source: Department of
                                State, <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_EST1">EST</gloss> Files: Lot 61 D 386, US-Argentine Relations,
                                General January–June 1959. Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> were part of the U.S.
                                Delegation representing the United States on the Special Committee
                                of the Council of the Organization of American States To Study the
                                Formulation of New Measures for Economic Cooperation (Committee of
                                21) which convened at Buenos Aires on April 27.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Olivos</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1959-04-29">April 29, 1959</date></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>His Excellency The President of the Argentine Nation, Dr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Arturo Frondizi</persName></item>
                            <item>Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Thomas C.
                                    Mann</persName></item>
                            <item>Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">R. R. Rubottom,
                                    Jr.</persName></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The President and Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName>
                            received us at their residence at Olivos following which the President
                            conducted us into his office for a pre-luncheon discussion, Mrs.
                                <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName> retiring to her
                            quarters. I expressed to the President our pleasure at being in
                            Argentina. Referring to his recent visit to the United States, I said
                            that it had left an indelible, favorable impression and that from every
                            side, the Government, the press, and the public at large, he had
                            received resounding <pb facs="0600" n="560" xml:id="pg_560"/> applause
                            for the forthright positions he had taken on the major economic and
                            political issues confronting Argentina and the rest of the free
                            world.</p>
                        <p>The President recalled his trip with pleasure and expressed gratitude for
                            the treatment he had been accorded.</p>
                        <p>The President did not seem disposed to press any particular subject and,
                            as the following will reveal, we took the initiative in raising most of
                            the important matters pending between the Governments of the United
                            States and Argentina.</p>
                        <p>The President stressed the difficulties which he and his Government were
                            facing but indicated an unfaltering determination to carry through with
                            the programs he had espoused in searching for solutions to Argentina’s
                            problems. He said Argentina had always had so much that it was difficult
                            for the people to accustom themselves to an austerity program. The pinch
                            was being felt everywhere. He said that the PL 480 program now being
                            contemplated would be of great assistance. I told him of the word from
                            Washington that consideration was now being given to approximately
                            75,000 tons of edible oil and 35,000 tons of rice. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> said that the matter of price was
                            a serious deterrent to any possible purchase program for wheat and/or
                            corn, but that we would do everything within the limits of our laws to
                            assist.</p>
                        <p>The President said that he was extremely grateful for the practical
                            assistance which we were already giving Argentina. It had strengthened
                            his hand and he need more if such were possible. Argentina wants nothing
                            in the way of gifts, he said, but is prepared to repay the United States
                            in the future for the help given now when it is so badly needed.</p>
                        <p>I told the President that we had received Dr.
                                <persName>Frigerio</persName> and gave him ample opportunity to talk
                            about the Argentine situation. He expressed approval and said that that
                            was exactly what he had wanted. I mentioned the small luncheon given Dr.
                                <persName>Frigerio</persName> by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> and myself and said that Ambassador Barros Hurtado
                            had been good enough to show me the copies of the letters, which he, the
                            President, had given to Dr. <persName>Frigerio</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Next, I raised the matter of military equipment, recounting all of [the]
                            discussions I had had with Ambassador Barros Hurtado and our first
                            conversations when the President visited Washington last January.</p>
                        <p>At this point the three of us went into the dining room for lunch.</p>
                        <p>I said that I felt personally responsible for having authorized
                            Ambassador Barros Hurtado to tell the President of our agreement “in
                            principle” to furnish an unspecified amount of military equipment to the
                            Argentine Armed Forces. This undertaking had perhaps raised the hopes of
                            the Armed Forces to obtain more equipment than was possible for the
                            present. I referred to the problem that had been created by <pb facs="0601" n="561" xml:id="pg_561"/> the late entry of the Army
                            into our consideration of the Argentine request; there was stressed also
                            the need for Argentina to coordinate the request of its three services
                            in such a way as to permit the Ambassador to speak for the entire
                            defense establishment of the Government. The President nodded
                            understanding of the situation and said that he had recently talked to
                            Ambassador Barros Hurtado by telephone and that he, personally, would
                            undertake to settle any future questions between the three services. He
                            was hopeful that Argentina would be able to obtain approximately $13
                            million of equipment which was vitally needed to maintain the morale of
                            the services to assure their continued loyalty, and to support minimum
                            measures of internal security against the threat of subversion. I told
                            the President that I had discussed this matter with Under Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> just before leaving
                            Washington and that I could not give him absolute assurance that the $13
                            million request would be approved.<note n="2" xml:id="d179fn2">At 9:12
                                p.m., the Department informed <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> in Buenos Aires that he had authorization
                                to proceed with the negotiations of the Argentine military credit
                                program which was not to exceed $13 million. (Telegram 1345 to
                                Buenos Aires, April 29; <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Central Files,
                                    735.5–<gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/4–2959)</note> I
                            wished to avoid making any firm commitment. Nevertheless, I was hopeful.
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> expressed his intention
                            to support the request if the funds could be found anywhere.</p>
                        <p>The President pointed out the difficulty in explaining to economic
                            sectors and the people at large that their stake in the success of the
                            Economic Stabilization Program is just as great as that of the
                            Government itself. He chose this way of saying that Dr.
                                <persName>Frigerio</persName> would probably assume the task of
                            explaining the Program to the public at large. He traced Dr.
                                <persName>Frigerio</persName>’s association with him—first, as a
                            close friend and official adviser; second, as completely unofficial
                            adviser but still known to be close to the President; and third and
                            last, he would “go out on the street” completely apart from the
                            Government in order to explain the meaning of the Economic Stabilization
                            Program to the people. I interpreted this as a confirmation of the
                            President’s oft-reported intention to downgrade
                                <persName>Frigerio</persName>. He gave no reason other than that
                            stated above and spoke in the friendliest terms about
                                <persName>Frigerio</persName>.</p>
                        <p>We talked for a while of the impending <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> visit.<note n="3" xml:id="d179fn3"><persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Fidel Castro</persName> visited Argentina May
                                2–4.</note> The President showed no concern, but in this context
                            mentioned the clamp-down on all activities of the Communist Party. I
                            said that <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> and his group
                            had behaved relatively well in the United States; that, while he had
                            given satisfactory and rather categorical statements on most of the
                            questions asked him, he had been evasive on the Communist question; that
                            he had satisfied nobody with his explanations of the reasons for
                            postponing elections to some four years hence because of <pb facs="0602" n="562" xml:id="pg_562"/> the demands of “the people”. The
                            President, himself, then phrased the question, “He is still an unknown
                            quantity?”, to which I replied affirmatively. The President certainly
                            revealed no enthusiasm over the prospects of seeing <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Next, I turned to the Chocón project, outlining our conversations in
                            Washington with <persName>Frigerio</persName> and then my own
                            conversations later with Ambassador Barros Hurtado, Burk Knapp and
                                <persName corresp="#p_BER1">Eugene Black</persName>. I stressed our
                            hope that Argentina would consider carefully this project and any other
                            of such magnitude that might have a serious impact on the country’s
                            capacity to borrow, and on the stabilization program itself. He
                            expressed understanding of this point of view and said that he had
                            already communicated to the World Bank Argentina’s agreement with the
                            position taken by the Bank, i.e., no contracts should be signed until
                            the electric power study being conducted by the Bank had been concluded.
                            The President said that the Italian Ambassador had called to protest
                            this decision. He had replied to the Ambassador that Italy was a member
                            of the World Bank and that Italian suppliers would have a chance to bid
                            on the equipment for the Chocón project later.</p>
                        <p>I told President <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName> that the
                            Department was following very closely the discussions with his
                            Government on the subject of Civil Aviation: that I had noted that the
                            Government’s approach so far to this sector seemed less liberal than its
                            approach to other economic matters. He acknowledged that Civil Aviation
                            was so far an unresolved problem, as much for him as it was for the
                            United States. He said that he would continue working on it, referring
                            to the importance which a satisfactory solution had for Argentina’s
                            well-being. He said that Argentina needed to strengthen its Civil
                            Aviation, both from the standpoint of its own vast requirements in a
                            country of such great dimensions and because of the tremendous returns
                            from tourism that this would bring.</p>
                        <p>We discussed the problem created by his efforts to have recognized
                            diplomas from private universities. He said he would win this issue but
                            acknowledged that it had led to a break with his brother, Rector of the
                            University of Buenos Aires, with whom he had not spoken in six
                            months.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> and I thanked the
                            President for his hospitality and excused ourselves at about 2:45
                            p.m.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>