<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="188" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d188">
                        <head>188. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>On June 15, a series of incidents involving the Argentina Army resulted
                            in a serious threat to the stability of the <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName> regime. In response to their alleged criticism
                            of the Argentine Government, two high-ranking Argentine military
                            officers were removed from their posts. Two days later, on June 17, the
                            commander of the Fourth Motorized Division in Córdoba arrived in Buenos
                            Aires with the proposal of his subordinates calling for the removal of
                            the Under Secretary of War, who subsequently submitted his resignation.
                            This shakeup led to additional rumors concerning military uprisings in
                            Córdoba and other areas, the resignation of the Secretary of War, and
                            active plotting by retired Argentine military officers. (Despatch 1896
                            from Buenos Aires, June 23; Department of State, Central Files, 735.00
                                (<gloss target="#t_W1">W</gloss>)/6–2359)</p>
                        <p>On June 18, at the 410th meeting of the National Security Council,
                                <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName>, in his review
                            of world developments affecting U.S. security, raised the subject of
                            Argentina. The memorandum of discussion reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> described the
                                    Latin American picture as boiling in many places. <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName> was hanging on by his
                                    eye teeth in Argentina. He might pull through. His fate depended
                                    on the behavior of the Argentine Army. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> felt that <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName> had put up a valiant
                                    fight against inflation even though he had not been wholly
                                    successful. It would be a pity therefore if he collapsed. The
                                    opposition to <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName> was
                                    spearheaded by Peronists and Communists. On balance, Mr.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> thought that
                                        <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName> would squeak
                                    through.” (Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Records)</p>
                            </quote></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>