<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>223. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, September
                    28, 1960</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1960-09-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-09-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recAHt1IiF33Lofk6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028349"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Development program</term>
                    <term ref="recibBhfq1Nhuo5rk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="rec8HXmBQjKyPk0EY" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062603"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Housing</term>
                    <term ref="recykDuvfC6iFH3Xe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85139643"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Unemployment</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recBS0IqgpfGXNR4a" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048310"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">International Financial Institutions</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="air-safety"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Civil aviation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-09-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-09-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="223"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d223">
                <head>223. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, September
                    28, 1960<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d223fn1">Source: Department of State,
                        Central Files, 835.10/9–2860. Confidential. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_OCJF1">O’Connor</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1960-09-28">September 28,
                            1960</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Additional Financial Assistance for Argentina</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Eng. Alvaro C. Alsogaray, Argentine Minister of Economy</item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName>Julio Gonzalez del Solar</persName>, Second Vice President,
                        Arg. Central Bank</item>
                    <item>Acting Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador-designate to Argentina <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">R. R.
                            Rubottom, Jr.</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MEM1">Edwin M. Martin</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">C. A. Boonstra</persName>, <gloss
                            target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>:<gloss target="#t_ESTA1">EST/A</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCR1">Charles R. Harley</persName>,
                        Treasury</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_OCJF1">James F. O’Connor, Jr.</persName>, <gloss
                            target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>:<gloss target="#t_ESTA1">EST/A</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Minister Alsogaray reviewed Argentine stabilization progress, which he said had
                    exceeded his Government’s expectations and made it unnecessary for Argentina to
                    seek further assistance in this field. He also referred to the constructive
                    results of the petroleum development program and to steps being taken to seek
                    majority private capital participation in the <gloss target="#t_SOMISA1"
                        >SOMISA</gloss> steel plant and to reorganize the Dock Sud (Buenos Aires)
                    power project under private auspices with <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss>
                    assistance.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said that he had discussed the
                    Dock Sud matter with Vice President Knapp of the <gloss target="#t_IBRD1"
                        >IBRD</gloss> and found that organization very interested and disposed to
                    help, although questioning the availability of Argentine private capital. Eng.
                    Alsogaray indicated that this was not a problem.</p>
                <p>The Minister said that the <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName>
                    Government’s policy was to promote private activity in the fields of oil, steel,
                    petrochemicals, pulp and paper, and transportation, and concentrate its activity
                    in the sectors where private capital was not available, such as road-building
                    and housing. He added that fifteen years of decay in the Argentine highway
                    system had to be overcome by repair and new construction, and said that an
                        <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss> transportation-survey mission was
                    studying Argentine needs. The Minister also explained that housing plans were
                    designed to serve two ends: facilitate worker relocation in combatting
                    unemployment and providing labor where needed; and to provide tangible evidence
                    to the Argentine people that the sacrifices required by the stabilization
                    program were bearing fruit and that the Government’s economic policy was a
                    constructive one. He added that economic progress would eliminate political and
                    labor problems, and that <pb facs="0684" n="644" xml:id="pg_644"/> Argentine
                    success in this regard would promote the spread of the <persName
                        corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName> Government’s philosophy elsewhere in
                    Latin America. Receipt of aid from the United States and international financial
                    institutions for the first stages of the highway and housing programs would
                    eliminate major problems for his Government.</p>
                <p>In reply to a query from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> as to
                    whether Argentine highway planning was being carefully worked out, Alsogaray
                    said that close contact was being maintained with the foreign transportation
                    experts now in Argentina to assure that plans were well-founded. While in
                    Washington he had been discussing export credits for road-building machinery
                    with the <gloss target="#t_EXIMBANK1">Eximbank</gloss>, and a peso loan for
                    local costs with the <gloss target="#t_DLF1">DLF</gloss>. In reply to another
                    query from the Acting Secretary, the Minister said that Argentina did not
                    contemplate direct government building, but financial assistance by the National
                    Mortgage Bank and the new Housing Administration to private builders.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> referred to the favorable
                    impression which President <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName> had
                    made in explaining his economic program when he visited the United States, and
                    went on to say that the success of this program was important, not only for
                    Argentina, but as an example for other countries. The United States wanted to
                    cooperate, but this would have to be done carefully, and procedures were
                    important. It did not give loans unless requested, and it would need more
                    details before it could make commitments, taking also into account its own
                    availabilities. Managing Director <persName corresp="#p_BV1">Vance
                        Brand</persName> of the <gloss target="#t_DLF1">DLF</gloss> would be
                    visiting Argentina shortly, and he could look into the highway program in
                    detail. He could also look into the housing program, although funds for this
                    should be channelled through the Inter-American Development Bank and had not in
                    fact yet been appropriated by the Congress.</p>
                <p>The Acting Secretary then said that he had been surprised by the attitude
                    displayed by some of the Argentine delegates to the meeting of the Committee of
                    21. One of them, Mr. Musich, claimed that Argentina had been forgotten by the
                    United States and advocated a strong stand to make the United States aware of
                    its problems.<note n="2" xml:id="d223fn2">The memorandum of conversation with
                        Arnaldo T. Musich, chief of the Argentine Delegation to the meeting of the
                        Committee of 21 is <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Secretary’s Memoranda of
                        Conversation: Lot 64 D 199.</note> He (Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1"
                        >Dillon</persName>) felt that this attitude was the result of a
                    misunderstanding, since approaches in such contexts made it more difficult to
                    extend financial assistance.</p>
                <p>Minister Alsogaray said that he was not responsible for political matters in
                    Argentina, but that the attitude to which the Acting Secretary referred did not
                    represent the policy of the Argentine Government, and he would take this up with
                    President <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName> on his return. <pb
                        facs="0685" n="645" xml:id="pg_645"/> Argentina did not like to come to the
                    United States frequently for assistance, as some other countries seemed to be
                    doing. It did not expect the United States to solve the Argentines’ own
                    problems.</p>
                <p>The Minister then said that Argentina would like to undertake a new policy of
                    developing its armed forces with some assistance from outside. The Government
                    wanted to organize the armed forces, which had been of assistance in connection
                    with stabilization, as leaders in carrying forward the Government’s economic
                    program. This would involve a small amount of US financial assistance to groups
                    which had supported the Government and its pro-Western policies.</p>
                <p>Eng. Alsogaray went on to suggest that the United States could not spread its
                    foreign aid to help all peoples raise their standard of living, and that it
                    would be most practical to concentrate its efforts where they would produce the
                    best results. If the Argentine emphasis on private enterprise were successful,
                    it would spread elsewhere. Despite what had occurred at Bogota, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> could be assured that President
                        <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName> and Alsogaray’s own team
                    believed in self-help above all. However, it needed some basic assistance to
                    show the Argentine people that the Government’s policy was a good one, thus
                    inhibiting Communism. Argentina’s present needs were for aid in road-building
                    and housing.</p>
                <p>The Acting Secretary said that he agreed with the Minister. US financial aid
                    could not solve all the world’s problems. A people’s will and own efforts were
                    important, and Argentina was in this regard a well-qualified country with whom
                    the United States could work very cooperatively.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> then said that he wanted to
                    raise two less important problems. He hoped that something could be done to move
                    the civil aviation problem, on which he understood the Argentines had internal
                    problems, toward solution. Minister Alsogaray said that President <persName
                        corresp="#p_FA1">Frondizi</persName> had authorized him to discuss the basis
                    for possible agreement while in Washington and he would be free to do so on
                    Friday, September 30. He added that the United States had no cause to worry
                    about this matter. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said
                    advance understanding on the basis for an agreement would be useful.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> then referred to the concern of
                    US meatpackers over a projected subsidy within that industry which would be
                    prejudicial to their interests. The Minister said immediately that there was no
                    cause for alarm. When fixed capital had been set a year ago for <gloss
                        target="#t_CAP1">CAP</gloss>, a cooperative which had Government support, no
                    working capital had been established. The present payment was merely to
                    establish the working capital in proportion to the fixed capital to complete
                    this matter. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> asked if this
                    were then a one-time operation and Eng. Alsogaray replied that it was.</p>
                <pb facs="0686" n="646" xml:id="pg_646"/>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> asked the Minister
                    about the status of the valuation of the American and Foreign Power Company’s
                    properties. Alsogaray said Mr. <persName>Sargent</persName> of that firm had
                    talked to him about this recently. He (Alsogaray) hoped that the Chief Justice
                    of the Argentine Supreme Court would make his decision by the end of
                    October.</p>
                <p>Minister Alsogaray commented that he was very pleased at Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName>’s assignment to Argentina.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d223fn3">On August 27, the Senate confirmed the appointment of
                            <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> as Ambassador to
                        Argentina. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> presented his
                        credentials on October 20.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1"
                        >Dillon</persName> said that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1"
                        >Rubottom</persName> was a good friend, who shared his views on major
                    problems.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
