<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-12-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="278" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d278">
                        <head>278. Letter From the Ambassador in Brazil (<persName corresp="#p_CJM1" type="from">Cabot</persName>) to the Assistant Secretary of State
                            for Inter-American Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1" type="to">Rubottom</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d278fn1">Source: Department of State, <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName>
                                Files: Lot 62 D 418, Brazil 1960. Confidential.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Rio de
                                        Janeiro</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-12-04"><hi rend="italic">December 4,
                                1959</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Dick</hi>: Four months have now gone by since I
                            arrived in Brazil and, to my great surprise, the shoe has not dropped,
                            either on my toe or, so far as I can see, anywhere else. I had assumed
                            on coming here that I should be confronted with a harassing campaign to
                            get large loans without any undertaking in return that they would be
                            properly spent. I will not say that broad hints have not been cast out
                            from time to time; for example, you will recall that the President <pb facs="0785" n="745" xml:id="pg_745"/> button-holed me the very day I
                            presented my credentials;<note n="2" xml:id="d278fn2">In telegram 135
                                from Rio de Janeiro, July 22, <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> reported on his presentation of credentials on
                                that day to President <persName corresp="#p_KODJ1">Kubitschek</persName>. (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Central
                                Files, 611.32/7–2259)</note> and <persName corresp="#p_SAF1">Schmidtty</persName> may have been looking for loans when he had
                            lunch with me, though he said he wasn’t.<note n="3" xml:id="d278fn3">A
                                memorandum of the conversation between Schimdt and <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> at a luncheon in Rio de
                                Janeiro is <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Rio de Janerio Embassy
                                Files: Lot 68 F 77, 320, Brazil-U.S. 1959.</note> Nevertheless, I
                            cannot say that the pressure so far has been heavy.</p>
                        <p>Brazil has been able to scrape by for six months primarily because of
                            coffee exports which were much bigger than expected. This is a process
                            which can scarcely continue. Brazil has probably wanted to scrape by,
                            partly in response to <persName>Walter Moreira Salles</persName>’ idea
                            that there should be a breathing spell and partly because having thumbed
                            its nose very publicly at the <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss>, it
                            did not choose to go round again in public asking for money which
                            probably would not be forthcoming except on terms which Brazil had just
                            rejected.</p>
                        <p>I do not think that we should be deceived by this lull. The situation is
                            gradually deteriorating, and I would say that our relations with Brazil
                            were deteriorating also. In part, this was inevitable. It was a risk
                            which we took with our eyes open when, after Brazil publicly stuck out
                            its tongue at the <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss>, we refused to
                            furnish any new money. I have no doubt that we then thought the
                            Brazilians would grab the gold loan which they insistently sought and
                            also would snatch at our offer to reschedule debts. These things have
                            not yet happened.</p>
                        <p>From our viewpoint, the most discouraging thing is that the internal
                            financial position of the Government is going from bad to worse. There
                            is no evidence that I can see that President <persName corresp="#p_KODJ1">Kubitschek</persName> has any real intention of
                            economizing. On the contrary, his whole philosophy is one of all-out
                            development and the hell with the economic consequences. He is not alone
                            in this. I would say that the great majority of Brazilians believe
                            almost hysterically in development and that they are not emotionally
                            able to appreciate the very direct relationship between development at
                            too rapid a pace and the price of <hi rend="italic">feijão</hi>. Of
                            course, the more literate and conservative elements do understand this
                            relationship, but they are not running the show at the present time.</p>
                        <p>The deterioration can be shown in various ways. The drop in the cruzeiro
                            from 150 when I arrived to about 200 today is one symptom. The decision
                            of the Government to buy beans and meat abroad and to put $1 million a
                            week extra into the official exchange market is another. A third is the
                            increasing rate of inflation associated with the increasing rate of
                            paper money issuance. Our Treasury Attaché thinks that by one
                            sleight-of-hand measure after another the present administration can
                            probably ride out the storm until a new one comes into office, but in
                            that event the new administration will take over with the <pb facs="0786" n="746" xml:id="pg_746"/> ship of state on the point of
                            sinking. I find this a very disturbing thought, particularly when one of
                            these fine days we may be confronted with the problem of synthetic
                            coffee.</p>
                        <p>We should realize that Brazil’s financial record is not quite as bad as
                            it has often been pictured. For example, in Washington I heard a good
                            deal of talk about the “billion dollars in balance of payments help
                            which Brazil has received since 1953.”<note n="4" xml:id="d278fn4">The
                                quotation has not been further identified.</note> In point of fact,
                            the net balance of payments help has been barely half of this and a good
                            deal of the gross has actually been paid. Thus, nearly two-thirds of the
                            $300,000,000 which Brazil borrowed in 1953 has been repaid. There has as
                            yet been no default on Brazil’s obligations. <persName corresp="#p_MHK1">Herbert May</persName>, our Treasury Attaché, prepared some figures
                            for us on total foreign loans and repayments from 1953 to 1958 which
                            showed a heavy deficit only in the last year; until then, income
                            approximately balanced outgo. Brazil has sharply curtailed imports,
                            particularly of luxury items; more drastic curbs would cut into
                            essentials or development. Brazil’s balance of payments problem has been
                            only partly due to extravagance, and it has been in very substantial
                            measure due to heavy short term maturities. (Of course, this is not to
                            deny Brazil’s need to take the measures necessary to expand its exports,
                            particularly in the face of the probable continuation of decline in
                            world coffee prices.)</p>
                        <p>The cold shoulder we have given the Brazilians in their economic plight
                            has had its inevitable repercussions on the political orientation of the
                            Brazilian Government. One sympton of this is the trade mission which is
                            now in Soviet Russia.<note n="5" xml:id="d278fn5">In despatch 594 from
                                Rio de Janeiro, December 11, the Embassy reported on a
                                Soviet-Brazilian trade agreement signed at Moscow, December 9, which
                                provided for $208 million in trade during 1960–1962. (Department of
                                State, Central Files, 832.00/ 12–1159)</note> A second is the
                            meeting at Itamaraty which I described in my telegram No. 770 of
                            November 20.<note n="6" xml:id="d278fn6">In telegram 770, <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> reported on a hastily called
                                meeting between diplomatic representatives of all the American
                                Republics and Brazilian officials including Foreign Minister Láfer
                                and Presidential Adviser <persName corresp="#p_SAF1">Schmidt</persName> at the Brazilian Foreign Office on that day.
                                During the discussion of Operation Pan America at that meeting,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> stated that he
                                thought it would be helpful to know specifically what Operation Pan
                                America envisaged, since he had “seen no concrete plan.” (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 363/11–2059)</note> A third is the
                            temperament so often displayed at inconvenient moments by <persName corresp="#p_SAF1">Augusto Frederico Schmidt</persName>. A fourth is
                            the way in which President <persName corresp="#p_KODJ1">Kubitschek</persName> impatiently harps on the need for development
                            in practically every major speech he makes. A fifth is the way in which
                            we have been blamed for the meat and feijão crises. (The American bean
                            scandal begins to look like a Communist masterpiece, but if it is I hope
                            we can make it boomerang.) I think we must anticipate a rough going <pb facs="0787" n="747" xml:id="pg_747"/> over at the Quito Conference,
                            with the Brazilians, who have so often in inter-American conferences
                            acted as moderators, now taking the leadership in turning the heat on
                            us.</p>
                        <p>The question is: What, if anything, should we do about it? It would seem
                            to me that there are really two problems. One concerns the long-term
                            development of Brazil, which is obviously a matter of great importance
                            to us. This involves the subsidiary problem of making it clear to the
                            Brazilians that, although we have our temporary differences with them in
                            regard to financial policy, we nevertheless hold firmly to the historic
                            concept of continued cooperation between our two great countries and
                            that we want to see Brazil strong, prosperous, progressive, and
                            respected. In his anxiety to be loved, Schmidtty expresses a national
                            Brazilian yearning which, I am afraid, we have not adequately satisfied
                            in recent years, [<hi rend="italic">remainder of paragraph (6 lines of
                                source text) not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>Our short-term objective is obviously to see that Brazil gets through the
                            present administration without some major over-turn and survives in such
                            shape that a new government taking office can restore Brazil’s economic
                            stability. We have, if I understand correctly, refused to loan Brazil
                            new money for balance of payment purposes, partly because we did not
                            wish to break a pattern we had established with many other nations, but
                            partly also because we did not wish to have the new administration’s
                            financial head pushed under water even before it took office. I think
                            this was a wise decision, since we cannot fill a bottomless pit with
                            gold.</p>
                        <p>While we must keep long-term objectives in mind, it seems to me there is
                            little reason at present to do any specific planning about them; we do
                            not now know even who the next president will be. Our present concern
                            should be to get through the next fourteen months with as little damage
                            as possible to Brazil’s economy and development, and to the relations
                            between the two countries.</p>
                        <p>It does not seem to me that our present negative attitude is a very
                            satisfactory way of attaining these aims. It lends itself to such
                            charming interpretations as Hanson’s Letters have been putting on
                                it<note n="7" xml:id="d278fn7">In a November 25 letter to <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> called attention to two
                                issues of <hi rend="italic">Hanson’s Latin American Letter</hi>,
                                October 31 and November 21, dealing with U.S.-Brazilian relations.
                                    (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Rio de Janeiro Embassy Files: Lot
                                68 F 77, 320 Brazil-U.S. 1959) <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName>’s reply of December 10 is <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>.</note>—and the Brazilians in their sensitive mood
                            are likely to accept such artful distortions as gospel. It runs counter
                            to the Brazilian yearning to be loved by us—and the more I think of
                            Alzira <persName corresp="#p_PEA1">Peixoto</persName>’s phrase the truer
                            I realize it is for Brazilian psychology, however strange we may find
                            it. More important, it does nothing to stop the economic rot here; and
                            it hobbles Brazilian development.</p>
                        <pb facs="0788" n="748" xml:id="pg_748"/>
                        <p>I feel that we do not adequately appreciate that, if there has been graft
                            and waste, Brazil’s progress under <persName corresp="#p_KODJ1">Kubitschek</persName> has been very rapid. The figures of increases
                            in the production of steel, electric power, alkalis, ships, oil, etc.,
                            are very impressive. Roads and railways are being built. In oil, we
                            thought six years ago that <gloss target="#t_Petrobras1">Petrobras</gloss> would be a flop; in that time oil production has
                            gone up twenty times. Though I am still skeptical that they will become
                            self-sufficient in oil in the next few years as they anticipate, it
                            seems to me we would find it difficult to argue now that we were right
                            and they were wrong; on the contrary, I doubt that private initiative
                            would have developed Brazil’s oil resources as fast. In short, they have
                            spent a lot of money, but they have a lot to show for their money.</p>
                        <p>Even their “extravagances” don’t appear so reckless on examination. The
                            principal reason for their inflation is coffee financing—and this
                            administration inherited this problem, though it has certainly not
                            contributed to its solution. Brasilia is expensive, but it is only a
                            small part of the broad development picture, and by securing for the
                            government a good part of of land values increment (they bought up a
                            block of 5000 square kilometers and are now selling it in lots) they
                            will recover much of their outlay, if not the inflation it engendered.
                            The Brazilians suffer from our defect of talking too much about their
                            defects—and finding that foreigners take their exaggerations
                            seriously.</p>
                        <p>You naturally wish suggestions as to what we should do. Here are some: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>It would be most helpful if the President could come to the
                                    inauguration of Brasilia. By that time the airport there should
                                    be able to take the President’s jet, and if he came on to Rio he
                                    could presumably do so in a prop plane. The Secretary should
                                    also visit Brazil at an early opportunity and not repeat
                                    Acheson’s and <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>’
                                    mistake of waiting too long.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>I am glad to see that the Secretary invited in Moreira Salles.
                                    An invitation to <persName corresp="#p_LH1">Lafer</persName> to
                                    come to Washington to discuss Quito would be most helpful, also
                                    any similar gesture to show how important we consider Brazil.
                                    They yearn to be considered a great power, and they feel we have
                                    treated them on a par with Honduras. Even 25 years ago we
                                    consulted them first on practically all inter-American and on
                                    many world problems—are they less important to us now? (Your
                                    letter of November 27 has just come in. I am very pleased that
                                    we have such very similar views.)</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>If the Inter-American Bank gets going soon, could we intimate
                                    to them that we would support a loan to <gloss target="#t_Petrobras1">Petrobras</gloss>? For many
                                    Brazilians our attitude towards <gloss target="#t_Petrobras1">Petrobras</gloss> is the test of our real purposes
                                    regarding Brazil. Our refusal to grant loans to <gloss target="#t_Petrobras1">Petrobras</gloss>, plus the campaign
                                    of our oil companies against it (I hear Standard is now burying
                                    the hatchet), has convinced a good many Brazilians that our <pb facs="0789" n="749" xml:id="pg_749"/> government is
                                    dominated by the “oil trust” and that the present squeeze on
                                    Brazil is really an effort to get our clutches on Brazil’s oil
                                    resources. We have good reason to be chary of direct loans, but
                                    if New York private banks will lend to <gloss target="#t_PEMEX1">PEMEX</gloss>, why shouldn’t the Inter-American Bank with
                                    our blessing lend to <gloss target="#t_Petrobras1">Petrobras</gloss>, which never expropriated any of our
                                    property? On the positive side, this would help to solve a very
                                    important balance of payments problem and, depending on how
                                    clearly we were willing to show our hand, would be a good
                                    refutation of many of the most damaging nationalist arguments
                                    against us.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item><p>While opposing balance of payments loans under present
                                        circumstances, it seems to me that we should be willing to
                                        make sound development loans. I understand none are now
                                        pending, but I imagine this is because the Brazilian
                                        Government thinks it would be rebuffed if it asked for one.
                                        Considering the immense needs of this country for
                                        development and the many sound projects on which money might
                                        be spent, it seems to me inadvisable for us to sulk while
                                        the situation in Brazil, and their relations with us,
                                        deteriorate. I do not think we should intervene in Brazil’s
                                        internal financial affairs as we inevitably would in
                                        connection with a balance of payments loan—and get all the
                                        blame for anything that went wrong. I do think, however,
                                        that it is essential that we should continue to identify
                                        ourselves with sound Brazilian development, since
                                        practically all Brazilians are nuts on the subject. It seems
                                        to me most inadvisable to turn off the spigot for any length
                                        of time if only because, with Brazil’s heavy maturities,
                                        this would be draining dollars rapidly out of Brazil.</p>
                                    <p>In this connection a particularly suitable project would be
                                        the development of the additional units for the <persName corresp="#p_PEA1">Peixoto</persName> Power Project. I
                                        understand that there is likely to be a power shortage in
                                        the area unless this is done, since Furnas will not be ready
                                        as soon as these additional <persName corresp="#p_PEA1">Peixoto</persName> units might be. In view of the large
                                        component of dollar equipment, the inflationary impact of
                                        this would be relatively minor. We would presumably insist
                                        on formal assurances that no further expropriation of
                                        American Foreign Power properties be
                                    contemplated.</p></item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item><p>If the Brazilian concept of <gloss target="#t_OPA1">OPA</gloss> is merely a technical plan drawn up with
                                        our help for the multilateral development of the Latin
                                        American republics, then it seems to me we can scarcely
                                        refuse it our positive support—we have warbled too often
                                        publicly of the high regard we have for <gloss target="#t_OPA1">OPA</gloss>. In fact, if that is all
                                        that is involved, surely we should sound as enthusiastic as
                                        possible rather than as defensive as possible. If, however,
                                        this is just the first step towards getting us sucked in,
                                        then we might refer blandly to the Inter-American Bank and
                                        the proposed International Development Association as new
                                        sources for financing projects. Our gold outflow, of course,
                                        puts us in a <pb facs="0790" n="750" xml:id="pg_750"/>
                                        stronger position to resist pressures, but so long as we
                                        continue to foot the budget deficits of Nationalist China,
                                        Korea, Vietnam, Jordan, etc., we cannot expect our Latino
                                        friends to be happy at getting nothing but loans at a high
                                        rate of interest. (I don’t favor grant aid except through PL
                                        480, but I do think we should lower interest rates to the
                                        point that <gloss target="#t_EXIMBANK1">Exim</gloss>
                                        operates as an instrument of national policy rather than a
                                        lush banking operation.)</p>
                                    <p>The Brazilians assert that <gloss target="#t_OPA1">OPA</gloss> is more political than economic, and are
                                        resentful of what they consider our negotiation attitude. We
                                        must of course resist signing a blank check for financing
                                        development and also to my mind anything too reminiscent of
                                        the old Mixed Commission, to which the Brazilians look back
                                        nostalgically. It seems to me on this account the more
                                        important to find out what the Brazilians want and take a
                                        friendly position attitude on all of the specific proposals
                                        that we endorse. Insofar as I have been able to get any
                                        positive information as to what <gloss target="#t_OPA1">OPA</gloss> envisages, it would seem to me to be
                                        precisely what we have been trying to do for years, with
                                        only a reservation re the financing we can make
                                        available.</p></item>
                                <label>(6)</label>
                                <item>To refute nationalist allegations re the alleged lush profits,
                                    remittances, etc., of American business in Brazil, we need the
                                    figures— and I hope they won’t show that the Nationalists are
                                    right. Herb May, our Treasury Attaché, has requested data from
                                    Washington, and I hope <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss> can
                                    insist that we be sent the essential facts.<note n="8" xml:id="d278fn8">Neither <persName corresp="#p_MHK1">May</persName>’s request nor the reply has been found
                                        in Department of State files.</note></item>
                                <label>(7)</label>
                                <item>We should surely make the local currency derived from PL 480
                                    sales available to Brazil and every other Latin American country
                                    for development on a grant rather than a reimbursable basis.
                                    This would in an immediate sense cost the American taxpayers
                                    nothing; on a long term basis the amount the taxpayer may
                                    recover is problematical, particularly now that the maintenance
                                    of value clause has been abolished. Why not get credit for what
                                    we are in fact doing? Moreover, we are making PL 480 local
                                    currency grants to such countries as India; I cannot too
                                    strongly emphasize that I think this further evidence of
                                    discrimination between the third force,
                                        <persName>Johnny</persName>-come-lately countries and our
                                    tried and true friends in Latin America is inexcusable and
                                    intolerable. Here is a field in which we can help Latin American
                                    development without affecting in the slightest our balance of
                                    payments problem.</item>
                                <label>(8)</label>
                                <item>While a solution for Brazil’s basic coffee problems must
                                    remain her own, we might help them and secure credit for
                                    ourselves by offering to cooperate with them in a comprehensive,
                                    scientific study of all kinds of possible uses of this product.
                                    I feel it would be essential to have this a strictly cooperative
                                    project in order that no suspicion might exist in Brazilian
                                    minds that this was a cover of the development of <pb facs="0791" n="751" xml:id="pg_751"/> synthetic coffee. If
                                    properly played, it would presumably be a psychological boost to
                                    the Brazilians as an indication of our interest in their
                                    problems.</item>
                                <label>(9)</label>
                                <item>In connection with the readjustment of sugar quotas, it would
                                    seem to me appropriate to act favorably on Brazil’s request for
                                    an increase of its quota,<note n="9" xml:id="d278fn9">The
                                        Brazilian request for a sugar quota increase was not further
                                        identified. Brazil ordinarily did not have a quota but after
                                        the President cut back the Cuban quota pursuant to Public
                                        Law 86–592, approved July 6, 1960 (74 <gloss target="#t_Stat1">Stat.</gloss> 330), 100,347 tons of
                                        the Cuban quota for 1960 was reassigned to Brazil. For
                                        additional information, see <hi rend="italic">Congressional
                                            Quarterly Almanac</hi>, 1961 (Washington, 1961), vol.
                                        XVII, p. 126.</note> considering the increase in Brazilian
                                    production, its substantial stocks, and the state of our
                                    relations with Cuba. I imagine that the Department may be
                                    considering alternative sources of sugar supplies in the event
                                    that a full-dress show-down with Cuba should occur.</item>
                                <label>(10)</label>
                                <item>The possibilities for increased technical assistance and
                                    special programs are enormous. Brazil is awakening in the need
                                    for accelerating industrial technical development and realizes
                                    that her educational system needs revising from top to bottom.
                                    We could make a grand gesture by making loans for both technical
                                    training and limited amounts of scientific and teaching
                                    equipment, including publications. A considerable amount of
                                    cruzeiros from PL 480 could be applied to construction of school
                                    buildings.</item>
                                <label>(11)</label>
                                <item>Dramatic assistance in advanced fields of scientific and/or
                                    military technology might well be considered. Assistance might
                                    be given in the form of, e.g., a large atomic energy plant, a
                                    large astronomic observatory, a cancer research center,
                                    fertilizer plants, etc.</item>
                                <label>(12)</label>
                                <item>With reference to the proposed world-wide program for
                                    improving community water systems, perhaps a special case for
                                    this program, as it applies in Brazil, would accelerate its
                                    approval and serve a useful purpose in Brazil.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>This is a horribly long letter for which I apologize, but I did wish to
                            place before you a rounded picture of the situation as I see it after
                            four months here. I have addressed this letter to you personally to be
                            certain you saw it, but I have no objections to its being circulated as
                            you see fit, and I have had it made up with that thought in mind. I do
                            hope it will be helpful to you.</p>
                        <p>With warmest good wishes of the Season,</p>
                        <p>Very sincerely,</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_CJM1"><hi rend="strong">John M.
                                        Cabot</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>