<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>297. Telegram From the Embassy in Brazil to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d297</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">297</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1960-10-07T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-10-07T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-10-07T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-10-07T17:00:00-05:00" n="297"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d297">
                <head>297. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Brazil</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d297fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 732.11/10–660. Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Rio de Janeiro</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-10-07T19:00:00-03:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 7, 1960—7 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>478. With election of <persName corresp="#p_QJS1">Janio Quadros</persName> as
                    next President of Brazil virtually assured, believe we should begin laying
                    groundwork for effective cooperation with his administration during vital 5
                    years which lie ahead. In this connection we should be able derive advantage
                    from fact that, as happens only once every 20 years, newly-elected US
                    administration will be taking office at approximately same time as new Brazilian
                    Government, thus providing relatively clean slate on which to record forthcoming
                    phase of US–Brazil relations.</p>
                <p>Indications are that <persName corresp="#p_QJS1">Quadros</persName> plans take
                    round-world trip prior his inauguration January, including visit to US following
                    US elections. This would provide first major opportunity for serious discussion
                    US-Brazil relations with <persName corresp="#p_QJS1">Quadros</persName>, in
                    which we believe our own President-elect should play prominent role. We believe
                    moreover <persName corresp="#p_QJS1">Quadros</persName> should be invited visit
                    US as official guest US Government and should be treated in manner befitting his
                    importance to US and his undoubted personal sensitivity to US recognition that
                    importance.</p>
                <p>Embassy believes this important juncture US–Brazil relations is appropriate time
                    for thorough going reappraisal those relations, having in mind that forthcoming
                    5 years of <persName corresp="#p_QJS1">Quadros</persName> administration may
                    well be most important in history our relationship with Brazil. While Embassy
                    not undertaking at this point make specific suggestions this regard, believe one
                    essential element in any fruitful policy vis-à-vis Brazil must be recognition on
                    our part of Brazil’s preponderant importance in Latin America. Other side of
                    this coin would of course be acceptance on Brazil’s part of sobering
                    responsibilities which are concomitant of national power and leadership. Believe
                    time to put these points across, if we are prepared to do so, would be in early
                    discussion between <persName corresp="#p_QJS1">Quadros</persName> and US
                    President-elect.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_QJS1">Quadros</persName> victory, marking as it does end
                    of 30 years of rule by Vargas and his political heirs, can be expected result in
                    general house cleaning and extensive replacement incumbents at many levels
                        <gloss target="#t_GOB1">GOB</gloss> with <persName corresp="#p_QJS1"
                        >Quadros</persName> followers. While Vargas heir Goulart seems likely be
                    reelected Vice President, <persName corresp="#p_QJS1">Quadros</persName> can be
                    expected surround himself with advisors of his own choosing, whose attitudes on
                    problems of concern to US can have almost as important effect on US interest as
                    attitude of new President himself. This suggests importance of effort <pb
                        facs="0831" n="791" xml:id="pg_791"/> on US part to cultivate sympathy and
                    understanding such advisors through judicious use of leader grants and other
                    means. Embassy will submit recommendations this regard in later message.</p>
                <p>While Embassy not yet prepared make recommendations re precise form and timing of
                    US invitation to <persName corresp="#p_QJS1">Quadros</persName>, we earnestly
                    hope main burden this message can be given serious consideration in Department
                    and decision in principle re <persName corresp="#p_QJS1">Quadros</persName>
                    invitation taken in advance in order make possible prompt issuance when optimum
                    circumstances determined.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Cabot</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
