<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum Prepared in the Department of State
                    Drafted by Mr. Popper of the Division of
                        International Organization Affairs.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d103</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">103</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-10-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-10-10T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-10-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="103" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d103">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BD/10–1046</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum Prepared in the Department of State</hi>
                    <note n="27" xml:id="d103fn27">Drafted by Mr. Popper of the Division of
                        International Organization Affairs.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-10-10">October 10,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">Draft</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Remarks of Mr. Leroy Stinebower<note n="28" xml:id="d103fn28">Leroy D. Stinebower, Special Assistant to the Assistant Secretary of State
                        for Economic Affairs (Thorp), also serving at New York as United States
                        Deputy Representative on the Economic and Social Council.</note> at
                    Membership Team Meeting October 10, 11:00 a.m.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stinebower, who had returned from New York a few days previously, discussed
                    with the Membership Team his recollection of the events which had taken place in
                    the process of reaching an agreement with the other members of the <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss> preparatory to the election of the
                    members of 8 Commissions by the Council.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stinebower stressed the fact that final agreement was reached after Mr.
                    Winant had talked directly with Mr. Acheson by telephone and had received
                    approval for raising the Soviet representation on the 6 original Commissions
                    from 13 to 14 states. Mr. Stinebower took the view that if there was any
                    dissatisfaction with the final results, it should be attributed to a failure to
                    keep Mr. Acheson adequately informed about the problem, as a result of which Mr.
                    Acheson took a decision which was not in accord with the instructions sent to
                    New York by the Membership Team.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stinebower also emphasized Mr. Winant’s desire to reach unanimous agreement
                    with the Soviets on the slates, as a desirable method of procedure and as a
                    method of possibly gaining sympathetic consideration by the Soviets for our plan
                    for an Economic Commission for Europe. The final agreement, Mr. Stinebower
                    stated came after a long evening session during which Mr. Winant negotiated with
                    the Soviets and the British. At that stage the Soviets were insisting on 15
                    Eastern European seats on the 6 original Commissions while our limit was 13
                    seats. Finally it was agreed to split the difference and give the Eastern
                    European bloc 14 seats. Since the Soviet representation on all 8 Commissions
                    thus rose to 19 seats it was considered necessary to raise the Latin American
                    representation 1 seat to preserve parity. Mr. Stinebower understood that the
                    concept of parity had been specifically accepted in these final negotiations. He
                    made the point <pb facs="0230" n="212" xml:id="pg_212"/> that the negotiators
                    linked together the seats allocated to the British Dominions and India and that
                    this total too reached 19 seats.<note n="29" xml:id="d103fn29">In a revised
                        memorandum drafted October 11 Mr. Popper wrote, following this paragraph:
                        “When the Soviets continued to insist on giving still another seat to the
                        Byelo-Russian <gloss target="#t_SSR1">SSR</gloss>, we indicated that our
                        absolute maximum allotment for the Eastern group was 19 seats for 8
                        Commissions. We said that if the Soviets wanted an additional seat for
                        Byelo-Russia, they would have to reduce the representation of some other
                        Eastern state. Eventually the Soviets acquiesced, but this necessitated a
                        considerable reshuffling of seats involving both the Eastern group and other
                        countries.” (501.BD/10–1146)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Stinebower further stated that no member of the Council appeared to be
                    aggrieved at the result of the elections except Greece, which had only one seat
                    as compared with two for Lebanon. He commented on the fact that there was no
                    sizable dissatisfaction among the four Latin American members of the Council,
                    who had demanded a total of 22 seats for the Latin American states. He also
                    explained the loss of Liberia on the ground that the Big Three considered it was
                    too backward to form [<hi rend="italic">perform</hi>] its responsibilities on
                    any Commission.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stinebower explained the inclusion of Poland on the Economic and Employment
                    Commission but noted that the Soviets had insisted on this concession as a
                    prerequisite for unanimity. He indicated that Mr. Acheson had approved by
                    telephone the addition of Poland on this Commission as the additional Soviet
                    seat.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stinebower further declared that it proved important [<hi rend="italic">impossible</hi>] to leave any Commission seat vacant in order to save them
                    for Sweden, which is not yet a member of the United Nations. Finally, he noted
                    that reaching unanimity it was possible to keep countries off the Commissions
                    when we did not wish them seated. In this connection he mentioned specifically
                    how difficult it was to keep the Dominican Republic representative, Miss
                    Bernardino, off the Commission on the Status of Women.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
