<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-12-06T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-12-06T19:00:00-05:00" n="246" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d246">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">501.AA/12–646: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Acting United States Representative at the
                                United Nations</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-12-06T19:00:00-05:00">December
                                    6, 1946—7 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>309. <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USdel</gloss>. In connection with telegram
                            No. 305 dated December 5, Department believes that the position you take
                            with respect to the timing of a decision by the Council on the Siamese
                            application should be guided by wishes of Siamese delegation and your
                            opinion as to the most opportune moment for favorable action.</p>
                        <p>Prince Wan informed Kenneth Landon of <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss><note n="56" xml:id="d246fn56">The Assistant Chief of
                                the Division of Southeast Asian Affairs.</note> on December 2nd that
                            he was prepared to ask the Council to defer consideration of the Siamese
                            application should this be necessary to avoid a Russian veto at the
                            present time. He stated further that he was prepared to do this because
                            of his confidence that the Russians would, in due course, withdraw any
                            opposition they may now have to Siamese application.</p>
                        <p>We do not wish to do anything which would embarrass or prejudice Siamese
                            opportunity to become a member of U.N. Accordingly, unless Prince Wan
                            wishes, US should not press for immediate <gloss target="#t_SC2">SC</gloss> consideration if it is anticipated that admission will
                            be blocked by a veto.</p>
                        <p>If we receive further information re Russian recognition of Siam, we will
                            inform you immediately by telephone.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>