<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Senator Austin to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d266</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">266</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-11-21T22:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-11-21T22:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF2jh59vGhjZ2KX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="recVanxJ0yM3HzUcM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037333"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Devaluation</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budgets</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-11-21T22:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-11-21T22:30:00-05:00" n="266"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d266">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Summaries/11–2146: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Senator <persName type="from">Austin</persName> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-11-21T22:30:00-05:00"
                            >November 21, 1946—10:30 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">[via Courier]</p>
                <p>836. <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> Secret Summary.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of several matters taking up the attention of the
                    General Assembly and the United States Delegation.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Committee V, Subcommittee on Contributions</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">2nd Meeting</hi>)</p>
                <p>At a continuation of the general debate on November 21, Turkey<note n="7"
                        xml:id="d266fn7">Mr. Sukru Esmer was the Turkish Member on the Fifth
                        Committee; the Alternate Member was Mr. A. Birden.</note> requested the
                    Subcommittee to review the Turkish quota in view of the recent devaluation of
                    Turkish currency and its consequent adverse effect on Turkish ability to secure
                    foreign exchange.</p>
                <p>St. Laurent<note n="8" xml:id="d266fn8">The Right Honorable Louis S.
                        Saint-Laurent, Canadian Secretary of State for External Affairs and Head of
                        the Canadian Delegation to the General Assembly (not one of the regular
                        Canadian members of the Committee).</note> (Canada) opened the discussion,
                    stating that Canada had no quarrel with the criteria which the Committee on
                    Contributions had used in defining “capacity to pay.” With respect to
                    Vandenberg’s statement at the opening meeting, St. Laurent reasserted the
                    Canadian view that relative per capita contribution was fundamental. If other
                    criteria than “capacity to pay” were considered, Canada would have to put its
                    case as strongly as possible to prevent less fortunate nations from having to
                    pay a higher per capita rate than the U.S.</p>
                <p>Geraschenko urged the Subcommittee to consider the substance of Vandenberg’s
                    arguments, and on the basis of its discussions to see whether or not something
                    had to be done to meet U. S. demands.</p>
                <p>The Soviet delegate recommended that the quotas of new members and the requests
                    of member nations, except the U. S., for the lowering of quotas be referred to
                    the Contributions Committee. Geraschenko (U.S.S.R.) declared that the
                    Subcommittee could come to no solution of its problems if it confined itself to
                    discussing the establishment of a ceiling. Vandenberg, he said, had suggested a
                    25 per cent ceiling for the U.S., but it might as well have been 33⅓ per cent,
                    or 40 per cent, and any discussion of an arbitrary ceiling would be academic.
                    Geraschenko rejected the Canadian per capita principle, the consideration of
                    contributions as a form of international taxation, and asserted that national
                    revenue as well as the national budgets should be used in establishing capacity
                    to pay.</p>
                <p>The Polish delegate<note n="9" xml:id="d266fn9">The Polish Member was Mr. Juliusz
                        Katz-Suchy; the Alternate Member was Mr. Aleksander Bramson.</note> asserted
                    that he appreciated that the U.S. position had been engendered by high
                    principles and not through a desire to save money, but that Poland would have to
                    oppose any attempt to establish ceilings at this time. He felt it was premature
                        <pb facs="0503" n="485" xml:id="pg_485"/> even to try to settle when
                    ceilings might go into effect. When peacetime economics had been restored, he
                    continued, quotas would have to be revised and due consideration given to
                    “capacity to pay” and per capita contributions. The Polish delegate then urged
                    lowering Poland’s quota.</p>
                <p>Pitblado (U. K.) asserted that to establish ceilings at this time would be an
                    arbitrary action taken in a period of changing conditions. He agreed that the
                    decision on the quotas of new members and appeals for lowering of quotas, except
                    that of the U. S., should be referred to the Contributions Committee.</p>
                <p>The U. S. request, he asserted, differed from other questions facing the
                    Subcommittee in that it was essentially political. Although under ideal
                    conditions no one would like to see so large a proportion of the UN costs
                    assigned to one nation, the U. K. position remained substantially as it had been
                    stated in Committee V.</p>
                <p>Pitblado said he had no very constructive proposals to suggest, but he reminded
                    the Subcommittee that in February the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> had
                    stated that if a ceiling were imposed it should not be one that seriously
                    obscured the relationship between contributions and capacity to pay.</p>
                <p>With respect to the U. S. assertion that all nations in the UN had certain
                    influence and responsibilities and that these should not necessarily be related
                    to “capacity to pay,” Pitblado reminded the Subcommittee that no nation could
                    escape consideration of the public opinion factor. Referring to the matter of
                    foreign exchange, Pitblado reminded the Subcommittee that the U. K. was well
                    aware of the difficulties of procuring it in terms of added effort at production
                    and reduction of goods for home consumption.</p>
                <p>China<note n="10" xml:id="d266fn10">Dr. C. L. Hsia was the Chinese Member on the
                        Fifth Committee: Mr. J. C. Pao was the Alternate Member.</note> opposed
                    consideration of support of the UN as a form of international taxation rather
                    than as national contributions. China recognized the justice of the U. S.
                    request for a reduction in its quota because the request stemmed from an
                    unselfish desire to give strong support to the UN. The Chinese delegate then
                    suggested that the principle of sovereign equality might be applied to the
                    smaller administrative budget and “capacity to pay” to the larger operational
                    budgets.</p>
                <p>The French delegate<note n="11" xml:id="d266fn11">The French Member was M.
                        Jacques Rueff; the Alternate Member was M. Andre Ganem.</note> asserted that
                    he did not believe that the Subcommittee had the technical ability or the time
                    to fix a new scale of contributions. Although no one could disagree with the
                    justness and fairness of Vandenberg’s statement of principles, the French
                    delegate questioned whether the U. S. meant those principles to be practically
                    applied in relation to the 1947 budget. He pointed out that <pb facs="0504"
                        n="486" xml:id="pg_486"/> in his belief, Vandenberg, even in his statements
                    in Committee V, had not pressed for immediate adjustment, and that it was his
                    understanding that what the U. S. wanted at this time was a recognition that the
                    present U. S. contribution should not be a precedent.</p>
                <p>Two suggestions were put forward by the French delegate (1) that the Subcommittee
                    defer any discussion of the foreign exchange element until it received advice on
                    the results of Vandenberg’s discussions with the U.S. Secretary of the Treasury,
                    and (2) that the Subcommittee seriously consider Rueff’s (France) proposal in
                    Committee V that the Secretariat Fiscal Committee be requested for a
                    redefinition of “capacity to pay.”</p>
                <p>Speaking as Chairman and the representative of Mexico, Martinez-Cabanas<note
                        n="12" xml:id="d266fn12">Dr. Gustavo Martinez-Cabanas.</note> recalled that
                    only the matter of administrative budgets was before the Subcommittee. He also
                    pointed out that the <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>’s remarks on
                    establishing a floor on contributions, as well as a ceiling, would have to be
                    discussed. He expressed some doubt that contributions could be too closely
                    related to per capita income in view of the fact that quotas were essentially
                    based on national income.</p>
                <p>[Here follow other items of the summary.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Austin</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
