<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="359" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d359">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">811.24590/10–2546</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Chief of the Division of
                            British Commonwealth Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Richards</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                            Deputy Director of the Office of European Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Hickerson</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-10-21">October 21, 1946</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Attached is the New Zealand draft trusteeship agreement for Western Samoa as
                        now revised by the New Zealand Government. This revision was handed to Mr.
                        Hiss on Saturday.<note n="34" xml:id="d359fn34">On October 19 Mr. Reid,
                            First Secretary of the New Zealand Legation, had handed to Mr. Hiss an
                                <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> dated October 18 with the text
                            of a revised draft trusteeship agreement for Western Samoa and a
                            memorandum of comment on the draft, none printed except the excerpt in
                            the following footnote. Memorandum of conversation of October 19 between
                            Messrs. Hiss and Reid not printed.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <gloss target="#t_SPA1">SPA</gloss> is now preparing a “position paper” on
                        this revision and has asked for our comments on Article X (4) which is much
                        more general than what was originally proposed.<note n="35" xml:id="d359fn35">In the course of revision of the draft terms, Article
                            IX (3) of the original draft had become Article X (4) in the revised
                            draft. The revised text provided that the administering authority should
                            be entitled “to take all such other measures in accordance with the
                            purposes and principles of the Charter of the United Nations as are, in
                            the opinion of the administering authority necessary to the maintenance
                            of international peace and security and the defence of Western Samoa”
                            (890.0146/10–1846).</note> Mr. Reid told Mr. Hiss orally that his
                        Government felt that the original wording was too broad and that they “did
                        not want to invite other powers” to share too much in the use of defence
                        installations. He added, however, that his Government felt that they had
                        such friendly relations with the US that we should have no conflict over the
                        revised wording.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Arthur Richards</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>