<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-11-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="382" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d382">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">
                        <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Files: US/A/C.4/32</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. John Foster Dulles of the United States
                            Delegation</hi><note n="68" xml:id="d382fn68">Addressed to the Secretary
                            of State and Senator Austin.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                York</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-11-30">November 30, 1946</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr. Gerig and I dined with Messrs. Gromyko and Novikov on November 28th. They
                        said they wished to consider whether some formula could be found to permit
                        the Trusteeship Council to be established. They said that the two big
                        difficulties, and the only serious difficulties, were: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>Which were the “states directly concerned”; and</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>Could trust areas be fortified without the approval of the
                                Security Council.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>They stated as to (1) that it was the Soviet view that the five Permanent
                        Members need not necessarily be considered “states directly concerned” in
                        relation to <hi rend="italic">all</hi> trust territory; that there could be
                        a prior agreement between them that some would be deemed to be “states
                        directly concerned” with reference to certain trust territories and others
                        be deemed to be “states directly concerned” with reference to other trust
                        territories. They intimated that the Soviet Union was not particularly
                        interested in being considered a “state directly concerned” so far as the
                        African mandated territory was concerned, but that they stood absolutely on
                        the proposition that they were a “state directly concerned” in so far as
                        related to enemy territory, specifically the Italian colonies, any Japanese
                        islands and the Japanese mandated islands. There was a slight suggestion
                        that if that position was conceded, they might not even claim to be a “state
                        directly concerned” in Western Samoa and New Guinea.</p>
                    <p>We said that if the Soviet Union would not claim to be a “state directly
                        concerned” as regards the African mandated territory, its position would be
                        the same as that of the United States as regards these territories. We
                        suggested that the Trusteeship Council might be set up on the basis of trust
                        agreements with Great Britain, France and Belgium for African mandated
                        territory. They said that they would not be willing to agree not to be a
                        “state directly concerned” as regards the African territories, except as
                        part and parcel of an agreement that they were a “state directly concerned”
                        as regards other areas, notably the Pacific islands.</p>
                    <p>We said that instead of discussing which were and which were not “states
                        directly concerned” it might be useful to consider what practical
                        consequences the Soviet might want to draw from being a “state <pb facs="0709" n="691" xml:id="pg_691"/> directly concerned” in Pacific
                        islands. They said that their particular interest was in military
                        fortifications. It was their view that under the Charter there was no right
                        to fortify for <hi rend="italic">national</hi> purposes. There was a right
                        to local defense and the maintenance of order. Otherwise, the only right was
                        for <hi rend="italic">international</hi> peace and security and that the
                        only body which could administer international peace and security was the
                        Security Council. Therefore, there could be no fortification beyond the need
                        of local defense except in accordance with special agreements negotiated by
                        the Security Council under Article 43. They indicated that in this respect
                        they saw no difference between strategic and non-strategic areas.</p>
                    <p>They also referred to a continuing right in the Security Council to inspect
                        fortifications which might be authorized by the Security Council in trust
                        territory.</p>
                    <p>We said that we could not agree at all with their legal construction of the
                        Charter, but that it might be more profitable to consider the practical
                        aspects of the matter. The concrete result of their theory was that the
                        United States would not have the right to maintain bases in trusteed Pacific
                        islands except as might be specifically authorized in each case by the
                        Security Council, i.e., by Russia, and subject to its supervision and
                        inspection. I said that that result was not one which was acceptable to the
                        United States and that they could take it as absolutely positive that the
                        United States would not agree to any construction which would involve those
                        consequences. We said that the United States preferred trusteeship to
                        annexation or <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> possession because that would
                        give the native inhabitants the benefit of the Charter provisions with
                        respect to the inhabitants of trust territories. Also, trusteeship would
                        make it easier to move toward internationalization of military
                        establishments if and when the Security Council actually demonstrated that
                        it could be relied upon to maintain the peace. However, that had not yet
                        been demonstrated and until it was demonstrated, we would want in the
                        Pacific Islands the same rights that the Soviet Union would presumably
                        exercise in such islands as the Kuriles Islands. We said that the Soviet
                        Union had shown no disposition to accept for the Kuriles Islands the regime
                        which it was seeking to impose on us as regards Pacific islands which might
                        come under our administration.</p>
                    <p>They said that this was different because it had been agreed between the
                        United States and the Soviet Union that the latter could annex the Kuriles
                        Islands. We said that that was an informal agreement which had not yet been
                        ratified by peace treaty and that other nations than the United States were
                        concerned in this matter, notably China.</p>
                    <p>I said that it was personally my strong hope that neither the United <pb facs="0710" n="692" xml:id="pg_692"/> States nor the Soviet Union would
                        have advanced military bases or military zones which would menace each other
                        or other friendly nations. But that the United States would not agree to a
                        double standard under which the Soviet Union did not subject to Security
                        Council control areas in its possession which it deemed vital; whereas the
                        United States, as to comparable areas in its possession, would be subject to
                        control and inspection by the Soviet Union.</p>
                    <p>Messrs. Gromyko and Novikov affirmed strongly that, if necessary, the Soviet
                        would fight the issue through to the floor of the Assembly, and they
                        expressed confidence that they could defeat approval of trusteeship
                        agreements with provision for bases, etc.</p>
                    <p>While the discussion was extremely frank, the atmosphere throughout was
                        friendly and cordial and it was agreed that we would each think the matter
                        over to see whether there was any possible basis for agreement which would
                        permit of going ahead harmoniously on the trusteeship matter.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>