<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Notes on a Staff Conference of the United States Delegation to the Atomic
                    Energy Commission, New York, August 1, 1946, a.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d460</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">460</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-08-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-08-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft treaty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-08-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-08-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="460"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d460">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of State Atomic Energy Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Notes on a Staff Conference of the <gloss type="from">United
                            States Delegation</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Atomic Energy
                            Commission</gloss>, New York, August 1, 1946, a.m.</hi>
                    <note n="24" xml:id="d460fn24">Drafted by Lincoln Gordon.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1946-08-01">August 1, 1946</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <table rend="width: 50%" rendition="#center-block">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Present:</cell>
                        <cell>Mr. Bernard M. Baruch</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. John M. Hancock</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. F. Eberstadt</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. John Parks Davis</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Lincoln Gordon</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>This conference was preceded by a general discussion of the meeting of Committee
                    No. 2 on July 31<note n="25" xml:id="d460fn25">For the summary record of the 4th
                        Meeting of Committee 2, July 31, see <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>, I,
                            <hi rend="italic">Special Suppl.</hi>, pp. 123–128.</note> and the
                    problems raised by the reference to the Scientific Committee of the question of
                    the technical possibility of control of atomic energy and the most effective
                    means of carrying out such control. There was some speculation as to the
                    considerations which motivated Mr. Parodi in breaking into the discussion of the
                    Soviet proposal with his suggestion for this reference to the Scientific
                    Committee. Some concern was also expressed, particularly by Mr. Eberstadt, that
                    the discussions in the Scientific Committee <pb facs="0888" n="870"
                        xml:id="pg_870"/> might eventuate in a complaint that the United States was
                    impeding progress by withholding technical information necessary to an
                    understanding of proposed control measures.</p>
                <p>The conference then proceeded to a review of the present status of the work of
                    the Atomic Energy Commission and the desirable course of action in the immediate
                    future.</p>
                <p>Mr. Baruch stated emphatically that he felt that we have no real cause for
                    disappointment at the progress to date. He felt that we had come along as
                    quickly and as well as we should expect at this time.</p>
                <p>Our goal remains a unanimous report adopting the principles of the American Plan.
                    He said that no alternative to this goal is now under consideration and that no
                    member of the Delegation should suggest in any manner that any thought was being
                    given to alternatives.</p>
                <p>Mr. Baruch said that we must endeavor to draw out the Russians on their ideas as
                    fully as possible, and that we must avoid at all costs any humiliation of the
                    Russians—even to the extent, if necessary, of some personal humiliation to
                    ourselves. If any breach in the negotiations arises at a later date, it must not
                    originate with us, and we must make it crystal clear that we have explored every
                    possible avenue of agreement.</p>
                <p>Mr. Baruch also said that in his judgment our plan was generous and just, and
                    that we had the right as well as the power on our side. He saw no reason to
                    believe at this time that the Russians would not be brought around, when they
                    had had an opportunity for complete understanding of our proposals.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hancock then outlined four lines along which he thought work should progress.
                    They were as follows: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Continuing Educational Work</hi> to attain complete
                            understanding of the American proposals among the other Delegations.
                            This should include a much more detailed explanation than had as yet
                            been given of the considerations which led the Lilienthal Board members
                            to the conclusions in the Acheson-Lilienthal report. He suggested the
                            possibility of talks by Dr. Oppenheimer, Mr. Charles Thomas and General
                            Groves to joint sessions of the scientific and political delegates. Mr.
                            Eberstadt suggested that we lay out a specific program for carrying out
                            this educational work. This will, of course, have to be preceded by
                            clarification of the effect of Section 10 of the McMahon Act.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Informal Contacts with Other Delegations</hi>. Mr.
                            Hancock noted that members of our staff had been making increasingly
                            useful contacts with staff members of the other Delegations. He felt
                            that there was a need for systematic informal discussion at frequent
                            intervals with the heads of other Delegations by the heads of our
                            Delegation. Mr. Eberstadt suggested that a regular timetable be
                            developed for this purpose, so that we are sure that no Delegation is
                            overlooked.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Treaty Drafting</hi>. Work is already under way on the
                            early stages <pb facs="0889" n="871" xml:id="pg_871"/> of drafting a
                            treaty incorporating the American proposals, under the supervision of
                            Mr. Fahy. Mr. Hancock suggested that Professor Manley Hudson might
                            usefully be brought into this work. There was no decision on this
                            point.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Stages</hi>. The elaboration of the stages in which
                            the American plan would be implemented is a major substantive task for
                            the Delegation at this time. Mr. Hancock felt that it may be desirable
                            to develop our proposal on stages as part of the draft treaty. Mr.
                            Eberstadt suggested that a Working Committee including Dr. Oppenheimer
                            (or Dr. Bacher) and Messrs. Fahy, Volpe and Gordon devote a period of
                            two weeks of concentrated effort to this problem, developing a
                            memorandum for further consideration by the Delegation.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
