<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-10-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="497" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d497">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">501.<gloss target="#t_BC1">BC</gloss>
                        Atomic/10–2446</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Fred Searls, Jr.</persName>, of
                            the United States Delegation to the Atomic Energy Commission, to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-10-24">October 24,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: You will have heard from Mr.
                        Baruch, who has also reported to the President, the status of negotiations
                        within <pb facs="0982" n="964" xml:id="pg_964"/> the Atomic Energy
                        Commission and the high lights of efforts that have been made during your
                        absence. No doubt, you have already formed some opinion as to the degree of
                        success likely to attend further attempts at a unanimous agreement to a
                        treaty, or recommendations to the Security Council.</p>
                    <p>It is assumed very generally indeed, not only by Mr. Wallace and the
                        Communist-scientist group, but by almost everyone else who has spoken or
                        written on “The Atomic Bomb,” that failure to reach an agreement by the
                        Atomic Energy Commission or some other creature of the United Nations, means
                        acceleration of an atomic armament race, which most—but not all—of the
                        writers and speakers believe will lead to war. Laurence of California,<note n="1" xml:id="d497fn1">Presumably Ernest O. Lawrence of the University
                            of California, inventor of the cyclotron and participant in Manhattan
                            Engineer District.</note> who is one of the realists, suggests that if
                        the Russians do not soon agree, we should increase production of fissionable
                        material, speed up the program for bases and B–36 planes, and in effect give
                        notice that <hi rend="italic">we</hi> are the future police force of the
                        Security Council.</p>
                    <p>However, my efforts in trying to assist Mr. Baruch have been chiefly in the
                        field of “raw materials” and the contacts I have had with the Russians,
                        particularly with Alexandrov,<note n="2" xml:id="d497fn2">Mr. S. P.
                            Alexandrov, Adviser, Soviet Delegation to the Atomic Energy
                            Commission.</note> and with the Manhattan District activities, convince
                        me that there is perhaps another, less openly belligerent route that we can
                        follow—indeed are following—which, if handled with great wisdom and not made
                        subject to interference by radicals, can accomplish years of delay in
                        competitive atomic weapon production, even if the Atomic Energy Commission
                        fails of agreement.</p>
                    <p>This procedure of growing importance lies in the field of continuation and
                        stimulation of preclusive and cooperative contracting in the field of raw
                        materials, particularly, of course, of the ores of uranium and thorium but
                        also of some other metals.</p>
                    <p>I know that, as a member of the Combined Policy Committee,<note n="3" xml:id="d497fn3">See footnote 14, <ref target="#pg_1205">p.
                            1205</ref>.</note> you are familiar with the May 13th and previous
                        agreements and, generally speaking, with the activities of the Combined
                        Development Trust.<note n="4" xml:id="d497fn4">See footnote 15, <ref target="#pg_1205">p. 1205</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>These activities have been of great importance but, if the Atomic Energy
                        Commission fails, it appears to me that they may become of surpassing
                        importance. It is, therefore, of the very greatest interest that they shall
                        remain in the most competent hands.</p>
                    <p>The attitude, questions, desires, and general behavior of the Russians, of
                        which I can give you details, support intelligence reports of declarations
                        by Alexandrov at Bikini of the lack by them of workable high-grade deposits,
                        and references to their consequent feverish activity in development of
                        processes for treatment of their abundant very <pb facs="0983" n="965" xml:id="pg_965"/> low-grade ore. It now seems to me that it may well be
                        ten years before they can become possessed of an adequate supply, if we can
                        prevent their obtaining it from other countries. Ten years may well mean
                        everything in relations with the Russians since, surely, it is only a
                        question of time before internal opinions will force a change in their
                        government’s behavior to its own people and to foreign nations.</p>
                    <p>What I am afraid of is that this most delicate and important series of
                        negotiations will fall into the wrong hands. So far, I think it has been
                        very well done; but if the Atomic Energy Commission fails, it will need to
                        be expanded wisely and promptly, particularly in the thorium field, and
                        particularly in Asia and the East Indies. It is for this reason that I asked
                        Donald Russell<note n="5" xml:id="d497fn5">Donald S. Russell, Assistant
                            Secretary of State for Administration.</note> to send Bain of the
                        Manhattan District with the delegation to the London Tin Conference.</p>
                    <p>It will be a tragedy if, just at the time this activity needs the greatest
                        care and wise expansion, it becomes a bureaucratic prize, or subject to
                        change of policy and public criticism or even knowledge because of
                        ideological theories. This can easily happen, and probably will happen, if
                        wrong appointments are made to the commission created by the McMahon Bill.
                        As you doubtless know, the transfers agreed to by the Combined Policy
                        Committee by the compromise agreement of May 13th have been held up until
                        the new commission is appointed and acts. It is certain, even required, that
                        the new commission will have “cognizance” (in the naval sense of the word)
                        of all of the Combined Trust’s activities, even in dealing with foreign
                        countries.</p>
                    <p>Nothing has been made quite so clear in the discussions of the Atomic Energy
                        Commission as that no nation is willing to surrender actual ownership of
                        deposits of these ores. With the possible exception of the United States, it
                        is, I believe, indisputable now that all nations will vigorously resist any
                        attempt to have an international agency actually take over ownership and
                        operation of such deposits. One by one, the delegations of Canada, Brazil,
                        Australia, France, United Kingdom, and China have expressed their relief at
                        our willingness to depart in this respect from the original proposals of the
                        Acheson-Lilienthal report. There is clearly distinguishable to anyone now
                        engaged in the metal business, a new interest and growing determination on
                        the part of all nations to regard as essential to sovereignty all metal
                        deposits—not only metals with the very high atomic numbers—but all metals.
                        As C. K. Leith<note n="6" xml:id="d497fn6">Charles K. Leith, a United States
                            trustee, Combined Development Trust.</note> says, there is little metal
                        crossing the water these days, save by government action or, at least, with
                        government approval.</p>
                    <p>The most stubborn advocate of international ownership of atomic energy ores
                        has been Lilienthal. If surrounded and encouraged by other left-wingers … ,
                        I think we can probably fold up the newborn <pb facs="0984" n="966" xml:id="pg_966"/> hope that little by little we can draw other nations
                        in with the United States, the United Kingdom, and Canada, to form a group
                        that will control atomic energy through possession of such an overwhelming
                        proportion of the raw materials, that those nations left without the circle
                        must pay the price of admission—real arrangements for permanent peace—or,
                        failing that, realize that they will be hopelessly behind in an atomic
                        energy race for many years to come.</p>
                    <p>I do not say that this is a permanent solution. There is too much uranium and
                        thorium available for that. But it may well provide a delay of many years
                        beyond the date, at which the Russians can make an atomic bomb or two. I am
                        convinced they already know how to make them, and that they are bending
                        every effort to get the material for many of them; but if the work initiated
                        by the District and furthered by the Trust is let alone and wisely handled,
                        it could provide the way to peace.</p>
                    <p>And it may be wise to include certain other metals in such a program. There
                        are several others important in the peaceful application of atomic energy;
                        and there are others still that will be needed, beyond the limits of
                        stockpiles plus production, when the next war comes. In view of the growing
                        importance of raw materials, it would be well if one member of the new
                        commission were a man like Leith or some younger man, approved by Groves,
                        who is experienced and informed on this subject.</p>
                    <p>It is not evident that Mr. Baruch has so far been successful in exercising
                        influence in the choice of the members of the new commission and, while my
                        fears may be founded on rumor, I think the importance warrants the anxiety.
                        Could you yet get Baruch another hearing, or intervene yourself, or, if it
                        is too late for that, could you get a Presidential edict, to which the
                        appointees must accede before their appointment, which would be so worded as
                        to leave this raw material program heading up to you and Patterson and
                        Forrestal? If something is not done, I fear we may throw away one of our
                        best approaches to the solution of an important segment of the world’s
                        difficulties.</p>
                    <p>Respectfully,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Fred Searls, Jr.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>