<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-11-22T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-11-22T09:00:00-05:00" n="536" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d536">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">
                        <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Files</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Twenty-fifth Meeting of the United States
                            Delegation, New York, Hotel Pennsylvania, November 22, 1946, 9 a.m.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-11-22T09:00:00-05:00">November 22, 1946, 9 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>[Here follow a list of persons (29) present, consideration of another
                        subject, and discussion of the Soviet resolution on reporting by United
                        Nations members of their troops on non-enemy territory.]</p>
                    <p>Mr. Cohen said that the Secretary’s view was that it was advisable to support
                        a merger of the two questions, making it clear that we did not want to delay
                        disclosures of the number of our troops.<note n="96" xml:id="d536fn96">The
                            merger under reference was proposed by British Foreign Secretary Bevin
                            at the 25th Meeting of the First Committee on November 21; in regard to
                            that meeting, see the memorandum of telephone conversation by Hiss, and
                            footnote 89, <ref target="#pg_1031">p. 1031</ref>.</note> That is, the
                        United States should support consideration of the two items together but it
                        should also vote for fairly prompt disclosure of the information requested
                        in a matter of thirty or sixty days or some such time.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Dulles inquired whether when the Delegation voted on the Bevin
                        resolution, that meant that we would disclose or would not disclose the
                        number of our troops abroad. Senator Connally said that it was simply a
                        question of discussing disarmament in the course of the debate and that some
                        resolutions would certainly be brought in but that there were none before
                        the Committee yet.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Dulles said that he thought it was all right to support the Bevin
                        resolution if it was made clear that we will make the disclosures of the
                        location of our troops whether the Bevin resolution passed or not. He said
                        that the Soviets were of the opinion that our troops were scattered around
                        the world engaged in some nefarious activities. <pb facs="1058" n="1040" xml:id="pg_1040"/> This was another kind of Soviet trap. The United
                        Kingdom wanted to be evasive about giving this information. If we went along
                        with them it would make us parties to the evasion. The alternative was to go
                        along with the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics against the United
                        Kingdom. If we went along with the Bevin resolution it should be made clear
                        that we would none the less report on the presence of our troops abroad.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Cohen said that he thought that he had made it clear that the Secretary’s
                        position was that we should support considering the two items
                        simultaneously, that is, the resolution on reporting and the discussion of
                        disarmament. It should be made clear that we did not want to delay the
                        prompt disclosure of the troops abroad. Mr. Dulles observed that the
                        reporting might be delayed unless the date for giving the information were
                        set. Mr. Cohen pointed [out] that if the Bevin resolution were passed it
                        amounted to considering the two agenda items, the report on the number of
                        troops and disarmament, as one item. Mr. Fahy pointed out that the
                        discussions might be held together but that the problems could be separated
                        when it came to voting.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Yost<note n="97" xml:id="d536fn97">Charles W. Yost, Adviser, United
                            States Delegation to the General Assembly.</note> observed that it was
                        likely that Manuilsky,<note n="98" xml:id="d536fn98">Dmitri Z. Manuilsky,
                            Minister for Foreign Affairs and Deputy Chairman of the Council of
                            People’s Commissars of the Ukraine; Chairman of the Ukrainian Delegation
                            to the General Assembly.</note> the Chairman, would push for a vote on
                        the Soviet resolution and he thought it likely that there might be a wrangle
                        over this question.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Sandifer said that he thought it was important that the point which Mr.
                        Cohen had made should be perfectly clear; our support of the Bevin motion
                        was with the understanding that it did not affect our position regarding the
                        prompt disclosure of our troops abroad. Mr. Dulles agreed that this was a
                        good idea.</p>
                    <p>Senator Austin said that he wished to poll the Delegation as where [<hi rend="italic">as to whether?</hi>] it supported the Bevin resolution for
                        merger of the two questions, at the same time serving notice we were ready
                        to disclose troops in the home territory and everywhere else.</p>
                    <p>Senator Connally said the matter should not be made contingent, for that
                        would give our hand away. Senator Austin said that he did not intend to make
                        the matter contingent and he restated the Delegation position to be that
                        this Delegation favored the merger of the resolution relating to information
                        regarding troops and that relating to disarmament to be accompanied by a
                        statement of our willingness to reveal the number of our troops abroad. This
                        position was unanimously approved by the Delegation.</p>
                    <p>[Here follow additional discussion of the troops question and discussion of
                        other subjects.]</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>