<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-12-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-12-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="565" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d565">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of State Atomic Energy Files</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the United States Representative on the
                            Atomic Energy Commission</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Baruch</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                York</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-12-08">December 8, 1946</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The Atomic Energy Commission has been given a definite task—in no mistakable
                        language—by the Assembly, on the suggestion of the Foreign Secretaries and,
                        originally, of the Chiefs of State.</p>
                    <p>The American representative on this Commission has made proposals aimed at
                        carrying out the duties of the Commission, regarding atomic energy, which
                        may well serve also to set a pattern for control of any other instrument of
                        mass destruction, or indeed for all instruments of war.</p>
                    <p>In the United Nations General Assembly’s Political and Security Committee,
                        discussions are taking place concerning atomic energy. The Atomic Energy
                        Commission is about to bring forward a report on its own work which,
                        necessarily is related to practically all of the points now being discussed
                        in the Political and Security Committee. The adoption, by the Political and
                        Security Committee, of specific resolutions relating to atomic energy, other
                        than one asking the Atomic Energy Commission to expedite its report, may
                        prejudice or even render impossible an unbiased report by the Commission,
                        since certain <pb facs="1108" n="1090" xml:id="pg_1090"/> of its members are
                        bound to be affected by their superiors now functioning in the General
                        Assembly.</p>
                    <p>No one knows exactly what some of the words in these proposed General
                        Assembly resolutions mean. Why pass them? Why not wait until the Atomic
                        Energy Commission has made its report. Passing oblique resolutions may
                        result in confusion and delay.</p>
                    <p>These declarations of principle should be referred to the Atomic Commission,
                        which is charged with responsibility for an authoritative plan to be placed
                        before the Security Council, while the General Assembly has only the right
                        of recommendations. The Atomic Energy Commission should not be impeded by
                        new and limiting instructions.</p>
                    <p>The American delegates are hampered more than others. We have not even had
                        the benefit of a full exchange of views between those who are dealing with
                        disarmament and those charged with atomic matters. There should be a close
                        and constant liaison between them.</p>
                    <p>As you may recall, I suggested at the time Stettinius was our representative,
                        that he, Winant, and I ought to discuss the subject of our duties. This you
                        did not believe wise at the time. In addition, I was instructed to keep out
                        of disarmament discussions, even though it was apparent such discussions
                        would be closely connected with atomic energy and other weapons of mass
                        destruction. The President, you and Senator Connally were especially
                        emphatic that I try to avoid the subject of disarmament in my atomic energy
                        actions.</p>
                    <p>I have not seen anything, so far, on disarmament, other than pious
                        resolutions. On the other hand, the Atomic Commission is in the midst of
                        preparing a definitive formula of action. But the program is bound to be
                        deteriorated by pressures from outside sources.</p>
                    <p>Therefore, I ask that instructions be issued to our representatives on the
                        Political and Security Committee, that all matters relating to atomic energy
                        be referred to the Commission organized to deal with the subject. Also, that
                        it be pointed out that if atomic energy is successfully dealt with in the
                        Commission—and I believe it may be—other categories of armaments can be
                        similarly treated.</p>
                    <p>What I ask for is support in the effort the President and you requested me to
                        direct, instead of permitting it to be submerged in a sea of words which,
                        unless canalized, will result only in harm, through obscurity and delay.</p>
                    <p>Delay is dangerous. Action is essential. I know that course has your warm
                        approval. The way to get action is to concentrate the efforts in the one
                        place where final responsibility exists. It is to that end that I address
                        this letter to you.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>B. M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Baruch</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>