<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-04-18T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-04-18T08:00:00-05:00" n="617" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d617">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">855.646/4–1846: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Belgium</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Brussels</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-04-18T14:00:00+01:00">April 18,
                                1946—2 p.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received 11:17 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>481. See Embassy’s telegram 465, April 16, 6 p.m.<note n="55" xml:id="d617fn55">Not printed.</note> Replying to my question Foreign
                            Minister<note n="56" xml:id="d617fn56">Paul-Henri Spaak.</note>
                        yesterday expressed increasing anxiety concerning possible cross questioning
                        on subject of disposition of uranium resources of the Belgian Congo. He
                        stated that Lalmand, Communist Minister of Food had, at a recent Cabinet
                        meeting, questioned the Minister of Economic Affairs on the subject of
                        uranium. M. Deveze had replied evasively, as had Spaak, but temporizing
                        could not be prolonged indefinitely. The Minister assured me, however, that
                        he would take no steps prior to consultation with British Ambassador and
                        myself.</p>
                    <p>I think [we] should recognize that sources of uranium ores are naturally of
                        world-wide interest, including much guessing on the part of the press. Also
                        that any nation which possesses such deposits will be the object of envy by
                        others. This may result in the popular mind placing an enhanced or
                        fictitious value upon such resources. From the above it follows that the
                        force of public opinion may demand answers to questions as to how their
                        government proposes to handle such assets. In addition there will always
                        exist the likelihood that other nations may inspire such inquiries designed
                        either to gain information or to cause embarrassment.</p>
                    <p>As local newspapers are devoting more space to the Congo and its
                        potentialities, and as questioning within the Cabinet has begun, it seems to
                        me we should in consultation with British formulate our line of action. I
                        feel that at some point it will be best policy to be honest and with
                        concurrence of both Belgians and British to announce frankly <pb facs="1256" n="1234" xml:id="pg_1234"/> what has been agreed to and why.<note n="57" xml:id="d617fn57">For text of the Memorandum of Agreement Regarding
                            Control of Uranium between the United States, the United Kingdom, and
                            Belgium, September 26, 1944, see <ref target="frus1944v02#pg_1029">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 1029</ref>.</note> It may be
                        preferable to have Belgians take initiative in any such announcement.</p>
                    <p>My main point is that the disclosure of our agreement may be forced by events
                        and I suggest we should have a definite plan to forestall criticism. Perhaps
                        the Acheson report on atomic energy,<note n="58" xml:id="d617fn58">See the
                            letter from the Secretary of State’s Committee on Atomic Energy to the
                            Secretary of State, March 17, <ref target="#pg_761">p. 761</ref>, and
                            footnote 90 thereto.</note> which is not yet available to me, may
                        contain features providing us an easy and frank solution. In any case I
                        recommend the problem be studied to determine (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                        what degree of secrecy is still required and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the
                        question of timing if any announcement is to be made and by whom.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Kirk</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>