<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Transatlantic Telephone Conversation, by the Chief of the
                    Division of Commercial Policy ( (Brown))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d690</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">690</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-08-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-08-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-08-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-08-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="690"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d690">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">560.AL./8–246</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Transatlantic Telephone Conversation, by the
                        Chief of the Division of Commercial Policy</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Brown</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-08-02">August 2,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Peterson<note n="82" xml:id="d690fn82">Mr. Avery Peterson, First Secretary of
                        the American Embassy at London.</note> called to say that the British would
                    not give any decision as to the inclusion of Norway, Chile and Lebanon before
                    August 7 and as to the distribution of the Charter before August 9. He said he
                    thought so far as the first was concerned the decision would be favorable, but
                    with regard to the second he thought the British would decide it was an unwise
                    thing to do at this time.</p>
                <p>I told Mr. Peterson I would consult with Mr. Wilcox and cable him our reaction
                    immediately but that I thought we would probably decide <pb facs="1363" n="1341"
                        xml:id="pg_1341"/> to go ahead with the distribution. We had made our plans
                    for discussion of the Charter with a number of countries and wanted them to have
                    time to consider it before the talks; we also planned to hold a meeting in
                    Washington, before the October 15 meeting, of all the Government officials who
                    had participated in the talks. In view of this, I did not think we would want to
                    delay any longer.</p>
                <p>Mr. Peterson said he would convey this reaction (after receiving our telegram) to
                    Mr. Helmore whom he planned to see on August 3.</p>
                <p>With regard to the October 15 meeting, Mr. Peterson said he was continuing to
                    press for provision of personnel by the British and exploring other possible
                    sources. He felt the meeting should certainly take place sometime in October. I
                    said that we, too, were doing all we could to provide a staff.</p>
                <postscript>
                    <p>I called Mr. Peterson back and told him we were sending him the attached
                            cable<note n="83" xml:id="d690fn83">
                            <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note> immediately, and summarized its
                        contents for him in case he met with Mr. Helmore before August 3.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
