<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Executive Committee on Economic Foreign Policy Document D–70/46, Washington,
                    July 25, 1946</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d709</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">709</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-07-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-07-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87004890"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International trade</term>
                    <term ref="recykDuvfC6iFH3Xe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85139643"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Unemployment</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-07-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-07-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="709"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d709">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 122: Box 22</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Executive Committee on Economic Foreign Policy Document
                        D–70/46, Washington, July 25, 1946</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1946-07-25">July 25, 1946</date>
                </dateline>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Chapter VI</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Intergovernmental Commodity Arrangements</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">Article 41</p>
                <p rend="center">[General statement regarding intergovernmental commodity
                        arrangements]<note n="1" xml:id="d709fn1">Brackets appear throughout Chapter
                        VI in the source text.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Members recognize that in the relationship between production and consumption
                    of some primary commodities there may arise special difficulties different in
                    character from those which generally exist in the case of manufactured goods and
                    that these special difficulties, if serious, may have such widespread
                    repercussions as to jeopardize the effectuation of the general policy of
                    economic expansion.</p>
                <p rend="center">Article 42</p>
                <p rend="center">[Special commodity studies]</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Members substantially interested in the production, consumption or trade
                        of a particular commodity shall be entitled, if they consider that special
                        difficulties exist or are expected to arise regarding a commodity, to ask
                        that a study of that commodity be made, and the Organization, if it finds
                        that these representations are well-founded, shall invite the Members
                        principally interested in the production, consumption or trade of that
                        commodity, and may invite non-Members having a similar interest, to appoint
                        representatives to a Study Group to make a study of the commodity.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The Study Group shall, in the light of an investigation of the root causes
                        of the problem, promptly report its findings regarding the production,
                        consumption and trade situation for the commodity. If the Study Group finds
                        that special difficulties exist or are expected to arise, it shall make
                        recommendations to the Organization as to how best to deal with such
                        difficulties.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">Article 43</p>
                <p rend="center">[Commodity conferences]</p>
                <p>If the Organization concludes that measures not involving the regulation of
                    production, trade or prices are unlikely to operate quickly <pb facs="1397"
                        n="1375" xml:id="pg_1375"/> enough in solving the problem, it may convene an
                    intergovernmental conference for the purpose of framing an intergovernmental
                    commodity agreement for the commodity concerned, in conformance with the
                    principles set forth in Article 45.</p>
                <p rend="center">Article 44</p>
                <p rend="center">[Objectives of Intergovernmental Commodity Agreements]</p>
                <p>The Members agree that the regulation of production, trade or prices through
                    intergovernmental commodity agreements is justified in the circumstances stated
                    in Article 43 to achieve the following objectives: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>To enable countries to find solutions to special commodity
                            difficulties without resorting to unilateral action that tends to shift
                            the burden of their problems to other countries.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>To prevent or alleviate the serious economic problems which may arise
                            when, owing to the difficulties of finding alternative employment,
                            production adjustments cannot be effected by the free play of market
                            forces as rapidly as the circumstances require.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>To provide, during a transitional period, a framework for the
                            development and consideration of measures, which will have as their
                            purpose economic adjustments designed to promote the expansion of
                            consumption or a shift of resources and manpower out of over-expanded
                            industries into new and productive occupations.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">Article 45</p>
                <p rend="center">[Principles governing the institution of intergovernmental
                    commodity agreements]</p>
                <p>Members undertake to adhere to the following principles governing the institution
                    of intergovernmental commodity agreements involving the regulation of
                    production, trade or prices: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Any Member having a substantial interest in the production,
                            consumption or trade of any commodity for which an intergovernmental
                            commodity agreement is proposed shall be entitled to participate in the
                            consideration of the proposed agreement. The Organization may invite the
                            participation of non-Member countries having a similar interest.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Members agree not to enter into intergovernmental commodity agreements
                            involving the regulation of production, trade or prices, except after: <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>investigation by the Study Group of the root causes of the
                                    problem which gave rise to the proposal;</item>
                                <pb facs="1398" n="1376" xml:id="pg_1376"/>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>determination, under procedures established by the
                                    Organization in accordance with paragraph 6 of Article 55,
                                    either: <list>
                                        <label>1)</label>
                                        <item>that a burdensome surplus of the product concerned has
                                            developed or is developing in international trade and
                                            such burdensome surplus would, in the absence of
                                            specific governmental action to prevent it, be
                                            accompanied by widespread distress to small producers
                                            accounting for a substantial portion of the total output
                                            and that these conditions cannot be corrected by the
                                            normal play of competitive forces because, in the case
                                            of the product concerned, a substantial reduction of
                                            price leads neither to a significant increase in
                                            consumption nor to a significant decrease in production;
                                            or</item>
                                        <label>2)</label>
                                        <item>that widespread unemployment, unrelated to general
                                            business conditions, has developed or is developing in
                                            respect of the industry concerned and that such
                                            unemployment cannot be corrected by the normal play of
                                            competitive forces rapidly enough to prevent widespread
                                            and undue hardship to workers because, in the case of
                                            the industry concerned, (i) a substantial reduction of
                                            price does not lead to a significant increase in
                                            consumption but leads, instead, to the reduction of
                                            employment, and (ii) the resulting unemployment cannot
                                            be remedied by normal reemployment processes;</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                <item>formulation and adoption by Members of a program of economic
                                    adjustment believed to be adequate to insure substantial
                                    progress toward solution of the problem within the time limits
                                    of the agreement.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Intergovernmental commodity agreements involving the regulation of
                            production, trade or prices in respect of other than primary products
                            shall not be resorted to unless the Organization finds that exceptional
                            circumstances justify such action. Such agreements shall be subject to
                            the principles set forth in this Chapter, and, in addition, to any other
                            requirements which the Organization may establish.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">Article 46</p>
                <p rend="center">[Principles and requirements of intergovernmental commodity
                    agreements]</p>
                <p>Members undertake to adhere to the following principles and requirements
                    governing the operation of intergovernmental commodity agreements: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Such agreements shall be open initially to accession by any Member on
                            terms no less favorable than those accorded to any other country party
                            thereto and thereafter upon such terms as may be approved by the
                            Organization.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Such agreements shall provide for adequate representation of Members
                            substantially interested in the importation or consumption of the
                            commodity.</item>
                        <pb facs="1399" n="1377" xml:id="pg_1377"/>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>In such agreements countries which are largely dependent for
                            consumption on imports of the commodity involved shall, in
                            determinations made relating to the regulation of prices, trade, stocks,
                            production or other substantive matters, have together a voice equal to
                            that of those largely interested in obtaining export markets for the
                            product.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>In order to minimize the need for production restriction such
                            agreements shall provide, where practicable, for measures designed to
                            expand world consumption of the commodity, consideration being given to
                            the possible effect on competing products.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Such agreements shall, with due regard to the transitional need for
                            preventing serious economic and social dislocation, make appropriate
                            provision to afford increasing opportunities for satisfying world
                            requirements from sources from which such requirements can be supplied
                            most effectively.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Under such agreements the treatment with respect to the imports or
                            exports of the commodity accorded by any participating country to any
                            Member shall not, unless otherwise agreed by the Organization, be less
                            favorable than that accorded to any other country.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>Such agreements shall be designed to assure the availability of
                            supplies adequate at all times for world consumption requirements at
                            reasonable prices.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>Such agreements shall contain provision for administration by
                            Commodity Councils set up in accordance with the provisions of Article
                            47, except that in the case of existing agreements this requirement may
                            be waived by the Organization.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>Such agreements shall not remain initially in effect for more than
                            five years. The renewal of an agreement shall be subject to the
                            principles governing new agreements set forth in Article 45. At the end
                            of each five years of the continuance of such an agreement the
                            Organization shall prepare and publish a review of the operation of the
                            agreement in the light of the principles set forth in Article 45. If the
                            operation is found to have failed substantially to conform to these
                            principles, and particularly if it is found not to have made substantial
                            progress toward a solution of the underlying commodity problem, the
                            Organization shall provide for termination of the agreement or for
                            revision believed adequate to make it effective for that purpose.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>Members agree that full publicity shall be given to any
                            intergovernmental commodity agreement proposed or concluded, to the
                            statements of considerations and objectives advanced by the proposing
                            Members, to the operation of the agreement, and to the nature and
                            development of measures adopted to correct the underlying situation
                            which gave rise to the agreement.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1400" n="1378" xml:id="pg_1378"/>
                <p rend="center">Article 47</p>
                <p rend="center">[Commodity Councils]</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>A Commodity Council shall be established under each intergovernmental
                        commodity agreement involving the regulation of production, trade or prices
                        of that commodity.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The voting membership of each Commodity Council shall consist of the
                        representatives of the countries participating in the intergovernmental
                        commodity agreement concerned, and voting power shall be determined in such
                        a way that the participating countries which are largely dependent for
                        consumption on imports of the commodity involved shall, in determinations
                        made relating to the regulation of prices, trade, stocks, production or
                        other substantive matters, have together a voice equal to that of those
                        largely interested in obtaining export markets for the product.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
