<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Canadian Embassy to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-09-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-09-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-09-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-09-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="98"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d98">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.<gloss target="#t_BC1"
                    >BC</gloss>/9–2646</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Canadian Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1946-09-26">undated</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Confidential and Informal Memorandum on the Views of Canada
                        on Elections to the Security Council and the Economic and Social
                        Council</hi>
                    <note n="9" xml:id="d98fn9">Transmitted to the Department by the Canadian
                        Embassy under cover of a letter dated September 26, not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. At present the six non-permanent members of the Security Council are: <table
                        cols="2" rows="6">
                        <row>
                            <cell rows="3">For two-year term:</cell>
                            <cell>Australia</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Brazil</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Poland</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rows="3">For one-year term:</cell>
                            <cell>Egypt</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Mexico</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Netherlands.</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0218" n="200" xml:id="pg_200"/>
                <p>2. The United Nations Assembly in October will elect successors to Egypt, Mexico
                    and the Netherlands. These states are not eligible for immediate
                    re-election.</p>
                <p>3. The Latin-American Republics appear to have agreed on Colombia. The Arab
                    states (Egypt, Syria, Lebanon, Saudi-Arabia, and Iraq) have agreed on Syria and
                    have secured the concurrence of Turkey and Iran. It is widely expected that
                    Belgium will be the candidate of the Western European states for the succession
                    to the seat of the Netherlands though there may be strong opposition to a state
                    being a member at the same time of both the Economic and Social Council and the
                    Security Council.</p>
                <p>4. According to the Charter (Article 23:1), the primary consideration to be taken
                    into account by the Assembly in elections to the Security Council is “the
                    contribution of Members of the United Nations to the maintenance of
                    international peace and security and to the other purposes of the Organization”.
                    The secondary consideration is “equitable geographical distribution”.</p>
                <p>5. In fact, however, at the elections in London in January scant attention was
                    paid to the principle of functionalism and the two governing principles were the
                    sharing of honours and equitable geographical distribution. The first principle
                    means that a state (other than one of the Big Five) should not be a member at
                    the same time of both the Security Council and the Economic and Social Council.
                    The second principle means that various groups of states are each entitled not
                    only to a seat on the Security Council but to agree among themselves on which of
                    them should have the seat. Of the six non-permanent seats five, in the minds of
                    the adherents of these principles, are divided as follows: <list>
                        <item>Western Europe (1)</item>
                        <item>The Soviet Zone of Europe (1)</item>
                        <item>Latin America (2)</item>
                        <item>Middle East (1)</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">The sixth seat was at London given to Australia and it is
                    debatable whether this seat is considered as belonging to the British
                    Commonwealth or to the area lying south of China and the Arab states and
                    including the whole of Africa.</p>
                <p>6. Regionalism, combined with the rotation of seats among the states members of
                    the regional groups, is likely to produce a weak Security Council. It has
                    already resulted in Syria being chosen as the Middle Eastern candidate. This has
                    been done certainly with little regard being paid “to the contribution of
                    Members of the United Nations to the maintenance of international peace and
                    security and to the other purpose of the Organization”. Two years from now it
                    may <pb facs="0219" n="201" xml:id="pg_201"/> result in the two Latin American
                    members of the Security Council being countries with little military or economic
                    force to contribute to the preservation of peace.</p>
                <p>7. The present system also means that the non-permanent members of the Security
                    Council are not in fact being elected by the Assembly but that the Assembly is
                    merely ratifying the decisions of regional groups. Not all states are members of
                    any recognized regional group and some states which might be useful members of
                    the Security Council will, as a result, be disqualified from membership in the
                    Council.</p>
                <p>8. From Canada’s point of view the situation is especially serious. Since the
                    United States is always on the Security Council, Canada can make no claim for
                    membership on the basis of equitable geographical distribution. Canada belongs,
                    moreover, to no organized regional group. If Latin America always has two seats
                    on the Security Council, Western Europe one seat, Eastern Europe one seat, and
                    the Arab bloc one seat—only one seat is left over for Canada, Australia, New
                    Zealand, South Africa and India and for the other states which do not belong to
                    one of the four regions. The argument will be made that that seat should go to a
                    representative of the vast area lying south of China and of the Arab states and
                    including the whole of Africa.</p>
                <p>9. We would be serving neither our own immediate interests or the interests of
                    the United Nations if we were to give support to the view that membership in one
                    Council disqualified a state, other than one of the Big Five, from membership in
                    the other Council. This would mean that Canada would be ineligible for
                    membership in the Security Council until its term on the Economic and Social
                    Council expires in January 1949 (i.e., Canada could not be elected until
                    September 1948). By limiting the choice of candidates for the Councils it would
                    weaken the Councils since they can do their most effective work only if they
                    contain the states which have the greatest contribution to make to the solution
                    of the problems with which they are dealing. Canada should therefore be prepared
                    to oppose any movement which may develop in the Assembly to disqualify Belgium
                    from membership on the Security Council because of its membership on the
                    Economic and Social Council.</p>
                <p>10. Should Canada stand for the Security Council this year, one of the main
                    arguments for our standing (even if we expect to be defeated) would be that by
                    so doing we would make clear our opposition to the acceptance of our [<hi
                        rend="italic">four?</hi>] undesirable conventions: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>The convention that the Assembly can properly disregard in elections
                            to the Security Council the principle of functionalism set forth in
                            Article 23 of the Charter;</item>
                        <pb facs="0220" n="202" xml:id="pg_202"/>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>The convention that a state is ineligible for election to the Security
                            Council if it is already a member of the Economic and Social
                            Council;</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>The convention that a number of regions of the world have a right to
                            be represented on the Council by a state designated by them no matter
                            what the qualifications of that state may be;</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>The convention that only one member of the British Commonwealth, apart
                            from the United Kingdom, should sit on the Security Council.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>, September 25, 1946.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
