<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>14. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-11-01T17:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-11-01T17:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077241"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Linkage</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-11-01T17:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-11-01T17:30:00-05:00" n="14"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d14">
                <head>14. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d14fn1"
                        >Source: Department of State, Office of the Secretariat Staff, <persName
                            corresp="#p_VC_1">Cyrus R. Vance</persName>, Secretary of State,
                        1977–1980, Lot 84D241, unlabeled folder. Secret; Exdis. Drafted by Tice on
                        November 2 and approved by <persName corresp="#p_AD_3">David
                            Anderson</persName> (<gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss>) on November 8.
                        The meeting took place in the Secretary’s office.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-11-01T17:30:00-05:00">November 1, 1977, 5:30 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Belize</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <list>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">British</hi>
                            </head>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Ted Rowlands</persName>, Minister
                                of State for Commonwealth Affairs</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_CH_3">Hugh Cortazzi</persName>, Deputy to
                                Minister <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>John Martin, Private Secretary to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RE_1"
                                    >Rowlands</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SW_2">William Squire</persName>, Counselor,
                                British Embassy</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <list>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">American</hi>
                            </head>
                            <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Under Secretary for Political Affairs Mr. <persName
                                    corresp="#p_HPC_1">Habib</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Assistant Secretary for <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>, Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_TTA_1">Todman</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Donald Tice (notetaker)</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> opened the discussion by
                    saying that, in his view, by Thursday<note n="2" xml:id="d14fn2">November
                        3.</note> it was possible there would be an agreement between himself and
                    Guatemalan Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_MOA_1">Molina</persName> on a
                    Belize package. <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> said that the
                    Guatemalans are “not coming up fighting” the way he had expected with regard to
                    territory in addition to the Moho.<note n="3" xml:id="d14fn3">In telegram 254508
                        to Guatemala City, October 22, <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>
                        noted that he was “convinced that the British have gone as far as it is
                        possible for them” and instructed <persName corresp="#p_AGR_1"
                            >Andrews</persName> to advise <persName corresp="#p_MOA_1"
                            >Molina</persName> that “Guatemala should give very careful
                        consideration to the British proposal,” which he described as “cession of
                        territory up to the Moho River (along Aguacate Creek, but excluding the
                        additional triangle from Orange Point), something on the cays and maritime
                        frontiers, plus a joint development project.” (National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D770389–1043) In telegram 6581 from Guatemala City, October 22, <persName
                            corresp="#p_AGR_1">Andrews</persName> confirmed that he delivered
                            <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>’s message to <persName
                            corresp="#p_MOA_1">Molina</persName>. (National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D770390–0426)</note> On the other hand, <persName corresp="#p_RE_1"
                        >Rowlands</persName>’ instructions had been to hold back on the cays and
                    grant those as a final concession if necessary to obtaining an agreement. But,
                        <persName corresp="#p_MOA_1">Molina</persName> had taken the cays for
                    granted from the start and therefore <persName corresp="#p_RE_1"
                        >Rowlands</persName> had already in effect had to concede them.</p>
                <p>The central issue of the first day’s discussion was that of a major development
                    project between the Monkey and Moho Rivers and its possible link to some type of
                    consultations or plebisite. <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> said
                    he was trying to talk the Guatemalans out of this because he could see no
                    prospect for the British putting some 100 million pounds into a <pb facs="0094"
                        n="43" xml:id="pg_43"/> project, which would be also funded by the
                    Guatemalans, in an area for which there had been no final settlement with regard
                    to sovereignty. In response to a question from the Secretary, <persName
                        corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> said that the idea of a joint
                    development project had first been raised in the London talks by the British,
                    but that it had become hopelessly complicated by the addition of the plebiscite
                    link by the Guatemalans. The point <persName corresp="#p_RE_1"
                        >Rowlands</persName> had made to the Guatemalans was why would they want to
                    invest a lot of money in a project in an area where a subsequent referendum
                    could very well go against them in a ratio of 9–1. Add to this the instability
                    inherent in the unsolved sovereignty question implied by the plebisite and it
                    did not seem to <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> that this made
                    sense to either side.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> asked what in the economic
                    sphere the British were prepared to offer in lieu of a joint project. <persName
                        corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> replied that the Guatemalans were
                    eager to have some type of road system linking the Peten to the coast and he
                    could propose the joint funding of such a system under which the British would
                    bear some of the cost of the roads inside Guatemala.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> asked about the role of
                    General <persName corresp="#p_MPLR_1">Mendoza</persName> in these negotiations
                    and whether he carries real authority. <persName corresp="#p_RE_1"
                        >Rowlands</persName> replied that the British had been told quietly by the
                    other Guatemalan negotiator, <persName corresp="#p_SKJ_1"
                        >Skinner-Klee</persName>, that they should be solicitous of <persName
                        corresp="#p_MPLR_1">Mendoza</persName> because he would have a key role in
                    delivering the military on any agreement.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> said that in his view there are
                    five ingredients which will need to be included if an agreement is to be
                    reached. These are:</p>
                <p>1. a territorial settlement;</p>
                <p>2. an agreement on the cays;</p>
                <p>3. agreement on a development project or projects but without linkage to a
                    plebiscite;</p>
                <p>4. some provision for ongoing consultation with regard to feasibility of port
                    construction and rights in connection with the ceding of the cays; and</p>
                <p>5. how to process the whole package through to final agreement.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> said that the United
                    States would, of course, be quite prepared to be helpful. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> replied that the way in which we could
                    probably be most helpful would be in mobilizing support for an agreement once it
                    had been reached. <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> was no way
                    near as sanguine as Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPC_1">Habib</persName> seemed to
                    be that Belizian Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_PGC_1">Price</persName>
                    would accept any agreement which entailed the ceding of territory. <persName
                        corresp="#p_PGC_1">Price</persName> would be travelling to London next week
                    and meeting with <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName>. <persName
                        corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> would inform him of any agreement that
                    had been reached with the Guatemalans and then it would be necessary for
                    everyone that <persName corresp="#p_PGC_1">Price</persName> spoke with to stress
                    to him the need to accept <pb facs="0095" n="44" xml:id="pg_44"/> the agreement.
                    The Secretary mentioned that <persName corresp="#p_PGC_1">Price</persName> would
                    be returning to New York and would be seeing Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_YA_1">Young</persName>. The Secretary said that <persName
                        corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> should inform us immediately of
                        <persName corresp="#p_PGC_1">Price</persName>’s reaction so that we would
                    know how to brief <persName corresp="#p_YA_1">Andy Young</persName> for his
                    discussion with <persName corresp="#p_PGC_1">Price</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> said that it would be key to
                    obtaining support of the British Commonwealth countries in the Caribbean, that
                    is, Trinidad and Tobago, Jamaica and Barbados. In <persName corresp="#p_RE_1"
                        >Rowlands</persName>’ view, if we could have the Commonwealth countries and
                    other key countries such as Canada, Mexico, Venezuela and Colombia supporting
                    the agreement, then <persName corresp="#p_PGC_1">Price</persName> would probably
                    not “come out fighting” and would know that he had to accept the agreement.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> said that we understand
                    the problem, that we will be thinking about it, and that we will be prepared to
                    be helpful.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> then raised one final item which
                    he said he considered to be key—this was the question of a security guarantee
                    which he said loomed much larger in the Belizian view than it did to us. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_HPC_1">Habib</persName> asked whether an <gloss
                        target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> guarantee would not take care of that since
                    Belize would join the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> upon gaining
                    independence. <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> responded that
                    there is a psychological problem there because the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1"
                        >OAS</gloss> is a Latin organization and Belize is not a Latin country. He
                    felt that it might be more acceptable to Belize were there to be some type of
                    expression of commitment or some type of guarantee jointly by the United States,
                    Canada and the Commonwealth Caribbean countries. Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> said that such things as commitments and
                    guarantees pose us with some real problems with Congress, but that we would look
                    to see what could be done in this area if in the final analysis an <gloss
                        target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> guarantee would not be sufficient.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPC_1">Habib</persName> said that one of the ways to
                    reassure the Belizians would be for the British to leave a significant armed
                    forces there for at least a couple of years after independence. This could be
                    done under the guise of training the Belize military.</p>
                <p>As the conversation ended Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName>
                    said that he would keep Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPC_1">Habib</persName>, and
                    through him the Secretary, informed of the progress of the talks.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
