<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>16. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Guatemala, the
                    Consulate in Belize City, and the Embassy in the United Kingdom</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-11-10T16:22:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-11-10T16:22:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recI9rTUZvuKoqAL4" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea">Maritime boundary</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-11-10T16:22:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-11-10T16:22:00-05:00" n="16"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d16">
                <head>16. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Guatemala, the
                    Consulate in Belize City, and the Embassy in the United Kingdom<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d16fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        P840070–0917. Secret; Priority; <gloss corresp="#t_NODIS_1">Nodis</gloss>.
                        Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_PL_2">Pfeifle</persName>; cleared by
                            <persName corresp="#p_MWHB_1">Matthews</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_TTA_1">Todman</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SSA_1"
                            >Shelton</persName>, and in <gloss target="#t_SSO_1">S/S–O</gloss>;
                        approved by <persName corresp="#p_HPC_1">Habib</persName>. Telegram sent
                        unchanged to the White House on November 11 with the same telegram number.
                        (Ibid.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-11-10T21:22:00+00:00">November 10, 1977, 2122Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>269573. Subject: Belize Negotiations.</p>
                <p>1. Guatemalan Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_MOA_1">Molina</persName> and
                    British Commonwealth Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName>
                    met secretly in Washington November 1 to 3. They reached an agreement on cession
                    of the territory south of the Moho-Aguacate line, straightening the western
                    boundary and cession of the cays up to the Monkey River (Sapodilla and
                    Ranguana). But the two sides are far apart on a development project. Guatemala
                    asked the British to pave a road entirely inside Guatemala which would cost
                    about $70 million, considerably more than the British wish to spend. Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> met with <persName
                        corresp="#p_MOA_1">Molina</persName> before and after the negotiations and
                    with <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> during the
                        negotiations.<note n="2" xml:id="d16fn2">No memoranda of conversation were
                        found for <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>’s two meetings with
                            <persName corresp="#p_MOA_1">Molina</persName>. For <persName
                            corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>’s November 1 meeting with <persName
                            corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName>, see <ref target="#d14">Document
                            14</ref>.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> saw Under Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_HPC_1">Habib</persName> after the negotiations.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d16fn3">Not found.</note>
                </p>
                <p>2. <persName corresp="#p_MOA_1">Molina</persName> told the Secretary before the
                    negotiations that Guatemala favored a joint development project in the Toledo
                    district followed by a plebiscite. The Secretary informed him that he thought
                    the British could not accept a plebiscite. <persName corresp="#p_MOA_1"
                        >Molina</persName> stressed the importance of keeping any agreed settlement
                    secret until after the March elections so Belize would not become a political
                    issue. He thought the settlement could be made public in April and would pass
                    the Council of State and Congress by May or June. He also emphasized the
                    importance of a mediator, who would not mediate, but who was necessary in order
                    to sell the agreement to the Guatemalan public.</p>
                <p>3. <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> told the Secretary on November
                    1 that he was optimistic an agreement could be reached by November 3, but he was
                    not very sanguine that Belizean Premier <persName corresp="#p_PGC_1"
                        >Price</persName> would accept any agreement which entailed ceding of
                    territory. He said the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> could be helpful by
                    mobilizing support for an agreement once it was reached. Support by the
                    Caribbean Commonwealth and Canada, Mexico, Venezuela, and Colombia would be very
                    important in convincing <persName corresp="#p_PGC_1">Price</persName> that he
                    had to accept an agreement. <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName>
                    brought up the question of a <pb facs="0099" n="48" xml:id="pg_48"/> security
                    guarantee which loomed large to Belizeans. He related that Belize had
                    psychological problems with an <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> guarantee
                    since it was a Latin organization and mentioned a joint Caribbean, Canadian,
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> expression of commitment. The Secretary
                    said commitments posed real problems with Congress, but we would consider what
                    could be done if an <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> guarantee would not be
                    sufficient.</p>
                <p>4. On November 3 after the negotiations, <persName corresp="#p_RE_1"
                        >Rowlands</persName> told <persName corresp="#p_HPC_1">Habib</persName> the
                    Guatemalans had requested black-topping of a 354 kilometer road wholly inside
                    Guatemala at the cost of $70 million. The British could not cede territory and
                    also provide a large financial contribution. It was left that <persName
                        corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> would return to London and consult his
                    government on what figure the British would be willing to provide with the
                    understanding it would be much smaller than if it were not connected with
                    territorial cession. <persName corresp="#p_RE_1">Rowlands</persName> would talk
                    to <persName corresp="#p_PGC_1">Price</persName> on November 8 and present the
                    proposed territorial cession to him.</p>
                <p>5. <persName corresp="#p_MOA_1">Molina</persName> told the Secretary on November
                    3 that the crucial problems—territorial boundary, maritime boundary, and the
                    cays—had been resolved. The British did not accept the Guatemalan idea of a
                    joint development project followed by a plebiscite so the <gloss
                        target="#t_GOG_1">GOG</gloss> needed an alternative to sweeten the package
                    presented to the Guatemalan people. They proposed the British pave a 354
                    kilometer dirt road running north-south in the Peten and eastern Guatemala. The
                    preliminary estimated cost was $70 million, but it might only cost $50 million.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MOA_1">Molina</persName> described the road project as
                    a modern version of the cart road in the 1859 convention and emphasized that
                    President <persName corresp="#p_LGKE_1">Laugerud</persName> believed it
                    necessary in order to sell a settlement to the Guatemalan public.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d16fn4">The 1859 Anglo-Guatemalan convention that set boundaries for
                        British Honduras and led to the 1862 establishment of the crown colony
                        included a provision for British assistance in building a road from
                        Guatemala City to the Caribbean coast. Guatemala declared that the
                        convention was nullified because the road was not built and subsequently
                        refused to recognize British claims to Belizean territory.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MOA_1">Molina</persName> also stressed the importance of
                    the “mediator” whose role would be to assist the negotiators, not mediate the
                    dispute. The Secretary said once the British and Guatemalans had reached an
                    agreement he would suggest names for a mediator and if help is needed with
                        <persName corresp="#p_PGC_1">Price</persName> we would do what we could.</p>
                <p>6. The fact of these negotiations not to mention their contents should be handled
                    with the utmost confidentiality, because any leak would run the danger of
                    compromising the Guatemalan position to a degree that could end any possibility
                    of a settlement.</p>
                <pb facs="0100" n="49" xml:id="pg_49"/>
                <p>7. A summary of British Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1"
                        >Owen</persName>’s follow-on talk in London with <persName
                        corresp="#p_PGC_1">Price</persName> follows septel.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d16fn5">Not found.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Vance</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
