<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>2. Study Prepared in Response to Presidential Review Memorandum
                    NSC–17–17</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-03-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-03-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-03-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-03-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="2"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d2">
                <head>2. Study Prepared in Response to Presidential Review Memorandum <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>–17<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d2fn1"
                        >Source: Carter Library, National Security Council, Institutional Files, Box
                        38, <gloss target="#t_PRM_1">PRM</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NSC_1"
                            >NSC</gloss>–17 (1). Secret. Under a March 12 covering memorandum,
                        Hornblow forwarded Presidential Review Memorandum <gloss target="#t_NSC_1"
                            >NSC</gloss>–17, dated January 26, directing a broad review of <gloss
                            target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> policy toward Latin America, including
                            <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> policies on the territorial dispute
                        over Belize, to the Vice President; the Secretaries of State, Defense,
                        Treasury, Agriculture, Labor, and Commerce; the Attorney General; the
                        Representative to the United Nations; the Administrator of the Agency for
                        International Development; the Special Trade Representative; the Chairmen of
                        the Council of Economic Advisers and the Joint Chiefs of Staff; and the
                        Directors of the Central Intelligence Agency, the Arms Control and
                        Disarmament Agency, and the United States Information Agency. <gloss
                            target="#t_PRM_1">PRM</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>–17 is
                        scheduled for publication in <ref target="frus1977-80v24">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. XXIV, South
                            America; Latin America Region</ref>. Printed here is a portion of an
                        undated paper entitled “Territorial Disputes,” attached at Tab 8 to the
                        March 12 memorandum.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates"
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1977-03-12">undated</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">Presidential Review Memorandum <gloss target="#t_NSC_1"
                    >NSC</gloss>–17</p>
                <p rend="center">Review of United States Policy</p>
                <p rend="center">Toward Latin America</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is material unrelated to Belize and Guatemala.]</p>
                <p>—<hi rend="italic">Belize:</hi> This colony, seeking independence from the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">U.K.</gloss>, poses a disproportionate problem in terms of
                    its present population of 140,000. While the British are eager to give Belize
                    its independence and be rid of a burden, Guatemala has threatened to invade
                    Belize if its historical territorial claim is not satisfied. The <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>, for its part, is unwilling to compel the
                    Belizeans to relinquish part of their territory to Guatemala. Guatemala has
                    little international support for its claims, but current efforts to settle this
                    dispute are foundering on the issue of territorial cession. The prospect of
                    Cuban intervention cannot be ignored.</p>
                <p>US policy has been to counsel moderation on both sides, while making clear that
                    we do not intend to assume the role of a mediator, arbitrator, or guarantor at
                    the present time. A US effort to mediate in <pb facs="0057" n="6" xml:id="pg_6"
                    /> the late 1960’s was an abject failure, used by both sides to avoid serious
                        negotiations.<note n="2" xml:id="d2fn2">British Honduras became a crown
                        colony in 1862. The colony gained full internal self-government under a
                        ministerial system in 1964. Guatemala’s Constitution claimed all of the
                        territory of Belize. The British and Guatemalan Governments formally
                        requested direct mediation by the United States in the UK-Guatemala
                        territorial dispute over British Honduras in 1965. Secretary of State
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName> authorized the proposal of
                        “a prominent and distinguished citizen or citizens of the United States to
                        undertake the mediation.” The Department appointed Bethuel M. Webster, a New
                        York City lawyer and former member of the Permanent Court of Arbitration, as
                        mediator with Ambassadorial rank. Despite numerous meetings over a 2-year
                        period with the British, Guatemalans, and British Hondurans, Webster was
                        unable to achieve a resolution to the dispute. <persName corresp="#p_RD_1"
                            >Rusk</persName> presented the Guatemalan and British Ambassadors with a
                        draft treaty in 1968. The British and Guatemalan Governments both indicated
                        that the draft treaty was unacceptable. British Honduras was officially
                        renamed Belize in 1973, and the colony gained independence on September 21,
                        1981. For documentation on the 1965–1968 mediation, see <ref
                            target="frus1964-68v31#d76">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1964–1968, vol. XXXI, South
                            and Central America; Mexico, Documents 76</ref>–<ref
                            target="frus1964-68v31#d78">78</ref>, <ref target="frus1964-68v31#d103"
                            >103</ref>, and <ref target="frus1964-68v31#d113">113</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>[Omitted here is material unrelated to Belize and Guatemala.]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">On the Belize issue</hi>, the options are:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Option A:</hi> Encourage the UK and Belize to make sufficient
                    territorial concession to Guatemala so that the issue goes away.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Option B:</hi> Counsel moderation, leave it to the contending
                    parties to work out a solution, and avoid involvement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Option C:</hi> Encourage Guatemala to abandon its pretensions
                    and claims to Belize territory.</p>
                <p>Under the first or third option, we would align ourselves with one party or
                    another in an intractable situation, would risk the same failure as greeted our
                    mediation efforts in 1965–68, and would necessarily alienate as much support on
                    one side as we might pick up on the other. Under Option B, which would satisfy
                    neither contending party, we would keep the door ajar, counsel moderation on
                    both sides, encourage others such as the <gloss target="#t_IDB_1">IDB</gloss> to
                    get involved with a financial assistance package as part of an eventual
                    settlement, and be prepared to involve ourselves in a constructive way if and
                    when the contending parties might finally near a settlement on their own.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
