<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-07-17T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-07-17T17:00:00-05:00" n="287" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d287">
                        <head>287. Telegram From the Embassy in Nicaragua to the Department of State
                            and the Embassies in Costa Rica, Venezuela, Guatemala, El Salvador, and
                                Honduras<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d287fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, P850036–1983. Secret; Flash; <gloss corresp="#t_NODIS_1">Nodis</gloss>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Managua</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1979-07-17T22:00:00+00:00">July 17, 1979,
                                2200Z</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>3250. Dept pass <gloss target="#t_USSOUTHCOM_1">USSOUTHCOM</gloss> Action
                            Flash. Subject: (S) <gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> Backs Off from
                            Agreement.</p>
                        <p>1. S-Entire text.</p>
                        <p>2. I just came back from a meeting with President <persName corresp="#p_UMF_1">Urcuyo</persName> and new Guard Commander General
                                <persName corresp="#p_MF_1">Mejia</persName>. I told them that I was
                            disturbed by recent statements which indicated that they were parting
                            from the agreement we had reached with Somoza.<note n="2" xml:id="d287fn2">In telegram 3231 from Managua, July 17, <persName corresp="#p_PL_1">Pezzullo</persName> reported that <persName corresp="#p_UMF_1">Urcuyo</persName> was “already showing signs
                                of being a problem” during the transition phase. <persName corresp="#p_UMF_1">Urcuyo</persName> had “frustrated a meeting
                                on the military side,” and <persName corresp="#p_PL_1">Pezzullo</persName> described him as “a plodding unimaginative
                                man, overwhelmed by his current position and seemingly confused by
                                the role he should play.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                P850036–1988) <persName corresp="#p_PL_1">Pezzullo</persName> noted
                                in telegram 3232 from Managua, July 17, that <persName corresp="#p_UMF_1">Urcuyo</persName> had “thrown monkey wrench”
                                in the military meeting among <persName corresp="#p_MF_1">Mejia</persName> and the Sandinista representatives to discuss
                                a ceasefire. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss>
                                59, Central Foreign Policy File, P900105–0882) <persName corresp="#p_PL_1">Pezzullo</persName> sent a further update in
                                telegram 3235 from Managua, July 17, that the proposed meeting among
                                    <persName corresp="#p_UMF_1">Urcuyo</persName> and Junta
                                representatives <persName corresp="#p_RRC_1">Rivas</persName> and
                                Jarquin had been cancelled by “the latter two because the military
                                talks were aborted by the interim regime.” (National Archives,
                                    <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy
                                File, P850036–1986)</note> I recounted the long negotiating sessions
                            with Somoza and some of their departed colleagues which included the
                            commitment on his part to resign; put in place an interim constitutional
                            successor who then would turn over power to a <gloss target="#t_GNR_1">GNR</gloss>. (The specific steps in the process had been repeated
                            by me to <persName corresp="#p_UMF_1">Urcuyo</persName> as late as two
                            days ago. I stated then that after assuming power he should dissolve
                            Congress and resign himself when the <gloss target="#t_GNR_1">GNR</gloss> came to Managua. He nodded and made no comment.) I said
                            they were aware of our conversations with other countries and the Junta
                            which provided a scenario and structure to bring about a cease-fire, no
                            reprisals, sanctuaries and the conditions under which a representative
                            democratic government could develop and prosper.</p>
                        <pb facs="0755" n="704" xml:id="pg_704"/>
                        <p>3. <persName corresp="#p_UMF_1">Urcuyo</persName> said that was not
                            repeat not his understanding, that he was a constitutional President and
                            would be prepared to enter into a dialogue with other groups but that he
                            was not repeat not prepared to surrender power to the Junta. I asked if
                            that were his firm position. He said it was. I said I would have to
                            advise my government immediately. I told him further that the historical
                            record of this period would show that he was violating an understanding
                            reached with representatives of his government. I emphasized that the
                            consequences of his attitude could be grave: it would prolong the
                            conflict, further deteriorate the <gloss target="#t_GN_1">GN</gloss>,
                            and reduce the possibility of a peaceful negotiated solution.</p>
                        <p>5. He appeared unmoved.<note n="3" xml:id="d287fn3">In telegram 3252 from
                                Managua, July 17, the Embassy reported that <hi rend="italic">Novedades’</hi> July 17 edition carried a “front page
                                photograph of President <persName corresp="#p_UMF_1">Urcuyo</persName>” with a caption reading: “The new President
                                    <persName corresp="#p_UMF_1">Urcuyo</persName> will complete the
                                constitutional period of ex-President <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza Debayle</persName> until May 1981.” (National Archives,
                                    <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy
                                File, D790323–1045)</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MF_1">Mejia</persName> did not comment.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_PL_1"><hi rend="strong">Pezzullo</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>