<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>35. Telegram From the Embassy in Guatemala to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d35</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">35</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-10-03T16:32:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-10-03T16:32:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006378"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public relations</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85006620"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Business community</term>
                    <term ref="rec2r0t2UkWjO2ZV1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004011274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Subsidies</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-10-03T16:32:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-10-03T16:32:00-05:00" n="35"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d35">
                <head>35. Telegram From the Embassy in Guatemala to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d35fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File, [no film
                        number]. Confidential; Immediate; Limdis.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Guatemala City</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1979-10-03T21:32:00+00:00">October 3, 1979, 2132Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>6616. Subj: (U) US Position on Inter-American Bank Loan. Ref: State 256788.<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d35fn2">In telegram 256788 to Guatemala City, September 29,
                        the Department discussed the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> intention
                        to abstain on Guatemala’s $15 million <gloss target="#t_IDB_1">IDB</gloss>
                        loan request in the October 4 <gloss target="#t_IDB_1">IDB</gloss> board
                        meeting and instructed <persName corresp="#p_OFFV_1">Ortiz</persName> to
                        inform <persName corresp="#p_LGFR_1">Lucas</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_BGHT_1">Bucaro</persName> that the United States “had no
                        choice but to take this position given our policies and legislation relating
                        to human rights” and that Guatemala should “make public its commitment to
                        respect human rights and to correct abuses, wherever they occur, through
                        followup investigations and judicial action.” (National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D790446–0520) <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>’s evening report
                        to <persName corresp="#p_CJ_3">Carter</persName> on September 29 reported
                        that the United States had decided to abstain on the “$15 million industry
                        and tourism loan to Guatemala from the <gloss target="#t_IDB_1">IDB</gloss>
                        on human rights grounds,” which was the “first non-basic human needs loan to
                        come to a vote since 1976.” The report also noted that “since this vote
                        might cause a seriously adverse reaction in Guatemala, we are instructing
                        our Ambassador to inform President <persName corresp="#p_LGFR_1"
                            >Lucas</persName>, in advance, of our decision.” <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJ_3">Carter</persName> wrote in the margin: “Why do it?
                        (discussed with Cy).” (Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Staff
                        Material, North/South, Pastor Files, Country Files, Box 24, Guatemala:
                        1/7–12/79)</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. (C-Entire text)</p>
                <p>2. Summary. On October 2, President <persName corresp="#p_LGFR_1"
                        >Lucas</persName> and I met alone for an hour and a half discussion mostly
                    centered on our human rights concerns. The President considers Guatemala is the
                    target of an unjust orchestrated campaign of defamation. The object of this
                    campaign, he says, is to destabilize Guatemala and halt its progress. He is,
                    however, confident that the truth will prevail. I counseled that Guatemala take
                    the necessary steps to improve its image and assure that objective facts are
                    publicized. End summary.</p>
                <p>3. I read the talking points contained in reftel to the President. He listened
                    very carefully. However, he took no notes as I had suggested. Speaking
                    personally I advised him that it was probable that despite our efforts or wishes
                    there would be publicity and consequent speculation in the media over the
                    significance of the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> position in the <gloss
                        target="#t_IDB_1">IDB</gloss>. He said such publicity would have unsettling
                    consequences in Guatemala.</p>
                <p>4. The President did not comment directly on our position in the <gloss
                        target="#t_IDB_1">IDB</gloss>. Instead, he referred again, as he has in the
                    past, to what he terms an orchestrated international campaign of defamation
                    against Guatemala. Much of the impetus for this campaign, he says, comes from
                    the University of San Carlos here in Guatemala. He said for years the
                    university, which is autonomous and which under the Constitution <pb facs="0150"
                        n="99" xml:id="pg_99"/> receives a fixed percentage of the national budget,
                    has been under the control of Marxists and frustrated intellectuals who
                    consistently adopt hostile and negative anti-government positions. He says these
                    embittered and often subversive elements are in constant contact with
                    like-minded groups abroad. Between them they organize campaigns of defamation
                    against Guatemala because they want to stop Guatemala’s progress and destabilize
                    the country preparatory to political and subversive actions in accord with their
                    plans for the country. He lamented that foreign groups seldom seem even to
                    attempt to verify objective facts.</p>
                <p>5. The President said this situation greatly worries the constructive and
                    patriotic sectors of Guatemala. They advise him that his government must hire a
                    good public relations firm to counter the bad image Guatemala is unjustly being
                    given. They have gone so far, the President said, as to have high-powered public
                    relations firms make bids to handle Guatemala’s account. The cost, he said,
                    would be about a million and a half dollars. He rejected this advice. He will
                    not spend money for such purposes. Rather, he will continue to invest in
                    schools, dispensaries, and in other public works. He is confident that
                    responsible and fair-minded people will perceive the truth about Guatemala.
                    There is a free press and anyone can come and go as they wish. He knows the
                    business community, however, is determined to carry out a publicity campaign to
                    counter the untruths. He will not try to stop them, but believes it will be
                    wasted effort and money.</p>
                <p>6. The President says he also has his problems with the media in Guatemala. He
                    initially sharply reduced and will soon cut off entirely the quote subsidies end
                    quote that the Presidency has long paid to a large number of Guatemalan newsmen.
                    They retaliate by printing or otherwise publicizing stories intended to
                    embarrass his administration. The unknowing accept media accounts at face value.
                    This contributes to the image problem his administration has.</p>
                <p>7. I raised the <persName corresp="#p_CAM_1">Colom Argueta</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_MAF_1">Fuentes Mohr</persName> murders and the lack of
                    any credible efforts to resolve those crimes, all of which shocks public opinion
                        greatly.<note n="3" xml:id="d35fn3">See <ref target="#d32fn4">footnote 4,
                            Document 32</ref>.</note> In addition to these murders, the continuing
                    killings of common criminals allegedly by a death squad, and the incident at
                        Panzos<note n="4" xml:id="d35fn4">See <ref target="#d28fn5">footnote 5,
                            Document 28</ref>.</note> all caused problems even for Guatemala’s best
                    friends that Marxist professors and disgruntled journalists can take advantage
                    of.</p>
                <p>8. The President said he wanted to tell me about <persName corresp="#p_CAM_1"
                        >Colom Argueta</persName>. He was a close personal friend of the
                    President’s. He helped the President <pb facs="0151" n="100" xml:id="pg_100"/>
                    greatly in the campaign. The President believes it is time for Guatemala to
                    consider a civilian President next term. The army as an institution must not
                    risk loss of popular support. He believed <persName corresp="#p_CAM_1"
                        >Colom</persName> had a good possibility to be elected as the next
                    President. President <persName corresp="#p_LGFR_1">Lucas</persName> implied he
                    would have supported <persName corresp="#p_CAM_1">Colom</persName> for the
                    Presidency. He said he saw to it that <persName corresp="#p_CAM_1"
                        >Colom</persName>’s party was officially registered so it could participate
                    in the elections. However, the President said this plan ran across the quote
                    political ambitions of another end quote. The result was that his friend
                        <persName corresp="#p_CAM_1">Colom</persName> was murdered. There is no
                    proof as to who was responsible. <persName corresp="#p_CAM_1">Colom</persName>’s
                    rival had also been assassinated. The President said that as is always the case,
                    the government was blamed for both murders. Twelve years ago it had even been
                    blamed for the assassination of the US Ambassador.<note n="5" xml:id="d35fn5"
                        >See <ref target="#d1fn6">footnote 6, Document 1</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>9. The President seemed to speak with feeling. Much was implied rather than
                    clearly stated. He appeared to be telling me that the Army Chief of Staff,
                        <gloss target="#t_Gen_1">Gen.</gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CBD_1">Cancinos</persName>, was somehow involved in the
                        <persName corresp="#p_CAM_1">Colom</persName> assassination. <gloss
                        target="#t_Gen_1">Gen.</gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CBD_1">Cancinos</persName> in turn was murdered, we
                    believe by the clandestine Marxist <gloss target="#t_EGP_1">EGP</gloss>.<note
                        n="6" xml:id="d35fn6">In telegram 3666 from Guatemala City, June 11, the
                        Embassy reported that unidentified gunmen had assassinated Army Chief of
                        Staff Major General <persName corresp="#p_CBD_1">David Cancinos
                            Barrios</persName> and noted that <persName corresp="#p_CBD_1"
                            >Cancinos</persName> was “widely considered to have been intellectual
                        author of <persName corresp="#p_CAM_1">Colom Argueta</persName>’s
                        murder—supposedly to remove him as rival for Presidency in 1982.” (National
                        Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy
                        File, D790264–0463)</note> The President added that an attempt was made on
                        <persName corresp="#p_CAM_1">Colom</persName> even before <persName
                        corresp="#p_LGFR_1">Lucas</persName> was in office, but he was only
                    wounded.</p>
                <p>10. The <persName corresp="#p_MAF_1">Fuentes Mohr</persName> case, the President
                    said, was one he did not know much about. At this point he spoke of his Vice
                    President, <persName corresp="#p_VKF_1">Villagran Kramer</persName>. He
                    described him as an incorrigible intriguer and posturer. He called <persName
                        corresp="#p_VKF_1">Villagran</persName> quote that scorpion I carry in my
                    shirt end quote. He went on to speak of his resentment over the slight of the
                    Panamanians (who invited <persName corresp="#p_VKF_1">Villagran</persName> but
                    not <persName corresp="#p_LGFR_1">Lucas</persName> to the ceremonies of October
                        1).<note n="7" xml:id="d35fn7">Ceremonies held in Panama City on October 1
                        marked the implementation of the Panama Canal Treaties. <persName
                            corresp="#p_MWF_1">Mondale</persName> and numerous Latin American
                        leaders attended. (John M. Goshko, “Panamanians Take Possession of Zone,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>, October 2, 1979, p. A1) See <ref
                            target="frus1977-80v29">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, volume XXIX,
                            Panama</ref>.</note> When I asked if an investigation had been made of
                    the <persName corresp="#p_MAF_1">Fuentes Mohr</persName> murder, he replied
                    there were no significant leads and spoke also of the unsolved murder of
                    prominent businessman Luis Canella. I do not believe he meant to connect the
                    two.</p>
                <p>11. The President took great pains to describe the clash at Panzos between Indian
                    peasants and the army. He said it occurred before his term of office and
                    essentially originated when nervous troops not speaking the local Indian dialect
                    panicked and fired upon an angry <pb facs="0152" n="101" xml:id="pg_101"/> group
                    of peasants. The peasants had been incited by political agitators. Able military
                    leadership on the spot would have avoided the clash. Nevertheless, Marxist
                    intellectuals greatly magnified the incident alleging that 200 peasants had been
                    killed when only a small fraction of that number died. The President said
                    foreign sectors, as usual, believed the maliciously exaggerated version even
                    though an impartial investigation was made. I suggested a blue ribbon commission
                    which published the results of its investigations had a better chance of being
                    believed than one formed at a lower level.</p>
                <p>12. The President asked me to report to my government that his administration was
                    trying to improve its image, but will do so through deeds not publicity
                    campaigns. I replied Guatemala had many friends who would welcome an improvement
                    no matter how it came.</p>
                <p>13. As I was leaving, <gloss target="#t_Gen_1">Gen.</gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_LGFR_1">Lucas</persName> said quote I stay calm and I
                    study the situation carefully and then I decide what to do and I stick by the
                    decision end quote.</p>
                <p>14. Comment. This discussion of the Colom, <persName corresp="#p_MAF_1">Fuentes
                        Mohr</persName> and Panzos cases was one I planned to have with the
                    President since my arrival here. I had delayed until I felt a better personal
                    rapport was established. The President was unusually frank in his comments to
                    me. He appeared to be speaking with sincerity and did not show resentment or
                    anger at my observations or towards the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> at
                    any point. I had the impression of a somewhat lonely man surrounded by people he
                    does not entirely trust and anxious for understanding and sympathy.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_OFFV_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Ortiz</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
