<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>386. Telegram From the Embassy in El Salvador to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d386</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">386</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-10-11T18:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-10-11T18:15:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reclIDTRPrn9Z53H4" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94004349"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">DCM</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec14HP3WEhVvFEi9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001220"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Private sector</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086014"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Missing persons</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="reclX4mzFRYzavuL4" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections">Free elections</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-10-11T18:15:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-10-11T18:15:00-05:00" n="386"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d386">
                <head>386. Telegram From the Embassy in El Salvador to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d386fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        P850027–2508. Secret; Immediate; Nodis. Sent for information to Caracas,
                        Panama City, and San José.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>San Salvador</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1979-10-11T23:15:00+00:00">October 11, 1979, 2315Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>5835. Subj: Situation in El Salvador. (S). Ref State 264095.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d386fn2">See <ref target="#d385">Document 385</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. (S-entire text)</p>
                <p>2. As instructed reftel A, reconfirmed by Oct 10 <persName corresp="#p_HBR_1"
                        >Hemenway</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_HRB_1">Howard</persName> telecon,
                        <gloss target="#t_DCM_1">DCM</gloss> and I met at 10:30 this morning with
                    Archbishop <persName corresp="#p_ROA_1">Romero</persName> and two of his closest
                        advisors.<note n="3" xml:id="d386fn3">Minutes for the October 10 telephone
                        conversation between <persName corresp="#p_HBR_1">Hemenway</persName> and
                            <persName corresp="#p_HRB_1">Howard</persName> have not been
                        found.</note> Drawing from we presented the questions in its para 8.</p>
                <p>3. In responding, Archbishop and associates made following points:</p>
                <p>A. Government position is bifurcated one. On the one hand it offers free and
                    honest elections, while on other hand it steps up level of violence and
                    repression;</p>
                <p>B. It is incorrect to speak of conflict between <gloss target="#t_GOES_1"
                        >GOES</gloss> and <persName corresp="#p_CF_2">Church</persName>—conflict is
                    between <gloss target="#t_GOES_1">GOES</gloss> and people of El Salvador. Church
                    is with the people and would have best possible will toward <gloss
                        target="#t_GOES_1">GOES</gloss> if it would reconcile its differences with
                    people;</p>
                <p>C. Parties of moderate opposition have tried to point up for <gloss
                        target="#t_GOES_1">GOES</gloss> the road toward better relations and
                    acceptable electoral climate; in return they have been threatened by “Mano
                    Blanca”;</p>
                <pb facs="1016" n="965" xml:id="pg_965"/>
                <p>D. In Church meeting with parties of moderate opposition and enlightened elements
                    of private sector, agreement has been reached on five indispensable elements for
                    free election;</p>
                <p>(1) Cessation of repression, this to include inter alia change of attitude of
                    heads of security services and reorganization of <gloss target="#t_ORDEN_1"
                        >ORDEN</gloss>;</p>
                <p>(2) Explanation of all the missing persons (desaparecidos);</p>
                <p>(3) Freedom to organize for both workers and peasants, and recognition of
                    organizations which already exist;</p>
                <p>(4) Effective freedom for political parties to organize and to campaign;</p>
                <p>(5) Observance of and respect for constitutional rights of all citizens.</p>
                <p>E. If <gloss target="#t_GOES_1">GOES</gloss> were to comply with points (1)
                    through (5) it would create a climate permitting necessary discussions. Moderate
                    opposition has made these requirements known publicly through its “popular
                    forum”;</p>
                <p>F. Church strongly supported effective dialogue with <gloss target="#t_GOES_1"
                        >GOES</gloss> aimed at meaningful democratic opening but President’s deeds
                    have contradicted his words. <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> assumption
                    that President <persName corresp="#p_RMCH_1">Romero</persName> has taken some
                    meaningful steps which merit positive response while understandable in terms of
                    what <persName corresp="#p_RMCH_1">Romero</persName> appeared to be promising,
                    is a mistaken premise; President <persName corresp="#p_RMCH_1"
                    >Romero</persName>’s so-called steps taken to date have represented no effective
                    advances in five areas outlined above in today’s world, President <persName
                        corresp="#p_RMCH_1">Romero</persName> has lost his credibility and his words
                    have no real backing or impact;</p>
                <p>G. Even so, some response has been forthcoming from moderate opposition in form
                    of political telecasts demonstrating that people are considering and commenting
                    on the political approach which he suggests. Similarly, Church has tried to be a
                    moderating force but finds so little real good to comment upon that archbishop’s
                    homilies nearly always sound negative. Nevertheless, Church for its part,
                    remains alert for good or positive news upon which to comment and in this way is
                    trying to respond;</p>
                <p>4. We turned then to question of alternatives. Archbishop <persName
                        corresp="#p_ROA_1">Romero</persName> said he was not sure it was for Church
                    to define these. He hears public clamor from the left for a popular
                    insurrection, and he hears much talk about possibilities of a coup d’etat,
                    either by ultra-rightist or by progressive elements within the military. He
                    agreed with our suggestion as to the danger of a coup d’etat splitting military
                    and opening the way for far left. He suggested however that this would depend on
                    the mentality and character of the coup itself. For the Archbishop, an autocoup
                    (#) or coup by the rightist military would change nothing of today’s situation
                    and would heighten the chances for armed insurrection. In contrast, a coup by
                    progressive military who would offer <pb facs="1017" n="966" xml:id="pg_966"/>
                    change—or chance for recent transition to something new—could well win public
                    confidence and isolate far left.</p>
                <p>5. At this point one of Archbishop’s advisors interjected that in his view <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> and Embassy pressure had led President
                        <persName corresp="#p_RMCH_1">Romero</persName> to make his Aug 16
                    declarations in favor of free elections. Could we not now exert similar pressure
                    to move President <persName corresp="#p_RMCH_1">Romero</persName> to compliance
                    with five “indispensable elements” (cited in para 3 above)? We explained that we
                    have discussed exactly these matters with President in the past and always
                    received from him and his associates pat <gloss target="#t_GOES_1">GOES</gloss>
                    position that charges are untrue. For President to accept suggestions from us
                    now on these points would entail complete reversal of <gloss target="#t_GOES_1"
                        >GOES</gloss> position as conveyed to us on previous occasions and therefore
                    seems somewhat unlikely.</p>
                <p>Note by OC/T: (#) as received.</p>
                <p>6. Archbishop’s other advisor then summed up present list of unpalatable
                    alternatives as:</p>
                <p>A. Popular insurrection;</p>
                <p>B. Elections in an atmosphere completely inappropriate and inhospitable for same;
                    and</p>
                <p>C. Coup d’etat.</p>
                <p>He then asked as to <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> preference among these.
                    We responded that all our recent actions have been directed toward alternative
                    “B” and finding ways and means to improve the climate for meaningful elections.
                    He said that was clearly Church preference as [garble], but that one must look
                    at matter with realism. In real, practical terms, at this late date, prospect of
                    any free, meaningful election looks completely theoretical and highly
                    doubtful.</p>
                <p>7. Church officials said that coup d’etat could conceivably be least among evils
                    facing the nation. They pointed out that it could conceivably open way for free,
                    meaningful elections. We pointed out it might also open way for popular
                    insurrection. They agreed and said danger lay in how the popular forces would
                    react. But, they said, trying to hold elections under present circumstances
                    could easily bring on popular insurrection. On balance, they appeared clearly to
                    believe that coup d’etat route offers more manageable risks than electoral route
                    in today’s conditions.</p>
                <p>8. When we inquired about points of contact and sources of information, Church
                    representatives were not particularly forthcoming.</p>
                <p>Admitted to some contacts with opposition political parties, limited contact with
                    military, some with progressive elements in private business sector, but denied
                    seeking or initiating contact with “illegal” groups or organizations.</p>
                <p>9. As a closing comment, our visit—under instructions—to archbishop is very
                    unlikely to go unnoticed. Depending on events of imme<pb facs="1018" n="967"
                        xml:id="pg_967"/>diate future, it will almost certainly be interpreted and
                    misinterpreted in many ways.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DFJ_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Devine</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
