<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-03-13T12:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-03-13T12:30:00-05:00" n="424" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d424">
                        <head>424. Telegram From the Embassy in El Salvador to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d424fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, P880137–1701. Secret; Flash; Nodis.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>San Salvador</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1980-03-13T17:30:00+00:00">March 13,
                                    1980, 1730Z</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1886. State for <persName corresp="#p_BWG_1">Bowdler</persName>, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> for <persName corresp="#p_PR_1">Pastor</persName>. Subj: Assistance to <gloss target="#t_GOES_1">GOES</gloss>; Timing and Composition. Ref. Brown-<persName corresp="#p_DMJ_1">Dion</persName> Telcon 3/12/80.<note n="2" xml:id="d424fn2">No record of the telephone conversation between
                                Brown and <persName corresp="#p_DMJ_1">Dion</persName> has been
                                found. See <ref target="#d427">Document 427</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>1. (S-Entire text)</p>
                        <p>2. Despite brief time here,<note n="3" xml:id="d424fn3">In telegram 1857
                                from San Salvador, March 12, <persName corresp="#p_WRE_1">White</persName> reported that he had presented his credentials
                                to the <gloss target="#t_JRG_1">JRG</gloss> on March 11. (National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, D800126–0310) <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>’s March 12 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> reported that Carter had read
                                    <persName corresp="#p_WRE_1">White</persName>’s telegram and
                                “commented that within a few days he would like Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WRE_1">White</persName>’s personal assessment of the
                                situation.” (Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Brzezinski
                                Material, Country File, Box 20, El Salvador: 3/80)</note> I have
                            gained several impressions about situation that I would like to record.
                            First, the Revolutionary Governing Junta (<gloss target="#t_JRG_1">JRG</gloss>) is composed of honorable men who are committed to
                            finding a moderate solution and recognize that our support will be key
                            to survival of non-Communist society in El Salvador. Second, they face
                            two formidable enemies in the ultraleft terrorists bent on provoking
                            security forces into mindless reprisals against the masses leading to
                            popular insurrection and the ultraright terrorists who are carrying out
                            inhuman reprisals against center-left aimed at total polarization,
                            ouster <pb facs="1123" n="1072" xml:id="pg_1072"/> of moderates from
                                <gloss target="#t_JRG_1">JRG</gloss> and civil war to implant
                            repressive dictatorship. I cannot emphasize too strongly that immediate
                            threat is from ultraright; it must be defeated before <gloss target="#t_JRG_1">JRG</gloss> can begin to detach accessible left
                            from foreign trained leftist terrorists.</p>
                        <p>3. It is clear to me that enactment of the agrarian and other reforms has
                            strengthened the <gloss target="#t_JRG_1">JRG</gloss> significantly.
                            Even Minister of Defense <persName corresp="#p_GMJG_1">Garcia</persName>
                            publicly pledged support to the Junta and to reform program in an
                            effective TV broadcast the evening of March 11. The limited state of
                                siege<note n="4" xml:id="d424fn4">In telegram 1719 from San
                                Salvador, March 7, the Embassy reported that the <gloss target="#t_JRG_1">JRG</gloss> had suspended certain individual
                                rights on March 6 after announcing its agrarian reform decree. The
                                Embassy noted: “It is not a declaration of martial law but it is
                                locally being called a ‛state of siege’ because of any suspension of
                                constitutional guarantees is commonly referred to by that term in
                                this country. A more precise characterization, however, would be a
                                ‛limited state of siege.’” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D800117–0207)</note> has calmed the country by removing from the
                            newspapers, radio and TV the inflammatory calls to insurrection from the
                            extreme left [garble—and extreme] right.</p>
                        <p>4. This sudden burst of effectiveness has caused the revolutionary left
                            to break stride and falter. There has not been a major incident from the
                            left in over two weeks, apart from a disastrous attack on guardia
                            barracks that left 15 attackers dead and one guardia wounded. These same
                            two weeks have seen a quantum leap in violence from the right. Each day
                            the toll mounts with the brunt of the violence falling on the left wing
                            Christian Democrats, on the Socialists (<gloss target="#t_MNR_1">MNR</gloss>), Orthodox Nonviolent Communists (<gloss target="#t_UDN_1">UDN</gloss>), and on the more moderate leaders of
                            the popular blocs. The strategy of the right is clear: (1) destroy the
                            accessible left, those who might be open to an appeal to reason from the
                                <gloss target="#t_JRG_1">JRG</gloss> and could potentially be
                            persuaded either to support or at least not violently oppose the Junta’s
                            reform program; (2) demonstrate the impotence of the Junta and the
                            tolerance of the armed forces for savage reprisals by the ultraright,
                            thereby radicalizing the moderates and insuring denunciations of the
                            government from the archbishop and other popular leaders; and (3)
                            convince the armed forces that its only hope of survival as an
                            institution is to return to its traditional alliance with the oligarchy,
                            especially those who are bankrolling the rightwing violence.</p>
                        <p>5. The Human Rights Commission of El Salvador published a statistical
                            table yesterday showing the January and February figures for deaths
                            caused by the left at 73 and by the right at 330. The source may be
                            biased and its figures somewhat suspect but they are all we have and
                            most people believe them. It is instructive to note that this Mission
                            has never kept such a tally and when I requested one yesterday <pb facs="1124" n="1073" xml:id="pg_1073"/> at our staff meeting there
                            were strenuous objections from some quarters. This introduces a separate
                            but related problem.</p>
                        <p>6. This is unquestionably the most disciplined diplomatic Mission I have
                            ever seen and a good share of our problems in El Salvador arise directly
                            out of the mixed signals we have been sending to the various political
                            actors here, especially to the armed forces. I am morally certain that
                            if <persName corresp="#p_CJJ_1">Jim Cheek</persName> had not taken
                            charge when he did and if he and <persName corresp="#p_DMJ_1">Mark
                                Dion</persName> had not engaged in a marathon effort to untangle the
                            mass of miscues and misreadings about our position, notwithstanding the
                            Department’s firm and public rejection of a rightwing coup,<note n="5" xml:id="d424fn5">See <ref target="#d417fn3">footnote 3, Document
                                    417</ref>.</note> we would now have an intractable rightwing
                            Junta in place and good prospects for a civil war. Over the next several
                            weeks we will speak here with one voice or see some of our speakers
                            depart. I will be meeting over the next few days with each member of the
                            Junta individually and with MinDef and commanders of each of the
                            security forces. One of my main themes will be the need to rein in the
                            rightwing terrorism hard. It would help if Washington agencies,
                            specifically <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_DIA_1">DIA</gloss>, gave clearest and most forceful
                            instructions to their representatives that <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> policy does not countenance a rightwing solution and
                            that every opportunity must be sought to denounce rightwing violence
                            that threatens to radicalize the country irretrievably.</p>
                        <p>7. To return to the overall analysis, let me say that I perceive a
                            substantial group within the armed forces, especially in the High
                            Command, that will never accept civilian leadership and who will attempt
                            to undermine all movement towards democracy. This group wields important
                            power and several of its members not only tolerate assassinations and
                            bombings but probably actively encourage the rightist terrorist
                            squads.</p>
                        <p>8. The rationale for us to provide this government with Military Training
                            Teams (MTTs) is not as many opponents claim, a military solution to a
                            political problem. The policy is designed to buy time for the government
                            to broaden its appeal all across the political spectrum to the point
                            that it will have sufficient strength to reform the military and then
                            turn to the real task, the elimination of the threat from the extreme
                            left. There are, however, several problems with that rationale.</p>
                        <p>9. First, it will do nothing to eliminate or discourage the threat of
                            another coup attempt—an attempt which I believe will certainly come
                            sooner or later. In fact, I believe the arrival of the MTTs will be
                            interpreted by the rightist officers as <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> support for the armed forces as presently constituted.
                            The rightwing terrorists will not be disciplined because we will have
                            committed our support already without demand<pb facs="1125" n="1074" xml:id="pg_1074"/>ing action to end the assassinations and bombings.
                            With the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> “in the bag”, the
                            rightwing officers will begin to press again for the ouster of Col.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MRAA_1">Majano</persName> and the <gloss target="#t_PDC_1">PDC</gloss>. In fact, we could easily find
                            ourselves with a coup in progress while the MTTs are here.</p>
                        <p>10. [garble], the extreme right is desperate and it may well be pushing
                            sympathetic elements in the military to move against the progressive
                            members of the Junta right now. This may well be the wrong time for the
                            right to do so. It is only human to try to postpone a crisis but I
                            believe it is perfectly logical to argue that an attempted rightwing
                            coup in the near future would have an odds-on chance of failure. A
                            failed coup could increase the support for the government from the
                            moderate left and moderate right, meanwhile providing the military an
                            opportunity and a strong rationale for cleaning house. At least one
                            senior officer, Col. <persName corresp="#p_CRN_1">Carranza</persName>,
                            has got to go and the sooner the better.</p>
                        <p>11. It might be possible to stave off a showdown but it is a fact that a
                            total incompatibility exists between this reform government and the
                            outlook and tactics of the Salvadoran military forces as presently
                            consituted. If we back this government we must accept that eventually
                            the “institutionalists” in the armed forces will move to destroy the
                            influence of the progressive younger officers like <persName corresp="#p_MRAA_1">Majano</persName>. The result could easily be
                            internal upheaval, beginning with the armed forces and spreading to the
                            society at large. In my judgement, to permit a rightwing coup or even a
                            veiled ouster of Col. <persName corresp="#p_MRAA_1">Majano</persName>
                            “in the interest of efficiency” could well provoke a split in the armed
                            forces, a bloody civil war ending in defeat for the right, and,
                            ultimately, another country gone the way of Nicaragua.</p>
                        <p>12. What should we do to avoid this? The first thing is to be very
                            careful about who we strengthen in the military and what signals we send
                            to the right, which at the moment is angry and confused from the bomb
                            squads of Major D’Aubisson through the bankers and brokers and
                            landowners to the shopkeepers and secretaries and housewives. We cannot
                            afford to suggest to these people, most of whom can be recruited into a
                            moderate solution once the terror squads are crushed, that we just might
                            be up for a rightwing alternative.</p>
                        <p>13. Another argument is that everyone to the left of <persName corresp="#p_PUA_1">Pinochet</persName> will begin shouting about
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> intervention and lump our MTTs
                            with the rightwing murder incorporated that is operating so freely in
                            Salvador. We could take that sort of smear a lot better when the reforms
                            are well underway and the ultraright has begun to phase out under <gloss target="#t_JRG_1">JRG</gloss> pressure and erosion of its financial
                            base among the former bankers and landowners. That is another argument
                            for holding off.</p>
                        <p>14. But don’t we owe the armed forces delivery on our MTTs because they
                            were promised to the institution in order to head off the <pb facs="1126" n="1075" xml:id="pg_1075"/> coup? I am not persuaded
                            that we owe a debt to anyone for not overthrowing a duly constituted
                            government to which he has sworn allegiance. However, I do believe we
                            need to show willingness to identify ourselves with the <gloss target="#t_JRG_1">JRG</gloss> and the armed forces here to the
                            extent that the assessment teams need to be brought in fast, the
                            helicopters should be offered immediately and the FMS/IMET must begin to
                            be available. But the <gloss target="#t_MTT_1">MTT</gloss> instructors
                            are a different matter. We have got to get the rightwing terrorism, the
                            excess use of force and the brutal indiscipline of the security forces
                            under control, in my view, before we commit our prestige so frontally as
                            to send in armed <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> training
                            teams.</p>
                        <p>15. As for economic aid, I would hope we would establish where Central
                            America and El Salvador stand on our order of priorities and then get
                            the programs funded and moving accordingly. We have to have <gloss target="#t_ESF_1">ESF</gloss> money and people to support the
                            agrarian reform or it could end in chaos as peasants slaughter the farm
                            animals to keep their families alive. We have got to be able to get
                            guarantees for raw [garble—materials?] shipments here or the factories
                            will close and put many more thousands of unemployed at the disposition
                            of the <gloss target="#t_FPL_1">FPL</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_ERP_1">ERP</gloss> and FALN. Let’s stop filling the terrorist recruitment
                            pool and get ExIm to start the insurance coverage up again. We should be
                            thinking seriously of an employment program on the WPA/CCC model. It
                            will cost money. However, in this way we may be able to head off a
                            disastrous leftist takeover here. But the symbol of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> assistance, I would argue, at least at
                            the outset, has got to be the loan signing ceremony, not the green
                            berets arriving on a C–130. We can perhaps bring the MTTs in quietly
                            when the current heat is off but not in an atmosphere of rightwing
                            mayhem to which the military fails to respond.<note n="6" xml:id="d424fn6">In a March 13 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_AD_1">Aaron</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PR_1">Pastor</persName> noted that <persName corresp="#p_WRE_1">White</persName> had spoken to him that afternoon while he was
                                drafting the cable. <persName corresp="#p_PR_1">Pastor</persName>
                                commented that <persName corresp="#p_WRE_1">White</persName> told
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PR_1">Pastor</persName> that he “regretted
                                sending” the telegram “since he was not there long enough to have
                                sufficient meetings to make the judgments we requested.” <persName corresp="#p_PR_1">Pastor</persName> added: “I think he
                                underestimates the degree to which his predecessor (<persName corresp="#p_CJJ_1">Cheek</persName>) committed the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> to sending these guys in, and he
                                underestimates the fact that the <gloss target="#t_MTT_1">MTT</gloss>’s can also be a <hi rend="italic">positive
                                    instrument</hi>.” (Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                                Brzezinski Material, Country File, Box 20, El Salvador:
                            3/80)</note></p>
                        <p>16. Lastly, this Mission needs urgently the personnel approved by the
                            last <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> meeting.<note n="7" xml:id="d424fn7">See <ref target="#d419">Document 419</ref>.</note>
                            If we are to get our message out and our programs in, we must have
                            prompt action.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_WRE_1"><hi rend="strong">White</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>