<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>477. Memorandum From Secretary of State Vance to President to President
                    Carter</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d477</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">477</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-08-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-08-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="reczhNQIs9rGlNS1M" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96008124"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Humanitarian assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="rec14HP3WEhVvFEi9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001220"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Private sector</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recUsSXH96nnonu86" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85115899"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rural development</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="reclX4mzFRYzavuL4" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections">Free elections</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">General Assembly</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-08-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-08-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="477"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d477">
                <head>477. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_VC_1"
                        >Vance</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_CJ_3">Carter</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d477fn1">Source: Carter Library, National
                        Security Affairs, Staff Material, Office, Presidential Advisory Board, Box
                        83, Sensitive XX: 8/79. Secret. <persName corresp="#p_CJ_3"
                            >Carter</persName> wrote in the top right-hand corner of the page:
                        “Cy—A) Sounds good. B) Severe budget restraints. C) See Zbig’s 2 questions.
                        J.” Reference is to two questions <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1"
                            >Brzezinski</persName> wrote on an undated note: “Two additional issues:
                        1) How do we reassure those whom we want to undertake reforms that they will
                        be protected from outside subversion; i.e. do we draw the line somehow? 2)
                        How do we discourage, isolate or punish the Cubans—and also entice them into
                        a healthier relationship?” <persName corresp="#p_DLG_1">Denend</persName>
                        (on behalf of <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>) returned
                            <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>’s memorandum and <persName
                            corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>’s handwritten note to <persName
                            corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> under an August 16 memorandum.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1979-08-14">August 14, 1979</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Central American Strategy</item>
                </list>
                <p>During my consultations with Latin American Chiefs of State and Foreign Ministers
                    in Quito, Ecuador, August 10 and 11, I found a remarkable consensus regarding
                    the situation in Central America.</p>
                <p>With regard to Nicaragua:</p>
                <p>—All recognized the potential danger we face in Nicaragua and the presence of
                    Marxists in some key positions. They agreed, however, that it would be a mistake
                    to assume that radical influences will inevitably prevail.</p>
                <p>—Virtually all agreed that it was important to assist the new government
                    actively, and to be highly visible in Nicaragua through extension of economic,
                    humanitarian and technical assistance.</p>
                <p>—All urged the US to respond promptly and generously to the needs and requests of
                    the new government. All urged that humanitarian and economic aid be extended
                    without “political conditions,” and that what the US did would be central to
                    what eventually happened.</p>
                <p>—All urged substantive economic aid; they also urged some response to bilateral
                    requests for military assistance, although they recognized this was more
                    complicated and difficult.</p>
                <p>—Most nations are planning or have undertaken economic and humanitarian
                    assistance. The Andean Group is planning extensive help to the new government
                    through the Latin American Economic System organization (<gloss
                        target="#t_SELA_1">SELA</gloss>). Most are dubious about their capacity to
                    help militarily, but Panama and Costa Rica are aiding the police, and Venezuela
                    is prepared to consider military requests.</p>
                <p>With regard to Central America:</p>
                <pb facs="1295" n="1244" xml:id="pg_1244"/>
                <p>—All agreed Honduras was in the best shape of the northern tier countries, was
                    embarked on an encouraging course, and should be assisted.</p>
                <p>—All agreed that the situation in El Salvador was dangerous, and that some
                    movement toward a more open system through the electoral process offered the
                    only chance to avoid confrontation and polarization.</p>
                <p>—All agreed on the rigidities in the Guatemala situation and potential dangers
                    there, and that moves to reduce these should be encouraged.</p>
                <p>A number of Latin American leaders stressed to me that the US was too inactive in
                    Latin America; that there was need for a “new dimension” to our relationship,
                    for more active involvement in and response to Latin American problems and
                    concerns. It was clear that Central American events have become something of a
                    watershed, and have focused the worries and concerns of Latin America on our
                    relationship. This gives us both a challenge and an opportunity.</p>
                <p>To respond to the Central American situation specifically, we are undertaking the
                    following lines of action:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">With regard to Nicaragua:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>—We will continue substantial amounts of food and humanitarian assistance.</p>
                <p>—We are requesting reprogramming of $8.5 million of <gloss target="#t_FY_1"
                        >FY</gloss> 1979 funds for reconstruction and humanitarian assistance, and
                    will be proposing substantial funds for <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 1980
                    for economic reconstruction aid. We have despatched technical personnel to
                    assess reconstruction needs.</p>
                <p>—We are encouraging private contacts with the private sector and private
                    institutions in business, labor, media and other sectors.</p>
                <p>—We propose to provide a military team to assess and vet Nicaraguan requests for
                    military assistance. We propose to be responsive in terms of training and
                    provision of non-lethal material. Mobile Training Teams can also assist in
                    reconstruction efforts.</p>
                <p>—We will provide technical experts and assistance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">With regard to Honduras:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>—We will encourage the Honduran Government’s present policy of return to
                    constitutional government, and its social and rural development programs.</p>
                <p>—We are planning increases in economic assistance for social and economic
                    development, including rural “impact” programs.</p>
                <p>—We will provide modest increases in military training and provision of
                    equipment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">With regard to El Salvador:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>—We propose to explore with the President of El Salvador the institution of
                    electoral reforms and a credible electoral process for the <pb facs="1296"
                        n="1245" xml:id="pg_1245"/> March 1980 municipal elections; we would propose
                    to provide a quid pro quo of economic and limited military assistance for human
                    rights and political improvement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">With regard to Guatemala:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>—We will continue to press for human rights improvement and to persuade the
                    Guatemala Government to prepare for free elections in the 1982 presidential
                    elections, preferably with a civilian president. We would be prepared to be
                    helpful to the extent we can to achieve these improvements.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Multilaterally:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>—We will continue in close consultations with other Latin American nations,
                    especially the democracies, and encourage parallel and coordinated actions.</p>
                <p>—I intend to go to the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> General Assembly
                    meeting in La Paz in October both to demonstrate high-level interest and to
                    continue personal consultations and exchanges.<note n="2" xml:id="d477fn2"
                        >October 20–23.</note>
                </p>
                <p>—We will strengthen cooperation with regional groups such as the Andean Pact.</p>
                <p>Clearly, our Central American strategy—and in Latin America generally—will
                    require substantial resource inputs. We have tried to promote reform in Latin
                    America by persuasion and encouragement. We have sometimes created political
                    vacuums by denial of economic and military assistance, but we have not been able
                    to formulate and deliver on a partnership approach to bring about constructive
                    change. As we have created vacuums, it has been inevitable that others would
                    enter; not just Cuba, but such countries as Panama in Nicaragua or China in
                    Chile. The crisis in Central America now challenges us to formulate a
                    partnership approach in which we provide substantial resources provided
                    constructive change moves forward. Our greatest challenge is in Nicaragua where
                    the devastation has been so great, and where the task of reconstruction will be
                    seen by Nicaraguans and Latins generally as a test of our sincerity and
                    capacity.</p>
                <p>Additional resources are clearly required for these new challenges and crises. I
                    will be sending you a separate memorandum outlining the funding I believe is
                    needed for Central America.<note n="3" xml:id="d477fn3">See <ref target="#d480"
                            >Document 480</ref>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
