<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-02-18T07:50:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-02-18T07:50:00-05:00" n="71" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d71">
                        <head>71. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in
                                Venezuela<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d71fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Office of the
                                Secretariat Staff, Records of the Office of the Deputy Secretary,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Warren Christopher</persName>, Lot
                                81D113, Box 17, Human Rights—Nicaragua II. Confidential; Niact
                                Immediate; Exdis. Drafted by text received from the White House;
                                cleared in <gloss target="#t_SSO_1">S/S–O</gloss>; approved by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MFFJ_1">McNeill</persName> (<gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>).</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-02-18T12:50:00+00:00">February 18, 1978,
                                1250Z</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>43981. Exdis for Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_VVPP_1">Vaky</persName>. Subject: Presidential Reply to <persName corresp="#p_PCA_1">Perez</persName> Letter on Nicaragua. Please
                            deliver following letter to President <persName corresp="#p_PCA_1">Perez</persName> from President <persName corresp="#p_CJ_3">Carter</persName> dated February 17, 1978.</p>
                        <p>Begin text: Dear Mr. President:</p>
                        <p>I very much appreciated your thoughtful letter of January 31.<note n="2" xml:id="d71fn2">See <ref target="#d68fn3">footnote 3, Document
                                    68</ref>.</note> I want to affirm the importance I attach to our
                            agreement to exchange views on all matters, but especially on the
                            defense and enhancement of human rights. I have been giving careful
                            thought to your letter.</p>
                        <p>I share your concern about the tumultuous situation which has developed
                            in Nicaragua. There are two important issues at stake: the status of
                            human rights in Nicaragua and the evolution of the Nicaraguan political
                            system.</p>
                        <p>Your description of the human rights situation in Nicaragua was a moving
                            one. We are in complete agreement on the need for an urgent visit by the
                            Inter-American Human Rights Commission. My Ambassador in Managua has
                            informed President <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> of our
                            concern and has suggested that the Government of Nicaragua invite the
                            commission for an urgent visit. After receiving your letter, I
                            instructed my Ambassador to speak to President <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> again and repeat our request.
                            If we do not receive a positive response soon, our governments should
                            consult on the most effective way to secure President <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName>’s cooperation.</p>
                        <pb facs="0253" n="202" xml:id="pg_202"/>
                        <p>On the broader issue of political change in Nicaragua, I would like to
                            share my thoughts with you. I deeply respect your strong feelings about
                            the need for fundamental and democratic political change in
                            Nicaragua.</p>
                        <p>We can and will voice our preference for increased democratization in all
                            countries, and have done so regarding Nicaragua. We can and will be
                            prepared to support basic human rights and to shape our policies toward
                            this end. But we will not intervene or impose specific political
                            solutions for individual countries. I know that our two governments will
                            act as one on these issues.</p>
                        <p>In this period of political crisis in Nicaragua, the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> Government has suspended new arms
                            transfers and withheld some economic assistance to the <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> regime, and he is clearly aware
                            that he is on his own. Though our sympathies are clearly in favor of
                            steady evolution toward greater democracy, I am convinced that the
                            Nicaraguans can only build a viable and lasting democracy that responds
                            to their own particular needs, if they undertake and complete the task
                            themselves.</p>
                        <p>Because of your knowledge and long experience with Nicaraguan and Central
                            American politics, I value your counsel as the situation develops. I
                            agree that we cannot remain indifferent to human rights violations in
                            Nicaragua and elsewhere, and I am proud that we speak together on
                            this.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely,</p>
                        <p>Signed <persName corresp="#p_CJ_3">Jimmy Carter</persName></p>
                        <p>His Excellency</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_PCA_1">Carlos Andres Perez</persName></p>
                        <p>President of the Republic of Venezuela</p>
                        <p>Caracas</p>
                        <p>P.S. (Handwritten) Best wishes. I look forward to seeing you in Caracas.
                            End text of letter.</p>
                        <p>When you deliver the letter to President <persName corresp="#p_PCA_1">Perez</persName>, the President would like you to deliver the
                            following oral message: “We sincerely regret the delay. We fully
                            understand the importance of the issue. Indeed the response was delayed
                            precisely because your letter raised many very difficult questions,
                            which led us to reexamine our longstanding policy to Nicaragua and to
                            the entire question of the appropriate role for the United States
                            Government in similar situations.”</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_VC_1"><hi rend="strong">Vance</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>