<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>73. Telegram From the Embassy in Nicaragua to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d73</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">73</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1978-03-14T11:40:00-05:00" notAfter="1978-03-14T11:40:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="rec14HP3WEhVvFEi9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001220"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Private sector</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051619"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fraud</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="reckOJp7RF2apAIO3" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85004558"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Amnesty</term>
                    <term ref="rec8uqG4zFwFzxdlO" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104422"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Political prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98003467"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democratization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-03-14T11:40:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-03-14T11:40:00-05:00" n="73"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d73">
                <head>73. Telegram From the Embassy in Nicaragua to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d73fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D780113–0799. Confidential; Immediate.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Managua</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1978-03-14T16:40:00+00:00">March 14, 1978, 1640Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1217. Subject: Status Report on <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName>’s
                    Initiatives.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary:</hi> President <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1"
                        >Somoza</persName> has taken several initiatives toward pacifying the
                    opposition which, since the assassination of <persName corresp="#p_CCPJ_1">Pedro
                        Joaquin Chamorro</persName>, has become highly polarized and dedicated to
                    ousting <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> now.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d73fn2">In telegram 1193 from Managua, March 13, the Embassy
                        reported on Solaun’s March 9 meeting with <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1"
                            >Somoza</persName> stating that <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1"
                            >Somoza</persName> was defensive and likely “genuinely frustrated by his
                        apparent inability to get any accommodating response from his opponents now
                        that he has launched what he believes are conciliatory initiatives.”
                            <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> was also frustrated by
                        “what he feels is a continuing coolness toward him on the part of the <gloss
                            target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>.” The Embassy commented: “The opposition,
                        of course, feels that it has been deceived so many times by the <persName
                            corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somozas</persName> in the past that it is not about
                        to grasp eagerly at the President’s initiatives.” (National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Office of the Secretariat Staff, Records
                        of the Office of the Deputy Secretary, <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Warren
                            Christopher</persName>, Lot 81D113, Box 18, Human Rights—PD–30)</note>
                    Some of the initiatives correspond to issues which had earlier been demanded by
                    the opposition. Others were the ideas of <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1"
                        >Somoza</persName> and his advisors and designed to obtain support from
                    certain sectors. To date the opposition, which comprises diverse political,
                    labor and private sector elements and public organizations, has not accepted as
                    constructive any of the initiatives. This reaction is primarily rooted in a
                    deep-seated belief that <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> cannot be
                    trusted regardless of what he says or appears to be doing. End summary.</p>
                <pb facs="0256" n="205" xml:id="pg_205"/>
                <p>1. On Feb 26, <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> publicly announced
                    for the first time his intention to return to private life at the end of his
                        term.<note n="3" xml:id="d73fn3">In telegram 1002 from Managua, March 1, the
                        Embassy analyzed <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName>’s February
                        26 speech to a Liberal Party rally. The telegram noted that speech was
                        “designed to demonstrate Liberal Party-<gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss>
                        strength” but “was far less successful than touted” and contained a “series
                        of proposals rather than tangible actions.” (National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D780094–0651)</note> This statement which specifically included dropping his
                    control of the National Guard (<gloss target="#t_GN_1">GN</gloss>) addressed the
                    concern of the opposition that <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName>
                    might try to retain the Presidency through some constitutional trickery or
                    perhaps even a coup as well as their belief that <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1"
                        >Somoza</persName> would continue to rule the country as Chief Director of
                    the <gloss target="#t_GN_1">GN</gloss>. Because the opposition does not trust
                        <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName>, their reaction is that there
                    still is no guarantee that he will comply with his declared intent. There is
                    also the belief that the results of the next Presidential election would be far
                    more favorable if it occurred when someone other than <persName
                        corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> were in the Presidency. The opposition
                    has suggested that as a demonstration of his intentions, <persName
                        corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> should resign now his position as Chief
                    Director of the <gloss target="#t_GN_1">GN</gloss>. It is not likely <persName
                        corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> would accept this demand during the
                    current civil strife and active insurgency, but he has not commented on this
                    issue. Such a step could have a significant impact on opposition thinking.</p>
                <p>2. <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> has announced a commitment to
                    having justice realized in the <persName corresp="#p_CCPJ_1">Chamorro</persName>
                    assassination case. This has been a key opposition demand. The <gloss
                        target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> invited an observer from the I–A Press
                    Association which the <gloss target="#t_IAPA_1">IAPA</gloss> rejected. It is
                    doubtful that an observer mission would have had any significant impact on
                    attitudes or on the investigation. On Feb 26 <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1"
                        >Somoza</persName> announced he would establish a national commission to
                    review the <persName corresp="#p_CCPJ_1">Chamorro</persName> assassination
                    investigation. On March 10 he stated he would ask Min. Gov. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MA_2">Mora</persName> to set up the commission. To date nothing
                    concrete has happened in the investigation to uncover the author(s) of the crime
                    which occurred two months ago. The problem in the assassination investigation
                    may be that the only significant witness(es) may be in the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> and not extraditable. If this is the case, the
                    assassination investigation may never be satisfactorily completed. The <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> lawyer for Dr. <persName corresp="#p_RP_1"
                        >Ramos</persName>, who has been indicted for the assassination, told EmbOff
                    his client may be willing to make depositions from Miami but is unwilling to
                    voluntarily return to Nicaragua.</p>
                <p>3. On Feb 26 <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> announced his
                    intention to open up the political process by making it easier for other
                    political parties to participate. The Liberal Party introduced in the Congress
                    partial amendments to the Constitution to this effect. The changes would: a) end
                    the Conservative Party’s 40 percent automatic congressional representation and
                        <pb facs="0257" n="206" xml:id="pg_206"/> representation in governmental and
                    autonomous entities; b) provide for other minority party representation in the
                    congressional leadership and in the electoral tribunals; and c) remove the
                    electoral law from the Constitution so it can be more easily amended to
                    implement this initiative. The opposition has varying reactions to this
                    initiative which they concede is the first tangible manifestation of <persName
                        corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName>’s action on a long-standing grievance.
                    The oppositionists are unanimous that the constitutional reform in itself is not
                    enough because it allows for the majority party (which they see to be the
                    Liberal in the next election) to control the election process, therefore, the
                    liberals can perpetuate their political power through fraud. They also see a
                    danger in removing the electoral law from the Constitution as this makes it
                    easier and quicker to amend, which they view as an open door to subsequent
                    manipulation by <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName>. Further they
                    want to have an idea of the nature of <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1"
                        >Somoza</persName>’s intentions in the electoral law reform before they
                    accept the constitutional reform. Where the opposition has had differences is
                    over whether they should make an effort to address these concerns in a
                    counter-initiative or should simply wash their hands of the entire proposal
                    leaving to <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> the responsibility for
                    unilateral action. The officially recognized conservatives are for a
                    counter-proposal, but the <gloss target="#t_UDEL_1">UDEL</gloss> coalition and
                    other splinter parties were reluctant to agree (partly because they were
                    uncomfortable with the conservatives defending their interests and partly
                    because they see a counter-proposal as the equivalent of initiation of renewed
                    dialogue which they feel is as yet not appropriate).</p>
                <p>Emb understands that on Feb 13, agreement was reached to go ahead with the
                    counter-proposal. <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> said in his
                    March 10 press conference that the details of the electoral reform initiative
                    are negotiable.</p>
                <p>4. <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> announced on Feb 26 he would
                    take an initiative to advance free trade unionism by removing the government
                    from passing on the merits of each application for official recognition. The
                    Social Christian and Socialist Labor Confederations labeled this move as
                    trickier and rejected it. The political opposition has argued <persName
                        corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> could show his intentions by approving
                    currently pending petitions for recognition, and is likely to be suspicious of
                    the new proposal until they see the proposed labor law revision. A potential
                    problem with this initiative is that it apparently would remove some protection
                    for officially recognized unions against rival management-organized and
                    supported organizational efforts. In disputes, the Labor Ministry would,
                    therefore, apparently gain flexibility in dealing with complaints from rival
                    factions.</p>
                <p>5. <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName>’s announcement of social
                    welfare initiatives in land sale guarantees, a code for renter-lessee relations,
                    and a tax policy change <pb facs="0258" n="207" xml:id="pg_207"/> on idle land
                    had been in the gestation stage for some time as a result of a study of changes
                    which would permit improved conditions of land tenancy in which <gloss
                        target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> participated. In fact, two of the initiatives
                    were based on prior agreement for continuation of US participation in the
                    Invierno Program.<note n="4" xml:id="d73fn4">The Invierno Program was a program
                        for rural development funded by the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                        Agency for International Development.</note> The opposition reaction was
                    two-fold: a) the idle land tax initiative was a reprisal against medium and
                    small farmers—this reaction ignores the fact that there is an exemption for
                    small land holders, and the wealthiest landowners are the ones who are most
                    likely to under-utilize their land and be forced to think about selling the
                    excess to others; and b) the initiatives are not true agrarian reform in that
                    they didn’t contemplate breaking up large land holdings and distributing parcels
                    to poor farmers. The counter-argument is that the initiatives are exactly so
                    designed in that the large landholders will be pressured to rent or sell unused
                    land to poor farmers and, if they want to sell, the guarantee proposal will give
                    the sellers confidence they will be paid.</p>
                <p>6. The other social welfare proposals regarding extending social security
                    coverage and making mandatory the 13th month bonus have been challenged only in
                    that there are doubts that they can be achieved in that the government has
                    strained resources for providing the benefits and that they are an economic
                    reprisal in that the employer has to pay the benefit. There has been no popular
                    reaction of support from the intended beneficiaries who by nature are skeptical
                    until they have a bird in hand. <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName>,
                    in answer, said in his March 10 press conference that funds were available
                    through international lending and that the social security system would be
                    extended to two departments this year and the rest of the country the following
                    year. He had previously offered to extend social security to rural workers in
                    his Labor Day speech last May first.</p>
                <p>7. Other <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> statements the equivalent
                    of initiatives have incuded the fact he would accept in a dialogue positive
                    suggestions for restructuring the National Guard, amnesty for political
                    prisoners; that reform of the radio and TV code had already been accepted for
                    study in the Congress, and that he would order a halt to the practice of busing
                    people like cattle in pickup trucks to Managua’s poor districts. The next day La
                    Prensa said the degrading busing practice continues. On this and the other
                    promises the opposition predictably and understandably will wait for concrete
                    results.</p>
                <p>8. In the area of atmospherics, <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName>
                    has for the first time in recent memory publicly acknowledged excessive use of
                    force by the <pb facs="0259" n="208" xml:id="pg_208"/>
                    <gloss target="#t_GN_1">GN</gloss>, has acknowledged that the participants in
                    the national work stoppage broke no laws, has repeatedly denied that he would
                    take any reprisals against opposition private sector leaders, and has implicitly
                    acknowledged publicly that <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName>-family
                    control of the <gloss target="#t_GN_1">GN</gloss> has impeded
                    institutionalization of that organization as well as democratization of the
                    country. The opposition would chalk these statements to pure atmospherics,
                    conceded under pressure and designed purely to appease the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                </p>
                <p>9. <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> has continued to publicly state
                    since his Feb 26 speech that he seeks dialogue with the opposition. His
                    sincerity in accepting true change toward democratization is doubted by the
                    opposition because <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> in the past
                    has always benefited from the deals he has struck with the opposition when the
                    intent of the compromise has not been respected. They see this situation as
                    equivalent to the fly accepting an invitation from the spider. This leads the
                    opposition to find it easier to agree to a common position that <persName
                        corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName> must go now than it is for them to
                    obtain common agreement on how to respond to the announced initiatives. At the
                    same time, however, many political and private sector oppositionists are
                    concerned about the growing sympathy for the <gloss target="#t_FSLN_1"
                        >FSLN</gloss> guerrillas and outbreaks of violence. These people are willing
                    to consider dialogue if they are not forced to run the risk of being seen as
                    being drawn in by <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Somoza</persName>. Their wariness
                    is only likely to be satisfied if they respond to the call to a dialogue by an
                    outside agent (e.g., the Church) and when <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1"
                        >Somoza</persName>’s initiatives are translated into a significant concrete
                    demonstration of his willingness to surrender power. To date neither of these
                    conditions exist in their opinion.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Solaun</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
