<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>105. Memorandum for the Record</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d105</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">105</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-08-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2HqULsC7KBoXeW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006378"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public relations</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="recWpOYNUONIWKYCh" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85109354"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Explosion</term>
                    <term ref="rec14HP3WEhVvFEi9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001220"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Private sector</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec_korean_war" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="korean-war" subject="korean-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073119" lcsh-match="exact">Korean War</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-08-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="105"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d105">
                <head>105. Memorandum for the Record<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d105fn1"
                        >Source: Johnson Library, National Security File, Country File, Vietnam,
                        Public Affairs Policy Committee. Confidential. Prepared by Gordon Chase of
                        the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff on August 4.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-08-03">August 3, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>August 3 Dinner Meeting on the Information Problem</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CSD1">Cater</persName>, Mr.
                            <persName>Bundy</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJA1"
                            >Califano</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLH1">Marks</persName>,
                        Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chancellor</persName>, Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_GJL1">Greenfield</persName>, Mr.
                        <persName>Jorden</persName>, Mr. <persName>Leibman</persName>, Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_CCL1">Cooper</persName>, and Mr. <persName>Chase</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>At Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CSD1">Cater</persName>’s invitation, the group met
                    for dinner at the White House Staff Mess to discuss the Government’s information
                    program in the field of foreign affairs, and primarily as it pertains to the
                    domestic audience. The discussion generally covered (a) the nature of the
                    information problem and (b) general and specific ideas and agencies for meeting
                    the information problem.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">1. The Nature of the Information Problem</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>(a)</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CSD1">Cater</persName> said that, with respect
                        to public information, we lack many of the strengths we once had. We don’t
                        seem to have independent validators of policy any more—the Vandenbergs and
                        the Connollys. We don’t seem to have elder statesmen any more—<persName
                            corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> is the exception. We don’t seem
                        to have the newscasting we once had—the Ed Murrows and the Elmer Davises, to
                        quieten us and to give us perspective; instead, the nature of T.V. is such
                        that we always seem to get our news on a fragmentary basis. Finally, with
                        the exception of the President, the Government does not seem to have the
                        spokesmen it once had. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CSD1">Cater</persName> went
                        on to say that our public posture is fragile; we rely too much on the
                        President and too much on specific facts. There seems to be no basic
                        understanding of the broader aspects on the part of the American people. And
                        with this situation, we are extremely vulnerable to rumor, gossip, and quick
                        reverses.</item>
                    <label>(b)</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GJL1">Greenfield</persName>, with specific
                            reference to Vietnam, outlined a number of dimensions that he sees as
                            part of the information problem. First, we are always meeting the crisis
                            of the moment. In practice, there is little time to think about the long
                            term or the philosophical. We only plug holes and run as fast as we can
                            to stay even. Second, we seem to be obsessed by Vietnam. Foreigners
                            especially believe that the President thinks of nothing else but
                            Vietnam. This is not a healthy image.</p>
                        <pb facs="0327" n="295" xml:id="pg_295"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Third</hi>, we do not always keep the arithmetic in
                            mind. There are almost 300 accredited correspondents in Vietnam and we
                            must recognize that we are going to have to live with some unfortunate
                            stories—e.g., brutality by Americans. Fourth, while our credibility with
                            the press is improving, we are still not credible enough. We suffer
                            substantial losses when we are not accurate, and there are plenty of
                            inaccuracies. (Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJA1">Califano</persName>
                            seconded this point.) Fifth, we do not have the highest quality military
                            spokesmen in Vietnam; they should be improved. Sixth, we are involved in
                            too many cliches. Some of them are all right but others may not be; we
                            should re-examine them. For example, we should look again at “Our
                            country’s honor is at stake”; one day we may be sorry that we are tied
                            too closely to this stand. Another cliche we ought to examine is “Our
                            friends won’t trust us if we desert the Vietnamese”; this one gives us
                            trouble when foreigners say publicly that they want us out of Vietnam—in
                            effect, pulling the rug out from under us. (Mr.
                                <persName>Bundy</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CCL1"
                                >Cooper</persName> differed with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GJL1"
                                >Greenfield</persName> at this point; both agreed, however, that we
                            should make more of foreign statements which support our argument—e.g.,
                            Willy Brandt’s reference to the conflict as “our war.”)</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Seventh</hi>, we should probably try to do something
                            about this curious business involving newsmen who say “the American
                            people don’t know what’s going on.” When asked what they want, these
                            newsmen say that they want more specific facts (e.g., how many tons of
                            bombs were dropped); at the same time, they agree, when pressed, that
                            the answer does not really bear at all on the essence of the Vietnam
                            situation. Maybe this curious questioning relates to the proposition
                            that the Vietnam war is different from anything we’ve seen and that we
                            are all groping for ways to understand it. Mr. <persName
                                corresp="#p_CCL1">Cooper</persName> agreed that part of the
                            information problem does relate to the fact that Vietnam represents a
                            difficult and brand new type of warfare. While correspondents may not
                            think it is important when B-52’s hit a rice dump, it really is
                            important. In short, we may not know how to fight the war in Vietnam but
                            the correspondents don’t know how to report it either.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(c)</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>Mr. <persName>Jorden</persName> said that an essential element in our
                            Vietnam information problem is that the South Vietnamese don’t say
                            anything. They don’t say why they are fighting or where they are going.
                            We must get them to state their own case—that what they are doing is
                            good, just, etc. It would not only help with their own people but with
                            the outside world as well.</p>
                        <p>Picking up on this thought, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CCL1"
                                >Cooper</persName> said that unfortunately the <gloss
                                target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> is shadowy—there is not even a <gloss
                                target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> ambassador here. As a matter of fact,
                            for some time we have been trying in vain to get the <gloss
                                target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> to do three relatively simple
                            things—appoint an ambassador to the U.S.; appoint an information officer
                            to the U.S.; and hire an American public relations firm to represent the
                                <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> in the U.S. Partly as a result
                            of the <pb facs="0328" n="296" xml:id="pg_296"/>
                            <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>’s ineffectual and mushy public
                            information program, the American people do not think we are really
                            associated with anyone in Vietnam. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLH1"
                                >Marks</persName> seconded this point and noted that the American
                            people do not really understand that the South Vietnamese have committed
                            500,000 people to the struggle.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>(d)</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chancellor</persName> said that this is
                        indeed a remarkable situation; we are faced with an entirely different kind
                        of war and there is no participation in the public information field by the
                        people one would expect to hear from the most—e.g., South Vietnam, North
                        Vietnam, and the Viet Cong. (Some members of the group noted that the Viet
                        Cong was indeed very active in the field.) In essence, perhaps we have, for
                        the first time in our experience, a non-packageable commodity. Perhaps,
                        therefore, we should try to emulate the 19th century British and try to get
                        a sort of general commitment and support by the American people rather than
                        a specific commitment and support for Vietnam. The “This is a long-term
                        proposition—we are a world power and are stuck with this sort of thing”
                        psychology may in fact bring greater comfort to the American people than the
                        definition of the struggle as one of sharp confrontation. Mr.
                            <persName>Bundy</persName> recognized the force in Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJ1">Chancellor</persName>’s argument but added, among other
                        things, that we could never hope for enough support, in the general sense,
                        to do the job. We must get involved in the specifics as well. We are faced
                        with a situation of instant transmission of village episodes. The Communists
                        know this dimension and deal with it effectively; we, too, must cope with
                        this dimension.</item>
                    <label>(e)</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Leibman</persName> said that the American people do not yet
                        really understand how we got into Vietnam in the first place; they have
                        received only generalities and they need specifics. Mr.
                            <persName>Bundy</persName> agreed that there is a problem here, but
                        thought that this particular piece of exposition might simply not be
                        manageable. Our best posture may be to say simply that somehow we are there
                        and that we have to stay.</item>
                    <label>(f)</label>
                    <item>The group noted that the nature of the information problem in Vietnam is
                        changing in some respects. Mr. <persName>Leibman</persName> said that the
                        problem will be intensified immeasurably when the effects of the doubling of
                        the draft are felt. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chancellor</persName>
                        said that the press is just beginning to get active in Vietnam. With
                        increased staffs, we are going to get fewer people doing general
                        interpretive work and we are going to get more of the poignant, Ernie
                        Pyle-type stories. This may help our effort in getting support from the
                        American people as the war starts to hit them locally. In this regard, Mr.
                            <persName>Leibman</persName> noted that it may be useful to consider
                        building local heroes rather than national heroes.</item>
                    <label>(g)</label>
                    <item>The group discussed the similarities and differences between the Korean
                        War and the Vietnamese war. Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName> said that the
                        American people may have more patience than they did during Korea; twelve
                        years have passed. He noted that people have been saying for the past <pb
                            facs="0329" n="297" xml:id="pg_297"/> several years that the American
                        people would explode if nothing decisive happened in Vietnam; yet, there has
                        been no explosion. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CSD1">Cater</persName> noted
                        the anomaly of Korea which, in fact, was a real success story but was never
                        understood as such by the American people. The job is even tougher in
                        Vietnam.</item>
                    <label>(h)</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GJL1">Greenfield</persName> raised two questions
                        which were largely left unanswered by the group: What reaction would we like
                        to get from the American people and from foreigners? Why do people seem to
                        understand that it is necessary to fight over Berlin but not over
                        Vietnam?</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">2. Meeting the Information Problem</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>(a)</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CCL1">Cooper</persName> ticked off some of the
                        specific projects that are now under way. First, there are the “American
                        Friends of Vietnam.” While they still have a long way to go, they have done
                        some good work; they work with students, publish a journal, run a speakers’
                        bureau and have an elaborate mailing list. While the Government has been
                        helping and advising this group, we can’t get too involved; if it becomes
                        too closely identified with the U.S. Government, its credibility will be
                        badly affected. Second, we have sent 30 students to Vietnam. Our follow-up
                        will, of course, be crucial. Third, we have brought some Vietnamese
                        intellectuals over here. Fourth, we have been providing kits to certain
                        speakers. There are other projects too.</item>
                    <label>(b)</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>Mr. <persName>Leibman</persName> said that the key elements that had been
                            raised are the complexity and built-in contradiction of policy and the
                            need for perspective and continuity. With regard to continuity, we
                            should use more effectively the President’s experience. Remember that
                            “he was there” for 30 years. Mr. <persName>Leibman</persName> went on to
                            say that part of the answer lies in using the private sector
                            effectively. The private sector is anxious to be used.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName>Leibman</persName> then went on to describe a number of
                            possible projects that might be explored. First, perhaps the private
                            sector could brief journalists and editors. There are plenty of
                            institutions and schools that would be willing and anxious to do the
                            job. Second, we could put into effect the “That Was the Week That Was”
                            concept to get across the idea of perspective and “the whole
                            chessboard.” Third, we could make use of the Industrial College of the
                            Armed Forces graduates. Fourth, with respect to high school teachers,
                            there are three different types of programs that could be used—(a)
                            special summer institutes on appropriate political subjects; (b) special
                            programs for all teacher attendees at summer school; (c) year-round
                            programs for teachers as part of in-service training. Fifth, we could
                            use trade association forums. Mr. <persName>Leibman</persName> added
                            that these ideas are only illustrative. The point is that there is a
                            vacuum. If we don’t fill it, then it will be filled against us. He went
                            on to emphasize that the teach-in problem is almost here again and that
                            we should be ready.</p>
                    </item>
                    <pb facs="0330" n="298" xml:id="pg_298"/>
                    <label>(c)</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GJL1">Greenfield</persName> noted that the only
                        thing that makes our present posture swing is that the people have
                        confidence in the President. Mr. <persName>Leibman</persName> added that
                        this is one reason why the President must always be absolutely credible. Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_CSD1">Cater</persName> interjected that this is
                        evidence of how fragile our posture is and went on to say that the President
                        should not have to bear the whole burden of explanation.</item>
                    <label>(d)</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJA1">Califano</persName> made the point that
                        there was great merit in repetition. The President and other spokesmen in
                        the Administration should keep repeating the same facts again and
                        again.</item>
                    <label>(e)</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CCL1">Cooper</persName> noted Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJ1">Chancellor</persName>’s point that there will be an
                        increase in coverage of Vietnam. He went on to suggest that we give serious
                        consideration to educating the editors so that they know which stories are
                        significant and fit to print.</item>
                    <label>(f)</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GJL1">Greenfield</persName> said that we can
                        only use the private sector effectively if there are effective Government
                        spokesmen to support. And there are only four people who can give the
                        Government position effectively—the President, Rusk, <persName
                            corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, and Bundy. Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJ1">Chancellor</persName> said that Bundy is probably not
                        good for the housewife in the back yard; unfortunately, Bundy appeals to the
                        sophisticated and the sophisticated are already rigid in their confusion or
                        in their position pro or con the Administration in Vietnam. Only the other
                        three can do the job that is needed—and, for that matter, <persName
                            corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> probably less than Rusk.</item>
                    <label>(g)</label>
                    <item>The group talked at some length about the problem of coordination of the
                        information effort. Mr. <persName>Leibman</persName>, while recognizing the
                        dangers of too much coordination, noted that it seemed to him that all sorts
                        of people were involved but that no one was clearly carrying the ball or
                        coordinating the effort. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJA1">Califano</persName>
                        said that there is a real need for orchestration on the Government side.
                        Moreover, the only one who can really do the coordinating job effectively
                        and get the right response from the major players is Bundy or <persName
                            corresp="#p_MBD1">Moyers</persName>. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CSD1"
                            >Cater</persName> said that what is needed is a sort of Tsar on the
                        outside—a man with great prestige, preferably from New York, who could pull
                        together and coordinate on the private side. Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName>
                        agreed that there is a coordination problem as well as the ever-present
                        problem of “finding the right man.” He went on to say, however, that the
                        private sector would probably not sit still for a ringmaster. He also
                        suggested that perhaps we do not want to get so heavily organized either in
                        the Government or in the private sector in the area of public
                            information.<note n="2" xml:id="d105fn2">A follow-up meeting was held on
                            August 4. (Memorandum for the record by Chase, August 4; ibid.) See also
                                <ref target="#d117">Document 117</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName>GC</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
