<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>121. Telegram From the Embassy in Vietnam to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d121</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">121</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-08-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-08-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="rec4kNZ3bN6ephN7u" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027420"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Coalition government</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="rec98wm19zxgnAte1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85074300"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Land reform</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HqULsC7KBoXeW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="foreign-currency" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Currency</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-08-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-08-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="121"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d121">
                <head>121. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d121fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 VIET <gloss target="#t_S1"
                            >S</gloss>. Secret; Priority; <gloss target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>.
                        The source text does not indicate a time of transmission; the telegram was
                        received at 9:06 a.m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-08-17"
                            >August 17, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>505. For the President.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Probably the most important political development of the week was an
                        interview with Buddhist bonze, <persName corresp="#p_TQ1">Tri
                            Quang</persName>, in a Hong Kong paper denouncing the Directory
                        government in general and General <persName corresp="#p_Thieu1"
                            >Thieu</persName> in particular. On the military front, the most notable
                        development was that the <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> estimate of
                            <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> losses (1,330 killed in action) was
                        the highest since the war began here.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The Hong Kong Far Eastern Economic Review interview with <persName
                            corresp="#p_TQ1">Tri Quang</persName> quoted him as having said “the
                        people” were against the government and he was also against the government,
                        as well as saying that he hoped the war could be stopped as soon as possible
                        by a cease fire or “by any negotiations which would have the peoples’
                        support”. He was also quoted as saying that a small country like Vietnam
                        could rely only on itself and “certainly on no outsider”. <persName
                            corresp="#p_TQ1">Tri Quang</persName> may claim to have been misquoted
                        as he did following an earlier interview with the same correspondent, but
                        the sentiments attributed to him with respect to the government are
                        consistent with what he has recently been telling Embassy officers. It is
                        harder to interpret his enigmatic remarks with respect to the war. Not many
                        weeks ago, he was privately telling visitors that we should pursue the war
                        more vigorously, bombing the north harder and even taking on the Chinese
                        Communists. Thus, I do not think that we <pb facs="0365" n="333"
                            xml:id="pg_333"/> should conclude that he is swinging toward
                        “neutralism”, that is, negotiations with the Liberation Front for a
                        coalition government. It is also too early to say what form his opposition
                        to the government may take. A few days ago, he told us that he had
                        discouraged the forming of demonstrations in Hue having anti-government
                        character.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> and his party took off for Taipei
                        early Sunday morning,<note n="2" xml:id="d121fn2">August 15.</note> will be
                        going directly from there to Bangkok, and returning here next Saturday or
                        Sunday. I had a good talk with him before he left, both on his trip and some
                        other matters including the “<persName corresp="#p_Chieu1">Chieu
                            Hoi</persName>” program, treatment of prisoners taken in combat and land
                        reform. I do not feel that the substance of what he does in Taipei will
                        cause us any problem but, given his propensity for flamboyant statements, I
                        will not make the same prediction for what he says publicly.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Our people in the field feel that there has been some improvement in
                        popular attitudes as a result of the recent military successes and that
                        popular aversion to the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> continues somewhat
                        to increase although this does not necessarily translate itself into active
                        commitment to or support for the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>On the military side, not only were the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                        losses highest ever but the ratio to friendly troops killed (214) was a
                        little better than six to one. The other indicators were also good with more
                            <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                        weapons captured than government troops missing in action and government
                        weapons lost. The <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> also continued to avoid
                        initiating any actions by major units although they kept up their heavy
                        harassment of villages and outposts. The government made a little progress
                        in clearing lines of communication.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>On the economic side, negotiations with the government on the US currency
                        “black mart” problem made good progress, and we hope that we can have this
                        tied up in the next few days. The rice imports from Thailand appear to have
                        met our immediate needs and should hold the situation until the arrival of
                        additional <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss>-480 rice.<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d121fn3">On a copy of this telegram retyped for President
                                <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>, the President wrote:
                            “Mc—Let’s rush him plenty of rice now.” (Johnson Library, National
                            Security File, Country File, Vietnam, Vol. XXXIX, Memos)</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName>Johnson</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
