<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>168. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d168</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">168</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-10-14T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-10-14T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec_world_war_ii" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="world-war-ii" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148273" lcsh-match="exact">World War II</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-10-14T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-10-14T19:00:00-05:00" n="168"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d168">
                <head>168. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d168fn1"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 27 VIET <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>. Secret; <gloss
                            target="#t_Limdis1">Limdis</gloss>. Drafted by Lisle and approved in
                            <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss> on November 26. The source text is
                        labeled “Part I of III.” The meeting was held in the James Madison Room of
                        the Department of State.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1965-10-14T20:00:00-04:00"
                            >October 14, 1965, 8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">SECRETARY’S DINNER FOR RUMANIAN FOREIGN MINISTER Manescu</p>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Vietnam</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">U.S.</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Secretary Rusk</item>
                            <item>Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">John
                                    Leddy</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Ambassador-Designate Richard H. Davis</item>
                            <item>Raymond E. Lisle, Director of the Office of Eastern European
                                Affairs</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Rumanian</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Foreign Minister Corneliu Manescu</item>
                            <item>Deputy Foreign Minister Mircea Malita</item>
                            <item>Ambassador Petre Balaceanu</item>
                            <item>Ion Baschiru, Counselor, Rumanian Embassy</item>
                            <item>Sergiu Celac, interpreter</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The Secretary said there is no lack of means for communicating with Hanoi,
                    Peiping or Moscow, but we have no evidence yet that they are prepared to talk.
                    We have the impression that Hanoi might be willing to talk, and that Moscow
                    would like to see talks take place, but that Peiping is the real obstacle.
                    Nevertheless, there has been some progress. Hanoi no longer denies the existence
                    of infiltration into South Vietnam from the North, and they no longer insist
                    upon a complete withdrawal of US forces as a precondition for discussions. They
                    still insist, however, that any settlement must be on terms imposed by the
                        <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss>—a condition which the US can never
                    accept.</p>
                <p>The Rumanians, according to Manescu, have some contacts with Hanoi. Since Hanoi
                    is no longer insisting on withdrawal of American forces from South Vietnam as a
                    prerequisite to negotiations, it is unfortunate that the United States
                    apparently cannot consider the cessation of bombings.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said we very definitely can think of stopping the bombing. The
                    Government has promised its own people—and this should be convincing—that
                    American troops will be withdrawn as soon <pb facs="0486" n="454"
                        xml:id="pg_454"/> as North Vietnam ceases its attempt to impose its system
                    on the people of South Vietnam by force. But Hanoi still insists on acceptance
                    of the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> program as a prerequisite to
                    negotiations. We cannot accept the imposition of the <gloss target="#t_NLF1"
                        >NLF</gloss> on South Vietnam—whether by Hanoi, a combination of Hanoi and
                    Peiping, or of Hanoi and Moscow. The Secretary said he was prepared to go to
                    Geneva tomorrow if Hanoi would agree to negotiate without preconditions. There
                    is hope that we may see moves toward peace in Vietnam early next year. It
                    appears that there are divided counsels in Hanoi. The Foreign Minister said he
                    hoped the Secretary was not being too optimistic. The US may be taking external
                    signs as indications of division in Hanoi.</p>
                <p>The US has sufficient contact with Hanoi and with Peiping, according to the
                    Secretary. Apart from our own regular contacts, there are many people who are
                    constantly offering their services. At critical moments, however, when there
                    seems to be possibility for agreement, Peiping moves to get in the way of a
                    settlement. Mr. <persName>Manescu</persName> asked whether the four points made
                    by <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> are unacceptable. The Secretary replied
                    that three of the four points are negotiable. One is entirely
                    unacceptable—imposing the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> program on the
                    people of South Vietnam.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Minister said that one of his colleagues had suggested that, in view
                    of Rumania’s relations with Hanoi, it should try to do something. Mr.
                        <persName>Manescu</persName> had replied that in his view a solution could
                    be reached only by direct talks and that Rumania could not act as a
                    mediator.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that we have our own contacts with Hanoi and he was not asking
                    Mr. <persName>Manescu</persName> to act as a mediator. One could never tell,
                    however, what channel, direct or indirect, might be used. If Rumania should pick
                    up a signal he would only ask Mr. <persName>Manescu</persName> to make sure that
                    the signal was not blocked. The Foreign Minister replied that he would inform
                    his Government of this request.</p>
                <p>Rumania wants its relations with the US to be better than “normal”. The present
                    situation in Southeast Asia could create very great problems. The Foreign
                    Minister said that so far as Vietnam is concerned, he would be saying too little
                    if he said only that we were in disagreement. Rumania cannot understand the US
                    position. The dangers of escalation are always high and the ladder of escalation
                    is one which is very difficult to descend. In the Rumanian view a military
                    solution is impossible; the problem of Vietnam can be solved only by the
                    Vietnamese.</p>
                <p>The Secretary pointed out that we had suffered a great disappointment in
                    Southeast Asia. President Kennedy had come into office and taken a new look at
                    Laos and concluded that if the Laotians were left alone they would not be
                    interested in killing each other. Both the President and Khrushchev had agreed
                    at Vienna that everyone should leave the Laotians to themselves. Thus the Geneva
                    Conference of 1962. We had <pb facs="0487" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/> withdrawn
                    our military, but Hanoi had never accepted the agreement, and had never had less
                    than 6,000 troops in Laos. Nor has <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> stopped
                    using Laos as an infiltration route into South Vietnam. We do not hold Moscow
                    guilty of bad faith, but it is a disappointment to us, since we had hoped it
                    would be the first step to peace in Southeast Asia.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Minister asked, “How do you think that the US will emerge from this
                    mixed-up and venturous program in Southeast Asia?”</p>
                <p>The Secretary replied that he did not know. The choice is between peace, which is
                    possible if North Vietnam leaves South Vietnam alone, or war. This is the
                    agonizing problem. The US would not object if South Vietnam should decide by
                    free and peaceful means to join with North Vietnam. We cannot permit North
                    Vietnam to impose this unity by force, however. We will remain only so long as
                    Hanoi persists in seeking to impose its solution by force. If North Vietnam
                    continues to use force for 20 years, we also will be there for 20 years. If
                    North Vietnam thinks it can wait until the US loses interest and withdraws its
                    forces, it is wrong. Moscow understands that we cannot accept a forceful change
                    in the status quo, just as Moscow itself would not accept a change in the status
                    quo by force. But Hanoi does not understand this.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Minister suggested that perhaps the US should look at the opinions of
                    other countries, to which the Secretary replied that we had done so and are
                    doing so. The 17 unaligned nations have urged negotiations without conditions;
                    we have agreed, but Hanoi has said no. The British Commonwealth had tried to
                    send a group to Peiping, but China had responded by calling the British Prime
                    Minister a nit-wit. Hanoi had sent a delegation to Moscow, but Peiping had moved
                    to block all possibility of agreement.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Minister remarked that Cambodia had put forward a sound proposal some
                    years ago, but the US had rejected it. The Secretary pointed out that we had
                    thought that before there was a general conference there should first be
                    bilateral discussions between Cambodia and Thailand, and Cambodia and South
                    Vietnam. We had used our influence to that end, but Prince Sihanouk had been
                    unwilling to discuss any problems with his neighbors. At any rate, that was
                    three years ago. The Laotian settlement of 1962 had been a critical moment in
                    the move toward peace, but Hanoi had rejected it.</p>
                <p>In response to a remark that in the long run everyone might say that the Chinese
                    were right, the Secretary said that China is being rejected by one country after
                    another—even Indonesia. The Chinese doctrine of military conquest has not been
                    accepted either by the Socialist world or by the Free World. China is headed
                    either to a basic change of policy or to catastrophe. Fortunately many of the
                    Chinese leaders are practical men who are more prudent in actions than in words.
                    The US is not looking for a pretext to attack China. After all, Chinese nuclear
                    capability within the <pb facs="0488" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/> foreseeable
                    future will always be trivial as compared to that of the US. We are not seeking
                    an opportunity for a preventive strike—all that we want is that smaller nations
                    within the range of China be allowed to live in peace. The Rumanians have a
                    stake in this—it is important to establish that the presence of a great power
                    does not mean that small powers in the area must lose their independence or
                    security. We cannot forget that Hitler moved into the Rhineland and into the
                    Sudetenland without opposition, as Japan moved into Manchuria. These
                    developments led to World War II, for which we were partly responsible. We are
                    not going to make the same mistake again. There is one important element which
                    might bring the opposing parties together in Southeast Asia. Peiping and Hanoi
                    continue to talk of the 1954 agreement, as do we. Both parties have also
                    referred to the 1962 Laos agreement. There is some reason to think that these
                    agreements can be the basis for peace in Southeast Asia. If there are disputes,
                    let them be solved by peaceful means. This is basically the position of Moscow,
                    although it cannot fail to support North Vietnam because of its own dispute with
                    Peiping.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
