<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>186. Telegram From the Embassy in Vietnam to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d186</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">186</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-11-02T06:40:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-11-02T06:40:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXe3hjASdIXoUSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066112"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Inflation</term>
                    <term ref="recr8VLurZi7KY9hd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture">Food shortages</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recgHSq0J1Seyqrw9" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="foreign-currency" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Currency</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-11-02T06:40:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-11-02T06:40:00-05:00" n="186"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d186">
                <head>186. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d186fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 15 VIET <gloss target="#t_S1"
                            >S</gloss>. Secret. Repeated to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1"
                            >CINCPAC</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_POLAD1">POLAD</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-11-02T19:40:00+08:00">November 2, 1965, 7:40 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1532. 1. <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> government is just over four
                    months old. While certain strengths are apparent certain stresses within and
                    outside the government also exist. Trouble spots have appeared although the
                    overall situation in Viet-Nam is better today than it was in the early part of
                    1965. Behind the shield of American power a greater measure of security has been
                    established but the political and administrative fabric has not yet developed
                    the necessary strength. This report is designed to outline some of the problems
                    which <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> now confronts as he seeks to
                    retain unity among the leadership and develop effective government.</p>
                <p>2. <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> is well aware of his problems. He
                    recognizes the need for actions and persuasive leadership if he is to survive
                    the pressures threatening a government massively engaged in fighting a bitter
                    war that reaches into almost every corner of the land and affects every facet of
                    Vietnamese life.</p>
                <p>3. Government is faced with complex and potentially dangerous economic problem in
                    form of shortages certain commodities, sharply rising living costs, and
                    inflation. Important as these are intrinsically, they take on greater importance
                    because they have become magnified in the public mind and provide political
                    enemies of government a “safe” weapon for attack. Too timorous to launch a
                    head-on campaign against military government, these elements consider themselves
                    quite safe in associating with spontaneous complaint against inflation and food
                    shortages.</p>
                <p>4. Situation has also produced internal stresses within <persName
                        corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> Cabinet. Minister National Economy Ton was
                    under such heavy fire that he was talking of resigning. Although <persName
                        corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> and Directorate colleagues considered his
                    replacement it appears that Ton has survived for the time being. Merits of case
                    aside, there is always powerful impulse to fire a minister when his area of
                    responsibility presents politically difficult problem.</p>
                <p>5. Pressures for change exist elsewhere within government. The Minister of
                    Interior is unsure of his job. Minister of Public Works and Minister of Social
                    Welfare have been drawing criticism because of alleged failures of their
                    Ministries to function effectively. (Friday <persName corresp="#p_Ky1"
                        >Ky</persName> told Ambassador he had dismissed Minister of Public Works
                    because of his inefficiency, but this has not yet been made known publicly.)</p>
                <pb facs="0538" n="506" xml:id="pg_506"/>
                <p>6. There continues to be grumbling within the military establishment. Dep<gloss
                        target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NHC1">Nguyen Huu Co</persName> is apparently still unhappy
                    at being relieved from post of Chief, Joint General Staff. He has criticized
                        <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> sharply before American and
                    Vietnamese auditors on a number of occasions and word of his remarks has
                    circulated widely in civilian and military circles (and must certainly have been
                    carried back to <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName>). In a recent
                    conversation with General <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName>,
                        <persName corresp="#p_Co1">Co</persName> wondered out loud whether anything
                    could be done to deflate <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName>’s arrogance
                    and force his nose to the grindstone. This is probably an unfair attack on
                        <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> but illustrates the lengths to
                    which <persName corresp="#p_Co1">Co</persName> is now going in his criticism. We
                    have also been hearing of milder criticism of <persName corresp="#p_Ky1"
                        >Ky</persName> from other senior military quarters.</p>
                <p>7. There is a rash of coup rumors, although none are worthy of my trying to react
                    in any way. Before his departure for Hue, Bonze Thich Tri Quang called to warn
                    EmbOff that at least three sudiste groups he knows of are plotting. Adherents to
                    General “Big” Minh and Major General Duong Van Duc, September 13-14 coup leader,
                    are allegedly involved. Story is given substance by fact that <persName
                        corresp="#p_NDT1">Duc</persName> was forcibly removed from Ba Xuyen Province
                    last week by military security service and returned to Saigon (where he was set
                    free) presumably at request of Province Chief who objected to his activities. Re
                    “Big” Minh, town has been full of stories of his imminent return for last two
                    weeks. As we have seen in past, Saigon rumor mills need little raw material in
                    order to operate at full blast. We have also noted that <gloss target="#t_VC1"
                        >VC</gloss> are quick to pick up and broadcast stories of disunity within
                        <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>. We can assume that they are not idle
                    now. While coup reports so far appear to have no firm basis, their currency is a
                    manifestation of the difficulties within the government. They have become so
                    common that <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> has seen fit to denounce
                    the possibility of a coup. Most recently he told press no one could organize a
                    coup at the present time.</p>
                <p>8. On Catholic side of ledger there has been rumor that Generals <persName
                        corresp="#p_NCT1">Nguyen Chanh Thi</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_NHC1">Nguyen Huu Co</persName> were plotting to become Chief of
                    State and Prime Minister respectively with Unified Buddhist Association
                    concurrence and support. Central Buddhists headed by <persName corresp="#p_TQ1"
                        >Tri Quang</persName> remain highly critical of government effectiveness and
                    of General <persName corresp="#p_Thieu1">Thieu</persName> in particular, while
                    old political circles continue to grumble on the sidelines. Catholic circles
                    have been remaining quiet and not agitating against the government but they are
                    basically uncommitted in support of the <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName>
                    government.</p>
                <p>9. Much of foregoing would be irrelevant and unimportant if <persName
                        corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> government could generate momentum and
                    successfully come to grips with more important problems confronting it. However,
                    on basis past experience, rumors and facts of this sort can have insidious
                    effect on minds of many Vietnamese. As the government steels into its tasks for
                    a <pb facs="0539" n="507" xml:id="pg_507"/> longer haul the “out-politicians”
                    launch what have often been irresponsible attacks against government. Members of
                    government are more fully aware of the enormity of tasks confronting them and
                    are forced to come to grips with the hard task of maintaining unity and getting
                    on with the work of government. Some of them, it appears, would rather think of
                    sudden change as a solution.</p>
                <p>10. <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> does not give any obvious outward
                    sign of running out of steam. He remains self-assured and has declared his
                    determination remain as Prime Minister regardless number and magnitude problems
                    confronting him. He is being responsive to the Ambassador’s advice to calm his
                    opponents, seek out his critics, and maintain his authority by persuasion as
                    well as action. He appears more and more as a reflective man. He retains control
                    of the air force and his potential rivals seem to show a healthy respect for
                    U.S. power and some consideration for the desirability of maintaining unity in
                    government. Although <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> has not been
                    receiving the credit due his successes, he has had a few. More than anything,
                    favorable trends in military solution over past few months have strengthened
                    government’s position and dampened earlier fears for security which fostered
                    irrational changes and inspired adventures in leadership.</p>
                <p>11. Important to recall that Directorate unity remains key to political stability
                    in present situation. As long as ten Generals who comprise this body remain in
                    essential accord on this point, coups which bring about fundamental changes in
                        <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>’s organization or direction can probably
                    be avoided. However, pressures such as those outlined above are putting their
                    unity to an important test.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
