<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-11-12T21:23:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-11-12T21:23:00-05:00" n="200" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d200">
                        <head>200. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d200fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27-7 VIET. Secret.
                                Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SAP1">Schwartz</persName>; cleared
                                by <persName corresp="#p_UL1">Unger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MLC1">Meeker</persName>, Sieverts, and Robert H.
                                Miller, Director of the Vietnam Working Group; and approved by
                                Rusk.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-11-12T21:23:00-05:00">November 12, 1965, 9:23 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1315. <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss> for Ambassador from
                            Secretary. I am deeply concerned about limited degree of <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> compliance with Geneva Conventions on
                            treatment of prisoners. As you know, US is responsible under GC for
                            treatment of prisoners transferred from US to <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> custody. Matter is urgent for sake of <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> and US image abroad and as it affects
                            plight of US prisoners held by <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> and
                                <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>We have an obligation to our soldiers and citizens to take every action
                            not detrimental to security that increases likelihood American prisoners
                            will receive satisfactory treatment. Leverage we can bring to bear on
                                <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> through <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss> and other
                            international efforts depends to considerable extent on degree to which
                            US and <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> standards of prisoner
                            treatment meet requirements of Geneva Conventions. I believe that
                            substantial compliance by <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> with Convention and publicity given
                            such compliance constitute one of best available protections against
                            further mistreatment American prisoners.</p>
                        <p>Accordingly request you raise matter personally on urgent basis with
                            Prime Minister and other <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> officials
                            where it will have most effect, impressing on them in strongest terms
                            need for concrete, visible <pb facs="0601" n="569" xml:id="pg_569"/>
                            actions to implement GC. Most urgent requirement is for compliance with
                                <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss> request for lists of prisoners
                            and unaccompanied visits to POW’s. This is essential first step, should
                            not cause serious difficulties, and would have high potential for
                            reciprocal benefits for American prisoners and for favorable
                            publicity.</p>
                        <p>Detailed discussion in <gloss target="#t_SEPTEL1">septel</gloss>.<note n="2" xml:id="d200fn2">Telegram 1314 to Saigon, November 12. (Ibid.)
                                In telegram 1725 from Saigon, November 15, <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> responded that he was
                                preparing an approach to <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> on
                                this issue, but would discuss it with South Vietnamese Foreign
                                Ministry officials to lay the groundwork in advance.
                            (Ibid.)</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong"><persName>Rusk</persName></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>