<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>54. Telegram From Secretary of Defense McNamara to the to the Embassy in
                    Vietnam</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d54</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">54</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-07-07T22:52:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-07-07T22:52:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRywIrZWsI9yUJ7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2007010556"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Helicopter</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="rec6SOt1hMx6m4tne" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085495"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="recTUqfVf9DyIITuJ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001281"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconnaissance</term>
                    <term ref="recTaMVSlos5cWGlh" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014367"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Population control</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military balance</term>
                    <term ref="recAWJwqRIM3ZNS4f" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="recuSPZDcCd8RkSsx" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002736"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Aircraft carrier</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-07-07T22:52:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-07-07T22:52:00-05:00" n="54"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d54">
                <head>54. Telegram From Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                        type="from">McNamara</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in
                        Vietnam</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d54fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Country File, Vietnam, <gloss target="#t_Nodis1"
                            >NODIS</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_LOR1">LOR</gloss>, Vol. II(A). Top
                        Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>. Drafted by
                            <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>. Repeated to <gloss
                            target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> with instructions to pass to
                        General <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName>, who was
                        visiting <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> headquarters. The
                        source text contains handwritten revisions by <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                            >McNamara</persName>; see <ref target="#d54fn2">footnotes 2</ref>–<ref
                            target="#d54fn4">4</ref> below.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-07-07T23:52:00-04:00">July 7, 1965, 11:52 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DEF1">DEF</gloss> 5319. Exclusive for Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>. From SecDef signed <persName
                        corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>. The main purpose of our visit will
                    be to receive from you your recommendations for the number of US combat
                    battalions, artillery battalions, engineering battalions, helicopter companies,
                    tactical aircraft, and total military personnel to be assigned to South Vietnam
                    between now and the end of this year; the time schedule on which such forces are
                    required; the results which we can expect to achieve with such force levels
                    compared to those of alternative programs; the probable requirements for
                    additional forces next year; and the program of political contacts which you
                    propose as a complement to your military actions—we will wish to discuss
                    possible additional political initiatives of our own, third party initiatives,
                    our dealings with the Soviets, and the possibility of some form of contact with
                        <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> and/or <gloss target="#t_NLF1"
                        >NLF</gloss>.<note n="2" xml:id="d54fn2">Before it was revised by <persName
                            corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, the latter part of this sentence
                        read as follows: “we will wish to discuss measures, including possible
                        additional initiatives of our own, third party initiatives, our dealings
                        with the Soviets, and possibility of some form of contact with <gloss
                            target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> and/or <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss>
                        for psychological warfare and other purposes.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>The two most basic questions we will ask in relation to your recommendations for
                    expanding US forces will be: <list>
                        <label>A.</label>
                        <item>Assuming your proposals are fully accepted, what assurance do we have
                            that with the resulting force level we can<note n="3" xml:id="d54fn3">At
                                this point, <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> deleted
                                the phrase “in a reasonable time.”</note> prove to the Viet Cong
                            they cannot win, and thereby force them to a settlement on our
                            terms?</item>
                        <label>B.</label>
                        <item>Will large increases in the number and involvement of US combat units
                            and military personnel in South Vietnam cause the Vietnamese Government,
                            and especially the Army, to let up; will it create adverse popular
                            reactions to our presence in the country?</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Subsidiary questions will include: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>How did you determine the number of US and <gloss target="#t_ARVN1"
                                >ARVN</gloss> battalions required to effectively counter the current
                            or prospective Viet Cong forces?</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Where do you propose to station US combat units and where and how will
                            they be used; what casualties do you expect?</item>
                        <pb facs="0167" n="135" xml:id="pg_135"/>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>How long do you think it will take with your recommended forces (a) to
                            seize the initiative, (b) to prove to the Viet Cong that they cannot
                            win, and (c) thereby to force them to a settlement on our terms?</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>
                            <note n="4" xml:id="d54fn4">
                                <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> deleted the
                                original paragraph 4 and renumbered the subsequent paragraphs. The
                                original paragraph 4 read as follows: “4. How good and timely is our
                                intelligence as to <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> locations and
                                activities in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> and in the
                                corridor, and how can it be improved?”</note> Would it be wise to
                            withdraw <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> military and paramilitary
                            forces from certain outlying or exposed positions in order to
                            concentrate in positions of strength and to reduce the penalties of the
                            serious shortage of Government troops?</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>What reaction to the expansion of US and third-country forces do you
                            expect from the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> and the <gloss
                                target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>?</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Is the currently approved construction program adequate for the
                            expanded force?</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>Is the current MAP program adequate?</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>What command arrangements do you propose for the expanded US force
                            when engaged in combat?</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>What program of military pressure (bombing, mining, etc.) against
                            North Vietnam, in terms of the types of targets, level of effort, etc.,
                            do you propose for the next six months as a complement to your plan of
                            action in the South?</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>How effective has been the bombing of the Laotian infiltration routes;
                            what Laotian bombing program do you recommend for the future in terms of
                            specific targets and level of effort?</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>How effective have been the B-52 strikes; assuming 800 B-52 sorties
                            are available each month, what bombing program do you recommend for the
                            future in terms of specific targets and level of effort?</item>
                        <label>12.</label>
                        <item>Exclusive of B-52 sorties, how many strike sorties and how many
                            reconnaissance sorties per month do you recommend against targets in
                            South Vietnam during the next six months; are all of your current
                            requirements being met; if not, why not; should we be planning on
                            additional airfields for South Vietnam and if so, by what date are they
                            required and where should they be placed?</item>
                        <label>13.</label>
                        <item>What has been the trend of each of the major indicators (population
                            control, area control, desertions, weapons losses, terror incidents,
                            price level, etc.) of the success or failure of the counterinsurgency
                            campaign over the past year?</item>
                        <label>14.</label>
                        <item>How does the freedom of movement today over the railroads and the
                            major highways and waterways compare with that of a year ago?</item>
                        <label>15.</label>
                        <item>What measures do we have of the success or failure of our efforts to
                            prevent infiltration of men and equipment by sea; has the recently <pb
                                facs="0168" n="136" xml:id="pg_136"/> expanded program reduced such
                            infiltration; if not, why not; are additional forces required?</item>
                        <label>16.</label>
                        <item>Outline and appraise the effectiveness of alternative plans (including
                            a barrier across the 17th Parallel) for the use of US troops in Laos for
                            the purpose of preventing infiltration of men and equipment through that
                            country into South Vietnam.</item>
                        <label>17.</label>
                        <item>If you think it is possible militarily to cut off or very
                            substantially cut down the infiltration of North Vietnamese personnel
                            and materiel from the North to the South, when do you believe it will
                            begin to have an important effect on <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                            activities and how decisive will that effect be?</item>
                        <label>18.</label>
                        <item>Has the <gloss target="#t_HopTac1">Hop Tac</gloss> Program<note n="5"
                                xml:id="d54fn5">Reference is to a plan developed by General
                                    <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> in 1964 to
                                concentrate military resources in the Saigon area and progressively
                                clear areas radiating outward from the capital.</note> succeeded;
                            if, as it appears to us, it has not, review the program in detail to
                            throw light on the causes of its failure?</item>
                        <label>19.</label>
                        <item>Outline the original plan for the expansion of the <gloss
                                target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> military, paramilitary and police
                            forces; the progress to date against that plan; and changes, if any,
                            which you propose for the future.</item>
                        <label>20.</label>
                        <item>Do you concur in the conclusions of the recent RAND study of the
                            morale of <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> forces?<note n="6"
                                xml:id="d54fn6">See <ref target="#d27">Document 27</ref>.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>21.</label>
                        <item>How important is the monsoon to military operations and to the
                            military balance, and how should we expect military prospects to change
                            when the monsoon ends?</item>
                        <label>22.</label>
                        <item>Would it be possible to implement the <persName corresp="#p_AD1"
                                >Acheson</persName> Plan<note n="7" xml:id="d54fn7">See <ref
                                    target="frus1964-68v02#d287">vol. II, Document 287</ref>.</note>
                            in the near future, starting in the 4th Corps; is it feasible to
                            initiate such a plan in a particular area before it has been proven to
                            the Viet Cong that they cannot win?</item>
                        <label>23.</label>
                        <item>After the deployment of the recommended US forces, how would the
                                <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> react to an extended pause (six
                            or eight weeks) in the bombing of the <gloss target="#t_DRV1"
                                >DRV</gloss>?</item>
                        <label>24.</label>
                        <item>Should we consider the imposition of press censorship after the
                            expansion of US forces?</item>
                        <label>25.</label>
                        <item>What contacts do the South Vietnamese now have with the <gloss
                                target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_DRV1"
                                >DRV</gloss>; what additional contacts would you recommend that they
                            or the US have with those parties or the Soviets; how should such US
                            contacts be initiated and with what notice to the <gloss
                                target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>?</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Assuming our party remains in Vietnam 4 or 5 days, certain members of the party,
                    including myself, probably should visit an aircraft carrier, the major US bases
                    at Bien Hoa, Da Nang, Phu Bai, Qui Nhon, Nha Trang, <pb facs="0169" n="137"
                        xml:id="pg_137"/> Chu Lai, and Cam Ranh Bay, the 2d Corps Headquarters in
                    the highlands; and the <gloss target="#t_HopTac1">Hop Tac</gloss> area.</p>
                <p>We hope it will be possible for us to avoid large ceremonial dinners. Instead, we
                    should like to dine with small numbers of Vietnamese, US or third-country
                    nationals in an atmosphere so informal that they will feel free to provide us
                    their personal comments on the Vietnamese scene.</p>
                <p>Upon our return, we expect that important policy decisions will be made. These
                    may well require major legislative and executive action (including possibly the
                    declaration of a national emergency, the calling up of reserve forces, large
                    additions to the Budget, etc.) for which we wish to be fully prepared.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
