<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-03-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-03-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="266" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d266">
                        <head>266. Memorandum From Secretary of State Vance and Secretary of Defense
                            Brown to President Carter<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d266fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Brzezinski
                                Material, Brzezinski Office File, Box 17, Iceland. Confidential. A
                                stamped notation beneath Brown’s initials reads “21 Mar
                                1978.”</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-03-23">March 23, 1978</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Assistance to Iceland</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">The Issue</p>
                        <p>The United States must respond on an urgent basis to a request from the
                            highest levels of the Icelandic Government for assistance in the
                            construction of a dual-purpose, military/civilian air terminal at the
                            vital US-manned NATO base at Keflavik.<note n="2" xml:id="d266fn2">In a
                                December 14, 1977, memorandum to Brown and Vance, Brzezinski wrote:
                                “I am concerned about the possibility of deterioration in our
                                defense relations with Iceland and the prospect that our presence at
                                Keflavik becoming a major issue in the next Icelandic elections. I
                                therefore hope that the recent Icelandic suggestion of converting
                                the planned civilian terminal into a dual-use facility might be
                                given careful consideration.” In a February 13 memorandum to Brown
                                and Vance, Brzezinski noted that he understood that Brown would
                                consult with Congress and asked them to “forward a joint
                                recommendation to the President as soon as possible.” (Carter
                                Library, National Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Country
                                File, Box 27, Iceland: 1/77–1/81)</note></p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Essential Factors</p>
                        <p>You will recall that during Vice President Mondale’s January 1977 stop in
                            Iceland, Prime Minister Hallgrimsson asked for a US financial
                            contribution to the construction of a new civilian air terminal building
                            at Keflavik airport.<note n="3" xml:id="d266fn3">See <ref target="#d259">Document 259</ref>.</note> Following an interagency examination
                            of the request, you agreed with a State recommendation that we not
                            provide assistance to Iceland for the civilian terminal.<note n="4" xml:id="d266fn4">See <ref target="#d261">Document
                            261</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>In November 1977, the Icelandic Government submitted a new proposal for a
                            dual-purpose, military/civilian facility.<note n="5" xml:id="d266fn5">Telegram 1598 from Reykjavik, November 7, 1977, reported that in a
                                November 7 meeting with Blake, Agustsson discussed the idea of
                                redesigning the proposed civilian air terminal to allow its use for
                                military purposes and asked if the United States would be willing to
                                help pay for construction. (National Archives, RG 59, Central
                                Foreign Policy Files, D770410–0889)</note> Under the revised
                            request, the new Keflavik air terminal would be reserved for the
                            exclusive use of the US armed forces during times of crisis, while
                            Icelandic civil aviation authorities would utilize the facility in
                            peacetime. In submitting the new proposal, the Icelandic Foreign
                            Minister stressed the longstanding US commitment to pursue a separation
                            of military and civilian facilities at Keflavik.</p>
                        <p>The present Icelandic Government of Prime Minister Hallgrimsson is as
                            pro-American as any we could ever hope to see in power in Iceland.
                            Hallgrimsson is convinced that he badly needs American support on the
                            terminal issue to fend off vocal opponents of the American presence
                            during the campaign period culminating in the June 1978 national
                                elections.<note n="6" xml:id="d266fn6">In parliamentary elections
                                held on June 25, 1978, the Independence Party won 20 seats (a loss
                                of five seats) and the Progressive Party won 12 seats (also a loss
                                of five seats). The People’s Alliance won 14 seats (a gain of nine
                                seats) and the Social Democrats won 14 seats (a gain of three
                                seats). The Liberal and Leftist Union lost its two seats. That same
                                day Hallgrimsson announced that his government, based on a coalition
                                between the Independence and Progressive Parties, would resign.
                                (“Iceland’s Cabinet to Resign After Election Losses,” <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, June 27, 1978)</note></p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Conclusions</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>The Joint Chiefs of Staff and the Supreme Allied Commander
                                Atlantic consider the US-manned NATO base at Keflavik as critical to
                                US security, particularly in view of the rapid growth of the Soviet
                                Northern Fleet.</item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>Failure to respond favorably to the Icelandic request for
                                financial assistance will cause a deterioration in relations and
                                could jeopardize our continued access to the military facilities at
                                Keflavik.</item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>The Departments of State and Defense believe we should agree in
                                principle to assist Iceland and be prepared to contribute a maximum
                                of $30 million toward the construction of the dual-purpose
                                facility.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendations:</p>
                        <p>That you authorize the Department of State to inform the Icelandic
                            Government: <list>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>The United States Government agrees in principle to assist the
                                    Government of Iceland in the construction of a dual-purpose,
                                    military/civilian air terminal at Keflavik.</item>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>The precise amount, form and timing of the US contribution
                                    will be resolved through subsequent bilateral
                                    negotiations.</item>
                                <label>—</label>
                                <item>Any agreement with respect to the US contribution arrived at
                                    in the course of bilateral negotiations will be subject to
                                    Congressional authorization and appropriation. In the light of
                                    the unique circumstances of this case, Congressional approval
                                    cannot be presumed.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>That you authorize the Departments of State and Defense to initiate the
                            necessary measures to secure up to $30 million for the terminal from a
                            combination of $15 million in Military Construction (MILCON) funds and
                            $15 million in Security Supporting Assistance (SSA) funds (Congressional
                            approval is far from assured and we will have to work hard to get
                            it).</p>
                        <p>SSA funds have been used for base-related or security purposes in Spain,
                            the Philippines and Malta. However, the AID Administrator is opposed to
                            the use of SSA funds in Iceland and his dissenting memorandum is
                                attached.<note n="7" xml:id="d266fn7">A memorandum from Gilligan to
                                Vance, March 7, is attached but not printed. In his memorandum,
                                Gilligan wrote: “Is there any justification whatever for using
                                economic aid to pay for construction of an air terminal in an
                                economically developed NATO-related country?”</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>