<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>282. Telegram From Secretary of State Muskie’s Delegation to the Department
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d282</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">282</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1980-12-13T05:01:00-05:00" notAfter="1980-12-13T05:01:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001519"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="recJgxebpUYqWj25O" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Defense spending</term>
                    <term ref="recbm2CDfl6YlSCnq" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Modernization</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe">Helsinki
                        Final Act</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Detente</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="reccOg5QXDp3EJxaF" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general">SALT II</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="reczbK4SIoOvxRAff" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050314"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Food aid</term>
                    <term ref="recowpyti3dV3RE8o" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066333"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Infrastructure</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2019102796"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Boycott</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-12-13T05:01:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-12-13T05:01:00-05:00" n="282"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d282">
                <head>282. Telegram From Secretary of State Muskie’s Delegation to the Department of
                        State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d282fn1">Source: National Archives,
                        RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D800593–0851. Secret; Immediate; Exdis.
                        Sent for information Immediate to Oslo. Sent for information Priority to
                        Moscow and all NATO capitals. Sent for information to Stockholm and
                        Helsinki. Muskie and Frydenlund were in Brussels to attend the NAC meetings.
                        Muskie traveled to London on December 12.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">Secto 10021.</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>London</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1980-12-13T10:01:00+00:00">December 13, 1980, 1001Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>NATOMIN: Muskie–Frydenlund Bilateral—12/11/80.</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>S—Entire text.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Summary: Frydenlund sought advice and understanding regarding his
                        impending visit to Moscow.<note n="2" xml:id="d282fn2">On December 22,
                            Frydenlund visited Moscow for talks with Gromyko. On December 23, Holst
                            briefed NATO Ambassadors in Oslo on the talks. (Telegram 7365 from Oslo,
                            December 24; National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                            D800609–1129)</note> The Secretary urged him to not let the Soviets put
                        him on the defensive regarding pre-positioning and other NATO reactions to
                        the Soviet build-up. We also noted it is important that Europeans send firm
                        signals to the Soviets about the potential costs of intervening in
                        Poland.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Frydenlund sought the Secretary’s views regarding his planned trip to
                        Moscow. He noted in recent days the Soviet Embassy in Oslo had grown more
                        reticent in planning details, and wondered if the trip would materialize. He
                        thought the timing, given Poland, might be awkward for both sides. If the
                        Soviets intervened, the Foreign Minister said he would depart
                        immediately.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The Secretary said it was hard to know whether the Soviets had already
                        made their decision—and were just waiting for the right time or
                        circumstances. Therefore, it was difficult to know if anything the West did
                        or said could deter them. In any event, the situation required that
                        Frydenlund try to discourage the Soviets, especially by passing along the
                        strong sense of resolve felt by all members of the Alliance.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Frydenlund said he hoped the Soviets realized that the reaction in Europe
                        after an intervention in Poland would be much different than following
                        Afghanistan. The Secretary emphasized the importance of the Soviets hearing
                        this from Frydenlund.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Frydenlund said Norway was interested in a high level meeting with the
                        Soviets because of bilateral issues, such as the boundary question. He
                        expected Brezhnev to be very critical of Norway’s role in NATO—especially
                        Norway’s increasing military commitments, and acceptance of
                        stockpiling.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Secretary Muskie said Frydendlund should not let the Soviets put him on
                        the defensive. Instead the Norwegians obviously have no aggressive intent;
                        their taxpayers have no interest in spending excess amount on weapons. NATO
                        has reacted to Soviet actions. The Secretary recalled that even before
                        recent troop movements to the Polish border, the Soviets had some 26
                        divisions in the GDR, Czechoslovakia and Poland. Surely this is a threat
                        rather than prepositioned materiel to be used in the event Norway were
                        attacked. Therefore there was no need to be defensive about Western efforts
                        in the defense field, be it defense spending in general or modernization
                        programs like TNF. In this regard the Secretary noted the Soviets had
                        already deployed 200 SS–20s against Europe and planned to deploy 100 more.
                        Therefore the Western TNF decision was a reaction, not an aggressive threat
                        against the Soviets.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>The Secretary said whenever he meets with Gromyko or Dobrynin he stresses
                        that the American people and government do not want confrontation, but
                        prefer normal relations with the Soviet Union. This, however, requires a
                        serious effort by the latter to offer material assurances, such as removing
                        Soviet troops from Afghanistan, and by living up to the principles contained
                        in the Helsinki Final Act. In such a case they would find the American
                        people ready to improve relations with the Soviet Union in all fields,
                        including enhanced trade and the movement of people and ideas.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Frydenlund asked if recent trends in the United States indicated that
                        these long term goals of increased contact and non-confrontational,
                        evolutionary change were being abandoned. Were events in Poland already
                        leading to a decisive change against detente even though the positive
                        changes which occurred in the labor movement in Poland, and elsewhere in
                        Eastern Europe, could not have occurred without the detente process of the
                        past decade?</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>The Secretary agreed that the progress we have seen in Eastern Europe was
                        a benefit of the CSCE process, and that in this period the United States had
                        been able to improve markedly its relations with governments in Eastern
                        Europe. Nonetheless a brutal suppression of Poland would not be just a
                        temporary side effect of progress brought about by CSCE. Mr. Bartholomew
                        then added that it would be doubtful that anyone could argue after an
                        intervention that a benefit of this thing called detente was that it
                        enlarged the freedom of action of Eastern European governments.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>Frydenlund agreed that such an action would be the end of detente and that
                        he would say so in Moscow. The Secretary noted the Soviets appeared
                        unwilling to listen or even to discuss the merits of the Polish situation.
                        He hoped a strong, unified signal from the Ministers would help. In response
                        to Bartholmew’s statement that an intervention would signal Soviet disregard
                        for detente,<note n="3" xml:id="d282fn3">No other record of Bartholomew’s
                            statement has been found.</note> Frydenlund noted that if they did not
                        intervene such restraint—in the face of Polish politico-social
                        experiments—would need to be seen as proof of the benefits of detente.
                        Therefore the next several weeks would be fateful.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>State Secretary Holst noted that one of the key problems was that the
                        Soviets had been unable to develop anything but inorganic power links with
                        Eastern Europe. Secretary Muskie added that they resisted change in all
                        aspects of society. Frydenlund said one hopeful exception could be seen in
                        Hungary, but that developments in Poland could be too much too fast.</item>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>SALT: Frydenlund then asked the Secretary if he thought SALT would go down
                        the drain. Muskie responded that both sides have vital national interests in
                        preserving the SALT process. Nonetheless, the ratification of SALT II
                        required broad support in the Senate which was made impossible by the
                        invasion of Afghanistan. If the Soviets suppressed Poland the Secretary did
                        not see how SALT could make progress and he felt the Soviets understood
                        this.</item>
                    <label>14.</label>
                    <item>Frydenlund noted that the Soviets will be facing great internal and
                        external problems in coming years, and that unfortunately they may well
                        choose to rely on the only area where they have had success—the massing of
                        modern military power. Holst noted that this was the one Soviet economic
                        sector where growth was possible without social or systemic change.</item>
                    <label>15.</label>
                    <item>Afghanistan: In response to a question from Frydenlund, the Secretary
                        explained the stalemated situation in Afghanistan despite the continuing
                        efforts of 85,000 Soviet troops. He noted that the disjointed resistance
                        movement manages to fight on with minimal outside assistance. Muskie also
                        noted that there are now over one million refugees in Pakistan who need food
                        aid. The Secretary concluded that the Soviets seem committed to sticking it
                        out and are building permanent infrastructure for their military.
                        Bartholomew noted that whatever their problems they do have the
                        geo-strategical benefit of occupying Afghanistan at an acceptable cost. The
                        Secretary noted that the Soviets must also know that the resistance is not
                        getting substantial help from outside, and that Pakistan is growing
                        discouraged. He noted that the erosion of European interest and sanctions
                        has an effect on prospects in Afghanistan. The Secretary concluded that the
                        Soviets would probably stay unless they found a real face-saving solution.
                        In the meantime they can afford to wait and they can even launch
                        peace-feelers like their recent one re the Persian Gulf, which the Secretary
                        characterized as a “fox in the chicken coop” effort.</item>
                    <label>16.</label>
                    <item>Nordic nuclear weapons free zone: Deputy Assistant Secretary Holmes
                        recalled that the Soviets often launch purposefully distracting political
                        ideas during such aggressive periods, and he asked if Frydenlund expected
                        them to push the Nordic nuclear weapon zone idea.<note n="4"
                            xml:id="d282fn4">See <ref target="#d274fn5">footnote 5, Document
                                274</ref>.</note> Frydenlund said he did not think they would push
                        it, especially since it was a Finnish proposal, though they might vaguely
                        support it. Should they push he said Norway could always refer to its
                        national position that any limits on nuclear weapons would logically need to
                        include those already in place in the areas—i.e. on the Kola Peninsula—which
                        should discourage the Soviets. He concluded that he would not raise the NNW
                        free zone idea in any event.</item>
                    <label>17.</label>
                    <item>Pre-positioning: Frydenlund then expressed his thanks for US efforts to
                        accommodate Norwegian concerns in working out the Memorandum of
                            Understanding.<note n="5" xml:id="d282fn5">Reference is to the January
                            16, 1981, Memorandum of Understanding Governing Prestockage and
                            Reinforcement of Norway. (TIAS 9966)</note> He said it had now been
                        submitted to the Parliament and that it should be approved in January.<note
                            n="6" xml:id="d282fn6">On January 13, 1981, the Norwegian Parliament
                            approved the MOU by a vote of 95 to 13. (Telegram 199 from Oslo;
                            National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D810020–0026) On
                            January 16, the MOU was signed in Oslo. (Telegram 444 from Oslo;
                            National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                            D810041–0360)</note> The Secretary said that the United States equally
                        appreciated Norway’s courage in taking on this enterprise. Frydenlund
                        replied that in isolation it should not have been sensitive but that when
                        added to the 3 percent, TNF, and the Olympic boycott it crested in a heated
                        defense debate, similar to those previously encountered in Belgium, Holland,
                        and Denmark. While the prepositioning issue would probably pass
                        successfully, Frydenlund was afraid that nuclear sensitivities would
                        continue to be a problem in Norway.</item>
                    <label>22.</label>
                    <item>Muskie concluded the meeting by noting that he hoped Frydenlund’s trip to
                        Moscow would take place since that would mean that other events in Poland
                        had not occurred.</item>
                    <label>23.</label>
                    <item>PARTICIPANTS <list>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">US Participants</hi>
                            </head>
                            <item>Secretary Muskie</item>
                            <item>Ambassador Bennett</item>
                            <item>Mr. Vest</item>
                            <item>Mr. Holmes</item>
                            <item>Mr. Hopper (Notetaker)</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Norwegian Participants</hi>
                            </head>
                            <item>Foreign Minister Frydenlund</item>
                            <item>Ambassador Vibe</item>
                            <item>State Secretary Holst</item>
                            <item>L. Mevik – Deputy Director General, Ministry of Foreign
                                Affairs</item>
                            <item>Notetaker</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Muskie</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
