<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>86. Memorandum From the Executive Secretary of the Department of State
                    (Tarnoff) to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Brzezinski)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d86</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">86</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1980-09-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1980-09-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85138573"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Tuna</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="organization-of-american-states">Coastal states</term>
                    <term ref="recygdArH3og8oA52" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008020036"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Migratory</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113036"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Research and development</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recb6XG1ZU9Ik84CR" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Broadcasting</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133456"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Television</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-09-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-09-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="86"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d86">
                <head>86. Memorandum From the Executive Secretary of the Department of State
                    (Tarnoff) to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (Brzezinski)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d86fn1">Source: Carter
                        Library, National Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Country File, Box
                        7, Canada: 10/79–1/81. Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1980-09-06">September 6, 1980</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Current Status of US–Canadian Relations</item>
                </list>
                <p>In June Ambassador Kenneth Curtis cabled from Ottawa his concerns over the
                    apparent downturn in US–Canadian relations.<note n="2" xml:id="d86fn2">Reference
                        is to telegram 3117 from Ottawa, June 10, in which Curtis wrote: “I sense
                        that we are on the verge of a downturn in U.S.-Canadian relations, certainly
                        in the atmosphere, probably in the substance, primarily as a result of
                        growing Canadian frustration over the U.S. failure to act on maritime
                        boundary and fisheries treaties.” (Ibid.)</note> He noted that Canadians
                    felt they had responded positively on global matters of vital US concern, but
                    that there had been no positive effect on bilateral relations. Ambassador Curtis
                    underscored Canada’s deep disappointment over the Senate’s failure to approve
                    the fisheries and boundary treaties, and Canada’s concern over the lack of
                    progress on other major bilateral issues.<note n="3" xml:id="d86fn3">Telegram
                        3127 from Ottawa, June 10, reported that in the first comprehensive
                        statement of foreign policy under the Trudeau government, MacGuigan “spoke
                        of ‘inexplicable delays’ in presenting the bilateral fisheries/maritime
                        boundary treaty to the U.S. Senate, called proposed amendments ‘wholly
                        unacceptable,’ and warned that Canada would take ‘appropriate steps’ to
                        protect its competitive position if U.S. fishermen continued
                        ‘over-fishing.’” (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D800284–0572)</note>
                </p>
                <p>The possible sharp downturn in relations which appeared likely in June has not
                    materialized, and over the past three months several positive developments have
                    improved the general atmosphere of US–Canadian relations. The signing in a few
                    weeks of a comprehensive tax treaty should continue that process.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d86fn4">On September 26, Miller and MacEachen signed a U.S.-Canada
                        tax treaty. (Telegram 270163 to Ottawa, October 9; National Archives, RG 59,
                        Central Foreign Policy File, D800483–0468)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Still, Canada’s deep-seated disappointment over the fisheries treaty is likely to
                    overhang the relationship. Even a resolution of the impasse, which will
                    inevitably require some retreat by Canada, will leave Canadians with a sense of
                    injury.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Fisheries and Boundary Treaties</p>
                <p>On August 26 Secretary Muskie and Lloyd Cutler met with Senators Kennedy, Pell,
                    Mitchell, Tsongas, and Cohen in an effort to soften the “Kennedy Amendments”
                    which shift the balance of benefits so far toward US fishermen that Canada finds
                    them unacceptable. At Mr. Cutler’s behest the Senators agreed to consult with
                    fishing industry representatives on the acceptability of less extreme amendments
                    to the fisheries treaty. When the views of the Senators and the fishing industry
                    have been received, the Department will consider further the presentation of
                    those views to Canada.<note n="5" xml:id="d86fn5">In telegram 276127 to Ottawa,
                        October 16, Pickering informed Curtis that “We have been working with
                        Senator Kennedy’s staff over the last few weeks to identify
                        mutually-acceptable amendments to the fisheries treaty which we would have
                        been willing to take to Canada. However, Senator Kennedy (and Senator Pell)
                        have not been able to resolve the issue with their constituents.” (National
                        Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D800494–0153)</note>
                </p>
                <p>In press and private comments Canadians have expressed concern that if the US
                    fishing industry calls for extensive changes in the treaty, Canada will be
                    placed in the position of either backing down or bearing the onus for the
                    failure of the agreement. Canadians believe this would be unfair, and such a
                    result would surely have repercussions on other aspects of our relations.
                    Whatever the outcome, the involvement of Secretary Muskie and Mr. Cutler should
                    make it clear to the Canadian Government that the US attaches top priority to
                    achieving approval of the treaties.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Alaska Gas Pipeline</p>
                <p>A serious bilateral problem<note n="6" xml:id="d86fn6">The relevant part of
                        Carter’s notes from his June 23 conversation with Trudeau in Venice reads:
                        “JC said US wants pipeline, intends to build Alaska leg—presumption is that
                        line would be good for US &amp; Can.—Cannot get Congressional action re
                        commitment, but key members will reassure Canadians.” (Notes prepared by
                        Carter, undated; Carter Library, Plains File, President’s Personal Foreign
                        Affairs File, Box 4, Summit Meetings, 7/78–6/80)</note> was resolved in
                    July, when the President and Congress provided Prime Minister Trudeau the
                    assurances sought by Canada that the US intends to complete the Alaska gas
                    pipeline project.<note n="7" xml:id="d86fn7">On July 2, Carter telephoned
                        Trudeau to inform him that his administration was committed to completing
                        the Alaska gas pipeline project and that the House and Senate had passed a
                        concurrent resolution with an “overwhelming majority” expressing support for
                        it. (Memorandum of conversation, July 2; Carter Library, National Security
                        Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Subject File, Box 38, Memcons: President:
                        7/80) On July 17, Carter sent Trudeau a letter to confirm U.S. support for
                        the pipeline. (Carter Library, National Security Affairs, President’s
                        Correspondence with Foreign Leaders, Box 3, Canada: Prime Minister Pierre
                        Elliot Trudeau, 4–12/80)</note> These assurances enabled Canada to authorize
                    the export of additional gas which will allow the early construction of the
                    southern legs of the pipeline and will improve the prospects for the completion
                    of the remainder of the project.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Air Quality</p>
                <p>Progress was made on this politically volatile question through the signing in
                    August by Secretary Muskie of a Memorandum of Intent committing both countries
                    to develop a bilateral agreement on effective domestic control programs. The
                    Memorandum established a mechanism to gather technical data necessary for a
                    formal air pollution agreement. The importance of the Memorandum of Intent
                    should not be overestimated, but it nonetheless makes clear that the US takes
                    Canadian concerns seriously.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Tuna Embargo</p>
                <p>Our year-long embargo on Canadian tuna exports to the US has been lifted. Last
                    year Canada seized 19 US tuna boats which were fishing off Canada contrary to
                    Canadian law. The US does not recognize the authority of coastal states over
                    albacore tuna and other highly migratory species, and under the terms of US law
                    an embargo on Canadian tuna and tuna products was imposed. In an agreement
                    reached last month Canada agreed to permit US tuna fishermen to operate off
                    British Columbia, in return for limited access by Canadians to US ports. The
                    same agreement called for negotiations (which have since begun) on a treaty
                    which would permit US tuna fishermen to operate off Canada on a permanent basis,
                    and allow Canadians to land their catch of albacore tuna at specified US West
                    Coast ports. The agreement was reached in time to avoid a renewed confrontation
                    as the tuna moved again this year into Canadian waters.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Auto Pact</p>
                <p>Canada has been increasingly concerned over its persistent deficit in automotive
                    trade with the US. With 1979’s deficit coming to $2.5 billion, Canada requested
                    consultations on the agreement early this year. Two rounds of consultations—one
                    at the ministerial level—have been held in an effort to meet Canadian
                    concerns.</p>
                <p>Under the economic and political climate which prevails in the US today, it will
                    be difficult to devise measures to reduce Canada’s deficit. We do not plan to
                    initiate proposals to modify the Auto Pact, although Canada may do so. We are
                    keenly interested in restoring strength to the North American auto industry and
                    are prepared to examine any Canadian proposals. Our willingness to discuss these
                    issues has demonstrated US sensitivity to Canada’s problems in this area.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">R&amp;D Waiver</p>
                <p>In July the US and Canada agreed on an arrangement to waive certain of the
                    research and development costs incurred by the US in the development of the
                    F–18A aircraft.<note n="8" xml:id="d86fn8">In a July 11 letter to Towe,
                        McGiffert informed him that the United States was prepared to reduce
                        recoupment charges on the F–18A aircraft (also known as the CF–18 aircraft)
                        to allow Canada to purchase a minimum of 137 aircraft. McGiffert noted that
                        “We would agree to such a reduction in the event and to the extent that the
                        Canadian Government is prepared, under a dollar-for-dollar matching
                        arrangement appropriate to the special circumstances of this acquisition
                        (such as a waiver of Canadian taxes), to provide an equal amount of funding
                        additional to the defense budget for its CF–18 aircraft program.” (Telegram
                        189733 to Ottawa, July 19; National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy
                        File, D800347–0297)</note> Canada is satisfied that the arrangement worked
                    out takes account of the special defense relationship between the two countries.
                    At the same time, the arrangement is defensible from the standpoint of criticism
                    from other Allies.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Border Broadcasting</p>
                <p>Canada denies a tax deduction for advertising placed by Canadians on US
                    television and radio stations. In July the President agreed to USTR’s
                    recommendation that in response the US should enact a similar law. This minimal
                    retaliation in kind will not affect other aspects of US–Canadian relations, and
                    should, at least for the time being, remove this issue from the agenda.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Implications for the Future</p>
                <p>Despite these positive developments, continued delay over the fisheries treaty
                    tends to confirm in Canadian minds that the US is not responsive to major
                    Canadian concerns. Until that issue is removed from the bilateral agenda, we
                    will encounter difficulties in our bilateral relations with Canada.
                    Additionally, Canada is experiencing a surge of economic nationalism, heightened
                    by the return of the Liberals to power this year. The House of Commons will
                    debate this fall new legislation designed to lessen foreign ownership of the
                    Canadian economy. The result will tend to underscore once more the inequalities
                    in the US–Canadian relationship, a given factor which complicates the resolution
                    of bilateral issues.<note n="9" xml:id="d86fn9">In a September 9 memorandum to
                        Brzezinski and Aaron, Blackwill summarized Tarnoff’s memorandum. Blackwill’s
                        memorandum bears a stamp that reads: “ZB has seen,” next to which an unknown
                        hand added: “9/13/80.” At the top of the memorandum, Brzezinski wrote “D.R.”
                        Below that notation, another unknown hand added: “Copy was given to Sit Room
                        for DR. 9/10/80.” (Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Brzezinski
                        Material, Country File, Box 7, Canada: 10/79–1/81)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Peter Tarnoff</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="10" xml:id="d86fn10">Bremer signed the memorandum for
                            Tarnoff.</note>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Executive Secretary</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
