<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-08-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-08-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="14" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d14">
                    <head>14. National Intelligence Estimate<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d14fn0"><p>Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> Files. Secret.
                                National Intelligence Estimates (NIEs) were interdepartmental
                                reports drafted by officers from agencies represented on the
                                Intelligence Advisory Committee (IAC), coordinated by the Office of
                                National Estimates of the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA),
                                approved by the <gloss target="#t_IAC1">IAC</gloss>, and circulated
                                to the President, the National Security Council, and other
                                appropriate officers of Cabinet level.</p>
                            <p>A note on the cover sheet states that <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 100–3–58 superseded <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 100–57, “Sino-Soviet Foreign Economic Policies and
                                Their Probable Effects in Underdeveloped Areas,” March 26, 1957.
                                    (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.)</p>
                            <p>Another note on the cover sheet reads as follows:</p>
                            <p>“Submitted by the Director of Central Intelligence. The following
                                intelligence organizations participated in the preparation of this
                                estimate: The Central Intelligence Agency and the intelligence
                                organizations of the Departments of State, the Army, the Navy, the
                                Air Force, and The Joint Staff.</p>
                            <p>“Concurred in by the Intelligence Advisory Committee on 5 August
                                1958. Concurring were The Director of Intelligence and Research,
                                Department of State; the Assistant Chief of Staff, Intelligence,
                                Department of the Army; the Director of Naval Intelligence; the
                                Assistant Chief of Staff, Intelligence, <gloss target="#t_USAF1">USAF</gloss>; and the Deputy Director for Intelligence, The
                                Joint Staff. The Atomic Energy Commission Representative to the
                                    <gloss target="#t_IAC1">IAC</gloss> and the Assistant Director,
                                Federal Bureau of Investigation, abstained, the subject being
                                outside of their jurisdiction.”</p></note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">NIE 100–3–58</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-08-05">August 5, 1958</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">THE NATURE OF THE SINO-SOVIET BLOC ECONOMIC THREAT IN THE
                        UNDERDEVELOPED AREAS</p>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">The Problem</hi></p>
                    <p>To assess the Sino-Soviet Bloc aid and trade programs in the economically
                        underdeveloped world, and to estimate their probable threat to the US.</p>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Conclusions</hi></p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The Sino-Soviet economic offensive continues to score successes for
                            the Bloc at the expense of the West. Although involving economic benefit
                            to the Bloc, it is conducted as an integral part of the Bloc’s cold war
                            policy against the West. The underdeveloped countries, many of which
                            have economic and political grievances against the West, are being
                            offered an alternative source of arms and a wide <pb facs="0066" n="34" xml:id="pg_34"/> range of economic relationships on attractive terms
                            and, at the outset, with no apparent political conditions, ([<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                            declassified</hi>])</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Although the economic program is of modest scope compared with the
                            total volume of world trade and capital flow, it has strengthened the
                            bargaining positions of certain of the underdeveloped countries
                            vis-à-vis the West, given some of them a capability to defy the West,
                            and helped to identify the Bloc with their nationalist aspirations.
                            Generally satisfactory performance in conducting its aid and trade
                            program has created for the Bloc an aura of respectability as a
                            legitimate business partner. Economic dealings have substantially
                            increased the ties of some countries with the Bloc, giving Bloc leaders
                            economic and political levers for future use. ([<hi rend="italic">less
                                than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>])</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>We believe that the Bloc leaders will intensify their economic
                            offensive, whether or not they shift to a harder general line toward the
                            major Western powers. Despite the requirements of the investment
                            programs within the Bloc, economic capabilities will impose no serious
                            limitation on the Bloc’s ability to continue, or even to double, its
                            present trade, aid, and technical assistance program, ([<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                            declassified</hi>])</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Bloc leaders will continue to direct their economic offensive at those
                            Middle Eastern and Asian countries which now occupy their primary
                            attention, but will probably also show increasing interest in Turkey,
                            Greece, Latin America, and the emerging states of Africa. The Bloc may
                            achieve dramatic economic inroads in certain of these countries,
                            including some which have to date been closely tied to the West. ([<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                            declassified</hi>])</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>We believe, however, that the trade and aid program will not alone
                            cause any state to align itself with the Bloc in the near future. We
                            also believe that, with the passage of time, the Bloc economic drive may
                            lose some of its initial glamour and effectiveness. The Bloc, as in the
                            case of Yugoslavia, may not always fulfill its promises and it will not
                            satisfy all the hopes which it has aroused. Some underdeveloped
                            countries may in time become more wary and require more persuasion than
                            they do now to accept Bloc offers of trade and aid. ([<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>])</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>The long-run threat posed by the Bloc economic offensive will
                            nevertheless remain substantial. The economic offensive will operate in
                            a context in which the steady growth of the economic, military, and
                            scientific strength of the Bloc will make it a more formidable opponent
                            of the West in the underdeveloped countries. Bloc trade, credits, and
                            technical assistance will support the Bloc image of progress and power,
                            and will provide opportunities for the propagation of Communist doctrine
                            and the idea of rapid industrialization through the Soviet-type <pb facs="0067" n="35" xml:id="pg_35"/> organization of society. In sum,
                            unless effectively countered, these psychological and economic inroads
                            will continue to erode the Western position in the underdeveloped world,
                                ([<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                                declassified</hi>])</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>[Here follow the “Discussion” portion of the estimate (paragraphs 7–32), with
                        sections headed “Introduction,” “The Bloc Program to Date,” “The Economic
                        Offensive’s Accomplishments,” and “The Future of the Economic Offensive,”
                        and seven tables.]</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>