<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>252. Memorandum for the Record by the President’s Deputy Assistant
                    (Harlow))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d252</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">252</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1960-02-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-02-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recoRXZiW0XKZ4ec4" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Development loan</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recp5DsIbsvFElug7" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recibBhfq1Nhuo5rk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec9aDoDi7sluDnsm" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="civil-rights"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026371"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil rights</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="rece9c3648fe9d1e98" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="mutual-security-program">Mutual Security Program</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-02-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-02-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="252"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d252">
                <head>252. Memorandum for the Record by the President’s Deputy Assistant (<persName
                        corresp="#p_HBN1">Harlow</persName>)<note n="0" type="source"
                        xml:id="d252fn0">Source: Eisenhower Library, <persName corresp="#p_WAC1"
                            >Whitman</persName> File, Eisenhower Diaries. No classification
                        marking.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-02-29">February 29,
                        1960</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>On February 15, at 5:30 pm the President met with the following people: <list>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon Johnson</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>Alexander Wiley</item>
                        <item>Carl Hayden</item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RRB1">Richard Russell</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Charles Halleck</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MTE1">Thomas Morgan</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_TJ1">John Taber</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_PGWB1">General Persons</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_DEM1">Everett Dirksen</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>J.W. Fulbright</item>
                        <item>Styles Bridges</item>
                        <item>Speaker Rayburn</item>
                        <item>John W. McCormack</item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_CC1">Clarence Cannon</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> (State)</item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_HBN1">Bryce Harlow</persName>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The President opened the meeting by stating that he would soon turn the
                    discussion over to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName>, it
                    not being his desire to “bore everyone” by repeating his well-known convictions
                    on Mutual Security. The President stated that he could not vouch for every
                    particular figure in the following, but was recently advised by a man who had
                    made a detailed analysis of the entire international situation that he was
                    gravely concerned over the increasing costs of American production and what this
                    is coming to mean to United States prosperity and American markets abroad.</p>
                <p>This man advised that increasing costs are beginning seriously to affect our
                    relations with the one and a quarter billion people who live in under-developed
                    nations other than China. It was his understanding that in these nations
                    productivity has been increasing about 1% a year, whereas their population has
                    been increasing about 2%. If this be true, the President stated, we must move to
                    increase productivity abroad by about an additional 1% if we possibly can, in
                    the process of keeping the markets we now have and regaining those we have lost.
                    The President stated that the people in these parts of the world will definitely
                    better their conditions and that this must be made possible for them or the
                    world will surely end up in chaos and disorder. He stated that he did not
                    believe that the United States should do all of this itself, but certainly we
                    must do better. The President said he had to repeat his conviction that our
                    entire national security and prosperity are tied up in this program of Mutual
                    Security and he reminded the group that in America’s earliest days we too were
                    dependent upon nations for investment and capital resources. He stated that this
                    meeting would be the last one of this kind with this particular group but <pb
                        facs="0518" n="486" xml:id="pg_486"/> that never has he been as sure as he
                    is now that America’s future is tied so tightly with this program despite the
                    adverse publicity the program has received. At this point he turned the
                    discussion over to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName>.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> explained that a
                    Presidential message to Congress would be sent forward the following day and
                    that hearings would shortly ensue in the Foreign Affairs Committee in the House
                    of Representatives. First, as to economic programs, Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> explained that in preparing these
                    programs this year the Department had been guided in good measure by the
                    so-called <persName corresp="#p_MM1">Mansfield</persName> Amendment which
                    required that reports be prepared on all countries receiving grant assistance to
                    determine whether or not and how soon such countries could have this kind of
                    assistance reduced or eliminated. The Secretary stated that this report should
                    be available by the end of this month.<note n="1" xml:id="d252fn1">Regarding the
                        President’s message to the Congress, see <ref target="#d253fn2">footnote 2,
                            Document 253</ref>. The “<persName corresp="#p_MM1">Mansfield</persName>
                        Amendment” is Section 503(c) of the Mutual Security Act of 1954, as amended.
                            <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> submitted his report to
                        the Congress on February 29; for text of his transmittal letter, see
                        Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin,</hi> March 21, 1960, pp.
                        459–460. The report, which was classified, has not been found. <persName
                            corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> sent an unclassified, general
                        summary report to the Congress on March 4. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.,
                        pp. 460–465)</note> He said that the philosophy of this report is already
                    reflected in the program presented to the Congress, because the funds requested
                    for grant assistance had been reduced by $155 million under last year. He added
                    that defense support alone had been reduced by $111 million, a 13% reduction
                    under last year.</p>
                <p>The Secretary stated that the funds requested in the new program are only
                    slightly above those appropriated last year for grant assistance. He pointed out
                    that a reduction is being requested also for the contingency fund.</p>
                <p>As for the Development Loan Fund, he explained that the same amount is being
                    requested as was requested last year. He explained that these funds are needed
                    in order to make it possible to use more of these loans in place of grant
                    assistance.</p>
                <p>The Secretary stated that the second major change in the program this year is
                    military assistance—an increase being requested in this item of $700 million
                    above the amount appropriated last year in keeping with the recommendations of
                    the <persName corresp="#p_DGWH1">Draper</persName> Committee and because the
                    pipeline funds have been virtually exhausted. The Secretary stressed the
                    necessity for modernizing the forces of our friends abroad and stated that an
                    increase in military assistance is imperative to that end.</p>
                <pb facs="0519" n="487" xml:id="pg_487"/>
                <p>As far as the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> nations are concerned, the
                    Secretary stated that the policy is to have no new commitments to those <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> countries which are economically the
                    strongest—England, Germany and France and that these nations are being urged to
                    make cost-sharing agreements in assistance programs.</p>
                <p>The Secretary stressed that the program has a better schedule of requirements
                    than heretofore because unified commanders and our ambassadors have been brought
                    into the program sooner.</p>
                <p>The Secretary stated that $940 million more than last year’s appropriations are
                    being asked this year, the great majority of the increase being for military
                    assistance.</p>
                <p>He cited the basic figures as being $4.175 billion requested, as compared with
                    $3.930 billion requested last year, as compared with $3.226 billion appropriated
                    last year.</p>
                <p>Speaker <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rayburn</persName> then stated that in the
                    House of Representatives there is a wide-spread feeling that there is a
                    tremendous amount of incompetence and waste in this program. He said that there
                    would be no difficulty on the military side of the program in the House, but
                    there will be great difficulty on the economic side of the program. The Speaker
                    emphasized that the people complaining to him have stressed waste and
                    incompetence, not graft or corruption, and that they mention this in connection
                    with economic aid. He identified the complaining Congressmen as members of the
                    House Committee on Foreign Affairs.</p>
                <p>Congressman <persName corresp="#p_MTE1">Tom Morgan</persName> observed that
                    military assistance is a continuing authorization, as is the Development Loan
                    Fund, so that in the authorization bill this year there is only $1.400 billion
                    to be authorized. He stated that the so-called Pilcher subcommittee returned
                    from a trip abroad with bad reports on large projects, but that the small
                    projects seemed to be going well.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> pointed out, respecting
                    the larger projects, that these are being shifted from grants programs to
                    Development Loan Fund projects. He stated that no money is included in this
                    year’s request for any projects of any size under grant aid except for a few now
                    being completed in the Far East. He stated that because of this arrangement he
                    did not anticipate difficulties on these projects in the future of the kind we
                    have had in the past.</p>
                <p>Congressman <persName corresp="#p_TJ1">Taber</persName> asked the President if we
                    could not get along without technical assistance and other smaller programs of
                    this kind. The President responded that this is one of the best parts of the
                    whole program. <persName corresp="#p_TJ1">Taber</persName> said that he would
                    agree if the program were honestly run, “but it isn’t.” At once the President
                    responded, most vigorously, that it is very difficult to get good personnel in
                    this program because the Congress insists upon a year by year program and has
                    refused to put it on a career basis. He stated that “the United States is coming
                        <pb facs="0520" n="488" xml:id="pg_488"/> damn close to making up its mind
                    as to what we are going to do in the world, and if it is to withdraw then we
                    will have to recompute our whole position on the face of the globe.” He stated
                    that both this Mutual Security Program and the <gloss target="#t_USIA1"
                        >USIA</gloss> programs will be much better off if the personnel can be made
                    career, and he feelingly commented on troubles he had experienced in prior years
                    (including, specifically, with <persName corresp="#p_TJ1">Taber</persName>)
                    trying vainly to get enough Army funds, whereas today the Congress is lavish on
                    defense but pinch-penny on the no less vital Mutual Security Program.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> stated that a new study
                    being made of the economic programs will be completed in about one year,
                    pointing out that these programs have not been tightly resurveyed for the past
                    decade. He said there is a possibility that some parts of the program are no
                    longer needed.</p>
                <p>Senator Wiley stated that he has had a letter asking why it is necessary to give
                    additional assistance to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> when they are in
                    such excellent economic condition. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1"
                        >Dillon</persName> explained that <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                    countries are contributing far more now—about 11% more—than last year. The
                    President pointed out that Holland, for instance, is contributing so much that
                    there is some doubt whether or not it can carry the load. Senator <persName
                        corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> interjected to state that while we
                    are approaching this in a highly critical and conservative fashion, Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> is celebrating his new
                    steel mill in India as well as a lot of additional economic efforts in other
                    parts of the world on the part of the Soviet Union. He stated that the decision
                    that America must make is whether or not to turn the rest of the world over to
                    the Soviet Union; otherwise we must continue our own programs.</p>
                <p>The Senator stated that he is much aware that in his own State this program is
                    highly unpopular, and so much so that in every speech he makes he has to defend
                    it. He says, however, that he does so unhesitatingly, because the Nation faces a
                    critical situation in the world and must meet the test.</p>
                <p>The President reiterated that almost his entire life had been spent in military
                    service during a period in which every dollar invested in defense was
                    characterized as waste. Now, he said, everybody insists on spending billions
                    extra for defense, while scrimping on this particular program, an essential part
                    of our own defenses.</p>
                <p>Senator <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> repeated that it is
                    unpleasant and unpopular to support this program but there is no alternative. He
                    said it is most unfortunate that it has been made an annual program. He stressed
                    that here we are watching the Soviet Union going around the world, in the
                    Caribbean as well as in Asia, and we in this country are getting started on a
                    battle royal in the Congress (referring to civil rights). He said that this
                    battle in the Congress will make the situation even more difficult. He said that
                    as far as he is concerned he will support this Mutual <pb facs="0521" n="489"
                        xml:id="pg_489"/> Security program all that he can. America has, he pointed
                    out, more than twice the gross national product of the Soviet Union. He said
                    that we can afford this program, and we must support it.</p>
                <p>Senator <persName corresp="#p_DEM1">Dirksen</persName> suggested, whimsically, to
                    Senator <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> that the latter should
                    live in <hi rend="italic">Chicago-Tribune</hi> area in order to get a real
                    feeling of the local impact of this program.</p>
                <p>The President stated that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                    had told him that none of us can afford this business of destroying each other.
                    However, the Soviets can place their emphasis in certain particular places to
                    achieve their results. Meanwhile the United States must look after the concerns
                    of all nations small or large. He stated that our job is tough indeed but that
                    our allies are today a very large part of America’s initial defense—in fact, our
                    outposts, even though we cannot tell them so.</p>
                <p>Senator <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> stated that the free
                    world has at least three times the wealth of the Soviet Union so there is no
                    doubt that we can afford a vigorous effort for mutual security. The President
                    laughingly stated that he would come to Arkansas and put on a toupee and support
                    Senator <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> in that state because
                    of his views on mutual security.</p>
                <p>The President then thanked everyone present for coming to this meeting. He stated
                    that he doesn’t care if he is characterized as “a stupid ox” but he believes
                    profoundly in this program and will keep on saying so. He said that if he should
                    survive for the next decade there will be, before it is over, a lot more
                    converts to this program, because he is going to have something to do with
                    getting them.</p>
                <p>Speaker <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rayburn</persName> then commented that the
                    President’s bourbon tasted very good to them; he hoped that this would not be,
                    as the President had indicated, the last meeting of this group. The President
                    laughingly answered that this was only to be the last meeting “of this
                    kind.”</p>
                <p>Thereupon at 6:15 pm the meeting adjourned.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">BNH</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
