<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="256" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d256">
                    <head>256. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> briefly mentioned
                        the Mutual Security Program in his May 2 address, terming it “one of the
                        greatest programs through which the United States can lead toward world
                        peace.” That evening, the President gave a major speech on the program at a
                        dinner sponsored by the Committee for International Growth and the Committee
                        to Strengthen the Frontiers of Freedom. For the texts, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Dwight D. Eisenhower</persName>, 1960–61,</hi>
                        pages 374–378, and <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy: Current
                            Documents, 1960,</hi> pages 836–841, respectively. The President also
                        transmitted a report on the Mutual Security Program to the Congress on May
                        2; for the text, see <hi rend="italic">Report to Congress on the Mutual
                            Security Program for the First Half of Fiscal Year 1960</hi> (Department
                        of State Publication 6950).</p>
                    <p>The following day, Eisenhower sent the Congress a special message urging
                        action on certain legislation, including the administration’s fiscal year
                        1961 Mutual Security appropriations request; for the text, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States:
                                <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Dwight D. Eisenhower</persName>,
                            1960–61,</hi> pages 385–394. Authorizing legislation for the
                        appropriation, H.R. 11510, was in conference.</p>
                    <p>On May 6, House and Senate conferees reported a compromise version of the
                        bill which cut $88.7 million from the President’s request. (U.S. House of
                        Representatives, Committee on Foreign Affairs, <hi rend="italic">Selected
                            Executive Session Hearings of the Committee, 1957–60,</hi> vol. XXI, <hi rend="italic">Mutual Security Program, Part 8</hi> (Washington, 1987),
                        pages 581–601) That day, <persName corresp="#p_HBN1">Bryce
                        Harlow</persName>, Eisenhower’s Deputy Assistant for Congressional Affairs,
                        reported he had spoken with Speaker of the House <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rayburn</persName> about the Mutual Security bill, and suggested the
                        President invite <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rayburn</persName> to the White
                        House to talk about it. Eisenhower agreed. Acting Secretary of State
                            <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName>, who had been discussing
                        other matters with the President, volunteered to provide a memorandum on the
                        effects a $1 billion or $1.5 billion reduction would have on the program.
                        (Memorandum of conference with the President, May 7; Eisenhower Library,
                            <persName corresp="#p_WAC1">Whitman</persName> File, Eisenhower Diaries.
                            <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName>’s paper is <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., <persName>Dulles</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_HCA2">Herter</persName> Series, <persName corresp="#p_HCA2">Herter</persName>—May 1960.)</p>
                    <p>Eisenhower met with <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rayburn</persName> at 5:30
                        p.m., May 9: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“The President asked the Speaker’s cooperation and advice in dealing
                                with the implacable resistance of Congressman <persName corresp="#p_POE1">Otto Passman</persName> to the mutual security
                                program. At the President’s direction I briefly presented the
                                consequences certain to ensue should there be a massive reduction in
                                mutual security appropriations for Fiscal Year 1961.</p>
                            <pb facs="0531" n="499" xml:id="pg_499"/>
                            <p>“It was pointed out to the Speaker that the ‘pipeline’ is now so
                                severely reduced that a cut of a billion dollars or more would
                                unavoidably fall mainly on force modernization in the military
                                assistance part of the program—and that this would mainly hit <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and certain countries in
                                Asia.</p>
                            <p>“The Speaker stressed the effectiveness of <persName corresp="#p_POE1">Passman</persName>’s criticisms of
                                administrative errors in the program. The President quickly conceded
                                that errors are bound to occur in a program of this character and
                                magnitude but that these cannot be allowed to destroy the entire
                                effort. It was pointed out to the Speaker that prior reductions have
                                not crippled the program because funds still remaining in the
                                pipeline have tided the program over the successive reductions—a
                                process no longer feasible because of the consumption of the
                                pipeline these past few years.</p>
                            <p>“The Speaker stated to the President that he would ‘do his best’ to
                                get the highest possible figure for mutual security but gave no more
                                specific assurance than this, and this assertion was coupled with
                                the reiteration of the great difficulties in handling the program
                                this year.” (Memorandum for the record by <persName corresp="#p_HBN1">Harlow</persName>, May 10; <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Eisenhower Diaries)</p>
                        </quote></p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>