<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="308" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d308">
                    <head>308. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>In the early morning hours of July 6, the last day before the Congress
                        recessed for the Democratic and Republican Presidential conventions, it
                        passed legislation amending the Sugar Act of 1948, as amended, and extending
                        the Act for 3 months beyond its expiration date of December 31, 1960. Had
                        Congress recessed without action on this legislation, Cuba could have sold
                        the remaining 25 percent of its annual 1960 quota at the U.S. domestic price
                        of about 2 cents per pound above the world market rate. The legislation as
                        passed specifically provided that the President should determine the new
                        quota for Cuba for the balance of 1960 and for the first 3 months of 1961,
                        and provided a formula for reallocation of the old Cuban quota. The
                        Eisenhower administration had requested from Congress broad discretion in
                        allocating the reductions in the Cuban quota, but because of the need to
                        demonstrate disapproval of the Castro government, the President signed the
                        legislation with its rigid formulas for reallocation.</p>
                    <p>Under the terms of the new legislation, the President was authorized to
                        import sugar to meet the needs of U.S. consumers in amounts not exceeding
                        the amount by which the Cuban quota was reduced. Under Congress’ formula,
                        the first reallocation was to be made to countries with quotas between 3,000
                        and 10,000 tons—Haiti, the Netherlands, China, Panama, and Costa Rica—to
                        bring their total imports to 10,000 tons each during the calendar year.
                        Next, the Act provided that 15 percent of the remainder of imports was to be
                        purchased from the Philippines. The balance of the allocations were to be
                        purchased from countries other than the six above which had quotas in the
                        U.S. market. These purchases were to be prorated according to their
                        established quotas. Countries in this category were Mexico, Peru, Nicaragua,
                        and the Dominican Republic. If additional sugar was required, the President
                        could under the terms of the new legislation authorize purchase from any
                        foreign producer without regard to allocation.</p>
                    <p>President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> announced on July
                        6 that he was reducing the Cuban sugar quota from 739,752 to 39,752 short
                        tons. In addition, Cuba was denied a quota of an additional 156,000 tons—its
                        share of the Puerto Rican and Hawaiian deficit, and any share occasioned by
                        increased U.S. domestic consumption, approximately 150,000 tons. In all, the
                        Cuban sugar quota was reduced by 1 million tons. (Department of State, <hi rend="italic">Current Economic Developments,</hi> No. 602, July 19,
                        1960)</p>
                    <p>The act to amend the Sugar Act of 1948, as amended, P.L. 86–592, approved
                        July 6, 74 Stat. 330, is in <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy:
                            Current Documents, 1960,</hi> pages 797–798. Eisenhower’s proclamation
                        reducing the Cuban quota is <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., pages 205–206.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>