<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>325. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d325</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">325</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-02-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-02-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic affairs</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recXmtj6SyvT64JYD" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic warfare</term>
                    <term ref="reckO9szxNydLBID0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85003956"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Aluminum</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="recgAskQzr2OrtpaG" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Trade control</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-02-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-02-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="325"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d325">
                <head>325. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d325fn0"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, 460.509/2–1858. Secret. Drafted
                        by Armstrong on February 21 and approved by <persName corresp="#p_DCD1"
                            >Dillon</persName> on March 26.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1958-02-18">February 18, 1958</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Strategic Controls</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Sir Harold Caccia, British Ambassador</item>
                    <item>Mr. Paul Henry Gore-Booth, British Deputy Under Secretary of State</item>
                    <item>Mr. G.F. Thorold, British Economic Minister</item>
                    <item>Mr. Douglas Dillon, Deputy Under Secretary of State for Economic
                        Affairs</item>
                    <item>Mr. T.C. Mann, Assistant Secretary of State for Economic Affairs</item>
                    <item>Mr. Willis C. Armstrong, Director, OR</item>
                    <item>Mr. E.G. Moline, Deputy Director, <gloss target="#t_BNA1">BNA</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. Myron Black, Officer in Charge Economic Organization Affairs, <gloss
                            target="#t_RA1">RA</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. Gore-Booth said that he wanted to consider the matter of strategic controls.
                    He had prepared himself for the discussion by going through the whole story with
                    his people in London. He observed that changes in this field usually come by
                    spasms and that we appeared to be due for another one. He noted that the United
                    States and the United Kingdom are some distance apart in their positions. There
                    were three aspects of the matter which he wished to discuss: (1) strategic
                    concepts, (2) political considerations and (3) economic effect. In connection
                        <pb facs="0730" n="698" xml:id="pg_698"/> with the first, he referred to
                    certain military strategic concepts which have been approved in <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. He pointed out that the British military
                    establishment has given full endorsement to these concepts, and he noted that
                    the U.S. had also approved them in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. [<hi
                        rend="italic">7½ lines of source text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>Mr. Gore-Booth then discussed the political aspect of strategic controls. He said
                    that the clamor for commercial opportunities in England has stimulated a demand
                    for relaxation of controls, which, when coupled with general impressions of the
                    technological achievements of the Soviet Union, made it impossible for the
                    government to take a position favoring the status quo for controls, or a more
                    rigid system. He said that he recognized that a relaxation of controls would
                    not, in fact, bring much growth in trade, and that the political point was
                    primarily psychological.</p>
                <p>He then turned to the economic aspect of controls and said that his impression
                    from the material presented to him was that the U.S. favored a broad program of
                    economic warfare. The British question was whether you could do very much damage
                    to the Soviet Union by this process. He noted that some of the goods now being
                    embargoed by western countries are also being exported by the Soviet Union, such
                    as aluminum. He said that the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> had recently
                    talked with economic experts of all the Commonwealth countries, and had
                    discovered that none of these countries would go along with any kind of general
                    program of economic warfare and, indeed, felt that underdeveloped countries
                    needed Soviet aid. Consequently, the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> is
                    convinced, both from its commercial contacts and its own experience, that a
                    wholesale approach to deterring Soviet growth and development would not work. He
                    also noted that, while the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> was much interested
                    in preventing Soviet economic penetration of underdeveloped areas, it did not
                    feel that there was any likelihood of intensified trade controls having any
                    effect on Soviet capabilities in this field. Furthermore, in most cases the
                    underdeveloped countries themselves were sophisticated about dealing with the
                    Russians.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said in response that he was
                    pleased to have the opportunity to clarify the U.S. views on this matter. He
                    noted that the discussion of List II quotas last autumn had led the U.S. to
                    conclude that there was need for a new look at the whole control picture, and
                    this intensive review had proceeded within the government for several months.
                    The review was not focused on criteria, which have generally been dedicated
                    toward blocking the Soviet military effort, and no significant changes in
                    criteria have been or are being proposed by the U.S. The emphasis of the U.S.
                    effort during the past several months had been on developing a set of proposals
                    for modifying the lists, which would correspond to the best intelligence data
                    and the latest expert opinion on technical and military implications. The result
                    of <pb facs="0731" n="699" xml:id="pg_699"/> this examination had been to remove
                    a lot of items from the list, including, for example, items which the Soviet
                    Union itself exports. We had proposed a very few items for embargo which had
                    previously been on List II because the new list applies as a whole to Communist
                    China as well as the Soviet Union, and there are special items, such as jet
                    fuel, in which Communist China is deficient and the Soviet Union is not. We
                    feel, in view of our special defense responsibilities in the Far Eastern area,
                    that it is necessary to limit the supply of jet fuel in the hands of the Chinese
                    Communists. We had nevertheless proposed dropping List II as a general concept,
                    and had proposed that we retain List III, under a modified set of ground
                    rules.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> then said that Mr. Gore-Booth’s
                    remarks had shown that there is a real difference of opinion in military thought
                    and concept, which is at the root of the difference of opinion between the U.S.
                    and <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> regarding the level, nature, and purpose
                    of controls. We had originally thought that the entire pressure for modification
                    of controls within the British Government originated in the Board of Trade for
                    commercial reasons, but we were now interested to learn that the British
                    position was based on the position of the Ministry of Defense. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> noted that we certainly agree that
                    priority in attention should be given to the items which would contribute to the
                    availability on D Day of goods and equipment, but our Chiefs of Staff also
                    believe that we should not neglect items which would be useful in a period
                    subsequent to the initial thermonuclear exchange. Also, they feel that the
                    military industrial potential is most important in connection with the
                    possibility of conventional or semi-conventional warfare in the area of the
                    Middle East or Far East, although we recognize the improbability of conventional
                    or semi-conventional warfare in the European area. Consequently, from a military
                    standpoint we feel that exclusive emphasis on the point selected by the British
                    Ministry of Defense is incorrect, and that a proper military view should also
                    take into account supplies for the subsequent period and the capacity of the
                    Sino-Soviet military industrial complex to wage conventional warfare, especially
                    in Asia.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> then dealt with the political
                    problems of the Executive Branch in dealing with this matter. He noted that the
                    whole Mutual Security concept is based on the theory that it is a bulwark
                    against Soviet expansion. He said that a substantial open break between the U.S.
                    and its allies over trade controls, or an agreement on the part of the U.S. to a
                    serious downward reduction of trade controls, might well lead to considerable
                    harm to the aid program at a time of crucial importance in its consideration by
                    the Congress. He did not wish to hazard a guess regarding the results. He
                    observed further that this problem is different from the problem regarding the
                    China differential, <pb facs="0732" n="700" xml:id="pg_700"/> because it has to
                    do with the nature of our general policy toward the Sino-Soviet Bloc, and not
                    with a question of a difference of opinion regarding one aspect of the whole
                    problem.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> then went on to consider the
                    relationship of strategic controls to Sino-Soviet economic penetration of the
                    underdeveloped areas. He said our views were not too different from those of the
                    British. We think that this is the most serious aspect of our struggle with the
                    Soviet Union at this time. He emphasized that we do not believe in broad-scale
                    economic warfare but rather in a selective approach. He said our proposals were
                    designed precisely for this purpose. He added that we have no intention of
                    suggesting to third countries that they do not engage in trade with or accept
                    aid from the Soviet Union. Our domestic problem of obtaining approval for trade
                    agreements legislation and of obtaining funds for foreign aid are closely
                    related, however, to the question of a general western policy response to the
                    Soviet economic challenge, and it is difficult to persuade people of this if we
                    are at the same time asked to agree to a serious and damaging modification of
                    controls.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> concluded his remarks by saying
                    that obviously the U.S. did not wish any open break on this issue, and that some
                    ground for agreement must be found. He said that he had a personal feeling that
                    it was much easier to deal with this matter in terms of an item by item approach
                    to the lists, rather than to argue one theory or another. He said we are
                    considering the whole matter at the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> level to
                    determine whether there is any basis for arriving at some form of compromise
                    position. He did hope that the British position has sufficient latitude so that,
                    given a willingness to arrive at an agreement, there can be some mutually
                    agreeable compromise.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gore-Booth said Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName>’s statement
                    of the U.S. position had made the matter very much clearer, and he could see
                    that a good deal of the argument turned on the question of what is a strategic
                    material. He had noted that the U.S. proposal called for a reduction of about 29
                    items from the 181 in List I. He said that the British view was that the list
                    could be approximately cut in half to about 93. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1"
                        >Dillon</persName> said that an American reading of the British paper had
                    led to the conclusion that the British had intended to abolish the list
                    entirely, except for 31 items, whereas we felt we were making a significant
                    reduction in proposing the elimination of about 40 items, rather than 29. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> and Mr. Gore-Booth agreed that
                    further analysis by both the U.S. and <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> would be
                    useful in determining the extent to which there is a real disparity in position.
                    He commented wryly that while it is in the U.S. interest to take as long as
                    possible to work out the situation, because of pressures it is to the British
                    interest to conclude the matter as rapidly as possible.</p>
                <pb facs="0733" n="701" xml:id="pg_701"/>
                <p>Mr. Moline said that he thought the discussion had thus far failed to mention one
                    significant aspect, which is that too much emphasis on what both sides would
                    have available on D Day, or thereafter, overlooks the need to consider the
                    material and technical position of the two sides in the period before D Day. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> emphasized the importance of
                    this point.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gore-Booth raised a question as to whether it was in our power to do very
                    much with this problem, in terms of restraining the Soviet Union. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> agreed that further analysis of the
                    impact of the trade control program was always in order, but noted that U.S.
                    intelligence sources indicate that the program has been effective in restraining
                    Soviet growth and development. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName>
                    raised the question as to whether the western world should act in such a way as
                    to facilitate meeting the needs of the Soviet population, or of Communist China,
                    or whether it should move in the opposite direction. Mr. Gore-Booth said that he
                    wondered whether the trade control device was the right piece of machinery,
                    assuming that it was our objective not to facilitate meeting the needs of the
                    Soviet population.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> and Mr. Gore-Booth agreed that
                    it was desirable to avoid endless argument on criteria, and that it would be
                    advisable for both sides to take a mild attitude on the question of criteria at
                    the <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> discussion beginning on the 20th.
                    Mr. Gore-Booth said his government would consider U.S. views seriously and
                    respond in due course. He could not predict the reaction of his Ministry of
                    Defense. He would consider whether the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> could
                    put emphasis on the list review. It was noted that care would have to be taken
                    regarding the sensitivities of the French, and possibly those of other countries
                    concerning the situation. It was agreed that the best place for technical
                    discussions was <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
