<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>347. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d347</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">347</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-09-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-09-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec2SKz4RNoMDKY9k" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040584"
                        lcsh-match="exact">East-West trade</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recco4TvraiYB3Tfh" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007556"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radar</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="reckGy7aTuZSfk4pU" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048847"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Fishing vessel</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-09-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-09-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="347"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d347">
                <head>347. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d347fn0"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, 460.509/9–1559. Confidential.
                        Drafted by Wright and approved by <persName corresp="#p_DCD1"
                            >Dillon</persName>’s Special Assistant, <persName corresp="#p_BRC1"
                            >Robert C. Brewster</persName>, on September 26.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1959-09-15">September 15, 1959</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> List Review</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The Viscount Hood, Chargé d’Affaires ad Interim, British Embassy</item>
                    <item>The Under Secretary</item>
                    <item>Mr. Harold A. Levin, Director, USRO/ST, Paris</item>
                    <item>Mr. L.O. Sanderhoff, Office of European Regional Affairs</item>
                    <item>Mr. Robert B. Wright, Chief, Economic Defense Division</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0804" n="772" xml:id="pg_772"/>
                <p>The Under Secretary referred to the British proposals for <gloss
                        target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> which had been transmitted to the
                    Department on September 8th.<note n="1" xml:id="d347fn1">The British draft
                        proposals are described below.</note> He said that the proposals were
                    described as being the product of the official working level within the British
                    Government, not as yet reviewed or approved by British Ministers. He said that
                    of course the United States had not made a detailed technical analysis of the
                    British proposals, but did have some initial views.</p>
                <p>The Under Secretary said that the cumulative effect of the British proposals was
                    so extensive as not to be in accord with the spirit of the general understanding
                    which prevailed at the time of the 1958 Consultative Group meeting to the effect
                    that the annual list review would involve only minor adjustments in the
                    international lists necessitated by significant changes in technology or Soviet
                    bloc utilization during the year. He said that the prevailing view had clearly
                    been that the 1958 list review represented a major revision and reshaping of the
                    international control system for a long-term period, at least several years. The
                    previous general list review had taken place in 1954 and it was the view of the
                    participating governments that the 1958 review would remove the necessity for
                    any major revision of the lists for approximately a similar period of time. He
                    said that of course it was understood that any participating country might make
                    a special proposal on a particular item at any time as, for example, the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> had done with respect to rolling mills.</p>
                <p>The British proposed changes, contrary to the view that the 1959 review should be
                    a minor overhaul operation, would affect half of the present embargo list. The
                    list contains 120 items at present and the British proposals would contemplate
                    removing 26 items plus an additional six sub-items, would propose redefinitions
                    for an additional 12 items, and might involve some potential changes in an
                    additional 16 items which are still under study within the British Government.
                    Changes of this magnitude would necessitate a major negotiation in <gloss
                        target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> on the scale which was necessary last year,
                    especially when the suggested changes of other participating governments were
                    added to the changes suggested by the British. One of the most disappointing
                    aspects of the British proposals was the fact that they proposed the deletion of
                    all the items which had been the subject of special compromise efforts in 1958.
                    This honestly seemed to us not to be in the real spirit of the 1958 agreement.
                    The Under Secretary said he hoped the British Ministers would consider this U.S.
                    reaction most seriously.</p>
                <p>He said that the British proposals left us in a difficult situation. A major
                    negotiation would require the assignment of large numbers of technicians and
                    lengthy discussions in <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> which would
                    unquestionably <pb facs="0805" n="773" xml:id="pg_773"/> extend for many months.
                    This negotiating process could not possibly be completed within the schedule set
                    by the Consultative Group. Instead of a January 1 effective date for the revised
                    lists, a June 30 date would be more realistic. Apart from the extended time
                    involved for such negotiation, the worst part of the situation is that it would
                    inevitably involve a sharp and unedifying debate between the United States and
                    the United Kingdom in the multilateral forum before the other participating
                    governments. Such an exhibition could not help but be damaging to the interest
                    of both the United States and the United Kingdom in maintaining a cooperative
                    atmosphere within the <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> and <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> community. Any such flare-up of basic
                    differences on East-West trade control questions would be particularly
                    unfortunate at this time since such good progress has been made in recent months
                    in resolving the various economic problems which have troubled <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss>–UK relations.</p>
                <p>The Under Secretary said that he felt there might be a better way out of the
                    difficult situation which we would face if the British proposals were tabled as
                    they stand in <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss>, and that he wished to
                    outline his views on this matter for consideration by the British Ministers when
                    they go over the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> official-level proposals. He
                    said that it might be possible for the British to select a few items which were
                    of special importance to them either for trade reasons or for political reasons
                    or because of other considerations of urgency, and propose changes on those
                    items in the forthcoming annual list review. If the British were to select six
                    or eight or, at most, ten of such items for discussion in <gloss
                        target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss>, this would represent a manageable task for
                    the Committee and would be quite acceptable to the United States in terms of a
                    feasible working program. The remaining items in the British proposals could
                    then be made the subject of bilateral technical discussions between the United
                    States and the United Kingdom, beginning at such time as the 1959 annual <gloss
                        target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> review has been completed. The purpose of
                    such bilateral <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_UK1"
                        >UK</gloss> discussions should be to discover whether a substantial
                    agreement might be reached between the two countries on the remaining British
                    proposals. If such agreement could be reached, the United States would then have
                    no objection to British submission of such proposals to <gloss
                        target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> at any time following the 1959 list review
                    or at the latest at the time of the 1960 list review. This arrangement would
                    have the advantage of permitting the British to deal with a few items which are
                    of importance to them and on which changes might be justified in <gloss
                        target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> and would be in accordance with the
                    prevailing concept of a limited annual list review. In addition, it would remove
                    the danger of an unrewarding semi-public debate between the United States and
                    the United Kingdom and would permit an orderly bilateral examination of the
                    British <pb facs="0806" n="774" xml:id="pg_774"/> proposals on their merits. As
                    a practical matter, the British would not really lose any time as compared with
                    a major review which would extend well into next year in any event.</p>
                <p>Lord Hood said that he was not familiar with the details of the items dealt with
                    in the British proposals but inquired whether the Under Secretary had in mind
                    that the British might make the selection of items for discussion in <gloss
                        target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> in the 1959 review themselves or whether he
                    had in mind that such selections would be a joint matter with the United States.
                    The Under Secretary said that he had in mind that the British would make the
                    selection themselves taking account of their own special interests. Lord Hood
                    said that he had little idea of what items might be of special importance, but
                    he did recall that he had heard considerable reference made to the importance of
                    aircraft. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> noted that the
                    British proposal with respect to aircraft did not appear to be a troublesome one
                    to deal with in the <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> discussions. He said
                    the British proposal was essentially for a clarification and extension of
                    embargo coverage for aircraft engines to bring this treatment into conformity
                    with the treatment of aircraft themselves, and seemed to be an appropriate
                    suggestion. He noted also that the British had made proposals for the
                    liberalization of certain instrument systems and navigation radar systems for
                    aircraft to make such equipment freely available for export to the Soviet bloc
                    for use on scheduled services to the free world. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1"
                        >Dillon</persName> said that this might be another point of special interest
                    to the British. It was a liberalization somewhat beyond our present policy on
                    such sales but might be a reasonable question to re-examine.</p>
                <p>The Under Secretary said that while there might be some items such as those which
                    had been mentioned which were of significance to the British and which might
                    profitably be re-examined, he felt that there certainly appeared to be many
                    items in the British list to which the British themselves might wish to give
                    some careful second thoughts. For example, he said that the proposal to delete
                    fishing vessels designed for speeds of 17 knots and over was a type of proposal
                    which seemed to be highly doubtful. It was clear that nobody would build a
                    fishing vessel of that speed unless it was actually intended for naval
                    applications. While the United Kingdom and the United States might not wish to
                    build or sell such vessels to the bloc, the removal of the item from the
                    international list would make it possible for other <gloss target="#t_COCOM1"
                        >COCOM</gloss> countries to take advantage of such trade, and the Japanese,
                    for example, might be most interested in building substantial quantities of
                    fishing vessels for sale to the Communist Chinese where they would in fact
                    constitute a significant military potential item.</p>
                <pb facs="0807" n="775" xml:id="pg_775"/>
                <p>The British Chargé said that he would report the U.S. reactions and proposal to
                    London for consideration there and indicated that he saw some merit to the
                    proposal which Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> had
                    outlined.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
