<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-04-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-04-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="66" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d66">
                    <head>66. Memorandum From Secretary of Agriculture <persName corresp="#p_BET1" type="from">Benson</persName> to the President’s Assistant (<persName type="to">Adams</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d66fn0">Source: Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_CFEP1">CFEP</gloss> Files: FRC 62 A 624, Agricultural Surpluses for Peace,
                                <gloss target="#t_CFEP1">CFEP</gloss> 570. Official Use Only.
                            Distributed as Tab A to a memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_CLCPH1">Cullen</persName> to the <gloss target="#t_CFEP1">CFEP</gloss>, May
                            12.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><gloss target="#t_CFEP1">CFEP</gloss> 570/info</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-04-29">April 29, 1958</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Agricultural Surpluses as a Tool for Peace</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>You are aware from our earlier discussions that John H. Davis, formerly
                        Assistant Secretary of Agriculture, has been engaged by the State Department
                        to make a study of how U.S. farm surpluses can better serve American foreign
                        policy. A copy of the study is attached.<note n="1" xml:id="d66fn1">Not
                            found attached.</note></p>
                    <p rend="center">I</p>
                    <p>The first part of this study has been completed. The cogent findings are
                        these: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Our surplus production capacity in agriculture is likely to be of
                                some duration.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Need for food in many countries outside the Soviet Bloc, above
                                what can be produced in these countries or bought with foreign
                                exchange, is likely to be large for some time to come. The
                                maintenance of political stability in these countries will probably
                                require that some share of this need be met by the United
                                States.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>This dual problem (our excess capacity and foreign need) can be
                                alleviated by a two-sided 5-year program: <list>
                                    <label>(a)</label>
                                    <item>Further adjustments in our programs for American
                                        agriculture, both administrative and legislative.</item>
                                    <label>(b)</label>
                                    <item>A food-for-peace program based on P.L. 480, gradually
                                        phased out as the receiving nations are assisted to raise
                                        their own production levels.</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list></p>
                    <pb facs="0189" n="157" xml:id="pg_157"/>
                    <p rend="center">II</p>
                    <p>To adopt a program such as <persName corresp="#p_DRH1">Davis</persName>
                        recommends would involve little change from what we are now doing except
                        that: <list>
                            <item>We would be <hi rend="italic">positive</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">negative;</hi></item>
                            <item>We would recognize that the problem is of <hi rend="italic">some
                                    duration</hi> rather than <hi rend="italic">temporary;</hi></item>
                            <item>We would emphasize the <hi rend="italic">helpful foreign policy
                                    aspects</hi> rather than to treat the operation as <hi rend="italic">iniquitous surplus disposal.</hi></item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p rend="center">III</p>
                    <p>The program proposed would have both advantages and disadvantages.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Advantages</hi>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Such an operation is likely to come into being in any case. The
                                question is whether we give it leadership.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Such a step would maximize our greatest advantage over the Soviet
                                Union. It would be agriculture’s share in our foreign policy.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Properly handled, it would lift production and living levels in
                                the free world.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Much credit would be reflected to this country for good
                                stewardship of our scientific know-how, for our compassion for the
                                world’s needy and for our contribution to peace.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The farm policy focus would shift from the negative fight to
                                reduce price supports to the more positive approach: “Use our
                                abundance in the cause of peace.”</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Such a program may increase support for the President’s
                                legislative recommendations in the Agricultural Message of January
                                    1958.<note n="2" xml:id="d66fn2">For text of Eisenhower’s
                                    January 16 special message to the Congress on agriculture, see
                                        <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the
                                        United States: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Dwight D.
                                            Eisenhower</persName>, 1958,</hi> pp.
                                100–107.</note></item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Disadvantages</hi>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>If production levels in the recipient countries should fail to
                                rise sufficiently, these countries would become dependent upon us
                                for continuing help. We would have created a group of more or less
                                permanent relief clients.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Unwisely handled, such a program could antagonize other
                                agricultural exporting nations.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Such a program might easily become an excuse to further postpone
                                needed changes in farm legislation.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Some people would object to spending so much American effort in
                                behalf of other nations.</item>
                            <pb facs="0190" n="158" xml:id="pg_158"/>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>We might be accused of embracing a proposal favored by Senator
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HG2">Humphrey</persName> and others from
                                the opposition camp.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p rend="center">IV</p>
                    <p>We have reviewed the proposal in the Department of Agriculture. While we are
                        not now ready to advocate the program proposed, we consider that it merits
                        consideration. It is my understanding that this also is the attitude of the
                        State Department. Therefore, I propose the following steps: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The attitude of the President should be ascertained as to whether
                                he considers the proposal deserving of serious consideration.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>If the President is so inclined, the proposal should be reviewed
                                by the various Departments, in the Francis Committee on Agricultural
                                Surplus Disposal,<note n="3" xml:id="d66fn3">President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> established the
                                    Interagency Committee on Agricultural Surplus Disposal on
                                    September 9, 1954, to coordinate the administration of P.L. 480.
                                    The Committee, headed by <persName corresp="#p_FC1">Clarence
                                        Francis</persName>, consisted of officials from the
                                    Departments of Agriculture, Commerce, the Treasury, and State;
                                    the International Cooperation Administration; and the Bureau of
                                    the Budget.</note> and in the <persName corresp="#p_RCB1">Randall</persName> Commission on Foreign Economic
                                Policy.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p rend="center">V</p>
                    <p>If the proposal receives approval in this review and if the White House
                        approves, one or more of these steps could be taken: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The President could call an International Conference on Food for
                                Peace. (A draft statement is attached, outlining what such a
                                Conference might attempt.)<note n="4" xml:id="d66fn4">Not
                                    printed.</note></item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The Secretary of Agriculture could launch the proposal in a series
                                of speeches.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The proposal could be made a part of the Administration’s
                                legislative program for 1959. (The actual legislative changes which
                                would be required are not many. Public Law 480 in slightly modified
                                form would be a suitable vehicle.)</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>I would be happy to confer with you on this matter as convenient.</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="strong">E.T. Benson</hi><note n="5" xml:id="d66fn5">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>