<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-02-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-02-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="10" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d10">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conference
                            184.01202/44½</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Major <persName type="from">Arnold
                                    Whitridge</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Commission to
                                    Negotiate Peace</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-02-15">February 15, 1919</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                February 18.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>1. There is inclosed herewith translation of speech delivered by Count
                            von Brockdorff-Rantzau, German Minister of Foreign Affairs, on the
                            foreign policy of Germany before the German National Assembly, Weimar,
                            February 14, 1919.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">A. Whitridge</hi></signed></closer>
                        <pb facs="0066" n="16" xml:id="pg_16"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Full Text of Speech of Count von
                                    Brockdorff-Rantzau Before the German National Assembly, Weimar,
                                    February 14, 1919</hi></head>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ladies and Gentlemen</hi>: The new government
                                has confirmed my appointment as Minister of Foreign Affairs. This
                                makes it my duty to render account to you concerning the fundamental
                                lines upon which it is my intention to conduct the foreign affairs
                                of the Empire within the bounds of the general policies of the
                                present government. The inheritance left by the collapse of the old
                                system to the new government is a bankrupt estate, and yet I realize
                                that this estate cannot be liquidated according to individual
                                judgment, but according to the wish of the creditors.</p>
                            <p>I may sum up the problems of German foreign policy in two categories:
                                The clearing away of the situation due to the war and the bringing
                                about of normal relations with the society of the nations. The
                                clearing up of the war-situation is a crying need of the whole
                                world. Germany is not responsible for the fact that it still exists.
                                When the former German government came to an agreement with the
                                Entente and the United States upon the basis of the Wilsonian
                                conditions of peace and accepted the armistice conditions upon this
                                basis, no one would have believed that peace would be so long
                                delayed. Unfortunately, Germany’s disarmament of her free will did
                                not render the enemies any milder, but rather put them in the
                                position to obtain from us still further concessions by repeated
                                threats of renewal of the offensive. Recently they have made the
                                attempt by this means to settle matters which, unquestionably,
                                belong among the subjects to be determined at the moment of the
                                signing of peace and which they intended to decide one-sidedly to
                                our disadvantage by armed pressure, while under the conditions of
                                peace agreed upon they were to be decided upon the basis of justice.
                                I have rejected this attempt and <hi rend="underline">shall</hi>
                                reject such attempts. Violence may be employed against us, but we
                                cannot be forced to recognize violence as justice.</p>
                            <p>We have expected an early peace because armistice conditions only had
                                reason of existence if made for a short duration of time. We are on
                                the point of demobilizing our entire forces hitherto existing and
                                replacing our old army of times of peace, that we could now make
                                good use of in the east, by new republican troops. Nevertheless, the
                                conditions of the armistice are made more stringent each month. If
                                our enemies think it their duty to punish us, they are serving the
                                idea of revenge instead of justice and are destroying the spirit
                                upon which, according to their own declarations, peace should be
                                made. Germany has accepted the results of her defeat and is
                                determined to fulfill the conditions agreed upon with her opponents;
                                these conditions <pb facs="0067" n="17" xml:id="pg_17"/> mean a
                                complete renunciation of the political aims of former Germany and
                                the recognition of the truth spoken by one of the former great
                                spirits of Weimar, “History is the Tribunal of the World”. But we
                                refuse our enemies as our judges because of the prejudices. We in
                                our hearts cannot bow to the opinion of the victor but only to the
                                judgment of impartial parties. Therefore, I shall not allow myself
                                to be thrust aside from the articles of the Wilsonian peace program
                                as it is recognized by both sides. Among these belongs first of all
                                the submission of our differences with other states to an
                                international court of arbitration and the renunciation of armed
                                preparations which would permit of a neighbor’s being attacked by
                                force of arms. We stand ready for both limitations of our
                                sovereignty if our former enemies and our future neighbors submit to
                                similar limitations. (Quite right!).</p>
                            <p>We admit that the position taken by Germany at the peace conferences
                                at The Hague in regard to these two fundamental questions comprised
                                an historic wrong (unfortunately!) for which our entire nation must
                                now suffer. This confession does not include by any means the
                                admission that, as the enemy insists, the German people alone are
                                responsible for the world-war and that they conducted it with a
                                barbarism that is exclusively peculiar to them. We have had reason
                                to complain about war plans of years standing on the part of our
                                enemies and about grave atrocities in their conduct of the war, and
                                we stand ready to permit unprejudiced men who enjoy the confidence
                                of both parties in the war to establish the guilt for the war and in
                                the war. Therefore, we hold fast to the Wilsonian theory that no
                                costs of the war are to be paid to the victor and that no
                                territories of the vanquished are to be ceded. (Applause.) We are
                                duty bound and willing to make good the damages incurred through our
                                attack by the civil population in the regions occupied by us. If we
                                rebuild in these regions what has been destroyed by us, we will do
                                so by our unfettered labor. (Quite right!) We protest against our
                                prisoners being utilized to do such work as slaves, and against the
                                possible continuance of the state of war in order to have an excuse
                                for this compulsory service under the law of nations (Lively
                                applause). Our enemies owe the vastly greater part of their victory
                                not to the military but to the economic conduct of the war (Quite
                                correct!). Hence it follows that peace must be not only a political
                                but inherently also an economic peace. Quite rightly President
                                Wilson characterized the principle of economic liberty and equality
                                of rights as a fundamental condition of a just and lasting peace. We
                                may, therefore, suppose that the decisions of the Economic
                                Conference of Paris of 1916 will be dropped. It is evident that any
                                differential treatment of Germany, even for a time in the matter of
                                trade and commerce would be unacceptable <pb facs="0068" n="18" xml:id="pg_18"/> to us (Applause). One cannot treat a people
                                like the German as a second-class nation (Quite right!). One cannot
                                impose upon it a period of quarantine before its admission into the
                                League of Nations, as one keeps a vessel from port on account of
                                fear of the pest (Lively applause!). If we accept just conditions of
                                peace and give guarantees for their fulfillment that a reasonable
                                opponent in a peace-treaty can demand, there is no ground for
                                refusing us most-favored nation conditions.</p>
                            <p>To be sure we have much to relearn in the sphere of commercial
                                politics. We have not always acted upon the principle that even in
                                international relationships the truth holds—If thou wouldst receive,
                                so must thou give (Very good!). That has come certainly in part from
                                the one-sided bureaucratic complexion of our foreign service. (Quite
                                right!) By bureaucratic means the economic relations of nations,
                                which have been profoundly disorganized by the war, can never be
                                re-established. (Quite right!) It is my intention, therefore, to
                                appoint more than in the past experienced specialists in the foreign
                                service. I have already made a beginning. I shall count upon it that
                                the economic side of our foreign policy will in the future make use
                                of the principle of commercial free trade that a just peace must
                                give us in a manner that is as far from unstable, reckless business
                                as it is from narrow minded, corner-grocer politics. In this way we
                                shall be able the more readily to avoid the dislike of other nations
                                to Germany’s business methods, which had considerable to do with
                                preparing the atmosphere of war.</p>
                            <p>Freedom of commerce presupposes, however, the freedom of the seas.
                                (Quite right!) Therefore that article of the Wilsonian Doctrine that
                                deals with the freedom of the seas is one of the most important for
                                Germany.</p>
                            <p>For us in connection with this point the important thing is not so
                                much the rules of sea-warfare,—we do not want to speak of new wars
                                at this time—but rather the peaceful use of the ocean highways and
                                of its coasts and ports. Regarding this important point of the
                                future laws of nations, however, a clear understanding does not yet
                                exist. The Entente last fall withheld their consent to this point;
                                the conditions that they have imposed upon Germany in connection
                                with the promise of delivery of food supplies and the prolongation
                                of the armistice, leads to the fear that they wish to rob Germany of
                                its entire commercial fleet. If it is desired that Germany be forced
                                to enter the League of Nations without a commercial fleet, that
                                would mean a high-handed upsetting of its economic development.
                                (Lively applause!)</p>
                            <p>Such a metamorphosis cannot take place without the accompaniment of
                                fearful convulsions that would spell continual danger to universal
                                peace.</p>
                            <pb facs="0069" n="19" xml:id="pg_19"/>
                            <p>Nor is it any more possible for Germany to enter the League of
                                Nations without colonies than without a commercial fleet. (Renewed
                                lively applause!) According to Wilson’s program, colonial questions
                                are to be subjected to a free, generous, absolutely unpartisan
                                settlement. According to this program we expect the restitution of
                                our colonial territories that have been taken from us, partly by
                                threadbare excuses. (Quite right!) We stand ready to discuss the
                                ceding of this or that colony, but as rightful owners. Future
                                colonial policies shall above all guarantee the humane treatment of
                                the native population. In this respect—we must admit it—mistakes
                                have been made also by us.</p>
                            <p>Missionary activities in which Germany played a large part—though
                                they have been greatly circumscribed by the war—must in the interest
                                of the natives be assured. In connection with this we favor the idea
                                of an international control over tropical colonies under the
                                condition that all colonial powers submit thereto and that Germany
                                receives a just share in the utilization and in the products of the
                                colonies. (Quite right!) To be sure participation in colonial
                                activities can only be of importance to us when the active firms,
                                who are to be regarded as the sole supporters of practical colonial
                                policies, are compensated for the damages they have received at the
                                hands of the enemy.</p>
                            <p>On the other hand we must be prepared to lose valuable portions of
                                the real territory of the Empire. This is above all true of
                                Alsace-Lorraine, the regaining of which was the fruit of our
                                victories and the symbol of German unity. You know that President
                                Wilson has posed the demand that the wrong done by Germany in 1871
                                by the annexation of Alsace-Lorraine shall be made good. From the
                                standpoint of the new laws of international morality, according to
                                which populations, in the game of the powers, should not be pushed
                                about like chessmen, it was unjust to decide the fate of the people
                                of Alsace and Lorraine without their consent, and even without
                                regard to language boundaries. (Lively applause!) I shall not refer
                                here to past injustices done the German people. I accept Wilson’s
                                point of view because the rights of the present population of
                                Alsace-Lorraine are at stake. Violence is being done these rights,
                                when at this moment the French forces of occupation treat the land
                                like a finally conquered one, and expel or imprison all persons whom
                                they regard as obstructions to their imperialistic plans, and
                                infringe on its language by making it French by violence. (Lively
                                applause from all sides) The Peace Conference has not yet put its
                                seal upon the fate of Alsace-Lorraine. Legally Alsace-Lorraine is
                                still territory of the Empire. From this fact we derive our right to
                                champion the cause of the population of Alsace-Lorraine that their
                                voices be heard in the determination of their fate. (Applause.)
                                Whether they wish to become French Departments <pb facs="0070" n="20" xml:id="pg_20"/> or a German free state, whether they
                                prefer autonomy or complete independence: Germany will never believe
                                that the new Europe is founded upon justice until the solemn assent
                                of the entire population of Alsace-Lorraine be given to that article
                                of the treaty of peace that determines the future of their land.</p>
                            <p>The French plan of joining the Prussian Saar district or the Bavarian
                                Palatinate with Alsace and Lorraine indicates an imperialistic
                                oppression which must be criticised just as sharply as the
                                intentions of former German Chauvinists in regard to the Longwy and
                                Briey basins. (Quite right!) The French are acting in just the same
                                way towards the coal treasures of the Saar as the German
                                Imperialists did towards the mineral wealth of the Longwy and Briey
                                basins. If such propositions are accepted by the Peace
                                Commissioners, then that is the last of any hopes towards ennobling
                                international relations. (Quite right! and applause). Naturally
                                France has a political interest in any weakening of Germany as long
                                as both great nations regard each other as mutual hereditary enemies
                                and therefore are pitted against each other armed to the teeth. The
                                Peace Conference will have the task of furnishing guarantees that
                                will make such a state of affairs seem senseless, but let them
                                beware of finding these guarantees in tearing loose parts of the
                                German Empire which are among its most important members. (Quite
                                right! and vigorous applause). You know what opinions are being
                                spread abroad by France and Belgium with suspicious zeal in
                                Rhineland and Westphalia:—the establishment of an independent
                                republic, which would soon fall under French leadership after the
                                French and Belgian borders had been pushed further into German
                                territory. With great ingenuity these plans make use of centrifugal
                                forces which were let loose in the West by an excessive
                                centralization of our whole economic life in the war offices of the
                                capital of the empire, and recently by certain phenomena attendant
                                upon the revolution in Berlin. (Quite right!) Thus true and honest
                                supporters of the idea of the German Empire have been made the
                                victims of a dangerous subordination, against which I must give most
                                emphatic warning in the interests of German foreign policies.
                                (Applause!)</p>
                            <p>I must direct the same warning to certain circles in the south of our
                                Fatherland whose cry, “Los von Berlin”, (Free from Berlin) finds an
                                echo which can be understood to a certain extent, but is none the
                                less lamentable. Even if the restoration of the line of the Main
                                might for the moment seem to promise advantages, which a certain
                                subterranean policy of our enemies tried to make the population
                                believe, even during the war, in the long run such a separation will
                                surely lead to the ruin of the political and economic independence
                                of the separated members. (Quite true! and applause). The German
                                people is beyond all <pb facs="0071" n="21" xml:id="pg_21"/> state
                                boundaries, even beyond the boundaries of the old Empire, a <hi rend="underline">living unity.</hi> One single state is its
                                natural form of existence. (Very true! and applause). We have no
                                intention of making either the Swiss or Dutch into Germans; the only
                                parts of Scandinavia we have annexed are her old Sagas and her
                                present writers. (Very good!)</p>
                            <p>But our Austrian brothers and we had the same history until the
                                collapse of the Holy Roman Empire of the German Nation. We sat with
                                them in the Paulskirche, and the war which separated us, has, at the
                                best, always been thought of as a civil war which realized the
                                “little-German”, instead of the greater-German idea. Once we find
                                ourselves together again, after all the non-German races in the old
                                Hapsburg Monarchy have declared their independence, we know that we
                                have only made a tardy correction of a mistake in the foundation of
                                the Empire, to which the Peace Conference will certainly not refuse
                                its sanction. (Applause!). The German National Assembly may already
                                protest and so may I as leader of German foreign policies, against
                                the injustice done to German-Austria by former members of the
                                Imperial Government. (Quite right!)</p>
                            <p>The new Czecho-Slovak State is only infringing on the law to which it
                                owes its own creation, when it attempts by the force of arms to
                                subject not only the Germans of Moravia and Bohemia to its rule, but
                                also lays claim to districts towards the southeast inhabited by
                                Germans. It even threatens to attack territory of the German Empire
                                itself. Sharp protest must be made against any such attempts.
                                (Lively applause!). The economic needs of the Czecho-Slovak State,
                                which arise from the fact that it is cut off from the sea, can be
                                discussed and settled quite calmly and quietly. The new Germany has
                                just as much interest in the prosperity of its aspiring neighbor, as
                                the latter has in Germany’s economic soundness. (Quite right!)</p>
                            <p>Even as we are determined hereafter to make good the rights of
                                nationality where they are in favor of German brothers, we will also
                                recognize these rights even when they are employed against our
                                power. This applies first of all to the Poles. We have declared
                                ourselves as ready to allow those parts of our Empire settled
                                indubitably by Poles, to join the Polish State. We will keep our
                                promise. What districts fall under Article 13 of Wilson’s principles
                                is open to discussion. Some impartial power should decide that
                                point. Until that is decided these territories belong to the Empire.
                                (Applause!). The Prussian State and the Imperial Government are the
                                only powers authorized to exercise sovereign prerogatives therein.
                                The impassioned Polish national propaganda has not been willing to
                                await the decisions of the Peace Conference, but has risen in force
                                against German and Prussian authority, in order to enter into the
                                peace negotiations with as favorable an array of possessions as
                                possible. So they are bringing the <pb facs="0072" n="22" xml:id="pg_22"/> horrors of war again to Eastern Germany, which
                                is already threatened with the greater danger of Bolshevic
                                Imperialism. Thus they prevent us from protecting the Prussian East
                                Provinces in an effective manner against the common enemy. These
                                facts must be sufficient to make it clear to everyone understanding
                                the political situation that it is our first duty to call the
                                Prussian Poles to order—to keep them from violence until the
                                decisions of the Peace Conference have been reached. They can no
                                longer claim that it is in self defence, for the new German
                                government has lifted the oppressive special legislation and was
                                ready to meet the Poles in the question of the selection of
                                officials. Despite this, the Poles represented us as the aggressors
                                and the Entente undertakes to forbid us using force against the
                                Poles in our own country. The Empire has refused this unreasonable
                                demand and has in turn demanded the withdrawal of all armed bodies
                                of Poles from German territory. (Applause!). The German government
                                will be in complete sympathy with any other form of procedure which
                                the allied and associated powers wish to institute to produce quiet
                                in Polish districts. We are obligated by the armistice conditions to
                                allow the passage of delegations for this purpose from the Baltic
                                Sea to the Polish State, and to assist them and the journey of the
                                Commission in any possible way. It would be to our advantage that
                                the atmosphere of hate that poisoned German-Polish relations even
                                before the beginning of peace negotiations give place to the purer
                                air of mutual understanding. Unfortunately we cannot foresee in
                                Poland an agreeable neighboring state. (Quite true!) It must and
                                will be our aim to find a <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> which
                                will carefully guard national interests and mutually protect
                                national peculiarities and characteristics. In this connection must
                                be recognized the right of the Poles to an assured communication
                                with the Baltic. This problem can be solved by a regulation by
                                treaty of navigation on the Vistula, and by railroad and harbor
                                concessions, without having to encroach on the prerogatives of the
                                Empire over inalienable West Prussian territory.</p>
                            <p>That which is just for the German Poles is fitting for the German
                                Danes. The German government considers it its duty to grant to the
                                Danes the same right to self-government that it demands for the
                                Germans themselves. After the development which affairs have taken,
                                I hope that on our northern boundary an example will be set showing
                                how a national disagreement of years’ standing may be harmoniously
                                settled. (Applause!). The German people is united in the wish to
                                live in peaceful relations with the Danes, relations not disturbed
                                by any secret complaints. The majority of the Danish people will
                                certainly not wish that Germany’s defeat should be misused in order
                                to make German land Danish. (Quite right!)</p>
                            <pb facs="0073" n="23" xml:id="pg_23"/>
                            <p>The coming peace negotiations will present a theme that is
                                characteristic of them. Among all the peoples engaged in the war,
                                millions of hearts are demanding the most serious attention for an
                                international regulation of the social question. Even as after the
                                Reformation, treaties of peace could not be signed without clauses
                                regarding religious liberty, and after the upheaval of the French
                                Revolution the question of political freedom concerned the Peace
                                Congress, now after the world war of the masses, the question of the
                                social freedom of the working classes must be internationally
                                settled. (Applause!). This demand can be founded on the principle of
                                economic equality of rights. This principle will open equal
                                possibilities on the world market, to every member of the League of
                                Nations. It would work to the disadvantage of socially conscientious
                                and progressive nations, if the exploiters of human energy were free
                                to take advantage of their low cost of production in cutting out
                                their competitors. (Lively applause!). But here the aim sought is
                                not only material but is of a more noble nature,—its basic thought
                                being that the common task of all men is to make life richer and
                                more complete, and not, in a period of high civilization to debase
                                it to mere parts of the machine in the process of production.
                                (ApplauseI). This thought is forcing its way with such elemental
                                strength, that circles which have withstood it up to the present
                                will finally have to bend before the momentum of social forces. I do
                                not mean by that decisions by force; on the contrary I see in the
                                policy of force now carried on by the Russian Bolshevists rather the
                                defeat than the victory of socialistic principles. (Quite right!) It
                                is a question of peaceful reasoning about the way which social
                                development shall follow. Germany is not running any danger of a
                                ruinous transformation of its existing conditions. For decades
                                Germany has been making considerable progress down the road which
                                all must travel. The thought of social freedom is nowhere more at
                                home than in Germany. That makes our duty all the more
                                imperative,—not to conclude peace without trying to secure
                                international assent to our social program. That the peaces
                                concluded in the east were of a purely capitalistic nature was a
                                disavowal of our social spirit. Such treaties are today a danger for
                                any conqueror. The German government has decided to take essentially
                                the ground held by the conferences at Leeds and Berne when it comes
                                to clauses in the peace treaty about labor laws and protection and
                                insurance of laborers.</p>
                            <p>We expect that the coming peace will create a strong organization of
                                the world in the League of Nations proposed by Wilson, which alone
                                will make possible such a common task. The idea of a League of
                                Nations, which only a short time ago seemed a vision of idealistic
                                dreamers, has now come into the clear light of actuality. Already a
                                great number of burning questions concerning a League of Nations <pb facs="0074" n="24" xml:id="pg_24"/> have been brushed aside in
                                Paris, which could not be settled by an interchange of opinions
                                among the Powers.</p>
                            <p>Germany is resolved to cooperate unhesitatingly in the establishment
                                of the League, even though the others should regard us with the
                                deepest suspicion and the League should have been planned to prevent
                                Germany from inaugurating a warlike policy,—which, indeed, is far
                                from our ideas. This suspicion we must overcome with a clean
                                righteous love of peace. (Approval!). An immediate proof of this
                                will lie in the determined renunciation of any policy of armament.
                                Germany will soon be forced for economic and financial reasons to
                                limit its armament greatly, retaining only what is necessary for the
                                preservation of internal order and for the security of our outer
                                boundaries. For a foreign policy that is founded on an overwhelming
                                armament may be a comfortable, but it is mostly an evil and an
                                unfruitful policy. (Very true, from the Left). In any case, you can
                                expect from me a conduct of national affairs which will not be
                                tapping its sword every moment in order to accomplish its designs,
                                but which rather will persuade its opponents that it is to their own
                                interest to fall in with our purposes. A material disarmament is not
                                sufficient, a spiritual disarmament must go hand in hand with it. We
                                must handle all differences of righteous nature that may arise
                                between us and any other nation in a conciliatory spirit. If they
                                cannot be avoided diplomatically, we must leave them to the decision
                                of a court of arbitration, even though there be danger that
                                sometimes a wrong might be done us. At the same time, we shall make
                                it our business to build up an international arrangement for
                                negotiation and settlement of all problems, which are difficult of
                                purely disinterested decision. The propositions made by Bryan<note n="5b" xml:id="d10fn5b">Treaties for the advancement of the
                                    general peace negotiated under the direction of William J.
                                    Bryan, Secretary of State, 1913–1915. For citations to treaty
                                    texts, see <ref target="frus1900-18Index#pg_420"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, General Index,
                                        1900–1918, p. 420</ref>.</note> were the forerunner for such
                                a union.</p>
                            <p>The establishment of the principle of arbitration in the League of
                                Nations will result in the allaying of differences of opinion
                                between its members, before they have taken on the harshness that
                                demands the opinion of a court. I am persuaded that the positive
                                problems that will eventually be placed before the League can be
                                solved only by a strong and enduring organization. From that arises
                                the need of officials chosen by common election and some Council of
                                a League-Parliament such as is already prepared for by the
                                Inter-Parliamentary Union. Finally, the League of Nations must have
                                strong means of enforcement in order to put its decrees into effect.
                                The surrender of a considerable part of sovereignty that results
                                therefrom can be demanded of a free people only when it can share in
                                the executive power and furnishes on its part the means of
                                enforcement.</p>
                            <p>We cannot enter into any League of Nations in which we shall be <pb facs="0075" n="25" xml:id="pg_25"/> only a subject for executive
                                action. (Right!) Particularly there will be many difficulties in
                                establishing the participation of the nations in the committees of
                                the League, as well as the jurisdiction of the committees and their
                                methods of operation. But I do not give up hope that mankind,
                                martyred by war, will attain to a new and better regulation of
                                national relation as the fruit of its sacrifices and suffering. It
                                will then be possible that hate will give way to consideration
                                without which no human relations can exist. That must be not only
                                for the enemy nations of the west with whose leaders we are now
                                negotiating but also for our neighbors on the east with whom the war
                                first broke out and with whom the first peace was made, but with
                                whom we remain in fact in a state of war without conventions or
                                diplomatic relations. The Russian Soviet republic has declared to
                                the Entente a willingness to join in negotiations on the basic
                                principles that it would stop the Bolshevistic propaganda among
                                other peoples, on condition that it might control the domestic
                                affairs of Russia without foreign intervention. As far as Germany is
                                concerned, I see no reason for refusing to enter into an
                                understanding with Russia on this principle. One would think that
                                such a program must secure the assent of all the statesmen of the
                                warring nations. There should be only one condition to it, that
                                Russia also should accept the principle of Wilson referring to the
                                self-determination of peoples. The League of Nations must remain
                                only a rump if those nations which can be kept from war are not
                                parties to it. It is not feasible to establish the permanent
                                existence of a League unless the neutral nations are heard. (Very
                                true!) The warring nations will be all the less willing to shut them
                                out since they owe gratitude to the neutral nations for the
                                suffering and sacrifices that they have gone through for the benefit
                                of the warring nations. I take this opportunity to acknowledge
                                gladly in the name of the entire German people that part of the debt
                                of thanks which is due from Germany, and I know that I have therein
                                the concurrence of the German National Assembly. (Vigorous
                                approval!). I am thinking especially of the conspicuous,
                                unforgettable service which the peoples and governments of Denmark,
                                Sweden, Holland, Spain and Switzerland rendered to interned Germans
                                and prisoners, and of the friendly reception which many of our
                                children and sick found among them. (Renewed vigorous approval!).
                                May an international truly humanitarian sentiment spring from this
                                seed which will be more enduring than the dragons teeth of the war.
                                (Applause!).</p>
                            <p>Ladies and gentlemen, the government in whose name I am about to
                                conduct our foreign policy is under the guidance of the German
                                working class. But it is the government of a unified socialist and
                                bourgeois democracy. On that memorable day which gave to the German
                                nation its first self-chosen government, it was established that the
                                leaders of democratic Germany could for the first time speak to
                                other <pb facs="0076" n="26" xml:id="pg_26"/> nations fully
                                empowered in the name of the German people. That means for me, as
                                long as I know myself to have the confidence of the leaders of the
                                German people, a mighty support, which my predecessors did not have.
                                The confidence that I beseech from you will not be lessened because
                                of the name which I have inherited from my ancestors. I hope to show
                                you that a man can be a Count and a convinced democrat. (Good!)
                                Democracy does not mean government by the masses as such; only the
                                ablest must lead and govern. A wholesome people wishes nothing else.
                                The will of the people must try for that in its elections, but it
                                has the means to correct its mistakes. (Very true!) I know that I
                                can hold this place only so long as it approves the conduct of my
                                office. You are assembled here to set up the new structure of the
                                German nation, a structure that must serve not the ends of warlike
                                might, but the works of peace and civilization. If I have taken so
                                much of your time on questions of foreign policy, I demand it as a
                                right because this National Assembly must also deliberate on the
                                different means whereby Germany may put an end to the war. The
                                decision which you will offer to the new nation, will be the
                                cornerstone on which the German representatives will establish their
                                negotiations with the enemy. The spirit that may animate your
                                debates will be conclusive on the question whether the conquerors of
                                the German people shall recognize it as deserving of justice, or
                                shall offer conditions which will force us rather to accept the
                                utmost consequences than to bow to them. (Applause!). Certainly
                                Germany will have heavy damages to pay both within and without,
                                especially to Belgium, and on that we have no inclination to speak
                                haughtily. (Very true! from Independent Socialists.) But we have
                                immeasurably valuable possessions both within and without, and
                                therefore a duty to look to our individuality and independence as
                                against our opponents. (Vigorous applause!). We are conquered but
                                not dishonored. (Bravo!) The greatest poet of German freedom says,
                                “Unworthy is that nation which does not gladly place its all on its
                                honor.” (Applause from the Right!). Contentment has gone from many
                                of us, but will, unshakeable will, stands fast. (Applause from the
                                Right!). A part of the dignity of the German people has been given
                                into my hand, and I swear that I shall preserve it. (Vigorous
                                applause and handclapping).</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>