<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Lieutenant Colonel Sherman Miles to Professor A. C. Coolidge</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d176</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">176</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-03-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-03-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-03-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-03-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="176"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d176">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 184.01102/256</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Lieutenant Colonel <persName type="from">Sherman
                            Miles</persName> to Professor <persName type="to">A. C.
                            Coolidge</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="37" xml:id="d176fn37">Transmitted to the Commission by Professor
                        Coolidge under covering letter No. 171, March 23; received March 26.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Spalato</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-03-20">March 20 (?),
                            1919</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I went down to Pola and back again by automobile, going and coming by different
                    routes. I spent a day there. I made this trip in order to see certain geographic
                    features of the Istrian Peninsula, but principally because I had letters to some
                    Austrian Naval officers and wanted to get their information on the Dalmatian
                    coast. I got all I wanted and also found an American Destroyer in port and
                    picked up some information from the officers. I have wired you twice that the
                    Navy is not reporting to Paris and I think this is a great mistake. Perhaps it
                    is too late to remedy it now, but I would suggest that you wire to Paris and
                    tell them that they can get a lot of local information on the Istrian and
                    Dalmatian questions if they put the Navy on the job.</p>
                <p>I had thought of writing a short report on Pola, but I hardly think it worth
                    while. Pola and lower Istria will go with Trieste; and I take it that Trieste
                    will certainly be given to Italy. Of course, the outstanding facts are well
                    known—that the interior is Slav (though not thickly populated) and that Pola has
                    no commercial importance, but is purely a military port. Pola must in any case
                    lose greatly in importance, but will probably be better off under the Italians
                    than under the Jugos.</p>
                <p>I have not tried to write any reports on the local difficulties between the
                    Allies. The fact of the matter is that the Italians are running things with a
                    high hand and are clashing with the French and to a lesser degree with the
                    British. As is well known in Paris, Fiume is in a narrow zone east of the Pact
                    of London line (Armistice Line). This narrow strip is nominally under
                    inter-allied occupation, but as a matter of fact the Italian troops very greatly
                    outnumber the British and French, and an Italian General is Governor of Fiume.
                    The whole question is complicated by the fact that the French have taken Fiume
                    as the base-port of their “Army of Hungary” (Franchet d’Esperey). The French
                    control all the railroads from a point five miles to the east of Fiume. This
                    makes the Italians furious, and the frontier is practically closed. The money
                    question, and the fluctuating value of the kronen would of itself make shipments
                    from Fiume into the interior at present almost impossible. The Italians are
                    trying to break the French hold over the railroads in the interior by refusing
                    anything but purely Italian control on the Fiume end of the line. This Italian
                    control is exercised by the so-called National Council, who are really the
                    self-appointed Italian leaders in Fiume, backed by the Italian military <pb
                        facs="0542" n="492" xml:id="pg_492"/> governor. There are also some strong
                    indications of a very bad feeling between the Italians and French. This is
                    because the French have had the good sense to play the game the Italians should
                    have played in the Balkan Peninsula. The Italian determination to antagonise the
                    Jugo-Slavs is a most amazing piece of stupidity, when one thinks of the
                    opportunity Italy might have seized in the Balkans. The British are very much
                    annoyed at every turn by the Italians, but of course are not so much involved as
                    the French.</p>
                <p>I hear rumors that the Italians are buying up the Hungarian interests in Fiume. I
                    cannot imagine where this money is coming from, unless it is out of our pockets.
                    This is the only indication of an Italian-Hungarian <hi rend="italic"
                        >rapprochement</hi> I have found.</p>
                <p>I found in Pola that the Italians have been on the whole pretty considerate of
                    the Austrian Naval officers there and of their property. I don’t suppose this
                    means much one way or the other, except that the Italian Admiral in command,
                    Cannay, is said to be one of the greatest imperialists. The Jugo-Slavs here
                    think that France is working against them, favoring Italy for the Italian
                    support regarding Alsace-Lorraine.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
