<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. A. W. DuBois to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d225</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">225</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-10-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-10-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recBu49iaA1LjksYs" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general">Government reform</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="rec4kNZ3bN6ephN7u" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027420"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Coalition government</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign currency</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recOAfZ9FRSJKK76a" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064772"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Income tax</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-10-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-10-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="225"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d225">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 184.011102/560½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">A. W. DuBois</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="48" xml:id="d225fn48">Copy transmitted to the Commission by Mr. DuBois
                        under covering letter No. 11, October 18; received October 23. Mr. DuBois
                        was in charge of the Mission to Austria during the absence of Mr. Halstead
                        in Paris.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1919-10-18">undated</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 11</seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum on Recent Political Events in Austria</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The peace treaty of Saint Germain was accepted on October 17th by the National
                    Assembly after a short report by Dr. Weiskirchner, chairman of the committee for
                    peace negotiations, without debate. The treaty goes to Dr. Seitz, president of
                    the National Assembly, for ratification. The Social Democrats and Christian
                    socialists voted for the treaty, while the All-German party withheld their
                    vote.</p>
                <p>The treaty having been accepted, the old cabinet under the leadership of Dr.
                    Renner, handed in its resignation. Dr. Renner stated that the work of the
                    cabinet, namely that of treaty making, had been concluded and since new problems
                    were to be undertaken a new government <pb facs="0631" n="581" xml:id="pg_581"/>
                    would have to be formed. The leaders of the Social Democratic and the Christian
                    Socialist parties have been in negotiation for some time for the formation of a
                    coalition cabinet and government and on October 16th had agreed upon a program
                    which was carried out on October 17th without a hitch.</p>
                <p>Dr. Renner was asked to present a cabinet list which was accepted. The new
                    coalition cabinet is as follows: <list>
                        <item>State Chancellor, Dr. Karl Renner</item>
                        <item>Vice Chancellor, Jodok Fink</item>
                        <item>Minister for Foreign Affairs, Dr. Karl Renner</item>
                        <item>Minister for Interior, Matthias Eldersch</item>
                        <item>Minister for Justice, Dr. Rudolf Ranek</item>
                        <item>Minister for War, Dr. Julius Deutsch</item>
                        <item>Minister of Finance, Dr. Richard Reisch</item>
                        <item>Minister for Agriculture, Joseph Stöckier</item>
                        <item>Minister for Commerce, Johann Zerdik</item>
                        <item>Minister for Ways of Communication, Ludwig Paul</item>
                        <item>Minister for Social Government, Ferdinand Hanusch</item>
                        <item>Minister for Food, Dr. Johann Loewenfeld-Russ</item>
                        <item>Minister for the Preparation of a Constitution and Government Reform,
                            Dr. Michael Mayr</item>
                        <item>Undersecretary for Education, Otto Glöcke</item>
                        <item>Undersecretary for Worship, Wilhelm Miklas</item>
                        <item>Undersecretary for Justice, Dr. Arnold Eisler</item>
                        <item>Undersecretary for War, Dr. Erwin Weiss</item>
                        <item>Undersecretary for Commerce, Dr. Wilhelm Ellenbogen</item>
                        <item>Undersecretary for Social Administration, Joseph Resch</item>
                        <item>Undersecretary for Health, Dr. Julius Tandler</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The new cabinet has thirteen ministers—secretaries of state—and seven
                    undersecretaries, of whom eight are social democrats, eight christian
                    socialists, and four professional men but conservative and probably also
                    christian socialists. This majority or apparent majority of the conservative
                    party has brought forth a cry of opposition from the radical elements who claim
                    that they have been sold out to the middle class. However the social democrat
                    leaders defend their position by claiming for themselves the six important
                    political posts in the cabinet, namely the state chancellorship, the ministry
                    for war, the ministry for foreign affairs, the ministry for interior, the
                    ministry for instruction, the ministry for social administration, and further
                    through the control of the socialization commission.</p>
                <p>Equally as interesting as the attempt to coalesce the two political parties, is
                    the attempt to bring about a better understanding between Vienna and the
                    counties by placing in the cabinet the representatives of the latter, namely,
                    minister for justice, a social democrat from Salzburg, the undersecretary of
                    justice, a social democrat from Graz, and the minister for constitutional and
                    administrative reform, a christian socialist leader from the Tirol.</p>
                <pb facs="0632" n="582" xml:id="pg_582"/>
                <p>In general it can be said that the new cabinet has been formed along common sense
                    lines and the selection of the individuals on the whole has been a good one. The
                    character of the chancellor and minister for foreign affairs is well known. Dr.
                    Deutsch retains his post as minister for war. His policy has been described in a
                    former report (No. 5, Sept. 17th).<note n="49" xml:id="d225fn49">Not
                        printed.</note> Dr. Reisch, the new minister for finance and who has one of
                    the most difficult positions conceivable, is leading director of the Boden
                    Credit Anstalt (Bank), is a leading financier and expert on taxation. He has
                    served as counsellor to the ministry for finance and bureau chief for tax and
                    finance reform and is well versed in governmental finance problems. He is
                    considered a great improvement over Schumpeter, his predecessor. The elimination
                    of Otto Bauer rids the cabinet of an extreme radical, an intelligent but
                    dangerous man. Kautz, Bauer’s secretary, who held a position in the foreign
                    office, has resigned thus further purging that office of extremists and allowing
                    the more reasonable elements to breathe more freely. Zerdik has been retained in
                    the cabinet, on account of his knowledge of the coal industry but has been
                    changed from interior to industry. The new government has four Jews in the
                    cabinet.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Program of the new administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Reichspost</hi>, the christian socialist paper, and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Arbeiter-zeitung</hi>, the social democrat paper, published
                    yesterday signed statements of the coalition government’s program, a copy of
                    which is attached to this memorandum.<note n="50" xml:id="d225fn50">Not found in
                        Department files.</note> Both parties are to be equally responsible in the
                    new government and neither is to make political material of labor or wage
                    questions.</p>
                <p>The first question of importance is that of finance reform for which the
                    following program has been set forth. Immediate contribution of wealth, to take
                    place but once (<hi rend="italic">einmalige Vermögungsabgabe</hi>); a large part
                    of the proceeds to be used for securing of foreign currency, to reduce the war
                    debt, to cover current deficits, and to secure government aid for important
                    undertakings. Demand for deliverance of gold and foreign securities, for payment
                    of foodstuffs, against complete reimbursement. The creation of a steady
                    currency. The tax system to be based on a graduated income tax. Division of tax
                    between State and counties. Regulation of payments of state employees. The
                    adaptation of selling prices of foodstuffs to production costs.</p>
                <p>The task next in importance is the drafting of the new constitution, in the
                    carrying out of which the administration will consult both parties and also the
                    counties. The new draft will constitute German Austria as a federated state;
                    German West Hungary will be considered <pb facs="0633" n="583" xml:id="pg_583"/>
                    as a separate county a part of the new federation. The powers of the federation
                    will be specified. The federal government is to have exclusive control over
                    foreign affairs, law making (civil and criminal), the army, the higher schools,
                    labor laws and insurance. The federal government will have the power to impose
                    taxes. All powers not specifically granted to the federal government fall to the
                    counties. Relation of state to church is to be regulated, all creeds to be
                    respected. The lawmaking power is to be vested in the national assembly and a
                    federal council, the latter to be modelled after the German Parliament. It will
                    introduce the initiative and referendum. It will do away with the bureaucratic
                    form of government.</p>
                <p>The program acknowledges the faults of organization of councils (soldiers and
                    workmens) and the misuse of their powers, but promises freedom to the
                    individual, clubs, meetings, and so forth.</p>
                <p>The new military is to be a democratic, republican army. All members are to swear
                    to defend the democratic republic and not to take part in political movements
                    directed against the republic. It is to be the army of the republic and not that
                    of a party. However the individual members will have all the rights of citizens
                    and outside of their duties can as individuals take part in politics. Men will
                    be selected from the officers of the old Austro-Hungarian army for commissions
                    and for non-commissioned rank. But also men who have become officers since the
                    overthrow and who are qualified may become officers. All former officers may
                    apply for entrance into the ranks of the new army on the same basis as other
                    citizens. For those officers of the old army who do not enter the new some means
                    will be found for their care. They will be especially selected for the work of
                    carry[ing] out the deliverance of wealth, collection of gold and jewelry,
                    agricultural operations, and census taking. The new army is to be subordinate to
                    the federal authorities. Delegates of the rank and file (soldiers councils) will
                    represent the economical interests and stipulated rights of the men, but they
                    will not be allowed to prejudice the powers of the commanders. Soldiers will
                    serve in their own counties. Only when the volunteers from any county do not
                    suffice will soldiers who are citizens of other counties be stationed
                    therein.</p>
                <p>The new program states in regard to its foreign policy that the government must
                    show the best will to carry out the peace terms, and that German Austria must
                    not attempt to carry out its national aims of union with Germany and reunion
                    with the German elements lost to it through intrigue or force but only with the
                    consent of the League of Nations. As far as possible good relations are to be
                    established with the neighboring countries, but there shall be no meddling with
                    their internal affairs. Alliances will not be sought with the neighboring
                    states. The first aim must be to conclude commercial treaties and to do away
                    with the system of compensation treaties. Representation <pb facs="0634" n="584"
                        xml:id="pg_584"/> of Austrian interests in foreign countries is solely
                    confined to the federal government. Diplomatic missions will be established in
                    the succession states and in England, Italy, and the United States as soon as
                    possible. (France is not mentioned probably through typographical error)</p>
                <p>The program further covers the food problem, but in a rather indefinite manner,
                    and in the same way handles the socialization work, labor, insurance and other
                    matters.</p>
                <p>Dr. Renner yesterday was unusually cheerful and seemed well satisfied with the
                    present political situation and line-up. The people as a whole however are
                    apathetic to appointments of new government officers and publishing of programs.
                    They want results and have very little faith in seeing them attained no matter
                    what government is in charge. They consider their position hopeless and are
                    greatly depressed with the prospect of a winter full of misery. There is some
                    faith in the proposition of establishing a <hi rend="italic">Notenbank</hi> to
                    raise credits and stabilize the currency but more in the Reparations Commission
                    which is to commence its work this week.</p>
                <p>The serious condition of the country has brought about a coalition of hostile
                    political elements that nothing else could possibly have accomplished. The
                    bright spot in the situation is that this coalition may go far to soften the
                    hatred between classes, at least between the classes as represented by the two
                    large political parties. The real monarchists and the communists, also the All
                    Germans, are left out but they have no program to offer which might alleviate
                    the present situation, and everything considered the present political and
                    administrative arrangement is the [best?] that could be brought about and
                    therefore the best for coping with the situation, hopeless as it may be.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
