<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>General Bandholtz to the Commission to Negotiate Peace</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d262</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">262</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-08-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-08-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-08-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-08-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="262"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d262">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 181.9202/11: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">General <persName type="from">Bandholtz</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Commission to Negotiate Peace</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Budapest</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-08-14">August 14,
                            1919</date>.<lb/>[Received August 15—12:30 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>4. General Graziani, the French representative of the Interallied Military
                    Mission, arrived on the evening of the 12th and was present at the session this
                        date.<note n="10" xml:id="d262fn10">Presumably reference is to session of
                        August 13.</note> He evidently expected the chairmanship of the Commission
                    to go by seniority and so stated. He was informed of the arrangement made by the
                    other three members of the Commission for rotation in chairmen and acquiesced
                    with a reservation that it would be necessary to notify his Government as the
                    French authorities undoubtedly expected the chairmanship to go by seniority. M.
                    Diamandi, the Roumanian High Commissioner, and General Mardarescu, with General
                    Holban, called upon the Commission in the morning session and explained the
                    arrangement they had made for alleviation all [<hi rend="italic">of?</hi>] the
                    food situation in Budapest. Captain Gregory of the Food Administration was
                    called in while these gentlemen were present and explained to them what he was
                    prepared to do under favorable conditions. In the afternoon M. Diamandi asked
                    for a private interview with the undersigned which took place during the
                    afternoon and during which he stated that he regretted that there had been any
                    misunderstanding whatever on the day preceding and added in effect that his
                    Government was prepared to accept as final the instructions given the Military
                    Commission by the Supreme Council.<note n="11" xml:id="d262fn11">For text of
                        instructions, see appendix B to HD–24, <ref target="frus1919Parisv07#pg_542"
                            >vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>, p. 542</ref>.</note> His attention
                    at the time was called to some excesses committed by Roumanians against
                    Armenians [<hi rend="italic">Americans</hi>] and he promised to have adequate
                    measures taken for reparation and punishment. The Commission had an afternoon
                    session during which the undersigned <pb facs="0689" n="639" xml:id="pg_639"/>
                    requested that M. Diamandi be asked to appear before the Commission and repeat
                    officially the remarks he had made during the personal conference but he could
                    not be found and has therefore been asked to see the Commission tomorrow
                    morning. The Italian, British, and American representatives are in complete
                    accord and there is general harmony.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bandholtz</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
