<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>General Bandholtz to the Commission to Negotiate Peace</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d297</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">297</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-09-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-09-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-09-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-09-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="297"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d297">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 181.9202/104: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">General <persName type="from">Bandholtz</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Commission to Negotiate Peace</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Budapest</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-09-12">September 12,
                            1919</date>.<lb/>[Received September 13—10:30 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>65. Roumanian requisitions of rolling stock to September 8th include 1,160
                    passenger coaches, 62 court and special cars, 21 sleeping cars, 16 postal cars,
                    281 service cars, 15,161 ordinary freight cars, 7,713 flat cars, 1,767 oil
                    tanks, 678 engines, and 289 miscellaneous. <pb facs="0727" n="677"
                        xml:id="pg_677"/> Hundreds of Transylvanians who refused to take oath of
                    allegiance of [<hi rend="italic">to</hi>] King of Roumania have been deported
                    and are coming to Budapest and vicinity, thereby complicating the supply
                    situation.</p>
                <p>At request of Lieutenant Colonel Causey, Roumanian Commander in Chief was
                    requested to turn over Hungarian telegraph line No. 264, so that the Peace
                    Conference might have direct communication with Belgrade. General Mardarescu
                    stated that he referred this matter to his Engineer Officer and would expedite a
                    reply in every way possible.</p>
                <p>General Bandholtz’s entire procedure while in Bucharest was read his colleagues
                    and met with their unanimous approval. A commission has left this date to
                    investigate the report of the large quantity of Mackensen<note n="38"
                        xml:id="d297fn38">Field Marshal August Mackensen, formerly in command of
                        German forces in Roumania.</note> supplies and Roumanian officials asked
                    this date what we intended to do in regard to this question and were told that
                    instructions to the Mission specifically included disposition of Mackensen
                    material and that the Allies would take charge of and be responsible for same.
                    It is reported that the Roumanians are deporting from Budapest to Roumania 1,000
                    iron workers with the object of making them set up and operate the seized
                    machinery. This is being investigated. Generals Mardarescu and Holban and M.
                    Diamandi appeared before Mission this date, it was understood for the purpose of
                    farewell call on the Mission, but nothing of kind came up. Several matters were
                    discussed, but nothing settled except question of Mackensen material. Meeting
                    was interrupted to attend review of Roumanian division at which all members of
                    the Mission were present.</p>
                <p>Diamandi stated that Roumania had unearthed Koran [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>]
                    Hungarian conspiracy against Roumanian Army and Government, that Friedrich,
                    Hungary’s Prime Minister, seriously implicated. This being further investigated,
                    probably Roumania will use this as pretext to get rid of Friedrich.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bandholtz</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
