<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-10-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-10-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="324" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d324">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 181.9202/181:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">General <persName type="from">Bandholtz</persName>
                                to the <gloss type="to">Commission to Negotiate
                            Peace</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Budapest</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-10-08">October 8, 1919</date>.<lb/>[Received October
                                8—5:27 p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>133. On September 16th Roumanians notified Military Mission that all
                            requisitions would cease except actually necessary for immediate <pb facs="0750" n="700" xml:id="pg_700"/> army needs. Following are
                            extracts from report of our committee which is endeavoring to keep track
                            of Roumanian exportations: Requisitions of cattle, horses and grain
                            continue, Mayor of Szolnok says never so numerous as at present. Trains
                            loaded with horses passing daily through Szolnok. Animals requisitioned
                            are still paid for but at Roumanian price which is 350 kronen per
                            animal. At present rate of exchange this would mean less than $5 United
                            States currency or about £1 British currency. At Kiskunfelegyhaza 200
                            horses were sent to Roumania on 28th, also large quantities of forage.
                            In Budapest on September 28 Roumanian lieutenant named Gotoschi seized
                            three automobiles from Hungarian garage and shipped them to Roumania.
                            Our record of rolling stock sent to Roumania up to midnight of 4th is
                            33,000 cars of all kinds and 1,230 locomotives.</p>
                        <p>It is reported that an Austrian Red Army is being formed independent of
                                <hi rend="italic">Volkswehr</hi>, chief of organization being
                            William Boehm, former Commander of Red Army. It is understood to be
                            their intention to break into Hungary with many thousands of workmen
                            soldiers, working upon their feeling by telling them that which [<hi rend="italic">while</hi>] Austria is starving there is still
                            abundance of food in Hungary. It is stated that large sums of propaganda
                            money are being spent in Austria.</p>
                        <p>Roumanians have requested Military Mission to aid them in getting two
                            monitors and two vedette boats now in Danube near Budapest. Have been
                            informed that this is a matter entirely within province of Danube River
                            Commission.</p>
                        <p>Evacuation of western Hungary up to Budapest bridgehead completed without
                            serious incident.</p>
                        <p>Many [<hi rend="italic">My</hi>] seals are still on the storeroom doors
                            of the National Museum. General Gorton requests copy of foregoing be
                            furnished British Commission.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Bandholtz</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>