<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-02-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-02-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="53" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d53">
                        <head>53. Intelligence Memorandum 490/70<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d53fn1">Source: Central Intelligence Agency, DI/<gloss target="#t_OCI1">OCI</gloss> Files, Job 79–T00830A, Box 2.
                                Secret; <gloss target="#t_Noforn1">Noforn</gloss>. Prepared in the
                                Office of Current Intelligence of the Central Intelligence Agency,
                                and coordinated with the Office of Economic Research, the Office of
                                National Estimates, the Office of Strategic Research, and the
                                Clandestine Service.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d53fn2">The 6 page report assessed
                                the revolutionary government of Libya as it effected the staying
                                power of the present regime and outlined the directions in which the
                                leaders appeared to be moving.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-02-13">February 13, 1970</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <pb facs="d53-02" n="2" xml:id="d53-02"/>
                        <p>An Intelligence Assessment of Libya</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="underline">Introduction</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This memorandum assesses current Libyan trends as they affect the staying
                            power of the present regime and the directions in which its leaders
                            appear to be moving.</p>
                        <p>NOTE: This memorandum was produced solely by <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>. It was prepared by the Office of Current Intelligence
                            and coordinated with the Office of Economic Research, the Office of
                            National Estimates, the Office of Strategic Research, and the
                            Clandestine Service.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="underline">Libya in the Arab World</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>1. Developments in Libya should be viewed within the context of general
                            trends in the Middle East. Foremost among these has been the growing
                            involvement of all Arab states in the Palestine issue. This has meant,
                            for the most part, joining the conflict against Israel or at least
                            supporting it. US prestige and influence in the Arab world has been
                            inversely related to this trend; from a high point of good will reached
                            as a result of President Eisenhower’s actions in the 1956 Suez war, the
                            course has been generally downward. The June 1967 war accelerated this
                            trend, and a sharp drop followed the US decision in early 1969 to supply
                            F–4 Phantom jets to Israel. Even the seven Arab states that could then
                            have been characterized as political moderates or conservatives and had
                            retained <pb facs="d53-03" n="3" xml:id="d53-03"/> diplomatic relations
                            with the US found it politically necessary to denounce the US publicly.
                            The actual delivery of the aircraft and their subsequent highly
                            publicized use in combat have led the Arab press to portray the US as a
                            supporter and ally of Israel and the primary enemy of the Arabs.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="underline">The Junta</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>2. The members of the Revolutionary Command Council that installed itself
                            in Libya in September 1969 were bound together by a common desire to
                            overthrow King <persName corresp="#p_IIS1">Idris</persName>, who was for
                            them a symbol of corruption, the presence of foreign bases, and a too
                            strong pro-West stance. They are young, inexperienced officers between
                            the ages of 25 and 30, and have only vague ties to the various pan-Arab
                            ideological movements. Although they proclaimed appropriate slogans in
                            the early hours of their coup, they have not as yet developed a clear
                            and agreed upon political program. Libya’s new rulers are seized both by
                            an enthusiasm for Arab nationalism and by a desire to modernize their
                            country. They have neither the expertise nor the machinery to make and
                            carry out decisions in an orderly manner, thus they are likely to be
                            caught up in cycles of failure and frustration.</p>
                        <p>3. The power relationship within the junta remains largely unknown.
                            Although Muammir Qaddafi has been named council president, prime
                            minister, and commander in chief of the armed forces, he does not appear
                            to be all powerful. The available evidence suggests that the 12-man
                            council, all of whose members have finally been publicly identified,
                            acts as a collegial group. There may also be other officers in the armed
                            forces who have a special relationship with and access to the council.
                            Recent evidence also suggests that the council has pro- and
                            anti-Egyptian factions with the former presently in the ascendancy.</p>
                        <p>4. The junta members, who were suspicious of the ease with which they
                            were able to oust the King, still are insecure. To date, however, the
                            junta has been challenged only by its own members. In December 1969, the
                            ministers of defense and interior were arrested before they could make a
                            planned move against <pb facs="d53-04" n="4" xml:id="d53-04"/> their
                            colleagues. There have been reports of discontent among the tribes of
                            Cyrenaica and elsewhere in the civilian sector. These groups do not
                            possess sufficient arms to challenge the army seriously, accordingly in
                            the present situation they do not appear to pose any real danger to the
                            regime. Under present circumstances, any move against the regime is
                            likely to come from within the army. The junta has begun transferring
                            units of the armed forces that seem most likely to become
                            troublesome—the Cyrenaicans—to Egypt for training and eventual duty
                            along the Suez Canal. Thus far, approximately 2,600 men have been sent
                            to Egypt, with another 1,900 scheduled to join them before the end of
                            February.</p>
                        <p>5. Perhaps of far more significance than this is the movement of Egyptian
                            troops into Libya, an operation that began in December. Some 1,500 to
                            2,000 Egyptian soldiers are now stationed in Benghazi and Tripoli.
                            Approximately 500 other Egyptians have been assigned to military,
                            security, and communications posts. Thus, the Egyptians may be in enough
                            key points to forestall any countercoup by indigenous elements. In the
                            event of foreign moves to topple the regime, these Egyptian units could
                            probably be considered as controlling an air- or beach-head through
                            which additional forces could be moved into Libya.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="underline">The Present Policy Trend</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>6. For Libya’s new rulers, there is no obvious conflict between Libyan
                            and Arab nationalism. One of the first statements issued by the junta
                            was an attack on King Idris for his relatively passive attitude toward
                            the Palestinian guerrilla movement and the Arab-Israeli conflict. In
                            fact, however, there had been some support of the Arab cause by Idris.
                            The Palestine Liberation Organization was allowed to carry out a number
                            of activities in Libya, and sizable official contributions had been made
                            to it. By the end of 1969 Libya had also contributed more than $200
                            million to Egypt and Jordan, but for the junta this was not enough.</p>
                        <pb facs="d53-05" n="5" xml:id="d53-05"/>
                        <p>7. At the recent Arab summit conference in Rabat, Qaddafi was most vocal
                            in his demands that wealthy Arab states increase their commitment to the
                            struggle against Israel. As proof of its own commitment the Libya
                            leadership now has decided to grant Egypt $96 million in addition to its
                            annual subsidy of $59 million. Another symbol of Libya’s commitment to
                            the Arab war effort is its transfer of troops to Egypt, even though this
                            also serves as a convenient way to remove possible dissidents.</p>
                        <p>8. Upon seizing power, the council announced that it would honor existing
                            oil concessions, which brought in revenues last year that may have
                            amounted to $1.2 billion, and the oil companies report that operations
                            in Libya have continued without significant harassment. In January the
                            Libyan Government began negotiations with a number of operating oil
                            companies, including some US corporations. These talks aim at securing
                            higher posted prices on which government revenues are based. The
                            companies are being threatened with unspecified punitive actions if they
                            fail to reach an agreement. Nationalization, always the ultimate
                            possibility, has not been raised by the new Libyan rulers and at this
                            point does not appear to enter the picture. Indeed, Libyan commitments
                            to purchase a sizable number of French aircraft and promises of more aid
                            to Egypt and Jordan would suggest that Libya cannot afford to engage in
                            adventurism in its oil arrangements.</p>
                        <p>9. So far, given the quick US decision to meet Libyan demands for the
                            evacuation of Wheelus Air Base, official relations have not been overly
                            difficult. Certain irritations have arisen, however, and the Libyans
                            have so far failed to delineate the nature and the form of the military
                            assistance relationship they profess to desire. This may have to await
                            complete evacuation of the base, because the Libyans continue to be
                            highly suspicious of US and British intentions.</p>
                        <p>10. To date, the junta has kept the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                            at arms length. The Soviets offered military assistance in the first few
                            days of the coup, but were quickly rejected. As far as we know,
                            subsequent approaches <pb facs="d53-06" n="6" xml:id="d53-06"/> have
                            also been rebuffed. This negative attitude of the Libyans may be
                            reinforced by the advice reportedly offered by Nasir not to become
                            dependent upon the Soviets for support. France, seeing a big power
                            vacuum in Libya and aware of the economic advantages available, is
                            seeking to fill that void partly. Paris’ future intentions are unclear,
                            other than its obvious desire to increase its influence all along the
                            North African littoral. The Maghreb states, which are themselves moving
                            toward a closer relationship with France, probably hope that the growing
                            role of France in Libya is a force that will help preserve Libya’s
                            Maghreb orientation.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="underline">The Junta and its Future</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>11. The life expectancy of the junta will ultimately depend upon several
                            factors. First and foremost, the junta must guard against serious
                            dissidence within its own ranks. In December 1969, Qaddafi had to act
                            quickly to a potential threat from within the junta. Coup attempts are
                            also possible by either members of the former ruling clique or other
                            disaffected civilian groups; however because they lack cohesion and an
                            effective power base, their chances of dislodging the junta are minimal.
                            Moreover, Nasir is apparently willing to give support in preventing any
                            effort of this type. Over the longer run, the rulers of Libya need to
                            find ways to encourage popular support. To be sure, much mileage will be
                            gained from publicizing the removal of Western military forces from the
                            country and the use of the US as a whipping boy for Arab military
                            shortcomings. Public attention, however, cannot be diverted from
                            domestic problems forever. Such civilian support as there is for the
                            regime comes from professional men, university graduates, lower grade
                            military officers, lower level government officials, and
                            students—precisely the same elements that were the most disaffected
                            under the monarchy. Having proclaimed its intention to modernize Libya
                            and rid it of the evil vestiges of the old regime, the junta will have
                            to show some signs of making good its promise.</p>
                        <p>12. Another factor is the relationship between the junta and Egypt. At
                            some point, it could well <pb facs="d53-07" n="7" xml:id="d53-07"/>
                            become a liability to both parties. At present it would be difficult for
                            opponents of the regime to attack its close cooperation with Egypt
                            without being accused of hampering the struggle against the Israelis. As
                            the relationship is maintained—and perhaps expanded—the presence of
                            large numbers of Egyptian advisers and troops in Libya could become a
                            source of irritation. A growing realization that financial resources
                            that could be used for internal development are being sent outside Libya
                            could add to public discontent. For the Egyptians, the tangible benefits
                            accruing from their present relationship are important. If the junta
                            maintains power and acquires a substantial arms inventory, Libyan
                            military equipment might eventually represent a contingency asset for
                            Cairo. During the next few years, however, Egyptian ability to
                            assimilate more sophisticated weapons will remain limited, and Libyan
                            arms will be of far less significance to Nasir than Libyan financial
                            support.</p>
                        <p>13. With the passage of time, increased self-confidence and experience
                            may make the Libyan junta more independent minded. Moreover, recalling
                            his previous difficulties in Syria and Yemen, Nasir himself may come to
                            have second thoughts about extensive involvement with the Libyan regime.
                            Whatever the course of Libyan-Egyptian relations and internal Libyan
                            politics, the junta’s policy is likely to remain militantly anti-Israel.
                            This is probably the one important issue on which few Libyans would
                            disagree. Although Libya’s business relations with the US will probably
                            be correct, Tripoli will be largely hostile, or at least cool, toward
                            the US which it will view as the chief mainstay of Israel.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>