<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-12-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-12-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="83" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d83">
                        <head>83. Letter From the Ambassador to Libya (<persName corresp="#p_PJAII1" type="from">Palmer</persName>) to the Assistant Secretary of State
                            for African Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_NDD1" type="to">Newsom</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d83fn1">Source:
                                National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                                Files 1970–73, DEF 12–5 LIBYA. Secret; <gloss target="#t_LIMDIS1">Limdis</gloss>; Official—Informal. The tabs are not
                                printed.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d83fn2">
                                <persName>Palmer</persName> conveyed his deepening concern at the
                                U.S. postponement of a decision on military sales to Libya.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Tripoli</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-12-22">December 22, 1971</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p>Dear <persName>David</persName>:</p>
                        <p>I followed with great interest your recent trip and gather it was most
                            successful. Numeiri’s backtracking was disappointing, although he seems
                            clearly to be moving in the right direction and the amount of time he
                            devoted to you was most impressive.</p>
                        <p>During your absence, our military supply problems have continued to
                            plague us. I had hoped to catch you in Europe on your way home to
                            discuss my concerns, but the telegram I sent to Khartoum suggesting this
                            missed you and I learned from Curt Moore that you would not be pausing
                            long in London.</p>
                        <p>I am therefore taking this means of letting you know of my
                            continuing—even increasing—concern with the accumulation of military
                            supply problems we are facing. To make things easier for you, I am
                            attaching the references.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="underline">1. F–5’s</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I know—and accept—that the “no decision” is the Secretary’s decision.
                            What I have difficulty in understanding, however, is why, when I propose
                            a reply to Yunis which is entirely consistent with the Secretary’s line
                            with only slight non-substantive embroideries, I get no answer at all
                            from the Department. (See Tripoli 2167—para 2—TAB A)</p>
                        <p>Nor do I understand why, when I ask for some Washington approved language
                            to explain our “no decision”, I again meet with the same silence. As you
                            well know, Libyans, like <pb facs="d83-02" n="2" xml:id="d83-02"/>
                            everyone else, ask questions. I just cannot continue to face them, smile
                            in a friendly manner, and say in effect that Washington has made no
                            decision but that I (1) don’t know; (2) can’t say; 3) won’t tell; (4) am
                            too embarrassed to discuss/choose one/why!</p>
                        <p>I note that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> in his
                            memorandum of December 2 (TAB C) to the Secretary suggests that we
                            explain our problem on the basis of our wish to limit arms deliveries to
                            all countries in the area in the light of the general situation. I
                            believe that this would be particularly dangerous: (a) Are we actually
                            going to deliver the F–5’s to Libya if we decide on further Phantom
                            deliveries to Israel? (b) Are we going to deliver the F–5’s if there
                            should be some improvement in the area situation? I doubt that the
                            answer would be affirmative on either score. Similarly, it has been
                            informally suggested at various times in the past that the rationale
                            might be tied to the incompatibility of various Libyan actions with US
                            interests in the area. I think this would be even more dangerous and apt
                            to provoke an even worse confrontation than a flat turn down.</p>
                        <p>The fact of the matter is the Department has left me for about 18 months
                            now with no credible and presentable explanation for our failure,
                            inability or unwillingness to take a decision. Perhaps the problem is
                            that those responsible for answering our telegrams cannot come up with a
                            satisfactory rationale either. I am frank to say that I can’t, but it
                            might help clear the air between Tripoli and the Department if we were
                            told frankly that Washington can’t either.</p>
                        <p>Meanwhile, because of the Department’s failure to address specifically
                            either of the two matters on which I requested guidance in paras. 2 and
                            3 of Tripoli 2167 (TAB A), I have lost the initiative with Yunis and I
                            am vulnerable once again to further importunings by him or by other
                                <gloss target="#t_RCC1">RCC</gloss> members pressing for some sort
                            of a response, and I shall have to go all through the sorry charade
                            again. I could understand the deafening silence if I had been pressing
                            for a reconsideration of the “no decision” policy, But I was not
                            pressing for such a reply. I was merely asking for an updated
                            reiteration of “no decision” tailored to a particular approach, and for
                            some additional guidance to explain the “no decision”. A month later I
                            have received nothing other than the pear-shaped second paragraph of
                            State 220238 (TAB B) which could equally as well have come by sea pouch
                            as by Immediate telegram.</p>
                        <pb facs="d83-03" n="3" xml:id="d83-03"/>
                        <p>Incidentally, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName>’s
                            suggestion for licensing the F–5’s from Spanish production (see Jim
                            Blake’s letter of December 6—TAB C) seems on the surface to offer a
                            possibly attractive way out of our commitment. At the same time, the
                            planes would presumably have to be built from scratch with a
                            considerable delay in delivery time compared with the US model which the
                                <gloss target="#t_LARAF1">LARAF</gloss> assumes are in storage and
                            ready for delivery anytime the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> is
                            prepared to release them. Since the <gloss target="#t_LARAF1">LARAF</gloss>’s principal desire is to get the planes quickly for
                            transition training to the Mirages, they are unlikely to be mollified by
                            this offer. Moreover, from a Washington point of view, I remain dubious
                            about circuitous ploys of this kind. If we are concerned about
                            Congressional and public reaction to US F–5 deliveries to Libya, we
                            certainly run the risk of being pilloried even more by resorting to what
                            many would regard as a subterfuge in making the planes available through
                            the less than popular Spanish! We tried this with Pakistan via Turkey
                            several years ago and got clobbered!</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="underline">2. C–130’s</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Enough on F–5’s. Turning to the C–130’s, let me first make clear my
                            concern that our Lockheed friends are playing fast and loose with us. At
                            least informally for the record, I would like to make several comments
                            on Cowden’s letter of December 1 to you (TAB D). In the first place, I
                            have not seen or heard any sort of a satisfactory explanation from
                            Lockheed as to how the quantum jump from 4 to 8 aircraft took place, and
                            I cannot escape the suspicion that Lockheed itself may have encouraged
                            this increase in the <gloss target="#t_LARAF1">LARAF</gloss> request to
                            help solve the problem of its Marietta production line. Is there any
                            reason why the Department should not press Lockheed for an explanation
                            of this rather important new dimension of the problem? Secondly, I find
                            it strange that Cowden never mentioned to me that Farjani had told him
                            that failure to license the additional C–130’s could result in a break
                            in diplomatic relations with the US. (All Cowden told me was that
                            Farjani had said that such failure could result in expulsion of the
                            Lockheed team, the “burning” of the present 8 planes, and the
                            acquisition of Soviet transport aircraft.) Again, I suspect that the
                            “break in relations” bit has been added after the fact in an effort to
                            influence the Department. Thirdly, I never told Cowden that I “did not
                            anticipate any problem in regard to Lockheed’s air drop equipment and
                            training <pb facs="d83-04" n="4" xml:id="d83-04"/> program.” I did tell
                            him before he saw Farjani that I had recommended a favorable Department
                            response to the licensing application for the air drop equipment, adding
                            that I could not however say what the ultimate decision would be.</p>
                        <p>As you know, I was not in favor at the outset of permitting Lockheed to
                            proceed with discussions with the <gloss target="#t_LARAF1">LARAF</gloss> for additional C–130’s. I was wrong in permitting
                            myself to be persuaded at that time that Lockheed explorations with the
                                <gloss target="#t_LARG1">LARG</gloss>, without commitment, would not
                            do any harm. It has done harm and added another horn to our present
                            dilemma. Nevertheless we started down the road and, if our objective is
                            to avoid confrontation, it seems to me that the present logic of the
                            situation is to permit Lockheed to go ahead with their contract and to
                            face up to the licensing problem in 1973. Meanwhile, like the baseball
                            team whose pitcher hasn’t shown up, we can always pray for rain!</p>
                        <p>However, I agree with Jim Blake that we should not let Lockheed maneuver
                            the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> into turning a blind eye on,
                            thereby tacitly approving, a type of contract that is misleading and
                            that will therefore give us even greater trouble with both the <gloss target="#t_LARG1">LARG</gloss> and Lockheed. I refer particularly to
                            paragraphs 2 c and d of Mr. <persName>Cowden</persName>’s letter to Jim
                            of December 3 (TAB E). Taken together they will lead, almost certainly,
                            to a situation where the <gloss target="#t_LARG1">LARG</gloss> has a
                            claim against Lockheed for return of advance payments—due to the export
                            licenses not being forthcoming from the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>. Again, we will be in the middle, where Lockheed wants
                            us.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="underline">3. Air Drop Equipment</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The next subject I would like to raise is air drop equipment, I simply do
                            not understand the Department’s reasoning in turning down this license.
                            This decision has already badly undermined the credibility of our “no
                            decision” on the F–5’s and C–130’s. (who will believe we will license 8
                            additional military C–130’s if we won’t license air drop equipment?)
                            Although I continue to believe we should have approved the request, it
                            seems to me that at the minimum we should have placed the item in limbo
                            with the F–5’s and C–130’s.</p>
                        <pb facs="d83-05" n="5" xml:id="d83-05"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="underline">4. Helicopters</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Finally, I would like to raise once again the question of the Sikorsky
                            helicopters which was the subject of our 2228 (TAB F), The only reaction
                            we have had to this message has been <persName corresp="#p_CWJ1">Warren
                                Clark</persName>’s short note of December 7 to Charles Marthinsen
                            (TAB G) saying that there has been “no approval by Sikorsky for the sale
                            of helicopters to the <gloss target="#t_LARG1">LARG</gloss>”, but that
                            “We would certainly want to look very closely at any such request,” I do
                            not know what “no approval by Sikorsky” means, but assume that “no
                            application by Sikorsky” was intended. In any event, the intent of our
                            telegram was to suggest that somebody contact Sikorsky, find out what
                            they have in mind, tell them right from the beginning that they haven’t
                            got a Chinaman’s chance of getting the necessary licenses, and urge them
                            to lay off. In short, we should do now with Sikorsky what I wish we had
                            done from the beginning with Lockheed. At least with Sikorsky there has
                            not been, as far as I know, any approach to the <gloss target="#t_LARG1">LARG</gloss> so we do have a chance to avoid the problem.</p>
                        <p>I regret the complaining tone which the foregoing recital of problems
                            conveys, I know the clearance problem on formal communications on such
                            sensitive and complicated problems, but informal channels are open to at
                            least let us know why our requests for instructions, guidance, etc.,
                            can’t be met, I would hope you will urge Jim, <persName corresp="#p_OHI1">Harry</persName> and <persName>Warren</persName>
                            to do better by us. It sometimes gets a little lonesome out here.</p>
                        <closer> Sincerely, <lb/>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_PJAII1">Joseph Palmer</persName> 2nd</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>