<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-05-22T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-05-22T06:00:00-05:00" n="202" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d202">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">852.00/5497: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul at Geneva</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gilbert</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-05-22T12:00:00+01:00">May 22,
                                1937—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received May 22—11:20 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>155. Consulate’s 151, May 21, 10 a.m. The European press is carrying
                            extensive accounts in varying details of British <hi rend="italic">démarches</hi> being made in Paris, Brussels and Borne and perhaps
                            in other capitals relative to effecting an armistice to be associated
                            with the withdrawal of foreign “volunteers” from Spain.</p>
                        <p>While fully believing that London and Paris basically very much desire an
                            accomplishment along such lines and although despatches under London
                            dates lines suggest that Rome’s attitude is receptive, diplomatic
                            circles here in touch with European capitals and viewing the general
                            circumstances are exceedingly skeptical respecting this project. It is
                            felt that Paris and in particular London are opposed to the Spanish
                            affair coming before the Council, especially in the form it is
                            apparently taking, being apprehensive of inflammatory repercussions in
                            Europe resulting in a widening of the existing breaches, that they
                            particularly fear developments taking place here which would render the
                            League still less advantageous for their employment in the European
                            picture. Coming at this juncture this British project is thus seen as
                            largely an effort to disassociate themselves <pb facs="0314" n="302" xml:id="pg_302"/> in advance from the Spanish presentation of their
                            case to the Council and perhaps by some means to sidetrack action or at
                            least to minimize the political and popular effects of what may
                            transpire in Geneva. Further clarification is, however, awaited.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Gilbert</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>