<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-06-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-06-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="223" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d223">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">852.00/5651</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-06-02">June 2, 1937</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Mexican Chargé d’Affaires called this morning by instruction from his
                            Government and delivered to me a formal note dated June 2.<note n="2" xml:id="d223fn2">Not printed.</note> Upon reading the note, I
                            ascertained that the purport of it was that <pb facs="0331" n="319" xml:id="pg_319"/> the Mexican Government requested President
                            Roosevelt “to take the steps which he might judge opportune in order to
                            invite the European countries to obtain a pacific solution of this
                            German-Spanish conflict”.</p>
                        <p>After I had read the note, I said to Dr. Quintanilla that, in view of the
                            importance of the contents of the note, it would, of course, be
                            necessary to give it consideration and that I would make at the earliest
                            possible moment a formal reply in writing.</p>
                        <p>Dr. Quintanilla took occasion to say that his interpretation of the step
                            taken by the Government of Mexico was that it felt itself helpless,
                            because of its situation and because of its relative unimportance, to
                            take the initiative in a matter of this kind and, consequently, turned
                            to its closest and powerful friend, the United States. I said that I was
                            deeply grateful for the friendly reference which the Chargé d’Affaires
                            made and that it was unnecessary for me to tell him that it was our hope
                            always to be able, so far as our national policy made it possible, to
                            accede to the requests made by the Government of Mexico and continue
                            cooperating with that Government in the interest of world peace.</p>
                        <p>I then said that I thought I would take the opportunity, for his
                            information and for that of his Government, of laying before him certain
                            aspects of the question.</p>
                        <p>I said that, of course, in the first place, we did not feel that we had
                            had an opportunity of knowing clearly what the facts in the recent
                            incident were; that, as he knew, the German Government made certain very
                            definite statements as to what had occurred in the matter of the bombing
                            of the <hi rend="italic">Deutschland</hi> and that the statements made
                            by the Spanish Government were quite distinct. It seemed to me that it
                            would be very premature for this Government to rush into any situation
                            of this highly delicate character without being certain of what the
                            facts really were.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, as he knew, the questions involved were questions which were
                            already receiving the most earnest attention of the Non-intervention
                            Committee at London and that I understood the Spanish Government was
                            likewise bringing the incident to the attention of the League. As he
                            knew, our policy was one of independent action, but we felt that the
                            primary responsibility for moving towards a pacific solution of the
                            difficulty which had arisen was certainly a European responsibility.</p>
                        <p>Third, I told him I had no doubt that he had read in the newspapers the
                            friendly and informal representations which had been made by the
                            Secretary of State to the German Ambassador and the Spanish Ambassador,
                            in which they had been requested to express to their two Governments the
                            very earnest hope of the United States that a peaceful solution might be
                            found.</p>
                        <p>In conclusion, I said that I had the very definite feeling that
                            precipitate action in this matter, however well intentioned, might
                            easily <pb facs="0332" n="320" xml:id="pg_320"/> prove more harmful than
                            beneficial in the interest of the maintenance of peace, and that I felt
                            that the moment was one in which the European powers, who were more
                            intimately concerned than the American continent with the controversy,
                            should be permitted to attempt to work out a satisfactory and pacific
                            solution.</p>
                        <p>The Chargé d’Affaires said that he would inform his Government of the
                            considerations I had advanced and expressed great appreciation for the
                            friendly way in which I had received his Government’s communication.</p>
                        <closer><signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps">elles</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>