<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of European Affairs (
                    (Moffat))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d319</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">319</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-09-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-09-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-09-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-09-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="319"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d319">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">852.00/6613</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of European
                        Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Moffat</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-09-29">September 29,
                            1937</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Italian Ambassador called this morning on his return from leave. He said he
                    found conditions in Europe much more normal than one would gather from the
                    American Press, which constantly dramatizes the threat of war. As a matter of
                    fact, although Spain is a source <pb facs="0418" n="406" xml:id="pg_406"/> of
                    concern, nobody wants to fight over Spain, neither Italy, nor Germany, nor
                    France, nor Russia. He reiterated that Italy’s sole interest in Spain was to
                    keep Bolshevism away from the Mediterranean and that any reports that she wanted
                    to keep the Balearic Islands or gain a foothold on the Peninsula were inaccurate
                    and misleading. He said that although the attitude of the French Government had
                    been correct an immense commerce in arms, munitions and airplanes had been going
                    on between Valencia and France. At the outbreak of the hostilities Valencia had
                    only one hundred planes. To date four hundred Loyalist planes have been shot
                    down and they still have a large number actually flying. All these have been
                    brought in from abroad.</p>
                <p>Italy, however, was pretty well satisfied that Franco was now winning. He thought
                    it would take another few weeks to finish the northern campaign, capture Gijon
                    and clear up the Oviedo region. After that Franco would have about 100,000 fresh
                    troops to throw into the line either at Madrid or near Valencia, and Italy was
                    calculating that this would suffice to end Loyalist resistance.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Pierrepont Moffat</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
