<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-10-18T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-10-18T13:00:00-05:00" n="339" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d339">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">852.00/6711: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Italy</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Reed</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-10-18T19:00:00+01:00">October 18, 1937—7
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received October 18—4 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>445. My telegram No. 443, October 17, noon.<note n="79" xml:id="d339fn79">Not printed.</note> The semi-official <hi rend="italic">Informazione Diplomattica</hi> announced today that there are at
                            present 40,000 Italian volunteers in Spain, including the auxiliary
                            services, whereas Valencia volunteers are far more numerous.</p>
                        <p>If the previous reliable estimates of approximately 60,000 Italian troops
                            serving in the Nationalist armies were correct, the publication of this
                            announcement would apparently indicate recent repatriation of large
                            numbers of Italians from Spain.</p>
                        <p>The British Ambassador, who saw Count Ciano just before Saturday’s
                            meeting of the London Non-intervention Committee, stated that he found
                            the Foreign Minister most anxious of finding a solution and willing to
                            accept very strong measures of control provided agreement on the other
                            two questions could be secured. The Italians insist, however, that an
                            equal number of volunteers be withdrawn from each side rather than
                            proportionally according to the numbers serving in each army. Lord
                                Perth<note n="80" xml:id="d339fn80">Sir Eric Drummond succeeded to
                                the earldom August 20, 1937.</note> said that the French Government
                            attached considerable importance to a proportional withdrawal as Paris
                            seemed to believe that more foreigners were serving with the Nationalist
                            Army than with the Valencia forces and that an equal withdrawal would be
                            definitely advantageous to Franco. Either solution, he added, would be
                            acceptable to the British Government.</p>
                        <p>A Foreign Office official today stressed the unfortunate impression which
                            Eden’s Llandudno speech<note n="81" xml:id="d339fn81">Made on October
                                15, 1937.</note> had created in Italian official circles and said
                            that such an attitude on the part of the British Government makes a
                            solution more difficult. The Italians seem, however, inclined to
                            restrained optimism and to consider that the Italian offer of a partial
                            withdrawal of volunteers offers a real possibility for agreement
                            although it is still feared that Soviets will continue to block
                            accord.</p>
                        <pb facs="0440" n="428" xml:id="pg_428"/>
                        <p>The impression prevails here that from a military point of view an
                            agreement with respect to volunteers is feasible particularly since it
                            is understood that Franco attaches more importance to a recognition of
                            his belligerent status than to continued foreign reenforcements.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Reed</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>