<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Bullitt) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d347</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">347</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-10-23T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-10-23T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-10-23T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-10-23T05:00:00-05:00" n="347"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d347">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">852.00/6750: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bullitt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-10-23T10:00:00+00:00"
                            >October 23, 1937—10 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 9:40 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1501. I discussed with Delbos also the question of Spain. He said that he still
                    was not sure that the apparent agreement of day before <pb facs="0446" n="434"
                        xml:id="pg_434"/> yesterday in London was a real agreement and telephoned
                    Corbin, French Ambassador in London, while I was in his office to hear the
                    latest news. Corbin gave him the news which the Department unquestionably has
                    from other sources that the Soviet representative had refused to accept the
                    British plan for the work of the committees in Spain and that Grandi had
                    immediately started to leave the meeting and that his departure had been
                    prevented only with the greatest difficulty. Delbos ordered Corbin to come to
                    Paris tomorrow for instructions and said that he hoped the matter could be
                    settled satisfactorily on Monday.</p>
                <p>I asked Delbos if he interpreted the acceptance of the British project by the
                    Italians as an indication that the Italians felt certain that Franco would soon
                    win the war. In contradistinction to Chautemps, he said that he did not believe
                    this. He felt that the Italians were in difficulties in Spain as the war in
                    Spain had become unpopular in Italy. He did not believe that the Valencia
                    Government was about to collapse and did not believe that Franco could attack
                    successfully either Madrid or Teruel. In my discussion with Blum later he
                    expressed the same opinion as Delbos.</p>
                <p>I asked Delbos whether the British had agreed to establish a permanent patrol
                    around Minorca. He said that they had not and that he would be unwilling to
                    establish a French patrol unless the British should participate.</p>
                <p>Both Blum and Delbos were much more optimistic with regard to the position of the
                    Barcelona Government than was Chautemps.</p>
                <p>I was informed yesterday (and both Blum and Delbos by eloquent silence in reply
                    to my questions seemed to confirm the information) that whereas when I left
                    France 3 weeks ago there was no passage of supplies across the French frontier
                    to Barcelona and Valencia at the present time the frontier was at least
                    partially open.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bullitt</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
