<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-01-16T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-01-16T17:00:00-05:00" n="637" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d637">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A5/851a: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-01-16T17:00:00-05:00">January 16, 1937—5
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>9. 1. For your confidential information, British tell us Clive will be
                        instructed this week to inform the Japanese Government (1) that the
                        Governments of the United States, Great Britain, France, Italy, Germany,
                        Soviet Union, and a number of lesser naval powers have agreed to limit the
                        caliber of guns on capital ships to 14 inches (with the exception of two
                        capital ships which the Soviets may build with guns of larger caliber); (2)
                        that the moment has come when the Japanese Government must decide whether it
                        is to be the only one opposing the 14-inch gun limit; (3) that it is hoped
                        that the Japanese will approach this problem more from the political than
                        the technical viewpoint. Clive will then be instructed formally to request
                        the Japanese Government (1) to give the necessary assurances to permit the
                        London Naval Treaty, 1936, to come into force with the 14-inch limit on
                        capital ship gun caliber; (2) to take no action in practice that would
                        entail invocation of the escalator clause by other powers and so bring the
                        whole Treaty system to the ground. In conclusion, Clive will be instructed
                        to state that if Japan is unwilling to join the other naval powers in this
                        general accord the British Government will find it difficult to reconcile
                        such an attitude on the part of the Japanese Government with recently
                        expressed professions of friendship.</p>
                    <p>2. The British have decided upon this course after the failure of Yoshida to
                        obtain a response from his Government due, it is believed, to the opposition
                        of Nagano.</p>
                    <p>3. We think it best for the British to make this formal inquiry of the
                        Japanese without action on our part. Clive will be instructed to keep you
                        posted on the outcome of his initiative. Please keep the Department
                        currently informed by telegraph.</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>