<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom ( (Bingham) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d659</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">659</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-06-18T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-06-18T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-06-18T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-06-18T07:00:00-05:00" n="659"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d659">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A5/893: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bingham</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-06-18T13:00:00+01:00"
                            >June 18, 1937—1 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received June 18—9:25 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>391. I transmitted the Department’s 223 of June 4, 8 p.m., to the Foreign Office
                    orally and this morning was read a reply in substance as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom for their part fully
                            reciprocate the views of the United States Government in this matter,
                            and as evidence of the sincerity of their intentions, have already
                            decided that the five capital ships included in their estimates for 1937
                            and 1938 should mount guns not exceeding 14-inch calibre. His Majesty’s
                            Government are prepared to abide by that limitation, unless and until
                            other principal naval powers, by their departure therefrom, are regarded
                            by His Majesty’s Government as having rendered such a course impossible.
                            They desire by this means to give a lead to the world and they earnestly
                            hope that the United States Government will see their way to join with
                            them in setting an example to other powers in regard to this particular
                            phase of naval limitation”.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>I then asked as to the matter of ratifications of the London Naval Treaty by this
                    Government and was informed that the French Government had informed the British
                    Government they desired to ratify the treaty before the present session of the
                    Chamber ended (presumably on the understanding that the British Government
                    likewise intended early ratification). The Foreign Office then added that the
                        <pb facs="0646" n="634" xml:id="pg_634"/> matter of ratification was before
                    the Cabinet now but that even though the Soviets had not given their final
                    agreement I might take an informal assurance that the British Government
                    intended ratification before the adjournment of Parliament.</p>
                <p>Craigie stated he was leaving England for Japan about the middle of August but
                    hoped before that time Mussolini’s frame of mind might be such as to bring him
                    into the treaty.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bingham</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
