<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Italy ( (Phillips) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d679</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">679</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-05-27T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-05-27T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-05-27T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-05-27T13:00:00-05:00" n="679"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d679">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A19/99: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Italy</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phillips</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-05-27T19:00:00+01:00"
                            >May 27, 1937—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received May 27—3:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>248. My 244, May 25, noon. The newspapers this afternoon under New York dateline
                    and with conspicuous headlines publish Mussolini’s <pb facs="0671" n="659"
                        xml:id="pg_659"/> statements to Simms as well as accounts of the foreign
                    comment which has appeared to date.</p>
                <p>Gayda<note n="21" xml:id="d679fn21">Virginio Gayda, editor of <hi rend="italic"
                            >Giornale d’Italia</hi>.</note> in an editorial says that this
                    invitation to the President to convene a world conference for the limitation of
                    armaments made by a well-armed and disciplined state is the result of “conscious
                    will not of necessity” and that it realistically indicates the limitations
                    within which such an initiative could prove successful. Gayda continues that “it
                    is from Roosevelt that there have recently come not without polemical tone
                    denunciations of Europe for the folly of its armaments race; and it is in
                    Roosevelt the leader of a great power whose own vital interests demand
                    solidarity with the rest of the world that this race may find a supreme force
                    for moderation through the initiative for a meeting among all the responsible
                    nations”. The United States being extraneous to all European conflicts “to such
                    a point as to base her foreign policy on deliberate absence from the League of
                    Nations and on neutrality” and having no need for huge armaments since she is
                    stronger than all her neighbors together, is the only country to which can fall
                    “the legitimate work of arbitration among the opposing interests of Europe and
                    the world and the competitive armaments in which those interests are expressed.
                    With the initiative mentioned by the Duce the United States would augment her
                    prestige as a world leader and would without incurring any of those dangerous
                    entanglements which she refuses strengthen the vital interests that unite her to
                    Europe.”</p>
                <p>After expatiating on the grave political and economic perils of the present
                    armaments race which President Roosevelt is in the best of positions to realize,
                    the writer says that world economic collaboration which the President is
                    promoting is inconceivable so long as the armaments race continues and that
                    anyone who rejects Mussolini’s “frank and documented warning to the United
                    States and the whole civilized world voluntarily places himself outside the road
                    to real peace.”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Phillips</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
