<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Bullitt) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d71</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">71</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-08-05T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-08-05T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-08-05T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-08-05T06:00:00-05:00" n="71"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d71">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">852.00/6164: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bullitt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-08-05T12:00:00+01:00"
                            >August 5, 1937—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received 5:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1117. Continuing my 1116, August 5, noon.<note n="40" xml:id="d71fn40">
                        <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_370">p. 370</ref>.</note>
                        Chautemps<note n="41" xml:id="d71fn41">Camille Chautemps, French Prime
                        Minister, June 22, 1937–January 15, 1938, and January 18–March 10,
                        1938.</note> then said that the British had decided to push the recognition
                    of the King of Italy as Emperor of Ethiopia at the next meeting of the League.
                    They were ready to offer Mussolini this real advantage in return for Mussolini’s
                    relinquishment of certain positions to which he had no right, such as his
                    occupation of the Balearic Islands, et cetera. Chautemps said he felt that the
                    British were right in attempting to reach reconciliation with Italy. Indeed he
                    would confess that he also had been thinking of making a similar move and he was
                    only sorry that the British had gotten ahead of him and had acted in the matter
                    without consulting him and thus might work out a reconciliation between Great
                    Britain and Italy while leaving French-Italian relations thoroughly bad.</p>
                <p>I asked Chautemps if he intended to make a similar move for <hi rend="italic"
                        >rapprochement</hi> with Italy immediately. He said that he did not since
                    Mussolini would come to the conclusion that France was merely being towed along
                    by England. As things stood now he would prefer to follow in England’s wake.</p>
                <p>I asked Chautemps if he had made any attempts recently to reach reconciliation
                    with Germany. He said François-Poncet had made many attempts but had been able
                    to get nowhere and repeated once more that France is prepared to make great
                    concessions to even giving up colonies provided it should seem possible to work
                    out a real reconciliation with Germany but will give up nothing unless a genuine
                    reconciliation should seem possible.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bullitt</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
