<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul at Geneva ( (Bucknell) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d849</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">849</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-11-23T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-11-23T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recDVvXJiNa7eCFyj" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89000875"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor market</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recUInGVZ0Y3MeuOS" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recIfFl6ouaEmS16p" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="recmcLXlokIhw3k5j" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="rec65d5a63ab10e2d2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Rubber</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="labor" subject="labor" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091" lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-11-23T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-11-23T09:00:00-05:00" n="849"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d849">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.C1199/306: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Geneva</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bucknell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-11-23T15:00:00+01:00"
                            >November 23, 1937—3 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received November 23—1:15 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>367. Department’s telegram 162, November 18, 1 p.m. Stoppani informs me that he
                    has arranged with the Chairman of the Economic Committee for Thompson’s
                    attendance as Grady’s substitute. He hoped that Thompson would participate in
                    the discussion. I replied that at present he was instructed merely to follow the
                    discussion and report to Grady.<note n="40" xml:id="d849fn40">The Consul was
                        informed by telegram No. 163, November 24, that telegram No. 162, November
                        18, 1 p.m., was not intended to prevent Mr. Thompson from participating in
                        the discussion as Mr. Grady’s substitute, and that general instructions from
                        Mr. Grady had been mailed on November 23.</note> I added that complete
                    instructions from Grady were expected by mail.</p>
                <p>I am mailing today a draft report on raw materials<note n="41" xml:id="d849fn41"
                        >League of Nations document B. 1004, Geneva, November 18; copy transmitted
                        to the Department by the Consul at Geneva in his despatch No. 92 Political,
                        November 23, not printed.</note> prepared by the Secretariat for the
                    Committee’s consideration which contains a draft declaration of policy<note
                        n="42" xml:id="d849fn42">“Draft Declaration Concerning (the Establishment of
                        Permanent Guarantees in Regard to) Commercial Access to Raw
                        Materials.”</note> which it is suggested that the Council submit to
                    Governments for their observations. In the light of the replies received a
                    decision could be taken as to whether individual governments should make
                    declarations along the lines suggested or whether a single text should be
                    established and opened for signature.</p>
                <p>The draft declaration sets forth the policy which the parties declare it is their
                    intention to follow towards other states associating themselves with the
                    declaration and is divided into three parts as follows: <pb facs="0835" n="823"
                        xml:id="pg_823"/>
                    <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>A declaration that no prohibition or restrictions will be placed on
                            the export of raw materials and that no export duties will be levied
                            except of a fiscal character. An exception is made for temporary
                            measures taken in extraordinary circumstances to safeguard vital
                            interests. The declaration would also apply to colonies, protectorates,
                            et cetera.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>A declaration that foreigners would have equality in law and in fact
                            with nationals in the production of raw materials. Exceptions are
                            provided for the control of the exploitation of mineral resources and
                            for laws and regulations concerning the admission, sojourn and
                            settlement of foreigners and for the protection of the national labor
                            market. It would also apply to colonies but makes special provision for
                            obligations towards indigenous populations provided there is no
                            discrimination between nationals and foreigners.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>A declaration that as respects effective international regulation
                            schemes which may be established concerning coal, petroleum, iron,
                            copper, tin, rubber, timber, cotton and wool the Government in order to
                            ensure that the schemes do not unduly interfere with the trade in raw
                            materials nor unduly raise prices will either participate directly in
                            the schemes or will obtain the necessary powers to exercise an effective
                            supervision. It further provides for “effective representation” of
                            consuming countries, for publicity and for the consideration of
                            complaints.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>These declarations would apply solely to industrial raw materials excluding
                    foodstuff. The document contains an additional declaration taken mainly from
                    Eden’s Assembly speech of September 20 containing an offer to consider specific
                    complaints respecting abuses of colonial preference treatment.</p>
                <p>Stoppani has written Grady urging that he send Thompson some indications as to
                    the attitude he should take towards the draft. He said these could be quite
                    general since the only decision the Committee could take would be to ask the
                    Council to submit the draft to governments. If not already desired that Thompson
                    endeavor directly or indirectly to influence the tenor of the report it would be
                    helpful in addition to any specific observations Grady may wish to cable upon
                    receipt of the document, to receive as soon as possible by mail any general
                    comments or material readily available for background.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bucknell</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
