<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-10-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-10-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="87" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d87">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">711.00 Pres. Speech, Oct. 5, 1937/99</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>) <hi rend="italic">of a Conversation With the
                            German Ambassador</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Dieckoff</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-10-11">October 11, 1937</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                    <p>The Ambassador then referred to the President’s Chicago speech. He said that
                        he was very interested to know the exact interpretation which he should give
                        to it. I said that it seemed to me hardly necessary for me to attempt to
                        interpret the President’s speech inasmuch as it was in my judgment a speech
                        which spoke for itself, but that I felt the Ambassador might wish to give
                        particular emphasis in his own consideration of the speech to the last
                        paragraph thereof. I said that the President sincerely believed that all of
                        the difficult problems with which the countries of the world were today
                        confronted could be solved through a spirit of friendly cooperation and by
                        recognition of each other’s difficulties, and that no permanent solution
                        could ever be found through force. I said that the President further
                        believed that the Government of the United States should work actively
                        towards peace inasmuch as a continuation of the policies of force undertaken
                        by certain governments of the world would in all likelihood bring about a
                        state of affairs which would jeopardize the interests of all peace-loving
                        nations, and that it was therefore imperative for all countries “actively to
                        work for peace.”</p>
                    <p>The Ambassador said that this was exactly the view which he himself had taken
                        of the speech; that he had so informed his Government; and that he again had
                        to express his regret that the press in Germany, as well as a portion of the
                        press in the United States, should, through erroneous and exaggerated
                        interpretations of the President’s statements, <pb facs="0151" n="139" xml:id="pg_139"/> endeavor to create further ill-will between the two
                        peoples. He reminded me, very significantly I thought, that throughout the
                        past years the German Government had declared its belief that the
                        restitution of German colonies was necessary for the solution of the German
                        problem. The German Government had at the same time repeatedly made it known
                        publicly that it did not intend to seek colonial restoration through force
                        but through negotiation and by peaceful methods. He stated that I should
                        remember—and I told him that I did clearly remember—that when the German
                        Government had taken unilateral action to abrogate certain provisions of the
                        Versailles Treaty, such action had always been taken within its own
                        territory and for the sole purpose of restoring to the German people their
                        own unimpaired national sovereignty. He reminded me that Germany had never
                        expressed a determination to regain the Polish Corridor through force nor
                        any other of its former continental territory of which it had been deprived
                        by the Versailles Treaty.</p>
                    <p>I said to the Ambassador that I was very glad to recognize the complete
                        accuracy of what he said, and that I believed that the influence of Germany
                        towards a solution of international problems by negotiation would be a
                        powerful factor in the cause of peace in the world today.</p>
                    <p>I asked the Ambassador if he had any information from his Government as to
                        developments with regard to the Spanish situation and particularly with
                        regard to the reply of Italy to Great Britain and France, refusing to
                        discuss a solution of the Spanish problem unless Germany took part in these
                        conversations. The Ambassador said that he had no information directly from
                        his Government, but that he himself hoped that his Government might find it
                        possible to take part since he thought that his Government might prove to be
                        a conciliatory influence. I expressed to him my personal opinion—and I
                        emphasized that it was purely personal—that the friendly participation by
                        Germany in a discussion of the problem based upon the Italian official
                        statement that the Italian Government would under no conditions undertake to
                        impair Spanish sovereignty over Spain herself, her colonies, or the islands
                        under the Spanish flag, would in fact be a helpful factor.</p>
                    <p>Before he left the Ambassador inquired as to the attitude of this Government
                        with regard to the meeting of the Nine Power Treaty signatories.<note n="65" xml:id="d87fn65">See <ref target="frus1937v04#pg_155">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 155</ref> ff.</note> I told him
                        that, while no official invitation had yet been received, this Government
                        had already made known its willingness to take part in such a meeting once
                        an invitation were received.</p>
                    <closer><signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps">elles</hi>]</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>