<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Bullitt) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-11-22T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-11-22T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-11-22T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-11-22T12:00:00-05:00" n="98"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d98">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00/225: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bullitt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-11-22T17:00:00+00:00"
                            >November 22, 1937—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received November 22—4:25 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1646. This morning I discussed the European situation with Delbos. He said that
                    he was extremely apprehensive that Germany would in the near future make some
                    sort of drive against Austria. It was clear that the Germans were determined in
                    one way or another to incorporate Austria in the German Reich and he felt that
                    the time might not be far off when they would act. He did not believe that there
                    would be any immediate German action against Czechoslovakia.</p>
                <p>He felt that the best chance of beginning negotiations which might lead to a
                    peaceful settlement of the situation in Europe or at least postponement of war
                    would be in the colonial domain. France and England could not offer Germany
                    “concessions” in Austria and Czechoslovakia because in the first place such
                    action would be dishonorable and in the second place the Germans would say that
                    the Austrians and the Germans of Bohemia belonged to them of right and there was
                    no concession whatsoever involved in permitting them to fall into the hands of
                    the Reich. In the colonial domain on the other hand France and England had
                    something to give and could therefore demand something in exchange. He felt
                    therefore that through the door of colonial concessions it might be possible to
                    enter into fruitful negotiations.</p>
                <p>He believed that if some progress could be made in the colonial field it might
                    not be impossible to begin conversations for a new Locarno. He was not averse to
                    including Poland in those conversations but felt that he would have to include
                    Czechoslovakia as well if he should include Poland.</p>
                <p>I asked Delbos if there were any possibility that the French Government in any
                    future Locarno negotiations would make “exceptions” with regard to the French
                    allegiances [<hi rend="italic">alliances</hi>] with Poland and Czechoslovakia
                    but would omit an “exception” dealing with the treaty of mutual assistance with
                    the Soviet Union. He said that he felt that would be impossible. French public
                    opinion had to be considered. The Government unquestionably would be overthrown
                    by the Communists. Moreover he doubted the wisdom of abandoning the Soviet Union
                    at this moment as he still feared greatly that Germany and the Soviet Union
                    would come to an immediate agreement if France should abandon Russia
                    altogether.</p>
                <p>He said that as far as he was concerned he favored making concessions to Germany
                    piecemeal in order to stave off war but in a democracy it was intensely
                    difficult to make piecemeal concessions and whose <pb facs="0171" n="159"
                        xml:id="pg_159"/> public opinion would very much prefer to submit to a <hi
                        rend="italic">fait accompli</hi> rather than make a concession which might
                    be much less objectionable than the <hi rend="italic">fait accompli</hi>.</p>
                <p>With regard to Italy Delbos said that neither he nor Chautemps would object to
                    accrediting an Ambassador to the King of Italy, Emperor of Ethiopia, if that
                    were the only bone of contention between France and Italy. He was now convinced
                    that the Italians had no intention of remaining in the Balearics; but the
                    Italians were conducting the most furious campaigns by radio and other sorts of
                    propaganda against France in the French colonies in North Africa and in the Near
                    East. They were, moreover, paying an enormous number of agents in Paris to stir
                    up trouble. If France could get a real understanding with Italy in return for
                    the appointment of an ambassador, that would be an extremely cheap bargain; but
                    he did not believe that Mussolini was inclined to make any such bargain.</p>
                <p>He had as now no information whatever with regard to the conversation between
                    Eden [<hi rend="italic">Hitler?</hi>] and Halifax but had been promised full
                    information tomorrow.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bullitt</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
