<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-08-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-08-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="983" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d983">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">701.0611/553a</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                <gloss type="to">American Diplomatic Officers</gloss></hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">Diplomatic Serial No. 2829</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-08-19">August 19, 1937</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sirs</hi>: The Department has recently received so many
                        inquiries concerning the subject matter of circular instruction Diplomatic
                        Serial No. 766 of November 9, 1928,<note n="1" xml:id="d983fn1">Not printed.
                            For previous statement on diplomatic exemptions, see note to the Irish
                            Minister, January 22, 1927, <ref target="frus1927v01#pg_414"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1927, Vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 414</ref>.</note> in regard to the
                        exemptions from taxation and customs duties enjoyed by foreign diplomatic
                        and consular officers within the United States, that it has seemed
                        advisable, in view of changes necessary therein, to issue a new circular
                        instruction.</p>
                    <p>Ambassadors and Ministers accredited to the United States and the members of
                        their households, including secretaries, attachés, and servants, who are not
                        citizens of the United States, are exempted from the payment of Federal
                        income tax upon their salaries, fees and wages, and upon the income derived
                        by them from investments in the United States in stocks and bonds and from
                        interest on bank balances in the United States. The income derived from any
                        business carried on by them in the United States would, however, be
                        taxable.</p>
                    <p>Miscellaneous federal excise taxes are imposed by the Revenue Act of
                            1932<note n="2" xml:id="d983fn2">47 Stat. 169.</note> on telegraph,
                        telephone, radio and cable facilities; admissions, dues and initiation fees;
                        transfers of stocks and bonds; conveyances; sales of produce for future
                        delivery; passage tickets; foreign insurance policies; and safe deposit
                        boxes.</p>
                    <p>Under the application of the principles of international law exempting from
                        taxation ambassadors, ministers and other duly accredited diplomatic
                        representatives of foreign governments, together with the members of their
                        families living with them and members of their households, including
                        attachés, secretaries, clerks and servants who are not citizens of the
                        United States, all such diplomatic representatives, together with the other
                        personnel above-mentioned, are entitled to exemption from the taxes
                        mentioned in the preceding paragraph.</p>
                    <pb facs="1004" n="992" xml:id="pg_992"/>
                    <p>It is understood that some foreign governments levy a transmission tax on
                        transportation. Sections 500 of the Revenue Acts of 1917 and 1918<note n="3" xml:id="d983fn3">40 Stat. 300 and 1057, respectively.</note> imposed a
                        similar tax on transportation charges. Article 99 of Treasury Regulations
                        49, relating to such tax provided that ambassadors, ministers and properly
                        accredited diplomatic representatives of any foreign government to the
                        United States were exempt from the payment of the taxes on amounts paid for
                        transportation services rendered them within the United States. Such tax was
                        repealed as of December 31, 1921.<note n="4" xml:id="d983fn4">Revenue Act of
                            1921; 42 Stat. 227, 320.</note> Therefore, at the present time there is
                        no Federal tax on transportation charges similar to the transmission tax
                        mentioned.</p>
                    <p>In the District of Columbia there is no charge corresponding to rates payable
                        by a tenant, and consequently diplomatic officers in Washington are not
                        obliged to pay rates.</p>
                    <p>Property in the District of Columbia owned by foreign governments for Embassy
                        and Legation purposes is exempt from general and special taxes or
                        assessments. Property owned by an Ambassador or Minister and used for
                        Embassy or Legation purposes is exempt from general taxes but not from
                        special assessments for improvements. The payment of water rent is required
                        in all cases, as this is not regarded as a tax but the sale of a
                        commodity.</p>
                    <p>The President approved on August 27, 1935, H. R. 7998,<note n="5" xml:id="d983fn5">49 Stat. 908.</note> entitled “An Act to exempt from
                        taxation official compensation of certain foreign representatives …”, the
                        pertinent portion of which reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“Be it enacted by the Senate and House of Representatives of the
                                United States of America in Congress assembled, That section 116 of
                                the Revenue Act of 1934<note n="6" xml:id="d983fn6">48 Stat.
                                    680.</note> relating to exclusions from gross income is amended
                                by adding at the end thereof a new subsection reading as follows:
                                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>‘(<hi rend="italic">h</hi>) Compensation of Employees of
                                        Foreign Governments.—Wages, fees, or salary of an employee
                                        of a foreign government (including a consular or other
                                        officer, or a nondiplomatic representative) received as
                                        compensation for official services to such government— <list>
                                            <item>‘(1) If such employee is not a citizen of the
                                                United States; and</item>
                                            <item>‘(2) If the services are of a character similar to
                                                those performed by employees of the Government of
                                                the United States in foreign countries; and</item>
                                            <item>‘(3) If the foreign government whose employee is
                                                claiming exemption grants an equivalent exemption to
                                                employees of the Government of the United States
                                                performing similar services in such foreign
                                                country.</item>
                                        </list></p></quote></p>
                            <p>‘The Secretary of State shall certify to the Secretary of the
                                Treasury the names of the foreign countries which grant an
                                equivalent exemption to the employees of the Government of the
                                United States performing services in such foreign countries, and the
                                character of the services performed by employees of the Government
                                of the United States in foreign countries.’”</p>
                        </quote></p>
                    <pb facs="1005" n="993" xml:id="pg_993"/>
                    <p>The members of foreign diplomatic missions and foreign consular officers in
                        the District of Columbia are exempt in the District from the payment of
                        personal property taxes on automobiles and other personal property, either
                        tangible or intangible, owned by them. They are furnished identification
                        tags and operators’ permits for their automobiles, without charge, provided
                        the applications made therefor bear the seal of the mission and the seal of
                        the Department of State. Automobiles bearing District of Columbia tags are
                        permitted to enter the several States without obtaining additional tags.
                        Members of foreign diplomatic missions in the United States and foreign
                        consular officers stationed in the District of Columbia are accordingly not
                        required to pay the fees ordinarily charged other owners of automobiles in
                        this country.</p>
                    <p>The fees and taxes for automobiles and other property to be charged foreign
                        consuls in the several States of the United States, in the absence of
                        applicable treaty provisions, are subject to regulation by the States in
                        which the consuls are stationed. However, practically all of the States of
                        the Union now accord to foreign consular officers on the basis of
                        reciprocity the free registration of their automobiles.</p>
                    <p>Diplomatic officers of foreign countries residing in the United States are
                        entitled to exemption from sales taxes, such as those imposed on gasoline,
                        automobile tires and inner tubes if they are parties to the importation or
                        sale which is made the subject of the tax, that is to say, if the gasoline,
                        automobile tires or inner tubes are imported by them or purchased by them
                        from the producer or manufacturer for their personal or official use.</p>
                    <p>By an order dated July 8, 1921, the Collector of Taxes of the District of
                        Columbia was authorized to issue dog licenses to foreign diplomatic officers
                        without charge.</p>
                    <p>Articles 425 and 426 of the United States Customs Regulations of 1931 provide
                        for the granting of customs courtesies and the exemption from the payment of
                        customs duties, to diplomatic and consular officers of foreign countries and
                        outline the procedure to be followed by such officers in requesting these
                        courtesies.</p>
                    <p>Foreign consular officers who are nationals of the State appointing them and
                        not engaged in any other business and their families are accorded the
                        privilege of the free entry of their personal and household effects,
                        including intoxicating liquors, at the time of their arrival in the United
                        States to take up their official duties or upon their return to their posts
                        in the United States after leave of absence. The entry of liquors into the
                        States of the United States is governed by state laws prohibiting or
                        regulating the importation or transportation of liquors for beverage use.
                        (Section 2, 21st Amendment to the Constitution of the United States, adopted
                        December 5, 1933).</p>
                    <pb facs="1006" n="994" xml:id="pg_994"/>
                    <p>In the absence of applicable treaty provisions, exemption from the internal
                        revenue tax on intoxicating liquors is not accorded consular officers.</p>
                    <p>There is enclosed a list showing the countries with which there are treaties
                        or reciprocal agreements<note n="7" xml:id="d983fn7">There were treaties
                            with the following countries: Cuba, El Salvador, Estonia, Finland,
                            Germany, Honduras, Hungary, Latvia, and Norway. Reciprocal agreements
                            existed with the following: Bolivia, Chile, China, Ecuador, Egypt, Irish
                            Free State, Iran, Lithuania, Netherlands, Panamá, and Sweden. The
                            agreements with Lithuania, Panamá, and Iran pertained only to Consuls on
                            temporary assignments.</note> containing special provisions with respect
                        to customs exemptions for consular officers and official supplies.</p>
                    <p>Supplies intended for official use of foreign embassies and legations and
                        foreign consulates in the United States, such as office furniture and office
                        material, may be entered free of duty. Exhibits of the products of foreign
                        countries, if forming a part of the permanent exhibitions in the consulates
                        may also be admitted free of duty.</p>
                    <p>The granting of these customs exemptions to diplomatic and consular officers
                        of foreign countries is conditional upon the granting of similar exemptions
                        to American diplomatic and consular officers by these countries.</p>
                    <p>Any material imported by a foreign government to be used in constructing an
                        embassy or legation building is exempted from the payment of customs
                        duties.</p>
                    <p>The above statement, although not exhaustive, describes some of the more
                        important immunities and exemptions accorded foreign diplomatic and consular
                        officers in the United States.</p>
                    <p>Should the occasion arise you may bring the foregoing information to the
                        attention of the governments to which you are accredited, and in so doing
                        you may state that should those governments not be disposed to grant to all
                        American diplomatic officers in those countries in matters relating to the
                        exemption from taxation and customs duties, privileges similar to those
                        enjoyed by foreign diplomatic officers in the United States, this Government
                        will have to reconsider its position with regard to the exemptions from
                        taxation and customs duties at present enjoyed by such officials in this
                        country.</p>
                    <p>You are instructed to make the following notation on the copies of Diplomatic
                        Serial No. 766 in your respective missions: “Cancelled—see C. I. Dip. Ser.
                        No. 2829.”</p>
                    <p>A copy of this instruction is being sent to the consular officers merely for
                        their information and files.</p>
                    <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">G. S.
                                Messersmith</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
            </body></text></TEI>