<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1872-02-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1872-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="138" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d138">
                        <head>No. 3.<lb/><hi rend="italic">General <persName type="from">Schenck</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-02-05"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 5,
                                1872</date>. (Sent at 8.30 p.m.)</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Reserving comment and further information until I can send written
                            dispatch, I communicate Granville’s note giving notice of British
                            interpretation of Treaty, as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Earl Granville to General
                                        Schenck.</hi></p>
                                <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>, <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 3, 1872.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Her Majesty’s Government have had
                                    under their consideration the Case presented on behalf of the
                                    Government of the United States to the Tribunal of Arbitration
                                    at Geneva, of which a copy had been presented to Her Majesty’s
                                    Agent.</p>
                                <pb facs="0448" n="426" xml:id="pg_426"/>
                                <p>I will not allude in this letter to several portions of the
                                    United States Case which are of comparatively smaller
                                    importance, but Her Majesty’s Government are of opinion that it
                                    will be in accordance with their desire that no obstacle should
                                    be interposed to the prosecution of the Arbitration, and that it
                                    will be more frank and friendly toward the Government of the
                                    United States to state at once their views respecting certain
                                    claims of an enormous and indefinite amount which appear to have
                                    been put forward as matters to be referred to arbitration.</p>
                                <p>Her Majesty’s Government hold that it is not within the province
                                    of the Tribunal of Arbitration at Geneva to decide upon the
                                    claims for indirect losses and injuries put forward in the case
                                    of the United States, including the loss in the transfer of the
                                    American commercial marine to the British flag, the enhanced
                                    payment of insurance, and the prolongation of the war, and the
                                    addition of a large sum to the cost of the war and suppression
                                    of the rebellion.</p>
                                <p>I have stated above the importance which Her Majesty’s Government
                                    attach to the prosecution of this arbitration.</p>
                                <p>The primary object of the Governments was the firm establishment
                                    of amicable relations between two countries which have so many
                                    and such peculiar reasons to be on friendly terms, and the
                                    satisfaction with which the announcement of the Treaty was
                                    received by both nations showed the strength of that
                                    feeling.</p>
                                <p>But there is another object to which Her Majesty’s Government
                                    believe the Government of the United States attach the same
                                    value as they do themselves, namely, to give an example to the
                                    world how two great nations can settle matters in dispute by
                                    referring them to an impartial tribunal.</p>
                                <p>Her Majesty’s Government, on their part, feel confident that the
                                    Government of the United States are also equally anxious with
                                    themselves that the amicable settlement which was stated in the
                                    Treaty of Washington to have been the object of that instrument
                                    may be attained, and that an example so full of good promise for
                                    the future may not be lost to the civilized world.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>SCHENCK.</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>