<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 96.General Schenck to Mr. Fish..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1872p2v2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d231</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">231</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1872-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1872-06-08T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1872-06-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1872-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="231" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d231">
                <head>No. 96.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">General <persName type="from">Schenck</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-06-08">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 8,
                                1872</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I received your telegram of yesterday early this morning, and
                            communicated it immediately to Lord Granville. I supposed any new
                            proposals <pb facs="0584" n="562" xml:id="pg_562"/> this Government
                            might make, or any attempt to arrive at agreement after that, would be
                            necessarily at Washington between you and Sir Edward Thornton, under
                            such instructions as he might receive. I thought there was no room for
                            new suggestions, but this evening Lord Granville sends me the following:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="center">[<hi rend="italic">Earl Granville to General
                                        Schenck.</hi>]</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: It appears to Her Majesty’s
                                    Government, from a review of the correspondence between the two
                                    Governments, that an agreement on the supplemental Article might
                                    probably be arrived at if sufficient time were given for
                                    discussion. If, therefore, the Treaty is to be maintained, an
                                    adjournment of the meeting of the Arbitrators from the 15th
                                    instant has become absolutely necessary. With this view, I have
                                    the honor ta propose that on the meeting of the Arbitrators on
                                    that day a joint application shall be made for an adjournment
                                    for eight months. If the Government of the United States concur
                                    in making an application for adjournment, it is the intention of
                                    Her Majesty’s Government to deliver to the Arbitrators on the
                                    15th instant the summary of their argument under the fifth
                                    Article of the Treaty, accompanied by a declaration, of which I
                                    have the honor to inclose you a copy for the information of your
                                    Government.</p>
                        <p rend="center">“<hi rend="italic">Sketch of draught note in
                                        presenting summary.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>“The undersigned Agent of Her British Majesty has the honor to
                                    deliver herewith to Count Sclopis, &amp;c., the printed
                                    argument, showing the points and referring to the evidence on
                                    which the Government of Her Britannic Majesty relies, as
                                    required by the fifth Article of the Treaty of Washington. The
                                    undersigned is instructed by the Government which he represents
                                    to state that the printed argument is only delivered to the
                                    Tribunal conditionally on the adjournment, requested in the note
                                    which he had the honor to address to the Tribunal this day
                                    jointly with the Agent of the United States,, “being carried
                                    into effect, and subject to the notice which the undersigned has
                                    the honor hereby to give, that it is the intention of Her
                                    Majesty’s Government to cancel the appointment of the British
                                    Arbitrator, and to withdraw from the arbitration at the close of
                                    the term fixed for the adjournment, unless the difference which
                                    has arisen between the two Governments as to the claims for
                                    indirect losses, referred to in the note which the undersigned
                                    had the honor to address to Count Sclopis on the 15th of April,
                                    shall have been removed.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>SCHENCK.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
