<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1857-12-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1857-01-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="69" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d69">
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Code of laws of the Russian Empire, edition
                                    of</hi> 1857.</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1857">undated</date>.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">Vol. 15, the Penal Code, book third of crimes against
                                the state.</p>
                            <p>* * * * * * * *</p>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Art.</hi> 293. If any Russian subject in time of
                                peace attacks with open force the inhabitants of neighboring or
                                other states, and through that exposes his country to danger of
                                rupture with a friendly power, or, at least, to a similar attack on
                                the part of subjects of that power on Eussian territories, for this
                                crime against national law, (the law of nations,) he himself and all
                                participating in it of their own will with knowledge of the crime
                                and of the unlawfulness of his undertaking are condemned:</p>
                            <p>To deprivation of all civil rights and to exile with hard labor in a
                                fortress for a period of from 8 to 10 years; and if they are not
                                exempt by law from corporal punishment, to punishment by whipping by
                                the executioner in the measure fixed in Art. 21 of this code for the
                                fifth degree of punishment of this kind with branding.</p>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">Complete collection of laws</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">vol. xxxiii, p</hi>. 757, 1858, <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 16, 33302,) <hi rend="italic">of the
                                        measure of punishment for crimes against the security of
                                        powers friendly to Russia.</hi></head>
                                <p><seg type="margin">[571]</seg> If one of the crimes mentioned in
                                    Articles 275, 276, *277, 283, 248 and 287, of the penal code,
                                    shall be committed against a foreign state, with which, on the
                                    basis of treaties or published laws or decrees, there is
                                    established a reciprocity in this respect, or against the
                                    supreme power of that state, those guilty, provided there is
                                    added to this no crime meriting a greater punishment, are
                                    condemned:</p>
                                <p>To loss of all civil rights and privileges and of all personal
                                    and class distinctions, and to exile in the government of Tomsk
                                    or Tobolsk; or if they are not exempt from corporal punishment,
                                    to delivery over to the companies of disciplinary arrest of the
                                    civil authorities for a period of from one and one-half to two
                                    and one-half years, or of from one to one and one-half
                                    years.</p>
                                <p>When the crime has been committed with aggravating circumstances,
                                    then to loss of all rights and to exile as a colonist in
                                    Siberia, in the not most distant places.</p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Code of laws, &amp;c, vol. xv, book iv, chap.
                                        vii.</hi>
                                </head>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Art.</hi> 367. Any one who, leaving his
                                    country, enters into the service of a foreign power, without the
                                    permission of the government, or becomes a subject of a foreign
                                    power, is liable for this breach of his duty of subjection and
                                    his oath of allegiance:</p>
                                <p><seg type="margin">[572]</seg> *To loss of all civil rights and
                                    étérnal exile from the limits of the empire; or, in case of his
                                    voluntary return to Eussia, to exile in Siberia.</p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>