<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Ireland ( (Gray) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d183</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">183</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-05-25T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-05-25T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-05-25T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-05-25T14:00:00-05:00" n="183"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d183">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/11288: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Ireland</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gray</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dublin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-05-25T20:00:00+01:00"
                            >May 25, 1941—8 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received May 26—1:06 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>55. For the Secretary and Under Secretary. Reference my telegram No. 54, May 24,
                    1 p.m. After sending this telegram yesterday I sent the Prime Minister the
                    purport of the three recent telegrams on this subject, obviously reserving
                    certain details. I said that if he were interested I would be glad to receive
                    constructive suggestions by telephone. At 5 o’clock he telephoned apparently
                    grateful for my good offices. He said it was exactly such a presentation of the
                    subject as he would make if he were himself dealing with it objectively. He had
                    no suggestions. I said I would be glad to work with him and would keep him
                    informed if I had word from my Government.</p>
                <p>His friendly tone pleased and surprised me as only last Tuesday I am informed he
                    told an opposition leader that I had misrepresented Ireland to you, that if the
                    situation were not so tense and if I were not a friend of the President he would
                    ask for my recall. At 8 o’clock he telephoned asking me to call him. I called
                    him at 11:30. His tone had changed, he said that I had asked for constructive
                    suggestions and he wished now to make it clear that my proposal of a so-called
                    escape clause for Catholics would not be satisfactory, that he could not accept
                    conscription for Irishmen. I said, “Do you mean that Orangemen cannot conscript
                    each other?” He evaded this point <pb facs="0246" n="238" xml:id="pg_238"/>
                    saying that public opinion in the South would not consent to it. I said that I
                    refuse to take any part in a controversy that raises the issue of partition at
                    this time and will so advise my Government. If you refuse any compromise that
                    offers a temporary avoidance of a conflict without prejudice to either party you
                    are taking a very dangerous course. I am concerned primarily for American
                    interests, secondarily for Irish interests, and thirdly for British interests as
                    they coincide with ours but in each case it is to the end of avoiding
                    precipitating a situation which may well become irremediable. I am deeply
                    disappointed that I cannot work with you except on these lines. We closed on a
                    note of tension. I felt that he had shifted his ground as is characteristic of
                    him when he felt an advantage offered.</p>
                <p>This morning Maffy, British representative, came to see me. He told me he thought
                    the revival of conscription came as the result of local conditions following the
                    Belfast air raids. Volunteers have not come forward for the needed local
                    services and manpower from Great Britain is lacking. He agreed that the
                    situation should be handled with regard to the American political situation, the
                    protection of the Irish opposition, and thirdly of the military needs in
                    Ulster.</p>
                <p>Later Mr. Cosgrave<note n="25" xml:id="d183fn25">William T. Cosgrave, leader of
                        Fine Gael.</note> called and asked if we could help. I read to him the same
                    digest of telegrams that I had sent the Prime Minister. He expressed
                    gratification and said he would accept the escape clause as a temporary way out,
                    but predicted that the Prime Minister would not, as he was looking for a
                    political issue. At this moment Mr. de Valera telephoned to say that he realized
                    that our talk last night had been unsatisfactory and would like to send me a
                    note. This has just arrived. It is temperate and conciliatory, but states that
                    for historic reasons his Government cannot accept less than the suspension of
                    conscription.</p>
                <p>I am writing him to the effect that I appreciate the friendly tone of his
                    communication, that without instructions I can make no commitments, that recent
                    information makes it appear that no decision has been taken in Westminster and
                    that if he makes a statement Monday indicating his position before the event and
                    calculated to excite anti-British feeling it will increase the difficulties of
                    my Government in case they feel their interests are concerned.</p>
                <p>I think a clash with this man is probably inevitable, but he should [not]<note
                        n="26" xml:id="d183fn26">Minister Gray inserted the word “not” on file copy
                        of this telegram on July 28, 1943.</note> be allowed to choose the issue and
                    the time.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gray</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
