<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Egypt ( (Kirk) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d291</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">291</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-09-09T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-09-09T03:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-09-09T03:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-09-09T03:00:00-05:00" n="291"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d291">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">883.5151/40: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Egypt</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-09-09T11:00:00+03:00"
                            >September 9, 1941—11 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received September 10—6:01 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1311. My 1306, September 8, 8 p.m. According to a British Embassy source, the
                    proclamation under reference is the result of informal representations recently
                    made by the British Embassy in conformity with instructions from London with the
                    immediate view to having the Egyptian Government ascertain the exact amount of
                    dollar funds held abroad by persons residing in Egypt. This source states that
                    at the time the representations were made, it was suggested that an endeavor
                    should be made also to ascertain the amount of all non-sterling holdings abroad
                    but that the proclamation was prepared and issued without further consultation
                    with the Embassy and before it was expected.</p>
                <p>The same source has stated that the ultimate aim of the proclamation possibly is
                    to oblige persons here holding dollar funds abroad to exchange them for Egyptian
                    or possibly British securities and that such action is necessitated owing to the
                    fact that the greatly increased demand for dollars in Egypt for the purchase of
                    American goods is causing a considerable drain upon the British exchequer
                    especially since Egypt now sells practically no goods to the United States. He
                    states further that although the Bank of England is endeavoring in various ways
                    to curtail dollar expenditures in Egypt and although the British desire that the
                    Egyptian Government establish an import licensing system, they are somewhat
                    reluctant for political reasons to insist thereon lest they should be further
                    criticized for interfering in internal affairs in Egypt. Nevertheless, he added,
                    such a system may prove necessary in the near future, particularly in view of
                    the large dollar expenditures now in Egypt for the purchase in the United States
                    of nonessential goods such as beer, toilet articles, and certain clothing as
                    silk stockings which can be sold at highly speculative prices and accordingly
                    have greatly increased the pressure for dollar credits on the part of local
                    merchants.</p>
                <p>In discussing this matter with the British Embassy it was pointed out that the
                    fact that the proclamation singles United States dollars <pb facs="0345" n="337"
                        xml:id="pg_337"/> out alone for declaration gives it the appearance at least
                    of a discriminatory measure.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kirk</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
