<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The British Embassy to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d42</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">42</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-01-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-01-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-01-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-01-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="42"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d42">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.34544/423½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In his letter of December 13th<note n="59" xml:id="d42fn59">Not printed.</note>
                    regarding the United States bases in Newfoundland, Bermuda and certain other
                    British possessions, the <pb facs="0062" n="54" xml:id="pg_54"/> Secretary of
                    State pointed out that the President was keenly desirous that all of the
                    negotiations in respect of the sites and leases for these bases should be
                    carried to a successful conclusion as soon as possible, and explained that with
                    that in view an informal committee composed of representatives from the
                    interested American Departments had been appointed to handle these negotiations
                    in Washington. It was suggested that it would facilitate the conduct of the
                    negotiations if some members of His Majesty’s Embassy were to confer with this
                    Committee. In a subsequent conversation between His Majesty’s Chargé
                        d’Affaires<note n="60" xml:id="d42fn60">Nevile M. Butler.</note> and Mr.
                    Dunn of the State Department, the latter explained that the United States
                    Government were of the opinion that the negotiations in connection with the
                    settlement of the terms of the final leases covering the bases should be held in
                    Washington. Mr. Dunn made it clear that the Administration felt that in present
                    circumstances it would not be practicable for American officials with the
                    necessary qualifications to be sent to London to conduct negotiations there.</p>
                <p>The substance of the Secretary of State’s letter and of Mr. Dunn’s statement was
                    at once communicated to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.<note n="61"
                        xml:id="d42fn61">Anthony Eden.</note> The latter has now replied,
                    emphasising that His Majesty’s Government for their part are equally anxious
                    that final agreement in regard to all matters connected with the bases should be
                    reached as soon as possible and that discussions in regard to the terms of the
                    final leases should be begun with the minimum delay. They are, however, most
                    anxious that these negotiations should be conducted in London. As Lord
                        Lothian<note n="62" xml:id="d42fn62">Former British Ambassador to the United
                        States; he died in Washington, December 12, 1940.</note> explained on
                    several occasions during the discussions leading up to the conclusion of the
                    agreement of September 2nd,<note n="63" xml:id="d42fn63">For exchange of notes
                        between the British Ambassador and the Secretary of State on September 2,
                        1940, see <ref target="frus1940v03#pg_73">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1940, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 73</ref> and <ref
                            target="frus1940v03#pg_74">74</ref>.</note> and as he stated in his
                    letter of October 14th to the Secretary of the Navy,<note n="64"
                        xml:id="d42fn64">Frank Knox.</note> His Majesty’s Government have
                    consistently held the view that for practical reasons these negotiations should
                    be held in London rather than in Washington. They are fully alive to the
                    difficulties to which Mr. Dunn referred in his conversation with Mr. Butler and
                    in the light of these remarks and of the expressed wish of the United States
                    Government that the discussions should take place in this country they have
                    given further careful consideration to the matter. They have, however,
                    reluctantly come to the conclusion that to hold the negotiations in Washington
                    would present the most formidable difficulties from the point of view of the
                    British authorities.</p>
                <p>In view of the complexity of the issues involved and of the number of separate
                    administrations concerned, it will be necessary for the <pb facs="0063" n="55"
                        xml:id="pg_55"/> British authorities during the discussions to have the
                    advice of representatives from a number of different departments, both civil and
                    military, of legal advisers, and of Colonial experts. A large interdepartmental
                    committee has in fact been sitting in London for some months past to consider
                    the administrative and other questions involved in the leases, and all the
                    necessary personnel is available there. It is, however, feared that it would be
                    quite impracticable for these persons to be spared to visit Washington in
                    present circumstances when so many demands are being made upon their time in
                    connection with the day-to-day conduct of the war.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, even if it were possible to send a delegation to Washington,
                    experience has already shown that the number of British Government Departments
                    concerned is so great that it would be inevitable that many of the points which
                    arose during the negotiations would have to be referred to London for further
                    consideration. As it will fall upon His Majesty’s Government to make the
                    detailed local arrangements so far as the Colonies are concerned, it seems only
                    appropriate that the discussions should take place in London where experts with
                    knowledge of the various territories are readily available.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, it is particularly desirable that Newfoundland and Bermuda and the
                    other colonies should be directly represented during the negotiations leading up
                    to the conclusion of the final leases. Appropriate arrangements to this effect
                    can be made without great difficulty if the negotiations are held in London, but
                    considerable complications would be caused if the discussions were to take place
                    in Washington.</p>
                <p>For the foregoing reasons, His Majesty’s Government feel convinced that an early
                    settlement of all matters connected with the bases would be greatly facilitated
                    if the necessary discussions were to be held in London. His Majesty’s Government
                    are ready to begin such discussions forthwith, and since they are no less
                    anxious than the United States Government that final agreement should be reached
                    with the minimum delay they trust that the United States Government will feel
                    able to arrange for the despatch of appropriate representatives to London in the
                    near future.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-01-03">3 January,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
