<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-10-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="461" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d461">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">891.001 P 15/220</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the
                                    Division of Near Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Murray</hi>)<note n="52a" xml:id="d461fn52a">Addressed to the
                                    Secretary of State, the Under Secretary of State (Welles), and
                                    the Assistant Secretary of State (Berle).</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-10-01">October 1,
                                        1941</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>I called on the Iranian Minister last Saturday afternoon to get his
                                reaction to the recent events in Iran leading to the abdication of
                                Reza Shah Pahlavi.</p>
                            <pb facs="0474" n="466" xml:id="pg_466"/>
                            <p>The Minister stated that, in his opinion, the British had committed a
                                great blunder in forcing the abdication of Reza Shah and that the
                                results of this blunder would soon come home to plague them. He said
                                he referred to the rearming of the native tribes of Iran. It had
                                taken Reza Shah twenty years to disarm effectively these tribes and
                                to start integrating them into the civilized life of the country.
                                Before they were disarmed, the tribes had rendered travel in Iran
                                precarious by reason of the pillaging, plundering and kidnapping
                                expeditions along the main routes of travel. (It may be recalled in
                                this connection that the Lurs captured three American consular
                                officers and held them for ransom in the mountains some years ago,
                                and only by a miracle and, in fact, inadvertently were they rescued
                                by the Iranian military.)</p>
                            <p>The name of Reza Shah, continued the Minister, had been a magic one
                                in Iran in preserving law and order and, whatever the temptation to
                                banditry, the tribal population had such a fear of the Shah that
                                they dared not move. The Minister claimed that, in subduing the
                                tribes, the Shah had not pursued a merciless policy of killing the
                                leaders but had brought several of them to Tehran and kept them
                                under surveillance in comfortable quarters.</p>
                            <p>Expressing the opinion that Iran had been thrown back forty years in
                                her latter day reforms and progress, the Minister said he believed
                                the British may have created a situation which would require a far
                                larger occupying force in the country than they had anticipated. If
                                this were the case, the British might, he said, use this argument
                                for any failure to evacuate the country at the termination of their
                                present hostilities with Germany.</p>
                            <p>Of interest in the above connection is the following comment made by
                                Mr. Dreyfus in the concluding paragraph of his telegram no. 171,
                                September 28, noon:</p>
                            <p>[Here follows concluding paragraph of telegram printed on <ref target="#pg_464">page 464</ref>.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Wallace Murray</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>