<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in Liberia ( (Walton))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d571</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">571</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-11-08T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-11-08T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="rec1XXkhQR86TB5ui" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85115918"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Medical services</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-11-08T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-11-08T18:00:00-05:00" n="571"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d571">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.79682/26: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in Liberia</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Walton</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-11-08T18:00:00-05:00"
                            >November 8, 1941—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>67. Your 100 [<hi rend="italic">101</hi>], November 1, 10 a.m. Recent
                    developments indicate that in addition to the commercial purposes for which the
                    Pan-American airport is intended, it may be necessary to use this landing field
                    as an alternative to Bathurst or Freetown in the ferrying of aircraft from the
                    United States to the Middle East. If the danger of an Axis attack appears
                    imminent as a result thereof, precautions would undoubtedly be taken to insure
                    the security of Liberia and the War Department might even desire to station
                    defensive forces and equipment in Liberian territory for that purpose. It may
                    also be desired eventually to use the Liberian airport as an intermediate point
                    in the transportation of American officials, mail and personnel between points
                    in Africa and Europe.</p>
                <p>While permission for these operations would in due course be requested of the
                    Liberian Government, it is believed that President Barclay should at this time
                    be informed of the above possibilities in the strictest confidence. You are
                    therefore authorized to bring these considerations to his attention, pointing
                    out that such developments would automatically obtain for Liberia the protection
                    of the United States Government during the course of the present war, the
                    alternative to which might be a threat to the independence and integrity of
                    Liberia.</p>
                <p>In view of the interest which the War Department has in the speedy construction
                    of the airport, it seems highly desirable to bring the present negotiations for
                    the Pan-American lease to an early conclusion. Mr. Firestone has described the
                    desire of the Liberian Government to obtain compensation for the lease, as well
                    as the inability of Pan-American to consider rental payments because of the
                    precedent which this would set in other cases. It appears that Pan American has
                    offered as partial compensation to provide a local amphibian airplane service in
                    Liberia for passengers and mail over a certain period of years, with payments of
                    $2,000 per annum for the remaining term of the contract if the venture proves
                    unprofitable and is withdrawn. The Department believes that such a service would
                    result in an important advantage for Liberia by knitting the country together in
                    accordance with modern methods of transportation, facilitating trips of Liberian
                    officials and making medical services quickly available in emergencies. You are
                    requested to stress the benefits of this proposal and to urge its acceptance
                    without the conditions reported to be attached by President Barclay such as free
                    mail carriage and guarantee of a minimum customs revenue for Pan American
                    supplies, neither of which suggestions appears to be practicable.</p>
                <pb facs="0550" n="542" xml:id="pg_542"/>
                <p>You may also state to President Barclay that the Department is giving
                    consideration to means by which additional compensation may be made available to
                    Liberia, possibly in the furnishing of assistance to the country’s road building
                    program. Further details in this connection will be sent to you shortly, but in
                    the meanwhile you should express the earnest hope of this Government that the
                    lease negotiations will soon be concluded.</p>
                <p>The Department is again requesting Firestone to have its representative in
                    Liberia keep in close touch with you. All developments should be reported by the
                    Legation by telegraph.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
