<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-04-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-04-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="619" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d619">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">867N.01/1741</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under
                                    Secretary of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-04-21">April 21,
                                    1941</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Mr. Butler of the British Embassy called on me this afternoon at the
                                request of Lord Halifax.<note n="10" xml:id="d619fn10">The
                                    Ambassador had called on the Secretary of State on April 19
                                    regarding this pro-Jewish activity and had been told that it
                                    would be difficult to deal with the matter.</note></p>
                            <p>Mr. Butler first spoke of the great concern occasioned the Embassy by
                                the announcement of the dinner which was to be held in Washington on
                                April 30 under the aegis of Senator Wagner and some other equally
                                prominent Senators and of Mr. William Green of the American
                                Federation of Labor at which Doctor Weizmann is due to speak in
                                behalf of the Zionist movement in Palestine. The British Embassy
                                feels that German propaganda is now directed in the Arab world
                                towards making it appear that the British Government is completely
                                under the domination of the United States and that the United States
                                would force Great Britain at the end of the war, if Great Britain is
                                victorious, to open up all of Palestine to Jewish resettlement. The
                                British Government believes that this is an exceedingly dangerous
                                form of propaganda and that if speeches are now made in the United
                                States by prominent persons high in the Government advocating the
                                immediate opening up of Palestine to the Jewish resettlement
                                planners in the event of a British victory, very great unrest will
                                be created in the Arab world, particularly in Iraq, where a highly
                                critical situation already exists. The British Government urged that
                                the Executive branch of this Government do what it could to make
                                this situation clear to the sponsors of the dinner.</p>
                            <p>I said that I would be very glad to look into the matter and that I
                                would let Mr. Butler know in the immediate future what steps, if
                                any, could be taken in that direction.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps">elles</hi>]</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>