<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Turkey ( (MacMurray) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d913</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">913</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-04-08T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-04-08T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec3b4QX8ohh76TF3" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88004886"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Journalist</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec332ed97b3bcc404" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="middle-east-and-north-african-relations" subject="near-and-middle-east">Near and Middle East</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-04-08T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-04-08T11:00:00-05:00" n="913"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d913">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/9783: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Turkey</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ankara</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-04-08T19:00:00+03:00"
                            >April 8, 1941—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received April 10—4:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>92. [For] Secretary and Under Secretary. A week ago I received visit from Rauf
                    Bey (former Prime Minister) who, while keeping politically inconspicuous, is
                    intimate personal adviser of President Ismet and whom I am disposed to believe
                    President is using as informal medium for communicating his ideas through us to
                    the British. He outlined to me as though they were his own private views
                    following appreciation of situation as regards Turkey’s attitude towards war:
                    This Government has committed itself wholeheartedly to the British cause; even
                    if there were doubt as to its wisdom that decision is nevertheless irrevocable.
                    It is therefore prepared to do whatever it usefully can do to make that cause
                    prevail. With utterly inadequate equipment now at its disposal, however, it
                    could not hope to carry out successful operation beyond Turkish borders either
                    in Bulgaria or in Greek Thrace. With that possibility excluded Rauf feels this
                    country’s best contribution to cause would be to remain on guard at its own
                    borders to perform function that he, as old naval man describes (by somewhat
                    loose analogy) as that of fleet in being. He said that British had for a long
                    time misunderstood that viewpoint; they and French had made to Turks promises of
                    all sorts of material assistance that had in fact proved impossible for most
                    part to fulfill, but had gone on thinking that Turks could, at suitable moment,
                    be projected into action in support of whatever plans might have been devised
                    for them. Implication of this attitude that Turks particularly resented was that
                    it seemed to indicate, on the part of British, distrust of their loyalty and
                    desire to get them involved, if only for sake of committing them. This had led
                    to certain degree of underlying distrust and shadow boxing until arrival of Eden
                    and Dill at end of February. That gave opportunity for completely frank exchange
                    of views which, although perhaps disappointing to British in that it made clear
                    limitations upon possibilities of active Turkish military support, was
                    nevertheless very satisfactory <pb facs="0849" n="841" xml:id="pg_841"/> to them
                    in that it dispelled previous doubts and enabled them to assess definitely
                    Turkey’s military potentialities and agree upon a clean-cut allocation to her of
                    a fixed, though relatively passive, role in any operations that might be
                    undertaken in Balkan area.</p>
                <p>Rauf said he came to me just for sake of talking out with a friend his own
                    apprehensions that Yugoslavia’s abrupt turning against Axis which of course
                    created new political situation might be taken by British as occasion for
                    reopening military understanding with Turkey reached during Eden’s visit, and
                    that they might again try to push Turkey into attempting role which would
                    involve defeat of Turkish Army, ruin of this country, and destruction of only
                    bulwark against German invasion and domination of Near and Middle East.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>When I saw Foreign Minister<note n="49" xml:id="d913fn49">Sükrü
                            Saraçoğlu.</note> next day he was somewhat reserved about developments,
                        but nevertheless, more categorical than he has ever been with me in stating
                        that Turkish Army is not prepared for offensive action and must of necessity
                        confine itself to purely defensive role. He insisted this country was
                        already doing its part by containing on Thracian frontier 5 divisions or so
                        of Bulgarians and (further back from boundary) perhaps as many as 10 German.
                        I asked if there were any way in which Turkey and Yugoslavia could
                        collaborate for mutual support. He answered only by pointing on map to
                        Macedonia and asking rhetorical question whether Turks here could really
                        help there. Saying that I quite understood that Turks might not think it
                        good strategy to enter vacuum which Greeks and British seemed to have
                        decided to create in Greece and Thrace I inquired whether his Government
                        contemplated possibility of putting into operation its conditional alliance
                        with Great Britain making air and naval bases available to British forces
                        and entering upon what would indubitably be state of war with Germany. He
                        replied negatively and (as I think with entire honesty) that his Government
                        did not think that in immediate circumstances that would be helpful to
                        cause.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>In even more than usually outspoken talks with British colleague I have
                        discussed these impressions and am disposed to feel that he and the various
                        British missions that have actually been here are fully cognizant of
                        situation of Turkish Army and in general sympathetic with military policy
                        based thereon. (Whereas London authorities have suggested possibility of
                        persuading Turks to send a few divisions to Greece as symbol of unity with
                        British, Greeks and Yugoslavs, British diplomatic and military
                        representatives here have not urged this directly because conscious that it
                        might dangerously arouse Turkish obstinacy against any appearance of
                        pressure but have confined themselves to intimations that Turks might be
                        well advised in their own interest to do something of the sort.)</item>
                    <pb facs="0850" n="842" xml:id="pg_842"/>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I now understand from him, however, that since German attack on Yugoslavia
                        and Greece he feels that Turks are showing tendency to translate that policy
                        of merely defensive military action into one of political aloofness that
                        balks even at giving any statement of continuing moral solidarity.
                        Immediately on receipt of news of German and Italian declarations he saw
                        Foreign Minister to ask his views and received intimation that nothing in
                        Turkey’s attitude had been changed thereby; he recalled Minister’s assurance
                        to him (my 17, January 24) that this Government would regard attack upon
                        Saloniki from any quarter as <hi rend="italic">casus belli</hi> and was
                        amazed to find Minister (for first time in his experience with him) evasive
                        to the point of professing not to recollect such assurance and not even
                        prepared to declare that such attack would be “mortal danger” to Turkey (see
                        my 80, March 25). Minister appears to have been equally noncommittal and
                        aloof with Greek and Yugoslav Ambassadors. All three seem to be seriously
                        perturbed lest Turkey’s passivity create impression of her having
                        dissociated herself from what she herself has hitherto urged as common
                        cause.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>At Hugessen’s instance I conveyed today to Rauf as my personal observation
                        impression that British still adhere to Eden’s assurance that as regards
                        military action they have nothing to ask of Turkey but that they (as well as
                        other friendly observers including American journalist) seem to sense on the
                        part of officials and inspired press sudden chill in Turkey’s sympathy
                        towards her allies; and I contrasted this Government’s failure to give even
                        confidential word of reassurance to Ambassadors of its allies at this new
                        crisis with the expressions of sympathy and helpfulness which oh this and
                        previous occasions our own Government has promptly and spontaneously offered
                        to Balkan countries although under no like obligations to them. He remarked
                        that criticism was destructive and asked what constructive step could be
                        suggested. Indicating I did not feel it was for me to suggest anything more
                        concrete I hoped that Turkish Government was bearing in mind great
                        psychological danger of maintaining politically negative attitude which
                        would create among her friends impression of indifference or lukewarmness.
                        He said that if British had any feeling that Turkey was not doing her full
                        part in that respect Hugessen should see President and thresh matter out
                        with him before such difference of opinion could develop into mutual
                        suspicion. I have passed on this suggestion.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>By way of summary statement of situation as I conceive it from this
                        viewpoint I submit following: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Turkey is desperately anxious to avoid hostilities but will fight
                                (perhaps inefficiently but courageously and doggedly) if
                                attacked.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>If she fights her military effort will not be directed (like
                                Poland’s) towards do or die defense of any particular line or
                                holding of any city.… I think they have made up their minds to
                                possibility <pb facs="0851" n="843" xml:id="pg_843"/> that their
                                Cakmak line (at frontier with Bulgaria) might either be broken by
                                frontal attack or turned from Greek Thrace that they would have to
                                fall back to so-called Catalca line and might then have to retire to
                                positions dominating Bosphorus and Dardanelles and perhaps have to
                                retreat into Anatolia and carry on war of harassment and
                                attrition.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>This situation might have been different (as possibly it may still
                                be) in event of fulfillment British promises of material assistance.
                                Turks accept without resentment fact that French could do nothing
                                and British only part of what they had undertaken to do in equipping
                                Turkish Army; but as case stands they have had to base plans upon
                                fact that in spite of admirable combative spirit their army must
                                measure and use its strength according to its possibilities in terms
                                of modern warfare and that they must not let themselves be persuaded
                                into attempting more than they can really do.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>For reasons substantially different from what our more sophisticated
                        Turkish friends expound I wholeheartedly agree with their conclusion that in
                        interest of cause it would be far wiser to let them stay neutral until
                        defensive part is forced upon them.…</item>
                </list>
                <p>Repeated to Athens.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">MacMurray</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
