<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-09-16T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-09-16T09:00:00-05:00" n="975" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d975">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">867.24/176: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Turkey</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Ankara</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-09-16T17:00:00+03:00">September 16, 1941—5
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received September 17—1:15 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>342. Your 141, August 15. Although I have taken several occasions to
                                mention to him Lease-Lend shipments to Turkey made or contemplated
                                as outlined in your 110, June 28, Minister for Foreign Affairs has
                                hitherto appeared uninterested and in fact politely incredulous.
                                Apparently in consequence of arrival here few days ago of 50
                                howitzers, he yesterday informed me that our generous assistance had
                                been matter of most [apparent omission] full comment among members
                                of Cabinet at their last meeting; and he asked me to repeat while he
                                took notes principal items specified in your telegram, and earnestly
                                requested more up-to-date list as soon as available. He inquired up
                                to what value Turkey might expect to receive such materials; and I
                                explained that I understood question was one not of any fixed limit
                                but of priorities among those requiring aid; and that although its
                                application presented some practical difficulties general principle
                                adopted was that Turkey should enjoy along with American Republics
                                priority next after those countries actually fighting. He was
                                profuse in expressions of gratitude.</p>
                            <p>2. Both at beginning and at end of this discussion he remarked
                                solemnly and oracularly that nobody can foresee what may develop
                                next spring and that Turkey must in meanwhile build up modernized
                                army.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">MacMurray</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>