<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>244. Letter From Nineteen Senators to President Carter</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v33</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d244</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">244</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-12-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="reccOg5QXDp3EJxaF" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general">SALT II</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122"
                        lcsh-match="exact">National security interests</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recr08QgEMEm1Bk04" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85089168"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">MX missile</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recAynYh8uzxYGQRH" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009928"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Strategic weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recvy4qghNg7RFWmN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Theater nuclear forces</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ground forces</term>
                    <term ref="recyvYvKBWCiz1E8g" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026326"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil defense</term>
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048697"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">High seas</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military balance</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113036"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Research and development</term>
                    <term ref="recyQwssZrUcxu4Pw" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recJgxebpUYqWj25O" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Defense spending</term>
                    <term ref="recpJMerwIQpQmCmI" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85137213"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Treaty ratification</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="recqaxqBsfTYVWHfR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Ground-launched cruise missiles</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="recv6AMbtMSgUYM1C" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military buildup</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-policy" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-policy"
                        >national security strategy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-12-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="244"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d244">
                <head>244. Letter From Nineteen Senators to President <persName corresp="#p_CJ_2"
                        >Carter</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d244fn1">Source: Carter Library, Office of
                        Congressional Liaison, Beckel, SALT II, Box 232, SALT II: Sen. Sam Nunn,
                        4/30/79–12/17/79. No classification marking. The letter was signed by the
                        following Senators: Sam Nunn (D–GA), John W. Warner (R–VA), Lawton Chiles
                        (D–FL), Henry Bellmon (R–OK), John Danforth (R–MO), Rudy Boschwitz (R–MN),
                        Harrison Schmitt (R–NM), Pete Domenici (R–NM), Edward Zorinksy (R–NE), John
                        Heinz (R–PA), Daniel Boren (D–OK), Richard Schweiker (R–PA), Lloyd Bentsen
                        (D–TX), S.I. Hayakawa (R–CA), J.J. Exon (D–NE), Larry Pressler (R–SD),
                        Dennis DeConcini (D–AZ), David Durenberger (R–MN), and Alan Simpson
                        (R–WY).</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1979-12-17">December 17, 1979</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Mr. President:</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>For some months now the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, the Armed Services
                    Committee, and the Intelligence Committee have been carefully examining the SALT
                    II agreement to determine if it meets our nation’s national security interests.
                    Public hearings on the Treaty have been accompanied by numerous private meetings
                    among Senators of both parties, Administration officials, and other individuals
                    possessing experience and expertise in arms control and related matters.</p>
                <p>From the hearings and from those individual meetings, a number of important
                    issues have emerged regarding both the proposed SALT II Treaty and the state of
                    our nation’s defense posture.</p>
                <p>With respect to the Treaty, we as individual Senators are deeply concerned over
                    certain provisions of, and omissions from, the Treaty. We hope that during the
                    course of Senate deliberations our concerns can be met. We are concerned over
                    the Protocol terms and their precedential effect. We are also concerned over the
                    Treaty provisions relating to “heavy” missiles, verification, limitations on
                    potential basing modes for the MX missile, the threat posed to the United States
                    by the Backfire and other Soviet weapons not limited by the Treaty, and other
                    issues. We are hopeful that these problem areas can be resolved in a manner that
                    strengthens the <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> Treaty and improves the
                        <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> process.</p>
                <p>In addition to these Treaty issues, we are also concerned over the ongoing
                    slippage in America’s comparative military position, awareness of which has been
                    accentuated by the Senate’s deliberations on <gloss target="#t_SALT_1"
                        >SALT</gloss> and by recent international events. In the last decade, the
                    Soviet Union has attained at the very least essential equivalence in strategic
                    weapons, has eliminated <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>’s longstanding
                    superiority in theater nuclear forces, and has expanded an already preponderant
                    advantage in ground forces and civil defense capability. Furthermore, the
                    Soviets are reducing our qualitative edge in tactical air forces and have <pb
                        facs="0998" n="969" xml:id="pg_969"/> constructed a navy that, for the first
                    time in modern history, threatens traditional Western supremacy on the high
                    seas. These trends have been accompanied by a growing Soviet and
                    Soviet-sponsored threat to the West’s sources of energy and raw materials.</p>
                <p>The erosion that has taken place in the East-West military balance can be
                    principally attributed to the failure of the U.S. and our Allies to compete
                    effectively with Moscow in the military arena in the past 15 years. While
                    diverting substantial conventional forces to the conflict in Southeast Asia in
                    the 1960’s and early 1970’s, we remained, in the category of nuclear arms,
                    basically content to live off of capital invested in the 1950’s and early
                    1960’s. In so doing, we provided the Soviet Union the opportunity to steal a
                    massive military march on the West. That the Soviets took advantage of that
                    opportunity is no longer questioned.</p>
                <p>During the period 1970–1978, the Soviet Union invested a total of $104 billion
                    more than the United States in military equipment and facilities, and $40
                    billion more in research and development. According to the <gloss
                        target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>, the Soviet Union is still militarily
                    outspending the United States overall by at least 40 percent annually; in the
                    critical categories of investment in weapons procurement and research and
                    development, they are outspending us by a 2:1 ratio.</p>
                <p>We do not believe that the SALT II agreement currently before the Senate can be
                    held directly responsible for this erosion in America’s military position.
                    However, during the seven years that the agreement was in negotiation, the hopes
                    for significant arms control did influence our force planning and the support
                    for defense initiatives. Thus, efforts which may have been needed to counter the
                    mounting Soviet threat were delayed, curtailed, or even abandoned. Ratification
                    of a SALT II Treaty will not reverse trends in the military balance adverse to
                    the United States.</p>
                <p>We applaud the statements by both you and Secretary of Defense <persName
                        corresp="#p_BH_2">Harold Brown</persName> relating to the Five-Year Defense
                        Program.<note n="2" xml:id="d244fn2">Apparent reference to <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJ_2">Carter</persName>’s December 12 remarks to the members
                        of the Business Council on U.S. defense spending. The text is in <hi
                            rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_CJ_2"
                                >Carter</persName>, 1979</hi>, Book II, pp. 2232–2237.</note> We
                    reserve the right to examine the submittal in detail, but it does represent a
                    positive step in acknowledging the Soviet buildup and in committing to real
                    increases in defense spending and capability.</p>
                <p>We have ourselves met on several occasions to discuss those considerations that
                    will be foremost on our minds as the Senate approaches its full floor debate on
                    the Treaty. All of us are agreed that the Treaty issues mentioned above are
                    important and that the manner in which they are resolved will influence our
                    final decision on Treaty ratification.</p>
                <pb facs="0999" n="970" xml:id="pg_970"/>
                <p>We are also agreed that the SALT II Treaty cannot be judged in a vacuum. In our
                    view, the Treaty represents but one facet of a much broader East-West
                    relationship that encompasses political and economic, as well as military
                    dimensions. Our final judgment on the Treaty will therefore not be confined
                    solely to the merits or flaws of the Treaty alone. We regard the following
                    considerations as crucial:</p>
                <p>1. The absence of definitive Administration proposals designed to narrow the
                    strategic nuclear window of vulnerability which will occur during the early and
                    mid-1980’s.</p>
                <p>2. The longstanding adverse trends in our own defense posture, and the extent to
                    which the Administration’s proposed Fiscal 1981 Defense Budget and Five-Year
                    Defense Plan establishes a firm foundation for reversing those trends, in both
                    conventional and nuclear forces. We believe that an objective review must be
                    made in the immediate future as to our manpower procurement problems.</p>
                <p>3. The plans and programs envisioned by the Administration to improve our
                    intelligence capabilities, with particular emphasis on investment in
                    high-technology collection systems and professional analytic resources. The need
                    is also apparent to reconstitute our sensitive operational intelligence
                    capabilities.</p>
                <p>4. The impact of the SALT II Treaty on our ability in concert with our <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> allies, to modernize European-based nuclear
                    and conventional forces. We are particularly interested in the Administration
                    plans as to the deployment date for ground-launched cruise missiles.</p>
                <p>5. The global military and political climate, particularly the increasingly
                    aggressive activities in the Third World of the Soviet Union and its proxies. We
                    are interested in the Administration plans to deter and counter such behavior
                    over the coming decade. We regard such behavior as inconsistent with the
                    underlying spirit of the <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> process.</p>
                <p>6. The effect of the Treaty on long-term prospects for meaningful arms control,
                    with respect not only to the attainment in SALT III of “deep cuts” in existing
                    levels of strategic armaments, but also to significant progress in our other
                    arms control efforts such as the negotiations on Mutual and Balanced Force
                    Reductions in Europe. The <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> process so far
                    has failed to restrain the momentum of the Soviet Union’s ongoing military
                    buildup.</p>
                <p>We believe that the Salt II debate will provide a unique opportunity not only to
                    examine the Treaty itself, but also to seek a bipartisan consensus on long-range
                    national security strategy and arms control.</p>
                <p>Further, we attach great value to the pursuit of arms control, provided it
                    enhances our nation’s security. Should circumstances arise in which there are
                    insufficient votes either to strengthen or to ratify the Treaty, we believe that
                    serious consideration should be given to post<pb facs="1000" n="971"
                        xml:id="pg_971"/>ponement. In view of the unforeseen delays in the Senate
                    debate, persistent worldwide tensions, and national political considerations,
                    any such postponement should be effective through the Presidential and
                    Senatorial elections of 1980. As we have indicated, we regard an effective
                        <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> process as being in our nation’s
                    interest.</p>
                <p>Each of the undersigned, of course, gives different weight to these individual
                    items but this letter expresses our general concerns. Because of our concerns,
                    largely covered by this letter, we are uncommitted as to how we will cast our
                    votes on the SALT II Treaty and proposed changes.</p>
                <p>We look forward to discussing these issues in detail with you and members of your
                    Administration.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,<note n="3" xml:id="d244fn3">The letter is signed by all 19 Senators.
                            <persName corresp="#p_CJ_2">Carter</persName> replied in December 19
                        letters to each of the Senators, noting his “desire to achieve a bipartisan
                        consensus on these issues of long-range national security strategy and arms
                        control.” See <hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_CJ_2"
                                >Carter</persName>, 1979,</hi> Book II, pp. 2256–2257.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
