<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-08-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-08-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="35" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d35">
                    <head>35. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_HWG_1">William Hyland</persName>
                        of the National Security Council Staff to <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Helmut
                            Sonnenfeldt</persName> of the National Security Council Staff<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d35fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon
                            Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box
                            889, <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>, SALT TWO–I–Geneva, April
                            1973. Secret; Sensitive. The memorandum was not initialed by <persName corresp="#p_HWG_1">Hyland</persName>. An attached note indicates it
                            was sent to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> as message
                                <gloss target="#t_Tohak_1">Tohak</gloss> 321, August
                        29.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-08-29">August 29,
                            1973</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item><gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> Reexamined</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">The Soviet Perspective</p>
                    <p>It is important to bear in mind that the present stage of <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> coincides with a transitional period in
                        Soviet strategic deployments. In effect, <hi rend="italic">a decade of
                            Soviet force build-up ended with the completion of the last <gloss target="#t_SS9_1">SS–9</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SS11_1">SS–11</gloss> silos,</hi> and the establishment of a ceiling on
                        both land and sea-based ballistic missiles.</p>
                    <pb facs="0141" n="112" xml:id="pg_112"/>
                    <p>For at least 5–7 years:</p>
                    <p>—The main backbone of the Soviet force will be about 1300 liquid propellant
                        ICBMs, equipped primarily with single warheads and with a very limited hard
                        target capability.</p>
                    <p>—The Soviet <gloss target="#t_SLBM_1">SLBM</gloss> force will be about
                        one-half Y–Class, with the limited range SS–N–6 and about one-half with the
                        extended range <gloss target="#t_SSN8_1">SS–N–8</gloss> with little <gloss target="#t_MIRV_1">MIRV</gloss> capability; the last of the 62
                        submarines permitted will become operational about 1978.</p>
                    <p>—The Soviets have not chosen to produce a new heavy bomber; their force of
                        about 140 will become more or less obsolete. The Soviet force is a duad for
                        all practical strategic purposes.</p>
                    <p>For public policy purposes, the Soviets claim that “parity” has been
                        achieved, but in important areas of technology and in an overall strategic
                        posture, the Soviets suffer from inferiority.</p>
                    <p>There is every chance that they can overcome their technical inferiorities
                        and even achieve certain strategic advantages, particularly in the threat
                        against our land-based missiles and bombers. This effort is now in its
                        initial stage and its relationship to <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>
                        is a key variable.</p>
                    <p>Having come this far since the Cuban missile debacle, and having achieved the
                        plateau from which important advantages can now be reached, it is almost
                        certain that the Soviets will not see <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>
                        as a means to freeze the status quo, or to bargain away their opportunities.
                        Given the record of obsession with “equality,” and their persistence in
                        defining the global balance to include all of our striking forces, the
                        Soviets are going to insist that their forces can in no way be
                        “inferior.”</p>
                    <p>This means that they must be survivable—which means new, hardened silos; they
                        must be more sophisticated than the first and second generation of ICBMs and
                        SLBMs—which means more accurate; they must give the General Staff planners a
                        greater degree of flexibility in strategic options—which means MIRVs.</p>
                    <p>In short, there is very little chance that we can use <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> to head off or drastically limit the
                        next phase of Soviet strategic development.</p>
                    <p>Does <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>, then, have any strategic value,
                        or is it to be pure politics?</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital"><gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>
                        Alternatives</p>
                    <p>The answer is that <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> still has value as
                        a means of stabilizing the relationship with the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, provided that we can work out an understanding about the
                        pace of change in the next decade.</p>
                    <p>Both sides are contemplating major changes in their strategic arsenals—the
                            <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> with the Trident and <gloss target="#t_B1_1">B–1</gloss> and perhaps an improved <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>, and the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> with a new family of ICBMs and probably yet one more
                        version of an <gloss target="#t_SLBM_1">SLBM</gloss>. If these systems are
                        brought into operation at <pb facs="0142" n="113" xml:id="pg_113"/> crash
                        speeds and publicly justified as compensation for threats from the other
                        side, then the impact will be unsettling politically and strategically. The
                            <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> agreement will eventually come
                        under attack, as it is now in some parts of the government. The chances for
                        a viable <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> agreement will be
                        reduced.</p>
                    <p>There is reason to believe that the Soviets, while not wanting to sacrifice
                        major programs, are willing to negotiate about how each side makes changes.
                        In the original <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> principles, the
                        Soviets proposed the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> would “exercise mutual restraint with
                        regard to new programs of armaments . . .” You will recall that we redrafted
                        this to include both armaments that would be limited (ICBMs, etc.) and those
                        not limited (<gloss target="#t_FBS_1">FBS</gloss>). The Soviets accepted
                        this provision, but we dropped it.<note n="2" xml:id="d35fn2">See <ref target="#d21fn3">footnote 3, Document 21</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>The point is that there has been some expression of Soviet interest in
                        “restraint” and this could be the genesis of the Trident–SS 16/17/18
                        discussion.</p>
                    <p>The testing of new ICBMs is being pressed on all fronts, but some
                        intelligence suggests that the deployment of the <gloss target="#t_SS18_1">SS–18</gloss>, for example, may follow the pattern established in the
                        build-up of the <gloss target="#t_SS9_1">SS–9</gloss>. Thus, we have
                        intelligence that through 1975 production calls for 215 missile/containers
                        for the <gloss target="#t_SS18_1">SS–18</gloss>; some percentage of these
                        are used for testing. Since we know that the target for 1974 and 1975 is 50
                        per year, a retrofitting program of about 40–45 would be plausible. Allowing
                        about an 18 month period for silo retrofitting, beginning early next year,
                        the full program would be completed in about 7 years or more.</p>
                    <p>In short, the <gloss target="#t_SS18_1">SS–18</gloss> would be fully
                        operational about the end of 1981. This is about the pace of the <gloss target="#t_SS9_1">SS–9</gloss> deployment. Similarly, if the <gloss target="#t_SS17_1">SS–17</gloss> or 19 replaces the <gloss target="#t_SS11_1">SS–11</gloss>, and the pace of the <gloss target="#t_SS11_1">SS–11</gloss> deployment is followed, then we are
                        also dealing with about an 8 year period of about 100 missiles per year.</p>
                    <p>The Soviets could plan to establish their new <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> force by around 1981–82. The purpose of <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> would be to stretch this period by as
                        many years as possible.</p>
                    <p><gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> could become a framework in which each
                        side would proceed with its modernization but at an agreed pace. In effect
                        we would buy time, time which we need to sort out our own response to the
                        basic question of force survivability. We would postpone or defer the
                        maximum threat to our land-based force by X years through an agreement in
                        which each side will deploy only so many new ICBMs or SLBMs each year.</p>
                    <pb facs="0143" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/>
                    <p>During this period the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> could and should
                        decide whether to adopt the blue water option of shifting to sea or to
                        procure a mobile <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> or both. We could
                        establish in <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> the schedule for Trident
                        and for the <gloss target="#t_B1_1">B–1</gloss>, along with a schedule for
                        the <gloss target="#t_SS18_1">SS–18</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_SS17_1">SS–17</gloss>/19. Verification would be facilitated
                        by the fact that the Soviets would be permitted to reconstruct their older
                        silos for the new missiles.</p>
                    <p>For the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> there would be the advantage that
                            <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> would be predicated on the advent
                        of our new systems. Thus Congress would be more or less obligated to accept
                        them in the name of strategic stability. Yet the “arms race” would be
                        greatly elongated, the changes in strategic arsenals could be accommodated
                        since each side could gradually adjust its posture.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">How Would <gloss target="#t_MIRV_1">MIRV</gloss>
                        Limits Fit In?</p>
                    <p>Perhaps the simplest approach would be to allow MIRVing and put the effort on
                        controlling the deployments. Since the Soviets are certainly not going to
                        hold their testing while we negotiate, denying MIRVs will become almost
                        academic. In fact, if the approach of a slowdown is adopted, it may be in
                        our interest to permit a free hand in developing the newer <gloss target="#t_SS17_1">SS–17</gloss>/18 systems as the <gloss target="#t_MIRV_1">MIRV</gloss> carrier. In this way, we reduce any
                        incentive to transfer <gloss target="#t_MIRV_1">MIRV</gloss> from <gloss target="#t_SS17_1">SS–17</gloss>s and 18s to <gloss target="#t_SS11_1">SS–11</gloss>s and 9s. The Soviets can bring up their new <gloss target="#t_MIRV_1">MIRV</gloss> force, but at a pace that is agreed
                        through limits on the number of silos retrofitted.</p>
                    <p>Obviously, a tight constraint on <gloss target="#t_MIRV_1">MIRV</gloss> would
                        be preferable to defer a threat to Minuteman, but, on balance, it is
                        probably utopian to expect the Soviets to abandon a major area of strategic
                        technology. Our strategy, as suggested in this memorandum, should be to
                        accept the inevitability of Soviet strategic “equality” and to concentrate
                        on codifying through <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> those <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> programs that will offset the Soviet
                        technological growth, and thereby make <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> politically dependent on their adoption in this
                        country.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">The Outline of an Agreement</p>
                    <p>1. <hi rend="italic">New</hi>
                        <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> silo construction would be frozen as
                        in the Interim Agreement.</p>
                    <p>2. Technology for Soviet ICBMs would be frozen at present models; the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> could develop the <gloss target="#t_SS17_1">SS–17</gloss>, 18 or 19, with a defined number of
                        RVs.</p>
                    <p>3. The retrofitting of silos would be set at, say, 100 in an <hi rend="italic">18 month</hi> period, i.e., no more than 100 would be torn
                        down and reconstructed, and of this total no more than, say, 30 <gloss target="#t_SS9_1">SS–9</gloss> type silos.</p>
                    <p>4. Mobile ICBMs would be permitted up to some agreed number, say 200,
                        provided that fixed ICBMs were dismantled one for one.</p>
                    <pb facs="0144" n="115" xml:id="pg_115"/>
                    <p>5. The Soviets could complete their <gloss target="#t_SLBM_1">SLBM</gloss>
                        build-up as in the Interim Agreement; at that point, however, modernization
                        of SLBMs would then proceed according to an agreed schedule; this schedule
                        would apply to Trident except that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                        would have up to 740 SLBMs to accommodate ten 24-tube boats if
                        necessary.</p>
                    <p>6. Bombers would be frozen at present levels; an agreed schedule for the
                            <gloss target="#t_B1_1">B–1</gloss> would be negotiated.</p>
                    <p>7. Compensation for <gloss target="#t_FBS_1">FBS</gloss> would be in the
                        Soviet throw weight and numerical advantages.</p>
                    <p>The net result would be something along the following lines:</p>
                    <p>—The Soviets would probably decide to deploy about 200 SS–16 mobiles, perhaps
                        tearing down 60 SS–13 silos and 140 <gloss target="#t_SS11_1">SS–11</gloss>s.</p>
                    <p>—They would then have a force of about 1200 fixed ICBMs.</p>
                    <p>—Starting in 1974 they could modernize this force; if the agreement allowed
                        100 per 18 months, they could overhaul one-half of their force by 1983; if
                        they abided by a 30 silo limit on heavy <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> launchers for every 18 months, it would take 15 years to
                        replace the <gloss target="#t_SS9_1">SS–9</gloss> force. (Probably they
                        would seek a faster pace, say 100–150 a year for all ICBMs. This would still
                        require 8–12 years.)</p>
                    <p>—If the <gloss target="#t_SLBM_1">SLBM</gloss> replacement rate were, say,
                        three submarines per year beginning in 1979, then it would take until 1989
                        to modernize the Y Class with <gloss target="#t_SSN8_1">SS–N–8</gloss> or a
                        follow-on missile.</p>
                    <p>—By the time the Soviets have a fully MIRVed force, the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> could complete the changeover to Trident,
                            <gloss target="#t_B1_1">B–1</gloss> and/or mobiles.</p>
                    <p>In sum, neither side could have an expectation of being able to launch, or to
                        be threatened by a disarming strike, at least not before 1983. The impact of
                        such an arrangement should give a major impetus to “stability” and
                        “restraint.”</p>
                    <p>This could be the kind of protracted process that the Soviets might accept.
                        It would be “equal”, but not require them to abandon their projected
                        programs.</p>
                    <p>It is in the nature of a fallback, from the present course of limiting <gloss target="#t_MIRV_1">MIRV</gloss>. It assumes that this effort will fail,
                        in that no significant limits will be negotiable. It meets some of the
                            <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss> concerns about flexibility of force
                        planning, yet includes sufficient “arms control” to satisfy others. Above
                        all, it builds into an agreement with the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> the right (and obligation) to proceed with modernization
                        of the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> strategic force and puts the worst
                        case “threats” far into the future.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>