<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-12-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-12-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="310" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d310">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">793.003/12–2642</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Chief of the
                            Division of Far Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Atcheson</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-12-26">December 26, 1942</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr. Liu Chieh telephoned me at noon and stated that a telegram had been
                        received from the Chinese Foreign Office in which the Foreign Office
                        requested that we revert to the preamble which we had suggested in the
                        original draft of the treaty handed to the Chinese on October 24. He stated
                        that he would come to the Department to discuss the matter with me. Before
                        his arrival I consulted with Mr. Hornbeck and it was decided that I should
                        hand to Mr. Liu a counter-suggestion drafted by Mr. Hornbeck, copy attached,
                        as a basis for discussion.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Liu arrived at 1:00 p.m. He said he felt most apologetic in the matter;
                        he realized that our “final” suggestion in regard to the preamble had been
                        formally accepted by the Chinese in the Chinese Embassy’s memorandum of
                        December 7 and that also Dr. T. V. Soong, the Chinese Foreign Minister, had
                        informed the American Ambassador at Chungking that the suggestion in
                        question was acceptable to the Chinese; he hoped nevertheless that as we had
                        in the first <pb facs="0423" n="413" xml:id="pg_413"/> place offered the
                        draft preamble which the Chinese now desired to adopt there would be no
                        objection to adopting that preamble.</p>
                    <p>I said to Mr. Liu that when our original draft treaty had been presented to
                        the Chinese it constituted a comparatively simple document providing for the
                        relinquishment of extraterritorial and other special rights and for the
                        taking care of immediately related matters which required attention. I said
                        that we had hoped to avoid including in the treaty extraneous matters but
                        that a number of them had been brought in and that the “final” draft
                        presented to the Chinese on December 19 covered, at the instance of the
                        Chinese, a number of questions not originally envisaged as part of the
                        treaty: coasting trade and inland navigation, visits of merchant vessels,
                        foreign pilots, visits of naval vessels, et cetera. I added that we had
                        striven very hard to meet Chinese wishes in every appropriate way; that, as
                        the treaty had been considerably broadened and was now actually a quite
                        comprehensive document, we felt that the preamble should be broad enough to
                        include some of the thoughts we had in mind when we presented our draft of
                        November 27, which, as he had mentioned, had been formally accepted by the
                        Chinese Government, and which exemplified an earnest endeavor to meet the
                        wishes of the Chinese Government in regard to the preamble.</p>
                    <p>I said that I could not at this moment make a definitive counter-suggestion
                        in regard to the preamble but I could offer him informally a tentative draft
                        to serve as a basis of discussion, and I thereupon handed him the text of
                        the draft attached. Mr. Liu stated that he was afraid that reference of this
                        counter-suggestion to the Foreign Office at Chungking would, as the time was
                        so short, cause delay in the signing of the treaty. I said that I thought
                        that it was quite possible that the desire at the last moment of the Chinese
                        to abandon the agreed upon preamble might have that result.</p>
                    <p>We discussed various phases of the matter, Mr. Liu handed me a revised and
                        “confirmed” Chinese text of the treaty, and after the usual amenities he
                        departed. Our conversation was friendly and cordial throughout.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">George Atcheson, Jr.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Annex]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Draft “Counter-Suggestion for Preamble”</hi><note n="29" xml:id="d310fn29">Handed to the Minister Counselor of the
                                Chinese Embassy on December 26 by the Assistant Chief of the
                                Division of Far Eastern Affairs; text transmitted to the Chargé in
                                the United Kingdom in Department’s telegram No. 6574, December 26, 5
                                p.m. The telegram added: “This development may conceivably delay the
                                signing of the treaty for two or three days.” (793.003/1055a)</note>
                        </head>
                        <p>The United States of America and the Republic of China, desirous of
                            emphasizing the friendly relations which have long prevailed between <pb facs="0424" n="414" xml:id="pg_414"/> their two peoples and of
                            manifesting their common desire as equal and sovereign States that the
                            high principles in the regulation of human affairs to which they are
                            committed shall be made broadly effective, have resolved to conclude a
                            treaty for the purpose of adjusting certain matters in the relations of
                            the two countries, and have appointed as their plenipotentiaries et
                            cetera.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>