<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-02-18T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-02-18T03:00:00-05:00" n="355" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d355">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/7413: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-02-18T15:00:00+07:00">February
                                    18, 1942—3 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received February 18—10:41 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>132. Embassy’s No. 123, February 14, 9 p.m. Several days ago the Ministry
                            of Finance convened an informal meeting of Chinese finance and banking
                            experts to discuss flotation of an internal bond issue secured from the
                            American and British credits. Niemeyer, Young and Adler<note n="92" xml:id="d355fn92">Solomon Adler, Treasury Department representative
                                and acting alternate American member of the Chinese Stabilization
                                Board.</note> were also present. The discussion centered around four
                            main points: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The conversion rate between <hi rend="italic">fapi</hi> and
                                    the dollar to be adopted in issuing bonds. Rates between five
                                    and six cents to the <hi rend="italic">fapi</hi> were suggested,
                                    the latter being favored on the grounds that the higher rate
                                    would prove attractive and permit issuance at par. There was
                                    inconclusive discussion with regard to whether the bonds should
                                    bear on their face the dollar, as well as the <hi rend="italic">fapi</hi> redemption value.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The rate of interest. Five and six per cent were mentioned,
                                    with the latter receiving principal support.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>The amount of the first issue. A figure as high as
                                    5,000,000,000 <hi rend="italic">fapi</hi> was suggested, but two
                                    and one-half million was favored, the idea being to follow a
                                    limited first issue immediately with a second issue, if the
                                    first issue was readily subscribed.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The term of the bonds. The general feeling was that they
                                    should be short term—5 to 10 years. While no decisions were
                                    taken at the meeting, it is understood that the foregoing
                                    indicates along broad lines the general thought of the Ministry
                                    of Finance with regard to a bond issue. Suggestions with regard
                                    to lifting exchange restrictions, importing United States
                                    currency, and issuing new currency with dollar support met with
                                    no encouragement from Kung or from others present. There was no
                                    discussion at the meeting of possible other uses which might be
                                    made of the credits.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>The degree of response which a dollar supported bond issue will meet
                            continue to be largely a matter of conjecture. There was talk at the
                            meeting of using various forms of compulsion if the response was
                            inadequate. Unless very carefully handled it is believed that the
                            adoption of such measures would prove to be unwise although the bonds
                            might be used to induce hoarders to disgorge their commodity holdings.
                            In implementing its avowed policy of agrarian reform, the Government
                            might advantageously use bonds to finance more equitable land
                            [distribution?] without increasing currency in circulation. The bonds
                            might also be utilized to encourage the responsible banks <pb facs="0480" n="470" xml:id="pg_470"/> to be more generous and more
                            effective in their financing of production for immediate use and in
                            making loans to farmers for small scale land reclamation and improvement
                            work.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Gauss</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>