<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-03-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="360" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d360">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/73974/5</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">Alger
                                    Hiss</persName>, Assistant to the Adviser on Political
                                Relations</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi></persName>)<note n="5" xml:id="d360fn5">Addressed to
                                Mr. Hornbeck.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-04">March 4, 1942</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I showed the attached memorandum<note n="6" xml:id="d360fn6">See document
                                prepared in the Department of State, dated February 28, <ref target="#pg_473">p. 473</ref>.</note> to Mr. Currie yesterday
                            and discussed it briefly with him.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Currie seemed to be in agreement with the views expressed in it. He
                            said that he did not think the term “board of review” would be a good
                            name to employ because it would imply too much in the way of veto power
                            or supervision. In general, he seemed to feel that we would have to rely
                            primarily upon consultation and said that he thought the most effective
                            consultation would have to take place in China.</p>
                        <pb facs="0487" n="477" xml:id="pg_477"/>
                        <p>He said that in addition to the points made in the memorandum as to why
                            the United States has a significant interest in the uses to which the
                            loan will be put, he considered it important to point out the necessity
                            that the executive report to Congress on the use made of these funds. He
                            remarked upon the fact that the loan had been consciously patterned
                            after the Lease-Lend operations. The Lease-Lend Act specifically
                            requires reports to Congress. He felt that as a practical matter the
                            executive could do no less in regard to the loan than it is required to
                            do in connection with operations under the Lease-Lend legislation. In
                            this same connection he said that all Lease-Lend requests are
                            individually scrutinized and passed upon by the United States
                            Government. The loan procedure which we envisage is, he said, certainly
                            far more liberal than the established Lease-Lend procedure.</p>
                        <p>I also showed a copy of the memorandum to Mr. Fox who expressed himself
                            as entirely in agreement with the points made in it. At his request I
                            let him have a copy for his own use and not for attribution.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>A[<hi rend="smallcaps">lger</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps">iss</hi>]</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>