<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in China ( (Gauss))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942China</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d388</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">388</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-03-28T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-03-28T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbfb6dc62c599a48" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Tobacco</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recXe3hjASdIXoUSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066112"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Inflation</term>
                    <term ref="recXoDJKMCaKGDSrd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-03-28T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-03-28T17:00:00-05:00" n="388"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d388">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.61331/313: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-28T18:00:00-04:00"
                            >March 28, 1942—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>235. Reference question of state monopolies of salt, tobacco, matches and sugar
                    in China.</p>
                <p>For your information the Department has prepared a brief memorandum<note n="40"
                        xml:id="d388fn40">Not printed.</note> in regard to the question of
                    monopolies in China for possible use by concerned American officials in
                    conversations here with representatives of the Chinese Government. There is
                    pointed out in the memorandum the inevitable inflationary effect of the large
                    expenditures that would be required for the purchase of properties and stocks
                    and of the setting up of machinery necessary for the financing and functioning
                    of monopolies at a time when every effort is being made to extend to China
                    assistance in curbing inflation. There is also mentioned the fact that the use
                    by China either directly or indirectly of any part of American credits for the
                    establishment of a government monopoly in China covering a commodity prominent
                    in the economy and export trade of the United States might cause embarrassment
                    to the Government of the United States. In this connection it is stated that the
                    experience of American leaf tobacco producers and exporters was that government
                    monopolies inevitably tended to restrict imports and that such American leaf
                    tobacco producers and exporters would be quick to criticize the Government of
                    the United States if credits made available by it to China were used, directly
                    or indirectly, in a manner resulting in increased restrictions on the exports of
                    American tobacco to China. It is pointed out that such criticism would tend to
                    place difficulties in the way of continuance of assistance by the United States
                    to China in further constructive, possibly post-war, work. It is also pointed
                    out that aside from the question of the inflationary effect which the
                    establishment of the proposed monopolies would inevitably have, such monopolies
                    would displace private agencies and enterprises which had been functioning for
                    many years and that such displacement would subject to further strain China’s
                    economy which is already being severely tested by China’s heroic war effort. It
                    is finally suggested that in view of the fact that all of the United Nations are
                    making every effort to streamline their activities and to subject every proposed
                    new activity to the <pb facs="0513" n="503" xml:id="pg_503"/> test whether such
                    activity would contribute to the prosecution of the war there is offered for
                    consideration the suggestion that the present time would seem most inopportune
                    for the outlay of large sums of money and for the expenditure of considerable
                    effort and thought in connection with the establishment of new government
                    monopolies of the type under reference.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding the above, the Department considers it not desirable to adopt a
                    too insistent attitude in regard to this matter. We intend to present our views
                    of the matter in terms not of legal rights or of national or private economic
                    interest but in terms of what we regard as a sound practice advantageous in the
                    long swing to all concerned.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
