<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The First Secretary of the British Embassy ( (Hayter) ) to the Assistant
                    Chief of the Division of Far Eastern Affairs ( (Salisbury))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942China</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d498</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">498</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-07-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-07-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001519"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Afghanistan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-07-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-07-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="498"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d498">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.24/1392</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The First Secretary of the British Embassy</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hayter</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Assistant Chief of the Division of Far
                        Eastern Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Salisbury</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-07-10">July 10,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Salisbury</hi>: On June 23rd I gave you a copy of
                    a telegram about a proposed supply route to China via Tibet.<note n="14"
                        xml:id="d498fn14">For further correspondence on this subject, see <ref
                            target="#pg_624">pp. 624</ref> ff.</note> The Chinese Government have
                    now approached us in regard to two other routes.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>These routes are both air routes whose terminal point in China would be in
                        the neighborhood of Kashgar. The first would go via Gilgit to a suitable
                        point in India near Peshawar, and the second via Kabul to India or Iran. His
                        Majesty’s Government were asked to grant facilities to survey the first
                        route and to approach the Afghan Government in regard to the second.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Our Ambassador at Chungking is informing the Chinese Government that the
                        first route is impracticable for aircraft other than stratosphere types, but
                        that the Government of India are prepared to give all necessary facilities
                        towards the establishment of a route from Northern India (Risalpur) to
                        Sinkiang as soon as the requisite <pb facs="0611" n="601" xml:id="pg_601"/>
                        planes are available. A survey flight by an American plane which happened to
                        be available in India at the time was arranged for June 23rd and 24th, but
                        we have not yet heard whether this actually took place.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>As regards the Afghan route, our Ambassador is informing the Chinese
                        Government that as a flight from Sinkiang to Kabul would have to cross the
                        Hindu Kush, this route offers no operational advantages over the direct
                        route between India and Sinkiang, in regard to which facilities have already
                        been offered. The Afghan National Assembly in November 1941 passed a
                        resolution that “the use of land or air routes in or through Afghanistan
                        must in no circumstances be conceded”, and the Afghan Government therefore
                        seems certain to refuse the request for facilities. For these two reasons
                        the Chinese Government are being informed that His Majesty’s Government do
                        not propose to pursue further the question of the Afghan route.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>It was thought that the above information might be of interest to the
                        United States authorities.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>W. G. <hi rend="smallcaps">Hayter</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
