<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in China ( (Gauss))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942China</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d538</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">538</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-03-14T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-03-14T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recmnRTtwUBtjR3ea" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="minerals-and-metals" lcsh-match="no_match">Tin</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-03-14T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-03-14T16:00:00-05:00" n="538"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d538">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20 Defense (M)/5788a: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-14T17:00:00-04:00"
                            >March 14, 1942—5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>174. The Government is most anxious that every possible step be taken to assure
                    the movement out of China of various strategic materials urgently needed in this
                    country. The War Department has suggested that the problem be submitted to
                    General Stilwell,<note n="8" xml:id="d538fn8">Lt. Gen. Joseph W. Stilwell,
                        Commanding General, United States Army Forces in China, Burma, and
                        India.</note> who is charged with the movement of goods into China.</p>
                <p>You are accordingly instructed to confer with General Stilwell or an appropriate
                    member of his staff and to impress upon him the great importance of transporting
                    the strategic materials out of China and of coordinating this movement with the
                    movement of goods into China.</p>
                <p>The materials in question, listed in the order of importance in so far as their
                    movement from China is concerned are tungsten, tin, silk, bristles, antimony and
                    tung oil.</p>
                <p>The tungsten, tin and antimony production are covered by contracts between Metals
                    Reserve Company and National Resources Commission. If these materials are to be
                    moved by air transport, it is possible that some adjustment may have to be made
                    to cover the additional cost involved. However, in view of the fact that these
                    materials are urgently needed in the war effort and are covered by contracts
                    with <pb facs="0649" n="639" xml:id="pg_639"/> a governmental agency, could it
                    not be arranged with General Stilwell to transport them in government owned
                    planes without additional cost. If this is not possible, please advise urgently,
                    giving your views as to excess costs and other matters standing in way of prompt
                    shipment.</p>
                <p>No direct contracts have been made by a governmental agency covering the purchase
                    of bristles and tung oil, but such contracts could be arranged if it would
                    expedite the transportation of larger amounts of these materials than would
                    otherwise be moved to the United States. Please telegraph the Department if you
                    believe such contracts advisable. In such event, please advise whether matter
                    should be discussed with Chinese representatives here or by the Embassy in
                    Chungking. In the latter event please state quantities and prices involved so
                    that necessary approval may be obtained from Reconstruction Finance Corporation
                    subsidiary here.</p>
                <p>The comments made above concerning air transportation are equally applicable to
                    bristles and tung oil.</p>
                <p>With respect to silk, no immediate problem is foreseen from the point of view of
                    the United States Government. The War Production Board have agreed to the
                    British proposal that no United States purchases of silk be made for the
                    present, thus leaving the way open to the British to purchase without
                    competition from the United States. Accordingly you are requested to advise your
                    British colleague that the United States Government does not intend for the
                    present to make any silk purchases. However, if you believe that the British
                    cannot buy and transport all of the raw silk available, please telegraph your
                    views as to the procedure which should be followed in order that the greatest
                    amount of silk can be moved out of China.</p>
                <p>The Department assumes that any action taken in conjunction with General
                    Stilwell, looking to the movement of materials out of China, will be coordinated
                    with continued movement to this country, either through representatives of
                    General Stilwell’s Mission or through representatives of the Maritime
                    Commission. In the latter connection, McKay, a representative of the Maritime
                    Commission, is on his way to Chungking to confer with General Stilwell. (See
                    Department’s 145 of March 3.<note n="9" xml:id="d538fn9">Not
                    printed.</note>)</p>
                <p>Please advise the Department urgently of any obstacles which may stand in the way
                    of prompt movement of these materials, and also please keep the Department
                    advised as to developments.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
