<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Department of State to the British Embassy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942China</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d623</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">623</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-09-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-09-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="623"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d623">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.6462/108</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">British Embassy</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Department of State refers to the British Embassy’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >aide-mémoire</hi> of August 29, 1942 in regard to a proposal by the Chinese
                        <pb facs="0733" n="723" xml:id="pg_723"/> Government that the Far Eastern
                    Development Company, a British firm, send technical experts to China, and wishes
                    to thank the Embassy for its courtesy in furnishing the information contained
                    therein. It is noted that the British Embassy desires an expression of the
                    Department’s views in the matter and asks to be informed whether a similar
                    approach has been made by the Chinese authorities to any American concern.</p>
                <p>As regards the question of the desirability of the proposal, it would seem to us
                    that this particular phase of the matter is one which would lie between the
                    Chinese Government and the British Government. If the Chinese Government should
                    desire the services of such experts, and if it appears that their services would
                    make a concrete contribution to the common war effort, there would not, of
                    course, arise any question of any deterrent considerations on the part of this
                    Government. If the project is carried out, the Department of State would
                    appreciate receiving any information in regard to the work of the technical
                    experts and the results of their mission which the British Government might care
                    to make available. It may be added that there has been some preliminary
                    consideration within this Government to the sending of an economic group to
                    China, but the matter has not so far been discussed with the Chinese
                    Government.</p>
                <p>So far as the Department is aware no similar request of an American firm has been
                    made by the Chinese Government. Inquiry in the matter is being made by telegraph
                    of the American Embassy at Chungking and if any affirmative information is
                    received the Department will expect to inform the British Embassy in due
                    course.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-09-10">September 10,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
