<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-12-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-12-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="646" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d646">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.9111/48</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 806</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-12-19">December 19,
                            1942</date>.<lb/>[Received January 13, 1943.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose for the
                        Department’s information a translation of an editorial from the <hi rend="italic">Ta Kung Pao</hi> (independent Chinese daily) of December
                        15, 1942, entitled “Problems in the Pacific and Canada”.<note n="18" xml:id="d646fn18">Not printed.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="italic">Ta Kung Pao</hi> takes the opportunity offered by the
                        meeting of the Institute of Pacific Relations in Canada to present what in
                        its <pb facs="0757" n="747" xml:id="pg_747"/> opinion are the three
                        important post-war problems in the Pacific area: (1) how to make Chinese
                        prosperous, (2) how to subdue Japan and (3) how to adjust relations in
                        Southeast Asia. The editorial states that the present hostilities had their
                        origin in the oppression of a weak China by a strong Japan and that
                        permanent peace in the Pacific can be assured only by the emergence of a
                        strong and prosperous China; that severe punishment must be meted out to
                        Japan and her leaders responsible for the war must be brought to trial; that
                        a new Japanese Government must represent the will of the people, the policy
                        of that government to be subject to examination by China; and that the
                        problem of the peoples of Southeast Asia should be easy to solve in
                        accordance with the principles of the Atlantic Charter. China’s position
                        with relation to the freedom and equality of those subject peoples is
                        reaffirmed by reference to Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek’s recent statement
                        that China had responsibilities, not rights, with respect to those people.
                        The editorial concludes with an appeal to Canada to take steps to improve
                        the treatment of overseas Chinese in Canada who are subject to painful
                        restrictions of Canadian immigration laws and discrimination.</p>
                    <p>This editorial reflects the oft-repeated opinion of the Chinese press, which
                        is shared by many in Chinese official circles, that Japan must be thoroughly
                        defeated and her armament industry completely destroyed and that China must
                        emerge as the strong power in the Far East. This opinion is based on the
                        feeling that a strong China can maintain surveillance over Japan and can
                        serve as a restraining influence to prevent further Japanese aggression,
                        thereby offering assurances of permanent peace in the Far East. Accompanying
                        these claims for the necessity of a strong China is the denial that China
                        aspires to the dominant position sought by Japan. As evidence of lack of
                        Chinese aspiration to a position of dominance, the press constantly refers
                        to the Generalissimo’s statement, first made at the closing session of the
                        Third People’s Political Council and repeated on later occasions, that
                        although China is the oldest and largest nation in Asia “it is not for us to
                        talk boastfully of her right to a position of ‘leadership’ and China shall
                        rather regard it as her responsibility to treat peoples of Asia as equals”,
                        toward whom China has responsibilities but not rights.</p>
                    <p>One cannot, however, entirely overlook the occasional references which have
                        appeared in the Chinese press to the treatment of overseas Chinese in
                        Thailand, to the large numbers of Chinese in Malaya, to the question of
                        Burmese independence, to the post-war position of Indochina under a possible
                        Chinese protectorate and to the important position of overseas Chinese in
                        the South Pacific, as evidenced by the resolutions in that regard passed by
                        the Third People’s Political Council <pb facs="0758" n="748" xml:id="pg_748"/> and the Tenth Plenary Session of the Central Executive Committee of the
                        Kuomintang. One sees increased Chinese attention to neighboring countries
                        and to her border regions in the organization under Chinese auspices of
                        Sino-Burmese and Sino-Korean Cultural Associations, in the attempts at
                        reassertion of Chinese authority in Sinkiang and in the greater emphasis
                        being placed on the border regions of the Northwest and the West, with
                        particular attention to the spread of education among the border tribes. It
                        seems likely, however, that Chinese internal post-war problems will be of
                        such a magnitude as to preclude any possibility in the near future of
                        Chinese assumption of a dominant position in the Far East or of the rise of
                        a Chinese imperialism to succeed that of the Western nations and that of
                        Japan.</p>
                    <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>C. E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Gauss</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
            </body></text></TEI>