<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-12-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-12-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="24" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d24">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">890b.6363 Gulf Oil
                                Corporation/170</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Great Britain (<persName corresp="#p_AR1" type="from">Atherton</persName>) to the
                                        <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 582</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-12-28">December 28, 1932</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                    January 7, 1933.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my
                                telegram No. 345 of December 28, 12 noon,<note n="17" xml:id="d24fn17">Not printed.</note> and to report that on
                                December 22 I called by <pb facs="0118" n="28" xml:id="pg_28"/>
                                appointment on <persName corresp="#p_VSRG1">Sir Robert
                                    Vansittart</persName> and invited his attention to the fact that
                                the Embassy had yet received no reply to the representations made by
                                the Ambassador in the matter of the Koweit oil concession, reported
                                in the Embassy’s despatch No. 558 of December 15, 1932. <persName corresp="#p_VSRG1">Sir Robert</persName> stated his regret at
                                the delay and promised an immediate reply.</p>
                            <p>On the evening of December 23 I received a Foreign Office note signed
                                by the Assistant Secretary of State, <persName corresp="#p_OSL1">Sir
                                    Lancelot Oliphant</persName>. A copy of this is attached hereto.
                                The contents of this note have been orally transmitted to the London
                                representative of the American interests concerned.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_AR1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Ray
                                            Atherton</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">The British Assistant Under Secretary of
                                        State for Foreign Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_OSL1" type="from">Oliphant</persName>) to the American Chargé
                                            (<persName corresp="#p_AR1" type="to">Atherton</persName>)</hi></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-12-23">23 December,
                                            1932</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear <persName corresp="#p_AR1">Atherton</persName></hi>: We have made enquiries about
                                    the point which you mentioned to <persName corresp="#p_VSRG1">Vansittart</persName> yesterday morning in connexion with
                                    the question of the proposed Koweit Oil Concession.</p>
                                <p>As you know, it concerns a number of different Departments of His
                                    Majesty’s Government and at every stage complicated
                                    interdepartmental discussions have been necessary. As <persName corresp="#p_VSRG1">Vansittart</persName> told your
                                    Ambassador in his letter of the 11th November, the document
                                    embodying the result of the examination of the two draft
                                    Concessions submitted by the Eastern and General Syndicate and
                                    by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company respectively had, at that date,
                                    been already despatched to the British Authorities in the
                                    Persian Gulf. But I fear that the suggestion in <persName corresp="#p_VSRG1">Vansittart</persName>’s letter of the
                                    11th November that this document would within a very short time
                                    of its receipt by them be communicated to the Sheikh for his
                                    consideration was somewhat over optimistic. Further
                                    inter-departmental discussions have had to take place in the
                                    interval, and have thus caused some further delay in the
                                    communication of the document to the Sheikh.</p>
                                <p>I have now done all I can to speed matters up, and the local
                                    British Authorities should now be in a position to proceed in
                                    the matter with the Sheikh in the very near future.</p>
                                <p>I am so sorry for this recent and quite unexpected additional
                                    delay which has arisen but which has now been terminated.</p>
                                <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
                                <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_OSL1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Lancelot Oliphant</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>