<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-12-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-12-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="306" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d306">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">868.51/1312</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Near
                                    Eastern Affairs (<persName>Murray</persName>)</hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-12-20">December 20,
                                        1932</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>The Greek Minister called this morning to inform me that he had been
                                instructed by his Government to request a postponement for a period
                                of 2 years of the payment in principal amount of $130,000 due this
                                Government from the Greek Government on January 1, 1933, under Part
                                1 of the Debt Funding Agreement of May 10, 1929, between the United
                                States and Greece. The Minister added that <pb facs="0515" n="425" xml:id="pg_425"/> although notice of postponement should, under
                                the Agreement, have been delivered to this Government 90 days before
                                the payment date, his Government had instructed him to request this
                                Government to waive the requirement as to the time of notice.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SC1">Simopoulos</persName> left with me the
                                attached copy of a communication dated December 19, 1932,<note n="42" xml:id="d306fn42">Not printed.</note> addressed to the
                                Secretary of the Treasury, concerning this matter.</p>
                            <p>The Minister at the same time informed me that after a meeting of the
                                leaders of all the Greek political parties held on December 18 it
                                had been unanimously decided that the second loan under the
                                Agreement of May 10, 1929, is to be considered as a war loan and
                                that no payment thereon could be made pending a solution of this
                                question. However, the Greek Government, with a view to showing its
                                good-will towards the Government of the United States, will retain
                                in exchange on New York in a blocked account 30 per cent of the
                                service of the second loan until a definite solution is reached on
                                the question as to whether or not this loan is a war loan. The Greek
                                Government considers that by the above procedure it is according to
                                the United States treatment as favorable as that accorded to other
                                creditors, in view of the decision of the Greek Government to retain
                                in blocked account the difference between payments in gold and
                                payments in paper currencies to other creditors pending a decision
                                as to whether the Greek Government is in fact obligated to make
                                payments in gold.</p>
                            <p>I pointed out to the Greek Minister that I was unable to see how the
                                above procedure could be regarded as constituting as favorable
                                treatment in respect of the payment due this Government on November
                                10, 1932, as was contemplated under the agreement arrived at in
                                London last September in the case of private bondholders, since, as
                                he was aware, this Government was insisting upon transfer as well as
                                payment.</p>
                            <p>For convenient reference, I quote paragraph 4 of the British
                                Government’s instructions to its member on the International
                                Financial Commission with respect to payment to British bondholders
                                on a gold basis:</p>
                            <p>[Here follows paragraph 4 of the instructions quoted in telegram No.
                                320, November 8, noon, from the Ambassador in Great Britain, printed
                                on <ref target="#pg_413">page 413</ref>.]</p>
                            <p>In a telegram dated November [<hi rend="italic">December?</hi>] 2,
                                    1932,<note n="42" xml:id="d306fn43">Not printed.</note> from
                                Athens Mr. <persName>Morris</persName> informed us that the Greek
                                Government objected to the retention by the International Financial
                                Commission of the difference between payments in gold and payments
                                in paper pending <pb facs="0516" n="426" xml:id="pg_426"/> an
                                arbitration of the matter between the Greek Government and the
                                bondholders as had been suggested by the International Financial
                                Commission.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>