<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-02-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="350" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d350">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">860M.01 Memel/148</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Germany (<persName corresp="#p_SFM1" type="from">Sackett</persName>) to the
                                        <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 1512</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-02-24">February 24, 1932</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                    March 7.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Supplementing despatch No. 1507 of
                                February 23, 1932,<note n="6" xml:id="d350fn6">Not printed.</note>
                                and confirming telegram No. 40 of February 23, 8 p.m., I have the
                                    <pb facs="0563" n="473" xml:id="pg_473"/> honor to report that
                                the Memel dispute is regarded by the German Government as
                                exceedingly grave.</p>
                            <p>The negotiations at Geneva, the various steps taken in the hope of
                                composing the differences between Dr. <persName>Böttcher</persName>
                                and Governor <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Merkys</persName>, the
                                Colban report,<note n="7" xml:id="d350fn7">Report made by a League
                                    of Nations committee headed by <persName>Erik Colban</persName>,
                                    Norwegian representative on the League Council, February 20,
                                    1932. For the report, see League of Nations, <hi rend="italic">Official Journal</hi>, March 1932, p. 540.</note> and
                                finally Dr. <persName>Böttcher</persName>’s resignation from the
                                Directorate, have all failed so far to relieve the extreme gravity
                                with which events in Memel are viewed at the Foreign Office.</p>
                            <p>According to Ministerialdirektor <persName corresp="#p_MR1">Meyer</persName>, who is in charge of Eastern affairs, there is
                                danger that Governor <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Merkys</persName>
                                will suddenly form a Directorate of his own, dissolve the Diet and
                                definitely torpedo the Memel statutes. Germany, he stated, could not
                                tolerate such injustice by Lithuania to the Memel population, which
                                had been German for the last 700 years and represented a far
                                superior culture.</p>
                            <p>Since the advent of <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Merkys</persName>, the
                                    <hi rend="italic">Memelländer</hi> had suffered oppression.
                                Protracted negotiations and good will on the part of Germany had
                                failed entirely to achieve any positive results for them. German
                                policy had not been directed at any frontier revision or
                                modification of existing treaty stipulations. It had been aimed
                                exclusively at the maintenance of the statutory rights of the local
                                population. At present, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MR1">Meyer</persName> continued, the attitude of Governor <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Merkys</persName> and the Lithuanian Government
                                had provoked a situation that was most dangerous; it was impossible
                                to foresee what might happen.</p>
                            <p>The German Consul General in Memel occupied a special position. The
                                Lithuanian Government suggested in the interest of better relations
                                that he be replaced. In reply, the German Government pointed out
                                that there were no grounds of complaint against him; that it could
                                not consider withdrawing him. A second note has been received in the
                                premises in which the Lithuanian Government persists in requesting
                                his withdrawal. The German Government has intimated in reply that if
                                the Lithuanian Government insists on the Consul General’s departure
                                merely because as a witness to events in Memel he is unwelcome to
                                the Lithuanian authorities the German Minister in Kovno would
                                likewise be recalled. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MR1">Meyer</persName> added that the exequaturs of Lithuanian
                                consuls in Germany would also be withdrawn. Economic reprisals, too,
                                would be considered, should <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Merkys</persName> attempt to overthrow the statutes or hold new
                                elections under martial law with the aid of Lithuanian military
                                organizations imported from outside the Memel territory.</p>
                            <p>The greatest danger, according to Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MR1">Meyer</persName>, was that the <hi rend="italic">Memelländer</hi>, in a feeling of desperation, might lend
                                themselves to disorders. <pb facs="0564" n="474" xml:id="pg_474"/>
                                In this event Governor <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Merkys</persName>
                                could be counted upon to employ drastic measures to restore
                                Lithuanian authority. The effect on public opinion in Germany would
                                be inflammatory; particularly in East Prussia. Meetings of protest
                                are being held all over the Reich, and the Chancellor, according to
                                Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MR1">Meyer</persName>, is being inundated
                                with telegraphic appeals from every conceivable quarter. And this
                                high pitch of popular feeling has been reached despite the fact that
                                every effort has been made to keep public discussion of the conflict
                                as quiet as possible.</p>
                            <p>Reverting to the charges against Dr. <persName>Böttcher</persName>,
                                Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MR1">Meyer</persName> explained that the
                                German Government gave formal assurances that he had not engaged in
                                any official negotiations when in Berlin. Dr.
                                    <persName>Böttcher</persName> gave similar assurances to
                                Governor <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Merkys</persName>. All this
                                proved to be entirely without result. The case against Dr.
                                    <persName>Böttcher</persName> and his associates, who
                                accompanied him to Berlin, had been entirely fabricated; was based
                                on unimportant circumstances. For example, the German Consul General
                                had been unwise in giving one of the party a special <hi rend="italic">laisser-passer</hi> in which the bearer’s mission
                                was described as in the interests of the Reich. This had not been,
                                Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MR1">Meyer</persName> insisted, in
                                accordance with the facts. The Consul General had been merely
                                imprudently anxious to assure control and customs courtesies on the
                                part of the German frontier officials.</p>
                            <p>I venture to confirm the element of danger from the side of Germany
                                which Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MR1">Meyer</persName> attributes to
                                the situation. As the Department is aware, public opinion in Germany
                                is particularly susceptible in respect of anything that concerns the
                                Eastern frontier of the Reich. Moreover, the Memel incident has come
                                at a singularly inopportune moment. Political passions are aroused
                                and national sentiment is being played upon in the present
                                domestic-political struggles; in a hotly contested presidential
                                election. Disdain of Lithuania contributes to make intolerable any
                                thought of Lithuanian success at the expense of German prestige or
                                interests. It is, I fear, no exaggeration to suggest that a cloud,
                                though a small one, has definitely appeared on the Eastern horizon.
                                Rash action by individuals or irregular formations could precipitate
                                a situation with widespread repercussions.</p>
                            <p>The Foreign Office expressed the hope that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SRP1">Skinner</persName> would find it possible to
                                proceed at once to Kovno. The next week is regarded as particularly
                                critical. It was hoped that his moderating influence might
                                contribute to appeasement.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_SFM1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Frederic M. Sackett</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>