<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Spain (Wiley) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1932v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d413</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">413</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1932-06-30T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1932-06-30T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-06-30T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-06-30T07:00:00-05:00" n="413"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d413">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.5231/728: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Spain (<persName corresp="#p_WJC1" type="from"
                            >Wiley</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-06-30T12:00:00+00:00"
                            >June 30, 1932—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received 8:32 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>58. Your 46, June 28, 5 p.m. I saw <persName corresp="#p_CML1"
                        >Calderon</persName> last night; he denied knowledge of alleged statement
                    which he will investigate but asserted categorically that nonreceipt of
                    amplified list did not constitute any obstacle. He insisted on holding forth on
                    trade complaints and declared that there had been no progress at all in
                    Washington for which reason the Ministry of Agriculture had vetoed list
                    submitted on April 23. <persName corresp="#p_CML1">Calderon</persName> made it
                    entirely clear that while Spanish Government had agreed that negotiations might
                    be separate it did not regard them as divorced. He referred with marked absence
                    of enthusiasm to recent American proposal to send experts to examine a certain
                    grape area which would involve considerable delay. As for cork markings
                        <persName corresp="#p_CML1">Calderon</persName> volunteered the information
                    that the question was of no particular interest as the necessary machinery had
                    been installed at considerable expense. Continuing he employed all the arguments
                    with which the Department is familiar. I replied appropriately impressing upon
                    him that I had come with a specific inquiry and could not discuss the Spanish
                    trade complaints which <pb facs="0645" n="555" xml:id="pg_555"/> were being
                    exclusively dealt with in Washington. He then proposed acquainting me privately
                    with the status of these complaints. I declined.</p>
                <p>The inference I drew from <persName corresp="#p_CML1">Calderon</persName>’s
                    remarks was that the Ministry of Agriculture and the grape interests dominate
                    the situation and that there is now small hope of any progress on present
                    basis.</p>
                <p>If the Department is not disposed at this juncture to adopt more energetic
                    measures would it not be well to explore the possibilities of <persName
                        corresp="#p_CML1">Calderon</persName>’s suggestion (<hi rend="italic"
                        >vide</hi> mail instruction 285 of May 14<note n="25" xml:id="d413fn25">Not
                        printed.</note>) for a provisional agreement? If without sacrifice of
                    principles we could obtain some sort of satisfactory <hi rend="italic">modus
                        vivendi</hi>, the chances are that it could be prolonged perhaps
                    indefinitely. Then in the course of time various questions at issue might be
                    conveniently disposed of or might even solve themselves.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WJC1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Wiley</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
