<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-02-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="464" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d464">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">883.05/438</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Egypt (<persName corresp="#p_JWM1" type="from">Jardine</persName>) to the
                                        <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 414</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-02-24">February 24, 1932</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                    March 24.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my
                                despatch No. 368 of December 23, 1931,<note n="5" xml:id="d464fn5">Not printed.</note> in the matter of the obtainment of the
                                appointment of an additional American judge to the Mixed Courts of
                                Egypt and to <pb facs="0714" n="624" xml:id="pg_624"/> transmit
                                herewith a copy of a communication of February 20, 1932, which I
                                have received from the British High Commissioner to Egypt, as well
                                as a copy of my reply thereto of February 23, 1932.<note n="10" xml:id="d464fn10">Neither printed.</note></p>
                            <p>When I mentioned to the Assistant Judicial Adviser that the support
                                of the Residency to the American contention for an additional judge
                                had been promised under certain conditions I was informed that no
                                difficulty was to be envisaged so far as the Egyptian authorities
                                were concerned.</p>
                            <p>The Assistant Judicial Adviser added that suggestions made to the
                                Minister of Justice by the Judicial Adviser in the matter of the
                                appointment of foreign judges to the Mixed Courts were equivalent to
                                nomination, as the Ministry of Justice invariably consulted the
                                Judicial Adviser in connection with the filling of vacancies on the
                                Mixed Courts. It was stated that the desire of the Egyptian
                                Government to defer to the recommendations of the Judicial Adviser
                                in the matter of the choice of a nominee was sometimes even
                                embarrassing and it was oftentimes only with difficulty that the
                                Ministry of Justice could be persuaded to exercise its discretion in
                                the making of an appointment from the list of candidates submitted
                                to the Egyptian Government.</p>
                            <p>The control exercised by the British Government through the Judicial
                                Adviser over appointments to the Mixed Courts and the fact, as
                                stated in the enclosed communication from the High Commissioner that
                                the seat finally accorded a fifth French judge in 1931 had been
                                originally offered to Sweden, may explain a remark made recently to
                                me by my French colleague that the Scandinavian judges were little
                                more than satellites to the Anglo-Egyptian influence on the
                                Courts.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_JWM1"><hi rend="smallcaps">W. M.
                                            Jardine</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>