<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-11-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-11-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="468" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d468">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">883.12/56</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Egypt (<persName corresp="#p_JWM1" type="from">Jardine</persName>) to the
                                        <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 354</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-11-24">November 24, 1931</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                    December 16.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                Department’s instruction No. 84 of August 27, 1931,<note n="22" xml:id="d468fn22">Not printed.</note> directing me, in the
                                absence of a favorable reply to my representations on the subject of
                                the appointment of an American representative on the International
                                Quarantine Board of Alexandria, to bring this matter once more
                                forcibly to the attention of the Egyptian Government and to
                                ascertain and report the reasons for the delay in this matter.</p>
                            <p>I forwarded the Department in my despatch No. 298 of September 14,
                                    1931,<note n="22" xml:id="d468fn24">Not printed.</note> a record
                                of my conversation on the subject which I had on September 3, 1931,
                                with the Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs. On November 17, 1931,
                                when calling on the Minister for Foreign Affairs on the day assigned
                                for the reception of members of the diplomatic corps, I had intended
                                to bring up again the question of American representation on the
                                International Quarantine Board, which I had been prevented from
                                doing by the Minister’s illness, but he anticipated the subject by
                                raising the question himself.</p>
                            <p>The Minister for Foreign Affairs stated that he had studied the
                                question at length and that he had discussed the subject with the
                                Prime Minister and that they had come to the conclusion that they
                                could not accede to the wishes of the United States as they regarded
                                the question as a purely domestic matter and that it was the
                                intention of the Egyptian Government not only to avoid the
                                appointment of new members but to abstain from the filling of any
                                vacancies which might occur in the future with a view to the
                                eventual transformation of the Board from an international to an
                                Egyptian institution.</p>
                            <p>The Minister for Foreign Affairs stated that there were countries
                                bordering on the Mediterranean at present unrepresented on the Board
                                which were asking for representation, a fact which I have previously
                                reported to the Department.<note n="23" xml:id="d468fn23">The
                                    countries referred to were Rumania, Germany, and Turkey
                                    (883.12/54).</note> He added that, if a formula might be devised
                                whereby a means might be found for the Egyptian Government to
                                appoint an American representative without opening representation on
                                the Board to the other countries seeking representation, <pb facs="0720" n="630" xml:id="pg_630"/> the Egyptian Government
                                would be pleased to give further consideration to the question of
                                American representation.</p>
                            <p>I inquired if I might regard the Minister’s reply as a definitive
                                reply to my Government’s inquiry. He stated that he would not go so
                                far as to say that his answer represented the last word on the part
                                of the Egyptian Government but that he had brought the matter up in
                                order that I might be apprised in general of the Egyptian
                                Government’s position and that he would prefer to have a further
                                opportunity to discuss the question with me before giving me a
                                definite answer and that he would be pleased to hear and to take
                                into consideration any further arguments which I might desire to
                                advance in support of my request for American representation.</p>
                            <p>In a conversation which I had with the British High Commissioner on
                                November 21, 1931, on a number of subjects I mentioned to the High
                                Commissioner the fact that my Government had repeatedly made
                                representations to the Egyptian Government with regard to the
                                appointment of an American representative on the International
                                Quarantine Board and that my Government had been promised at one
                                time that it would be accorded such representation<note n="25" xml:id="d468fn25">See note of June 21, 1928, from the Egyptian
                                    Minister for Foreign Affairs to the American Chargé, <ref target="frus1928v02#pg_777"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, 1928, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>,
                                        p. 777</ref>.</note> but that in a conversation which I had
                                had very recently with the Egyptian Minister for Foreign Affairs I
                                had been informed that the Egyptian Government could not accede to
                                the wishes of the American Government in this respect for the reason
                                that it regarded the matter as a domestic question and since the
                                Egyptian Government intended to make the Quarantine Board an
                                Egyptian body by refraining from the appointment of representatives
                                of foreign powers either in the form of additional members or to
                                fill any vacancies which might subsequently arise.</p>
                            <p>I inquired if the Egyptian Government had the support of the
                                Residency in the attitude which it had taken. The High Commissioner
                                informed me that the question had not been discussed with him at
                                all, but that in his opinion it was out of the question to consider
                                the conversion of the International Quarantine Board from an
                                international to a purely Egyptian institution. He added that he
                                regarded the matter as one of considerable importance and as one
                                which he proposed to examine without delay.</p>
                            <p>In view of the foregoing I have thought it desirable to postpone any
                                further representations on the subject to the Egyptian Government
                                until I might discuss the question further with the High
                                Commissioner after he had studied the question and had made himself
                                acquainted with the question involved of the eventual transfer of
                                the functions of the International Quarantine Board to an Egyptian
                                    <pb facs="0721" n="631" xml:id="pg_631"/> Board, as I have felt
                                that I would be better prepared to continue my representations or to
                                make recommendations to the Department on the basis of the attitude
                                which the Residency was likely to adopt.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_JWM1"><hi rend="smallcaps">W. M.
                                            Jardine</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>