<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Mr. Ellis O. Briggs of the Division of Western European
                    Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1932v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d540</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">540</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1932-06-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1932-06-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-06-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-06-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="540"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d540">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">882.20/377</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BEO1">Ellis O.
                            Briggs</persName> of the Division of Western European Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-06-18">June 18,
                            1932</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <persName>Colonel George W. Lewis</persName>, Adviser to the Liberian Frontier
                    Force under the terms of the Loan Agreement of 1926, called at the Department on
                    June 16 to state that he had resigned, effective July 15, 1932.</p>
                <p>He said that his work in Liberia had been very discouraging for the reason that
                    he had been unable to exercise any real authority and that as a result little or
                    no improvement in the Frontier Force had been brought about during his time in
                    Liberia. A large part of his time was spent in preparing a manual of
                    regulations, which the Liberian Government has not printed.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BL1">Boal</persName> asked him whether, in the event
                    that some new arrangement for an American adviser should be made, sufficient
                    authority would accrue to such adviser if he himself actually received the money
                    direct and himself paid it out to officers and enlisted men. <persName
                        corresp="#p_LCGT1">Colonel Lewis</persName> said that that would certainly
                    be desirable but that he felt that unless the adviser actually commanded the
                    Frontier Force, it would be very difficult to do an effective job. He cited many
                    instances drawn from his own experience to develop this idea and urgently
                    recommended <pb facs="0831" n="741" xml:id="pg_741"/> that if and when a new
                    arrangement should be made, the adviser be given absolute command and in
                    addition receive and disburse all Frontier Force money.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BEO1">E[<hi rend="smallcaps">llis</hi>] O. B[<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">riggs</hi>]</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
