<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Canadian Minister (Herridge)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1932v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d59</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">59</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1932-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1932-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recTuGOvJtSQ72Bn1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Patrol boat</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recdDEAik5EmT8luP" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="organization-of-american-states"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87007400"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Coast Guard</term>
                    <term ref="rec7wEECiiCfq0TDz" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85123713"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Smuggling</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="59"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d59">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.114 <persName>Josephine
                    K.</persName>/257</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Canadian Minister (<persName corresp="#p_HWD1" type="to"
                        >Herridge</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-10-25">October 25,
                            1932</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your note No. 110, of June 8, 1932, concerning the seizure of the Canadian
                    vessel <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> and its cargo of liquor, in the course of which the master,
                        <persName corresp="#p_CCWP1">William Cluett</persName>, was fatally
                    injured.</p>
                <p>It is observed from your note that the Canadian Government fails to apprehend the
                    relevance of the decrees entered in favor of the United States against the
                    vessel and its cargo, with the consent of the claimant, to the issues raised by
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WHH1">Wrong</persName> in his note of March 16,
                    1931.</p>
                <p>It is the opinion of this Government that by consenting to the, entering of the
                    decrees the claimant admitted the correctness of the contention of this
                    Government that the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> was within the distance from the coast of the United States that it
                    could traverse in one hour at the time of seizure and, also, that reasonable
                    cause existed for the belief that the vessel was committing an offense against
                    the laws of the United States prohibiting the importation of alcoholic
                    beverages. It will be recalled that when the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> was first sighted it was in contact with and transshipping its cargo
                    to an American barge, to which an American speed boat was also made fast, and
                    that as soon as the presence of the patrol boat was made known by its
                    searchlight, the speed boat made for the shore and the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> cast off from the barge and proceeded at full speed in a
                    southeasterly direction toward the open sea.</p>
                <p>The claimant’s own admission in regard to these two points, as shown by his
                    consent to the entry of judgment against him, is considered decisive as to the
                    fundamental issues involved, namely, the position of the vessel and the legal
                    justification for its seizure.</p>
                <p>In his note Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WHH1">Wrong</persName> states that, so far
                    from establishing that the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> was within the distance from the coast of the United States that it
                    could traverse in one hour, the report of the Treasury Department and the record
                    of the Board of Investigation establish conclusively that the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> was at all times more than one hour’s distance from shore. He also
                    stated in the same note that the position of the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> when discovered, as determined <pb facs="0179" n="89" xml:id="pg_89"
                    /> by the technical officers of the Government of Canada, was 10.4 miles from
                    the coast of New Jersey. Since the vessel’s registered speed is 11 knots, such a
                    position would still be within the distance that could be traversed by the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> in one hour.</p>
                <p>After carefully checking and rechecking the computations made by the several
                    officers of this Government who determined the position of the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName>, the appropriate authorities are convinced that the vessel when
                    discovered was 9.4 miles from the nearest territory of the United States and was
                    10.6 miles from shore when seized.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WHH1">Wrong</persName> apparently assumes the vessel’s
                    speed to be that which was established by the speed test conducted by the Board
                    of Investigation on January 29, 1931. The result of a speed test, however, can
                    be considered as little more than evidence that under the conditions prevailing
                    at a given moment in connection with weather and sea, engines and operating
                    personnel, a certain speed was attained. Such a test is not necessarily a
                    reliable method for determining the right to board Canadian vessels. At the time
                    of seizure the Coast Guard personnel were unable to start the engines of the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> until emergency repairs had been made as the ignition wires had been
                    ripped out. Furthermore, at the time of the test the conditions of wind and sea
                    were not the same as on the night of the seizure, and the engines were operated
                    by Coast Guard personnel unfamiliar with the installation.</p>
                <p>There is hardly any measurement of distance more indefinite and variable than the
                    speed of a vessel. It varies with every condition of loading and trim, with
                    every change of weather conditions, with every change of condition of engines
                    and hull, with change of course, with change of operating personnel. It varies
                    not only from day to day but from hour to hour. Article II of the Convention of
                    January 23, 1924, is silent on the subject of the method of determination of the
                    speed that shall govern. In the opinion of the appropriate authorities of this
                    Government there are two methods of determining the speed of a vessel which
                    establish beyond a reasonable doubt whether that vessel is within the distance
                    from the coast of the United States that it could traverse in one hour, as
                    contemplated by the Convention. First, in the case of a known smuggling vessel
                    of several years’ standing, such as the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName>, by actually trailing the vessel at sea. The second method is to
                    assume the accuracy of the statement concerning the speed of the vessel set
                    forth in its official certificate of registry issued by the country whose flag
                    the vessel flies. When the latter corroborates the former, it would appear that
                    the evidence is conclusive. In the case of the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName>, extracts from log books of Coast Guard vessels and special reports
                    concerning <pb facs="0180" n="90" xml:id="pg_90"/> the speed of the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> show that the vessel, while actually engaged in smuggling
                    operations, attained on a number of occasions a speed of 11 knots. This is also
                    the speed given in the vessel’s official register.</p>
                <p>With reference to the amount of force which may be applied to compel obedience to
                    a lawful command, I have noted the statement in Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WHH1"
                        >Wrong</persName>’s note that the right to board, search and seize for
                    adjudication a vessel within the distance from the coast of the United States
                    that it can traverse in one hour is not to be exercised by the application of
                    force under circumstances which may reasonably be taken to involve loss of human
                    life. In this connection, I would say that officers of this Government refrain
                    from using force except as a last resort, in which case the greatest precautions
                    are taken to avoid any loss of life. I would emphasize the fact that this
                    Government regrets that forcible measures are ever necessary and would welcome
                    any suggestions as to how, in the case of habitual offenders who will not
                    voluntarily recognize the authority of the United States Government, the law is
                    to be enforced. It could not have been the intention of the parties to the
                    Convention of January 23, 1924, that it should be enforced only with the consent
                    of the violator; that would be a new doctrine to which this Government could not
                    possibly subscribe. On the contrary, it would seem to be the duty of the master
                    of a ship to stop when ordered to do so by a vessel which has properly
                    identified itself as a police vessel. If the ship fails to stop, then the use of
                    force to compel obedience is authorized by Section 2765 of the Revised Statutes
                    of the United States (14 U. S. C. 68), which reads as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Whenever any vessel liable to seizure or examination does not bring-to,
                            on being required to do so, or on being chased by any cutter or boat
                            which has displayed the pennant and ensign prescribed for vessels in the
                            revenue service, the master of such cutter or boat may fire at or into
                            such vessel which does not bring-to, after such pennant and ensign has
                            been hoisted, and a gun has been fired by such cutter or boat as a
                            signal; and such master, and all persons acting by or under his
                            direction, shall be indemnified from any penalities or actions for
                            damages for so doing. If any person is killed or wounded by such firing,
                            and the master is prosecuted or arrested therefor, he shall be forthwith
                            admitted to bail.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>A similar provision is found in Section 7(2) Chapter 43, of the Revised Statutes
                    of Canada, reading as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“On any such ship, vessel or boat, failing to bring to when required,
                            being chased by any such Government vessel or cruiser having such
                            pennant and ensign hoisted, the captain, master or other person in <pb
                                facs="0181" n="91" xml:id="pg_91"/> charge of such Government vessel
                            or cruiser may, after first causing a gun to be fired as a signal, fire
                            at or into such ship, vessel or boat.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>It is the understanding of this Government that Canadian Preventive vessels in
                    pursuance of this authority have on occasion used force to compel obedience to
                    lawful commands to stop, and, in one case, as the result of the application of
                    such force a member of the crew of an escaping American vessel was killed.</p>
                <p>The death of the master of the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> was regrettable. However, the small size of the vessel, the motion
                    of the sea, and the fact that both ships were traveling at top speed would
                    naturally render it extremely difficult to hit a spot that would disable the
                    ship without at the same time incurring the risk of injuring someone on board.
                    Had the master heeded the Klaxon signals, blank cartridges and warning shots of
                    the patrol boat and stopped when ordered to do so, and allowed the question of
                    the seizure to be adjudicated by the means provided for that purpose both by law
                    and by the Convention of January 23, 1924, his unfortunate death would not have
                    occurred.</p>
                <p>In view of the fact, therefore, that the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> was legally seized in accordance with the provisions of the
                    Convention, and that the death of the master arose out of a legitimate effort to
                    compel the vessel to stop, no reason is perceived why this Government should
                    make reparation to the widow and children of the late Captain <persName
                        corresp="#p_CCWP1">Cluett</persName>. Everything possible was done in an
                    effort to save his life when it was found that he had been injured, but the
                    responsibility for his death must rest upon Captain <persName corresp="#p_CCWP1"
                        >Cluett</persName> himself, who could have avoided any danger either to his
                    vessel or to himself and his crew by complying with the command of a police
                    vessel which had properly identified itself.</p>
                <p>I sincerely hope that the Canadian Government will realize that the authorities
                    of this Government are anxious to avoid any use of force in carrying out its
                    laws. But when those in charge of vessels which are engaged in a business having
                    for its object the systematic violation of law refuse to heed any other lawful
                    commands to stop, the use of force is made mandatory by their own action. In
                    such cases those who ignore lawful commands must be accounted solely responsible
                    for the consequences.</p>
                <p>The <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> was built in 1926 for use in the liquor traffic and has apparently
                    engaged in no other business from the time it was launched. It has violated not
                    only the laws of this Government prohibiting the importation of alcoholic
                    beverages, but it has also violated the International Rules of the Road<note
                        n="17" xml:id="d59fn17">U.S.C., title 33, secs. 61–141.</note> by
                    extinguishing its <pb facs="0182" n="92" xml:id="pg_92"/> lights at night and
                    thereby becoming a menace to the navigation of other vessels. Its action in this
                    latter regard was brought to the attention of the Canadian Government by the
                    American Legation at Ottawa in a note dated January 24, 1932.<note n="18"
                        xml:id="d59fn18">Not found in Department files.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Moreover, there appears to be great doubt as to whether the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> is entitled to the protection of the Canadian Government as a
                    Canadian vessel. Reference is made in this connection to a note dated February
                    15, 1927,<note n="19" xml:id="d59fn19">Not printed.</note> which this Government
                    addressed to the British Ambassador at this capital, stating that information
                    had been received that the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> was controlled by interests in the United States and adding that it
                    would be appreciated if steps were taken to cause an investigation to be made
                    “with a view to determining whether this vessel is entitled to the protection of
                    the British flag in its operations”. No reply has been received to this note,
                    nor to one addressed by this Government to the Minister of the Dominion of
                    Canada, dated April 28, 1927,<note n="19" xml:id="d59fn20">Not printed.</note>
                    referring to the previous note and inquiring as to the action taken in this
                    case. Since that time further information has been obtained which confirms the
                    belief that the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> is actually owned by citizens of the United States and that the
                    Canadian flag is being used merely to cover and protect a venture which is
                    directed at violating the laws of a friendly Government.</p>
                <p>The <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Josephine K.</hi>
                    </persName> was released on bond shortly after its seizure and almost
                    immediately re-entered the liquor traffic. There are enclosed detailed records
                    showing its operations both before and since its seizure.<note n="19"
                        xml:id="d59fn21">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CWR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">W. R. Castle, Jr.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
