<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>132. Telegram From the Embassy in France to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-06-30T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-06-30T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ministerial meeting</term>
                    <term ref="recAgu4u4GprMJCKN" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037341"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developing countries</term>
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Allocations</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="european-economic-community" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="european-economic-community">European Community</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-06-30T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-06-30T06:00:00-05:00" n="132"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d132">
                <head>132. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in France</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d132fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967-69, FN 10.
                        Confidential; Priority; Limdis; Greenback. Repeated to the Embassies in
                            <gloss target="#t_G101">G-10</gloss> capitals (sent to the Treasury
                        representatives in Bonn, London, Rome, Tokyo, and <gloss target="#t_USOECD1"
                            >USOECD</gloss> in Paris) and to <gloss target="#t_USEC1"
                        >USEC</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1969-06-30T11:00:00+00:00">June 30, 1969, 1100Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>9840. From Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VPA1">Volcker</persName> and
                    Governor <persName corresp="#p_DJD2">Daane</persName> to Treasury Secretary
                    Kennedy, for <persName corresp="#p_PJR1">Petty</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_DWB1">Dale</persName>, US Executive Director, <gloss
                        target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss>, and to FedRes for Chairman Martin. Section I
                    of II.</p>
                <p>Subject: Meeting of Deputies of <gloss target="#t_G101">G-10</gloss>-<gloss
                        target="#t_SDR1">SDR</gloss> Activation, June 28.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d132fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_WGH1">George H. Willis</persName> was a member of the
                        U.S. delegation. His handwritten notes on the meeting are in the Washington
                        National Records Center, Department of the Treasury, Deputy to the Assistant
                        Secretary for International Affairs: <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 56
                        83 26, <persName corresp="#p_WGH1">Willis</persName> Notes. <gloss
                            target="#t_SDR1">SDR</gloss> activation was also discussed in the <gloss
                            target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss>’s WP-3 June 27-28. A report on the WP-3
                        meeting is in telegram 9836 from Paris, June 29. (National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967-69, FN 10 1 <gloss
                            target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss>)</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Outcome of first full day’s negotiations on <gloss target="#t_SDR1"
                            >SDR</gloss>’s satisfactory, with a number of European delegations
                        adopting initial negotiating position at somewhat higher level than
                        anticipated.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Chairman (Ossola, Italy) summarized initial positions, characterizing them
                        as not firm national positions, but indications of emerging national
                        positions, as follows (amount per annum in billions of dollars, followed by
                        number of years for first decision): <pb facs="0382" n="354" xml:id="pg_354"/>
                        <list>
                            <item>U.S.—4.5-5 years (strong presumption)</item>
                            <item>Netherlands—2.0-5 years (preferably with low first year)</item>
                            <item>Germany—3.0-2-3 years</item>
                            <item>Italy—3.0-3 years</item>
                            <item>Belgium—2-2-1/4-2 years</item>
                            <item>Japan—3-4-2 years</item>
                            <item>Sweden—3.0 plus-5 years (tolerate 3 years)</item>
                            <item>U.K.—middle figure-2-5 years (with large initial year)</item>
                            <item>Canada—upper range-5 years</item>
                            <item>France—not participating</item>
                            <item>Switzerland—not participating</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Chairman stated general consensus in favor of activation around time of
                        September annual meeting of <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss>. This
                        required Group of Ten to reach decision by end August to be communicated to
                        Managing Director of <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> as part of
                        consultations preceding his formal proposal. Either Deputies (acting for
                        Ministers) or Ministers might have to meet in late August if matter not
                        settled in July. Belgian Deputy entered only reservation among participants
                        as to ability to commit his government within a few weeks. General
                        preference for settling matter in Deputies if possible, with British and
                        French making strong plea against Ministerial meeting. U.S. took position
                        they strongly hoped Ministerial meeting could be avoided, but were fully
                        prepared for such meeting if required to reach agreement.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>For guidance U.S. Missions in discussions of subject with officials, our
                        view is that satisfactory consensus can be reached in July, or latest in
                        August. It is natural that initial discussion of activation amounts shows
                        some range in initial positions. We continue to believe that $4.5 billion a
                        year for five years is amount called for (a) to achieve reasonable reserve
                        growth objectives of both industrial and developing countries, (b) to
                        facilitate adjustment process, and (c) to assist in repayment of reserve
                        credits extended in past five years. Further progress toward this view is
                        needed, but seems achievable as various governments focus on arithmetic of
                        reserve needs and its implications.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>FYI: A number of delegations accepted $4.5 billion a year as amount of new
                        reserves needed in all forms, but deducted anticipated net new reserve
                        creation due to anticipated resumption U.S. official settlements deficits
                        and possible net growth of reserve credit. This contrary to our projections,
                        which imply net reductions in reserves on these two counts taken together.
                        Further negotiations will explore these differences of view. At this point
                        we believe that possibilities of agreement between present German-Italian $3
                        and $4-1/2 billion in early years are good, and that we can hope to reach
                        some agreement for full period of five years. In latter connection Japanese
                        have emphasized and we concur that it is important that legal staff of Fund
                        produce promptly paper on options open to Fund to adjust allocations for
                        later years to allow for subsequent selective quota increases. End
                        FYI.</item>
                    <pb facs="0383" n="355" xml:id="pg_355"/>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>We understand Finance Ministers of European Community meet on July 21-22
                        prior to Deputies’ meeting July 23-24. U.S. Missions should bear in mind
                        importance of meeting of the Six and our interests in avoiding inflexible
                            <gloss target="#t_EC1">EC</gloss> group position. Believe Italians and
                        Germans will be sympathetic to desirability of retaining flexible
                        negotiating position at reasonable levels of <gloss target="#t_SDR1"
                            >SDR</gloss> activation.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Section II will follow on subject of <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss>
                        quota increase.<note n="3" xml:id="d132fn3">Section II was sent in telegram
                            9871 from Paris, June 30. Governor <persName corresp="#p_DJD2"
                                >Daane</persName> reportedly argued “that issues involved in working
                            out quota increase very complex and delicate, and should not be allowed
                            intrude on priority business of <gloss target="#t_SDR1">SDR</gloss>
                            activation.” Paragraph 3 reports on a short discussion of Italian
                            Minister Colombo’s proposal for an <gloss target="#t_SDR1"
                            >SDR</gloss>-aid link. The Netherlands, Belgian, French, Canadian,
                            Swedish, and Japanese representatives reportedly all said they had great
                            conceptual difficulties with the link. Governor <persName
                                corresp="#p_DJD2">Daane</persName> shared their concern but felt
                            “that in case of some donor countries voluntary pledges of type
                            suggested by Colombo could be appropriate, and that Group should
                            continue study how achieve without linking liquidity creation and
                            capital requirements.” (Ibid., FN 10)</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">Shriver</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
