<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-09-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-09-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="173" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d173">
                    <head>173. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_HDR1" type="from">Deane R.
                            Hinton</persName> of the Council on International Economic Policy Staff
                        to the President’s Assistant for International Economic Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_PPG1" type="to">Peterson</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d173fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, White
                            House Central Files, FG Federal Government Organizations, Treasury
                            1/1/71-2/29/72, Box 2. Confidential. A copy was sent to <persName corresp="#p_ARV1">Richard Allen</persName> (without
                            attachments).</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-09-01">September 1, 1971</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_VPA1">Volcker</persName> Group</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pete:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The <persName corresp="#p_VPA1">Volcker</persName> Group met for three hours
                        August 31 for a lively, but as usual, quite inconclusive exchange of views.
                        Paul obviously enjoyed himself playing games with the rest of us.</p>
                    <p>We began by discussing the August 28 paper on balance of payments
                            equilibrium.<note n="2" xml:id="d173fn2">Not found, but see <ref target="#d76">Document 76</ref> which is presumably the successor of
                            the August 28 paper.</note> The main issue seemed to be whether this
                        paper, or something like it, should be given to the Deputies of the Group of
                        10. It was agreed that there was a case for quantifying what we were
                        after—apparently, Paul has previously only said “substantial
                        improvement”—but it was also agreed that this paper would have to be
                        rewritten before it could be passed out. As usual, Paul was left with a free
                        hand to do what he thinks best, but it is possible that he will use the
                            <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss> Working Party 3 paper (attachment
                        1), and comment orally to the effect that the <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss> estimates are very conservative.<note n="3" xml:id="d173fn3">Not printed. The August 30 WP-3 paper is entitled
                            “Brief Résumé of Material Relevant to Assessment of Present
                            International Payments Situation.” The <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss> WP-3 and the <gloss target="#t_G101">G-10</gloss>
                            Deputies met in Paris September 2-4. According to a September 12
                            memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_ETLJ1">Eliot</persName> to
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> on “Foreign
                            Reactions to the President’s Economic Program—Afternoon September 10,”
                            during the previous week’s <gloss target="#t_G101">G-10</gloss> Deputies
                            meeting <persName corresp="#p_VPA1">Volcker</persName> estimated the
                            United States needed a $13 billion balance-of-payments adjustment,
                            primarily in the trade account. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970-73, <gloss target="#t_E1">E</gloss> 1 US 9/1/71)</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>There was some discussion of the agenda (attachment 2)<note n="4" xml:id="d173fn4">Not printed.</note> and what kind of answers Paul would
                        give. If you have questions I could, perhaps, answer. He stressed that they
                        would not discuss exchange rates leaving that for the Ministers at the
                        September 15-16 meeting.<note n="5" xml:id="d173fn5">See <ref target="#d175">Document 175</ref>.</note> Paul agreed that the issue of exchange
                        rate realignments, <hi rend="italic">at the best,</hi> would not be resolved
                        before the <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> meetings at the end of
                        September.</p>
                    <pb facs="0515" n="487" xml:id="pg_487"/>
                    <p>Paul noted that both the <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss> and U.S. ideas
                        of equilibrium call for the <gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss>’s to bear a
                        significant part of the adjustment burden!</p>
                    <p>At one point, he introduced into the discussion some estimates of what we are
                        after in “non-monetary areas” recognizing, however, that a large enough
                        monetary adjustment would reduce the pressure to deal with these problems.
                        His list, as I understood it, follows: <list>
                            <item>Multilateral defense offset in Europe—$1-1.5 billion;</item>
                            <item>Canadian trade practices, including auto agreement—$100
                                million;</item>
                            <item>Japanese QR’s—$250 million;</item>
                            <item>Dismantling the Common Agricultural Policy—$250 million;</item>
                            <item>Eliminating European agricultural subsidies in third markets—$150
                                million.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>There were some pointed remarks about the unlikelihood of accomplishing much
                        on these in negotiations with the Europeans, at least in the short run.</p>
                    <p>The discussion then turned to the August 30 options paper<note n="6" xml:id="d173fn6">Not found.</note> and we went round and round with
                        almost everyone but Paul arguing that these were not the kinds of options
                        that should be put to the President. At the very minimum, we urged that
                        Option 1 be developed to spell out the main elements of a possible new
                        international monetary system, that is, to examine such questions as: <list>
                            <item>Should the dollar remain a reserve currency and, if not, what
                                should take its place?—i.e., how consolidate a new reserve
                                unit?</item>
                            <item>What is the future role of gold?</item>
                            <item>What kind of convertibility for the dollar should be
                                envisaged?</item>
                            <item>Should there not be presumptive rules for exchange rate changes,
                                particularly on the up side?</item>
                            <item>How else to get more rate flexibility?</item>
                            <item>How to provide sufficient liquidity, assuming the U.S. runs a
                                large Current Account surplus?</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Ezra Solomon, Nat Samuels, and Governor <persName corresp="#p_DJD2">Daane</persName> also talked about the danger of the surcharge being
                        frozen in the system. Paul just smiled.</p>
                    <p>Finally, you might find of interest two papers done in the Fed on reserve
                        asset consolidation (attached),<note n="7" xml:id="d173fn7">Not printed. A
                            paper entitled “Consolidation of Outstanding Official Dollar Balances,”
                            forwarded to Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VPA1">Volcker</persName> by Ralph Bryant on January 2, 1973, and
                            circulated to the <persName corresp="#p_VPA1">Volcker</persName> Group
                            Alternates as VGA/73-1 on January 4 appears to be a successor to these
                            papers. (Washington National Records Center, Department of the Treasury,
                                <persName corresp="#p_VPA1">Volcker</persName> Group Masters: <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 56 86 30, VGA/73-1-VGA/73-25)</note> as
                        well as the attached <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> paper on the future
                        position of the U.S. dollar.<note n="8" xml:id="d173fn8">Not printed. The
                                <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> paper, EBS/71/232, August 27,
                            entitled “Some Thoughts on the Future Position of the U.S. Dollar in the
                            International Monetary System,” was circulated to members of the
                                <persName corresp="#p_VPA1">Volcker</persName> Group as VG/LIM/71-28
                            on August 31. (Ibid., VG/LIM/71-1-)</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>