<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>223. Letter From President Pompidou to President to President Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1972-02-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1972-02-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="rec6BvhdMDi4TnEMh" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067405"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">International monetary system</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="recVanxJ0yM3HzUcM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037333"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Devaluation</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-02-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-02-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="223"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d223">
                <head>223. Letter From President <persName corresp="#p_PG5" type="from"
                        >Pompidou</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to"
                        >Nixon</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d223fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Agency Files, Box 290, Treasury,
                        Volume III. No classification marking. The French text of Pompidou’s letter
                        was sent telegraphically. (Ibid., Subject Files, Box 356, Monetary Matters)
                        This translation is attached to an undated memorandum from <persName
                            corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName>, which indicates that the translation, made by
                            <persName corresp="#p_SHH1">Sonnenfeldt</persName>, is a “slightly
                        sanitized” version of Pompidou’s message, which <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> could give to Secretary Connally. <persName
                            corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> reminded <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> that an interim response had been sent to
                            <persName corresp="#p_PG5">Pompidou</persName> indicating his message
                        would be given “careful and serious consideration” when <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJBJ1">Connally</persName> returned from Texas. The interim
                        response was not found. Additional documentation concerning this letter,
                        including a memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                        transmitting this “hot line” letter to Connally, drafts of President
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s response, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_SHH1">Sonnenfeldt</persName>’s comments on the drafts are
                        ibid.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-02-04"
                            >February 4, 1972</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">My dear President,</p>
                <p>At the time of our meeting at the Azores, we reached agreement on two texts,
                    namely an official communique and a document intended, in principle, to remain
                        confidential.<note n="2" xml:id="d223fn2">
                        <ref target="#d220">Document 220</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>But the essential fact in my opinion is that our conversations of December 13 and
                    14, 1971, were characterized by a frankness and mutual understanding that were
                    particularly useful on account of the very general character of most of the
                    problems which were raised.</p>
                <p>It is notably within this framework that the international monetary problems were
                    touched upon in a more technical and precise fashion. Without doubt, it was
                    impossible in our brief conversations to discuss these questions in detail.
                    Nonetheless, very important accords were concluded on numerous points.</p>
                <p>For these reasons, I feel obliged to describe to you more than six weeks after
                    our conversations my uneasiness with regard to the evolution of the
                    international monetary situation. I should like to call your attention to
                    certain shortcomings which risk weakening the correct implementation of our
                    agreements as well as to my preoccupation over steps taken or of positions
                    envisaged by your administration and which, at first glance, do not seem to me
                    to be consistent with what we agreed.</p>
                <p>First, however, I would of course not permit myself to pass a judgment on your
                    internal economic policy. I know that you have obtained remarkable results
                    insofar as the movement of prices and salaries are concerned. Nevertheless, I am
                    not confident that the combination of a large budgetary deficit and of a policy
                    of systematically low interest rates can strengthen the confidence of the
                    international financial community, <pb facs="0633" n="605" xml:id="pg_605"/>
                    always very sensitive. Nor do I believe such a course affords in the best of
                    circumstances for the defense of the new parity of the dollar which you yourself
                    have fixed.</p>
                <p>At the time of our Azores conversations, I well understood that there was no
                    question of the complete convertibility of your currency. But I did indicate to
                    you that if you agreed to control the movements of capital, initiate a system
                    which would permit the consolidation of dollar balances and also the defense of
                    your currency, the dollar balances notwithstanding, this would in effect mean a
                    convertibility from currency to currency.</p>
                <p>I also told you that I understood very well that you insisted on refraining from
                    an official and immediate declaration but that all these things were understood.
                    [I also said] that failing these steps there would be no real defense of the
                    dollar and it would become necessary for the Federal Reserve Board to defend
                    your currency by exchanging it, if need be, against other currencies.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d223fn3">Brackets in the source text. In addition to some
                        “editorial” changes that were made in translating President <persName
                            corresp="#p_PG5">Pompidou</persName>’s letter from French to English, at
                        this point a phrase in the French text was omitted to the effect that
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> had also made this
                        point. According to the memorandum of the Presidents’ conversation on the
                        afternoon of December 13, during his review of the current international
                        economic problems <persName corresp="#p_PG5">Pompidou</persName> said he
                        understood that during a discussion that morning (presumably the meeting
                        with <persName corresp="#p_GdEV1">Giscard</persName>), “Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJBJ1">Connally</persName> had said that we would defend the
                        dollar.” At the conclusion of <persName corresp="#p_PG5"
                        >Pompidou</persName>’s intervention, “Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> said that we would have to buy dollars with other
                        currencies in order to defend it. President <persName corresp="#p_PG5"
                            >Pompidou</persName> replied that this was correct. There was no other
                        defense.” See <ref target="#d219">Document 219</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It was my understanding that you understood well<note n="4" xml:id="d223fn4">The
                        language in the French text for this phrase indicates that after he
                        discussed this matter with President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                            >Nixon</persName> and Secretary <persName corresp="#p_CJBJ1"
                            >Connally</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                        had assured <persName corresp="#p_PG5">Pompidou</persName> the next morning
                        that these were President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s
                        understandings. According to the memorandum of <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName>’s December 14 breakfast conversation with
                            <persName corresp="#p_PG5">Pompidou</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_PG5">Pompidou</persName> opened the discussion noting that
                        he had talked with <persName corresp="#p_CJBJ1">Connally</persName> and
                        thought <persName corresp="#p_CJBJ1">Connally</persName> had then talked
                        with <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>. <persName
                            corresp="#p_PG5">Pompidou</persName> said “he had found someone who had
                        firm ideas. He had said that the U.S. would defend the dollar after
                        devaluation.” <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> replied that
                        “he understood what President <persName corresp="#p_PG5">Pompidou</persName>
                        was saying. After talking to him he had spoken to the President and the
                        President’s view is that when we speak of defending the dollar, as he
                        understood it, we are talking about what happens in the new monetary system.
                        The President believes that as long as there is the expression on our part
                        that is what President <persName corresp="#p_PG5">Pompidou</persName>
                        described as defending the dollar, but President <persName corresp="#p_PG5"
                            >Pompidou</persName> seemed to feel that there were others. Leaving
                        aside the present balances, the way to defend is to buy when it falls.” In
                        the ensuing discussion President <persName corresp="#p_PG5"
                            >Pompidou</persName> said “he understood that the present dollar
                        balances would not be included as they were too big. The President
                        apparently felt we were thinking of something else.” <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> replied “that his impression
                        after talking to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_CJBJ1">Connally</persName>
                        is that the Secretary feels if the exchange alignment is correct then we
                        will be prepared to operate the system.” <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> then read <persName corresp="#p_PG5"
                            >Pompidou</persName> item 6 of the draft Framework Agreement, with
                            <persName corresp="#p_CJBJ1">Connally</persName>’s formulation on “what
                        we were prepared to do as part of a general package on margins and rates.”
                        See <ref target="#d219">Document 219</ref>. For the Framework Agreement, see
                            <ref target="#d220">Document 220</ref>.</note> that in the new monetary
                    system the dollar would be defended pursuant to the methods that I had
                    described; that it appeared evident that there was no <pb facs="0634" n="606"
                        xml:id="pg_606"/> other method and, not counting the existing dollar
                    balances, the new methods on which agreement had been reached represented in a
                    way a form of convertibility.</p>
                <p>In any event, these intentions have not for the moment come into play since, on
                    the money markets, the dollar is not at its support level and the problem
                    therefore has not posed itself for the United States to defend its currency as
                    any other country would, by intervening to preserve the dollar rate within the
                    margins defined by the Washington accords.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, the reversion of floating capital towards the United States which
                    you and I expected has not yet occurred, perhaps for psychological reasons but
                    also because of the interest rates that prevail, in practice, in your country.
                    Moreover, the widening of the dollar margins, which was decided in Washington
                    following our meetings, gives speculators the possibility to realize more
                    substantial gains in capital without a new modification of the parity of your
                    currency.</p>
                <p>You yourself proposed setting the enlargement of these margins of fluctuation at
                    2.25 percent on either side of parity which represented on your part, as on
                    mine, an important sacrifice in relation to our initial positions of principle.
                    Therefore, I could not fail but note that in the report of your advisors which
                    accompanied the message you addressed to Congress on January 27 on budgetary and
                    economic problems,<note n="5" xml:id="d223fn5">The President’s “Annual Message
                        to Congress: The Economic Report of the President,” dated January 27, is
                        printed in <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the United
                            States: <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Richard M. Nixon</persName>,
                            1972,</hi> pp. 111-114.</note> note was made of a growing consensus in
                    favor of greater flexibility in exchange rates. This does not seem to conform to
                    the undertakings that were reached between you and me. I would add that the
                    experience of the last six weeks gives me reason to believe that, setting aside
                    these formal considerations, the above mentioned remark (by the President’s
                    advisors) does not correspond to a clear analysis of the present situation.</p>
                <p>You must no doubt be impressed to see the extent to which we Europeans are
                    directly interested in the strength of your currency. This is true because it is
                    evident that it would be disastrous for the international monetary system and
                    thus for the entire free world should the accords of December, whose historic
                    character you yourself noted, become only a precarious pause along the path
                    towards a new crisis.</p>
                <p>The central problem of course remains that of your balance of payments, which,
                    all things being equal, one cannot expect with certainty to correct in a short
                    period of time. For that reason I suggested to you that you increase your
                    controls on the movement of capital. You indicated <pb facs="0635" n="607"
                        xml:id="pg_607"/> to me that you were initiating certain measures in this
                    regard which were not substantial, but that you were ready to go further. This
                    course would have clearly improved the situation of your balance of payments,
                    and therefore the level of the dollar on the exchange markets. It was for this
                    reason that I was surprised to see not only that nothing has started in this
                    direction, but that the Treasury of the United States has—at a moment where for
                    psychological and technical reasons, it would seem necessary to improve
                    confidence in the dollar—postponed from December 31, 1971 to February 29, 1972
                    the date at which the subsidiaries of American corporations established abroad
                    must repatriate their profits. Such a measure taken at such a moment does not
                    appear to me consistent with the objectives we set.</p>
                <p>Lastly, I would add that you provided me with certain details about the
                    procedure, which you obviously are alone competent to judge, that you intended
                    to pursue with respect to Congress regarding the legal devaluation of the
                    dollar. You also indicated to me in this connection that you would convene the
                    Committee Chairmen with a view to speeding consideration of a bill which,
                    according to you, was desirable since the Congress was adjourning immediately
                    after the conclusion of our conversations. Thus have I welcomed with all the
                    more pleasure the February 3 notification from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJBJ1"
                        >Connally</persName> to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GdEV1">Giscard
                        d’Estaing</persName>, of the transmission in the very near future of this
                    text to the Congress.</p>
                <p>I wish in closing to emphasize the point that my concerns are those of a friend,
                    that the prosperity of the United States and the maintenance of the value of the
                    dollar are of fundamental importance for the entire Western world, and I would
                    thus be happy if you could dispel these concerns which I have very freely
                    brought to your attention in the spirit of our good conversations of 13 and 14
                    December, 1971.</p>
                <p>Please, my dear Mr. President, accept my highest regards.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">Georges Pompidou</hi>
                        <note n="6" xml:id="d223fn6">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
