<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-05-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-05-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="229" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d229">
                    <head>229. <persName corresp="#p_VPA1">Volcker</persName> Group Paper<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d229fn1">Source: Washington National Records
                            Center, Department of the Treasury, <persName corresp="#p_VPA1">Volcker</persName> Group Masters: <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 56 86 30, VGA/72-1-VGA/72-50. Confidential. Willis’ May
                            31 cover note circulating the paper to the <persName corresp="#p_VPA1">Volcker</persName> Group Alternates indicates the minutes are a
                            revised version of the April 23 discussion in London. See <ref target="#d227fn2">footnote 2, Document 227</ref>.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">VGA/72-50 Rev.</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-05-10">May 10, 1972</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">MINUTES OF THE DISCUSSION IN LONDON CONCERNING PROCEDURES FOR
                        PREPARING MONETARY REFORM</p>
                    <p rend="center">(April 23, 1972)</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">I. Scope of future work on reforms</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>1. While the main task would no doubt be the reform of the international
                        monetary system, there was a consensus that the future equilibrium of the
                        world economy was also dependent on adequate trade rules, on rules for the
                        responsibilities of surplus and deficit countries respectively
                        (“burden-sharing” in the widest sense, as well as burden-sharing in the
                        narrower sense of sharing aid and military burdens), rules on capital flows,
                        etc. The U.S. representative mentioned also the relationship between the
                            <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> as a possible subject of review and reform. The close
                        linkage of reform of the monetary system with other problems was generally
                        acknowledged. However, there was a prevalent opinion to the effect that the
                        preparatory work for solving the totality of these problems could not be
                        entrusted to one single group but had to be delegated to several bodies.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">II. Group of Twenty</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>2. There was general agreement that a new “Group of Twenty” (G 20) should be
                        the main forum for discussing the reform of the monetary system. This Group
                        should be set up by a decision of the Board of Governors of the Fund as a
                        special committee of Governors of the <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss>.
                        Its composition should correspond to the regional composition (the
                        “constituencies”) of the Executive Board of the Fund. The Managing Director
                        of the <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> would be an ex-officio member.
                        Switzerland could participate as an observer.</p>
                    <p>3. There would be one chief representative for each constituency (and
                        possibly one or two alternates). The Group would elect its own Chairman. As
                        the Governor’s Committee would hardly be able to assemble frequently and
                        undertake the detailed work, a committee of deputies would have to be
                        established which would prepare the work <pb facs="0648" n="620" xml:id="pg_620"/> of the Governor’s Committee. The idea was mentioned
                        that the Chairman of the deputies should perhaps work on a full-time or
                        nearly full-time basis and he should be assisted by adequate staff.</p>
                    <p>4. The terms of reference would request the G 20 to prepare proposals for
                        reform of the monetary system. This could also include rules for
                        balance-of-payments adjustment, for capital movements, etc. Adequate
                        reference should also be made in the mandate to the close linkage with some
                        non-monetary problems. The G 20 should be authorized to draw not only on the
                        work and staff of the <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> but also on other
                        international organizations and on work done outside such organizations. The
                        Group would submit its proposals to the Board of Governors of the Fund who
                        would decide upon them.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">III. Other international organizations</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>5. It was emphasized that trade negotiations would fall within the competence
                        of <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>, and that any proposal for changes
                        in trade rules would also have to be acted upon by <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>6. It was recognized that the so-called “non-monetary problems” could not be
                        thoroughly dealt with by the Group of Twenty which would mainly be occupied
                        with problems of the international monetary system. There were suggestions
                        that these “non-monetary problems”—and also rules for the respective
                        responsibilities of surplus and deficit countries and for capital
                        movements—could be discussed, and proposals could be worked out, by
                        appropriate committees of the <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss>. To this
                        end, existing <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss> groups could be
                        re-structured, or a new <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss> group could be
                        established. The <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss> would enter the
                        picture only as a forum for preparatory discussion and it would submit its
                        proposals to the appropriate organizations.</p>
                    <p>7. The Group of Ten should have no specific mandate for participating in the
                        preparation of monetary reform. It should continue within its narrower
                        mandates in the framework of the <gloss target="#t_GAB1">GAB</gloss> and in
                        the consultation procedure for <gloss target="#t_SDR1">SDR</gloss>
                        allocations. It was left open whether it should be used also for other tasks
                        of coordination among the major industrial countries.</p>
                    <p>8. Several participants in the discussion in London emphasized that the work
                        to be done in G 20 or in other groups should in no way impinge on the
                        competence and work of other international organizations.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">IV. Further procedure</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>9. Draft minutes of the discussion in London should be sent to the
                        participants and, if possible, agreed upon in the course of May. A draft of
                        possible terms of reference for the Group of Twenty should be prepared <pb facs="0649" n="621" xml:id="pg_621"/> by one of the participants. Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_VLE1">Van Lennep</persName> said that he will
                        prepare a paper for the Council of <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss> on
                        how the <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss> could contribute to the
                        discussions on monetary and non-monetary issues and in particular their
                        inter-relationship. As concerns the establishment of G 20 the aim was to
                        have a decision by the Board of Governors of the Fund somewhen in June or
                        July.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_EO1">
                                <hi rend="strong">O. Emminger</hi>
                            </persName><note n="2" xml:id="d229fn2">Printed from a copy that bears
                                this typed signature.</note>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>