<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>60. Memorandum From the Under Secretary of the Treasury for Monetary Affairs
                    (Volcker) to the President’s Assistant for International Economic Affairs () to
                    the President’s Assistant for International Economic Affairs (Peterson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d60</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">60</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-04-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-04-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rGICCioSV3my" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Financial crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-04-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-04-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="60"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d60">
                <head>60. Memorandum From the Under Secretary of the Treasury for Monetary Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_VPA1" type="from">Volcker</persName>) to the
                    President’s Assistant for International Economic Affairs (<persName
                        corresp="#p_PPG1" type="to">Peterson</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d60fn1">Source: Washington National Records Center, Department of
                        the Treasury, Files of Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VPA1"
                            >Volcker</persName>: <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 56 79 15,
                            <gloss target="#t_CIEP1">CIEP</gloss> Study Memoranda. Confidential. A
                        17-page, March 23 analytical memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_WJH2"
                            >Wilson</persName> Schmidt to <persName corresp="#p_VPA1"
                            >Volcker</persName> on the “Effect of Capital Controls Program” is
                        attached but not printed.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1971-04-01">April 1, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Capital Controls Program</item>
                </list>
                <p>In <gloss target="#t_CIEP1">CIEP</gloss> Study Memorandum No. 1, you requested
                    comments on a paper by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName> which
                    recommended abandonment of the capital control program.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d60fn2">
                        <ref target="#d55">Documents 55</ref> and <ref target="#d54">54</ref>,
                        respectively.</note> Although the Treasury fully concurs in the view that
                    these controls should be removed as soon as the U.S. balance of payments
                    position permits, we believe that it would be a serious mistake to remove them
                    at the present time.</p>
                <p>The issue at present is not simply one of the statistical or even economic
                    effectiveness of the controls.<note n="3" xml:id="d60fn3">On March 18 Federal
                        Reserve Governor Brimmer sent Assistant Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_PJR1">Petty</persName> a letter to which he attached the
                        Federal Reserve’s preliminary conclusions regarding <persName
                            corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName>’ paper. The preliminary conclusions
                        were that the paper was “superficial,” failed “altogether to do justice to
                        the analytical complexity of the questions raised by the [capital controls]
                        program,” and was “deliberately misleading.” (Washington National Records
                        Center, Department of the Treasury, Files of Under Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_VPA1">Volcker</persName>: <gloss target="#t_FRC1"
                            >FRC</gloss> 56 79 15, <gloss target="#t_CIEP1">CIEP</gloss>
                        Meetings)</note> It seems to me unavoidable that removing the controls at
                    this time would be interpreted abroad as “malign neglect” of our
                    responsibilities as a key currency country for the stability of our currency and
                    the monetary system and as an overt affront to other countries dealing with what
                    they consider to be highly excessive dollar inflows. Beyond any effort on our
                    part to explain the “ineffectiveness” of the controls, action could not only
                    trigger loss of confidence in the dollar and a major international financial
                    crisis, but, in the eyes of much of the world, cast us in the role of initiating
                    villain. As you know, our official settlements deficit last year, excluding the
                        <gloss target="#t_SDR1">SDR</gloss> allocation, was $10.7 billion. In the
                    first three months of 1971, the rate is, unfortunately, much higher. While we do
                    not expect the deficit to continue at anything like this level, there is grave
                    concern among foreign monetary authorities at the present time.</p>
                <p>It is important to note that the Congress accepts the need for retaining the
                    controls at present without a murmur and, in fact, insisted upon giving us more
                    authority to apply controls over our objections. The <pb facs="0175" n="147"
                        xml:id="pg_147"/> Interest Equalization Tax extension passed the House
                    without dissent.<note n="4" xml:id="d60fn4">The vote on HR 5432 was 393 to 5,
                        with 34 members voting. See <hi rend="italic">Congressional Record,</hi>
                        March 10, 1971, pp. 5859-5866.</note> In the hearings, there was specific
                    recognition of the inadvisability of eliminating the controls, and even directly
                    affected financial houses did not ask for elimination at this time but, rather,
                    accepted the need for continuance.</p>
                <p>Finally, on the issues raised by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SGP1"
                        >Shultz</persName>, we simply do not find the evidence presented persuasive,
                    although I suspect we can all agree there is very considerable “slippage” in
                    controls of this type.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_VPA1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Paul A. Volcker</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
