<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of Embassy ( (Caffery), ), temporarily in the United States, to
                    the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918Russiav01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d116</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">116</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-06-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-06-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-06-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-06-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="116"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d116">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72/5334</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of Embassy</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi>
                    </persName>), <hi rend="italic">temporarily in the United States, to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Othello, Wash.</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-06-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 15, 1917</hi>
                        </date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received June 16, 9 a.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mission arrived this morning Seattle and now <hi rend="italic">en route</hi>
                    Chicago. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BBA1">Bakhmeteff</persName> expresses
                    to me his pleasure in being on American soil and states that lie looks forward
                    with much pleasure to his stay in this country. The Ambassador advises that his
                    Government attaches the very greatest importance to the work and cooperation of
                    the two special missions now in Russia and United States respectively. He says
                    that the Russian Government considers that the aims and ideas of the two
                    countries in this war are identical; that the relations should be of the closest
                    kind and that the cooperation of Russia and America will have great influence on
                    the future politics of the world. The Ambassador says that he wishes to
                    emphasize that his Government regards the work to be accomplished by his mission
                    to be of the utmost importance. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BBA1"
                        >Bakhmeteff</persName> feels that he understands America and American
                    institutions and people and that this knowledge will aid him materially in
                    conducting negotiations here; that Russia is looking to United States aid along
                    different lines, notably financial, railroads, agriculture, munitions and
                    supplies, that the heads of the technical bureaus under him will take up these
                    questions; that the Provisional Government feels that it can look more to the
                    United States than to any other country for the proper assistance in developing
                    a new democracy; that he does not underestimate the difficulties of the
                    situation but believes that with sympathy and understanding much progress can be
                    accomplished.</p>
                <p>The Provisional Government appointed Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BBA1"
                        >Bakhmeteff</persName> head of the Extraordinary Mission as the political
                    representative of all factions of the Provisional Government and at the same
                    time desired to have him received as Ambassador Resident at Washington until
                    such time as a permanent Ambassador may be appointed. With this end in view he
                    bears with him letters of credence in addition to special powers to treat of
                    special subjects.</p>
                <pb facs="0232" n="158" xml:id="pg_158"/>
                <p>General <persName>Roop</persName>, representative of the Russian General Staff
                    and Army, is a Lieutenant General in rank. He ranks next to the Ambassador.
                    Professor <persName>Lomonosov</persName>, chief of the railway mission, has
                    power in the United States of Minister of Communications; Professor
                        <persName>Borodin</persName>, who was a professor in the Agricultural
                    College at Petrograd, is interested in studying agricultural problems; Colonel
                        <persName>Oranovski</persName> of the artillery is vice president of the
                    munitions committee in New York and is interested in munitions and supplies; Mr.
                        <persName>Novitski</persName>, chief of the Credit Bureau of the Ministry of
                    Finance, will take up financial matters; Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJ1"
                        >Sookine</persName> of the Foreign Office is diplomatic secretary of the
                    mission.</p>
                <p>The ladies of the party will leave the train at Harrisburg and go direct to New
                    York, are not coming to Washington. The following members of the mission will
                    remain in Washington: the delegates from the Foreign Office; the delegates from
                    the War Office; the delegates from the Ministry of Finance; the representatives
                    of the press and special attaché. The following will go to Washington for the
                    official reception, remain a few days and then go to New York where they will be
                    located: Professor <persName>Lomonosov</persName>, <persName>Borodin</persName>,
                    Colonel <persName>Oranovski</persName>. The other members of the party will
                    travel direct to New York with the ladies of the party.</p>
                <p>Recommendations for house in Washington following: Ambassador, General
                        <persName>Roop</persName>, <persName>Lomonosov</persName>,
                        <persName>Borodin</persName>, <persName>Oranovski</persName>,
                        <persName>Novitski</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SJ1"
                    >Sookine</persName>, <persName>Karpovich</persName>, private secretary to
                    Ambassador, <persName>Dubasov</persName>, aides-de-camp, Captains
                        <persName>Shutt</persName>, <persName>Martinov</persName>.</p>
                <p>Rank of chief members of party after Ambassador: General
                        <persName>Roop</persName>, <persName>Lomonosov</persName>,
                        <persName>Borodin</persName>, <persName>Oranovski</persName>,
                        <persName>Novitski</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SJ1"
                    >Sookine</persName>, <persName>Dubasov</persName>,
                    <persName>Shutt</persName>.</p>
                <p>The mission desires that General <persName>Khrabrov</persName>, president of the
                    Committee of Munitions and Supplies in New York, join the mission in
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>Following changes original list: Nos. 5, 19 and 32 did not arrive. No. 18 should
                    read <persName>Sergievski</persName>. No. 28 should read Mrs.
                        <persName>Oranovski</persName> with son. Following additions to list: Mrs.
                        <persName>Lipits</persName>, wife of a Russian officer now in this country;
                    also two sailors and one valet.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador requests especially that his thanks be conveyed for the manner of
                    his reception in this country.<note n="1" xml:id="d116fn1">The mission reached
                        Washington on June 19 and on July 5 was converted into an ordinary Embassy
                        through the presentation by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BBA1"
                            >Bakhmeteff</persName> of letters of credence as permanent Ambassador.
                        Papers relating to the ceremonial aspects of the reception of the mission
                        are not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
