<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-03-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-03-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="14" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d14">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 861.00/365</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Russia</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_FDR1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Francis</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 657</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Petrograd</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="julian gregorian" when="1917-03-26">
                                    <hi rend="italic">March 13/26, 1917</hi></date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received May 19.</hi>]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In my unnumbered despatch of
                                yesterday,<note n="1" xml:id="d14fn1">Not printed.</note> the
                            original of which was sent in pouch to Stockholm and a copy of which is
                            in this pouch, I gave the details and sequence of my recognition on
                            behalf of our Government of the new Government of Russia.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to forward herewith copies of the correspondence between
                            the American Embassy and the Foreign Office on the subject.<note n="2" xml:id="d14fn2">Note of Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_FDR1">Francis</persName> of Mar. 9/22 not printed.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_FDR1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">David R. Francis</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                                    (<persName corresp="#p_MPN1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Milyukov</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American
                                    Ambassador</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_FDR1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Francis</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 5112</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Petrograd</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="julian gregorian" when="1917-03-25">
                                        <hi rend="italic">March 12/25, 1917</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Ambassador</hi>: By a note of the 9th/22d
                                instant, your excellency was good enough to set forth the
                                circumstances accompanying the recognition by the American
                                Government of the Russian Provisional Government, that is to say:
                                that your excellency, having received on March 9/22 instructions
                                from your Government to formally and officially recognize this
                                Government, was good enough to call on me at 11 o’clock in the
                                morning of the same day to inform me of the said decision of the
                                Government of the United States and that the same <pb facs="0088" n="14" xml:id="pg_14"/> day, at half past 4 in the afternoon,
                                having come to the Council of Ministers with the staff of the
                                Embassy, you were officially introduced by me to the Premier as well
                                as to the Council and were good enough on that occasion, according
                                to the instructions of your Government, to officially communicate
                                the news that the Government of the United States recognizes the
                                Russian Provisional Government.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to thank you for this courteous communication and
                                would appreciate it if you would kindly transmit to the Federal
                                Government the lively gratitude of the Russian Provisional
                                Government for the proof of friendly sympathy which the United
                                States has been good enough to extend through its decision to the
                                new democratic regimé established in Russia.</p>
                            <p>I am certain that henceforth the ties of traditional friendship which
                                unite our countries will become still closer and imbued with greater
                                confidence for the good of the two nations.</p>
                            <p>Be good enough to accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MPN1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Paul Milyukov</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>