<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Russia ( (Francis) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918Russiav01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d311</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">311</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-12-17T14:29:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-12-17T14:29:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec6XfF2Oe1IjakB2" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-12-17T14:29:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-12-17T14:29:00-05:00" n="311"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d311">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72119/1029</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Russia</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_FDR1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Francis</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Petrograd</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-12-17T23:00:00+03:31">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 17, 1917, 11 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received December 20, 11.18 p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2113. Armistice made for twenty-eight days subject to termination on seven days’
                    notice but otherwise automatically extended. Understand <persName
                        corresp="#p_TLDB1">Trotsky</persName> thinks has achieved a success, but
                    such another success were worse than a defeat. It means, in my judgment, that
                    Russia is out of the war. He spoke Saturday threatening guillotine and <persName
                        corresp="#p_LNVU1">Lenin</persName> asserted that Soviet government superior
                    to Constituent Assembly and justified treatment of Cadets. Two Poles called
                    claiming could raise Polish army of 800,000 to fight Germany and that 400,000
                    Poles in Austrian Army would turn against Central Empire. Shall investigate and
                    report but so many rumors prove unfounded I attach little importance thereto.
                    Reported arrangements being made for German commissioners to come to Petrograd
                    to negotiate peace and for German soldiers to come for their protection.
                    Depredations ceased in Embassy neighborhood but continue in other sections and
                    people so nervous that they would welcome monarchy or Germans if order could be
                    restored thereby.</p>
                <p>Diplomatic Corps met this afternoon to consider note couriers, see my 2107,<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d311fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_303">p. 303</ref>.</note>
                    adjourned till 20th after providing for committee of two Allied and one neutral
                    employee who will be instructed to visit Smolny unofficially and state that
                    proposed plan is impossible and to suggest another. British, French and Danish
                    employees were selected as those countries say require couriers. I can do
                    without courier service for a month provided cables not prohibited but fears
                    thereof were expressed by my colleagues. I opposed proposition to accept
                        <persName corresp="#p_TLDB1">Trotsky</persName> plan on condition that
                    couriers should not do propaganda work and asked in what capital Soviet
                    government has a diplomatic mission. Dutch Minister replied, “In Sweden,” but
                    Swedish Minister not present. Appears British and French Embassies have been
                    requested to visé Soviet courier’s passports but declined on the ground that
                    government not recognized. No application made to vise courier passport to
                    America.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_FDR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Francis</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
