<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-05-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-05-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="33" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d33">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72/4389</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Russian Chargé</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_OC1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Onou</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 343</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-05-03">
                                        <hi rend="italic">May 3, 1917</hi></date>.<note n="1" xml:id="d33fn1">The date on which this note was sent out by
                                        the Russian Minister of Foreign Affairs, for communication
                                        to the American and Allied Governments, was May 1, and it is
                                        generally referred to as of that date in historical accounts
                                        and in the discussion which followed in Russia; see despatch
                                        from the Consul in Petrograd, No. 300, May 8, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_42">p.
                                            42</ref>.</note>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received May 4.</hi>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: The Provisional
                                Russian Government, on March 27 [old style/April 9, new style],
                                published a manifesto to the citizens in which it set forth the
                                views of free Russia’s Government on the aims of the present
                                war.</p>
                            <p>The Minister of Foreign Affairs directs me to communicate to you the
                                said document and to accompany it with the following remarks:</p>
                            <p>Our enemies have lately been endeavoring to sow dissension among the
                                Allies by propagating inane reports about the alleged intention of
                                Russia to conclude a separate peace with the Central Monarchies. The
                                text of the enclosed document will best refute such fabrications.
                                The general principles therein enunciated by the Provisional
                                Government are in entire agreement with the lofty ideas that have
                                constantly been proclaimed to the most recent hour by eminent
                                statesmen in the Allied countries. Those principles have also been
                                given luminous expression in the words of the President of our
                                latest ally, the great Republic beyond the seas. The government of
                                the old regimé in Russia assuredly was not in a position to imbibe
                                and share those views on the liberating character of the war, the
                                creation of a stable basis for the pacific cooperation of the
                                peoples, the liberties of oppressed nations, etc. Emancipated Russia
                                can now speak a language that will be understood by modern
                                democracies and hastens to mingle her voice with those of her
                                allies. Imbued with this new spirit of a freed democracy, the
                                Provisional Government’s declarations cannot of course afford the
                                slightest ground for the deduction that the collapse of the old
                                edifice means a lesser share taken by Russia in the common struggle
                                of all the Allies. Quite to the contrary, the national will to carry
                                on the world war to a decisive victory has been still further
                                accentuated by that sense of responsibility which now rests upon all
                                jointly and severally. This tendency has been rendered even more
                                active by the fact that it is centered on the immediate task which
                                all have so much at heart—that of driving <pb facs="0113" n="39" xml:id="pg_39"/> back the enemy who invaded the territory of our
                                fatherland. It remains understood, and the enclosed document
                                expressly so states, that the Provisional Government, while
                                safeguarding the rights acquired by its country, will continue the
                                strict observance of the engagements assumed toward Russia’s allies.
                                Firmly convinced of the victorious outcome of the present war, and
                                in perfect accord with its allies, the Provisional Government is
                                equally sure that the problems arising out of this war will be
                                solved by means of the creation of a firm basis of a lasting peace
                                and that, inspired by identical sentiments, the Allied democracies
                                will find means of obtaining the guarantees and sanctions needed to
                                prevent a recurrence of sanguinary conflicts in the future.</p>
                            <p>Be pleased to accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_OC1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">C. Onou</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Declaration of the Russian Provisional
                                        Government, March 27/April 9, 1917</hi>
                                </head>
                                <p>The Provisional Government, having looked into the military
                                    situation of Russia, has decided in the name of its duty to the
                                    country to give the people straightforwardly the whole truth.
                                    The power that has now been overthrown left the defense of the
                                    country in a difficult and disorganized situation. Through its
                                    guilty inaction and unskilful measures it disorganized our
                                    finances, supply service, transportation, and the furnishing of
                                    the army with ammunition. It has shaken our whole economic
                                    organization. The Provisional Government, with the lively and
                                    active cooperation of the whole people, will devote its entire
                                    strength to repairing those weighty consequences of the old
                                    régime. There is, however, but little time. The blood of many
                                    sons of the fatherland has been lavishly spilt in the course of
                                    these two and one-half long years of war, yet the country is
                                    still under the power of the mighty enemy who occupies whole
                                    territories of our state and in these present days of the birth
                                    of Russian freedom, threatens us with another decisive
                                    onslaught. The defense, at any cost, of our national patrimony
                                    and the liberation of the country from the enemy who has invaded
                                    our borderlands constitute a capital and vital problem for our
                                    warriors who are defending the freedom of the people. Leaving it
                                    to the will of the people, in close union with our allies,
                                    finally to settle all questions relative to the World War and
                                    its conclusion, the Provisional Government deems it its right
                                    and duty to declare here and now that free Russia does not aim
                                    to dominate other peoples and deprive them of their national
                                    patrimony, to occupy foreign territories by force, but to
                                    establish a firm peace on the foundation of the right of peoples
                                    to determine their own destiny. The Russian people do not covet
                                    any accession of power abroad at the expense of other peoples,
                                    do not aim to subjugate or degrade any one. In the name of the
                                    higher principles of equity it has removed the shackles that
                                    weighted down the Polish people. But the Russian people do not
                                    admit that their country should come out of the great struggle
                                    debased or shaken in its vital forces. These principles will
                                    form the basis of the foreign policy of the Provisional
                                    Government, which unfailingly carries out the will of the people
                                    and safeguards the rights of our country, while abiding by the
                                    pledges given to our allies. The Provisional Government of free
                                    Russia has no right to hide the truth from the people—the state
                                    is in danger. Every element of strength must be brought into
                                    play to save it. Let the country respond to that truth—not with
                                    a futile <pb facs="0114" n="40" xml:id="pg_40"/> depression and
                                    discouragement, but with a unanimous <hi rend="italic">élan</hi>
                                    arising out of the creation of a unified national will. It will
                                    give us renewed strength for this struggle and will secure our
                                    salvation. May the whole country, in the trying hour of ordeal,
                                    find within itself the needed strength to consolidate the
                                    freedom that has been conquered and devote itself to untiring
                                    labor for the welfare of free Russia! The Provisional
                                    Government, which has taken a solemn oath to serve the people,
                                    is firmly convinced that with the general and unanimous support
                                    of each and every one it will be in a position to fulfil its
                                    duty to the country to the very end.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Prince <persName corresp="#p_LGE1">Lvov</persName>
                                        </hi>
                                    </signed>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">President of the Council</hi>
                                </closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>