<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-03-07T05:29:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-03-07T05:29:00-05:00" n="395" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d395">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 861.00/1258</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Moscow</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SM1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Summers</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d395fn1">Sent via the Consulate at
                                    Vladivostok.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-03-07T13:00:00+02:31">
                                        <hi rend="italic">March 7, 1918, 1 p.m.</hi>
                                    </date>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received March 9, 4.35
                                    a.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>236. In confidential conversation with Consulate General … [a high
                                Soviet official] stated that peace terms will not be observed and
                                that Germans will continue to advance occupying or controlling all
                                Russia to the Volga. The non-fulfilment by Russia of any of the
                                clauses will serve as reason further advance. As Bolsheviks will
                                refuse to demobilize Red Guard, inevitable result will be the
                                continuance <pb facs="0468" n="394" xml:id="pg_394"/> of military
                                operations. Germans have advanced already from Narva to Yamburg,
                                only 75 miles from Petrograd, simultaneous peace was signed [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>].</p>
                            <p>Bolsheviks had hoped that by signing peace time would be gained for
                                organizing new army. This he admits is now recognized by Bolsheviks
                                as serious mistake as Germans will not discontinue operations until
                                the already demoralized army is completely dissolved leaving country
                                defenseless. He further stated that <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi>
                                government will soon remove to Moscow of those though [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] have endeavored to persuade Petrograd
                                Soviets to go to some place beyond the Volga. He stated that
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LNVU1">Lenin</persName>’s position was
                                still very strong but that <persName corresp="#p_TLDB1">Trotsky</persName> had recently lost much of his influence.</p>
                            <p>The general impression gained from conference was that a large
                                section of the Bolshevik Party realized the disastrous situation
                                brought on by the party and the absolute defenselessness of Russia
                                against German domination. …</p>
                            <p>I shall keep Department fully advised proceeding of coming congress
                                Soviets. It is not thought they will oppose peace terms.</p>
                            <p>Embassy at Vologda still. All newspapers except anarchist and
                                Bolshevik friendly.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SM1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Summers</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>