<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-01-14T15:29:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-01-14T15:29:00-05:00" n="448" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d448">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 701.7161/1</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Russia</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_FDR1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Francis</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Petrograd</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-01-14T23:00:00+02:31">
                                    <hi rend="italic">January 14, 1918, 11 p.m.</hi>
                                </date>
                                <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received January 16, 10.50
                                p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>2233. Nineteen heads of missions visited <persName corresp="#p_LNVU1">Lenin</persName> by appointment, 4 p.m., at Smolny and presented
                            following in French through myself as dean: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>The undersigned chiefs of diplomatic missions of all the nations
                                    represented in Russia, viz.: United States, Japan, France,
                                    Sweden, <pb facs="0552" n="478" xml:id="pg_478"/> Norway,
                                    Switzerland, Denmark, Siam, China, Serbia, Portugal, Argentine
                                    Republic, Greece, Belgium, Brazil, Persia, Spain, Netherlands,
                                    Italy and Great Britain, profoundly indignant at the arrest of
                                    M. <persName corresp="#p_DCJ1">Diamandi</persName>, Minister of
                                    Rumania, and affirming the unanimity of their sentiments on the
                                    subject of the violation of diplomatic immunities respected for
                                    centuries by all governments, demand the immediate liberty of M.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_DCJ1">Diamandi</persName> and of the
                                    members of his Legation.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Then follow in order above-named signatures of all the chiefs.</p>
                        <p>Arriving Smolny were promptly admitted and pleasantly received by
                                <persName corresp="#p_LNVU1">Lenin</persName> to whom I introduced
                            colleagues, each by title, and when all seated I presented above demand.
                            On <persName corresp="#p_LNVU1">Lenin</persName> beginning to explain
                            assassination [arrest] caused by Rumania’s killing and starving Russian
                            soldiers I stated we would not discuss causes or justification but only
                            the principle involved. French Ambassador then entered into
                            conversation, also Belgian Minister and Serbian; Belgian stating
                            feelingly, Serbian emotionally, that notwithstanding outrages in their
                            countries diplomatic immunity never violated. I finally told <persName corresp="#p_LNVU1">Lenin</persName>, who had said arrest was made to
                            avoid war between Rumania, Russia, that retention of Minister would be
                            more likely to promote than prevent war and would weaken his government
                            in Russia and throughout the world. He said that if I thought so he
                            would refer matter to Council of People’s Commissioners and when French
                            Ambassador said we must have prompt reply <persName corresp="#p_LNVU1">Lenin</persName> said would telephone American Ambassador this
                            evening. Am now awaiting advice which think will be favorable. Many
                            chiefs including British and French and Japanese said would ask their
                            Governments to authorize request of passport if Minister not released.
                            Am not prepared to say what I would do, depends on what I think effect
                            would be on separate peace. Have you any instructions?</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_FDR1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Francis</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>