<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul at Petrograd ( (Winship) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918Russiav01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d73</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">73</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-07-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-07-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recKrzVuLHn3WbqNd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85063084"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Hunger</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec4kNZ3bN6ephN7u" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027420"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Coalition government</term>
                    <term ref="recb140a4efc2e771d" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general">Warships</term>
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-07-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-07-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="73"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d73">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 861.00/1724</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Petrograd</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_WN1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winship</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 338</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Petrograd</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-07-03">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 3, 1917</hi>
                        </date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received August 2.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that the All-Russian
                    Convention of Delegates from Councils of Workmen’s and Soldiers’ Deputies has
                    adopted a resolution on the war corresponding in all details to the mood and
                    program outlined by Mr. <persName>Dan</persName> in the speech mentioned in
                    despatch No. 335 of June 26, 1917,<note n="1" xml:id="d73fn1">Not printed. Dan,
                        a leader of the Social Democrats (Mensheviks), was reporter for the
                        executive committee on the resolution defining the attitude of the congress
                        toward the war.</note> given there in enclosure No. 2.</p>
                <p>This resolution is obligatory on the present Temporary Government, as the <hi
                        rend="italic">bourgeois</hi> ministers must either carry out the desires of
                    the soldiers and workmen (as Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TMI1"
                        >Tereshchenko</persName> is already doing) or else resign and thus replace
                    the present masked dictatorship of the proletariat by an open dictatorship of
                    the proletariat. The resolution <pb facs="0174" n="100" xml:id="pg_100"/> is a
                    clear and emphatic statement of the present intentions of the all-powerful
                    soldiers and workmen, gathered in a convention which is now the national
                    parliament or congress of Russia. First of all, it adopts the fundamental
                    attitude of the pro-German Zimmerwald conference in refusing to pay any heed to
                    where the guilt for the origin of the war lies. (Paragraph 1: “The present war
                    broke out on account of the imperialistic tendencies of all countries. …”)
                    Secondly, it is not a statement as to how the war should be continued but
                    entirely a statement as to how the war should be ended. (Paragraph 2: Entire
                    [paragraph], and especially the words:” It [the war] distracts the country’s
                    attention from the labor of fortifying the liberties newly won.” Also paragraph
                    3: … “The struggle for the quickest possible conclusion of the war is the most
                    important current task of the revolutionary democracy.”) Thirdly, it gives up
                    all idea of ending the war by defeating the Central powers. (Paragraph 4: “For
                    the war to end by the crushing of one of the two groups of belligerents would
                    cause new future wars and would even further deepen the differences between
                    peoples and bring them to complete exhaustion, hunger and ruin.” And paragraph
                    6: … “The war can only be ended by the united efforts of the democracies of all
                    countries. …”) Fourthly, it means that it is the intention of the Russian
                    soldiers and workmen to end the war, if they can, by arousing the workmen and
                    soldiers of the Allied countries against their present governments so that the
                    English, French, Italian and American Governments will be forced by the
                    workmen’s and soldiers’ organizations to adopt the Russian plans, in the belief
                    that when this is done the German and Austrian workmen and soldiers will act
                    accordingly. (Paragraph 6: “An appeal to the democracies of all nations urging
                    them to accept the slogan ‘peace without annexations or contributions on the
                    basis of each nation’s right to determine its own future’ and to put pressure to
                    bear on their respective governments along this line.”) The encouragement of the
                    revolt against the majority government in England, France, Italy and America is
                    held to be necessary because the recent notes from the first three countries, in
                    answer to the Russian note, and President <persName corresp="#p_WW1"
                        >Wilson</persName>’s message to the Russian people, are considered
                    unsatisfactory, imperialistic. (Paragraph 6: “The latest announcements of their
                    respective governments put the Russian revolution in an extremely difficult
                    position.”)</p>
                <p>The situation created by this resolution is, therefore, that while the Temporary
                    Government, at the bidding of the workmen and soldiers, puts what pressure it
                    can on the Allied Governments, the convention itself undertakes to influence
                    those governments from below (paragraphs 9 and 10) through the respective
                    populaces, and <pb facs="0175" n="101" xml:id="pg_101"/> calls on the official
                    Russian Government to assist in this work to the extent of assuring the free
                    passage of socialist delegations between Russia and the other Allied
                    countries.</p>
                <p>Thus the encouragement of revolt and revolution in Allied countries is a plank in
                    the platform of the convention.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Dan</persName> remarked that the capitalistic governments are only
                    open to arguments when force may be brought to bear and that therefore the
                    efficiency of the Russian Army must be maintained in order to impress France,
                    England, Italy and America. This was not, however, included in the
                    resolution.</p>
                <p>That the convention believes its policy will be successful, and that it can bring
                    about general peace regardless of the English, French, Italian, Japanese and
                    American Governments, is shown by paragraph 6, section 2, stating that the
                    international socialist conference which is to be called by the “revolutionary
                    democracy of Russia” will outline “final peace terms, and ways and means of
                    realizing these final peace terms.”</p>
                <p>The final paragraph, paragraph 12, which reads, “In particular the convention
                    deems that the question as to whether an aggressive forward movement of the army
                    should be decided purely on strategical grounds,” is really a declaration that
                    the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> on the front should remain the same as at
                    present unless the Germans attack. Any unprovoked forward movement of the army
                    against the Germans would be deemed a political imperialistic move until the
                    Allies have been brought into full accord with Russian workmen and soldiers.
                    This confirms the truce at the front for an indefinite time, unless a reaction
                    or counter movement takes a firm hold.</p>
                <p>The resolution on the war adopted at the Cossack Convention is a very different
                    document. Its first words are: “The first Cossack Convention holds that an
                    immediate and decisive aggressive forward movement of the army is the only way
                    to attain the peace which is so needed for national constructive labor.” It then
                    continues: “The war must be carried on to such a victory as will assure a full
                    mutual agreement with the Allies, and make it possible to conclude peace based
                    on the full right of each nation to determine its own future, without violent
                    annexations, and without punitive contributions.” This is the war-peace program
                    of the middle classes of Russia to-day. As has been noticed, the workmen and
                    soldiers have no war program, only a peace program.</p>
                <p>The resolution on the war proposed to the All-Russian Convention by the
                    Maximalists (socialist-pacifists), the party of <persName corresp="#p_LNVU1"
                        >Lenin</persName>, the party with which <persName>Robert Grimm</persName>
                    worked most intimately during his stay in Russia, differs mainly in violence of
                    language rather than in <pb facs="0176" n="102" xml:id="pg_102"/> principle from
                    the resolution adopted by the All-Russian Convention. The first paragraph of the
                    Maximalists’ resolution reads: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The official announcements of the English and French Governments
                            published May 23, in answer to the notes of the Temporary Government,
                            the annexation of Albania by Italy and the violence done to Greece by
                            the Anglo-French capitalists, show again and again that the <hi
                                rend="italic">bourgeois</hi> classes of the “Allied countries” do
                            not want to adopt the slogan “peace without annexation or contribution
                            “on the basis of each nation’s right to determine its own future.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The second paragraph of the Maximalists’ resolution declares that the— <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="flushleft">policy of the coalition Temporary Government, promising
                            to lead the country to peace by means of diplomatic negotiations with
                            the imperialistic Governments of France and England in order to
                            influence these Governments to surrender their annexationist program,
                            has undergone a complete fiasco.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Mr. <persName>Dan</persName> practically said this himself in
                    reporting the resolution adopted. The resolution repeats this in a milder way in
                    demanding wide thoroughgoing changes in the personnel of Ministry of Foreign
                    Affairs and the Diplomatic Corps, and in demanding more energetic direct action
                    on the part of the convention itself.</p>
                <p>The contrast between the Cossack resolution and those of the All-Russian
                    Convention and the Maximalists is clear. The Ail-Russian Convention and the
                    Maximalists want no aggressive forward movement now, as it would be sacrificing
                    Russian blood to further the selfish aims of the Allies. An aggressive forward
                    movement may not be possible until the Allies are forced to change their war
                    aims by the socialist-pacifist minorities in their respective countries. This of
                    course with the provision that the Central Empires do not, in the meantime, also
                    change their war aims, in which case there should be an immediate peace
                    conference.</p>
                <p>The Maximalists, of course, differ from the majority of Minimalists and Socialist
                    Revolutionists in the All-Russian Convention, in that they demand that the ten
                        <hi rend="italic">bourgeois</hi> ministers still in the coalition Government
                    resign, whereas the majority in the convention demand only that the Government
                    take more energetic measures. If the ten <hi rend="italic">bourgeois</hi>
                    ministers do not resign it can only be because they are now reconciled to the
                    policy of the All-Russian Convention toward the Allies, or despair of combating
                    it. As a matter of fact it cannot be combated until the present dictatorship of
                    the socialist-pacifist Zimmerwald proletariat is broken.</p>
                <p>The resolution, in paragraph 4, goes so far as to admit that a “separate peace
                    would strengthen one of the belligerent groups,” but the leaders of the
                    convention do not hesitate to prolong the “separate truce.”</p>
                <pb facs="0177" n="103" xml:id="pg_103"/>
                <p>The understanding the ignorant masses of soldiers place on the present policy of
                    the All-Russian Convention and the Temporary Government toward the Allies and
                    regarding peace, is vividly shown in the resolution adopted by the Russian
                    “Territorial Committee of the Army, Navy and Workmen for Finland,” representing
                    the Russian soldiers, sailors and workmen quartered in Finland. This resolution
                    reads in part: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The territorial committee declares that the refusal of the Allied
                            Governments to accept the peace platform of the Russian democracy makes
                            it impossible for the Russian democracy to continue further united
                            political and strategical cooperation with the Allies. The new
                            confirmation of the annexationist Allied Governments puts them in the
                            same class with our enemies, the imperialistic Governments of Germany
                            and Austria. … The first result of the Allied Governments’ refusal to
                            accede to the demands of the Russian democracy should be a complete
                            break with them.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>A similar resolution was passed by the joint committee of seven warships
                    (cruisers and battleships) lying at Helsingfors, protesting against sending
                    Russian troops to France until France accepts Russian slogans. A resolution of
                    the Union of Soldiers and Sailors calls for the confiscation of foreign banks
                    and the expulsion from Russia of foreign capitalists. …</p>
                <p>The great demonstration set by the All-Russian Convention for Sunday July 1, that
                    brought terror to the hearts of the Petrograd populace who left the city in
                    great numbers for the day, passed off quietly, as any other great parade might
                    have, except in two instances where banners for the Temporary Government were
                    torn with the natural resulting confusion. The convention had no intention of
                    organizing a parade until it became known, during the night of June 22, that the
                    Maximalists were secretly preparing a grand armed demonstration against the
                    counter-revolution, the Temporary Government and the war. After the
                    uncompromising embargo laid on this Maximalist demonstration by the majority of
                    the convention, the convention found itself so placed that it was forced to
                    organize a manifestation of some sort to escape the accusation of being itself
                    reactionary. This it did in the last three days of the week of June 24.</p>
                <p>The Maximalists were in the majority, as most of the parties supporting the
                    Temporary Government, including the Cossacks, determined at the last moment not
                    to parade, and the enormous number of placards they had carefully prepared for
                    the workmen and radical troops to carry gave the entire parade a color strongly
                    at variance with the ideas of the convention majority. Every tenth placard bore
                    the legend, “Down with the counter-revolution! “The other placards read, “Down
                    with the Temporary Government!” “Down <pb facs="0178" n="104" xml:id="pg_104"/>
                    with the ten capitalist Ministers!” “Down with the war!” “All power to the
                    Councils of Workmen’s and Soldiers’ Deputies!” and the whole propaganda of the
                    Maximalists was summed up in the many placards, “Bread, peace and liberty!”</p>
                <p>In spite of the ban laid by the convention majority on the bearing of arms in the
                    parade, the anarchists, who appeared in far greater numbers than ever before,
                    had an armed guard around each of their black banners. Several such banners bore
                    a skull and crossbones and the legend, “Death to the capitalists!”</p>
                <p>After the parade a body of anarchists went to the Kresty prison on the Viborg
                    side and demanded the release of certain anarchists and Maximalists, as well as
                    several other radicals arrested on charges of being German spies. The head of
                    the prison released the men. At the same time a jail delivery took place at the
                    transfer prison and 480 prisoners awaiting transfer to other prisons and courts
                    escaped. The anarchists and Maximalist crow proceeded to the Villa Durnovo with
                    the freed persons. In the meantime the Temporary Government issued strict orders
                    to the Minister of Justice, who at once proceeded to the villa with troops and
                    Cossacks under the personal command of the Commander in Chief of the Petrograd
                    Military District. The Minister demanded the immediate surrender of the escaped
                    convicts, which was refused. The matter was then handed over to the military.
                    The Commander in Chief of the Petrograd District then demanded the surrender,
                    which was also refused. The troops then forced an entrance into the villa
                    through the back windows. A bomb was thrown at them but it failed to explode. An
                    anarchist committed suicide and sixty anarchists and Maximalists were arrested,
                    including the escaped prisoners.</p>
                <p>This is the first time that force has actually been used by the Temporary
                    Government, and the act met with universal approval from all sides except from
                    the Maximalists. On the day after (Monday), workmen and soldiers, and
                    representatives of Maximalist organizations, in small groups, went to the
                    Tauride Palace to the room of the Executive Committee of the Petrograd Council
                    of Workmen’s and Soldiers’ Deputies, demanding the release of the anarchists and
                    Maximalists and announcing the beginning of partial strikes in many factories. A
                    committee was formed for the purpose of obtaining the release of all those
                    arrested, except those under a criminal charge, in twenty-four hours.</p>
                <p>This evidence of a stronger attitude on the part of the Temporary Government,
                    made possible by the assured support of the Cossacks, is the only means of
                    averting the openly talked-of counter-revolution.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WN1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">North Winship</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0179" n="105" xml:id="pg_105"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolution on the War, Adopted at the All-Russian
                            Convention of Delegates from Councils of Workmen’s and Soldiers’
                            Deputies, June 25, 1917</hi>
                    </head>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The present war broke out on account of the imperialistic tendencies
                            of the ruling classes of all countries in their effort to seize new
                            markets and submit small and backward countries to their economic and
                            political influence.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>It leads to the complete economic exhaustion of all countries and
                            peoples and it brings the Russian revolution to the verge of ruin. By
                            swallowing up millions of lives and billions of the national treasure it
                            threatens to further intensify the disorganization inherited from the
                            old régime by Russia, and it brings with it hunger, and it distracts the
                            country’s attention from the labor of fortifying the liberties newly
                            won.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The All-Russian Convention of Councils of Workmen’s and Soldiers’
                            Deputies recognizes, therefore, that the struggle for the quickest
                            possible conclusion of the war is the most important current task of the
                            revolutionary democracy. This task is made important both by the
                            interests of the revolution and by the eagerness of the working classes
                            of all countries to put an end to the mutual slaughter and again
                            establish their brotherly union in order to fight together for the
                            complete freedom of humanity.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The All-Russian Convention recognizes: (1) that for the war to end by
                            the crushing of one of the two groups of belligerents by the other would
                            cause new future wars and would even further deepen the differences
                            between peoples and bring them to complete exhaustion, hunger and ruin;
                            (2) that a separate peace would strengthen one of the belligerent
                            groups, make it possible for it to attain a decisive victory over the
                            other group, increase the annexationist appetites of the ruling classes,
                            fail to free Russia from the claws of world imperialism, and hinder the
                            international union of the working classes, and therefore the convention
                            categorically rejects any policy that is, in practice, directed toward a
                            separate peace, or the threshold to a separate peace—a separate
                            armistice.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>An attempt on Russia’s part to attain the peace program she desires by
                            means of a break with the Allies and a declaration of war against all
                            Europe would mean the final ruin of Russia.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>In view of the fact that the war can only be ended by the united
                            efforts of the democracies of all countries, the convention states that
                            it is necessary (1) for the democracy of Russia, through its empowered
                            agent, the All-Russian Convention of Councils of Workmen’s and Soldiers’
                            Deputies, to address an appeal to the democracies of all nations, urging
                            them to accept the slogan “peace without annexations or contributions,
                            on the basis of each nation’s right to determine its own future” and to
                            put pressure to bear on their respective governments along this line;
                            (2) for the revolutionary democracy of Russia to work toward the
                            earliest possible reestablishment of the International, the earliest
                            possible summoning of an international socialist conference to
                            reestablish the international solidarity of the working class, the
                            outlining of final peace terms, and ways and means of realizing these
                            final peace terms; (3) for the revolutionary democracy of Russia to draw
                            the attention of the democracies of all belligerent powers to the fact
                            that their insufficiently energetic opposition to the latest
                            announcements of their respective governments about the annexationist
                            objects of the war puts the Russian revolution in an extremely difficult
                            position and hinders the international union of the working
                            class.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>In order to realize the above aims it is necessary to send delegates
                            to the Allied and neutral countries immediately and to invite delegates
                            to Russia from the socialists of all tendencies from these
                            countries.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>The convention decisively protests against the difficulties that the
                            imperialistic governments have put in the way of these
                            delegations.</item>
                        <pb facs="0180" n="106" xml:id="pg_106"/>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>Recognizing the fact that the temporary revolutionary government has
                            based its foreign policy on the peace program adopted by the Russian
                            democracy, the convention holds it to be necessary for the government to
                            take all the steps it can, and as soon as possible, in order to bring
                            about the adherence of the countries allied to Russia to this
                            program.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>The convention holds it necessary for the government to undertake all
                            possible steps now in order to bring about the revision of the treaties
                            with the Allied Governments along the line of a decisive surrender of
                            annexationist desires. It is necessary to renew the personnel of the
                            Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the Diplomatic Corps by democratizing
                            them as soon as possible, so as to successfully carry out the foreign
                            policy adopted by the Russian democracy.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>The convention announces that until the war is ended by the
                            international efforts of democracy, the Russian revolutionary democracy
                            is bound to take every possible measure to strengthen the fighting power
                            of the army and its ability to undertake both defensive and offensive
                            action, because the wreck of the Russian front would be equivalent to a
                            defeat administered to the Russian revolution and a heavy blow to the
                            entire international democracy.</item>
                        <label>12.</label>
                        <item>In particular, the convention deems that the question as to an
                            aggressive forward movement of the army should be decided purely on
                            strategical grounds.</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
