<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>106. Despatch From the Consulate General at Leopoldville to the to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-08-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-08-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recSWpZOc8YpkYHHD" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008008484"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Public affairs</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general">Consular offices</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="reccab053b473a4a56" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-i" subject="world-war-i" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148236" lcsh-match="exact">Councils</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-08-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-08-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="106"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d106">
                <head>106. Despatch From the <gloss type="from">Consulate General at
                        Leopoldville</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d106fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 122.536H3/8–2757. Confidential. Also sent to Brussels and repeated to
                        Elisabethville, Luanda, and Yaoundé.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 40</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Leopoldville</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-08-27">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 27, 1957</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="references">
                    <head>REF</head>
                    <item>Embassy Brussels D–132, August 2, 1957;<note n="2" xml:id="d106fn2">Not
                            printed. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 122.536H3/8–257)</note>
                        <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 27, repeated to Brussels 306<note
                            n="3" xml:id="d106fn3">Telegram 27 requested the Consulate General’s
                            views on the Embassy’s suggestions, conveyed in despatch 132 cited in
                                <ref target="#d106fn2">footnote 2</ref> above, that the Belgians
                            should be told that any U.S. official who encouraged a Congolese
                            independence movement would be recalled but that the Consulate General
                            could not conduct its business without dealing with Congolese. (<hi
                                rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>)</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Activities of the United States Government Personnel in the Congo</item>
                </list>
                <p>In the reference despatch on the above subject, Mr. <persName>Sprouse</persName>
                    reports a conversation in which M. <persName>Jacques Delvaux de
                        Fenffe</persName>, Director General of Political Affairs in the Belgian
                    Ministry of Foreign Affairs, asserted that the Consulate General at Leopoldville
                    was giving the impression of encouraging independence or liberation movements in
                    the Congo as a result of contacts of United States Government personnel with
                    political leaders of the three political movements known as Conscience
                    Africaine, Abako, and Royaumedu Congo.<note n="4" xml:id="d106fn4">A second
                        complaint made by M. <persName>Delvaux</persName>, to the effect that the
                        Consulate General refused to comply with Belgian requirements for
                        immatriculation of its non-officer personnel, is being treated in a separate
                        dispatch. [Footnote in the source text. The despatch referred to is not
                        printed.]</note>
                    <pb facs="0341" n="315" xml:id="pg_315"/> M. Delvaux stated that these contacts
                    between United States Government personnel and these political movements were of
                    a nature to demonstrate a marked interest in these independence movements and
                    represented definite encouragement thereof. M. <persName>Delvaux</persName>
                    charged that our Public Affairs Officer, Consul <persName>Gilbert E.
                        Bursley</persName>, had been particularly active in contacts with the
                    leaders of these political movements and expressed the hope that he would not
                    return to the Congo at the end of his home leave. These are serious allegations,
                    which, if true, would reflect very adversely on the Consulate General and on me
                    personally.</p>
                <p>This despatch sets forth a detailed record of the post’s contacts with Africans
                    since my arrival here in late October 1956. It is hoped that this record will
                    prove useful in further conversations to be undertaken with the Belgian
                    Government on this subject. If the Department approves, I shall use this record
                    in a future conversation with the Governor General or the Vice Governor General
                    here.</p>
                <p>So far as we are able to determine, there is no substance whatever to the
                    allegations made by M. <persName>Delvaux</persName>. On the contrary, as the
                    record below shows, my colleagues and I have been so conscious of Belgian
                    sensitivities and so determined to avoid any suspicion of exactly the kind of
                    activities described by M. <persName>Delvaux</persName> that we have refrained
                    almost entirely from contacts with Africans, with the result that our reporting
                    on developments in the Congo has been impaired.</p>
                <p>[Here follows a detailed account of contacts with Africans by the Consulate
                    General’s staff.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Conclusions</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The foregoing record shows that American employees of the Consulate
                        General, with the exception of Vice Consul Bearce, have had only a minimum
                        of contacts with Africans, whether political leaders or not. It must be
                        concluded, therefore, that this latest protest in Brussels is based on
                        either a misunderstanding of the facts or a misinterpretation of them. On
                        the principle that one might as well be hanged for a sheep as for a lamb, my
                        colleagues and I are now inclined to regret that we did not do more in
                        developing contacts with Africans!</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The new protest obviously reflects once more the extreme sensitivity of
                        the Belgian authorities about anything done or said by Americans with regard
                        to the Belgian Congo and Ruanda-Urundi <pb facs="0342" n="316"
                            xml:id="pg_316"/> and, in particular, to anything done or said by the
                        American personnel at this post. Our personnel has been urged to be even
                        more circumspect than ever in their activities here, especially in relation
                        to Africans, and to report to me any contacts with Africans.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The new protest probably reflects an increasing anxiety among Belgian
                        officials, in both Brussels and Leopoldville, over the beginning of
                        political activity and unrest in the Congo. After 75 years of relative
                        tranquillity in the political sphere, the Belgian Administration is now
                        being confronted by an ever increasing number of évolués who are conscious
                        of events elsewhere in Africa, critical of one or more aspects of life in
                        the Congo, and ambitious to participate in the government of their country.
                        The Belgians are probably unhappy about these developments and anxious about
                        the future; and, being human, they tend to blame anything unpleasant on
                        someone else. In looking for a scapegoat, they quite naturally regard the
                        United States as a leading candidate. As Mr. <persName>Sprouse</persName>
                        rightly points out in his despatch, the Belgians are beginning to fall into
                        the same state of mind as the French did concerning Morocco in the early
                        1950’s.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>As Mr. <persName>Sprouse</persName> suggests in his memorandum for use in
                        a conversation with the Belgian Ambassador in Washington, one wonders
                        whether any évolué can be said to be politically active or inactive.
                        However, even though the Consulate General has made no special effort—as
                        charged—to seek out the politically active évolués, the Consulate General
                        will certainly have to make sure in the future that its contacts include
                        Africans in all walks of life and with non-political as well as political
                        interests. It should be noted that among the fairly large group of évolués—a
                        term that has only economic and social connotations—there is a small group
                        of African immatriculés who have a legal status giving them all the rights
                        and privileges of Europeans.<note n="5" xml:id="d106fn5">There are three
                            terms used to describe the more advanced Africans: évolués are those who
                            have had enough education to speak French; holders of the Carte de
                            Merite Civile are the more advanced évolués, whose children may attend a
                            European school; and immatriculés are those who are found, by careful
                            examination by a committee, to dress, live, and eat like Europeans and
                            who are legally granted the status of “Europeans”. They report to the
                            Population Blanche rather than the Population Noire on all official
                            matters. [Footnote in the source text.]</note> What few contacts we have
                        had with Africans, have been almost entirely with the immatriculés, who are
                        legally “Europeans”. It is quite clear, in connection with the present issue
                        and with many others, that the Belgian authorities are trying to do two
                        contradictory things at the same time—to turn the most advanced of the
                        African évolués into Europeans but to continue to treat them as
                        Africans.</item>
                    <pb facs="0343" n="317" xml:id="pg_317"/>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The Consulate General is grateful for the response made to M.
                            <persName>Delvaux</persName> by Mr. <persName>Sprouse</persName> and
                        warmly endorses the memorandum proposed by Mr. <persName>Sprouse</persName>
                        as the basis of a conversation with the Belgian Ambassador. It would suggest
                        only one addition: the Belgian Government might be asked to be more specific
                        and name the persons we are alleged to have seen too frequently.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The Consulate General suggests that the Belgian authorities be asked for
                        specific suggestions as to how our personnel here can keep in touch with
                        local leaders in the Congo, as do our consular offices as well as diplomatic
                        offices elsewhere in the world, and report the views of the African leaders
                        on political, economic, and social developments. If the Consulate General is
                        to refrain even more than it has in the past from developing contacts with
                        African leaders, its reporting to Washington will become even more
                        inadequate in this regard than it is at present. It has been our hope that
                        during the next year or so the post could submit voluntary reports on such
                        political subjects as the implementation of the Statut des Villes<note n="6"
                            xml:id="d106fn6">A municipal reform effective March 26, intended to give
                            Africans a means of taking part in urban administration. The African and
                            European quarters of Elisabethville, Jadotville, and Leopoldville were
                            to be integrated into a new administrative unit or ville.</note> and the
                        development of the advisory councils, which obviously have a direct bearing
                        on the whole future, including the economic future, of the Belgian Congo. We
                        also hope to report on several subjects that have political implications,
                        such as the growth of an African middle class, the present status of African
                        education, and a required basic report on labor. None of these reports will
                        be complete unless the officers concerned can talk with African leaders as
                        well as with Belgians. In fact, Vice Consul Gross proposed six months ago
                        that he prepare a report on the African middle class; but I discouraged him
                        because it would require too much direct contact with Africans.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>There are two minor adjustments that might possibly be made here, quite
                        independently of any consultation with the Belgian authorities. <list>
                            <item>First, in view of the evident sensitivity of the Belgian
                                authorities to <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> activities,
                                perhaps it would be wise to soft-pedal those activities somewhat for
                                the next year or so. Rather than eliminate any single function, it
                                might be advisable to decrease the staffing pattern from what it was
                                earlier this year. Originally <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss>
                                had 2 officers and 1 American assistant; then, for a long period, 1
                                officer and 1 assistant; and more recently, beginning last February,
                                again 2 officers and 1 assistant. With the departure of Public
                                Affairs Officer Bursley, it is recommended that for the present the
                                    <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> staff <pb facs="0344"
                                    n="318" xml:id="pg_318"/> consist of Consul Stephen and 1 <hi
                                    rend="italic">capable, French-speaking</hi> assistant.
                                Alternatively, if a second officer is to be appointed he should be a
                                young, <hi rend="italic">French-speaking</hi>, junior officer,
                                preferably a trainee, without a consular title. Either arrangement
                                would have the additional advantage of reducing our number of
                                consular titles. Furthermore, the English classes could be continued
                                on a more modest basis, even though there are some <hi rend="italic"
                                    >350</hi> applications pending, and with a special effort being
                                made to include Belgians as well as Africans.</item>
                            <item>Second, the literal translation of American Information Service is
                                Services Americains d’Information, which in French can mean American
                                Intelligence Service. This awkward translation, which presumably has
                                created difficulty in other French-speaking countries, probably
                                creates some confusion in the minds of the public here and perhaps
                                even among the officers of the Administration. (The Administration,
                                however, uses the title Service de l’Information for its own
                                agency.) Mr. <persName>Bursley</persName> mentioned his concern
                                about this matter several times. After his departure for home leave,
                                I substituted in the new Consular Corps list the phrase Relations
                                Publiques for Services d’Information. It might be advisable for
                                    <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> gradually and quietly to
                                change its signs and letterheads to Relations Publiques, and next
                                year to make the same change in the local telephone
                                directory.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>In conclusion, I must say that I am surprised and disappointed that the
                        Belgian Government should have raised this issue—as well as the
                        immatriculation issue, discussed separately—with the Embassy in Brussels,
                        before allowing the local Administration to discuss it with me here. When I
                        completed my conversation with the Vice Governor General last May in
                        response to the earlier protest of the Belgian Government about the size and
                        activities of the post, he said that he would talk to the Governor General
                        and communicate with me further if necessary. In the absence of any further
                        communication, I had assumed that they were satisfied with the explanation I
                        had made.</item>
                </list>
                <p>In accordance with the stated desire of the Belgian authorities for full and
                    frank understanding of our common interests and problems, it would seem more
                    appropriate for the local Administration to call me in first whenever they are
                    dissatisfied with the activities of the post. If I cannot either remedy a
                    particular situation or provide a satisfactory explanation of it, then they
                    would be fully entitled to raise the matter in Brussels or Washington. In the
                    future, I shall try to see the Governor General or the Vice Governor General
                    more regularly, although they are both extremely busy men, and give them an
                    opportunity to raise such matters if they wish to do so. I shall also ask them
                    periodically about political developments, <pb facs="0345" n="319"
                        xml:id="pg_319"/> explaining that I am aware of their desire that the post
                    not undertake too much political reporting among the Africans.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">James Frederick Green</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
