<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>149. Despatch From the Embassy in Libya to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d149</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">149</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-11-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-11-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="149"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d149">
                <head>149. Despatch From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Libya</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d149fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 601.6173/11–3055. Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 185</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Tripoli</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-11-30">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 30, 1955.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Libyan Exchange of Diplomatic Representatives with <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and the United States Position in
                        Libya</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary:</hi>
                </p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>The Libyan decision to exchange diplomatic representatives with the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> was not made because of any feeling of
                        friendship for Communism or support of the Soviets. Rather it was based on
                        (1) a desire to refute charges that Libya is subservient to the West <pb
                            facs="0448" n="422" xml:id="pg_422"/> and (2) the belief that Western
                        aid to Libya would be increased if we felt that she might turn to the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> for aid.</p>
                    <p>The Embassy feels that continued sporadic anti-Western acts and statements
                        may be expected until the time comes when the Arab World as a whole has been
                        convinced that to be anti-Western is not in itself proof of pro-Arabism. The
                        Embassy is also of the opinion that a carefully considered and realistic
                        analysis of our interests in Libya and the size of the investment we are
                        willing to make to preserve them is essential. When this has been done, the
                        Embassy recommends that we should make our assistance available slowly,
                        using the hope of more as an incentive to keep Libya aligned with the West
                        on major issues but not allowing ourselves to become unduly perturbed by
                        generalized anti-Western statements.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>The announcement on September 25, 1955, that the Governments of Libya and the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> had agreed to exchange diplomatic
                    representatives requires a review of the present trend of Libyan policy and its
                    effect on the position of the United States in Libya. While it is probably too
                    much to say that infiltration of Libya is, in itself, a primary target of the
                    Soviet Union in this area, it is clear that Libya could be important as a means
                    of extending Soviet influence westward across North Africa. Should Libya become
                    a channel through which Communist subversion could be directed and supported in
                    Tunisia, Algeria and Morocco and the usual nationalist and anti-imperialist
                    slogans and agitation (as well as material assistance) used to keep the area in
                    turmoil, <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> would, in effect, be outflanked.
                    It is enough to recall the concern offers the French Government at reports
                    (fortunately false) that anti-French “terrorists” were being assisted from Libya
                    to see the dangerous possibilities of the situation. This Embassy is, of course,
                    not in a position to evaluate Soviet <hi rend="italic">intentions</hi> with
                    regard to Libya. However, on the assumption that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss> desires to exploit North African unrest, it is essential to
                    review the situation and consider counter-measures.</p>
                <p>Obviously, if Libyan-Soviet diplomatic relations presage close and friendly ties
                    between the two countries, the position of the United States here will be
                    seriously undermined. It does not seem to the Embassy, however, that there is
                    any chance that this will occur in the forseeable future. In fact, all
                    indications are that the Libyan decision to agree to repeated Soviet suggestions
                    that the two countries exchange diplomatic representatives was made on entirely
                    different grounds.</p>
                <p>In the first place, Libyan policy for the past year has become more and more
                    openly one of maintaining a balance between the West (especially the US and
                        <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>) and the Arab League (especially Egypt).
                    This is not a new policy, but during the first years of Libyan independence the
                    political and economic realities made it essential that Libya’s primary effort
                    be directed toward stabilizing her relations <pb facs="0449" n="423"
                        xml:id="pg_423"/> with the US, the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, and
                    France and ensuring adequate foreign financial contribution to permit the
                    country to survive economically. While not neglecting the Arab League, Libya
                    found herself unable to take any great part in the consideration of League
                    problems because her own immediate interests lay in negotiations with the
                    West.</p>
                <p>As a result of the conclusion of treaties with the <gloss target="#t_UK1"
                        >UK</gloss> and France and a Base Agreement with the United States, Libya
                    thus became the target of accusations that she was a vassal of the West. Some of
                    these accusations were based on her willingness to make concessions to the West,
                    while others were founded on Libyan unwillingness (and inability) to do more
                    than pay lip service to the two pet themes of Arab extremists—that Israel must
                    be obliterated and that the French presence in North Africa must come to an end.
                    This is one reason why Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_HSMB1">Mustafa Bin
                        Halim</persName> feels that he must make periodic statements (usually in
                    Cairo) in which he plays down Libya’s connections with the West and argues that
                    Libya’s interests are identical with those of the other Arab League States. In
                    the present instance the whole Libyan Government, including the King, seems to
                    have been under the impression that “proof” of Libya’s independence of the West
                    must be provided, and that the exchange of diplomatic representatives with the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> would provide such “proof”.</p>
                <p>In the second place, it seems obvious that Libyan policy makers understand the
                    fact that the West, especially the United States, tends to pay more attention to
                    areas where there is an immediate danger of Soviet penetration. Moreover, there
                    is a wide-spread impression that one good way to obtain assistance from the
                    United States is to flirt with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. For
                    example, <persName>C. Pitt Hardacre</persName>, Principal Finance and Economic
                    Adviser, has hinted slyly that Libya might have to turn to the Soviet bloc for
                    assistance in financing the purchase and rehabilitation of the Tripoli power
                    plant should no funds be forthcoming from Western sources. The Embassy is of the
                    opinion that Libya expects that more attention from the United States and in all
                    probability more assistance will be forthcoming as a result of this recent
                    decision.</p>
                <p>Other factors of less fundamental importance, including the King’s naive
                    explanation to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TJL1">Tappin</persName> that
                    having a Soviet Embassy would mean that the Communists would be in the open and
                    could be watched more easily, were probably taken into consideration. Among
                    these was the Libyan desire to obtain <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    membership, previously blocked by a Soviet veto. It appears, however, that the
                    major reasons for the Libyan decision were those described above: (1) a feeling
                    that such an action would provide a needed “proof” of Libyan independence of the
                    West and (2) the hope that <pb facs="0450" n="424" xml:id="pg_424"/> increased
                    assistance would accrue to Libya as a result of Western reaction to the Soviet
                    threat. If this analysis is correct, the danger of active Libyan cooperation
                    with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> is remote.</p>
                <p>There is as yet no information available as to the form which Soviet diplomatic
                    representation in Libya will take and the Libyan Foreign Office states that to
                    date no request for agrément has been received. Until the size and nature of the
                    Soviet diplomatic mission is known and it actually appears in Libya, it is
                    impossible to evaluate the effect which Soviet activities will have. One obvious
                    move would be the infiltration of potential saboteurs into Wheelus Field Air
                    Force Base, and the Base Commander is already increasing security measures as a
                    precaution.</p>
                <p>To a very real extent, however, the long term Libyan attitude toward such
                    operations as the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> may attempt to initiate
                    here will depend on the attitude and actions of the Western powers, particularly
                    the US and <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>. The Embassy is of the opinion that
                    it is not only possible to prevent the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                    from establishing an advanced base in Libya (assuming that it desires to do so),
                    but that it can be a relatively inexpensive operation. … , and a carefully
                    considered and properly phased continuing program of military assistance to
                    Libya should provide an effective barricade to Soviet penetration of the Libyan
                    Army through … , as well as tying the Army to the West. Continued and expanded
                    assistance to the Libyan Government in the training of police officers is
                    another means by which direct action can be taken to forestall possible
                    subversive activity. In the long run, economic and technical assistance on a
                    realistic scale and an energetic information program should be adequate to
                    prevent the growth of any large indigenous Communist movement. However, in all
                    our thinking and planning it seems to the Embassy that we must keep in mind two
                    important considerations: (1) The Libyan Government will continue to be
                    influenced by criticism from the Arab League to the effect that it is
                    subservient to the West and will take those steps it feels are necessary to
                    refute this criticism. Recent examples of what may be expected are public
                    statements in which Libya is pictured as having been the center of all
                    anti-French activity in North Africa, and flurries of anti-Israeli editorial
                    comment. In addition, we can expect some specific statements or actions tending
                    to align Libya against the West. Until the <pb facs="0451" n="425"
                        xml:id="pg_425"/> Arab World as a whole no longer believes that any
                    anti-Western statement or act is of necessity pro-Arab, Libyan attempts to prove
                    independence and “Arabism” can be expected to take this form. In the meantime,
                    we should not be unduly alarmed by such activities so long as Libya remains a
                    friend on the major issues.</p>
                <p>(2) The Libyan Government will use every means in its power to persuade us to
                    increase our assistance, whether it be technical, economic, or military.
                    Flirtations with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and confidential
                    revelations of offers from the Soviets or their satellites or from other
                    anti-West sources are one tactic which the Libyans will very probably use to
                    obtain favorable action on their requests. One way to handle this type of
                    maneuver would be to give the Libyans immediately anything and everything they
                    request. Obviously this would be unwise, although not impossibly expensive
                    simply because Libya’s total needs plus her total desires are quite limited. A
                    more realistic approach, and one which the Embassy endorses, requires that we
                    first make sure in our own minds exactly how much we are willing to invest in
                    Libya. Having done this, we should under no circumstances reveal our plans in
                    toto to the Libyans. Rather we should move slowly but steadily, staggering our
                    contributions over a period of time and using the hope of more as a “carrot”,
                    but not openly using the threat of reducing assistance. We can, however,
                    tactfully point out on occasion the importance to Libya of continued cooperation
                    with the West. The Embassy feels that this approach to our Libyan policy will
                    produce the desired results, but the key to its success lies in constant
                    attention to the problem of our position in Libya coupled with recognition of
                    the fact that we must concentrate on obtaining Libyan cooperation on <hi
                        rend="italic">major</hi> issues.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>For the Ambassador:<lb/>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">David G. Nes</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">First Secretary of Embassy</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
