<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>321. Telegram From the Mission at the United Nations to the to the Department
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d321</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">321</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-11-20T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-11-20T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recLEJU0igInf5ESh" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005905"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Apartheid</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="rec9aDoDi7sluDnsm" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="civil-rights"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026371"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil rights</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-11-20T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-11-20T16:00:00-05:00" n="321"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d321">
                <head>321. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Mission at the United
                        Nations</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d321fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 845A.411/11–2057. Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-11-20T16:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 20, 1957—4 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 453. For Secretary from <gloss
                        target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss>. Re apartheid. As <gloss target="#t_GA1"
                        >GA</gloss> each year discusses problem racial segregation in South Africa,
                    I find it increasingly difficult justify our position abstention.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d321fn2">Telegram 398 to <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>,
                        October 31, instructed the delegation to abstain on the apartheid resolution
                        then under consideration by the Special Political Committee on the Question
                        of Race Conflict in South Africa. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                        845A.411/10–3157) The draft resolution was adopted on November 4 by a vote
                        of 59 to 5, with 10 abstentions.</note> Declaring as we so often do our
                    belief in moral principles and necessity support Charter, our inability join
                    others this issue has effect confirming suspicion many African and Asian members
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> that on racial and colonial issues we have
                    different standards in judging problems white and non-white peoples. Fortunately
                    this year our stand could in part be mitigated by pointing to our
                    responsibilities on South West Africa Good Offices Comite.</p>
                <p>This question taken up by del before and after consideration in Special Political
                    Comite, del is firmly convinced that if we mean what we say on racial
                    segregation we should be more forthright in our stand in <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss>. Del recommends US revise policy on apartheid before next year
                    with view to supporting moderate resolution critical South African policy this
                    issue for following reasons: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>“Yes” vote on moderate resolution critical of apartheid is most
                            consistent with US beliefs, traditions and law. Ethical position US
                            before world rests on bedrock human rights and civil liberties, <pb
                                facs="0860" n="834" xml:id="pg_834"/> and it is our interest
                            maintain best possible posture on racial questions before <gloss
                                target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Department’s policy abstaining on apartheid was set before Supreme
                            Court’s decision to effect segregation in education was necessarily
                                discriminatory,<note n="3" xml:id="d321fn3">Reference is to the
                                Supreme Court’s decision of May 17, 1954, in the case of <hi
                                    rend="italic">Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka.</hi>
                            </note> before new civil rights legislation, and before President’s
                            decision use troops to enforce decisions Federal Court in Little
                                Rock.<note n="4" xml:id="d321fn4">President <persName
                                    corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> sent Federal troops to
                                Little Rock Arkansas, in September 1957.</note> These developments
                            make it even more important we express ourselves positively on racial
                            issues.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Apartheid arouses strong feelings particularly among peoples of
                            colonial backgrounds. Our abstention regarded by them in simplest terms
                            as meaning we have one standard for white and another for colored races.
                            It will not help us when next we seek Afro-Asian support on US-Soviet
                            issues involving human rights and freedoms.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>Regardless our feelings on desirability apartheid issue being placed
                            before <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, fact is it probably will
                            continue to be and resolution critical of South Africa’s apartheid
                            policies will be put forward. Indians and Pakistanis themselves kept
                            resolution remarkably moderate this year, but because of our known
                            policy of abstention US Del was unable to exert any influence on it. We
                            were not even shown copy until it was introduced. Ability to vote “yes”
                            on resolution along lines of one this year would enable US Del in future
                            to assure <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> action remains moderate and
                            in proper perspective.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>View these considerations US Del urges reconsideration at high level of our
                    present position on apartheid.<note n="5" xml:id="d321fn5">The United States was
                        one of 14 nations abstaining on November 26 when the General Assembly
                        adopted Resolution 1178(XII) by a vote of 59 to 6. The General Assembly
                        thereby appealed to the Union Government “to revise its policy in the light
                        of” the purposes and principles “enshrined in the Charter of the United
                        Nations” and in response to world opinion. See <hi rend="italic">Yearbook of
                            the United Nations 1957,</hi> pp. 98-102.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Lodge</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
