<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-08-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="40" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d40">
                        <head>40. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington,
                            August 9, 1956<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d40fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 350/8–956. Confidential. Drafted
                                by <persName>McKay</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1956-08-09"><hi rend="italic">August 9, 1956</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>French request for United States support for resolution on French
                                Togoland</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LC1">Charles Lucet</persName>, Minister,
                                French Embassy</item>
                            <item>Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName>—<gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Roberts</persName>—<gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Dumont</persName>—<gloss target="#t_AF1">AF</gloss></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>McKay</persName>—<gloss target="#t_ODA1">ODA</gloss></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> telephoned the French
                            Ambassador this morning in order to give the Department’s reply to the
                            request made by the Ambassador to the Secretary on August 7th<note n="2" xml:id="d40fn2">See <ref target="#d39"><hi rend="italic">supra</hi></ref>.</note> for United States support for a French
                            request to the Trusteeship Council to send observers to a forthcoming
                            referendum in French Togoland.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LC1">Lucet</persName>, the French Minister,
                            came to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName>’ office
                            shortly afterward. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName>
                            handed him the attached memorandum, the underlined portions of which are
                            to be introduced in the Trusteeship Council by the United States
                            Delegation as amendments to the text which is being introduced by the
                            French Delegation.<note n="3" xml:id="d40fn3">The attachment is not
                                printed. See <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> doc. T/L.731 and
                                Add.1, and Rev.1 for text of the French draft resolution and
                                revision, together with the Secretary-General’s statement with
                                regard to the financial implications of the proposal. For the U.S.
                                amendments to the draft resolution, see <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> doc. T/L.732.</note> These amendments were
                            previously cleared by <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_WE1">WE</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_AF1">AF</gloss>, and
                                <gloss target="#t_ODA1">ODA</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> explained the U.S.
                            position to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LC1">Lucet</persName> in the
                            following terms: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>We do not like the French text because we are afraid that it
                                    will cause future difficulties for both France and the
                                    U.S.;</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>However, because we appreciate the importance which France
                                    attaches to the problem, as indicated by the Ambassador’s call
                                    on the Secretary, we are not going to vote against the French
                                    text;</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>We are willing either to: <list>
                                        <label>(a)</label>
                                        <item>abstain on the present French text, or</item>
                                        <label>(b)</label>
                                        <item>vote for it after formally introducing the attached
                                            amendments. (Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> explained that we felt it
                                            necessary to introduce these amendments in order to
                                            clarify our position in the <gloss target="#t_TC1">TC</gloss>.)</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <pb facs="0186" n="160" xml:id="pg_160"/>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>We cannot commit ourselves regarding the position we would
                                    take on any amendments that might be proposed by other
                                    delegations; we would have to deal with any such amendments on
                                    their merits;</item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>We want to make it clear to the French Government that our
                                    vote in favor of the resolution would not in any way commit us
                                    to support France in any future <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> difficulties that might arise from the present
                                    French course of action.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> added that the same
                            amendments with the same explanation had just been handed to Mr.
                                <persName>Bargues</persName>, the head of the French Delegation in
                            New York, by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Sears</persName>, the head
                            of the U.S. Delegation.</p>
                        <p>In view of the fact that the Council may end its session tomorrow, the
                            French text and the U.S. amendments might have to be introduced in the
                            Council this afternoon in order to be reproduced by the Secretariat for
                            the vote tomorrow.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LC1">Lucet</persName> thanked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> and said that he would study the
                            amendments and contact Mr. <persName>Bargues</persName> immediately. It
                            was pointed out to him that in view of the urgency of the matter that it
                            would probably be better to leave any future negotiations to Mr.
                                <persName>Bargues</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Sears</persName> in New York.<note n="4" xml:id="d40fn4">The French
                                introduced their draft resolution in the Trusteeship Council on
                                August 9 and the United States followed by introducing its three
                                amendments. <persName corresp="#p_LC1">Lucet</persName> telephoned
                                    <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> on August 10 and
                                asked the United States to substitute for the words “without
                                endorsing the referendum terms” in its third amendment the
                                following: “while reserving its final position as to the terms of
                                the referendum and its stand with regard to future <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> action in conformity with Article
                                76(b).” This was agreed to in the Council later that day.
                                (Memorandum of conversation by <persName>McKay</persName>, August
                                13; Department of State, <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ODA1">ODA</gloss> Files: Lot 62 D 225, Togolands) At
                                its 744th meeting on August 14 the Council was twice deadlocked 7 to
                                7 on the French draft resolution, which thus was defeated. The
                                French announced their intention of proceeding with the referendum
                                anyway. At its 745th meeting, on the same date, the Council adopted
                                a draft resolution introduced by Burma, Guatemala, India, and Syria
                                by a vote of 7 to 5 (France), with 2 abstentions (New Zealand and
                                the United States). For text of Resolution 1499 (XVIII), see <hi rend="italic">Yearbook of the United Nations 1956</hi>, pp.
                                372-373, and 375.</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>