<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-10-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-10-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="55" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d55">
                        <head>55. Instruction From the <gloss type="from">Department of
                                State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Consulate General at
                                Salisbury</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d55fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 601.0045C/10–1557. Confidential.
                                Sent also to Rome, Paris, Lisbon, and London.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><gloss target="#t_CA1">CA</gloss>–3526</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-10-15"><hi rend="italic">October 15,
                                    1957</hi>.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Diplomatic Relations with the Federation of Rhodesia and
                                Nyasaland</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Government of the Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland sent a letter
                            on July 17 to foreign consular offices in Salisbury, including the
                            American Consulate General, stating that the Federation Government is
                            “now ready to consider any representations which may be made to it
                            regarding the establishment in the Federation of a diplomatic mission in
                            charge of a Diplomatic Agent.” The letter emphasized that the Federation
                            itself does not intend immediately to seek establishment of diplomatic
                            missions abroad, and that the initiative for establishing Diplomatic
                            Agencies in the Federation must come from the interested foreign
                            governments themselves.<note n="2" xml:id="d55fn2">Despatch 23 from
                                Salisbury, July 23, transmitted the text of the July 17 letter. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 601.0045C/7–2357) Steere subsequently
                                reported in despatch 46, August 1, that the Federation was looking
                                to the United States to take the lead in establishing diplomatic
                                relations. He advised that it was in U.S. interest to do so without
                                delay and thought such a step would lay the foundation for
                                “friendly” and “advantageous” relations on a permanent basis. He
                                further believed that the United States could exert more influence
                                and pressure on the Federation’s racial policies by initiating full
                                diplomatic relations rather than by withholding recognition. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 601.0045C/8–157) The Assistant
                                Secretary of Commerce for International Affairs, <persName>Henry
                                    Kearns</persName>, seconded Steere’s recommendation in an August
                                30 letter to <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">William M.
                                    Rountree</persName>. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                                611.45C/8–3057)</note></p>
                        <p>While the Federation has not yet been granted full sovereignty or
                            autonomy in international affairs by the United Kingdom, the Department
                            has confirmed that the United Kingdom has no objection to the
                            Federation’s receiving Diplomatic Agents.</p>
                        <p>As far as the Department knows, no country has yet announced any plans
                            for establishing a Diplomatic Agency in Salisbury. The <pb facs="0239" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/> Department understands from the Italian
                            Embassy in Washington that the Government of the Federal Republic of
                            Germany, which has growing commercial interests in the Federation, is
                            very favorably disposed toward the proposal. The Italian Embassy
                            inquired regarding the intentions of the United States; it is the
                            Department’s impression that the Italian Government is also favorably
                            interested in the proposal but that it is awaiting the course of the
                            United States.</p>
                        <p>The Department recognizes that there are several cogent reasons for
                            establishing diplomatic relations with the Federation. Created in 1953,
                            the Federation already has most of the attributes of sovereignty and may
                            well become an independent state within 3 to 5 years. In recent years
                            its rate of economic development has been unsurpassed by any other
                            country in the world. American private investment has reached a high
                            level and can be expected to grow further.</p>
                        <p>The Department considers, however, that the future of this new country
                            depends ultimately on its ability to win the loyalty and cooperation of
                            its African inhabitants, who constitute over 95% of the population but
                            who do not yet play any significant part in the government of the
                            country. Most of the politically conscious Africans opposed the creation
                            of the Federation in 1953 because they considered it to be a device for
                            this perpetuation and extension of white minority rule in that part of
                            Africa. Despite the great economic benefits which have resulted from
                            federation, the opposition of the Africans has intensified; secessionist
                            sentiment is strong in Nyasaland and Northern Rhodesia. The officially
                            professed policy of the Federation Government is one of “racial
                            partnership”, but its implementation to date has apparently been
                            inadequate to counter the opposition of the African nationalists. The
                            white minority electorate which has a virtual monopoly of political
                            power, does not appear to be willing in the near future to endorse any
                            political concessions which would be apt to placate the African
                            inhabitants.</p>
                        <p>The Department has therefore considered very carefully the question of
                            whether the establishment of limited diplomatic relations might enhance
                            the ability of the United States to influence the Federation Government
                            to accelerate the implementation of its racial partnership policy, or,
                            whether such recognition by the United States might be interpreted by
                            both Africans and the governing European element as an endorsement of
                            lip-service support to the policy of racial partnership. In view of the
                            known position of the United States on racial and colonial questions in
                            Africa, it would be preferable that the United States not be the first
                            country to establish diplomatic relations with the Federation. Such an
                            initiative and precedent on the part of the United States might be
                            construed as a gratuitous endorsement of the racial status quo in the
                            Federation and <pb facs="0240" n="214" xml:id="pg_214"/> serve to
                            encourage the latter country’s pressures on the United Kingdom to grant
                            full independence before the future political and social position of the
                            Africans is adequately clarified.</p>
                        <p>If other countries plan, without reference to United States action, to
                            establish diplomatic agencies in Salisbury, the problem of a United
                            States initiative and precedent would no longer apply. Therefore, the
                            Embassies at Rome, Paris and Bonn are requested to ascertain informally
                            whether the Italian, French and German governments definitely intend to
                            send Diplomatic Agents to Salisbury in the near future. In their
                            informal inquiries, these Embassies may mention, but without
                            elaboration, that the initial thinking of the United States is that its
                            appointment of a Diplomatic Agent to Salisbury at this time would be
                            premature.</p>
                        <p>The Embassy at Lisbon should informally ascertain the intentions of the
                            Portuguese Government, but without indicating any United States views or
                            intimating that a political consideration is involved.</p>
                        <p>These four missions should report by despatch the reactions of the
                            respective governments as soon as possible.<note n="3" xml:id="d55fn3">Despatch 758 from Bonn, October 31, reported that Germany did not
                                wish to be first to appoint a diplomatic agent though, if the United
                                States led the way, it might designate one. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 601.0045C/10–3157) The French were in no rush to
                                act, thinking that it would be premature. (Despatch 594 from Paris,
                                October 23; <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 601.5145C/10–2357) The
                                Italians expressed no enthusiasm for establishing diplomatic
                                relations with the Federation and intended to say nothing for the
                                moment. (Despatch 505 from Rome, October 22; <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 601.6545C/10–2257) The Portuguese were studying the
                                matter and had not yet determined their course of action. (Despatch
                                208 from Lisbon, October 28; <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi>
                                601.5345C/10–2857)</note> Once the Department is informed regarding
                            the thinking of the interested powers, the Consulate General at
                            Salisbury will be instructed regarding the nature of the reply to be
                            made to the letter of July 17 from the Federation Government.<note n="4" xml:id="d55fn4">Telegram 81 to Salisbury, January 25, 1958,
                                contained the points which Steere was to make orally to <persName corresp="#p_WSR1">Welensky</persName> in response to the note of
                                July 17. In essence, the U.S. position was that full diplomatic
                                relations could not be established with non-sovereign states. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 120.245C/1–2558)</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DAW1"><hi rend="strong">Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>