<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Extract From Political Report of the Ambassador in Germany ( (Dodd))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d136</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">136</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-08-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-08-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsxQ6o7GtJ2WzZv" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-08-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-08-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="136"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d136">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">862.00 P.R./204</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Extract From Political Report of the Ambassador in
                        Germany</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Dodd</hi>)<note n="94" xml:id="d136fn94"
                        >Transmitted to the Department by the Ambassador in Germany in his despatch
                        No. 2994, August 19; received August 28.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1936-08-19">undated</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Interim Anti-Jewish Measures</hi>. It has been learned first
                    hand from various sources that it is becoming practically impossible for Jews to
                    obtain passports or have their expired passports renewed. This practice was
                    instituted in Bavaria about a year ago, when the issuance of passports was still
                    a matter for the separate states to handle, but in view of the fact that the
                    latter function has now been taken over by the Reich Government, it would appear
                    that the denial of passports to Jews is based upon a general order. In cases of
                    extreme urgency or for business trips abroad, Jews are being granted travel
                    documents the validity of which is limited to two or three weeks. As far as is
                    known, Jews already in possession of valid passports are not being deprived of
                    them but the present restriction means of course that Jews will be unable to
                    renew their passports after the ordinary five year term of validity has
                    expired.</p>
                <p>While the exact reason for the new policy is not known, it has been suggested
                    that the Government is aware that many German Jews have substantial accounts in
                    foreign countries, and that while it may not be able to prove its suspicions, it
                    is at least taking steps to prevent Jews from following their capital abroad and
                    enjoying its use. (Incidentally the Berlin visa officer of a certain country has
                    stated that he has been surprised to learn as the result of inquiry into the
                    resources of prospective Jewish immigrants, how much money in foreign accounts
                    many applicants have; as he has no precise knowledge of how they transferred
                    their funds from Germany, although he assumes they did it illegally, he has not
                    considered it his duty to report them to the German authorities.) Other
                    suggested reasons for the denial of passports to Jews are first that the
                    Government may desire to limit the emigration of elements who would certainly be
                    hostile to Germany once they had left the country, and secondly that the refusal
                    to Jews of ordinary Reich passports may be preliminary to the introduction of
                    new travel documents which would recognize the division of the population into
                    two classes of “citizens” created by the Nuremberg racial legislation of last
                    year.</p>
                <pb facs="0301" n="202" xml:id="pg_202"/>
                <p>The owners of several large Jewish stores in Berlin who would ordinarily be
                    prohibited from flying the national emblem received instructions from the
                    Propaganda Ministry last month that they should participate in the ordered
                    general display of flags. In view of the efforts made to render the city
                    colorful during the Games the instruction is viewed as quite the reverse of a
                    concession and it is no exaggeration to say that the Jewish population awaits
                    with fear and trembling the termination of the Olympic period which has
                    vouchsafed them a certain respite against molestation, although it may be
                    doubted whether the National Socialists will be quite so foolish as to spoil the
                    good impression upon foreign opinion made by the management of the Games by an
                    immediate resumption of the more spectacular anti-Jewish activities.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
