<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-05-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-05-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="19" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d19">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.60F31/138</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Czechoslovakia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wright</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 441</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Prague</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-05-19">May 19, 1936</date>.<lb/>[Received June
                                2.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In continuation of my despatch No. 437 of
                            May 6, 1936, and subsequent telegraphic correspondence, especially my
                            telegram No. 11, May 19, 4 p.m., I have the honor to report as follows
                            regarding the further developments which have taken place here in
                            connection with the discussion of the <hi rend="italic">Modus
                                Vivendi</hi> at present governing Czechoslovak-United States trade
                            relations.</p>
                        <p>The enclosures to this despatch are as follows:<note n="14" xml:id="d19fn14">Enclosures not printed.</note>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>A copy of the written reply from the Foreign Office to the <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi> a copy of which was enclosed
                                    in my despatch No. 437.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>A copy of a supplemental <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                                    regarding apparent discriminatory treatment in respect to
                                    paints, varnishes, polishes and certain other chemicals falling
                                    under Tariff Item 624—evidence of which was brought to my
                                    attention subsequent to the preparation of the first <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi>.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>A self-explanatory memorandum of my conversation with the
                                    Chief and Assistant Chief of the Economic Section of the Foreign
                                    Office on May 14th.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>A supplementary <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi> dated May
                                    18th and handed to these officials on that date in partial reply
                                    to the aforementioned written reply of the Foreign Office to my
                                    first <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi>.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>A self-explanatory memorandum of my conversation with these
                                    officials on the same date (May 18, 1936).</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>These documents should be read in the order mentioned and while I regret
                            that they may be considered somewhat lengthy, they will be found to give
                            such a clear idea of the nature of the negotiations as well as the
                            apparent inability—I shall not yet say unwillingness—of these officials
                            to submit at once a comprehensive explanation of certain of the more
                            glaring irregularities, that I believe that they will be found worthy of
                            perusal.</p>
                        <p>It will be found in the memoranda of the conversations which took place
                            that reference is repeatedly made to previous discussions of the manner
                            in which quotas are established in this country and the consistency of
                            the quota accorded to American automobiles: this phase <pb facs="0137" n="38" xml:id="pg_38"/> of the subject occupied the greater portion
                            of my first conversation with these officials on April 29th, which it is
                            not necessary to report in detail as it was repeatedly discussed in the
                            later conversations, and it was at this time that the discrepancy arose
                            between the quota accorded us and that stipulated in the
                            Czechoslovak-French Treaty which provides for an importation of 1000
                            French cars per annum.</p>
                        <p>Suffice it to say in this connection that Dr. Friedmann, the Chief of the
                            Section, observed that the Treaty in question had been negotiated at a
                            time when optimism was running fairly high, when the world economic
                            crisis had not yet caused prices and products to fall and when every
                            nation was confidently hoping for large trade. “Therefore”, he said, “We
                            did the best we could, but without a very sound basis”. I informed him
                            in reply that I intended to discuss this phase of the matter later and
                            it is this conversation to which reference is made in the enclosed
                            memoranda of ensuing conversations.</p>
                        <p>After a preliminary discussion of the quota system as practiced in
                            various countries—which was really nothing more than preparatory to the
                            detailed discussions herein reported—the question of exchange
                            difficulties arose. Dr. Friedmann observed with some degree of intensity
                            that in his opinion the American officials in Prague had previously been
                            far from well informed upon such questions, (he was good enough to state
                            that that did not apply to the present incumbents of the Legation,
                            Consulate General and Commercial Attaché’s Office) and added that this
                            lack of information had been seriously enhanced by the attitude of the
                            importers, who were continually complaining about restrictions which
                            they did not understand and who were moreover malicious in intent. At
                            this point I improved the opportunity of stating that I was trying to
                            demonstrate that the competent American officials in Prague were well
                            informed upon these points, and also that the importers in question were
                            in no case American citizens but in all (or practically all) cases were
                            Czech citizens. I then added that he was quite correct in stating that
                            they were continually registering complaints—which was one of the
                            reasons why I was now making every effort to be fully informed upon
                            every point in question, in order that I might not only so inform my
                            Government but that the Legation and the other officers of the United
                            States Government in Prague might be in a position to deal with such
                            complaints of local importers.</p>
                        <p>Dr. Stangler then observed that he must refute any charge that the
                            Exchange Commission is anything but entirely neutral and completely
                            honest, and he elaborated at some length upon the arrangements which are
                            made in order to assure that no car is admitted into the country unless
                            the payment of duty has been made or is assured. I replied that I
                            trusted that the observation made under item 1 (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) would not be <pb facs="0138" n="39" xml:id="pg_39"/> construed
                            as any accusation whatever on the part of this Legation as regards the
                            practices or ethics of the Exchange Commission: in fact it had been very
                            carefully worded so as to place the responsibility for such allegations
                            upon “persons considered competent in the automotive trade”, which were
                            by no means confined to exporters of American nationality but, as I had
                            said before, included importers of non-American nationality. Dr.
                            Stangler then said that the Commission was always subject to such
                            attacks—having been accused of making special arrangements and
                            agreements with American manufacturers and importers. I replied that I
                            regretted this as much as he and hoped that this would prove an
                            additional reason for complete clarification of all points for the
                            benefit of all concerned.</p>
                        <p>There are also included as accompaniments to this despatch copies of two
                            memoranda prepared by the Office of the Commercial Attaché, dated April
                            29th and May 18th:<note n="15" xml:id="d19fn15">Neither printed.</note>
                            the first prepared by Mr. Theodore Hadraba, Clerk to the Commercial
                            Attaché, which, during the absence of Mr. Woods on leave of absence
                            which had been granted him, was utilized in the preparation of the first
                                <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi> delivered to this Government:
                            the second prepared by Commercial Attaché Woods upon his return which
                            has been, and will continue to be, utilized by both of us in support of
                            our contentions during the conversations—both of which have proven of
                            great value and for which the officials concerned deserve full
                            credit.</p>
                        <p>It is our opinion that in the determination of any quotas which may
                            hereafter be agreed upon, it is absolutely necessary to take into
                            consideration the factor of indirect shipments (see pages 6, 8, 14, 16,
                            19, 21, 24 and 26 of the memorandum of the Commercial Attaché dated May
                            18th).</p>
                        <p>I would also appreciate an expression of your views not only with regard
                            to the applicability of the unconditional most-favored-nation principle
                            to cartel agreements and whether I shall insist that quotas for these
                            products be equal to those granted the most-favored-nation as requested
                            in my telegram of to-day’s date, but also regarding the respective
                            periods which may be considered as representative and the practice of
                            compensatory agreements.</p>
                        <p>Conversations are continuing with regard to the remaining points which
                            have not yet been orally discussed on the basis of this Government’s
                            first reply as well as the various phases of the situation regarding
                            which difficulties have arisen as set forth in the enclosed memoranda of
                            conversations. These conversations are proceeding with the utmost
                            friendliness, and Mr. Woods and I agree that we seem to detect in many
                            instances an attitude of distaste and concern on the part of the Foreign
                            Office officials that a situation has been <pb facs="0139" n="40" xml:id="pg_40"/> allowed to develop as a result of the practices or
                            policy followed by other departments of this Government.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed>J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Butler Wright</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>