<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-08-31T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-08-31T05:00:00-05:00" n="327" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d327">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.5731/143: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Norway</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Biddle</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Oslo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-08-31T11:00:00+01:00">August 31, 1936—11
                                a.m.</date><lb/>[Received 2 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>50. Morgenstierne, Norwegian Minister to Washington, has asked me on
                            behalf of this Government to ascertain as soon as possible whether the
                            American Government would agree to consider a Norwegian move to
                            negotiate a preliminary trade agreement respecting a limited number of
                            items prior to negotiating a broader agreement later. He prefaced his
                            inquiry by stating frankly that Norway’s principal consideration
                            inducing desire for trade agreement with us is hope of regaining
                            American market for whale oil. Accordingly, in order to open an American
                            market to Norwegian whale oil, Morgenstierne indicated that his
                            Government might be prepared to accord improved import facilities to a
                            limited number of American products. Furthermore, since whaling
                            expeditions start December 1st the time element from the Norwegian
                            Government point of view constitutes an important factor. Hence the
                            Norwegian Government desire to reduce to a minimum the period required
                            for public hearings in Washington through limiting this suggested
                            preliminary agreement to as few items as possible. It was suggested, for
                            example, that Norway might grant a concession on American automobiles to
                            compensate us for corresponding concession on whale oil.</p>
                        <p>Compare in the above connection similar Norwegian point of view conveyed
                            to Department by Minister Philip’s despatch No. 509, August 11,
                                1934.<note n="6" xml:id="d327fn6">Not printed.</note> Our
                            preliminary survey here indicates desirability of binding present tariff
                            treatment on the following American imports into Norway: Raw cotton,
                            naval stores, toilet soap, cellulose, lacquer, automobile tires,
                            tobacco, office machines, motion picture films and <pb facs="0499" n="400" xml:id="pg_400"/> electric refrigerators. The most important
                            items to be recommended for duty reductions include: apples, pears,
                            dried and canned productive packing house products, salmon, silk hosiery
                            and motor vehicles. It is expected that all commodity digests should be
                            completed and transmitted by September 15. I do not believe the
                            Norwegians would be willing to make concessions on more than two or
                            three items in return for any import facilities granted to their whale
                            oil. I am also convinced that while rejection of Norwegian proposal for
                            preliminary agreement would be disappointing to Norwegians it would not
                            be a serious impediment to negotiation of general trade agreement.
                            Please telegraph our Government’s decision on the above Norwegian
                            proposal for communication to Morgenstierne.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Biddle</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>