<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-12-04T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-12-04T12:00:00-05:00" n="534" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d534">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">852.00/3993: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Germany</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Dodd</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-12-04T18:00:00+01:00">December 4, 1936—6
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received December 4—2:52 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>359. The British Embassy here states confidentially that it has
                                received a report from the British Consul at Seville that about
                                5,000 Germans passed through that city a few days ago on their way
                                to join the Spanish Nationalist forces and that although they did
                                not wear uniforms they were equipped with rifles and some artillery
                                pieces. It is understood that prior to this or about the 20th last
                                month a German anti-aircraft detachment consisting of some 700 men
                                with equipment was landed in Cadiz. Most of the Germans despatched
                                to Spain appear to have some connection with the German Army either
                                as reserves or as regular soldiers who while technically on a leave
                                status have “volunteered” for service abroad. They have apparently
                                sailed from Stettin and it is said that a liner from the east
                                Prussia service is being used as troop transport. It is believed
                                that the actual <pb facs="0686" n="587" xml:id="pg_587"/> recruiting
                                and organization is being undertaken possibly by a party political
                                body rather than by the Army authorities themselves who however are
                                being “accommodating” in furnishing facilities.</p>
                            <p>German official news sources do not deny that German nationals are
                                fighting in Spain but maintain that none has been sent or are
                                present there as regular German Army units. The same line was taken
                                by the DDPK<note n="24" xml:id="d534fn24">Deutsche
                                    Diplomatisch-Politische Korrespondenz (organ of the German
                                    Foreign Office).</note> yesterday which, recalling that last
                                August Germany suggested an embargo being put upon foreign
                                volunteers, complains against the hypocrisy of the same circles
                                which defeated the German proposal in now being indignant “if
                                Germans including such persons whose existence was destroyed when
                                they withdrew from red Spain should voluntarily fall into line in
                                the dam against the international red flood”. The commentary
                                stresses that the participation of volunteers does not infringe the
                                non-interference agreement and official circles declare that Germany
                                has no intention of leaving the Noninterference Committee.</p>
                            <p>While it is recognized that a considerable proportion of the Germans
                                fighting in Spain may consist of former residents there the despatch
                                nevertheless of trained soldiers is causing concern in diplomatic
                                circles here where it is thought that Germany is evidently as
                                determined as Italy that Franco shall not fail and is probably
                                choosing to lend assistance in the land fighting in order to avoid
                                possible naval complications with Great Britain. Hitler’s policy
                                respecting the Spanish situation is causing apprehension in official
                                German quarters including the Army and in all except possibly the
                                most radical Nazi groups. Even here, however, we understand that the
                                length of the siege of Madrid may have a salutary effect in
                                discouraging the belief that a war can be won in a single swift blow
                                without prolonged fighting.</p>
                            <p>Copies by mail to London, Paris, Borne.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Dodd</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>