<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom ( (Bingham) ) to the Acting Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d548</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">548</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-12-09T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-12-09T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-12-09T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-12-09T15:00:00-05:00" n="548"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d548">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">852.00/4040: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bingham</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-12-09T20:00:00+00:00"
                            >December 9, 1936—8 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received December 9—3:45 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>601. It will be noted that the view expressed by Eden reported in my 600 December
                    9, 7 p.m., is at variance with the views of the Assistant Secretary of State in
                    charge of Spanish affairs and the French Embassy, as reported in my 593,
                    December 3, 6 p.m., and 595, <pb facs="0698" n="599" xml:id="pg_599"/> December
                    4, 4 p.m., and also the views of Vansittart reported in my despatch 2697,
                    December 4.<note n="33" xml:id="d548fn33">Despatch not printed; Vansittart
                        confirmed the statements of the British Foreign Office respecting the
                        Spanish situation transmitted in telegram No. 593, December 3, 6 p.m., from
                        the Ambassador in the United Kingdom, <ref target="#pg_585">p.
                        585</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I venture my personal opinion that in seeking any action by the American
                    Government Eden confuses the fact that, while he suggests we should make a
                    statement “blessing” any effort to end the Civil War in Spain, what he really
                    wishes is support of the British and French thesis against interference in the
                    Spanish situation by the Governments of Italy, Germany and Russia. While it may
                    be true as Eden states that fully three-fourths of the Spanish people have had
                    enough blood to satisfy them, I believe from the sources of information
                    available to me that this applies to the inarticulate mass of the people and as
                    the situation stands today I am not at all convinced that the leaders on either
                    side in the Spanish struggle desire to arrest the Civil War until their
                    particular side is victorious.</p>
                <p>In my opinion therefore the French and British Governments are seeking a
                    compromise solution of peace without victory in Spain primarily to ease the
                    European situation. Consequently I am led to the conclusion that the United
                    States Government should be very clear in its mind before it reaches any
                    decision to make a public statement in regard to Spain, that it does not become
                    by implication involved in the larger European issues inherent in the
                    situation.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bingham</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
