<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-04-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="61" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d61">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.5131/1487</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Phillips</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-04-30">April 30, 1936</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The French Ambassador called this afternoon to inform me, so he said, of
                            the “good news” which he had received from his Government with respect
                            to the trade agreement. His Government had accepted substantially all of
                            the concessions requested by the United States; one point relating to
                            apples and pears would be decided at a special meeting of the Cabinet to
                            be held tomorrow morning at 10 o’clock and, therefore, by two or three
                            in the afternoon he was hopeful of receiving a telegram with regard to
                            this point. Furthermore, the Government was very anxious to sign the
                            agreement on Saturday or Sunday at the latest,—and this for “political”
                            reasons. At this point I questioned the Ambassador as to what he meant
                            by political reasons, as if the agreement were signed on Saturday or
                            Sunday I could not see that it would have any political repercussions on
                            the Sunday’s elections. The Ambassador replied that it was not a
                            question of affecting the elections, but merely that there would be an
                            interim government after Sunday which would not have sufficient power to
                            put through the agreement without parliamentary approval. The present
                            government, therefore, while continuing in power might not feel able to
                            approve such an important matter as the trade agreement.</p>
                        <p>We discussed at some length our view, which was to sign next week; we
                            felt that it would be unfortunate to have a gap between the date of <pb facs="0192" n="93" xml:id="pg_93"/> signing and the date of giving
                            publicity to the agreement; should the signing take place on Saturday,
                            it would take, I said, a week before we should be ready with our
                            prepared publicity and, in the circumstances, therefore, it would be
                            absolutely essential for both governments to refrain from any leakage
                            with respect to any part of the agreement. The Ambassador readily agreed
                            that it would be better to limit any statement which would be made after
                            the signing on Saturday to a mere statement of the fact of signature; he
                            suggested that we prepare some such statement and let him telegraph it
                            to Paris this afternoon for the approval or suggestions of his
                            Government; the statement should, of course, be issued simultaneously in
                            Paris and Washington.</p>
                        <p>I said that I appreciated the situation in which the French Government
                            found itself and that we would proceed on the theory that we would sign
                            on Saturday<note n="11" xml:id="d61fn11">On May 1, the French Ambassador
                                telephoned to the Under Secretary that the French Government had
                                consented to the delay requested by the Department of State
                                (651.5131/1490).</note> and I promised to send him up this afternoon
                            the suggestion that he asked for.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">William Phillips</hi></signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>[For text of reciprocal trade agreement between the United States and
                                France, signed at Washington, May 6, 1936, and related notes, see
                                Department of State Executive Agreement Series No. 146, or 53 Stat.
                                2236. For press releases regarding the trade agreement, see
                                Department of State, <hi rend="italic">Press Releases</hi>, May 9,
                                1936, page 428; May 16, 1936, pages 448–484; May 23, 1936, pages
                                501–503.]</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>