<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Third Secretary of Embassy in Spain ( (Wendelin) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d619</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">619</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-07-29T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-07-29T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recRAvRT7ZvyjvRU2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-07-29T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-07-29T13:00:00-05:00" n="619"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d619">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">852.1115/201: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Third Secretary of Embassy in Spain</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wendelin</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-07-29T18:00:00+00:00"
                            >July 29, 1936—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 10:50 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>X–7. My telegram No. X–4 of July 28, 1 p.m. Note from Foreign Office to Chilean
                    Ambassador in reply joint request of Diplomatic Corps for special train to
                    evacuate foreign residents Madrid with formal guarantee of safety states: (1) no
                    special requirement, except those which for reasons of security may be
                    established by the Ministries of Interior and War, is necessary in order to make
                    this journey; (2) it is not necessary to determine in advance the time of
                    departure because railway service with Mediterranean ports is functioning
                    normally and trains are leaving on time; (3) it would not be possible at present
                    to organize special trains because of the necessity of giving preference to the
                    transportation of troops, war material and foodstuffs.</p>
                <p>Diplomatic Corps met at noon today and decided in view of Government’s attitude
                    to seek arrangement with the railroad for additional coaches on regular trains
                    to Alicante and Valencia. As I am in direct touch with manager of the railroad,
                    I am investigating this possibility on behalf of Diplomatic Corps. Railroad is
                    prepared to attach as many additional coaches to daily morning and evening
                    trains as can be carried and will furnish first or third class coaches as
                    desired. Diplomatic Corps meeting tonight to consider feasibility such
                    evacuation and question of safety of passengers en route. Will report further
                    details promptly. Please advise Department’s attitude evacuation by this means.
                    Americans who have voluntarily left by train for Valencia and Alicante during
                    past 3 days believed to have arrived safely.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wendelin</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
