<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-09-07T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-09-07T10:00:00-05:00" n="703" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d703">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">852.00/3043: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul at Seville</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Bay</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Seville</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-09-07T15:00:00+00:00">September 7, 1936—3
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 6:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Following is translation of the Spanish text dated Cáceres September
                                6, received this noon from General Franco: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“His Excellency, the General of the Second Division has
                                        transmitted to me your memorandum relating to the aerial
                                        bombardment of the destroyer <hi rend="italic">Kane</hi>
                                        which took place the afternoon of August 30 last. In reply
                                        to the memorandum, I have the honor to inform you that as a
                                        result of investigations made we have no information that
                                        any plane belonging to the national forces has committed an
                                        act of aggression against any destroyer of another nation;
                                        but since definite aerial attacks have been carried out
                                        against the Red squadron the possibility of an error of such
                                        deplorable consequences cannot be excluded. At the same time
                                        the presence of Red aeroplanes in Malaga and the state of
                                        anarchy of the revolted forces of the navy makes it possible
                                        and even probable that the Marxist forces are responsible
                                        for the aggression referred to.</p>
                                    <p>In regard to the responsibility that attaches to the aerial
                                        forces under my command, I hasten to make known to you, with
                                        the request that it be communicated to the American
                                        Government, the regret which this incident has caused me—an
                                        incident so repugnant to the standards and conduct of the
                                        national forces which respect and uphold lawful procedure. I
                                        avail myself et cetera.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Bay</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>