<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-11-13T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-11-13T07:00:00-05:00" n="795" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d795">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">352.1115/2248: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Portugal</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Caldwell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Lisbon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-11-13T12:00:00+00:00">November 13,
                                        1936—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received November 13—11:20
                                    a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>62. Department telegrams 39 and 40<note n="88" xml:id="d795fn88">Neither printed.</note> and circular November 11, 6 p.m.,<note n="89" xml:id="d795fn89">Circular telegram to all consular
                                    officers in Spain not printed; it contained instructions
                                    regarding relief of Filipinos stranded in Spain (352.11B
                                    15/98).</note> telephoned Graves who dictated following message:
                                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“Court martial sentenced Celaya to 20 years in prison. I am
                                        advised orally that Captain General and Auditor General of
                                        the Eighth Division will approve this sentence. They feel
                                        that they cannot conscientiously take more favorable action
                                        since prosecuting attorney at court requested death
                                        sentence. Sentences not involving death are not usually
                                        subject to higher revision than that of the divisional
                                        authorities.</p>
                                    <p>Although the Department will undoubtedly consider sentence of
                                        20 years severe it should be borne in mind that death or
                                        life imprisonment are virtually the only sentences being
                                        handed down by courts martial trying cases of alleged
                                        military rebellion. The question of the mitigation of
                                        Celaya’s sentence and his ultimate release can be taken up
                                        whenever the Department considers the time opportune.</p>
                                    <p>The Auditor General at Coruna informed me yesterday that
                                        nothing has been heard from Burgos concerning Lamas
                                            case.<note n="90" xml:id="d795fn90">On January 20, 1937,
                                            the Department was informed that the death sentence
                                            imposed upon Francisco Lamas Zarauza had been commuted
                                            to life imprisonment (352.1115/2723, 2860).</note> He
                                        promised to let me know as soon as anything was received.
                                        Referring to Department’s telegram of November 4, 2
                                            p.m.,<note n="91" xml:id="d795fn91">Not printed.</note>
                                        third paragraph, I desire to emphasize that I can find no
                                        evidence that any action or correspondence of Vigo Consulate
                                        has prejudiced insurgent authorities in any case handled by
                                        it. Stewart’s relations with all authorities in the district
                                        excellent.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Caldwell</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>