<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Germany ( (Dodd) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d99</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">99</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-03-30T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-03-30T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-03-30T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-03-30T06:00:00-05:00" n="99"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d99">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">862.00/3584: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Germany</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dodd</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-03-30T12:00:00+01:00"
                            >March 30, 1936—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received March 30—10:50
                        a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>99. The election yesterday resulted in a preliminary estimate, which will not be
                    varied substantially, of 98.79 percent for Hitler, et cetera, <pb facs="0240"
                        n="141" xml:id="pg_141"/> out of 98.95 percent participation. There were
                    45,500,000 odd votes cast of which 45 odd million for Hitler leaving opposition
                    and invalid votes combined of an odd 500,000 votes. The corresponding
                    percentages for the previous votings were 90 percent out of 96.3 in 1933 and
                    89.15 percent out of 95.71 in 1934. Yesterday’s figures are of course not
                    representative of national feeling in the sense of a free election with an
                    “open” opposition. In Germany there was not even an opposition ticket on the
                    ballot. The so-called election was therefore merely a pledge from which it took
                    courage to abstain let alone to vote against. Furthermore, the subject chosen
                    was one which made it tragically difficult for even those hostile to the regime
                    to oppose. For example, even the Catholic Church authorities counselled voting
                    in the affirmative with certain rather pathetic mental reservations. The only
                    organized opposition of which we have heard was that of the Communists. It is
                    reliably reported that efforts have been made during the past week to distribute
                    anti-Government leaflets and to put up anti-Government posters. We understand
                    there have been some two hundred arrests of Communists in Berlin in this
                    connection.</p>
                <p>Without going into the merits of the case or trying to establish the real
                    attitude of the country toward the regime or in favor of Hitler’s action on
                    March 7, the net of it is that this election gives Hitler at least the
                    appearance of complete support for his present policy and represents a record
                    vote in his favor and a correspondingly strong springboard for his next
                    international move tomorrow, Tuesday.<note n="4" xml:id="d99fn4">On March 31,
                        1936, Germany offered a 19-point peace plan for political problems to be
                        followed by a conference on disarmament and economic problems. For text, see
                        British Cmd. 5175, Miscellaneous No. 6 (1936): <hi rend="italic"
                            >Correspondence With the German Government Regarding the German
                            Proposals for an European Settlement, March 24–May 6, 1936</hi>, p.
                        4.</note>
                </p>
                <p>There is still no definite information on this although we are reliably informed
                    that the question of an agreement not to fortify the Rhineland zone for a brief
                    definitive period, say for six months, is being seriously considered. It is
                    becoming increasingly evident that this is the real crux of the situation both
                    from the near and long term view (see my 85 of March 18, 8 p.m.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d99fn5">Not printed.</note>).</p>
                <p>Repeated to London, Paris, Rome, Geneva.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dodd</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
