<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>174. Message From John D. Negroponte of the National Security Council Staff
                    to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the National
                    Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d174</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">174</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1972-12-14T06:56:00-05:00" notAfter="1972-12-14T06:56:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">National reconciliation</term>
                    <term ref="recfglDm81FXoMhAJ" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007327"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Ceasefire</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="rec71J8TWoV3HlQ1Q" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133293"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications equipment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-12-14T06:56:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-12-14T06:56:00-05:00" n="174"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d174">
                <head>174. Message From <persName corresp="#p_NJD_1">John D. Negroponte</persName>
                    of the National Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d174fn1">Source: Library of Congress, Manuscript
                        Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box
                            <gloss target="#t_TS_1">TS</gloss> 43, Geopolitical File, Vietnam,
                        Bombing, 1972–73. Top Secret; Sensitive; Eyes Only. Sent via <persName
                            corresp="#p_GGR_1">Guay</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1"
                            >Haig</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1972-12-14T11:56:00+00:00">December 14, 1972,
                        1156Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_WH_1">WH</gloss> 46. Subject: Hanoi’s behavior in the
                    negotiations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary:</hi> The purpose of this paper is to summarize
                    Hanoi’s negotiating behavior both in substance and procedure since the reopening
                    of the negotiations on November 20. It concludes that Hanoi has no intention to
                    meet any of the basic requirements that we made clear to them at the end of
                    October; and through a series of irritating dilatory tactics has pursued a
                    course which can be interpreted as desire to achieve either no agreement at all
                    or an agreement substantially worse than that achieved in late October. Hanoi’s
                    tactics have been clumsy, blatant, and fundamentally contemptuous of the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">End summary.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Substance:</p>
                <p>We came back to Paris on November 20 on the assumption that some of our essential
                    concerns about the October draft agreement could be met. Those concerns were
                    made clear to Hanoi well before our first meeting.</p>
                <p>When we entered into the new phase of negotiations with Hanoi in October we did
                    so on the assumption that there had been a fundamental shift in their strategy
                    and that they were willing to take some risks in the pursuit of a peaceful
                    settlement. At that time we acknowledged that to drop their demand for the
                    dismantlement of the <gloss target="#t_GVN_1">GVN</gloss> represented a
                    significant departure from their previously enunciated policies. Both sides
                    recognized that the pursuit of a settlement on this basis involved taking
                    chances and it seemed, for a period at least, that U.S. and <gloss
                        target="#t_DRV_1">DRV</gloss> interests had converged sufficiently to form
                    the basis for a settlement. This is to say that we were prepared to disengage
                    from South Vietnam in exchange for which Hanoi was willing to forego
                    accomplishment of all its objectives in the South immediately.</p>
                <p>Among the essential elements of this negotiating framework were Hanoi’s apparent
                    willingness to leave the political process in the South <pb facs="0675" n="632"
                        xml:id="pg_632"/> to a reasonable period of evolution, to restrict its right
                    to intervene militarily in the South by accepting a prohibition on further
                    infiltration, and their agreement to withdraw forces from Laos and Cambodia.</p>
                <p>As the latest series of negotiations have unfolded, however, it has become clear
                    that Hanoi is either dissatisfied with or undecided about an arrangement that
                    gives it a better than equal chance of ultimately achieving its objectives.
                    Whether they have decided to scuttle the agreement or not, their present course
                    seems devoted to the pursuit of every minor tactical advantage with little
                    perspective for the longer term.</p>
                <p>When we resumed the talks on the 20th of November we came with three basic
                    objectives, none of which would have been that difficult to settle had Hanoi
                    really wanted to do so. First, we wanted some modifications in language in the
                    political chapter so as to make it absolutely clear that the National Council of
                    National Reconciliation and Concord did not have governmental functions. Second,
                    we wanted to obtain an inoffensive phrase somewhere in the agreement which
                    established the principle, however indirectly, that the North Vietnamese did not
                    have the unequivocal right to intervene militarily in South Vietnam. Lastly we
                    wanted to insure that there was some effective international supervisory
                    mechanism in place at the time of ceasefire.</p>
                <p>What has been the record on these three issues?</p>
                <p>We have achieved a very minor success in diluting the functions of the National
                    Council of National Reconciliation and Concord and we have succeeded in
                    obtaining the deletion of the description of the Council as an “administrative
                    structure” which they have mistranslated from the very outset. But in exchange
                    Hanoi has pressed for every conceivable political concession which, if accepted,
                    would render the political provisions of the agreement even more onerous than
                    had been before and would in fact call into question the very principle on which
                    our willingness to proceed in October was actually based. First they agreed to
                    drop the maintenance of the ceasefire and the preservation of peace as functions
                    to be ascribed to the Council but now they have asked that among the functions
                    to be added to the Council’s responsibilities is the promotion of the
                    implementation of the agreement’s attached protocols. In military as well as
                    political matters, it is clear that one of their primordial objectives is to
                    deprive the 1954 Geneva Accords of any meaning whatsoever as a basis for a
                    settlement.</p>
                <p>Finally, on supervisory matters, Hanoi knew from the outset that we wanted to
                    ensure that some international supervisory machinery be in place at the time of
                    the ceasefire. Without going into all the substance of their supervisory
                    protocol, suffice it to say that they only passed it over to us on December 12,
                    roughly six weeks after you had made your public statement that this was one of
                    the issues on which we would <pb facs="0676" n="633" xml:id="pg_633"/> seek
                    agreement before signing a settlement. This is not to mention the fact that the
                    content of their protocol is such that our two drafts are irreconcilable over
                    any short time span and agreement on the <gloss target="#t_ICCS_1">ICCS</gloss>
                    is likely only if we deprive it of any teeth whatsoever in exchange for which
                    they may be willing to tone down the political demands contained in their
                    protocol. Their <gloss target="#t_ICCS_1">ICCS</gloss> and ceasefire protocols
                    are truly political rather than technical documents.</p>
                <p>Procedure:</p>
                <p>Hanoi’s procedural negotiating tactics have been tawdry, petty and at times
                    transparently childish.</p>
                <p>To cite but a few examples of the kinds of tactics that Hanoi has pursued, one of
                    their basic approaches has been to agree to phrases which they know are
                    important to us in exchange for certain concessions and then subsequently they
                    would reopen the matter in an attempt to extract further concessions, after we
                    had already communicated these changes to our allies. The most blatant example
                    of this was when in the first week of our resumed talks they agreed to a number
                    of significant changes only to reopen every one of them during the following
                    week’s negotiating session. Among the concrete examples of this tactic are the
                    replacement provision which they first traded for reference to Article 21 (b) on
                    prisoner matters in October, which they again agreed to in late November, and
                    then on the final day of our meeting, without any forewarning whatsoever,
                    reopened a substantive issue with respect to that provision. Another example, of
                    course, is their agreement to <gloss target="#t_DMZ_1">DMZ</gloss> language
                    during our first week of meetings in November which they subsequently
                    retracted.</p>
                <p>Another tactic has been to delay on substantive issues which they know are
                    important to us, particularly the protocols. We can be almost certain that their
                    protocols were ready well in advance of this latest round or at least in
                    sufficient time to table them in late November and they have had our protocols
                    for almost three weeks. And yet they did not provide us any protocols whatsoever
                    until the next to last day of our meetings, including on such matters as the
                        <gloss target="#t_ICCS_1">ICCS</gloss>. As for the prisoner protocol, which
                    they well know is of vital importance to us, it was not tabled until the very
                    same day of your departure.</p>
                <p>Another tactic of theirs has been to make concessions and then try to recuperate
                    them in some other form. One example is their attempt to introduce into protocol
                    matters of substance which have not been agreed in the basic text itself and in
                    fact were left out as explicit concessions to us. The role of the <gloss
                        target="#t_NCNRC_1">NCNRC</gloss> is one example. The repeated naming of the
                        <gloss target="#t_PRG_1">PRG</gloss> in the ceasefire protocols is another.
                    Yet another example is the way they have tended to treat the Vietnamese and
                    English versions of the agreement as two separate texts, often conceding to us a
                    word in English but maintaining their language in Vietnamese which <pb
                        facs="0677" n="634" xml:id="pg_634"/> has different implications. To some
                    extent one could say that they are attempting to take advantage of our less than
                    total expertise in the Vietnamese language, although this is not something that
                    we can complain to anyone else about.</p>
                <p>Another good example of their dilatory tactics has been their claim that they
                    work slowly because they do not have modern means and that they do not receive
                    instructions quickly from Hanoi. As anyone familiar with the <gloss
                        target="#t_DRV_1">DRV</gloss> knows they have close to a 100-man delegation
                    in Paris capable of cranking out papers at whatever rate is desired; they have
                    several times as many language officers as any U.S. delegation they have ever
                    dealt with; and surely the SIGINT experts can confirm that Hanoi is in
                    possession of modern Soviet communications equipment. If they can get
                    instructions to <gloss target="#t_COSVN_1">COSVN</gloss> in one or two days,
                    they can certainly get them to <persName corresp="#p_LDT_1">Le Duc
                        Tho</persName> in the same period of time.</p>
                <p>Hanoi has also on occasion used experts meetings designed for the explicit
                    purpose of conforming texts to introduce major issues of substance. This was
                    particularly flagrant on the final day of our meetings when they reintroduced
                    issues relating to the replacement provision and the chapter on Cambodia and
                    Laos.</p>
                <p>Hanoi also has a proclivity for using the past record of negotiations in a
                    fashion that is completely out of context. To cite the most ludicrous example,
                    when our first series of renewed meetings began, they reintroduced the question
                    of <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName>’s resignation arguing that
                    this was simply a matter on which even the U.S. had made a proposal in
                    September. They have likewise, in preparing their understandings, pursued a
                    tactic of quoting from the record out of context. Finally they have at times
                    distorted your remarks beyond recognition such as on the issue of international
                    supervision of Article 13 which they read to me at an experts meeting and raised
                    again at the last meeting with you. It was absolutely obvious to anybody
                    familiar with the record that you had meant to drop reference to international
                    supervision in the article itself and that we fully intended to retain in it the
                    international supervisory chapter.</p>
                <p>In sum Hanoi’s tactics have been to unnecessarily prolong and delay the
                    discussions, to distort the past record to their purposes and to renegotiate
                    concessions several times over.</p>
                <p>End of message.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
