<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-12-19T00:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-12-19T00:45:00-05:00" n="198" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d198">
                        <head>198. Backchannel Message From the President’s Deputy Assistant for
                            National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName>)
                            to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d198fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 859, For the
                                President’s Files (<persName corresp="#p_LW_1">Winston
                                    Lord</persName>)—China Trip/Vietnam, Sensitive Camp David, Vol.
                                XXIII. Top Secret; <gloss target="#t_Flash_1">Flash</gloss>;
                                Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes Only.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-12-19T05:45:00+00:00">December 19, 1972,
                                0545Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Haigto 4/301. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName>
                            and I have just completed a two hour and fifty minute meeting with
                            President <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName> and Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_HDN_1alt1">Nha</persName>.<note n="2" xml:id="d198fn2">See <ref target="#d197">Document 197</ref>.</note>
                            Mr. <persName>Duc</persName> had been lined up to participate but I
                            insisted on a private meeting with only <persName corresp="#p_HDN_1alt1">Nha</persName> to interpret. Of course, I wanted <persName corresp="#p_HDN_1alt1">Nha</persName> to hear the discussion. I
                            presented to <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName> in the
                            bluntest and most unequivocal way all of the considerations which made
                            it imperative that he join with us in accepting the agreement if North
                            Vietnam meets our minimum requirements. I outlined for him what those
                            requirements were and the current state of the draft agreement. I noted
                            specifically the actions President <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> had courageously taken Saturday and this morning
                            and the costs that these actions entailed for the U.S. in manpower,
                            matériel and political good will at home. At the outset of the meeting,
                            I handed him President <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>’s
                            letter which I told him had been dictated personally by the President in
                            my presence before my departure on Sunday.<note n="3" xml:id="d198fn3">Sunday was December 17; for the letter, see <ref target="#d189">Document 189</ref>.</note> I told him that no one else in the
                            U.S. Government had a copy of this letter and that it represented the
                            most painful and most deliberate judgment of his strongest supporter and
                            friend in Washington. <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName>
                            was obviously shaken. I then proceeded for over an hour and a half to
                            outline all of the considerations which dictated his acceptance of the
                            agreement.</p>
                        <p>When I completed my presentation, <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName> went on at great length and stated that it was
                            obvious that he was being asked not to sign an agreement for peace but
                            rather an agreement for continued U.S. support. I told him as a soldier
                            and one completely familiar with Communist treachery that I agreed with
                            his assessment. I added, however, that both you and the President would
                            be equally ready to accept that assessment. <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName> stated that he was confident
                            that the ceasefire would last at the most three months and would be
                            followed by a resumption of guerilla warfare. During the first three
                            months the enemy would use knives and bayonets. They would then take up
                            their weapons after U.S. forces had been withdrawn and a period of peace
                            ensued. He stated <pb facs="0798" n="755" xml:id="pg_755"/> that Hanoi
                            would never undertake actions which would justify U.S. retaliation.</p>
                        <p>I generally agreed with his assessment but pointed out that the situation
                            was now the reverse of what it was in the early fifties, and he was far
                            more powerful than was the Diem regime at that time. I pointed out that
                            all our assessments—military, political and intelligence—confirmed that
                            he would be victorious in a guerilla struggle and he conceded that this
                            was so. I then told him that in any event the question was moot. We were
                            at the final juncture at which he would have to speak in favor of moving
                            with us or be prepared to proceed alone. He stated that he understood
                            completely and while I suspect he may waffle his answer somewhat, I am
                            equally confident that he will go along providing we achieve the minimum
                            changes to the agreement which you and I have discussed. This would
                            include the three document signature, the elimination of the term
                            “administrative structure” and the return to the interim <gloss target="#t_DMZ_1">DMZ</gloss> language which Hanoi gave us in
                            November.</p>
                        <p>I know we have been around this track before and that I may be faced
                            tomorrow morning with a response that is a total stonewall. Be this as
                            it may, I told him at departure that I have been ordered not to
                            participate in a meeting with his National Security Council and that our
                            discussion tomorrow morning should again be with the same participants.
                            Both Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName> and I are
                            of the impression that <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName>
                            will come along even if he does not give us an affirmative answer
                            tomorrow. There is no question in my mind that he understands completely
                            the alternatives. I told him that if he did not give me an encouraging
                            answer to provide to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Thursday night that we would consult our own
                            interests and work out an arrangement that could only result in his
                            downfall and the failure of all that we have worked for. He stated that
                            the issue was simple and he understood it. I will give you a more
                            detailed report tonight upon my return from Phnom Penh.</p>
                        <p>Concerning the air strikes against the North, I am scheduled to meet with
                            General <persName corresp="#p_WFC_1">Weyand</persName> first thing
                            tomorrow morning. Please do not permit Department of Defense concerns to
                            deter us from what must be done. I feel that <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName>’s attitude which was
                            cordial, frank and totally honest throughout the discussion was in large
                            measure influenced by the President’s decision to move violently against
                            Hanoi. He seemed reassured that we are not naive about the outcome of
                            the agreement and very amenable to the reality that we must have a new
                            basis for continuing our support to him.</p>
                        <p>Warm regards.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>