<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-12-20T11:53:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-12-20T11:53:00-05:00" n="210" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d210">
                        <head>210. Backchannel Message From the President’s Deputy Assistant for
                            National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName>)
                            to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d210fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 1020, <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Alexander M. Haig</persName> Special File,
                                Gen. <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName>’s Vietnam Trip,
                                Tohaig/Haigto &amp; Misc., December 17–22, 1972 [2 of 3]. Top
                                Secret; Operational Immediate; Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes
                                Only.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-12-20T16:53:00+00:00">December
                                    20, 1972, 1653Z</date>. </dateline></opener>
                        <p>Haigto 11. I spent about one hour with <persName corresp="#p_SP_1">Souvanna</persName> and his Vice Premier this afternoon giving him
                            a rundown on the negotiation situation in general and as it affects Laos
                            in particular.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SP_1">Souvanna</persName> was in good form. The
                            only specific question he pressed on was ensuring that the Laos
                            ceasefire occurs as soon as possible after the Vietnam agreement. He
                            believes that every day that passes between a Vietnam ceasefire and Laos
                            ceasefire gives the <gloss target="#t_NVA_1">NVA</gloss> more
                            opportunity to create trouble for Laos.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SP_1">Souvanna</persName> expressed some concern
                            at the prospects for continued U.S. Congressional support if the Vietnam
                            talks continue deadlocked. I confirmed that this was indeed the crux of
                            the problem and that in many respects the agreement would be our best
                            guarantee of continued U.S. support to the countries of Southeast Asia.
                            I explained in detail the various factors which might be influencing
                            Hanoi’s adoption of stalling tactics, with considerable emphasis on
                            their awareness of <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName>’s
                            intransigence. <persName corresp="#p_SP_1">Souvanna</persName> stated
                            that there was no excuse for <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName>’s attitude given the fact that he had one of the
                            most powerful armies in the world, while Laos was struggling with merely
                            a fraction of South Vietnam’s assets. I then went over each of the
                            specific points which the U.S. Government hoped that <persName corresp="#p_SP_1">Souvanna</persName> would keep in mind in
                            negotiating with the Pathet Lao and their mentors. <persName corresp="#p_SP_1">Souvanna</persName> emphasized that he would never
                            accept a settlement with the Pathet Lao and North Vietnamese which
                            permitted Hanoi’s use of the <persName corresp="#p_HCM_1">Ho Chi
                                Minh</persName> Trail. Such usage, he insisted, would constitute the
                            violation of any agreement. He agreed that Laos would insure that local
                            provisions would permit U.S. reconnaissance, would insist on retaining
                            the provisions of the 1962 Accords, would not go beyond the external
                            provisions of the Accords, would insure the provisions of Article 6 of
                            the Accords, would abide by the concept of constitutionality and would
                            insist on arrangements for a ceasefire before completion of the
                            political solution. The problem of keeping the proper sequence between
                            ceasefire, withdrawal and political arrangements was discussed in detail
                            with <persName corresp="#p_SP_1">Souvanna</persName>. He is fully in
                            accord with the U.S. position.</p>
                        <pb facs="0837" n="794" xml:id="pg_794"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SP_1">Souvanna</persName> expressed great interest
                            in international control arrangements. He was highly skeptical of North
                            Vietnamese intentions and noted that he was going to speak with Madame
                                <persName corresp="#p_GI_1">Gandhi</persName> in January and hoped
                            to get her acquiescence in the stationing of Indian troops along the
                                <persName corresp="#p_HCM_1">Ho Chi Minh</persName> Trail.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SP_1">Souvanna</persName> had a number of amusing
                            remarks to make about the North Vietnamese, some of which he says he
                            made to you at your recent dinner together with <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName>. He said we must start from
                            the assumption that we cannot count on their sincerity and added that
                            his experience with them convinced him that they were inveterate
                            liars.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SP_1">Souvanna</persName> said that he had spent
                            nine years in North Vietnam as a young man and he could say with
                            complete honesty that despite all his time there he did not have a
                            single Vietnamese friend. Quote They always have ulterior motives, they
                            appear to be frank but they always know what they want. Unquote.</p>
                        <p>On balance, the discussion with <persName corresp="#p_SP_1">Souvanna</persName> was constructive and realistic. He is clearly
                            aware of the pitfalls of the settlement with North Vietnam. At the same
                            time, he clearly recognizes that the war has been largely won and is,
                            therefore, extremely enthusiastic about the air action against the
                            North, providing of course that some minor assets remain available for
                            Laos. <persName corresp="#p_SP_1">Souvanna</persName> noted that he is
                            under considerable pressure from the Government of South Vietnam to
                            insist that Laos be included in the international conference. He stated,
                            however, that this is unimportant to him since if worse came to worst he
                            could always send an observer. I, of course, supported this view. It is
                            very evident that the South Vietnamese have been working on the Lao to
                            garner support for their opposition to the settlement but it is equally
                            evident that <persName corresp="#p_SP_1">Souvanna</persName> is
                            skeptical of <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName>’s motives
                            and correctly feels that as far as Laos and Cambodia are concerned the
                            settlement more than provides for their interests. In the case of South
                            Vietnam, he evidently believes that <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName> has more than enough power to cope with the risks
                            that the settlement imposes on him.</p>
                        <p>Warm regards.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>