<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-12-20T16:06:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-12-20T16:06:00-05:00" n="211" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d211">
                        <head>211. Message From the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff (<persName corresp="#p_MTH_1">Moorer</persName>) to the Commander in Chief,
                            Pacific (<persName corresp="#p_GNAM_1">Gayler</persName>) and the
                            Pacific Command Senior Commanders<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d211fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 218, Records of the Chairman, Records of <persName corresp="#p_MTH_1">Thomas Moorer</persName>, Box 71, Linebacker
                                II Messages, December 1972. Top Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Specat_1">Specat</gloss>; Exclusive.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-12-20T21:06:00+00:00">December 20, 1972,
                                2106Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>8786. For Commanders from Admiral <persName corresp="#p_MTH_1">Moorer</persName>. Deliver upon receipt. <gloss target="#t_Subj_1">Subj</gloss>: Linebacker II/Surge (U). Ref: <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss> 7807/1923227 Dec 72.<note n="2" xml:id="d211fn2">The message, December 19, 2322Z, to <persName corresp="#p_MJC_1">Meyer</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_WFC_1">Weyand</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_GNAM_1">Gayler</persName> reminded them of the
                                guidelines for prioritizing <gloss target="#t_Sortie_1">sortie</gloss> allocation in the bombing campaign and for
                                delivering specific orders to each commander. (Ibid.)</note>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>(<gloss target="#t_TS_1">TS</gloss>) I note that favorable weather
                                is forecast over <gloss target="#t_DRRD_1">Red River Delta</gloss>
                                during daylight hours 21 December, and possibly 22 December.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>(<gloss target="#t_TS_1">TS</gloss>) It is essential that we
                                continue heaviest possible pressure on authorized targets north of
                                20 degrees north and to do this we must take full advantage of every
                                weather window that opens. These all too infrequent occurrences
                                afford us the opportunity to let the enemy feel the full weight of
                                our air capability and to attack those critical targets requiring
                                visual delivery.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>(<gloss target="#t_TS_1">TS</gloss>) I anticipate that you will
                                surge the force to the maximum for strikes north of 20 degrees north
                                on the 21st, recognizing we may have to reduce the weight of effort
                                in other areas and other missions, including Destructor seedings.
                                Priorities in the ref apply.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Warm regards.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>