<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>324. Memorandum From the Department of State Deputy Legal Adviser (Aldrich)
                    to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs () to the President’s
                    Assistant for National Security Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d324</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">324</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-01-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-01-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recb140a4efc2e771d" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general">Warships</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-01-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-01-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="324"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d324">
                <head>324. Memorandum From the Department of State Deputy Legal Adviser (<persName
                        corresp="#p_AGH_1">Aldrich</persName>) to the President’s Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d324fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files,
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 109,
                        Country Files, Far East, Vietnam Negotiations, Rationale. Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-01-22"
                            >January 22, 1973</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Summary and Analysis of the Protocols</item>
                </list>
                <p>The four protocols constitute the necessary advance implementation of the
                    Agreement. In particular, they work out the necessary arrangements for the
                    International Commission of Control and Supervision (Article 18), the Four-Party
                    Joint Military Commission (Article 16), and the Provisional Two-Party Joint
                    Military Commission (Article 10). They also define the cease-fire, determine in
                    greater detail than the <pb facs="1178" n="1135" xml:id="pg_1135"/> Agreement
                    the obligations of the parties concerning return of prisoners, and specify
                    certain arrangements for the clearance of mines.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Positive Elements.</hi> In my judgment, the protocols do the
                    following important things: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>They provide personnel for control and supervision totalling 4,460 for
                            the first 60 days and at least 2,810 thereafter. <list type="simple">
                                <item>
                                    <label>(a)</label> International Commission—1,160</item>
                                <item>
                                    <label>(b)</label> Four-Party Joint Military
                                    Commission—3,300</item>
                                <item>
                                    <label>(c)</label> Two-Party Provisional Joint Military
                                    Commission—1,650</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>They ensure that these supervisory personnel will be scattered around
                            South Vietnam at various points of strategic and political significance,
                            including points on or near infiltration routes from North Vietnam,
                            Laos, and Cambodia.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>They require the International Commission to report separate and
                            minority views of its members.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>They require the International Commission to make investigations when
                            requested by any one of the four parties to the Agreement (U.S., <gloss
                                target="#t_DRV_1">DRV</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_GVN_1">GVN</gloss>,
                                <gloss target="#t_PRG_1">PRG</gloss>).</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>They ensure that both the International Commission and the Joint
                            Military Commissions can be equipped with adequate communication and
                            transportation facilities.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>They require the two South Vietnamese parties to permit freedom of
                            movement for all persons except combat forces throughout South Vietnam
                            after the cease-fire.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>They define the cease-fire in such a way that aggressive and hostile
                            actions are prohibited, but other movements of military personnel and
                            units are permitted.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>They place no restriction on the movement of ships, except for the
                            movement of warships into areas of South Vietnam controlled by another
                            party.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>They require legitimate imports of armaments, munitions and other war
                            material (for replacement only) to enter through agreed points of entry
                            and under the control and supervision of a team of the International
                            Commission.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>They ensure that both the International Commission and the Four-Party
                            Joint Military Commission will be able to control and supervise the
                            release of American prisoners in North Vietnam.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>They establish minimum standards for the treatment of prisoners during
                            the period prior to their release.</item>
                        <label>12.</label>
                        <item>They ensure that a Four-Party Joint Military team will remain after
                            the Four-Party Joint Military Commission ends its operations in 60 <pb
                                facs="1179" n="1136" xml:id="pg_1136"/> days to finish the tasks of
                            accounting for the missing in action and locating graves.</item>
                        <label>13.</label>
                        <item>They provide for North Vietnam’s cooperation in the clearance of mines
                            from North Vietnamese waters and assure protection for U.S. personnel
                            engaged in this mine clearance activity.</item>
                        <label>14.</label>
                        <item>They avoid establishing any fixed date for the completion of mine
                            clearance operations in North Vietnamese waters.</item>
                        <label>15.</label>
                        <item>They provide that mines may either be destroyed, deactivated, or
                            removed. The United States cannot be committed to removal without its
                            consent in a specific case and we made it clear in the negotiations that
                            removal will almost never occur. The <gloss target="#t_DRV_1"
                                >DRV</gloss> accepts that fact.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Negative Elements.</hi> Some difficult questions, such as
                    designation of points of entry, were left for the two South Vietnamese parties,
                    but, by and large, the negative features of the protocols reflect unavoidable
                    problems which are also evident in the basic Agreement, particularly political
                    problems inherent in the concept of two “areas of control” in South Vietnam.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>They provide that the International Commission and the Joint Military
                        Commission work on the principle of unanimity, which could prevent them from
                        acting effectively in a crisis.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The large size of the Four-Party Joint Military Commission, however
                        desirable in other respects, inevitably results in spreading the legitimate
                        presence of the Communist members of the Commission to many cities and towns
                        throughout South Vietnam where they could not otherwise openly
                        appear.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The definition of the cease-fire makes it clear that control by the <gloss
                            target="#t_PRG_1">PRG</gloss> of certain, as yet undefined, areas of
                        South Vietnam is recognized in principle and is not to be challenged by
                        armed force.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The definition of the cease-fire will prohibit the Vietnamese air force
                        from flying <hi rend="italic">armed</hi> combat aircraft over South
                        Vietnam.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Under the protocols there will be large stretches of South Vietnam’s
                        border which will be inadequately patrolled either by <gloss
                            target="#t_GVN_1">GVN</gloss> forces or by the International Commission
                        or the Joint Military Commission to detect and deter infiltration of men and
                        arms.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The protocols postponed for subsequent agreement by the two South
                        Vietnamese parties the designation of the legitimate points of entry for
                        replacement armaments, munitions and war materials. This may be a political
                        advantage as far as our relations with the <gloss target="#t_GVN_1"
                            >GVN</gloss> are concerned, but operationally it’s a
                        disadvantage.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>The protocols leave for subsequent agreement in the Four-Party Joint
                        Military Commission the designation of places to which prisoners will be
                        returned.</item>
                    <pb facs="1180" n="1137" xml:id="pg_1137"/>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Protocols limit normal police armament to pistols, except in “unusual
                        circumstances.” The flexibility in this quoted phrase seems adequate for
                        practical purposes, but it may still have some negative political
                        effect.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>The protocols make U.S. mine clearance operations in North Vietnamese
                        waters subject to concurrence by the <gloss target="#t_DRV_1"
                        >DRV</gloss>.</item>
                </list>
                <p>[Omitted here is a detailed analysis of the protocols.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
