<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-01-22T03:50:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-01-22T03:50:00-05:00" n="326" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d326">
                        <head>326. Backchannel Message From the Ambassador to Vietnam (<persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName>) to the President’s Assistant
                            for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d326fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 860, For the
                                President’s Files (<persName corresp="#p_LW_1">Winston
                                    Lord</persName>)—China Trip/Vietnam, Sensitive Camp David, Vol.
                                XXIV. Top Secret; Operational Immediate; Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes
                                Only.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-01-22T08:50:00+00:00">January 22, 1973,
                                0850Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>349. Ref: WHS 3107.<note n="2" xml:id="d326fn2">Document 325. This
                                message included the President’s letter and the draft note mentioned
                                in paragraph 1.</note>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>I delivered the President’s letter and the draft note to <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName> at noon today. <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName> seemed pleased with the
                                letter and with the revisions in the note conforming to points made
                                in his letter of January 21, especially with the President’s offer
                                to state our views publicly along the same lines.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In response to my question whether he would make a statement at
                                the same time or immediately following the President’s speech
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName> said that what
                                he would say would depend in part on what the President planned to
                                say and what <gloss target="#t_FM_1">FonMin</gloss> Lam reported
                                from Paris. He asked whether we could supply an outline of what the
                                President proposed <pb facs="1183" n="1140" xml:id="pg_1140"/> to
                                say which would be helpful to him in planning his own statement; he
                                would appreciate having this as soon as possible. I informed him
                                that present plans called for the President to speak at 2200 January
                                23, which would be 1100 January 24, Saigon time.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName> said that there
                                were two important points in connection with the protocols on the
                                Joint Military Commissions on which he had asked <gloss target="#t_FM_1">FonMin</gloss> Lam to concentrate: <list>
                                    <label>1)</label>
                                    <item>Police force: <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName> said that as far as he was aware no
                                        police force anywhere was prevented from having weapons
                                        necessary to maintain law and order. He believes that in the
                                        case of the protocols the limitation should be only on the
                                        use of police weapons, i.e., a prohibition on their being
                                        used to provoke hostilities or violate the ceasefire. I
                                        called his attention to the statement in the President’s
                                        letter that if we failed to obtain the proposed modification
                                        we will interpret the phrases in the protocol “unusual
                                        circumstances” in a way that gives us the necessary
                                        latitude.</item>
                                    <label>2)</label>
                                    <item>
                                        <gloss target="#t_VC_1">VC</gloss> cadre having diplomatic
                                        immunity: <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName>
                                        suggested that some limitation be placed on the number or
                                        eligibility of those entitled to diplomatic immunity or
                                        restricting diplomatic immunity to certain rank levels. In
                                        any case there should be a prohibition against using
                                        diplomatic immunity to spread propaganda. Perhaps some
                                        wording along the following or similar lines might cover
                                        this point: “Members of the Joint Military Commission are
                                        explicitly barred from undertaking any political,
                                        proselytizing or any other activity intended to influence,
                                        change or otherwise alter the political situation of the
                                        area in which they are stationed by virtue of their
                                        membership in the Joint Military Commission.”</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>I said that Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                                planned to meet with <gloss target="#t_FM_1">FonMin</gloss> Lam this
                                evening on his arrival in Paris and would see him both before and
                                after the meeting tomorrow.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_NVT_1alt1">Thieu</persName> appeared more
                                cheerful and relaxed today than last night when he seemed rather
                                discouraged and resigned. He has clearly crossed the bridge.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>More power to you. My prayers are with you. Warm regards.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>