<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-11-02T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-11-02T10:00:00-05:00" n="1009" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1009">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 861.00/3144</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Sweden</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_WS1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Whitehouse</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-11-02T16:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">November
                                            2, 1918, 4 p.m.</hi></date>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received November 3, 1.23
                                    a.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>3090. Have received note from Russian Minister here, of which
                                following is substance: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>Natural consequences of recent events would seem to be
                                        retreat of German troops from the occupied Russian provinces
                                        and recrudescence of Bolshevism would then be inevitable in
                                        these regions. Many Russian refugees have appealed to our
                                        Legations to intervene with the Allied Governments to point
                                        out this danger and obtain their consent for the German
                                        troops to remain in these territories until they can be
                                        replaced by Allied forces.</p>
                                    <p>I have not wished to take any steps chiefly because the
                                        Germans themselves were urging the inhabitants of the
                                        occupied provinces to express themselves in their favor in
                                        this way and I did not wish even indirectly to comply with
                                        the views of our enemies, not being able to judge how much
                                        military interest the Germans had in remaining in Russia
                                        under the pretext of fighting the Bolsheviks. However,
                                        although absolutely opposed to the presence of German troops
                                        in any [my] country, I cannot remain deaf to the appeals of
                                        my compatriots who were worried over the fate of their
                                        relatives in these provinces, and I have therefore decided
                                        to request you to give me your support with your Government
                                        in begging it to consider among the alternatives which the
                                        Allies may take in view to preserve order in the occupied
                                        provinces, the installing at any rate an Allied
                                    command.</p></quote></p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed><persName corresp="#p_WS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Whitehouse</hi></persName></signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>