<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan ( (Morris) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918Russiav02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d111</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">111</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-03-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-03-12T00:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-03-12T00:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-03-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="111"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d111">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 861.00/1271</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MRS1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Morris</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-03-12T14:00:00+09:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 12, 1918, 2 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received 2.12 p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>On March 7, I read to the Minister for Foreign Affairs the con-tents of
                    Department’s telegram March 5, 4 p.m.,<note n="1" xml:id="d111fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_67">p. 67</ref>.</note> and at
                    his request left a copy with him. He expressed his deep appreciation of the
                    frankness and friendly spirit of the communication. He assured me again that his
                    Government had made no formal request and had reached no decision in reference
                    to the situation eastern Siberia but had sought simply an exchange of views. On
                    the evening of March 9, the long-postponed meeting of the Advisory Council of
                    Foreign Affairs was held. The deliberating lasted several hours, but no
                    statement of the matters discussed has been issued.</p>
                <p>Late yesterday afternoon in accordance with instructions received from his
                    Government, British Ambassador called upon the Minister for Foreign Affairs to
                    suggest informally to him the advisability of Japan’s intervention in Siberia.
                    The plans as outlined by the British Ambassador contemplated military occupation
                    as far as the Ural Mountains. If Japanese Government deemed special mission
                    advisable at this time, formal request would be submitted by the Government of
                    Great Britain supported by France and Italy.</p>
                <pb facs="0169" n="79" xml:id="pg_79"/>
                <p>The Minister for Foreign Affairs expressed regret that this suggestion had not
                    been offered earlier, when public sentiment in Japan was far more favorable than
                    now to some form of intervention. Have repeated to <persName corresp="#p_KAAM1"
                        >Admiral Knight</persName> and Peking.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MRS1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Morris</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
