<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-04-26T11:29:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-04-26T11:29:00-05:00" n="183" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d183">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 861.00/1728</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Russia</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_FDR1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Francis</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Vologda</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-04-26T19:00:00+02:31"><hi rend="italic">April 26,
                                            1918, 7 p.m.</hi></date>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received May 3, 6.26
                                    p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>127. I have just received telegram from <persName corresp="#p_RLCR1">Robins</persName>, whom I have asked what disposition he made
                                of the communication other than forwarding me and whether <persName corresp="#p_CGV1">Chicherin</persName> desired same transmitted
                                you other than through me.</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p><persName corresp="#p_RLCR1">Colonel Robins</persName>, Chief of
                                    the American Red Cross Mission to Russia: The People’s
                                    Commissaire for Foreign Affairs transmits herewith the
                                        documents<note n="1" xml:id="d183fn1"><hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_142">p. 142</ref>.</note>
                                    regarding the discovery of the conspiracy against the government
                                    of the Soviets in Siberia and has the honor to request you to
                                    bring to the notice of the Government of the United States that
                                    the following published documents establish the undeniable fact
                                    that in this conspiracy participated the consular
                                    representatives of America, Great Britain, and France at
                                    Vladivostok and that the diplomatic representatives of the same
                                    powers at Peking were in communication with the
                                    counter-revolutionary organization which organization calls
                                    itself the Siberian government. On the basis of the above the
                                    government of the Russian Soviet Federated Republic requests the
                                    Government of the United States: <list>
                                        <label>(1)</label>
                                        <item>If possible without any delay to recall the American
                                            consular representative at Vladivostok;</item>
                                        <label>(2)</label>
                                        <item>If possible without any delay to appoint a public open
                                            investigation of the activity of the agent, also of the
                                            participation in the said counter-revolutionary
                                            [conspiracy] of the provisionally appointed [American
                                            diplomatic] mission at Peking;</item>
                                        <label>(3)</label>
                                        <item>To declare definitely and unequivocally the policy of
                                            the Government of the United States toward the Soviet
                                            government and toward all attempts of its
                                            representatives to interfere in the internal affairs of
                                            Russia.</item>
                                    </list></p>
                                <p>Please accept, Colonel, my assurances of deep regard. Acting
                                    Commissaire for Foreign Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_CGV1">Chicherin</persName>.</p></quote>
                            <p>Motives of [forwarding] summary of documents in later cable. Only
                                partially received, not convincing. French Consul General, Moscow,
                                received similar communication demanding removal French Consul,
                                Vladivostok.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed><persName corresp="#p_FDR1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Francis</hi></persName></signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>