<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-07-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-07-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="373" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d373">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 861.00/2957</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Embassy</gloss>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <dateline>
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1918-07-30">[July 30, 1918]</date>
                            </dateline>
                            <p>[A copy of the following telegram was handed by the Counselor of the
                                British Embassy to Mr. <persName>Auchincloss</persName> of the
                                office of the Counselor for the Department of State on July 30,
                                1918:]</p>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">The British Secretary of State for Foreign
                                        Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_BAJ1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Balfour</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Ambassador at Washington</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_RERDI1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Reading</hi></persName>)</head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-07-29"><hi rend="italic">July 29,
                                            1918</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>The following memorandum has been approved by the Imperial War
                                    Cabinet: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>His Majesty’s Government recognize to the full the spirit
                                            in which the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of July
                                                17<note n="1" xml:id="d373fn1"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_287">p.
                                                287</ref>.</note> is conceived, and they sincerely
                                            welcome the decision of the United States to assist
                                            towards safeguarding the Czecho-Slovak Army, though they
                                            entertain serious misgivings that the proposed force may
                                            prove inadequate for its purpose.</p>
                                        <p>They are also in complete accord with the President’s
                                            proposal to send an economic mission through Vladivostok
                                            in order to supply material assistance to a people
                                            sorely tried by the miseries of war and revolution.</p>
                                        <p>These are in themselves most admirable schemes, which
                                            deserve and will assuredly receive the gratitude of
                                            America’s allies. His Majesty’s Government <pb facs="0406" n="316" xml:id="pg_316"/> have, however,
                                            never concealed their view that they are insufficient in
                                            themselves to cope with the Russian situation, regarded
                                            as an element in a great military and political problem
                                            with which the Allies are confronted. The arguments,
                                            indeed, which have led us to this conclusion have been
                                            so often stated by the European Allies that it seems
                                            neither necessary nor desirable to repeat them on the
                                            present occasion. But there are two points, the one
                                            military and the other political, on which the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> seems so seriously
                                            to misconceive the attitude of the Entente powers as to
                                            require further comment and explanation.</p>
                                        <p>The military misconception bears on the relations between
                                            the western and eastern theatres of operations. His
                                            Majesty’s Government are entirely in accord with the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> in thinking that of
                                            these two theatres, the western is the more important.
                                            They admit to the full that it is on the west that the
                                            great effort must be made, and they believe that to
                                            endanger successes in the west in the hope of securing
                                            advantages in the east would be not only foolish but
                                            suicidal. But for this very reason they desire Allied
                                            intervention in Russia. Their scheme is not designed to
                                            diminish the relative strength of the Allied armies in
                                            the west by sending to Russia American troops who might
                                            be fighting in France or Italy, but to increase our
                                            relative strength in France by retaining in the east
                                            important bodies of Germans and Austrians, achieving
                                            this purpose by utilizing forces that are not available
                                            for the western front. In our view this can only be done
                                            on a considerable scale by enabling Japan, should she be
                                            willing, to employ her unused military strength against
                                            the common enemy. If this were possible the gain would
                                            be incontestable, and nowhere would it be more
                                            appreciated than in the western theatre of war. It may
                                            be too sanguine an expectation that Russia can, with
                                            Allied aid, recover the military strength she possessed
                                            before the revolution, but it is not unreasonable to
                                            look forward to a recovery which would constitute a real
                                            menace to German occupation of conquered territories,
                                            thus absorbing considerable German forces which would
                                            otherwise have been employed in France. If this could be
                                            accomplished the task of French, British, and American
                                            forces in France next year would be materially
                                            lightened.</p>
                                        <p>The second misconception which (as it seems to us)
                                            pervades the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>, is
                                            that the Allies, in advocating intervention in Russia
                                            are not thinking of Russia, but solely of themselves.
                                            “Military intervention,” says the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>, “even supposing it to be
                                            efficacious in its repeatedly avowed object of
                                            delivering an attack upon Germany from the east, would
                                            be merely a method of making use of Russia, not a method
                                            of serving her.”</p>
                                        <p>If this statement is based upon the assumption that the
                                            Allies wish to make use of Russia merely for their own
                                            purposes His Majesty’s Government must observe that
                                            their attitude has been misunderstood. In our view,
                                            Germany has used and misused the struggle for liberty of
                                            the Russian people to serve her own selfish end. Herself
                                            the great example of efficient autocracy, she has
                                            sedulously fostered in Russia every influence, from
                                            extremes of socialism to extremes of reaction, to
                                            paralyze the national will and destroy the national
                                            integrity. She has forced the country into a degrading
                                            and disastrous peace. Even that peace she has refused to
                                            keep. Russian territories which she has forcibly taken
                                            under protection she is treating with characteristic
                                            brutality. Russia is to her no more than a conquered
                                            area from which she can squeeze supplies, and the
                                            Russian people are no more than a subject rabble, to be
                                            stripped and plundered in exact proportion to Germany’s
                                            strength and Russia’s weakness.</p>
                                        <p>To His Majesty’s Government, therefore, it seems that an
                                            attack on German forces in Russia would confer upon the
                                            Russian people the most signal service that could be
                                            imagined. If Russia is ever to develop along her own
                                            lines, if she is ever to regain her self-respect, she
                                            must first be free from an alien domination, the whole
                                            object of which is to shatter her political fabric and
                                            exploit her material resources.</p>
                                        <p>The <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> also seems to
                                            carry a possible suggestion that intervention has a
                                            political as well as a military object; and even that it
                                            may be in some fashion calculated to foster reaction. We
                                            had hoped that our reiterated declarations upon this
                                            subject made doubts about our policy impossible. Above
                                            all things we desire to keep free from party disputes,
                                            by which Russia is torn. There is no principle on which
                                            we have laid greater stress than that she should manage
                                            her own affairs. We wish her to choose her own form of
                                            government and to pursue in her own way her own line of
                                            self-development. But, unless <pb facs="0407" n="317" xml:id="pg_317"/> all the information which reaches
                                            us is worthless, the best hope—perhaps the only hope—of
                                            allowing the voice of the Russian people to be heard,
                                            lies in the cleansing of the country by [from] German
                                            influences supported by German soldiers. This, it seems
                                            to us, can only be accomplished by foreign aid. Were it
                                            accompanied by a proclamation of the kind approved by
                                            the President, and repeatedly suggested by His Majesty’s
                                            Government, there should be no error or misconception as
                                            to the motives of the Allies; and there seems no reason
                                            to doubt that all the best elements in the country,
                                            whatever be their political opinions, would rally to the
                                            Allied standard and make use of Allies’ support.</p>
                                        <p>We desire to acid that in making admittance of the great
                                            difficulty of the Russian problem, we know how deeply it
                                            has engaged the attention of the President, we rejoice
                                            to recognize the spirit of disinterested cooperation
                                            which animates all his policy, whether in the west or in
                                            the east, and we firmly count upon its continuance. We
                                            have, however, thought it right to deal briefly in this
                                            memorandum with certain points solely for the purpose of
                                            removing any possible misconceptions as to the attitude
                                            of His Majesty’s Government.</p></quote></p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>