<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-08-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-08-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="407" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d407">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 861.00/2507</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The French Ambassador</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_JJAAJ1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Jusserand</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-08-12"><hi rend="italic">August 12,
                                        1918</hi></date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received August
                                        13.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: At this time when
                                the Allies are about to exert their action in both Siberia and
                                northern Russia, the Government of the Republic, thinking that this
                                dual action will be more effective if better coordinated, has
                                directed me to offer to the Federal Government suggestions tending
                                to the establishment of some sort of political direction of and
                                connection between the two operations simultaneously set on foot at
                                Archangel and Vladivostok. The successes of the Czechs, the
                                weakening of the Bolsheviki, the growing difficulties encountered by
                                the Germans are, one and all, reasons for resolute action by the
                                Allies in the two or three months when it can be taken and for the
                                earliest possible establishment of northern as well as eastern
                                connection with the Czechs.</p>
                            <p>With a view to the best possible harmonizing of that dual action and
                                to the settling of the political or economic questions that may
                                arise, my Government believes it would be the part of wisdom and
                                foresight, while adhering to the local military command, British on
                                one side, Japanese on the other, to organize an inter-Allied
                                civilian board charged with the duty of safeguarding unity of action
                                toward <pb facs="0431" n="341" xml:id="pg_341"/> the Russian people.
                                That board should have the last say in all questions flowing from
                                the assistance brought to Russia by the Allies, decide the political
                                disputes, give the economic, financial, and technical directions,
                                define the relations between the Allied Governments and the local
                                authorities.</p>
                            <p>If the Federal Government concurred in my Government’s view the
                                chairmanship of the board would go to the United States. A few
                                Russians might be admitted or attached to the board in an advisory
                                capacity. This would facilitate an adjustment of the differences
                                that have arisen among the several Russian groups, whose proneness
                                to improvise is but too well known and who are seeking recognition
                                by the Allies.</p>
                            <p>I should be thankful to your excellency if you would kindly let me
                                know whether the foregoing suggestions coincide, as is my
                                Government’s hope, with the Federal Government’s view.</p>
                            <p>Be pleased to accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed><persName corresp="#p_JJAAJ1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Jusserand</hi></persName></signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>