<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-01-27T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-01-27T14:00:00-05:00" n="118" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d118">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/3719a: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Forbes</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-01-27T14:00:00-05:00">January 27, 1932—2
                            p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                    <p>25. During the week preceding January 20 there were, according to official
                        reports, several clashes between Japanese and Chinese at Shanghai, in one of
                        which a Japanese was killed, two Japanese were wounded, a Chinese policeman
                        was killed and several Chinese were injured. Several thousand Japanese held
                        a mass meeting on the afternoon of January 20 and subsequently paraded
                        through the streets of the International Settlement, assaulting several
                        Chinese citizens and smashing the windows of Chinese shops. On that
                        occasion, the Japanese and Chinese elements of the International Settlement
                        police worked harmoniously together. January 23 was selected as the date for
                        another Japanese mass meeting, and on January 22 the Japanese Admiral
                        published a statement to the effect that, unless the mayor of the Chinese
                        municipality complied with the demands presented by the Japanese Consul
                        General with reference to several anti-Japanese incidents, the Japanese
                        Admiral would take “appropriate steps to protect the rights and interests of
                            Japan.”<note n="1" xml:id="d118fn1">See first report, February 6, 1932,
                            of the Consular Committee appointed to report on events in Shanghai and
                            the neighborhood, League of Nations, <hi rend="italic">Official
                                Journal</hi>, March, 1932, p. 374.</note> Accordingly, on January
                        23, the Japanese Consul General and the Chairman and the Secretary General
                        of the Municipal Council called on the Japanese Admiral, who, after
                        protracted discussions, agreed to take no action in the International
                        Settlement without prior consultation with the authorities of the
                        Settlement. It is reported that, subsequent to this conversation, the
                        Japanese Consul General had promised that the reply which the Chinese Mayor
                        makes to the Japanese demands will be communicated to the Council 24 hours
                        in advance of any Japanese action.</p>
                    <p>While this account may not be altogether complete or precise in all details,
                        it is a sufficient indication that the action of Japanese subjects, both
                        officials and private citizens, is contributing to the aggravation of what
                        is already a serious situation at Shanghai, and that the consular and naval
                        officers of the Japanese Government on the spot are <pb facs="0258" n="162" xml:id="pg_162"/> seriously considering the use of force near to or in
                        the International Settlement as an instrument of Japanese policy.</p>
                    <p>Shanghai is China’s most important port. In the International Settlement
                        there are about 40,000 foreigners, of many nationalities, American as well
                        as Japanese, over a million Chinese, a great mass of physical property, and
                        a focus for commercial and other legitimate interests. A disturbance to the
                        peace at the port of Shanghai is a serious concern to every nation. Direct
                        or indirect interference with the commerce of the port of Shanghai would
                        injure the trade of all the chief commercial countries, as well as the trade
                        of China.</p>
                    <p>The Government of the United States cannot regard with indifference a
                        situation in which apparently a foreign government has authorized the
                        commander of its naval forces at Shanghai to use force, according to his own
                        judgment, to support demands made by the local consular representatives of
                        that government to obtain objectives which are peculiar to that government,
                        without the agreement, request or approval of the local representatives of
                        other governments which have interests and nationals at Shanghai and which,
                        on the basis of treaties and other agreements, have common rights and
                        interests with respect to conditions of trade and residence at Shanghai and
                        are warranted in feeling solicitude with respect to any developments
                        menacing the local situation at Shanghai. Especially is this true with
                        respect to the International Settlement; however, concern with regard to the
                        interests and rights in relation to the Settlement of necessity carries with
                        it concern with regard to any action which may affect the life of the port
                        of which the International Settlement is a part.</p>
                    <p>Unless the local authorities have failed or are manifestly unable to
                        discharge the duties of protection, no nation has the right, under
                        international procedure, to land armed forces on foreign soil for the
                        protection of its nationals. The Municipal Council, in the first instance,
                        is responsible for the administration of the International Settlement at
                        Shanghai and disposes of a well disciplined, organized police force, with
                        reliable personnel and under responsible control. Should the Council decide
                        that its agencies are inadequate to meet their responsibilities, it should
                        so advise the Consular Body, through the Senior Consul, and the Consular
                        Body should then issue such call as appears necessary, not upon any single
                        one, but upon all of the foreign forces available.</p>
                    <p>Please call at once upon the Minister for Foreign Affairs and discuss this
                        subject orally, leaving no memorandum, giving him in substance the narrative
                        of events and the outline of views as expressed above, adhering closely to
                        the text of this telegram. You should then inform the Minister for Foreign
                        Affairs that this Government hopes that it may assume that the Japanese
                        Government does not contemplate action at Shanghai in contravention of the
                        interests and rights of other <pb facs="0259" n="163" xml:id="pg_163"/>
                        nations, China included, and that the Japanese Government does not
                        contemplate any action which would jeopardize the property and lives of the
                        nationals of the many countries concerned, including China, Japan and the
                        United States. You should say, finally, that this Government, which desires
                        to preserve the rights and interests of all concerned, urges that the
                        Japanese Government exercise the maximum of self-restraint.</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Stimson</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>