<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-10-31T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-10-31T21:00:00-05:00" n="184" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d184">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A5/211: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-10-31T21:00:00-05:00">October 31, 1934—9
                                p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>186. The developments in London since October 25 are as follows:</p>
                        <p>On October 25 Davis and the Prime Minister<note n="5a" xml:id="d184fn5a">J. Ramsay MacDonald.</note> exchanged views regarding the Japanese
                            proposals. The idea of a common maximum <pb facs="0354" n="258" xml:id="pg_258"/> limit will not be accepted by the British. It was
                            their hope that when the Japanese perceived that the British and the
                            Americans would not agree to fundamental changes, the Japanese would
                            become more reasonable and would be content with a statement in the
                            preamble to the treaty voicing equality of sovereign rights, the treaty
                            itself fixing respective relative limits approximately according to the
                            present ratios. Before coming to grips, the British wished to have
                            further explanation from the Japanese. In order not to unsettle unity of
                            British-American views regarding the Japanese position, Davis avoided
                            raising technical questions.</p>
                        <p>The London press on October 26, under information from the Foreign
                            Office, deprecated the views relative to the Anglo-Japanese alliance
                            which were expressed in Tokyo by spokesman for the federation of British
                            industries mission in the Far East; the press emphasized the close
                            approximation of British-American naval policies.</p>
                        <p>At the American-Japanese meeting on the morning of October 29, Matsudaira
                            stated that his Government would denounce the Washington Naval Treaty
                            before the end of the year. Matsudaira also said that the same common
                            upper limit proposed by Japan would apply to France and Italy. In regard
                            to a possible meeting of the technical experts of the two delegations,
                            Davis told the Japanese that we were willing to listen to their
                            technical views only if it were understood that neither side would make
                            any commitments in principle. Admiral Yamamoto saw little value in
                            technical meeting unless we were prepared to state the technical details
                            of our program. Davis replied that we had no technical details, as the
                            American program was a percentage reduction within the existing system,
                            although as to carrying it into effect in individual categories we were
                            open-minded. The two delegations agreed that the matter be taken up at a
                            subsequent meeting.</p>
                        <p>In the afternoon on October 29 the British and the American delegations
                            met and the Prime Minister raised question of increased cruiser tonnage.
                            Davis stated that technical discussions would lack reality in view of
                            the fundamental changes proposed by the Japanese and their intention to
                            denounce the Washington Naval Treaty. The Prime Minister said that the
                            Japanese position was more serious for Britain than for the United
                            States and that the British were determined to meet the situation with a
                            fleet that would be adequate for defense in the Pacific as well as at
                            home; they would do this either by building a fleet of sufficient size
                            or by seeking a political agreement that would cover the Pacific for the
                            requisite security there.</p>
                        <p>MacDonald reiterated that the British did not agree to the Japanese idea
                            of a common upper limit, which would apply also to France, <pb facs="0355" n="259" xml:id="pg_259"/> Italy and probably to Germany
                            and to Russia as well. The Prime Minister felt that for the present a
                            patient attitude toward Japan should be continued, but that if a
                            tripartite agreement became impossible he did not question British
                            parity with America based on the British conceptions of their own risks.
                            Davis stated that we had no desire to impose on the British a treaty
                            incompatible with their national safety, but that we must consider joint
                            adoption of a course by which a naval race with Japan would not be
                            invited. The suggestion was made by the British that when the Americans
                            next met with the Japanese they should urge the latter to contemplate
                            the situation which would result from no treaty. The British had set
                            before the Japanese a face-saving device, but they had adopted an
                            unreceptive attitude toward it. When the Japanese situation should have
                            definitely cleared up, the British agreed on the desirability of
                            tripartite meetings; and they also agreed that for the time being
                            British-American technical discussions would be inadvisable. It is
                            Davis’s belief that the British view policy of the Japanese with deep
                            concern, and that in their own minds the British have reached no
                            solution.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Phillips</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>