<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Address Delivered by the Secretary of State on “Our Foreign Policy” at
                    Washington on March 17, 1938</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931-41v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d320</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">320</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-03-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-03-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International relations</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87004890"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International trade</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recQ0ODajfiIQB8Cy" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85115805"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rule of law</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recNuUP5FwVBYX7g7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic policies</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-03-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-03-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="320"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d320">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Address Delivered by the Secretary of State on “Our Foreign
                        Policy” at Washington on March 17, 1938</hi>
                    <note n="75" type="source" xml:id="d320fn75">Before the National Press Club.
                        Reprinted from Department of State Publication No. 1146 (Washington,
                        Government Printing Office, 1938).</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1938-03-17">March 17, 1938</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>In the course of the daily press conferences at the Department of State, I have
                    occasion to see many of you and to touch upon day-today developments in our
                    foreign relations. Such information as I am able to give you in these
                    conferences must, of necessity, relate to specific questions and, oftentimes, to
                    isolated events. Yet upon you, representatives of the press, rests a heavy
                    responsibility in keeping our people currently and accurately informed on the
                    vital issues which arise in our country’s relations with other nations. I
                    welcome, therefore, this opportunity to meet with the members of the National
                    Press Club in the calmer atmosphere of an occasion like the present one, and to
                    discuss with you some of the fundamental conditions and problems presented by
                    our international relations and our foreign policy.</p>
                <pb facs="0549" n="453" xml:id="pg_453"/>
                <p>The primary objectives of our foreign policy are the maintenance of the peace of
                    our country and the promotion of the economic, the social, and the moral welfare
                    of our people. Unfortunately, the means of attaining these objectives involve
                    today so many factors of great complexity that their real significance is
                    frequently misunderstood and misinterpreted.</p>
                <p>By instinct and tradition our country has been, throughout its history, sincerely
                    devoted to the cause of peace. Within the limitations imposed by time and
                    circumstance we have earnestly sought to discharge our responsibilities as a
                    member of the family of nations in promoting conditions essential to the
                    maintenance of peace. We have consistently believed in the sanctity of treaty
                    obligations and have endeavored to apply this belief in the actual practice of
                    our foreign relations. In common with all other nations we have, since the end
                    of the World War, assumed a solemn obligation not to resort to force as an
                    instrument of national policy. All this gives us a moral right to express our
                    deep concern over the rising tide of lawlessness, the growing disregard of
                    treaties, the increasing reversion to the use of force, and the numerous other
                    ominous tendencies which are emerging in the sphere of international
                    relations.</p>
                <p>On July 16, 1937, I issued a public statement setting forth the fundamental
                    principles to which our Government adheres in the formulation of its foreign
                        policy.<note n="76" xml:id="d320fn76">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_325">p. 325</ref>.</note> On
                    behalf of our Government I transmitted a copy of this statement to every
                    government of the world, requesting such comment as each might see fit to offer.
                    To our profound gratification an overwhelming majority of those governments
                    joined in affirming their faith in these vital principles.</p>
                <p>The most important of these principles, which are indispensable to a satisfactory
                    international order, are as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Maintenance of peace should be constantly advocated and practiced.</p>
                        <p>All nations should, through voluntary self-restraint, abstain from use of
                            force in pursuit of policy and from interference in the internal affairs
                            of other nations.</p>
                        <p>All nations should seek to adjust problems arising in their international
                            relations by processes of peaceful negotiation and agreement.</p>
                        <p>All nations should uphold the principle of the sanctity of treaties and
                            of faithful observance of international agreements.</p>
                        <p>Modification of provisions of treaties, when need therefor arises, should
                            be by orderly processes carried out in a spirit of mutual helpfulness
                            and accommodation.</p>
                        <p>Each nation should respect the rights of others and perform scrupulously
                            its own established obligations; in brief, international law and the
                            spirit which underlies it must be revitalized and strengthened.</p>
                        <pb facs="0550" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/>
                        <p>Steps should be taken toward promotion of economic security and stability
                            the world over through lowering or removal of barriers to international
                            trade, according of effective equality of commercial opportunity, and
                            application of the principle of equality of commercial treatment.</p>
                        <p>National armaments should be limited and be progressively reduced; at the
                            same time, realizing the necessity for maintaining armed forces adequate
                            for national security, each nation should to that end be prepared to
                            reduce or increase its own armed forces in proportion as reductions or
                            increases are made by other nations.</p>
                        <p>Apart from the question of alliances with others, each nation should be
                            prepared to engage in cooperative effort, by peaceful and practicable
                            means, in support of these principles.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The peace and progress of every nation are just as dependent on international law
                    and order, based upon the foregoing principles, as the welfare, stability, and
                    progress of a community are dependent upon domestic law and order, based upon
                    legal, moral, and other recognized standards of conduct. No government faithful
                    to the sacred trust involved in the task of providing for the safety and
                    well-being of its people can disregard these universal principles. Every nation,
                    whatever its form of government, can support them. Every nation must support
                    them, if civilization is to survive. The longer the nations delay acceptance and
                    observance of these fundamental tenets of constructive statesmanship, the graver
                    will be the jeopardy into which all worth-while international relationships will
                    be plunged, and with them the welfare, the happiness, and the civilized
                    existence of all nations.</p>
                <p>The crucial issue today is whether these principles will be vitalized and be
                    firmly established as the foundation of an international order or whether
                    international anarchy based on brute force will inundate the world and
                    ultimately sweep away the very bases of civilization and progress. That issue is
                    universal. No more than a community or a nation, can the world base its
                    existence in part on law and in part on lawlessness, in part on order and in
                    part on chaos, in part on processes of peace and in part on methods of
                    violence.</p>
                <p>On August 23 I made another public statement,<note n="77" xml:id="d320fn77">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_355">p. 355</ref>.</note>
                    reaffirming the principles which should underlie international order, peace, and
                    justice, if the world is to avoid a relapse into another dark night of
                    international anarchy and general retrogression. I called attention again to the
                    fact that if these principles are to be effective they must be universal in
                    their application. This statement was prompted by the fact that the progress and
                    possibilities of armed conflict were becoming more alarming both in the European
                    and the Far Eastern areas and that the basic principles to which I have just
                    referred were <pb facs="0551" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/> being challenged and the
                    doctrine of armed force was gaining supremacy in important regions of the
                    world.</p>
                <p>During the early months of the conflict in the Far East I appealed on several
                    occasions, in the name of our Government, to both Japan and China to desist from
                    using armed force and to resort to the well-recognized processes of peaceful
                    settlement for the adjustment of whatever differences existed between them. I
                    said that we would be glad to be of assistance toward facilitating, in any
                    manner that might be practicable and mutually agreeable, resort by them to such
                    processes.</p>
                <p>On August 17,<note n="78" xml:id="d320fn78">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_349">p. 349</ref>.</note> and
                    with frequent reiteration thereafter, I stated that we did not intend to abandon
                    our nationals and our interests in China.</p>
                <p>From time immemorial it has been the practice of civilized nations to afford
                    protection, by appropriate means and under the rule of reason, to their
                    nationals and their rights and interests abroad. This policy has been pursued by
                    the Government of the United States throughout the existence of our country.</p>
                <p>Methods and means of affording protection abroad vary according to the places in
                    which and the circumstances under which protection is called for. In the case of
                    China, where unusual local conditions were such that the protection afforded by
                    local authorities did not suffice to give security against excited and lawless
                    elements, there have occasionally been sent—not by this country alone but by a
                    number of countries—armed forces, to contribute to the affording of such
                    protection as is due under the rules of international law and the provisions of
                    treaties. American forces thus sent to China have at no time had any mission of
                    aggression, and it has been the practice of the American Government to withdraw
                    such forces whenever and as soon as the local situation so develops as to
                    warrant the view that their withdrawal can be effected without detriment to
                    American interests and obligations in general.</p>
                <p>In announcing our intention to afford appropriate and reasonable protection to
                    our rights and interests in the Far East, I stated clearly that we are fully
                    determined to avoid the extremes either of internationalism or of isolationism.
                    Internationalism would mean undesirable political involvements; isolationism
                    would either compel us to confine all activities of our people within our own
                    frontiers, with incalculable injury to the standard of living and the general
                    welfare of our people, or else expose our nationals and our legitimate interests
                    abroad to injustice or outrage wherever lawless conditions arise. Steering a
                    sound middle course between these two extremes, we are convinced that a policy
                    of affording appropriate protection—under <pb facs="0552" n="456"
                        xml:id="pg_456"/> the rule of reason, in such form as may be best suited to
                    the particular circumstances, and in accordance with the principles we
                    advocate—is imperatively needed to serve our national interest.</p>
                <p>Our decision in this matter is based not only on what we firmly believe to be a
                    specific and elementary duty of a government toward its citizens, but also on
                    other and broader considerations. Respect by a country for the rights and
                    interests of others is a visible test of the fulfillment of obligations assumed
                    by virtue of acceptance of international law and of undertakings embodied in
                    negotiated international instruments. It is, therefore, a test of the observance
                    of those fundamental principles of civilized relations among nations, which, if
                    firmly established, provide in themselves the best means of protection against
                    violation and abuse of the legitimate rights and interests of every nation.</p>
                <p>To waive rights and to permit interests to lapse in the face of their actual or
                    threatened violation—and thereby to abandon obligations—in any important area of
                    the world, can serve only to encourage disregard of law and of the basic
                    principles of international order, and thus contribute to the inevitable spread
                    of international anarchy throughout the world. For this country, as for any
                    country, to act in such manner <hi rend="italic">anywhere</hi> would be to
                    invite disregard and violation of its rights and interests <hi rend="italic"
                        >everywhere</hi>, by every nation so inclined, large or small.</p>
                <p>To respect the rights of others and to insist that others respect our rights has
                    been the traditional policy of our country. This policy was admirably expressed
                    by James Monroe when, in his message to Congress on December 2, 1823, he said:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Our policy … remains the same: … to cultivate friendly relations … and
                            to preserve those relations by frank, firm, and manly policy, meeting in
                            all instances the just claims of every power, submitting to injuries
                            from none.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>In a world in which the rule of force has not as yet been firmly and surely
                    supplanted by the rule of law, it is the manifest duty of a great nation to
                    maintain armed forces adequate for its national defense. Writing on this
                    subject, which was as vital to our national life 150 years ago as it is today,
                    James Madison said: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The means of security can only be regulated by the means and the danger
                            of attack. They will, in fact, be ever determined by these rules, and by
                            no others.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>It is the duty of the Federal Government to insure the safety of our country and
                    to determine what “means of security” are, at any given moment, needed to
                    provide against “the means and the danger of attack.” The responsible heads of
                    our naval establishment offer convincing reasons in support of the program, now
                    before the Congress, <pb facs="0553" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/> to render
                    adequate the means of our national defense. No policy would prove more
                    disastrous than for an important nation to fail to arm adequately when
                    international lawlessness is on the rampage. It is my considered judgment that,
                    in the present state of world affairs, to do less than is now proposed would lay
                    our country open to unpredictable hazards. It would, moreover, seriously
                    restrict our Nation’s ability to command, without purpose or occasion for
                    resorting to arms, proper respect for its legitimate rights and interests, the
                    surrender of which would constitute abandonment of the fundamental principles of
                    justice and morality and peace among nations.</p>
                <p>The maintenance of these principles that are of concern to all nations alike
                    cannot and should not be undertaken by any one nation alone. Prudence and common
                    sense dictate that, where this and other nations have common interests and
                    common objectives, we should not hesitate to exchange information and to confer
                    with the governments of such other nations and, in dealing with the problems
                    confronting each alike, to proceed along parallel lines—this Government
                    retaining at all times its independence of judgment and freedom of action. For
                    nations which seek peace to assume with respect to each other attitudes of
                    complete aloofness would serve only to encourage, and virtually invite, on the
                    part of other nations lawlessly inclined, policies and actions most likely to
                    endanger peace.</p>
                <p>In the present Far Eastern emergency, we have consistently collaborated with
                    other peace-seeking nations in the manner I have just described. I have said
                    often, and I repeat again, that in this collaboration there is not a trace of
                    alliance or involvement of any sort. We have scrupulously followed and we intend
                    to follow the traditional policy of our country not to enter into entangling
                    alliances or involvements with other countries.</p>
                <p>When the Brussels Conference was called, this country, as one of the original
                    signatories of the Nine Power Treaty and in accordance with its treaty
                    obligations thus assumed, promptly accepted the invitation to the Conference.
                    Our delegation cooperated fully with the representatives of the other Conference
                    powers in examining the situation in the Far East and exploring methods of
                    bringing about peace by processes of agreement. The Conference made a
                    substantial contribution toward keeping alive principles of world order and of
                    respect for the pledged word. Its declarations placed a new emphasis upon the
                    deep concern of peaceful nations over any developments that threaten the
                    preservation of peace.</p>
                <p>In connection with the Far Eastern situation, this Government was confronted with
                    the question of applying the existing neutrality legislation, which was designed
                    primarily to keep our Nation out of war. After mature deliberation the
                    conclusion was reached that in the <pb facs="0554" n="458" xml:id="pg_458"/>
                    circumstances attending the controversy in the Far East—a type of circumstances
                    which the authors of the legislation could scarcely have visualized—application
                    of the law would be most likely to endanger the very objectives which the law
                    was designed to promote. Accordingly, exercising the discretion vested in him by
                    the law itself, the President has refrained from putting the provisions of that
                    law into operation. At the same time, in pursuance of our general policy of
                    avoiding unnecessary risks, the President announced, on September 14, 1937,<note
                        n="78a" xml:id="d320fn78a">See <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_201">vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 201</ref>.</note> that “Merchant
                    vessels owned by the Government of the United States will not hereafter, until
                    further notice, be permitted to transport to China or Japan any of the arms,
                    ammunition, or implements of war which were listed in the President’s
                    proclamation of May 1, 1937,”<note n="78b" xml:id="d320fn78b">50 Stat.
                        1834.</note> and that “Any other merchant vessels, flying the American flag,
                    which attempt to transport any of the listed articles to China or Japan will,
                    until further notice, do so at their own risk.”</p>
                <p>Our Government pursues, in relation to every world area alike, a policy of
                    noninterference, with ill will toward no nation and a sincere desire to be
                    friendly with all. At the same time, we endeavor to afford appropriate
                    protection to American citizens and American interests everywhere. During recent
                    months, as throughout the past 150 years, the Government of the United States
                    has sought to exercise moral influence and to cooperate in every practicable way
                    with all peace-seeking nations in support of those basic principles which are
                    indispensable to the promotion and maintenance of stable conditions of
                    peace.</p>
                <p>We have affirmed on every possible occasion and have urged upon all nations the
                    supreme need for keeping alive and for practicing sound fundamental principles
                    of relations among civilized nations. We have never entertained and we have not
                    the slightest intention to entertain any such notion as the use of American
                    armed forces for “policing the world.” But we equally have not the slightest
                    intention of reversing a tradition of a century and a half by abandoning our
                    deep concern for, and our advocacy of, the establishment everywhere of
                    international order under law, based upon the well-recognized principles to
                    which I have referred. It is our profound conviction that the most effective
                    contribution which we, as a nation sincerely devoted to the cause of peace, can
                    make—in the tragic conditions with which our people, in common with the rest of
                    mankind, are confronted today—is to have this country respected throughout the
                    world for integrity, justice, good will, strength, and unswerving loyalty to
                    principles.</p>
                <p>The foregoing is the essence of our foreign policy. The record is an open book.
                    We spare no effort to make known the facts regarding <pb facs="0555" n="459"
                        xml:id="pg_459"/> our attitude, our objectives, and our acts. We are always
                    ready to furnish to the members of the Congress essential information. You,
                    gentlemen, have first-hand knowledge of our constant effort to keep the press
                    and the public informed.</p>
                <p>There is one thing that we cannot do; and that is, to prepare and to place before
                    every government of the world a detailed chart of the course of policy and
                    action which this country will or will not pursue under any particular set of
                    circumstances. No man, no nation, can possibly foresee all the circumstances
                    that may arise. Moreover, to attempt to make such a detailed chart of future
                    action would merely result in impairing our effectiveness in working for the one
                    objective toward which we constantly strive and on which, I am certain, there is
                    not a vestige of disagreement among the people of our country—the establishment
                    of durable peace.</p>
                <p>So strong, indeed, is the desire of this country for peace that many measures
                    have been suggested toward our keeping out of war—some of them in complete
                    disregard of both experience and practicability. It has been urged that we apply
                    the neutrality law automatically in all circumstances, without adequate
                    consideration of the possible consequences of such action for our own peace and
                    for the safety of our citizens. It has been urged that we withdraw precipitately
                    from any part of the world in which violators of international decencies choose
                    to assert themselves. It has even been urged that we change the very basis of
                    our representative form of government in a frantic search for something which
                    the proposers assume would make it more likely that this country avoid war.</p>
                <p>I take it for granted that all of us alike are sincere friends of peace. This
                    makes it all the more necessary for every one of us to scrutinize carefully
                    every measure proposed, lest in our attempts to avoid war we imperil the chances
                    of preserving peace.</p>
                <p>The problem of the form of government best adapted to this country’s needs was
                    one with which the founders of our Republic came to grips in those stirring days
                    when the structure of our independent national existence was being given form
                    and substance. After exhaustive deliberation and discussion they decided upon
                    the system of representative democracy in preference to that of pure democracy
                    as the system through which the people could best safeguard their liberty and
                    promote their national security and welfare. The wisdom of the founders of this
                    Nation in deciding, with conspicuous unanimity, to place the conduct of foreign
                    relations in the hands of the Federal Government has stood the test of
                    generations as providing the most effective means that can be devised for
                    assuring the peace, the security, and the independence of our people.</p>
                <p>What warrant is there, in reason or in experience, for the assumption—which
                    underlies such proposals as the plan for a popular referendum <pb facs="0556"
                        n="460" xml:id="pg_460"/> on the subject of declaring war—that the Chief
                    Executive and the Congress will be at any time more eager and more likely to
                    embark upon war than would be the general body of citizens to whom they are
                    directly responsible? No President and no Congress have ever carried this
                    country into war against the will of the people. On the other hand, there is not
                    a vestige of doubt that the adoption of a procedure like the referendum plan
                    would hopelessly handicap the Government in the conduct of our foreign relations
                    in general and would thus disastrously impair its ability to safeguard the
                    interests of the Nation, in the forefront among which is that of peace.</p>
                <p>Likewise dangerous, from the viewpoint of the preservation of peace, is the
                    proposal that we retire from the Far East, comprising the chief portion of the
                    Pacific area. Unfortunately, many people in this country have wholly
                    misunderstood the position and policy of our Government in relation to that
                    situation. Some have visualized only our trade and investment relationships with
                    China, or our moral and cultural interests there, symbolized by missionary,
                    educational, medical, and similar activities. Some have concentrated their
                    attention solely upon the incidental and exceptional facts of the existence of
                    extraterritoriality and the maintenance of some armed forces to assist in
                    safeguarding our nationals against possible mob violence and similar
                    disorders—special rights which it is our policy to give up and forces which it
                    is our policy to withdraw the moment the unusual conditions disappear.</p>
                <p>All these are important. But the interest and concern of the United
                    States—whether in the Far East, in any other part of the Pacific area, in
                    Europe, or anywhere else in the world—are not measured alone by the number of
                    American citizens residing in a particular country, or by the volume of
                    investment and trade, or by exceptional conditions peculiar to the particular
                    area. There is a much broader and more fundamental interest—which is, that
                    orderly processes in international relationships based on the principles to
                    which I have referred be maintained.</p>
                <p>As I have already indicated, what is most of all at stake today, throughout the
                    world, is the future of the fundamental principles which must be the foundation
                    of international order as opposed to international anarchy. If we and others
                    were to abandon and surrender these principles in regard to the Pacific area,
                    which is almost one-half of the world, we would have to reconcile ourselves to
                    their certain abandonment and surrender in regard to the other half of the
                    world.</p>
                <p>It would be absurd and futile for us to proclaim that we stand for international
                    law, for the sanctity of treaty obligations, for nonintervention in internal
                    affairs of other countries, for equality of industrial and commercial rights and
                    opportunities, for limitation and <pb facs="0557" n="461" xml:id="pg_461"/>
                    reduction of armaments—but only in one-half of the world, and among one-half of
                    the world’s population. The catastrophic developments of recent years, the
                    startling events of the past weeks, offer a tragic demonstration of how quickly
                    the contagious scourge of treaty breaking and armed violence spreads from one
                    region to another.</p>
                <p>Those who contend that we can and should abandon and surrender principles in
                    one-half of the world clearly show that they have little or no conception of the
                    extent to which situations and developments in any part of the world of today
                    inevitably affect situations and conditions in other parts of the world. The
                    triumph of this seclusionist viewpoint would inescapably carry the whole world
                    back to the conditions of medieval chaos, conditions toward which some parts of
                    both the eastern and the western worlds are already moving. Such is the fate to
                    which extreme isolationists—isolationists at any price—all those who contend
                    that we should neither protest against abuses nor cooperate with others toward
                    keeping principles alive, those who say that under no circumstances should we
                    insist upon any rights beyond our own territorial waters—such is the fate to
                    which blind extremism of this type would consign this country and the world.</p>
                <p>The momentous question—let me repeat—is whether the doctrine of force shall
                    become enthroned once more and bring in its wake, inexorably, international
                    anarchy and a relapse into barbarism; or whether this and other peaceful
                    nations, fervently attached to the principles which underlie international
                    order, shall work unceasingly—singly or in cooperation with each other, as
                    circumstances, their traditional policies and practices, and their enlightened
                    selfinterest may dictate—to promote and preserve law, order, morality, and
                    justice as the unshakeable bases of civilized international relations.</p>
                <p>We might, if we could reconcile ourselves to such an attitude, turn our backs on
                    the whole problem and decline the responsibility and labor of contributing to
                    its solution. But let us have no illusions as to what such a course of action
                    would involve for us as a nation.</p>
                <p>It would mean a break with our past, both internationally and domestically. It
                    would mean a voluntary abandonment of some of the most important things that
                    have made us a great nation. It would mean an abject retreat before those forces
                    which we have, throughout our whole national history, consistently opposed.</p>
                <p>It would mean that our security would be menaced in proportion as other nations
                    came to believe that, either through fear or through unwillingness, we did not
                    intend to afford protection to our legitimate national interests abroad, but, on
                    the contrary, intended to abandon them at the first sign of danger. Under such
                    conditions the sphere of our international relationships—economic, cultural, <pb
                        facs="0558" n="462" xml:id="pg_462"/> intellectual, and other—would
                    necessarily shrink and shrivel, until we would stand practically alone among the
                    nations, a self-constituted hermit state.</p>
                <p>Thrown back upon our own resources, we would find it necessary to reorganize our
                    entire social and economic structure. The process of adaptation to a more or
                    less self-contained existence would mean less production and at higher costs;
                    lower living standards; regimentation in every phase of life; economic distress
                    to wage earners and farmers, and to their families; and the dole, on an
                    ever-increasing scale.</p>
                <p>All this we would be doing in pursuit of the notion that by so doing we would
                    avoid war. But would these policies, while entailing such enormous sacrifices
                    and rendering the Nation more and more decadent, really give us any such
                    assurance?</p>
                <p>Reason and experience definitely point to the contrary. We may seek to withdraw
                    from participation in world affairs, but we cannot thereby withdraw from the
                    world itself. Isolation is not a means to security; it is a fruitful source of
                    insecurity.</p>
                <p>We want to live in a world which is at peace; in which the forces of militarism,
                    of territorial aggression, and of international anarchy in general will become
                    utterly odious, revolting, and intolerable to the conscience of mankind; in
                    which the doctrine of order under law will be firmly established; in which there
                    will no longer be one code of morality, honor, justice, and fair play for the
                    individual in his relations with other individuals, and an entirely different
                    code for governments and nations in their relations with each other. We want to
                    live in a world in which fruitful and constructive international relationships
                    can serve as a medium for disseminating throughout the world the benefits of the
                    material, spiritual, and moral progress of mankind.</p>
                <p>To that end we will continue to give full and sincere adherence to the
                    fundamental principles which underlie international order; we will continue to
                    urge universal acceptance and observance of these principles; we will continue,
                    wherever necessary and in every practicable and peaceful way, to cooperate with
                    other nations which are actuated by the same desires and are pursuing the same
                    objectives; we will persevere in appropriate efforts to safeguard our legitimate
                    rights and interests in every part of the world; and we will, while scrupulously
                    respecting the rights of others, insist on their respecting our rights.</p>
                <p>To that end we will continue to strive, through our reciprocal trade program and
                    through other economic policies, to restore the normal processes and to expand
                    the volume of mutually beneficial trade among the nations, which is
                    indispensable to an increase of production, employment, purchasing power, and
                    general economic <pb facs="0559" n="463" xml:id="pg_463"/> well-being here and
                    everywhere; we will continue to promote peace through economic security and
                    prosperity; we will continue to participate in the numerous international
                    scientific, technical, and other conferences and collaborative efforts, which
                    have been such powerful influences in assisting the stream of new ideas, of new
                    discoveries, of learning and culture, to flow throughout the world; and we will
                    continue to urge other nations to give their support to such policies and
                    efforts.</p>
                <p>We believe that a world at peace, with law and justice prevailing, is possible,
                    and that it can be achieved by methods to some of which I have referred. That is
                    the cornerstone of our foreign policy—a policy graphically described by
                    President Roosevelt when he said:<note n="79" xml:id="d320fn79">See address of
                        October 5, 1937, <ref target="#pg_379">pp. 379</ref>, <ref target="#pg_383"
                            >383</ref>.</note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“There must be positive endeavors to preserve peace. America hates war.
                            America hopes for peace. Therefore, America actively engages in the
                            search for peace.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The objectives of our foreign policy are as easy to grasp as they are
                    fundamental. The means we are using to attain these objectives are the only
                    means approved by reason and by experience. For the sake of the best interests
                    of our people, we must maintain our strength, our courage, our moral standards,
                    our influence in world affairs, and our participation in efforts toward world
                    progress and peace. Only by making our reasonable contribution to a firm
                    establishment of a world order based on law can we keep the problem of our own
                    security in true perspective and thus discharge our responsibility to
                    ourselves—to America of today and to America of tomorrow. No other course would
                    be worthy of our past or of the potentialities of this great democracy of which
                    we are all citizens and in whose affairs we all participate.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
