<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-09-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-09-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="341" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d341">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/10157</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>)</head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extract<note n="4" xml:id="d341fn4">For
                                    remainder of this memorandum, see <ref target="#pg_359">p.
                                        359</ref>.</note>]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-09-01">September 1, 1937</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Called on the Minister for Foreign Affairs by appointment at his official
                            residence at 5 o’clock.</p>
                        <pb facs="0589" n="493" xml:id="pg_493"/>
                        <p>I began the interview by referring to our combined efforts during the
                            past years to improve Japanese-American relations. It was my constant
                            endeavor to see those relations maintained and consolidated. Now,
                            however, I felt a daily dread that some serious incident might occur in
                            China arising out of the indiscriminate bombing operations of the
                            Japanese forces which might result in the injury or death of American
                            citizens, and such an incident, as the Minister could well appreciate,
                            would exert a most unfortunate effect on Japanese-American relations
                            because it could not fail to enflame public opinion in the United
                            States. My purpose today was to appeal to the Minister in the most
                            earnest manner to take steps which would obviate the grave risks to
                            which peaceful Americans in China, going about their daily occupations
                            or perhaps on their way to places of greater safety, were now constantly
                            subjected.</p>
                        <p>[Here follow statements giving in substance the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of September 1, 1937, printed <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>.]</p>
                        <p>I then said to the Minister, after reading to him and leaving with him
                            our <hi rend="italic">Aide mémoire</hi> of September 1, that he himself
                            was responsible for the conduct of Japan’s political relations with
                            other countries and that these relations should be considered paramount
                            to military considerations. I therefore appealed to him with great
                            earnestness and strong emphasis to exert his authority in this direction
                            having especially in mind the great importance of avoiding the risk of
                            grave incidents which could injure the friendship between Japan and the
                            United States for the maintenance and development of which we both had
                            been constantly working during the past four years.</p>
                        <p>The Minister inquired whether the bombing on August 26 of which I had
                            spoken, had taken place within the area mentioned in my representations
                            to the Vice Minister on August 23. I replied that I believed this to be
                            the case but whether this was so or not, it did not alter the
                            humanitarian and other aspects of the situation which I had just brought
                            out in my representations to him. Mr. Hirota said that it was the
                            intention of the Japanese military forces to attack only military
                            establishments but that sometimes the bombs failed to reach their
                            precise objectives and accidents happened. He said that he would bring
                            my representations to the attention of the War and Navy Ministries.</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <closer><signed>J[<hi rend="smallcaps">oseph</hi>] C. G[<hi rend="smallcaps">rew</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>