<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs ( (Arita) ) to the American Chargé
                    in Japan ( (Dooman))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931-41v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d486</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">486</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-07-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-07-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec8HXmBQjKyPk0EY" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062603"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Housing</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-07-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-07-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="486"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d486">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">393.1163 Lutheran Brethren/101</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Arita</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Chargé in Japan</hi> (<persName
                        type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dooman</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 90, American I</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-07-17">July 17,
                            1939</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have carefully perused your notes, no. 1272,
                    May 22, 1939, no. 1273, May 22, 1939, and no. 1274, May 22, 1939,<note n="98"
                        xml:id="d486fn98">None printed.</note> in which it was stated that property
                    belonging to the Lutheran Brethren Mission at Tangho, Honan Province, was bombed
                    by Japanese military planes on May 4, 1939; further that the property of the
                    Lutheran Brethren Mission at Tungpeh, Honan, the same property at which the
                    incident resulting in death and injury to members of the Nyhus family on October
                    24, 1938, occurred, was again bombed on May 2, 1939, by Japanese airplanes. You
                    stated that both properties were marked; <pb facs="0759" n="663" xml:id="pg_663"
                    /> and that particularly in the latter case it was entirely improbable that the
                    Japanese military authorities could be ignorant of the existence of the above
                    property. At that time, you stated, there was an American flag flying from a
                    pole on the property and also there was an American flag painted on the roof. In
                    view of these facts, you stated that this bombing of the same property must be
                    viewed as especially flagrant. You protest to the Japanese Government concerning
                    these incidents, and request that measures be taken to prevent any future
                    occurrences of a similar nature.</p>
                <p>The actual facts, however, according to the investigations of the Japanese forces
                    which have recently entered Tangho and Tungpeh, are as set forth in the addendum
                    herewith attached.</p>
                <p>As I have already frequently explained to you, the Japanese air forces have paid
                    from the beginning, and are paying, the strictest attention to the protection of
                    the rights and interests of third countries in China. Nevertheless, in time of
                    war accidental injury may be done to such rights and interests. The Imperial
                    Government sincerely regrets such instances, but it has been learned that these
                    injuries are very often caused, as in the cases at Tangho and Tungpeh, by the
                    fact that the property of American nationals has given the appearance of being
                    that of the enemy, or for the reason that enemy forces have assembled in large
                    numbers, or have constructed their military emplacements in close proximity
                    thereto. The Imperial Government being greatly embarrassed by these facts, I
                    desire emphatically to invite your attention to instances of the above
                    nature.</p>
                <p>You conclude in the latter part of your above-mentioned note no. 1274 that the
                    Japanese authorities are not uniformly animated by a spirit of concern for
                    American rights and interests. As the Minister for Foreign Affairs has, at every
                    opportunity, affirmed to His Excellency, Ambassador Grew, and to you, the
                    Japanese people, the Japanese Government and authorities both civil and military
                    at home and abroad, have always been and are anxious for the maintenance and
                    promotion of friendly relations between Japan and the United States, and have
                    invariably considered in good faith the protection of American rights and
                    interests in China. Accordingly, under present circumstances your statements,
                    such as those mentioned above, are indeed inapposite. I earnestly hope that to a
                    greater degree than heretofore the sincerity of Japan’s attitude will be
                    appreciated.</p>
                <p>Needless to say, the Japanese Government will take all possible measures to
                    protect rights and interests in China. It is requested that the United States,
                    on its part, cooperate fully with Japan toward avoidance of such damages by
                    preventing the Chinese forces from utilizing such property, by prohibiting the
                    building of military emplacements of the Chinese forces in close proximity to
                    that property, and by other measures.</p>
                <pb facs="0760" n="664" xml:id="pg_664"/>
                <p>Finally, I wish to call your attention to the fact that officials of the Japanese
                    Army at Shanghai, officials of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and other
                    officials concerned are at present conferring and are giving particular
                    attention to the question of a solatium for the members of the Nyhus family who
                    were injured in the recent unfortunate accident at Tungpeh.</p>
                <p>I avail myself [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hachiro Arita</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Addendum</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>1. It was determined that Japanese airplanes did, in fact, bomb and destroy
                        an American mission at Tungpeh. This mission was comprised of two buildings
                        constructed near the provincial government’s building. Of the above two
                        buildings, one, the main building a two story structure, was struck by a
                        bomb and destroyed with the exception of one portion of about one hundred
                        and forty-four square feet in the north corner. On the roof of that part
                        left standing, there was a small observation lookout. The other building was
                        a barrack-like structure. Inside there were definite evidences of the
                        housing of a large number of people and straw was spread on the floor. There
                        was a brick wall around this mission and there were loopholes cut into the
                        wall. The property clearly had enemy character.</p>
                    <p>It is definitely established that all of the buildings within the walls of
                        Tungpeh were appropriated by enemy forces and were utilized as barracks. For
                        example the school building in the center of the walled city was remodeled
                        as a military barracks and a neighboring house was used as a military
                        telephone exchange with many telephone lines converging on it. There was a
                        room marked “Commander’s Headquarters” in the provisional government’s
                        office building near the above mission which clearly indicates that this
                        served as the headquarters of the enemy forces. Further, houses in the
                        immediate or close proximity of this same mission were practically all
                        marked “Training Corps no.”. There were many evidences that these buildings
                        were barracks of the enemy forces and such buildings were destroyed by the
                        Japanese air forces. The propriety of such action from the standpoint of
                        prosecution of hostilities may be proved by actual evidence.</p>
                    <p>2. The Japanese air forces had discovered at the time of the bombing of
                        Tangho that there was a large concentration of enemy troops near the
                        American mission at that place. This discovery was later verified as a fact
                        through investigations among the local populace. This mission was very small
                        and not more than one very small part of it was destroyed. Even in this case
                        as well, there are many evidences that the enemy forces took military
                        advantage of American rights and interests.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
