<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The American Ambassador in Japan ( (Grew) ) to the Japanese Minister for
                    Foreign Affairs ( (Arita))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931-41v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d606</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">606</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-11-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-11-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec3U9TKkW5rS0s3i" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea">Freedom of navigation</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-11-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-11-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="606"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d606">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.811/1060</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The American Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Arita</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1111</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-11-07">November 7,
                            1938</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: In the note No. 1076 of October 6,
                    1938, which I had the honor to address to Your Excellency’s distinguished
                    predecessor, mention was made, among other points, of the exclusion from the
                    lower reaches of the Yangtze River of American and other non-Japanese shipping
                    although Japanese merchant vessels are carrying Japanese merchandise between
                    Shanghai and Nanking, to the exclusion of merchandise of other countries. I
                    pointed out to His Excellency Prince Konoye that this treatment of American
                    shipping and commerce, as well as the treatment by Japanese authorities of other
                    American interests in China, not’ only violates American rights but is in direct
                    contravention of assurances repeatedly affirmed by the Japanese Government to
                    the American Government that the principle of the open door and equal
                    opportunity in China would be supported by the Japanese Government. In the
                    aforementioned note, request was made on behalf of the Government of the United
                    States that the Japanese Government implement its assurances already given with
                    regard to the maintenance of the open door and to non-interference with American
                    rights by taking prompt measures to cause the discontinuance, among other forms
                    of interference with American interests in China, of the restrictions placed
                    upon American trade and shipping.</p>
                <p>Acting under instructions from my Government I now have the honor to point out to
                    Your Excellency that the armed forces of Japan have now advanced up the Yangtze
                    River as far as Hankow and that below Hankow there are no longer major
                    hostilities on the river or along the banks of the river. A large number of
                    Japanese ships in the meantime have proceeded up the river to Hankow. Japanese
                    armed forces, furthermore, following their arrival at Hankow, have had ample
                    time in which to systematize the movement of Japanese vessels on the river.</p>
                <p>During the period when active hostilities were taking place on certain reaches of
                    the Yangtze River below Hankow, American shipping refrained from exercising its
                    right to freedom of navigation on the river. That the Japanese Government should
                    no longer place obstacles in the way of the exercise of this American right, my
                    Government considers only reasonable. The Yangtze River as the main artery of
                    transportation in Central China is a highly important channel for the movement
                    of vessels, persons and merchandise and the width of the river is amply
                    sufficient to take care of the traffic needs of all concerned. No reasonable
                    basis to account for the restriction <pb facs="0891" n="795" xml:id="pg_795"/>
                    by the Japanese Government of the free use of this river under the circumstances
                    existing at present is perceived by the Government of the United States.</p>
                <p>Under the circumstances set forth above I have the honor on behalf of my
                    Government once again to request that the Japanese Government forthwith
                    implement its repeated assurances with regard to American navigation rights on
                    the Yangtze River by promptly discontinuing the restrictions on American trade
                    and shipping thereon between Shanghai and Hankow.</p>
                <p>I avail myself [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph C. Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
