<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-09-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-09-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="646" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d646">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.94/1795</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-09-20">September 20, 1940</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The Japanese Ambassador called to see me this afternoon at my request. I
                            handed the Ambassador the “oral statement”<note n="70" xml:id="d646fn70"><hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note> which the Far Eastern
                            Division had prepared as a reply to the memorandum which the Ambassador
                            had left with me on August 23.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador read the memorandum very attentively, but before he had an
                            opportunity of commenting upon it, I told him that, as he would see from
                            the last paragraph of the statement handed to him, I had found it
                            necessary to express regret for the tone of the language used in the
                            document which the Ambassador had left with me and I felt that it was
                            necessary to emphasize the fact that I did not believe that the friendly
                            and equitable solution which the Ambassador and I both desired of the
                            questions at issue between the two Governments could be advanced by the
                            employment of the kind of language employed by the Japanese Government
                            in this recent communication.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador immediately said that if the tone or the language employed
                            seemed to me discourteous, this was far from the intention of his
                            Government and that it should be attributed solely to the faulty
                            vocabulary and knowledge of the English language of those responsible
                            for the drafting of the document. I told the Ambassador that I was very
                            glad to accept this explanation.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador then said that he noted with great regret that no progress
                            was made in the solution of the July 7 incident<note n="70a" xml:id="d646fn70a">See telegram No. 671, July 22, 1940, 1 p.m., from
                                the Consul at Shanghai, <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_101">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 101</ref>.</note> or in the
                            adjustment of the Sector question.<note n="70b" xml:id="d646fn70b">See
                                statement by the Secretary of State, September 4, 1940, <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_111">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 111</ref>.</note> He stated that in his opinion
                            both of these questions were of relatively minor importance and that he
                            could not but feel that a satisfactory compromise could be found should
                            the Government of the United States desire to find it. He stated that he
                            was informed that in 1931 and 1934 the commanding officers of the
                            International Settlement Forces had recommended that Sectors D and B be
                            policed by the International Police Force with the temporary assistance
                            from time to time of the Volunteer Force should these additional
                            services be required. He urged that a compromise of this nature now be
                            agreed upon.</p>
                        <p>I told the Ambassador that I was not prepared to make any comment upon
                            this suggestion beyond saying that this suggestion had not been found
                            acceptable by our authorities in the past because of <pb facs="0974" n="878" xml:id="pg_878"/> our belief that it was not a practical
                            suggestion, but that I would convey the Ambassador’s remarks to the
                            appropriate authorities of the Navy Department.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador then said with regard to the July 7 incident that it
                            seemed to him that all that was required was an agreement on the
                            language of some expression of regret on the part of the American
                            authorities.</p>
                        <p>I called the Ambassador’s attention to the fact that in the oral
                            statement which I had just handed him, it had been made entirely clear
                            that the United States did not believe that any apology from its
                            officials was called for.</p>
                        <p>I then said that to my very great regret, the Ambassador’s mission in
                            Washington was soon to terminate and that I wanted to tell him again how
                            sorry I was to see him leave because of my recognition of the constant
                            efforts which he had made to work towards an improvement in the
                            relations between our two countries.</p>
                        <p>I said that as he was now leaving, it was all the more regrettable to me
                            to note that the divergences of opinion between the two Governments and
                            the serious misunderstandings which had arisen between Japan and the
                            United States were not only not diminished in scope, but appeared,
                            unfortunately, to be increasing materially both in volume and character.
                            I said it must be evident to him as it was to me that no matter how much
                            men of good will in both countries might try to prevent it, if this
                            situation continued no one could prophesy with any assurance that the
                            result might not be of a very serious character.</p>
                        <p>I said that the Ambassador was undoubtedly aware of the information which
                            had reached this Government that the Japanese military representative in
                            French Indo China, General Nishihara, had been instructed yesterday to
                            present an ultimatum to the French Governor General making demands which
                            were tantamount to a demand for complete occupation of French Indo
                            China, with the threat that if these demands were not accepted before
                            ten p.m. Sunday, September 22, the Japanese military forces would at
                            once invade Indo China.<note n="70c" xml:id="d646fn70c">See telegram No.
                                357, September 19, 1940, 9 p.m., to the Ambassador in Japan, <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_294">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 294</ref>.</note> I said the Ambassador was
                            likewise in all probability further informed that the French Governor
                            General had refused the demands in question. I said that therefore the
                            civilized world was confronted with a spectacle which in all probability
                            meant that in the immediate future the Government of Japan, in addition
                            to the acts of aggression which it had committed against the Government
                            of China during the past nine years, especially during the past three
                            years, was now about to commit an act of aggression on a colonial
                            possession of the Government of France.</p>
                        <pb facs="0975" n="879" xml:id="pg_879"/>
                        <p>I then read to the Ambassador from a memorandum which had been prepared
                            by the Far Eastern Division<note n="71" xml:id="d646fn71">Not
                                printed.</note> the various official utterances of Japanese
                            statesmen and spokesmen during the past six months in which they had
                            repeatedly reiterated as the official position of the Japanese
                            Government the desire of the latter to maintain the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> in the Far East and in the course of which
                            statements they had upon repeated occasions indicated their entire
                            concurrence with the United States in the expressed desire of the latter
                            that the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> be maintained. I said that
                            here was once more presented a flagrant case where the official
                            announcements of the Japanese Government were completely counter to the
                            policies and acts of its military authorities, and I concluded by saying
                            that I was, of course, fully aware that the Japanese Ambassador himself
                            could be under no misapprehension as to the very serious disquiet and
                            very open opposition which the action threatened by the Japanese
                            Government would create in the minds of the members of the United States
                            Government and on the part of public opinion in general in this
                            country.</p>
                        <p>The Japanese Ambassador at first attempted to say that all that the
                            latest demands made by General Nishihara amounted to was compliance with
                            the agreement reached on August 30 between the Vichy Government of
                            France and the Japanese Government. I immediately stated that this
                            obviously was not the case since the demands had been rejected by the
                            French Governor General of Indo China on the specific ground that they
                            were entirely outside of the scope of the agreement of August 30. The
                            Ambassador then said that he had not been informed of the exact terms of
                            the ultimatum presented and that he had not been advised of the
                            confirmation of this information which had been given to Ambassador Grew
                            by Foreign Minister Matsuoka the night before.<note n="71a" xml:id="d646fn71a">See memorandum by the Ambassador in Japan,
                                September 20, 1940, <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_295">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 295</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>The Ambassador said that I should bear in mind the fact that there was a
                            very great likelihood that Japan was undertaking the occupation of
                            French Indo China not only as a means of expediting a conclusion of the
                            hostilities in China and solely as a temporary measure with no thought
                            of a permanent occupation of the colony, but also as a means of
                            preventing the German Government, should Germany now prove victorious in
                            her battle with Great Britain, from occupying the French, British, and
                            Dutch possessions in the Far East.</p>
                        <p>To this I said that it would seem to me obvious that if the Japanese
                            Government found it necessary, for reasons of which we were not aware,
                            to consider taking precautionary measures as a means of preserving,
                            rather than disrupting, the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> in the Far
                            East, this <pb facs="0976" n="880" xml:id="pg_880"/> Government would
                            not only have been willing, but glad, to discuss these possibilities
                            with the Japanese Government since, as I had said before, it had
                            repeatedly been stated by this Government as its considered policy that
                            it would support the whole structure of international treaties and
                            agreements covering the maintenance of the stability and the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> in the Far East, except in so far as
                            modifications thereto might be agreed upon through negotiation and
                            peaceful processes. I said that I could hardly accept with any sincerity
                            the argument that Japan was now occupying French Indo China solely in
                            order to prevent Germany from undertaking such occupation.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador then said that this Government only recently, as a means
                            of insuring its own security, had obtained air and naval bases on
                            British possessions in the Western Hemisphere.<note n="71b" xml:id="d646fn71b">See exchange of notes at Washington, September 2,
                                1940; Department of State, <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                                September 7, 1940 (vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, No. 63), p.
                                199.</note></p>
                        <p>I said to the Ambassador that I was sorry to have to say that I could
                            imagine no parallel less well chosen than that he mentioned for the
                            action which the Japanese Government contemplated in French Indo China.
                            On one side—the Anglo-American side, we had an agreement freely entered
                            into on a basis of give and take, and reached because of the belief of
                            the two Governments that the bargain so consummated enhanced the
                            security of the two nations involved; whereas on the other hand, we had
                            a demand presented by Japan to French Indo China stating that if the
                            local authorities would not immediately pave the way for complete
                            occupation of the entire territory by Japanese troops, the Japanese
                            troops were going to walk in and take charge by force through acts of
                            aggression. I said I could not for the moment accept any parallel
                            between the two questions.</p>
                        <p>In conclusion I said that I felt it necessary for me to remind the
                            Ambassador of the policy which this Government had publicly announced as
                            the policy which it would pursue with regard to Great Britain, namely, a
                            policy of furnishing to the utmost measure of its ability all material
                            supplies, munitions, et cetera, to Great Britain in order to assist the
                            latter nation to defend herself against the aggression of Germany and
                            her allies. I said that in the Pacific region where this Government
                            likewise desired in its own interest to see peace maintained, the United
                            States was confronted by a series of acts of aggression committed by
                            Japan against her neighbor China, and now in all probability, against
                            the adjacent colony of Indo China. I said that I would be lacking in
                            candor if I did not make it clear to the Ambassador that, consistent
                            with its policy with regard to Great Britain, the United States would
                            likewise feel it necessary to furnish such means of assistance in the
                            way of supplies, munitions, et cetera, for these victims of aggression
                            in the Pacific area as might be required. I said that in view of the
                            violation by Japan of the structure of international <pb facs="0977" n="881" xml:id="pg_881"/> law in her dealings with her neighbors in
                            the Far East and her infringement of the legitimate rights of the United
                            States and of American nationals, the Government of Japan could
                            certainly have no ground for complaint because the United States lent
                            assistance of the character I had indicated to China, and to Indo China
                            in the event that the latter was attacked.</p>
                        <closer><signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps">elles</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>