<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-07-11T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-07-11T09:00:00-05:00" n="219" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d219">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72112Sa/7</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Denmark</hi> (<persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_GSU1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grant-Smith</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Copenhagen</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-07-11T15:00:00+01:00">
                                    <hi rend="italic">July 11, 1918, 3 p.m.</hi>
                                </date>
                                <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received July 12, 12.15
                                a.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>2493. Your 955, July 5, 6 p.m.<note n="1" xml:id="d219fn1">Not printed;
                                see telegram to the Minister in Norway, No. 374, July 6, <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1084">p.
                                1084</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The German shipping demands made of neutrals are a direct result of the
                            agreements now being concluded between them and ourselves. A
                            counter-move was inevitable. I am informed that they demand that Norway
                            deposit in Germany 1,000 crowns per ton dead weight for each ship
                            applying for safe-conduct previous to departure, as guaranty. Disputes
                            to be adjudicated by German courts. Should this excessive figure prove
                            accurate, it would indicate an intent to preclude compliance, while
                            ostensibly throwing the blame on us.</p>
                        <p>The German desire is of course through extreme pressure applied to
                            neutrals to obtain the release by the Associated Governments of as much
                            tonnage as possible, and to secure a hold over them for <hi rend="italic">post bellum</hi> service. The effect on exchange as
                            the result of such deposits would at once be marked. I have assurances
                            from reliable sources, that the Germans have made no new demands of
                            Denmark, but they fear the influence of <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_HPv1">Von Hintze</persName> at Berlin.
                            One American interested <pb facs="0254" n="1088" xml:id="pg_1088"/> in
                            shipping stated that it appeared now to be Germany’s policy to avoid
                            sinking neutral ships on account of after-the-war trade, and also
                            because it was to her interests to encourage the import into Denmark of
                            as much goods as possible, knowing that a portion must leak through into
                            Germany.</p>
                        <p>Denmark has a long-standing shipping agreement with Germany, a copy of
                            which I have never succeeded in obtaining, but Mr.
                                <persName>Foss</persName> yesterday assured me that it contained
                            nothing inimical to the interests of the Associated Governments. I would
                            suggest that the delegates be requested to produce it, or to cause a
                            copy to be confidentially communicated to me here.</p>
                        <p>Should need arise, the only way to meet such a situation as regards this
                            country would seem to be by threatening to decline to sign an agreement
                            with Denmark, and to dispose of her tonnage as we saw fit, for the
                            purpose of placing her in a position to plead <hi rend="italic">force
                                majeure</hi> to the Germans. A consequent public announcement to the
                            effect that we were forced in the circumstances to withhold bunkers from
                            all ships bound for Denmark in spite of our keen desire to supply them
                            with certain commodities, might possibly stir the country to such an
                            extent that sufficient public pressure might be exerted to cause a
                            sensible diminution for a time of the export of foodstuffs to Germany
                            and thus cause the latter to modify her attitude. The policy of the
                            Danish Government seems to be one of helpless acquiescence. Copy to
                            London.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_GSU1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Grant-Smith</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>