<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Norway ( (Schmedeman) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918Supp01v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d269</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">269</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-03-09T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-03-09T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-03-09T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-03-09T13:00:00-05:00" n="269"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d269">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72111N83/5</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Norway</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_SAG1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Schmedeman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Christiania</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-03-09T19:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 9, 1918—7 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received March 10, 3.50 p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>576. The following is translation of note dated today which has been
                    confidentially handed me by the Minister for Foreign Affairs with the request
                    that it be transmitted to my Government.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>The Norwegian Government considers it advisable to reaffirm its neutrality
                        during the war, which is still continuing between other powers, and to make
                        the following declaration which is entirely in accord with the policy it has
                        followed during the whole war and which I have the honor to request you
                        kindly to bring to the knowledge of the American Government: Norway will,
                        during the war, remain impartially neutral, will maintain her independence,
                        and is determined if necessary to resist by force of arms any violation by
                        any power or group of powers of her territorial rights, and to prevent the
                        use of Norwegian territory as a base by any power whatever. The Norwegian
                        Government considers it a logical consequence of its policy of neutrality
                        that it should refuse during the war to enter into any negotiations with a
                        power or group of powers or conclude any agreement which would render it
                        impossible to maintain neutrality.</p>
                    <p>Finally it is a satisfaction to the Norwegian Government to be able to point
                        out that at no time in the course of the war has any power requested Norway
                        to participate in the war, or approached her for assistance or for
                        permission to establish a base on Norwegian territory, or in any way made
                        requests or representations with a view to persuade Norway to abandon her
                        neutrality.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>A similar note is understood to have been handed to all ministers here. Minister
                    for Foreign Affairs informed me that foregoing note was occasioned by articles
                    which have lately appeared in German newspapers attacking Norway in view of
                    general pro-Ally sentiment and the contemplated trade agreements with the Allies
                    as well as by allegations which have again reached the Minister for Foreign
                    Affairs that certain Allied Powers are endeavoring to obtain a naval base in
                    Norway.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_SAG1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Schmedeman</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
