<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-08-22T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-08-22T16:00:00-05:00" n="362" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d362">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 658.119/576</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Whitehouse</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-08-22T22:00:00+01:00">
                                        <hi rend="italic">August 22, 1918, 10 p.m.</hi>
                                    </date>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received August 23, 8.10
                                    a.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>2694. On August 20 Mr. <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_WM1">Marcus Wallenberg</persName> at the request of Swedish prime
                                Minister informed British Minister of the following:</p>
                            <p>The Swedish Government made a coal arrangement with the German
                                Government in April, to continue till the end of September, by which
                                certain articles whose export is Prohibited by the London agreement
                                were to be exported to Germany. Under this arrangement Sweden was to
                                receive 150,000 tons of coal monthly and in return was to give
                                monthly export licenses for 25 tons impregnated canvas and 50 tons
                                animal hair, as well as certain ores and slags. <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_WM1">Wallenberg</persName>
                                explained that the impregnated canvas belonged to stocks which
                                Germans had held in the country for a considerable time past, while
                                the animal hair was of Swedish origin. Further they were to give
                                licenses for 3,500,000 kroner worth of wood pulp, amounting to about
                                100,000 tons, up to October 1, and for 3,000,000 kroner worth of
                                spinning paper, amounting to about 27,690 tons, of which 14,000 tons
                                was exported up to the beginning of August. About 6,000 tons of
                                other paper has also been exported during the same period. The <pb facs="0448" n="1282" xml:id="pg_1282"/> Swedish Government now
                                desire to export in compensation for coal received the balance of
                                the spinning paper, making in all 27,690 tons, and to spread this
                                remainder out over a period of a further six months until April 1,
                                1919.</p>
                            <p>The pulp exported [until] now under coal arrangement is already in
                                excess of the quarterly amounts fixed by London agreement,<note n="1" xml:id="d362fn1">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1240">p.
                                        1240</ref>.</note> but the yearly export may in the opinion
                                of the Swedish Government be brought within limits so fixed by also
                                spreading the remainder over a further six months.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_WM1">Wallenberg</persName>, on behalf of the Swedish Government,
                                expressed the hope that such an arrangement with reference to the
                                pulp and spinning paper would meet with the requirements of
                                Associated Governments and that the export of these goods could thus
                                be arranged so as to fit in with the London agreement. As regards
                                the exports of canvas and hair, Mr. <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_WM1">Wallenberg</persName> referred
                                to letters 19 and 20 [<hi rend="italic">9 and 10</hi><note n="2" xml:id="d362fn2">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1272">pp.
                                        1272</ref>, <ref target="#pg_1273">1273</ref>.</note>]
                                attached to London agreement which were exchanged between himself
                                and Commander <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_HFL1">Harris</persName> and according to which certain licenses
                                [were] already granted Germany for goods to be given in compensation
                                for goods received from Germany. Mr. <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_WM1">Wallenberg</persName> informed
                                him officially of an arrangement also made in April between the
                                Storakopparberg Company, of which he is chairman, and the German
                                Government for the export of 40,000 tons pyrites annually to Germany
                                in return for coal and coke required by the company. License for the
                                whole 40,000 tons had been granted in April by the Swedish
                                Government but Mr. <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_WM1">Wallenberg</persName> said that he had [not] been informed of
                                this in London or he would certainly have communicated it to the
                                Allied negotiations and endeavored to secure a settlement.</p>
                            <p>Twenty-five thousand tons of these pyrites had been exported to
                                Germany from the beginning of May up to now, but the Swedish
                                Government would give assurances that this export would now
                                altogether cease, although this would mean a very serious loss to
                                the company which would hardly be able to carry out work at their
                                iron foundries without German coke. Though chairman of the company,
                                he had thought it his duty to urge on the Swedish Government the
                                cessation of this export so as not to produce a conflict with the
                                London agreement.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_WM1">Wallenberg</persName>
                                promised to hand British Minister a memorandum which was received
                                yesterday and of which the following is a summary:</p>
                            <p>Owing to prolonged negotiations in London it was impossible for
                                Swedish Government to curtail export to Germany of several articles
                                merely on a presumption that proposed agreement might contain
                                restrictions in regard to such export. Before conclusion of the
                                agreement <pb facs="0449" n="1283" xml:id="pg_1283"/> the Swedish
                                delegates in London strongly emphasized the difficulties which would
                                arise during the first months after the agreement came into
                                operation, as contracts would have been made and licenses granted
                                with the sanction of the Swedish Government. It is especially the
                                coal agreements with Germany which bind Sweden to deliver various
                                articles and make it impossible for her to fulfill strictly the
                                agreement of May 29, before several months reorganization
                                elapsed.</p>
                            <p>According to article 13 of the agreement, the export to the Central
                                Powers of pulp and paper is limited with a further restriction that
                                “the quantity of each in any one quarter shall not be greater than
                                the quantity of each which has been exported in the corresponding
                                quarter of 1917.” As regards pulp, the figures for the quarter June
                                to August, 1917, are so low that it will be absolutely essential to
                                combine them with the figures of the next quarter in order to be
                                able to fulfill the contracts made with Germany. It would greatly
                                help Sweden if henceforth the restrictions of paper and pulp exports
                                could be calculated half yearly instead of quarterly.</p>
                            <p>Sweden would also desire to be entitled to make sulphite and sulphate
                                interchangeable with the restriction that the stipulated quantity of
                                sulphate will not be exceeded.</p>
                            <p>Concerning paper, quarterly exports in 1917 are more equally divided,
                                but in order to be able to fulfill previous arrangement with
                                Germany, Sweden desires the half yearly instead of quarterly
                                calculation, and the same applies to the reduction of textile
                                rations.</p>
                            <p>Under the general agreement exportation of pyrites to Central Powers
                                is prohibited. The memorandum then refers to the Storakopparberg
                                contract with Germany for 40,000 tons of pyrites, and states that
                                after the agreement was ratified the Government informed the company
                                that the export of pyrites must cease. The Swedish Government has
                                granted the export of in all 25,000 tons of pyrites of which about
                                18,000 tons were shipped before the ratification of the agreement,
                                and the company now desires to fulfill the whole contract and export
                                15,000 tons more, pointing out the disastrous position in which it
                                will be [placed] by not receiving German coals in the future, as the
                                company cannot be run on English coal, the price being
                                prohibitive.</p>
                            <p>In order to comply with arrangements made in connection with delivery
                                of coal and in compensation for other articles already obtained,
                                Sweden has to send to Germany articles, a list is here given, of
                                which following are the most important items: manganese ore 2,500
                                tons, cinders 6,950 tons, sulphuric acid 15 tons, matte containing 7
                                per cent of copper and 7 per cent of nickel, 150 tons. Copy to
                                London.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Whitehouse</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>