<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Commercial Adviser of the British Embassy ( (Crawford) ) to the Counselor
                    for the Department of State ( (Polk))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918Supp01v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d487</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">487</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-03-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-03-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112903"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Repatriation</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-03-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-03-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="487"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d487">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 656.119/299</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Commercial Adviser of the British Embassy</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_CSR1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Crawford</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Counselor for the Department of State</hi>
                        (<persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_PFL1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Polk</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-03-21">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 21, 1918</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_PFL1"
                            >Polk</persName>
                    </hi>: With reference to our conversation of yesterday, I now enclose text of
                    the communication which is to be addressed to the Netherlands Government in
                    connection with the requisitioning of Dutch tonnage. I have sent a copy to Mr.
                        <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_MVC1">McCormick</persName>.</p>
                <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_CSR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Richard Crawford</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Communication to be made by the British Minister in the
                            Netherlands</hi> (<persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_TSWB1"
                            type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Townley</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Netherland Minister of Foreign
                            Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_LJJ1" type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Loudon</hi>
                        </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d487fn1">Telegraphed on Mar. 21 to the
                            British Minister in the Netherlands, who delivered it to the Netherland
                            Government on Mar. 22.</note>
                    </head>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>After full consideration, the Associated Governments have decided to
                            requisition services of Dutch ships in their ports in exercise of right
                            of angary. They would have preferred to obtain use of <pb facs="0587"
                                n="1421" xml:id="pg_1421"/> ships by way of agreement with the
                            Netherlands Government and, as Your Excellency knows, an arrangement for
                            this purpose was made between representatives of the Netherlands
                            Government and of the Associated Governments as long ago as beginning of
                            last January.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Unfortunately the Netherlands Government for more than two months did
                            not see their way to ratify that arrangement. They moreover had found it
                            impossible to carry out in all its terms <hi rend="italic">modus
                                vivendi</hi> which had been arrived at pending a ratification of
                            agreement, explaining that the German Government would not allow them to
                            do so. It seemed therefore clear to the Associated Governments that
                            proposals originally made were not adequate to present situation. Delay
                            had altered circumstances. Condition that Dutch shipping was not to be
                            used in danger zone was no longer acceptable in itself and might at any
                            time have been made still less so by an extension of zone by our
                            enemies. Further, fate of <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> had shewn
                            that in very difficult position in which Netherlands Government were
                            placed execution of agreement would probably have been attended with
                            difficulties and delays still more prejudicial to interest of Associated
                            Governments.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The Associated Governments therefore proposed that limitation on use
                            of Dutch shipping contemplated under the original scheme should be
                            abandoned, and that in its altered form, agreement should come into
                            force immediately. To this the Netherlands Government could not assent
                            except upon terms which would have made it practically impossible for
                            the Associated Governments to make any use of Dutch shipping. To say
                            that shipping shall not be employed for carriage of war material is at
                            this stage of war equivalent to saying that it shall not be used at all.
                            For with regard to great majority of cargoes it is impossible to say
                            that they are not required directly or Indirectly for purposes of
                            war.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>For these reasons Associated Governments have felt compelled to fall
                            back on their unquestionable right to employ any shipping found in their
                            ports for necessities of war. But they are very anxious that exercise of
                            this right should be as little burdensome to shipowners and as little
                            obnoxious to Netherlands Government as it can be made.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Associated Governments hope that it may be possible to arrive at an
                            agreement with owners as to rates of pay, values for insurance, etc.,
                            and on these points a further communication to the Netherlands
                            Government will be sent very shortly. At the end of the war the ships
                            will be returned to their owners who will of course be compensated for
                            any losses caused amongst ships by enemy action. Associated Governments
                            are willing further to offer owners, on conditions to be mutually agreed
                            upon, an option to have any ship which <pb facs="0588" n="1422"
                                xml:id="pg_1422"/> may be so lost in the danger zone as it exists at
                            present, actually replaced by another ship within shortest possible
                            period after the conclusion of peace. I need hardly assure Your
                            Excellency that all facilities in power of Associated Governments will
                            be given for repatriation of crews if desired and that all precautions
                            will be taken to ensure that they be treated with every courtesy and
                            consideration.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Further, the Associated Governments hereby give the Netherlands
                            Government an undertaking that Dutch ships which may leave a Dutch port
                            after the date of this communication shall not be brought into Allied
                            services otherwise than in agreement with owners.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>Associated Governments having been informed that unless the stocks of
                            grain now in the Netherlands be replenished in time, Holland is
                            threatened with a serious shortage during third quarter of this year,
                            will at once place at her disposal 50,000 tons of wheat (or an
                            equivalent quantity of flour) in a North American port and 50,000 tons
                            in a South American port. It is hoped that the Netherlands Government
                            will immediately send out such part of tonnage remaining in Holland as
                            may be necessary to lift this grain. The Associated Governments
                            guarantee that as far as it is in their power these ships shall enjoy
                            immunity from delay and detention and receive every facility for
                            bunkering.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>The United States Government have already intimated that the steamship
                                <hi rend="italic">Nieuw Amsterdam</hi> at present in New York will
                            not be utilised by them and will under the special arrangement covering
                            it be allowed not only to return at once to Holland but to load a cargo
                            of foodstuffs consisting of rice and coffee. This cargo will be composed
                            of original cargoes of steamship <hi rend="italic">Samarinda</hi> and
                            steamship <hi rend="italic">Adonis</hi> which would have been allowed to
                            proceed to Holland if <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> already
                            referred to had come into force.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>As regards further supplies of cereals, foodstuffs, raw materials and
                            all other articles importation of which is provided for in proposals for
                            general arrangement, Associated Governments are willing to give Dutch
                            vessels now in Dutch ports every facility for their importation into
                            Holland in accordance with provisions and terms of general agreement, if
                            Netherlands Government are ready (as Associated Governments hope they
                            are) to signify their acceptance of its terms generally.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>Associated Governments believe that Dutch ships now in their ports do
                            not fully correspond to tonnage to whose services they had hoped to
                            become entitled under terms proposed of general arrangement and that
                            vessels now in or on their way to Dutch ports will be found to exceed
                            tonnage needed for imports of Netherlands and their colonies calculated
                            on basis of original tonnage proposals provisionally <pb facs="0589"
                                n="1423" xml:id="pg_1423"/> agreed by Dutch delegates. If contrary
                            to this expectation it should be proved to satisfaction of Associated
                            Governments that this is not the case, latter will be ready to make up
                            any deficiency of tonnage left at Holland’s disposal on lines of various
                            provisions of general arrangement covering use and distribution of Dutch
                            tonnage, as soon as Netherlands Government shall have supplied Allied
                            Governments with definite figures of tonnage now in or on the way to
                            Dutch ports.</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
