<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-09-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-09-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="587" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d587">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 656.119/763</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Netherland Chargé</hi> (<persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_DBWH1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">De Beaufort</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-09-03">
                                        <hi rend="italic">September 3, 1918</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                receipt of your note of August 21, 1918,<note n="1" xml:id="d587fn1">Not printed.</note> concerning certain ships which my
                                Government desires to use in transporting grain cereals to the
                                Netherlands. I have not failed to acquaint my Government with the
                                contents of this note and have now received instructions enabling me
                                to give the following reply:</p>
                            <p>The Minister for Foreign Affairs at The Hague has been informed by
                                the American Minister there that he cabled a very complete <pb facs="0696" n="1530" xml:id="pg_1530"/> statement to your
                                Department relative to the reply <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_LJJ1">Jonkheer Loudon</persName>
                                gave on May 27 last to a member of Parliament and in which he
                                communicated the protest of Her Majesty’s Government against the
                                modification of article 55 of the German prize regulation.<note n="1" xml:id="d587fn2">Telegram No. 2980, May 31, from the
                                    Minister in the Netherlands, <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1498">p. 1498</ref>.</note> If nevertheless you
                                desire to obtain for submission to the President the exact text of
                                the reply in question, my Government will enable me to forward it to
                                you.</p>
                            <p>
                                <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_LJJ1">Jonkheer
                                    Loudon</persName> observed to the American Minister—and wishes
                                me to call the same point to your attention—that in Holland the most
                                efficient method to obtain publicity is to reply in writing to a
                                written question of a member of Parliament. These are not ordinary
                                questions and replies which may escape public attention. To the
                                contrary these questions and replies are always prominently
                                published by the newspapers and this was also done in regard to the
                                question and reply concerning the protest mentioned above. The
                                people of the Netherlands was consequently placed in a position to
                                reach an unprejudiced conclusion and the Minister for Foreign
                                Affairs is convinced that it has indeed reached such conclusion in
                                the sense indicated by the President although not much comment has
                                been made by the Dutch press.</p>
                            <p>My Government is confident that the above will furnish the President
                                with the further information he desires and that no more impediment
                                stands in the way of a favorable decision.</p>
                            <p>Please accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_DBWH1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. de Beaufort</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>