<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-01-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-01-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="795" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d795">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 600.119/488a</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Consul at Barcelona</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Hurst</hi></persName>)<note n="2" xml:id="d795fn2">The same, except last sentence, to consuls in other
                                ports served by the steamship lines mentioned in the telegram; see
                                last paragraph for instruction to repeat to the consuls at Valencia,
                                Malaga, and Cadiz.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-01-19">
                                    <hi rend="italic">January 19, 1918</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>War Trade Board states that in consideration of bunker and ship’s stores
                            licenses, which have been granted to various steamers of Compañía
                            Transatlántica and Pinillos Line, and as an aid to avoid possible future
                            delay, both lines have agreed to adopt all such safeguards as will
                            protect United States Government, and in particular have agreed to
                            following with respect to every vessel under their control: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>As to our searching vessels at any United States ports or
                                    possessions in any way we desire;</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Permit our sending two representatives on voyages whenever
                                    desired, giving them first-class fare and accommodation
                                    equivalent to that furnished masters and officers, the masters
                                    keeping such representatives thoroughly informed always
                                    regarding all matters respecting destination, intended loading
                                    and discharging of all cargo, bunker fuel, ship’s stores,
                                    vessel’s equipment or supplies of any kind;</item>
                                <pb facs="0897" n="1731" xml:id="pg_1731"/>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>To carry no cargo excepting as approved by Bureau of Exports,
                                    War Trade Board, who will send you separate instructions;</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>Masters upon arrival each port, whether United States or
                                    foreign, will deliver to you complete manifest all cargo
                                    intending to load or discharge your port, copies of all
                                    agreements with this Government, and won’t load or discharge any
                                    cargo, bunker fuel, ship’s stores, vessel’s equipment or
                                    supplies of any kind, until authorized by you, and will allow
                                    you to take any reasonable steps to satisfy yourself all
                                    agreements with this Government are fulfilled, and will allow
                                    you to supervise all such loading and discharging.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Further instructions will follow.</p>
                        <p>Repeat to Valencia, Malaga, Cadiz.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_PFL1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Polk</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>