<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-08-13T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-08-13T11:00:00-05:00" n="870" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d870">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72111N83/53</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Chargé in Norway</hi> (<persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_SHFA1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Schoenfeld</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-08-13T12:00:00-04:00">
                                    <hi rend="italic">August 13, 1918, noon</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>423. Your 964, August 8, 9 p.m. Department desires you to avoid taking
                            joint action with the British Minister. You are, however, instructed
                            immediately to present the following note independently to the Minister
                            for Foreign Affairs: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Your Excellency:—The Norwegian regulations for submarines in
                                    Norwegian territorial waters as promulgated by Royal decree
                                    (here insert date) prohibit belligerent submarines from making
                                    use of Norwegian territorial waters on any conditions except on
                                    account of damage, or by reason of stress of weather, or in
                                    order to save human life, and when in Norwegian waters the
                                    vessel must remain on the surface and must have her national
                                    flag hoisted and also the international signal to explain her
                                    presence and that the vessel must quit territorial waters as
                                    soon as the cause justifying her entrance no longer remains.
                                    These regulations have faithfully been complied with by the
                                    American Navy while numerous reports have been received,
                                    amounting to incontrovertible evidence, of the passage through
                                    Norwegian territorial waters of German submarines. The result in
                                    fact amounts to an unfavorable discrimination against the United
                                    States in that the Norwegian Government has not enforced
                                    impartial compliance with this Norwegian decree of neutrality
                                    which this Government has scrupulously respected. The
                                    consequence has been the establishment of a privileged channel
                                    for the submarines of an enemy of this country as a route to and
                                    from his areas of operations, resulting in facilitating the
                                    destruction of American ships and lives.</p>
                                <p>It is not apparent how the Norwegian Government can, with the
                                    best of intentions, by any measures so far adopted, prevent the
                                    use of these territorial waters by sub-surface vessels, the
                                    nominal steps taken having unquestionably failed in their
                                    purpose.</p>
                                <p>I am therefore directed by my Government to recommend to Your
                                    Excellency, very earnestly and urgently, that the Norwegian
                                    Government forthwith proceed with such new and effective
                                    measures as will prevent effectually the passage of German
                                    submarines through Norwegian territorial waters, by which
                                    Norwegian neutrality is violated. My Government feels that in
                                    the light of past occurrences and present experience, the grave
                                    importance will commend itself to Your Excellency of finding an
                                    immediate solution of a problem at once vital to Norway, in
                                    upholding her scrupulous neutrality, and to the United States,
                                    in maintaining her full rights of belligerency.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>After having read and presented the foregoing note textually to the
                            Minister of Foreign Affairs you may, in your discretion, informally and
                            orally discuss with him the measures proposed by the British Minister,
                            as contained in your 964, and you are authorized <pb facs="0939" n="1773" xml:id="pg_1773"/> to point out to him informally and
                            orally that those proposed measures appear to be the most effective and
                            practical method by which Norway can uphold her neutrality in the
                            direction indicated.</p>
                        <p>For your own information: The Norwegian regulations for submarines in
                            Norwegian territorial waters provide that submarines equipped for use in
                            warfare, and belonging to a belligerent power, must not traverse or stay
                            in Norwegian territorial waters; that breach of this prohibition will
                            expose them to armed attack without previous warning; that this
                            prohibition does not prevent a submarine from entering Norwegian
                            territorial waters on account of damage, or by reason of stress of
                            weather, or in order to save human life; that when in Norwegian waters
                            the vessel must remain on the surface and must have her national flag
                            hoisted and also the international signal to explain her presence and
                            that the vessel must quit territorial waters as soon as the cause
                            justifying her entrance no longer remains. Furthermore submarines
                            equipped for use in warfare, and belonging to a foreign non-belligerent
                            power, are also forbidden to enter or traverse Norwegian territorial
                            waters unless such entrance or passage takes place by daylight in clear
                            weather and on the surface and with the national flag of the vessel
                            hoisted.</p>
                        <p>These regulations would appear to be quite satisfactory but it has been
                            apparent from the beginning that the difficulty lies in their
                            enforcement. Mere nominal steps have been and are ineffective and have
                            resulted, as stated above, in the establishment of a privileged channel
                            for the enemy.</p>
                        <p>Report fully by cable the attitude of the Minister towards your
                            representations.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_LR1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lansing</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>