<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-09-28T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-09-28T15:00:00-05:00" n="882" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d882">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72111N83/85</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Norway</hi> (<persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_SHFA1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Schoenfeld</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Christiania</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-09-28T21:00:00+01:00">
                                    <hi rend="italic">September 28, 1918, 9 p.m.</hi>
                                </date>
                                <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received September 29, 3.45
                                p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1185. My telegram No. 1184 today.<note n="1" xml:id="d882fn1">Not
                                printed.</note> Following is the translated text of Norwegian
                            Government’s instructions to its Legations at Washington, London, Paris,
                            and Berlin to announce this Government’s decision to mine Norwegian
                            territorial waters in order to prevent their violation by belligerent
                            submarines: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>I request the Legation to make a verbal announcement to the
                                    Foreign Office concerned, while referring to your two previous
                                    representations (see my telegrams of August 19 and 28) to the
                                    following effect: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>The Norwegian Government has noted the answer which, in
                                            reply to its former representations, it has received
                                            from the British Government to the effect that it had
                                            been established that a British submarine had violated
                                            the Norwegian resolution of January 30, 1917, in respect
                                            of which violation, the Norwegian Government has lodged
                                            the most definite protest. In regard to the other
                                            instances complained of, assurances have been received
                                            from the American, British, and French Governments that
                                            no submarines belonging to these countries have violated
                                            the above-mentioned resolution. The Norwegian Government
                                            is still without a reply from the German Government to
                                            its former representations. The Norwegian Government has
                                            previously given warning that it will be obliged to take
                                            special military measures in <pb facs="0954" n="1788" xml:id="pg_1788"/> the areas affected in order to
                                            maintain its rights. Up to the present, the Norwegian
                                            Government has delayed taking such special measures
                                            except that it has caused to be extinguished certain
                                            lights on the west coast of Norway which was done
                                            amongst other reasons owing to the violation of the
                                            resolution. The Government as a matter of fact before
                                            taking steps towards a more effective measure, desired
                                            to give all the belligerents concerned opportunities to
                                            furnish it with the fullest possible information as it
                                            could not of course in advance be considered precluded
                                            that there might in individual cases at least to a
                                            certain extent be extenuating circumstances. With the
                                            passing of time, however, the Norwegian Government’s
                                            anxiety has increased as it has not been able to close
                                            its eyes to the risk that the numerous cases which have
                                            already been observed with certainty might at any time
                                            be succeeded by others. The Norwegian Government,
                                            therefore, finds that it must now proceed to lay mines
                                            in certain areas. In so doing, the Norwegian Government
                                            will take care that peaceful commercial navigation will
                                            not be stopped in traffic along the Norwegian coast.</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </p>
                                <p>The present circular telegram sent to Legations Berlin, London,
                                    Paris, Washington.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>London advised.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_SHFA1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Schoenfeld</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>