<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-10-22T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-10-22T13:00:00-05:00" n="99" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d99">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 600.119/1602b</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Chargé in Great Britain</hi> (<persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_LIB1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Laughlin</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-10-22T14:00:00-04:00">
                                        <hi rend="italic">October 22, 1918, 2 p.m.</hi>
                                    </date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>2340. For <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_SLP1">Sheldon</persName> [from War Trade Board]:</p>
                            <p>No. 1438. Referring to Department’s 1648, September 27, 3 p.m., our
                                1282; Department’s 1727, October 1, 7 p.m., our 1328; <pb facs="0172" n="1006" xml:id="pg_1006"/> Department’s 1790,
                                October 3, 7 p.m., our 1338.<note n="1" xml:id="d99fn1">The last not
                                    printed.</note> War Trade Board has been allowing sailers under
                                German safe-conduct to proceed to Cette with cargoes for Swiss,
                                under condition that if cargoes included petroleum, petroleum
                                by-products and foodstuffs, these commodities must be stored beneath
                                other cargoes so as not to be easily reached. Board has now agreed,
                                Navy consenting, on account of peculiarly difficult position of
                                Swiss in regard to shipping, to remove previous cargo restrictions
                                concerning storing of petroleum, byproducts of petroleum, and
                                foodstuffs on safe-conduct sailing boats in Swiss service. The
                                prohibition concerning copper and similar metals still obtains.
                                Awaiting your report on the cables set forth above, the Navy
                                concurring, we are not permitting shipments of petroleum,
                                by-products of petroleum, and foodstuffs aboard Swedish sailers. The
                                prohibition against copper and similar cargoes aboard Swedish
                                sailers still obtains. Danske Petroleum Co. wishes to use sailing
                                tank bark <hi rend="italic">Astrid</hi> to carry oil from United
                                States to Denmark. Please also refer to our 1282, also our
                                    1328,<note n="2" xml:id="d99fn2">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_997">pp.
                                    997</ref>, <ref target="#pg_1000">1000</ref>.</note> also our
                                1338, concerning schooner <persName>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Charles de Rouvres</hi></persName>, asking you
                                to confer with <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_SAWS1">Sims</persName>, consult Transport Council, and cable
                                recommendation. Pending your reply, must also withhold licenses from
                                four French auxiliary sailers on Pacific coast with coal to Rio,
                                thence to France Prompt decision on general policy necessary in view
                                approaching completion of some forty French schooners on Pacific
                                coast. Urgently request you consult Transport Council at once and
                                also have <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_SAWS1">Sims</persName> consult Admiralty and other authorities
                                involved, in order we may have full opinion on whole question of
                                permitting sailing vessels under German safe-conduct and bound for
                                northern neutrals to carry cargoes of mineral oil and foodstuffs as
                                well as on case of French motor schooners. Delay causes hardship.
                                Prompt reply would also strengthen our position in upholding
                                practice of consulting Transport Council whenever possible.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="frus1918Supp01v01#p_LR1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lansing</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>