<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 133.Mr. Bancroft to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1872p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d133</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">133</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1871-11-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1871-11-20T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692" lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="population-demographics" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969" lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1871-11-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1871-11-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="133" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d133">
                <head>No. 133.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bancroft</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American
                                        Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-11-20">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 20,
                                    1871</date>. (Received December 8.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 298.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The session of the German Parliament will
                            be closed on Saturday next. One of its measures was to lay aside forty
                            millions of thalers in specie as a fund not to be used for any purpose
                            but preparations for a campaign on the outbreak of a war. Such a reserve
                            brings with it a <pb facs="0281" n="185" xml:id="pg_185"/> loss of two
                            millions a year, but the measure was adopted by a great majority.</p>
                <p>On the reform of the coinage there was a great diversity of opinion. The
                            result has been the adoption of the measure proposed by the government,
                            though not without some variation. The act contemplates a transition
                            period to be followed by a definitive act establishing one uniform
                            currency for the German Empire. The thaler and the groschen are
                            abolished; the unit of currency is fixed at the mark, ⅓ of the thaler,
                            about 24 cents. The mark is divided into 100 parts, as the franc in
                            France. During the interim gold and silver are alike legal tender, the
                            relation of gold to silver being, as in France, 15½ to 1. All gold
                            coinage now in circulation and under weight will be withdrawn, and the
                            old silver coinage is likewise gradually to disappear. The right to coin
                            is not reserved exclusively to the Emperor.</p>
                <p>The reason assigned by the German government is that one single mint
                            could not issue the new coin fast enough to meet the public wants, and
                            therefore every state which has a mint must take part in coining the new
                            pieces.</p>
                <p>A very large minority were in favor of an international coinage, but an
                            amendment tending to that result was voted down.</p>
                <p>The measure therefore does no more than regulate and unify the coinage of
                            the German Empire.</p>
                <p>On the part of Bavaria a measure has been proposed taking from the pulpit
                            any immunity it may have had as a disseminator of sedition or treason,
                            rendering preachers amenable to law.</p>
                <p>The Catholics in this kingdom, constituting about one-third of the
                            population, have always been treated by the Prussian government with
                            forbearance and even with favor, and by the conservative party were
                            esteemed and almost cherished as allies. But the new dogma has led to
                            complications that have disturbed the former state of tranquillity.</p>
                <p>In a public School the Catholics attempted the dismissal of a Catholic
                            teacher who declined to accept the dogma of infallibility, and the
                            government refused to remove him for that cause.</p>
                <p>The Catholic bishops, most of whom before going to the late council were
                            opposed to the new dogma, proceeded to address the King directly, and
                            claim his interposition to save them from what they called an
                            interference with the liberty of conscience. The King was most reluctant
                            to be brought into controversy with the Roman Catholic prelates. But
                            being forced to reply, he took his ground with decision. Fully asserting
                            the principle of religious liberty, he reminded the bishops that they
                            did not even pretend that any law had been infringed, reproved them for
                            exciting discontent in the Catholics in Prussia, and offered them no way
                            to a change except through the established constitutional channels.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GEO. BANCROFT.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
