<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 181.Sir Edward Thornton to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1872p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d181</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">181</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1872-07-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1872-07-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048668"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fishery</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1872-07-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1872-07-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="181"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d181">
                <head>No. 181.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Sir <persName type="from">Edward Thornton</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-07-10">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 10, 1872</date>. (Received July
                        11.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In compliance with an instruction which I have
                    received from <pb facs="0317" n="221" xml:id="pg_221"/> Earl Granville, I have
                    the honor to state that the Government of the United States having declined to
                    take steps with a view to the refunding of duties collected on fish-oil and fish
                    imported into the United States from Prince Edward’s Island, his lordship has
                    been informed by the colonial office that a telegram has been received from the
                    governor of Prince Edward’s Island, stating that his ministers are of opinion
                    that the privilege of fishing on the coast of Prince Edward’s Island should not
                    be conceded to the American fishermen until the United States Government shall
                    have carried into effect the arrangement in pursuance of which the American
                    fishermen were provisionally admitted to the use of those fisheries during the
                    season of 1871, namely, the refund of the duties levied during that season upon
                    fish and fish-oil imported from the colony into the United States.</p>
                <p>Her Majesty’s government cannot contest the justice of the position thus assumed
                    by the governor of Prince Edward’s Island, and as that colony does not possess
                    revenue-vessels by which its fishery laws can be enforced, they have thought it
                    right to send instructions to the officers commanding Her Majesty’s ships as
                    regards the protection of the Prince Edward Island fisheries, similar to those
                    issued for the protection of the North American fisheries generally, by Admiral
                    Wellesley, in 1870, as modified by the memorandum issued by him on the 25th of
                    June of that year.</p>
                <p>Such is the course which I am instructed to inform the Government of the United
                    States Her Majesty’s government have been forced to adopt, in consequence of the
                    non-fulfillment of the condition on which the provisional use of the fisheries
                    was conceded by the governor of Prince Edward’s Island.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>EDW’D THORNTON.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
