<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 270.Mr. Nelson to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1872p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d270</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">270</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1871-11-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1871-11-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1871-11-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1871-11-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="270"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d270">
                <head>No. 270.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Nelson</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-11-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 28, 1871</date>. (Received December
                        26.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 476.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I herewith transmit a translation of a
                    proclamation of General Porfirio Diaz, dated at Huajnapam, November 19, (A.)
                    Also of a proclamation signed by the insurgent General Negrete, dated at
                    Alta-maja, November 20, (B,) and two proclamations of the federal General
                    Alatorre, dated from his headquarters at Acatlan, November 23, (C and D.)</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>THOMAS H. NELSON.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure A.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">proclamation of general diaz.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Citizen-General Porfirio Diaz to the Republican
                            troops:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Companions in arms</hi>: When, filled with the noble
                        pride of patriotism, we divided together the adversities and glories of the
                        colossal task to turn out from our soil the audacious French and Austrian
                        armies, in order to guarantee definitely the independence and liberty of our
                        adored soil, we never suspected that we should soon have to see our brothers
                        face to face as enemies. But a disloyal government, despotic and parricidal,
                        and to which the country did not owe the triumph of its holy cause, has
                        cunningly deposited in your noble hearts the germs of division, in order to
                        make the great and generous liberal party the laughing-stock of the nations
                        that observe us, in order to perpetuate in power those who disregard the law
                        and the universal voice of the nation. Shall this venomous plant germinate
                        in your pure hearts, palpitating with glory, and even now agitated by the
                        vivifying sun of the 5th of May? Answer your sincere friend, your brother.
                        Why are you going to tight against my men? Why say we are traitors? Do we by
                        chance invoke monarchy? Do we call to a foreign prince to govern the country
                        of Montezuma? Do we beg for the humiliating protectorate of the United
                        States, like Juarez and his clique of degraded Cubans and cowardly
                        parasites? O, never! Like you, we carried five years since the tri-color
                        standard in one hand and our constitution of 1857 in the other. With the
                        first we wished to affirm our nationality, removing it from the bastard
                        influences of every foreign <pb facs="0452" n="356" xml:id="pg_356"/>
                        country. Do you hear it? We wished to be free Mexicans, not pupils. With the
                        second we wished to consolidate our means of being liberal, free, and
                        progressive, indeed, and not by means of vain promises, which are being
                        converted into positive military dictatorship. What are you going to
                        sustain? For what are you going to shed your blood and that, of your
                        brothers? Why perpetuate the power of Juarez, who has dreamed of being a
                        prince; who invites us to cowardice by his stupid despotism, or by the
                        Yankee whip, with which he will scourge our people, as was done in 1847;
                        thanks to the division, which, then as now, was the normal state of our
                        unhappy soil. And do you accept this offering; you, the invincible sons of
                        Hidalgo and Iturbide? Do we accept it; we, the brothers of Zaragoza and
                        Salazar? O, do not believe it! It is a lie! Mexico will never give use to
                        such a stupid scandal, without outraging its good liberal sons. Comrades:
                        There are but two roads; either that of the infamy sustained by Juarez, or
                        that of glory, binding us, as before, to save our country; in such a
                        dilemma, we prefer yielding with glory than to live covered with ignominy.
                        Choose, my friends; here is my hand, as ever, and conquering or conquered,
                        you shall never despise your brother.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>PORFIRIO DIAZ.</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Huajuapam</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-11-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 19, 1871</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>Proclamation of General Negrete.</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Miguel Negrete, general of division, to his
                            fellow-citizens:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>An humble child of the people, I undertook the military career with the sole
                        aim of being one day useful to my adored country and to its
                        institutions.</p>
                    <p>I am democratic by birth and principles, and for this reason I cannot be
                        indifferent to the evils that Mexico suffers; for this cause, you have seen
                        that, whenever the institutions or the independence have been in danger, I
                        have lent my aid in order to save them, after having been present at the
                        humiliation, which, in the illustrious Zaragoza, the first soldiers of the
                        world suffered, and in which I took a part at the side of the men whom I now
                        command, because it was the emanation of the people in order to save their
                        independence; but in Chihuahua I noted that these men sold their fatherland,
                        and their treason being proved upon them, I separated from them; a little
                        afterward I seized the banner which the illustrious Porfirio Diaz has to-day
                        raised aloft, and which I am sure he will soon place over the palace of the
                        Montezumas. Since that period until now I have been constant in my
                        undertaking, even if unfortunate, for the political movements that I have
                        indicated have had a bad issue, being that of the citadel in which my
                        enemies, who are also the energies of democratic institutions, have tried to
                        wound me with calumny. The time will come in which the nation will have a
                        detailed knowledge of what happened, and then justice may know who were the
                        authors of this unhappy event, and the people may distinguish them by the
                        mark of infamy.</p>
                    <p>Before General Diaz shall have taken up arms in order to vindicate the rights
                        of the people of whom it is the emanation, the nation will have already
                        manifested the desire that the tyrants should retire, leaving the free
                        passage to the sons of the people; the central club that I had the honor to
                        found and preside over, and also others that existed in all the republic
                        seconding their views, is the undeniable proof of this truth; and this being
                        so, the true soldier of the people, following his inspirations, ought to
                        say, Long live General Diaz! long live the constitution of ’57! death to the
                        tyrants!</p>
                    <p>The movement initiated by the worthy General Diaz, and which I second in all
                        its parts, is the salvation of the country; is the struggle of the free
                        against the feudalists; is the extinction of the scandalous robberies of the
                        satellites of power, and is the triumph of order and morality; peace will
                        restore tranquillity to families; the workman will dedicate himself to his
                        workshop, in order to attend to the education of his children; the women
                        will wipe their tears; the horrible hectacombs which are now in Atexalto,
                        Ovejo, Tampico, the citadel, and other points, will have disappeared
                        forever; for from this day forward the constitution of ’57 will not be a
                        beautiful illusion, because we have sworn to sustain it at the cost of our
                        blood, and do so, that its bountiful sap may vivify all the children of the
                        great Mexican family.</p>
                    <p>Group yourslves, then, fellow-citizens, under this banner, and when it waves
                        majestically over the national palace, you will see the titles that the
                        tyrants have founded disappear as if by magic; among such titles being the
                        various monopolies that the political sons of the usurper of the rights of
                        the people now possess.</p>
                    <p>And you, companions in arms, who from this moment commence to suffer the
                        penalties of the campaign, ought to be proud because you work for the
                        regeneration of the people, which labor will soon be concluded, for the
                        victory will be ours, owing to your valor, because you are Mexicans, and
                        defend the most holy cause of free nations. <pb facs="0453" n="357"
                            xml:id="pg_357"/> Fight, then, with faith, and victory will crown our
                        efforts, and all the free nations of the world will send us their blessings,
                        because the cause which you defend is the cause of humanity.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>MIGUEL NEGRETE.</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hacienda of Atlamaja</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-11-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 20, 1871</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>Proclamation of General Altatorre.</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">The general of division, Ignacio B. Alatorre, to his
                            subordinates:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Companions</hi>: General Porfirio Diaz has thrown down
                        the glove, trampling under foot the titles with which you have honored him,
                        despising the distinctions which the nation awarded him for the loyal and
                        patriotic conduct that was supposed of him. He has raised the standard of
                        rebellion, to drive us anew into parricidal struggles. What cause, what
                        principles does he invoke? What great interest leads him to this criminal
                        act? The nation and yourselves know very well! <hi rend="italic">General
                            Diaz rebels because he has not been elected president of the
                            republic</hi>, and pretends to seize by violence that which the popular
                        vote of his fellow-citizens has denied to him. This, companions, is the sad
                        reality, notwithstanding that insidious proclamations and false acts invent
                        distinct causes; men of heart will not see anything in them but stupid
                        pretexts.</p>
                    <p>Behold, then, the Mexican Cincinnati parodying the celebrated Santa Anna.</p>
                    <p>Comrades! the troops and the nation, anxious for the indispensable peace, in
                        order to arrive at the progress that the supreme government aims at, are
                        duelling in a terrible contest. Let us accept it, then, for it is our duty,
                        and because far above us weighs the sacred obligation to sustain, at the
                        cost of our blood, the rights of the people, the law, and the national
                        government.</p>
                    <p>Let us march tranquilly to the battle-field; we shall not be responsible for
                        the desolation of our soil; we shall not have to reproach ourselves with the
                        tears that will flow, with the blood shed, nor with the national ruin; these
                        horrors will fall back upon those who promote the tumult and mutiny, and who
                        have caused so many evils to the republic.</p>
                    <p>My friends, you will soon go and fight. I have nothing to recommend to you,
                        because I know that discipline, valor, and honor are gifts which shine in
                        you. I know that you fulfill your duties, performing your noble mission as
                        warriors without hate or rancor. The fatherland already considers you as its
                        best sons, and you know how to answer to it with dignity.</p>
                    <p>Forward, comrades! remember that the nation is leaning on you, and that its
                        tranquillity and progress, yet once again, depends upon your valor and
                        intrepidity.</p>
                    <p>Forward! in whatsoever situation you may find yourselves, there will be
                        always at your side your friend and companion.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>I. R. ALATORRE.</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters, <placeName>Acatlan</placeName>
                            </hi>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-11-23">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 23, 1871</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>Proclamation of General Altatorre.</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">The general-in-chief of the division of operations over
                            the insurgents, to the Oaxacan people:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Fellow-Citizens</hi>: When the national government sent
                        me to the State, in order to re-establish peace, disturbed by the lamentable
                        errors of some of its children, it was not only guided by the fulfillment of
                        the first of its most precious duties as the supreme authority, but also by
                        the desire of emancipating you from the tyranny exercised by a government
                        without titles to hold it—titles which it broke by separating itself from
                        the federation, and abusing the power which the people and the constitution
                        confided to it in order to promote its happiness and welfare.</p>
                    <p>I am very sensible of entering, with the sound of war, into one of the most
                        heroic States of the republic; but the evils existing in it are alone owing
                        to the rebels, against whom my action will be direct and energetic—not
                        against the peaceful people, riot against the honorable citizens, toward
                        whom I bind myself in the most vehement sympathies and the most sincere
                        affection.</p>
                    <p>My stay in this magnificent State will be merely transitory; but there shall
                        be established in it peace and public confidence: there shall be reorganized
                        in it a just and constitutional government; and there shall be enjoyed in it
                        all kinds of guarantees.</p>
                    <pb facs="0454" n="358" xml:id="pg_358"/>
                    <p>One of the inconveniences which has impeded, during the last few years, the
                        progress of the State, has been its bad fiscal system, that, exacting from
                        commerce and landed property the most exorbitant contributions, has
                        obstructed the roads of labor, industry, agriculture, and the arts, which
                        to-day are buried in sad decadence. My efforts shall be dedicated to the
                        liberty of commerce, as also to break the dikes which retain the fountains
                        of public riches, in as far as it lies in my power.</p>
                    <p>Fellow-citizens, in order that with the honorable men my mission may be one
                        of peace, and purely a reorganizing one, for that I need your aid, which I
                        hope you will not deny to me; for that end you are invited by your
                        fellow-citizen and friend,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>I. R. ALATORRE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters, Acatlan</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >November</hi> 23.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
