<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1871-12-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1871-12-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="277" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d277">
                        <head>No. 277.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Nelson</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                        the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-12-18"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 18,
                                    1871</date>. (Received January 11.)</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 487.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On the 15th instant the first session of
                            the sixth constitutional congress adjourned until the next regular
                            session, in April, 1872.</p>
                        <p>President Juarez delivered, in person, an address, a copy and translation
                            of which I inclose, (A and 0.) I also inclose a copy and translation of
                            the response of the president of congress, (B and D.)</p>
                        <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>THOMAS H. NELSON.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosnre C.—Translation.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>Speech of the President of the Republic, Don Benito Juarez, at the
                                closing of the First Session of the Sixth Constitutional Congress,
                                December 15, 1871.</head>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Citizen Deputies</hi>: At closing the first
                                period of sessions, the sixth constitutional congress can
                                congratulate itself with the idea that, in the presence of the
                                actual crisis, it has effected all that could he anticipated from
                                its patriotic efforts. In the first place, by the election of the
                                President of the republic, it has given a legal termination to the
                                political contention which was agitating the country, and which thus
                                no one has been able to renew without rebelling against our
                                institutions.</p>
                            <p>In continuation, you have discussed and approved the suspension of
                                guarantees, initiated by the executive, in view of the extraordinary
                                and difficult events, giving them, moreover, ample authority in the
                                war and finance departments. Grateful: for this confidence, and in
                                the fulfillment of my duties as constitutional ruler, I protest to
                                you that I shall make use of the faculties you have invested me with
                                solely in that which, may be strictly indispensable, and for the
                                time necessary to re-establish the dominion of the law, laying them
                                on one side, or not exercising any of them, as I have-done on former
                                occasions, even while the authorization for their use was still in
                                force.</p>
                            <p>Lastly, you have decreed the penal code, and have authorized the
                                executive to carry into effect, provisionally, the law of
                                proceedings in civil and criminal matters for this district and
                                Lower California. With these measures a great benefit has been
                                obtained toward moral order; the immediate adoption of a clear and
                                methodical legislation, suited entirely to the necessities of the
                                times, in place of any other more or less vague and complicated, or
                                opposed to the principles of modern civilization. It is to be hoped
                                that these new legislative decrees will be imitated or adopted
                                entirely by the other States of the federation, as has already
                                occurred with the civil code; and then the amelioration to which you
                                have so prudently given your sanction will become of general
                                interest for the republic. Even were it for this legislative act
                                alone, the good name of the sixth constitutional congress would be
                                now preserved in our parliamentary annals.</p>
                            <p>While you are temporarily resting from your labors, the executive
                                will direct all its efforts to extinguish the flame of the rebellion
                                which threatens to destroy legal order, and therewith all the hopes
                                of our population. The faculties you have been pleased to confer
                                upon me would not suffice for the re-establishment of peace, if I
                                did not count, as I fortunately do, on the co-operation of the
                                people in general, who, day by <pb facs="0468" n="372" xml:id="pg_372"/> day, comprehend their interests better and
                                better—interests identified with our institutions, and threatened
                                with death by the civil war. To put a prompt and radical end to the
                                latter is all that can be desired for the present; and to attain
                                this, I trust to be assisted by your counsels, as well as by those
                                of every Mexican who loves the honor, independence, and happiness of
                                his country.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure D.—Translation.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>Reply of the President of the Congress–Session of the 15th
                                December, 1871.</head>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Citizen President</hi>: On the closing of the
                                first period of its sessions, the sixth constitutional congress has
                                the satisfaction of having fulfilled important duties in resolving
                                the serious political questions presented at commencing its labors,
                                as an inheritance from the late electoral term. The revision of
                                powers required the lengthened and conscientious attention of the
                                citizen deputies; and they had also to occupy themselves with no
                                less solicitude in the presidential election, to the result of which
                                all Mexicans were looking forward, as to whether it were to be the
                                continuation of the legal regimen or the beginning of anarchy. The
                                solution of so important a question, although confirming the
                                constitutional tradition, was made a motive for the dissatisfied to
                                raise the banner of rebellion. Congress, always watchful to dictate
                                the requisite measures for re-establishing peace, one of the
                                greatest blessing of the people, occupied itself in a detailed and
                                rational discussion regarding the granting ample faculties to the
                                executive in the war and finance departments, and the approbation of
                                a suspension of guarantees, and thereby give additional strength to
                                the authorities charged by our fundamental charter with the
                                preservation of tranquillity and providing for the welfare of the
                                republic.</p>
                            <p>Matters so serious require to be fully discussed, and have
                                consequently occupied nearly the whole of the period ending to-day.
                                Notwithstanding, congress has found time, not only to attend to
                                certain ameliorations in the states and other affairs of private
                                interest, but has also been enabled to decree a code of penal laws,
                                which has been compiled by a board of distinguished counselors named
                                by the executive, to take effect in the district and territory of
                                Lower California, as respects ordinary crimes, and in the whole of
                                the republic as regards offenses against the federation.</p>
                            <p>No one can be ignorant of the great benefit conferred upon the
                                country by this decree, as no one is unacquainted with the important
                                service rendered by the promulgation of the civil code, which has
                                now become a general law, a great number of the States having
                                adopted it. The penal code is a matter of greater interest still,
                                because, although the civil laws which formally governed us were
                                antiquated, it is also certain that, since the Roman laws, but
                                little progress has been made in civil jurisprudence; but this has
                                not occurred respecting penal laws, which have always received the
                                beneficent influence of social improvement; it was, therefore, an
                                incomprehensible absurdity that in the nineteenth century we should
                                be ruled by the criminal laws issued in the Middle Ages, and
                                dictated under the influence of the fanaticism, and the difference
                                of the classes ruling at that time, which was a species of chaos, in
                                which the gestation of modern civilization was being prepared; laws
                                of which were, therefore, inapplicable in general, and which made
                                room for arbitrariness of the judges, at all times dangerous; laws
                                which have been reformed by the progressive institution of trial by
                                jury, the adoption of which, inspired by the ideas of the time, has
                                been developed according to the conceptions of the King Alfonso the
                                Wise, at the commencement of the eighteenth century.</p>
                            <p>These slight considerations will suffice to show that the sixth
                                constitutional congress has inaugurated its labors in a worthy and
                                beneficial manner, and with a constant view to advancement.</p>
                            <p>But, moreover, experience having demonstrated the serious
                                difficulties arising from the want of proceedings analogous to the
                                ideas of the codes of law, this congress, anxious to complete its
                                work, has authorized the executive to carry out the respective laws
                                now under preparation. Therewith, Citizen President, we shall have
                                been enabled to improve considerably the administration of justice;
                                one of the affairs of most importance, as closely affecting the
                                persons and property of the inhabitants of the republic.</p>
                            <p>The nation is persuaded that its representatives, animated with these
                                intentions, will continue their exertions in its behalf in the
                                coming sessions. Congress expects to dedicate itself in April next
                                to so desirous a task, without having to pre-occupy itself with
                                political disturbances, as it doubts not that the executive, armed
                                with sufficient powers, will, ere then, have re-established peace,
                                and will be able to deliver over to the chamber the powers conceded
                                to it, and return to the inhabitants the guarantees it has been
                                requisite to suspend.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>