<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 307.Mr. Fish to Mr. Nelson,,</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1872p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d307</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">307</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1872-04-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1872-04-13T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558" lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079" lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421" lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236" lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218" lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1872-04-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1872-04-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="307" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d307">
                <head>No. 307.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Fish</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Nelson</persName>
                    </hi>,</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                        of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-04-13">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 13,
                                1872</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 237.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Attorney General has addressed a
                            letter to this Department under date of the 5th instant, covering a
                            “report” of the grand jury of the United States district court of Texas,
                            relative to the depredations perpetrated upon citizens of that State by
                            persons coming from the Mexican side of the Rio Grande. Copies of these
                            papers are inclosed herewith. You are requested to lay them before the
                            minister for foreign affairs, to remonstrate earnestly against the
                            outrages therein alleged, and to demand redress for them.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>HAMILTON FISH.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williams</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Justice</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-04-05">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 5,
                                        1872</date>. (Received April 6.)</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit, for your
                                consideration, the report of the grand jury of the United States
                                district court for the eastern district of Texas, relative to the
                                invasions of that State, and depredations committed upon the people
                                by persons from the Mexican side of the Rio Grande.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>GEO. H. WILLIAMS.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Report of the grand jury, impaneled at the March
                                    term, A. D</hi>. 1872, <hi rend="italic">of the United States
                                    district court held in Brownsville, within the eastern district
                                    of Texas, and submitted to the court on their
                                discharge.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Brownsville, Texas</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-03-25">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 25, 1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">federal grand jury report.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">The United States of America, eastern district of
                                Texas.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">To the Hon. Amos Morrill, judge of the district
                                    court of the United States for the eastern district of
                                    Texas.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The grand jurors of the United States, in their final presentment to
                                your honorable court, at the close of their session, respectfully
                                present:</p>
                    <p>That since they were impaneled on the 7th instant, they have found
                                fifty-seven true bills of indictment, being mostly for violations of
                                the revenue laws.</p>
                    <p>That they have collected a considerable mass of testimony, to which
                                they will again respectfully call the attention of the honorable
                                court. That the exigencies of the public service demand the erection
                                in the city of Brownsville of a building large enough to serve for a
                                custom-house, a federal court-room, and a post-office. It is
                                respectfully suggested that the construction of such a building
                                would be a measure of economy on the part of the United States, and
                                would save the paying out of large sums for the rent of houses not
                                in every respect calculated to meet the wants and afford the proper
                                conveniences to the officers and employés occupying them, while in
                                the service of the Government. An appropriation for the purpose is
                                respectfully suggested.</p>
                    <p>In approaching the matter of the depredatory war which has been waged
                                against the defenseless citizens of the United States, and residents
                                of the valleys of the Rio Grande, the Nueces, the Rio Frio, and
                                their tributaries, there is hesitancy, because the short limits of a
                                presentment will not give an adequate idea of the extent of the
                                hostile operations, the number of valuable lives lost, and the
                                aggravated character and <pb facs="0511" n="415" xml:id="pg_415"/>
                                the enormity of the excesses which organized hands of men, fitted
                                out in Mexico, have perpetrated upon the people of Western
                                Texas.</p>
                    <p>The honorable court is respectfully referred to the accompanying
                                evidence, but at the same time we would request that the same be not
                                filed and made a part of the records of the court, and be not
                                published, but deposited with the district attorney. The motives
                                inducing this request will appear by a perusal of the evidence.</p>
                    <p>A reign of terror is proven to exist between the Rio Grande and the
                                Nueces. Mercenary bands of marauders, Mexican officers and soldiers,
                                and Mexican outlaws and bandits, have been, for about seven years,
                                holding a saturnalia of crime, violence, and rapine upon the soil of
                                Texas. They have denounced the penalty of death against any who may
                                become informers. They have already sacrificed life upon mere
                                suspicion, as in the case of young Cleveland, of San Antonio, and
                                others. Should our request be unheeded the lives of the witnesses
                                would be taken with certainty and without remorse.</p>
                    <p>The evidence submitted justifies the declaration that a depredatory
                                war has existed on this frontier since 1865; that it has been waged
                                by men organized in Mexico, by Mexican soldiers acting under the
                                orders of a Mexican general, and commanded directly by officers of
                                the Mexican army; that the authorities of Mexico, civil and
                                military, have countenanced, aided, and supported these hostile
                                operations; that the robbery of our citizens has been legalized so
                                far as the acts of Mexican officials could legalize murder, robbery,
                                and other criminal outrages; that the markets of Mexico have been
                                used openly, publicly, and shamelessly, to effect the sale of
                                property robbed from the people of Texas; that Mexican officials,
                                merchants of that and other nationalities, and all classes of
                                Mexicans, have bought and sold cattle, hides, horses, and other
                                property, stolen from the people of Texas, and they have done so
                                knowing they had been dishonestly obtained; the custom-house and
                                municipal authorities of Mexico have profited by the piratical acts
                                of Mexican soldiers and highwaymen, and a tax has been levied upon
                                cattle which they knew had been taken by armed bands from the
                                rightful owners; that the people on the Mexican side of the Rio
                                Grande consider and treat the Americans as enemies; they claim the
                                country between the Nueces and the Rio Grande, and express a
                                determination to drive the Americans from it.</p>
                    <p>Among the grievances of which this people justly complain, there is
                                none more galling than the sending of General Juan Nepomuceno
                                Cortina to this frontier. It may be truly said that he has written
                                the history of his career on this side of the Rio Grande in letters
                                of blood and fire. The criminal who stands charged upon the oaths of
                                twelve men, good and true, of murder, theft, and treason, who levied
                                war upon the United States, murdered its citizens and soldiers, and
                                robbed its mails, who laid waste one hundred and twenty miles of
                                frontier, and who now occupies the double position of ranking
                                officer of the Mexican army upon the line of the Bravo, and ranking
                                cow and horse thief on both frontiers, has been retained on duty
                                against the protest of General McCook, Which was communicated to
                                President Juarez. His retention is a deliberate, willful, and
                                studied insult to the Government of the United States, its officers
                                and people.</p>
                    <p>General Cortina has given his officers and soldiers orders to kill
                                and rob the people of Texas. He has received a large share of the
                                plunder. He has stocked four ranches mostly with cows and horses
                                stolen from Texas.</p>
                    <p>It is believed from the evidence and from other reliable authority
                                that since the close of the civil war in this country there has been
                                an average of five thousand cattle stolen from Texas monthly, and
                                driven into Mexico, and this estimate is confined to the lower Rip
                                Grande. The total number is estimated at four hundred and twenty
                                thousand, and the actual value at six million three hundred thousand
                                dollars. This does not include losses accruing from the depredations
                                of the Kickapoo Indians, naturalized citizens of Mexico. The loss of
                                life, the sense of insecurity, the decreased value of property, the
                                paralyzation of business, and the moral effects resulting from this
                                war cannot be estimated. Some of these defy the sordid valuation of
                                dollars and cents.</p>
                    <p>The grand jurors would respectfully call attention to the assaults
                                which have been made upon officers of the United States Government
                                while in the discharge of their duties, to the threats against them,
                                to their forcible detention, and to the obstructions preventing them
                                from performing their duty; and all these acts are shown to have
                                been done by raiders with the approval and protection of Mexican
                                authorities. It is known to the world that United States officers
                                have been killed on the Rio Grande by armed Mexicans, and that
                                employment in a public capacity, requiring the officer to visit
                                out-of-the-way places, is a position of peril. Inspector Dupout
                                killed in Brownsville, and the murder of Inspectors Hammond and
                                Phelps, and the wounding of others at Clarksville, are facts
                                officially recorded; and the fate of Inspector McLaughlin may be
                                attributed to the same hands.</p>
                    <p>The evidence of all witnesses, irrespective of nationality, is
                                conclusive as to the insecurity of life and property on this
                                frontier. There is no protection to the citizen in the enjoyment of
                                his rights and privileges. His life, his liberty, and whatever a
                                freeman holds dear are at the mercy of armed invaders. They invade
                                his home, insult <pb facs="0512" n="416" xml:id="pg_416"/> his
                                family, and violate the properties, the decencies, and even the
                                sanctities of private life with impunity. Our fellow-citizens of
                                Mexican origin and of other nationalities have suffered alike with
                                the native American, because the same flag covers them, and they
                                have incurred the hostility of a people who hate everything
                                American, and deem it legitimate to assault and plunder all over
                                which the American banner floats.</p>
                    <p>This deplorable state of affairs, this loss of life and property, and
                                the misfortunes which have, in a manner, crushed this frontier, have
                                resulted from the want of an adequate force of cavalry to cover and
                                protect the inhabitants of the Rio Grande Valley.</p>
                    <p>A mounted force, properly handled, which could follow marauders into
                                the fastnesses of the chaparrals, pursue with Parthian vigor and
                                perseverance over the broad prairies could give protection and roll
                                back upon Mexico the wave of invasion. That nation is laboring under
                                the incurable disease of chronic revolution. Its masses have become
                                demoralized by half a century of war and internal convulsions and
                                dissensions. The absence of United States troops on the line of the
                                lower Rio Grande in 1859 resulted in the Cortina war. The absence of
                                a cavalry force capable to protect this frontier has invited the
                                attacks of our hostile and aggressive neighbors, and the pillage of
                                a territory covering not less than sixty thousand square miles are
                                the fruits of the omission.</p>
                    <p>The inhabitants of this territory have suffered all the horrors of
                                warfare, and have known none of the securities of its usages, and
                                have appealed in vain for protection. They have published authentic
                                statements of the wrongs and the outrages committed upon them by
                                merciless invaders, and no sympathetic response has been returned.
                                They are reduced to the last extremity. The alternative is
                                presented, in the event governmental protection shall not be
                                extended, to abandon their homes to their enemies, or to defend
                                them. They feel that the great law of humanity allows them to resort
                                to measures of self-defense, to repel force by force, and to meet
                                their invaders and de-spoilers as freemen should, with ball and
                                blade. And your grand jurors, though generally not residents of the
                                section in question, acting under the solemn obligations of their
                                oaths, do present that, in their opinion, should these plundered,
                                harassed, and wronged people be impelled to strike for vengeance
                                upon the breasts of those who have filled the land with violence and
                                bloodshed, assassination, and a long catalogue of inhuman excesses,
                                they can appear before the bar of public opinion and plead such a
                                justification as no people in modern times have been able to produce
                                during a period of miscalled peace.</p>
                    <p>Your grand jurors have seen with pleasure the joint resolution
                                introduced into Congress by the Hon. John Hancock. They would
                                respectfully suggest that a commission for the purposes contemplated
                                would be very proper, but it would bring no relief to the suffering
                                frontier. An effective and efficient force of cavalry to chastise
                                and expel the armed bands, and to drive from our soil the Mexican
                                troops now using it for making descents upon Mexican territory, as
                                from the Lopeña ranch in Zapata County, and for plundering our
                                people, is imperiously demanded, and at once.</p>
                    <p>Our Representatives and Senators in Congress are requested to use
                                their influence in procuring the sending of this force to the Rio
                                Grande.</p>
                    <p>In conclusion, your grand jury would call attention to the good
                                understanding which has existed between themselves and the able
                                gentlemen presiding over the honorable-court, the district attorney,
                                and all the officers of the court.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>JOHN S. FORD,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreman, Cameron
                                                County, Texas.</hi>.</item>
                                <item>C. DART,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Galveston,
                                            Texas:</hi>
                                </item>
                                <item>J. J. HAWKINS,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Columbus,
                                                Colorado County, Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>J. M. CONRAD,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Galveston,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>R. B. HAWKINS,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Colorado County,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>M. M. JORDAN,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Galveston,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>JAS.W. FIELDS,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Colorado County,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>L. F. HARRIS,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Galveston,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>JAMES NORTON,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Galveston,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>SAMUEL PARR,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Galveston,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>T. W. PIERSON,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Victoria,
                                                Texas.</hi>
                                </item>
                                <item>OLYMPUS FERGUSON,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Colorado
                                                County, Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>GEORGE WILSON,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Nueces County,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>W. F. BROWN,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Brazoria County,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>W. H. POWELL,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Matagorda County,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>THOMAS McGOVERN,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Galveston,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>H. H. WILLIAMS,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Victoria County,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>D. C. ROBERTS,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Brazoria County,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>DANIEL BUCKLEY,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Galveston,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>R. K. SMITH,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Galveston,
                                                Texas</hi>.</item>
                                <item>JAMES F. MAGUIRE,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Galveston,
                                                Texas.</hi>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
