<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 415.Mr. Biddle to Mr. Fish</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1872p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d414</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">414</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1872-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1872-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1872-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1872-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="414"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d414">
                <head>No. 415.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Biddle</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">San Salvador</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-09-07">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 7, 1872</date>. (Received October
                        8.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 78.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: It is with great grief that I present to you the
                    accompanying correspondence, which reveals the assassination of the
                    vice-president of this republic, Señor Don Manuel Mendez, in the public street,
                    on the night of the 1st instant. No greater calamity could have befallen
                    Salvador. Señor Mendez was a virtuous man, honorable, energetic, and talented,
                    with the esteem of the whole community. He was in the prime of life, and at the
                    time of his death added to his trust as vice-president the charge of all the
                    departments of the government, save the ministry of foreign relations.</p>
                <p>President Gonzalez said to me to-day, “Great is the loss to Salvador, but
                    greatest of all to me, I counseled with him in all things, I confided in him as
                    a brother; his clear head unraveled every difficulty; he was truth and fidelity
                    itself; lean never replace him.” And these words convey the appreciation I had
                    myself formed of him. He was the ablest and best man here, and his personal
                    character was symmetrical.</p>
                <p>In the perplexing phases of local discord he was a power of strength to the
                    administration, and at this hour, when the organic law of the land is even
                    suspended, until reformed, his clear vision was resolving chaos into order and
                    liberty.</p>
                <p>The President is much depressed, but ever labors at his post of duty, I believe,
                    with singleness of heart for his country’s good.</p>
                <p>It is not thought that the assassination of the vice president was prompted by
                    other motives than personal revenge. The murderer is yet at large, although
                    strenuous efforts are being made for his apprehension. He is known to have been
                    a mere tool in the hands of others, who, of infamous character themselves, had
                    had a disgraceful enmity toward Señor Mendez, because in the path of duty he had
                    clashed with their interests.</p>
                <p>He was shot in the back, the ball passing through his heart. He uttered one cry
                    and died. He had been at my house in health and spirits a few hours
                    previous.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>THOS. BIDDLE.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure No. 1.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Caceres</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Biddle</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ministry of Foreign Relations of Salvador</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">National Palace, San Salvador</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-09-01">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 1, 1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Señor</hi>: I have to communicate to you the sad
                        intelligence of the death of the citizen the Licentiate Don Manuel Mendez,
                        the vice-president of the republic, minister of public instruction, justice,
                        and ecclesiastical affairs, which occurred on the 1st instant, in
                        consequence of a cowardly assassination.</p>
                    <p>Señor Mendez has been the victim of an atrocious crime,-which, from present
                        information, appears to have been instigated solely by personal motives.
                        This event has caused to the government, and to all the Salvadorean people,
                        a poignant and profound grief, for Señor Mendez, by his honorable
                        antecedents, patriotism, and endowments enjoyed the general esteem of his
                        fellow-citizens.</p>
                    <p>Will you communicate this information to the Government which you so worthily
                        represent, and accept the consideration and distinguished appreciation of
                        your obedient servant, in the absence of the minister of foreign relations,
                        the under-secretary,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>MANUEL CACERES.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0644" n="548" xml:id="pg_548"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Biddle</persName> to <persName
                                type="to">Bon Manuel Caceres</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">San Salvador</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-09-04">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 4, 1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Señor</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge receipt of
                        your note conveying the sad intelligence of the death by assassination of
                        the illustrious citizen Señor Don Manuel Mendez, vice-president of the
                        republic, and minister of public instruction, justice, and ecclesiastical
                        affairs, and requesting me to communicate the information to my
                        Government.</p>
                    <p>In complying therewith, I shall inform it of his public virtues and his
                        private worth; how that Salvador has lost a distinguished son, an able
                        statesman, jurist, and scholar, bat, above all, a citizen of incorruptible
                        integrity and honor, whose life was a model of excellence, and whose death
                        will be deplored, not only by his afflicted country, but by the lovers of
                        republican liberty in all lands.</p>
                    <p>Tendering my deepest sympathy with your government in this public calamity,
                        with assurances of the highest consideration, I have the honor to subscribe
                        myself, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>THOMAS BIDDLE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
