<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 472.Mr. Boker to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1872p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d471</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">471</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1872-08-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1872-08-20T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHKBrLbO74DsZpb" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136190" lcsh-match="exact">Torture</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1872-08-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1872-08-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="471" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d471">
                <head>No. 472.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Boker</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                        the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-08-20">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 20, 1872</date>.
                                Received September 11.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 43.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to say, in reply to
                            dispatch No. 33, from the Department of State, relating to the inhuman
                            persecutions of the He <pb facs="0775" n="679" xml:id="pg_679"/> brews
                            in the principalities of Moldavia and Wallachia, that yesterday I had an
                            interview with the Turkish minister of foreign affairs, in which I
                            represented to him the sentiments of the Government of the United
                            States, and presented hi in with a copy of the dispatch just mentioned.
                            In reply to my inquiries the minister said that the prejudice against
                            the Hebrews was confined to the people of Roumania, and that it was in
                            no way shared or countenanced by the Roumanian government nor by the
                            Sublime Porte. The present minister of foreign affairs, Safvet Pacha,
                            holds a temporary appointment, which he will resign on the arrival of
                            Djemil Pacha, in favor of the latter.* * * * *</p>
                <p>Finding that I could neither receive nor impart knowledge in this
                            quarter, I applied to the mustichar, or under-secretary, of the former
                            government. By him I was assured that on the first remonstrance made by
                            the great powers of Europe regarding the persecutions of the Hebrews in
                            Roumania, strong representations had been made by the Ottoman’ to the
                            Roumanian government, and that all which the former could do had already
                            been done to prevent a recurrence of these disgraceful popular
                            outbreaks.</p>
                <p>* * * * *</p>
                <p>It therefore seems a little unjust to charge the sins of Roumania against
                            Turkey, in which the latter feels that she has no more moral
                            responsibility than for the social enormities committed in our Territory
                            of Utah. It is said here that the anti-Hebrew riots in Moldavia and
                            Wallachia were fomented by intrigue, in order to prove to Europe that
                            there could be no safety for person or property in the principalities,
                            save under a strong government, into whose waiting paternal arms it is
                            hoped that this fair country will one day drop by the well-recognized
                            law of national gravitation.</p>
                <p>When Mr. Costaforo, the Roumanian minister of foreign affairs, was in
                            Constantinople on business relating to the persecution of the Hebrews in
                            his country, in an interview which I had with him, he assured me that
                            the government sincerely desired to protect all classes of its subjects,
                            and that it would be its effort to prevent hereafter a recurrence of any
                            kind of riots in the principalities. Mr. Costaforo is now out of office,
                            but I have received the same assurances lately from Prince Ghyka, the
                            Roumanian diplomatic agent in Constantinople.</p>
                <p>As for the past persecutions, bad as they really were, their violence has
                            been greatly exaggerated by <hi rend="italic">ex-pa rte</hi> statements.
                            I have read, through the courtesy of the British embassador, a report
                            just made by the British vice-consul at Bucharest, Mr. St. John, a
                            judicious gentleman, in which he bears testimony as to the exaggerated
                            character of the early reports. For example, as a correction of what was
                            then reported as matter of fact, Mr. St. John says that it now appears,
                            from incontestable evidence, that during the whole of the anti-Hebrew
                            riots no Hebrew was killed and no Hebrew woman was violated. To prove
                            that Mr. St. John is an impartial witness, he says, on the other side of
                            the question, that although the Hebrews were found with the church
                            property, said to have been stolen by them, in their possession, and
                            although they confessed the theft, they were persuaded to make that
                            avowal by torture—a facility toward unreserved communication still in
                            use with the Roumanian courts, to their shame be it said, in the face of
                            the nineteenth century. I am happy to be able in some degree to mitigate
                            the tragical character of the first reports which were made concerning
                            the persecutions, and all true friends of the Hebrews will rejoice that
                            their sufferings were not so great as they appeared to be to excited
                            spectators of the scenes. Only prejudiced partisans, who desire the
                            Roumanian <pb facs="0776" n="680" xml:id="pg_680"/> government to
                            receive more than just odium for its censurable weakness, would have the
                            facts otherwise.</p>
                <p>About the season of Easter anti-Hebrew riots are looked for, as a matter
                            of course, throughout the Turkish empire. It is a relic of the
                            superstition, commemorated in our ancient ballad of Thomas o’ Reading,”
                            that at Easter the Hebrews have a custom of immolating a living
                            Christian child. The consequence is that if any Christian should
                            disappear about that period—and the latitude is very great as to the
                            time, and the Christianity of the supposed sufferer—a riot against the
                            Hebrews is the inevitable consequence. This year there were such riots
                            in the islands of the Sea of Marmora, in Smyrna, and in various parts of
                            Russia.</p>
                <p>* * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GEO. H. BOKER.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
