<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1871-10-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1871-10-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="49" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d49">
                        <head>No. 49.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Fish</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Partridge</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                        of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-10-26"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 26,
                                1871</date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 21.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your dispatch No. 8, of the 9th ultimo,
                            was duly received. That part of it which relates to the diminution of
                            duties on certain principal articles of export from the United States to
                            Brazil was referred to the Secretary of the Treasury, a copy of whose
                            answer upon the subject is herewith inclosed. This Department concurs in
                            the views of Mr. Boutwell. It is desirable that the fiscal legislation
                            of all foreign countries should be so shaped as to increase their
                            consumption of the products of the United States, and the state of the
                            trade between this country and Brazil makes such legislation on the part
                            of the latter particularly to be desired, and it is to be hoped that
                            Brazil may find it consistent with her interests to make such changes as
                            may tend to an increased introduction of the products of this
                            country.</p>
                        <p>The disparity of the rates of duty upon certain leading articles, the
                            production of the one country imported into the other, has from the
                            beginning of our diplomatic intercourse with Brazil been pretty much the
                            same as it now is.</p>
                        <p>The representations which from time to time may have informally been made
                            by us upon the subject, appear to have had no effect in changing the
                            policy of that government. Threats of a countervailing duty upon
                            Brazilian coffee do not at anytime appear either to have been made by
                            us, or to have been apprehended by Brazil.</p>
                        <p>The statesmen of that country are probably aware of the extensive
                            consumption, positive and comparative, of Brazilian coffee in the United
                            States.</p>
                        <p>If, in your unofficial intercourse with leading men in Brazil, it should
                            be in your power, without giving offense, so to impress them with the
                            injustice of their duties on flour and lard from this country, as to
                            lead to their material reduction, you would render a service which would
                            signalize your mission, and would merit the thanks of your
                            Government.</p>
                        <p>I am, &amp;c,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>HAMILTON FISH.</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>