<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 62.Mr. Partridge to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1872p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d62</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">62</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1872-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1872-04-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="rec6SOt1hMx6m4tne" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085495"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1872-04-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1872-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="62"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d62">
                <head>No. 62.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Partridge</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>(<hi rend="italic"
                                >Petropolis</hi>,) <hi rend="italic">Rio de Janeiro</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-04-22">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 22, 1872</date>. (Received May
                        21.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 49.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On the 20th instant some changes took place in
                    the Brazilian cabinet, probably induced by the result of the late elections in
                    this province (of Rio) for the three candidates from whom the Emperor is to
                    select a senator, in place of the Yiscount Itaborahy, whose death I mentioned in
                    a late despatch.</p>
                <p>The Viscount de Rio Branco (formerly Senhor Paranhas) remains as president of the
                    council, but in place of the Counselor Tobato, as minister of justice, Mr.
                    Duarte de Azevedo has been named. Mr. Oliveira Jiinqueira (now president of the
                    province of Pernambuco) takes the place <pb facs="0194" n="98" xml:id="pg_98"/>
                    of Mr. Soyão Tobato in the war office, and the Baron de Itauna (senator) becomes
                    minister of commerce and public works in place of Mr. Freire Pereira da
                    Silva.</p>
                <p>The newly-appointed ministers are still of the same (conservative) party; and it
                    may be said, without error, that, in fact, the Viscount de Rio Branco is really
                    the minister-general. The Counselor Correa remains at the foreign office. As
                    there are no representatives in the house of deputies of the liberal party, this
                    change is merely meant to strengthen that portion of the party in power, which,
                    contrary to the wishes of the slaveholding party, passed the emancipation bill
                    of September last.</p>
                <p>It seems that there have been obstacles placed in the way, and delay in the
                    execution of that law in many of the provinces, and as the more liberal portion
                    of the conservatives, with Bio Branco at their head, is resolved upon its
                    execution, the ministry issued circulars to the presidents of the provinces,
                    providing for the registration and evidence of freedom to those children of
                    slaves born since the passage of the bill.</p>
                <p>Their continuance in power depends, in fact, upon their compliance with this law,
                    for though the slaveholding interests in the southern and coffee-growing
                    provinces bitterly oppose the ministry for this act, that interest well knows
                    that the access of the liberal party to power would be the occasion of
                    emancipation to the slaves now held, either immediate or after an intermediate
                    and short stage of apprenticeship.</p>
                <p>The news from the other parts of the empire shows continued quiet in polities$
                    but it is known that the liberal party is already at work for the elections in
                    January next.</p>
                <p>We have had here and in the provinces immediately south, very heavy and incessant
                    rain-storms of long continuance, which have done great injury to property, and
                    especially to the railway from Santos to Saint Paulo, washing away the inclined
                    planes from the ascent of the Serra, and the last rains particularly have done
                    damage in Rio, flooding the streets and undermining the foundations of many
                    houses so that they have fallen.</p>
                <p>On invitation of the manager of the Uniãoe Industria (turnpike) road, one of the
                    finest works of its kind anywhere, I made an excursion (Rear-Admiral Lanman and
                    other guests being of the company) to Juiz de Fora, in the province of Minas
                    Geraes, spending one day in going, (one hundred miles,) two days there and one
                    in returning, and passing through a fine coffee-growing region. At Juiz de Fora
                    is a nourishing German colony, and an agricultural college, which is not very
                    flourishing. The coffee-trees were heavy with berries, and there appears to be
                    nodanger this year of any short crop, which will be gathered in May and June.
                    The great Don Pedro Segundo Railway runs parallel to the Union road from Intre
                    Rios, and will be finished to Juiz de Fora in two years. Beyond that point, at
                    present, there are no roads, properly so called—only wide mule-paths, which
                    wagons, hauled by six and seven yoke of oxen, travel with difficulty, and this
                    into a region where mining and planting have been carried on for three hundred
                    years.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JAMES R. PARTRIDGE.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
