<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 74.Mr. Root to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1872p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d74</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">74</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1872-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1872-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94005552" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Epidemic</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418" lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="religious-freedom" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026944" lcsh-match="exact">Clergy</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271" lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664" lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="population-demographics" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969" lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856" lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131" lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447" lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698" lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184" lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862" lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="labor" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091" lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="confidence-building-measures" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257" lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130" lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576" lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1872-09-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1872-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="74" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d74">
                <head>No. 74.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Root</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                        the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Santiago de
                                        Chili</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-09-07">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 7,
                                    1872</date>. (Received October 9.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 53.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In one of my last dispatches I alluded to
                            the epidemic of smallpox which was raging with fearful results in
                            Santiago, and suggested that perhaps at a later day I might give some
                            account of the same, and inasmuch as the head of this legation has had
                            more or less connection with the public endeavors to stay the progress
                            of the pestilence, it may not be improper for me to give a partial
                            history of his acts and their results. Having my family with me, of
                            course felt all the personal interests attaching to that circumstance,
                            and as some months since the small-pox assumed an epidemic form and
                            threatened to prove of a most malignant character, I felt deeply the
                            need of the adoption of some active sanitary measures to stay the spread
                            of disease, but desired to prevent unnecessary personal notoriety, for
                            which purpose I wrote some articles suggesting sanitary changes which
                            appeared in the daily papers accredited to other sources, but as the
                            disease assumed more and more terrible proportions, I hesitated no
                            longer, but offered my professional services publicly and privately. My
                            letters to the intendent and other articles published from time to time,
                            together with complimentary letters received from various sources, and a
                            few only of the many similar notices taken from the newspapers, the
                            copies of which I inclose, will give you a general idea of my connection
                            with the epidemic, and the manner in which the same is viewed here, all
                            of which I trust may not be deemed unworthy of the representative of my
                            country.</p>
                <p>The disease early assumed a very malign ant form, seeming to pay but
                            little heed to the usual preventives to the malady. As, for example, all
                            the members of my family had been previously successfully vaccinated,
                            and three times during my life had vaccination “taken” most thoroughly
                            on my own person, the last time only a few months since, yet three of my
                            children and myself were victims of the epidemic, though, tnanks to
                            early and active treatment, none of us were long or severely ill. At the
                            present time there are only a few hundred in the hospital. Nearly 50 per
                            cent, of the adults attacked have died, and the mortality among children
                            has been much greater.</p>
                <p>My previous professional life as a physician and surgeon in civil and
                            military life had given me an opportunity of knowing something of what
                            should be done in such a trying emergency as the one alluded to, and I
                            felt perfectly free to give all with whom I came in contact the benefit
                            of the same. As well from visiting hospitals, attending meetings of the
                            society for the care of “<hi rend="italic">lazaretos,</hi>” &amp;c, I
                            have attended a vast number of the poorer classes who dislike to go to
                            the “<hi rend="italic">lazaretos</hi>, (small-pox hospitals,) and who
                            were too poor to pay a physician. (It is unnecessary to state that all
                            my services have been gratuitously given.) While confined to my room
                            with the disease, I was daily visited by parties who described the
                            symptoms of their friends sick with the prevailing epidemic, and whom I
                            “doctored” by proxy, sending them advice and medicine from my room, and
                            since my recovery, as well from visiting a large number as above alluded
                            to, I have daily by proxy medicated <pb facs="0207" n="111" xml:id="pg_111"/> great numbers in remote parts of the city. Since
                            commencing this dispatch, a young mail just commencing the study of
                            medicine has called to consult me touching a case I placed him in charge
                            of this morning. This young man has for more than two months been
                            similarly engaged. It is very gratifying for me to know that all whom I
                            have treated, either directly or indirectly, have completely recovered
                            or are out of danger. My system of treatment may be found in some of the
                            articles which I inclose published in newspapers. They have been very
                            generally copied by all the papers of the country, which, with the
                            exception of the one from which said articles are cut, are printed in
                            Spanish. Though full reports have not yet been made, it is fair to state
                            that many thousands have died during the epidemic.</p>
                <p>It is very creditable to the generosity and philanthropy of this people
                            to be able to say that all classes of society lent a helping hand, and
                            vied with one another in the Christian work of saving the sick and
                            staying the scourge. The President of the Republic, and his Ministers,
                            the Intendentes of the city, the Clergy, the Sisters of Charity,
                            together with the physicians and students of medicine, gentlemen and
                            ladies from all quarters, in person or with their money, assisted in the
                            great work. The President and Intendentes in person often visited the
                                <hi rend="italic">lazaretos</hi>, thus setting a noble example to
                            those in the lower walks of life.</p>
                <p>At one time there were more than twelve hundred daily reported in the <hi rend="italic">lazaretos</hi>, and probably, at the same time, an
                            equal number were sick in private dwellings.</p>
                <p>From my observation and experience in this epidemic, and in previous
                            years, I trust I may be excused for saying I am thoroughly convinced of
                            the importance of the suggestions found in my articles, copies of which
                            are inclosed. In fact, I am perfectly satisfied that by carefully
                            following the indications therein found, <hi rend="italic">every ease of
                                small-pox may be cured</hi> when seen early in the disease, no
                            matter how malignant its character may be. The grand idea never to be
                            lost sight of being to destroy the poison of the disease both inside and
                            outside of the body, and at the same time support the strength of the
                            patient, and by following the rules referred to not only will all
                            recover, but no pitting or other mark whatever of the disease will
                            remain in any part of the body and the patients thus treated will not be
                            confined to their beds except for a very few days, and frequently, as I
                            have had cases, never take their beds at all, except at night, suitering
                            no pain or especial inconvenience after the system is once thoroughly
                            under the influence of the remedies prescribed, only requiring care for
                            some weeks not to take cold, or otherwise expose the system by overt
                            acts of any kind, for in this, as in all other exanthematoas diseases,
                            there is danger of some one or more organs of the body becoming disabled
                            through lack of care after convalescence is supposed to have given place
                            to perfect health.</p>
                <p>The copies inclosed are marked A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H, J, K, L, M. N,
                            O.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. P. ROOT.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure A in No. 53.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Saturday</hi>, <hi rend="italic">June 22</hi>,
                                1872. In our issue of the 15th instant we informed our readers that
                                the Hon. J. P. Root, minister plenipotentiary of the United States,
                                had generously offered to lend his-professional services toward
                                checking the ravages of the present terrible epidemic of small-pox
                                in Santiago; and we have now the pleasure of presenting to our
                                readers the <pb facs="0208" n="112" xml:id="pg_112"/> following
                                highly interesting report, presented by that gentleman to the
                                indefatigable Intendente of the capital, Don Benjamin Vicuna
                                Mackenua: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p rend="right">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi>, <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 16, 1872,</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">“To the Intendente of
                                            Santiago, Don Benjamin Vicuna Mackenua:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: In accordance with the
                                        resolution passed yesterday at the Intendencia, I have this
                                        day visited the lazarettes of Santiago, accompanied by
                                        Captain Castro, who kindly presented me to the directors of
                                        the various establishments visited, and by the, Rev. Mr.
                                        Ibanez, who examined with me each room occupied by the sick
                                        of the smallpox, as likewise all the departments annexed to
                                        the lazerettes My desire to set forth some of the principal
                                        facts connected with my visit of to-day as briefly as
                                        possible will be my excuse for anything that may be hasty in
                                        this report, since I consider it to be of vital importance
                                        that some changes should be made immediately in reference to
                                        the condition of the lazerettes, which are at present
                                        crowded with the victims of the terrible scourge that now
                                        afflicts this city.</p>
                            <p>“The first place visited was the hospital of San Rafael,
                                        situated in Yungai, opened yesterday, which contained on my
                                        leaving it twenty-six sick persons, two having been received
                                        during my visit. The hospital is under the charge of a
                                        doctor, who visited it at 9 a.m., and who, it is expected,
                                        will visit it the same hour every day. There are four male
                                        nurses, two for the day and two for the night, and one
                                        female nurse, who has under her special charge a sick boy,
                                        her own son; there are, besides, a steward, two watchmen,
                                        and a cook. There are two wards containing sick, and it is
                                        believed that when they are full they will contain seventy
                                        beds. The wards at present occupied are well ventilated, and
                                        the air was comparatively pure. I should not omit to state
                                        that four medical practitioners, possessed with love toward
                                        humanity, and impelled by their holy calling, lend their
                                        services there night and day; it being worthy of observation
                                        that in this hospital only have we found professors of
                                        medicine. The hospital and its appurtenances presented a
                                        good appearance, and all there appeared to be entering on
                                        their work of charity with a spirit that awakens hope for
                                        the well-being of the sick under their care.</p>
                            <p>“Saviour’s Hospital has one hundred and sixty-two sick; seven
                                        died during the last twenty-four hours, and twelve were
                                        admitted during that time. Four Sisters of Mercy assist
                                        there continually, and personally administer the medicines,
                                        besides attending to the general administration of the
                                        hospital. There are eleven nurses, seven for day and four
                                        for night service. There are seven wards occupied. A greater
                                        proportion of children die than adults. There are at present
                                        thirty children here. There is a cook who works under the
                                        immediate orders of a sister especially charged with the
                                        kitchen. There are no other nurses than the servants.</p>
                            <p>“The wards are swept once a day, and the floors washed only
                                        when and where any impurity falls upon them. The building is
                                        a large house with two floors, with passages which traverse
                                        it centerwise, and corridors to both floors. The position is
                                        good, there being no other buildings near; nor is there any
                                        reason why the sick should not enjoy a wholesome atmosphere;
                                        but the air of the rooms is in a terrible condition,
                                        sufficient of itself to produce the most serious results
                                        even in a perfectly healthy person, it being difficult to
                                        understand why the mortality, at present so appalling, is
                                        “not even greater. The building, notwithstanding, can easily
                                        be converted into a lazarette of the first class, where,
                                        with the proper attention and suitable medical assistance.,
                                        almost all the sick should recover. The rooms are all clean;
                                        each one, however, containing double the number of patients
                                        it ought to have. When it is ventilated as is thought
                                        proper, as was said, during the day a door or a window is
                                        opened from time to time, though this was done rarely during
                                        my visit, which took place about 12 o’clock on a beautiful
                                        day. At night the rooms are all closed, so that no fresh air
                                        can enter, the poisoned air within not being allowed to
                                        escape. The beds are all occupied, and thirty of them are
                                        without bedsteads. There was no doctor present or near. Up
                                        to the present time no disinfectant whatever has been
                                        employed. The bodies are buried every other night, being
                                        kept in the mean time in a ventilated house at a few yards
                                        distant from the principal building. The doctor in charge of
                                        the hospital was absent, but on a commission of the in
                                        tendency.</p>
                            <p>“The hospital of San Francisco de Borga contains 470 sick,
                                        150 of them being children, many yet suckling. Seven died
                                        during the last twenty-four, hours; the day previously, 24.”
                                        The number of sick received during the last day has reached
                                        30. There are nine wards, each one of which is under the
                                        charge of a Sister and two female nurses. There are twelve
                                        washerwomen, ten night-nurses, besides two Sisters, four
                                        female cooks, with two Sisters who direct them, one
                                        mattress-maker and six seamstresses, and six men-servants
                                        for the work in general. The wards are cleaned thrice a day,
                                        and some disinfectants are employed. Ventilation is
                                        comparatively good, and the yards extensive, which supply
                                        pure and wholesome air. The bodies are buried every night.
                                        The terrible mortality of this hospital cannot apparently be
                                        attributed to want of attention on the part of the
                                        self-denying Sisters who, moved by charity, lend their <pb facs="0209" n="113" xml:id="pg_113"/> services to
                                        suffering humanity. The Lady Superior stated that there was
                                        yet a surplus of a hundred beds. There was no doctor
                                        present, though one or more daily visit the hospital.</p>
                            <p>“The hospital of La Maestranza contains 152 sick. Although we
                                        waited nearly half an hour, the only person who appeared in
                                        charge of the hospital was the porter, who, after taking a
                                        turn all round the establishment, said that he could not
                                        find any one that we could speak to; that the three sisters
                                        in whose charge the establishment is, must have gone out. In
                                        view of this, we suggested that he should show us the wards.
                                        Of these there are five, completely crowded, dark,
                                        ill-ventilated, and full of a terrible and extremely
                                        pestilential smell. We had to retire without having been
                                        able to obtain any satisfactory data, and under the
                                        impression that this sad establishment needs a prompt and
                                        complete renovation.</p>
                            <p>“To sum up, allow me to add that, in my opinion, there should
                                        be an immediate change in the treatment of the variolose; as
                                        likewise an early preparation of new buildings dedicated to
                                        the reception of those victims of the small-pox who apply to
                                        them in search of medical assistance.</p>
                            <p>“It is astonishing to see how little attention has been paid
                                        to the use of disinfectants for the purpose of destroying
                                        the deleterious emanations proceeding from the sick. Not a
                                        single case has been shown me in which all the body of the
                                        sick has been cleansed with any kind of bath, except when
                                        convalescence has so far been established that the patient
                                        is at the point of leaving the hospital. Thus the sick have
                                        been left to struggle against internal and external
                                        accumulations until, owing to good luck or a robust
                                        constitution, the sickness has been overcome, and the
                                        patient is allowed to withdraw from the putrid exhalations
                                        that have saturated his skin for days and weeks together.
                                        Bat I have neither time nor space to enter into details. An
                                        important fact, notwithstanding, I should not pass over, and
                                        that is, perhaps, with a single exception, that all the
                                        drains into which are thrown the vomits, the evacuations,
                                        and all kinds of contagious impurities, pass through, more
                                        or less, considerable portions of the city, producing thus
                                        an inevitable source of this malignant and mortiferous
                                        disease. This should at once be remedied, a thing not
                                        difficult to do. The same thing is taking place, likewise,
                                        in all parts of the city, where there probably exist at
                                        present thousands of cases of variolose; and what is
                                        surprising is that the disease has not spread more rapidly
                                        among all classes of society. A scab of the small-pox thrown
                                        into a drain may readily be carried miles off and find a
                                        multitude of means to produce contagious effects in persons
                                        far from its starting-point.</p>
                            <p>“That these matters, as also others of greater importance,
                                        may be placed under the control of the authorities, is a
                                        strong argument in favor of suitable places being
                                        immediately prepared, in order that those persons may be
                                        transferred to them who are suffering in their houses.</p>
                            <p>“Have the goodness to excuse the frankness of some of my
                                        observations, a frankness which proceeds from a sentiment of
                                        charity toward my fellow-creatures.</p>
                            <p>“In concluding, allow me to suggest that the three great
                                        things that should be done are: 1st. To restrain immediately
                                        the development of the epidemic, visiting every house, and
                                        obliging every person not recently protected by vaccination
                                        to receive the cow-pox, employing force, if necessary. 2d.
                                        To cure the already immense number of sick, making use of
                                        all the science, wisdom, and philanthropy that are within
                                        reach. 3d. Cleanse perfectly streets, yards, drains, &amp;c,
                                        to prevent the same or another disease in future. And as all
                                        these things require immediate attention, every good citizen
                                        should contribute with his best efforts, and thus co-operate
                                        with the indefatigable Intendente, who is giving an example
                                        worthy of being imitated, and to whom I have the pleasure of
                                        offering anew my humble efforts in all that which is
                                        connected with the sad crisis through which the beautiful
                                        city of Santiago is passing.</p>
                            <p>“May all extend a helping hand, adopting the golden rule of
                                        doing to the brother in humanity as they would be done by,
                                        and then purity, health, and happiness will return, and the
                                        beautiful light of the sun will disperse all the clouds
                                        which now obscure and sadden our sky.</p>
                            <p>“With sentiments of the highest consideration and esteem, I
                                        remain, your obedient servant,</p>
                            <p rend="right">“J. P. ROOT.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure B in No. 53.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Saturday</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-07-06">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 6,
                                    1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>We regret to say that the United States minister, the Hon. J. P.
                                Root, is suffering from an attack of small-pox, contracted during
                                his indefatigable efforts to combat that fell complaint while acting
                                in his self-imposed capacity as a member of the board of health, in
                                Santiago. We learn from a private source that the attack from which
                                Mr. Root is suffering is of a mild form, and we are, therefore, glad
                                to say there is no ground for alarm. The illness of the honorable
                                gentleman has elicited the sympathy <pb facs="0210" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/> of the entire population of the capital, as it
                                will most assuredly do from all our readers, both far and wide, who
                                are already acquainted with the eminent and disinterested services
                                he has rendered to suffering humanity during the prevalence of the
                                present epidemic in the-capital.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure C in No. 53.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Small-pox is raging with unabated vigor in Santiago and the adjoining
                                districts, but the energetic measures adopted by the Intendente, and
                                in which he has been nobly seconded by his fellow-citizens and many
                                foreigners, notably among the latter the United States minister, the
                                Hon. J. P. Root, are beginning to tell favorably, for, although
                                there is little or no diminution in the number of cases, there is a
                                decrease in the rate of mortality.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure D in No. 53.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">a few suggestions for the treatment and cure
                                    of small-pox patients</hi>,</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">To the Intendente of Santiago, Don B. Vicunã
                                    Mackenna:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>In an epidemic like the one now in progress in Santiago, <hi rend="italic">fear</hi> is always a promoter of the spread of
                                disease, and the almost direct cause of the death even of
                                multitudes. Therefore, while the community in general should be
                                stirred to the greatest extent as regards its duty in warding off
                                the pestilence and caring for the afflicted, the victims thereof
                                should, from the first, be made to have full confidence in their
                                speedy and safe recovery; and their confidence must be inspired by
                                all those coming in contact with them, not only by words, but by
                                looks, actions, and surroundings; the object of treatment and care
                                being, in the language of the great physician of Galilee, <hi rend="italic">to save life, and not destroy it.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>It has been said that some one in one of the hospitals of Santiago
                                has been in the habit of telling those that are brought thither that
                                they must at once prepare for another world, as they will never
                                leave the hospital alive. Such a view of the situation, from such a
                                source, is sufficient to make the life of the unfortunate sufferer
                                very short in this world. The person alluded to, however, deserves a
                                great deal of credit for honest efforts; and right here I will say
                                that those parties who are devoting their energies and their lives
                                to the curing of the sick—toiling night and day amid far from sweet
                                and pleasant scenes—are offering prayers that amount to something,
                                their <hi rend="italic">faith</hi> showing itself by their <hi rend="italic">works. Science</hi>, however, should step in and
                                give direction to the truly Christian labors of love of these
                                individuals, whose works of self-denying charity will surely find
                                their reward, as no good deed, in wisdom performed, was yet even
                                forgotten or ever can go unrewarded. But never frighten the sick;
                                fear is a most depressing agent, and the hospital should be made an
                                attractive place, where pleasant thoughts may be engendered, a pure
                                air breathed; where smiles, and hope, and joy, and gladness may
                                mingle in all that appears; everything which can help to enliven and
                                strengthen the prostrated energies of the patient, and dissipate the
                                sad thoughts and fearful forebodings incident to a weakened
                                condition of body and mind, should be cultivated in the hospital.
                                The aim should always be to make everything connected with the place
                                devoted to the curing of the sick perfect in all their parts. Not an
                                impure spot should be allowed anywhere from which an unwholesome
                                emanation can arise. Not a tainted breath should be permitted a
                                second time to enter the lungs of the sick, but the currents of air
                                should be so arranged that each breath loaded with disease may be
                                taken at once beyond the contact of any one into the outer air, and
                                fresh air supplied in its place. It is surprising what a vast amount
                                of disease is thrown from the lungs of an invalid in the act of
                                breathing, and how soon a room ill-ventilated is poisoned thereby;
                                therefore the importance of continued and active efforts in this
                                direction. The air of the sick-room must be kept constantly
                                perfectly sweet and pure, so that not even the slightest unpleasant
                                odor can be noticed. In order that this may be the case, an easy
                                ingress for fresh air, and an equally easy egress for foul and
                                tainted air, must be had, and all so arranged that unpleasant
                                currents may not strike directly upon the patient. A quite strong
                                current of good air, however, is infinitely safer to be in than to
                                be obliged to breath over and over again an atmosphere poisoned by
                                the diseased exhalations from lungs, body, bed, &amp;c, as is too
                                often the case; and this condition of pure air must continue during
                                the night as well as day. To ventilate properly, the air must enter
                                near the floor of the room and go out at the upper part; and where
                                rooms are not thus provided, the fault should immediately be
                                remedied, a task not difficult; but, whether difficult or not, <hi rend="italic">it must be done at once</hi>, care being taken
                                that the air entering from the lower parts through the walls of the
                                room comes from a <pb facs="0211" n="115" xml:id="pg_115"/> pure
                                source, the great fact being kept in view that the patient must at
                                all hazards breath nothing but a continually pure atmosphere. The
                                walls and ceilings of rooms should always be white, a thing easily
                                done by whitewashing. The temperature also of the room is of great
                                importance, and can only be regulated by artificial means. At this
                                season of the year fires are very necessary, so that, without
                                closing the room, and thus preventing a free circulation of fresh
                                air, the atmosphere of the apartment may be kept constantly at an
                                even temperature, the heat being regulated by a thermometer in each
                                room. Heat from an open fire-place, with a good chimney, is
                                preferable, but a stove is the next best thing where the heat cannot
                                be obtained from pipes or ranges, heated by steam or hot air. Heat
                                materially assists in the ventilation of the room, the heated air
                                rising and passing out at the upper part, carrying with it the
                                impurities in the atmosphere. The brasero is a very unsafe and even
                                dangerous source of heat.</p>
                    <p>It is often the case when the vital powers are exhausted in some of
                                the later stages of disease that the patient dies from lack of heat;
                                an hour’s cold, in a large hospital, caused by the sudden change of
                                the temperature of the air, no provision having been made against
                                its effect, may cause the death of a large number who otherwise
                                might have recovered.</p>
                    <p>It is important that a hospital should be located, if possible, apart
                                from the thickly settled portions of the city. The location of the
                                “Hospital del Salvador” is fortunate in this particular, and the
                                building now occupied might be made very serviceable by being
                                arranged in accordance with the above suggestions.</p>
                    <p>It is of great importance that disinfectants are constantly used in
                                and arround all hospitals, not only the yards, the houses, the
                                rooms, the floor, the beds, but the patient must be constantly
                                cleansed from all poisonous and infectious emanations. The object
                                should be to destroy the poison both in the body and out of it; the
                                first by proper remedies properly administered, and the second by a
                                variety of appliances and precautions. Fire, the surest destroyer of
                                contagious matter, should be used for all articles not possible to
                                be cleansed by other means. Nothing should be swept or thrown into
                                any corner, or allowed to remain in waste-heaps; but all filthy
                                rags, sweepings of rooms, &amp;c, should be instantly burned. Never
                                bury any article or throw it into an acegnia. All vomits,
                                evacuations, washings, &amp;c, not subject to be burned, should be
                                thrown into a deep hole in the ground, in which quicklime, strong
                                solution of sulphate of iron, carbolic or other acids, or other
                                appropriate articles, are constantly kept, sufficient in amount and
                                strength to destroy at once all contagious influences; and the hole,
                                when partially full, thoroughly covered, and a new one opened; but
                                never should anything unhealthy be thrown into an acegnia, even
                                though it runs directly into the country, the constant effort being
                                to annihilate both the disease and its possible future effects.</p>
                    <p>The sick-room should be the object of constant and unremitting care
                                and attention; it is not enough to purify once each day; every
                                moment the condition of the atmosphere must be watched, and wherever
                                and whenever an unpleasant or foul and unwholesome odor or influence
                                is observed, at once it must be eradicated. Every part of the room
                                should be constantly so sweet and pure that the most fastidious
                                could detect nothing disagreeable. In the severest cases the sheets
                                and the shirts of the patient should be changed every day and the
                                whole clothing of the bed often aired and purified, that the
                                diseased accumulations maybe removed as speedily as possible; every
                                article being thoroughly disinfected, either by fumigations,
                                washings, or otherwise, before being used the second time, and all
                                being thoroughly fresh, sweet, and dry before coming in contact with
                                the patient. The floor, walls, ceilings, bedsteads, and furniture of
                                the room need constant cleansing and purifying, so that the air,
                                when coming in contact with them, cannot be vitiated thereby. Some
                                of the best disinfectants for the purpose are carbolic acid,
                                chloride and other preparations of lime, together with many other
                                articles commonly used for this purpose.</p>
                    <p>As regards the medical treatment of the small-pox patients, no
                                special rules can be given which will meet the wants of every case,
                                therefore it becomes necessary that a scientific physician examine
                                carefully each patient very often, that each change may be noted,
                                and the treatment modified to meet the sometimes rapidly changing
                                phases of the disease, as a few hours lack of proper attention may
                                decide the fate of the invalid.</p>
                    <p>The first thing to be done with patients when attacked with small-pox
                                is to revaccinate them properly with virus known to be good, no
                                matter whether they have ever been vaccinated previously or how
                                recently. The philosophy for this treatment I have not time to give,
                                but of the beneficial results I have no doubt, and it should be done
                                at anytime previous to the suppuration of the small-pox pustules;
                                after this stage its efficacy is perhaps questionable, though even
                                then it can do no harm.</p>
                    <p>There is not a single stage of the disease when the bathing in some
                                form of the entire body every day, and sometimes oftener, is not
                                absolutely necessary. This operation, however, must he performed
                                with the utmost care, and not left to the charge of ignorant or
                                careless nurses, else dangerous results may follow. The skin is one
                                of the great emunctories of the system, and the amount of waste and
                                diseased matters thrown upon the surface of the body is truly
                                wonderful. Nature exerts itself to the <pb facs="0212" n="116" xml:id="pg_116"/> utmost to get rid of the poisonous matters
                                that circulate in the body in various ways, but constantly by means
                                of the lungs and the skin. I have already shown how the impurities
                                thrown from the lungs by the act of inspirations may be disposed of
                                in a harmless manner, through the means of perfect ventilation. It
                                becomes as necessary also to dispose of the emanations from the
                                skin, which, by being allowed to accumulate around the body, not
                                only prevent the free exit from the surface of the body of other
                                vile and diseased matters, thus by force preventing the escape from
                                the system and obliging the poisons to continue in the circulation,
                                with all their fatal tendencies and actual effects upon the vital
                                forces of nature, but contaminating the clothing, air, and
                                everything coming in proximity with the person, as well as poisoning
                                the atmosphere further, thus forming a sort of endless chain of
                                poisonous influences, which, entering through the lungs into the
                                circulation, and thence after a time finding their way to the
                                surface, again contaminate the air destined once more for the lungs,
                                and so on; this <hi rend="italic">must</hi> be avoided. The time and
                                mode of bathing must be directed by the physician in charge, and
                                whether it shall be cold, tepid, or hot water, or whether ice in
                                various ways may be used, must depend entirely on circumstances;
                                whether the bathing shall be with strong or weak acids, of an
                                alkaline character, or of water alone, must also be subject to the
                                decision of the time, but some one of these it is necessary to use
                                every day, that the emanations from the skin may be thoroughly
                                cleansed therefrom. Sometimes a mixture of chalk and water, or
                                chalk, charcoal, and water, may be used on the entire surface of the
                                body with decidedly beneficial results; also an ointment of chalk,
                                charcoal, and sweet-oil, in certain stages may be of benefit, having
                                a decidedly disinfecting and healing effect upon the suppurating
                                surface.</p>
                    <p>It is impossible to specify what remedies shall be absolutely given,
                                as each case must be treated upon its own merits, and whoever
                                prescribes a wholesale treatment, applying the same to each and
                                every case, will see his patients die on his hands. There is no <hi rend="italic">specific</hi> for small-pox; that which comes
                                nearest to this is <hi rend="italic">perfect purity and cleanliness
                                    of everything connected with the patient</hi>. The medicines
                                most of service are those of a supporting and cleansing, or
                                antiseptic and stimulant character; all debilitating remedies are
                                worse than useless. Severe purging is very dangerous. Enemas of
                                various kinds are frequently indicated, and in a multitude of ways
                                may be advantageously used. This is often a popular method of
                                introducing antiseptics into the system, as well as by the
                                mouth.</p>
                    <p>The internal administration of antiseptics and disinfectants, such as
                                “crystallized phenic acid,” is of vast importance; also chloride of
                                potash dissolved in water; chloride of sodium (common salt)
                                dissolved in water, with an addition of acetic acid, (common vinegar
                                answering,) or citric acid, (the juice of the lemon serving a good
                                purpose.)</p>
                    <p>The carbolic acid as an antiseptic, deodorizer, and disinfectant
                                should be largely used in various ways in and around the hospital.
                                An excellent method of purifying a room filled with unpleasant and
                                infectious emanations is, with an atomizer (an instrument which, by
                                a rapid current of air, separates fluids into minute parts) to throw
                                the vapor of a mixture of carbolic acid and water and a very little
                                alcohol (the alcohol assisting in dissolving the carbolic acid) into
                                all parts of the room, beneath the bed, and in all corners and
                                places where there is any impurity whatever; this should be done
                                several times each day. Whenever the floors, walls, vessels, or
                                furniture of the sick-room are washed, carbolic acid should be put
                                into the water; its daily use in strong or weak solutions for
                                bathing all parts of the body is highly beneficial.</p>
                    <p>When there are hemorrhagic tendencies, the oil of turpentine may be
                                given with good results. Quinine and other articles of its class are
                                indicated when the strength seems failing from exhaustion, and it is
                                always better to be too early than too late in their
                                administration.</p>
                    <p>Acidulated drinks of various kinds are usually very grateful to the
                                patient; sometimes, however, those of an alkaline character are
                                indicated; weak lime-water with water of roses, or even a chalk
                                mixture, or, as before observed, a solution of the chlorate of
                                potash, are often remedies of very great service, and are more
                                frequently indicated than acids.</p>
                    <p>Suppurated surfaces artificially made upon the chest or other
                                portions of the body have often prevented an excess of pustular
                                pitting upon the face. When this operation is performed upon the
                                chest, its tendency is also to prevent lung complications. An
                                ointment made of sweet oil, charcoal, and wax, and placed upon the
                                face and neck, is a favorite remedy with some, to prevent pitting in
                                those places.</p>
                    <p>As much sunlight should be obtained in the room as the eyes of the
                                patients can tolerate, and if some of them are too sensitive, owing
                                to the location of their beds or other cause, it is better to use
                                shades for them than to exclude all the light from the room, as the
                                rays of the sun are great promoters of health. The statement that
                                pustular inflammation is seriously aggravated by the light is not
                                well supported, but if there is danger of this, it is better to
                                cover the exposed surfaces with the ointment above alluded to, or to
                                cover the same with oiled silk, making holes for the eyes, nose, and
                                mouth, rather than lose the health-giving effects of God’s pure
                                sunlight.</p>
                    <pb facs="0213" n="117" xml:id="pg_117"/>
                    <p>Great care should be taken that not too many patients are crowded
                                into each room, as in this condition it is impossible to obtain a
                                sufficient amount of fresh air for the use of all; aside from this,
                                it is important that patients should not be inconvenienced and
                                disturbed by the condition of their neighbors, as the mind has much
                                to do with the restoration of health; and when it is impossible to
                                prevent the death of a patient, the scenes necessarily connected
                                therewith should be excluded as much as possible from the other
                                inmates of the room.</p>
                    <p>All persons attacked with small-pox should at once be placed under
                                the care of an <hi rend="italic">intelligent and attentive
                                    physician.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Sometimes wines and other similar stimulants maybe used with good
                                effects, but their indiscriminate administration cannot be too
                                strongly deprecated. Diffusible stimuli, like the carbonate of
                                ammonia, are often of great service. No preparation of mercury
                                should be given. A multitude of medicinal and remedial agents might
                                be named, and their use commented upon, but the fact that from time
                                immemorial educated physicians have never agreed upon the exact
                                remedies suitable for the treatment of this disease is a strong
                                argument against placing too much reliance upon the beneficial
                                action of any one article of medicine; but experience has
                                satisfactorily demonstrated the efficacy of what may be called the
                                hygienic treatment, and that when certain great sanitary principles
                                are carried out, such as are intended in this article, a very small
                                percentage of small-pox patients will die; but when there is a
                                failure in this direction, no matter what the medical <hi rend="italic">treatment</hi> may be, a very large percentage
                                must die.</p>
                    <p>The general rule, therefore, is to support the patient from first to
                                last, obliging perfect purity and cleanliness to be observed on all
                                sides, being careful not to push medical aid so as to interfere with
                                nature’s operations, but only to follow her indications, and assist
                                instead of hindering her efforts to drive out the foreign enemy that
                                has taken forcible possession of her territory; thus nearly all
                                those taken with the small-pox will recover. Those only need have
                                any fears whose constitutions have been broken down by severe
                                dissipations of any kind.</p>
                    <p>As regards diet, the patient should be <hi rend="italic">fully
                                    nourished</hi>, but in the early stages the food should be free
                                from oily substances, which will not be readily digested, and only
                                tend to produce increased febrile excitement, and perhaps tend to
                                prepare the way for intestinal complications. At this stage also the
                                stomach loathes this class of food, an indication that it is not
                                needed. But, during this period, the diet should be largely of
                                boiled rice, or similar articles of food, with broth without a
                                particle of grease. The patient should be strongly encouraged to use
                                quite freely rice-gruel and a thick mucilage of gum-arabic for
                                drinks during the entire disease, being careful that they are always
                                pure and fresh, and preserved for use in apartments not occupied by
                                the sick, as fluids have the power of absorbing impurities from the
                                atmosphere. All drinks may be cold or hot, to suit the taste of the
                                patient. If the stomach is not crowded with articles too oily or
                                difficult of digestion during the early stage of the disease, it
                                will readily digest more supporting food a little later. Nourishment
                                should be given with as great regularity as possible, though no
                                arbitrary rules can be followed in this or any other plan of
                                treatment; therefore, as has been previously observed, each patient
                                must be the object of especial care on the part of the medical
                                attendant, as well as of all his assistants.</p>
                    <p>The above presents a general view of the proper treatment of
                                small-pox patients, the adoption of which will cure those already
                                sick, and prevent the spread of the contagion from the persons of
                                those being cured.</p>
                    <p>It will be very apparent from the foregoing somewhat hastily written
                                suggestions, that the labor absolutely necessary to be performed in
                                the cure and treatment of small-pox patients is far from being
                                light; the number of assistants required should be in proportion to
                                the service demanded. The number of nurses should be such that they
                                should not be exhausted with overwork or watching, as it is all
                                important that those coming in contact with the sick and feeble
                                should not only be free from disease themselves, but be able to
                                impart from their own pure, healthy, strong, and vigorous
                                constitutions, life-giving influences. The weak, diseased, and those
                                lacking life and energy, should never, if possible to avoid it,
                                attempt the cure of the sick. A cadaverous face with tottering limbs
                                and a trembling hand, cannot successfully combat disease and
                                debility. The presence of the elastic step and smiling, joyous face,
                                together with the touch of the steady hand of the strong and
                                healthy, carry hope and actual life to the suffering invalid. There
                                is a nervo-magnetic fluid circulating in all our bodies which is
                                imparted to a greater or lesser extent to those with whom we come in
                                contact, and its effects correspond in a great degree to the
                                conditions of our own persons and lives.</p>
                    <p>He who saves his patients and they who labor under his guidance
                                occupy no easy position; their tasks during such trying epidemics as
                                the one now afflicting this country are arduous in the extreme, and
                                strongly test their moral, mental, and physical capacities. All such
                                parties should be freely and liberally sustained by the community
                                    <pb facs="0214" n="118" xml:id="pg_118"/> at large. It speaks
                                well for Santiago that there are so many who are most
                                philan-thropically giving all their energies to this noble work.</p>
                    <p>Christ, the great physician, commanded his followers to “pray without
                                ceasing;” I believe that, whether they think it or even desire it,
                                the labors of the faithful, self-denying physician, assistant, and
                                nurse, passing quietly yet firmly through danger, disease and
                                pestilence, are not excelled in their Christian character by the
                                acts of any other human beings. If they do their duty, no matter
                                what their mouths utter, their hearts, brains, and hands mutually
                                unite in working out unceasing prayer most acceptable to God and
                                humanity. I have written the above in plain language that it may be
                                easily understood by all.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>J. P. ROOT.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure E.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Saturday</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-07-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 20,
                                        1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The Hon. J. P. Root, though scarcely convalescent from his recent
                                attack of smallpox, has again taken his seat at the board, and a few
                                days ago he visited all the hospitals in company with Dr. Aguirre,
                                and we are happy to say that his inspection has been the means of
                                introducing many beneficial reforms in the lazarettes.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure F.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Mackenna</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Root</persName>.—Letter from the central
                                    society of hospitals.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-07-01">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 1,
                                    1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The very interesting memorial upon the
                                arrangement of hospitals and the treatment of those afflicted with
                                small-pox, which your excellency has had the goodness to direct to
                                us, has filled with satisfaction and gratitude the society of
                                citizens charged with combating the epidemic which to-day is making
                                its terrible effects felt in this capital.</p>
                    <p>The wealth of information and vast experience which its author places
                                in it to the service of humanity, as well as the practical and
                                scientific application of knowledge which he applies to the present
                                case and circumstances, fill us with gratification. And we are no
                                less inspired with profound gratitude by that self-denial with which
                                your excellency personally has visited the poor sick in the
                                hospitals and investigated in those places most scrupulously
                                everything connected with their wants and the treatment of the sick,
                                so that we have been permitted to see at one view the learned
                                physician who determines the best remedy for the malady of the
                                patient, and the practical Christian who closely approaches the
                                sufferer in order to relieve him, and even, if necessary, to
                                participate in his pains in order to alleviate them.</p>
                    <p>This society, in view of all this, has decided to present to your
                                excellency, in this note, a testimony of the high appreciation which
                                so noble acts merit. Besides, each and all of the members that
                                compose it offer to your excellency their perfect attachment.</p>
                    <p>Your excellency’s obedient servants,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>J. I. V. EYZAGUIRRE, <hi rend="italic">President</hi>.</item>
                                <item>VALENTIN MARCOLETA.</item>
                                <item>FRANCISCO I. B. EGUIGUREN.</item>
                                <item>JOSÉ M. GUZMAN.</item>
                                <item>VICENTE IZQUIERDO.</item>
                                <item>M. OVALLE.</item>
                                <item>JAMARIO OVALLE.</item>
                                <item>MANUEL ARRIARAN, <hi rend="italic">Secretary</hi>,</item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure G.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Mackenna</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Root</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-06-27">
                                <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 27,
                                        1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Notwithstanding the Central Society for “Lazeretos “has offered to
                                your excellency the most expressive thanks for your excellent
                                article upon the internal organization of “Lazeretos,” and the
                                curing of their patients, this “Intendencia” takes pleasure in
                                multiplying the manifestations of its especial acknowledgments for a
                                service as opportune <pb facs="0215" n="119" xml:id="pg_119"/> as
                                charitable. It is truly a great consolation and a distinguished
                                honor for our enlightened capital to excite sympathies so high and
                                so sincere as those which your excellency has contributed, it being
                                worthy of note that this is perhaps the first occasion in which the
                                representative of a friendly nation has proved to our
                                fellow-citizens by especial acts of self-denial, and of work that
                                appeals to the human soul, which it has been the custom hitherto to
                                leave exclusively to toasts and protocols. God guard your
                                excellency.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>B. VICUÑA MACKENNA.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure H.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Mackenna</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Root</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-07-12">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 12,
                                        1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor of placing within the
                                knowledge of your excellency that this Intendencia has unanimously
                                decided to name one of the new streets of Santiago with the name of
                                Root street, (Calle de Root,) in memory and honor of the generous
                                and philanthropic services which your excellency has been pleased to
                                lend to the unhappy sick during the epidemic which has afflicted and
                                yet saddens the city. God guard your excellency.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>BEN J, VICUÑA MACKENNA,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Intendente of
                                        Santiago.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure J.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Root</persName> to Mr.
                                        <persName type="to">Machenna</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Santiago de Chili</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-07-15">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 15, 1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: It is with mingled feelings of
                                surprise and pride that I acknowledge the reception of the official
                                communication of your honor notifying me that the Intendencia of
                                Santiago has named one of its new streets by my name as a token of
                                its appreciation of the humble efforts I have made in behalf of
                                those afflicted with the small-pox in this city. I am surprised that
                                so little on my part has been deemed worthy so much present pleasant
                                notice and future remembrance.</p>
                    <p>My feelings of pride are not a little appealed to by being thought
                                deserving the esteem, commendation, and recollection of the city of
                                Santiago, within the limits of which are found so many noble
                                self-denying souls, whose generous philanthropic sentiments—in this
                                sad hour—are being demonstrated to such an extent in courageous,
                                self-sacrificing acts, thereby, unknown to themselves, erecting in
                                the dearest memories of their fellow-men monuments more to be
                                cherished than pillars of marble, or statues of brass.</p>
                    <p>That the blessings of an ever kind and watchful Providence may
                                continually be vouchsafed to yourself, your co-workers, and those
                                under your care, is the earnest prayer of</p>
                    <p>Your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>J. R. ROOT.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure K.—Translation from La
                                    Republica.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-06-18">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 18,
                                        1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The representative of the United States, Mr. Root, has contributed in
                                a great measure to manifest to the authorities the true condition of
                                the lazaretos, (small-pox hospitals,) and the best means to combat
                                the epidemic.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Root has visited all the places of contagion, in many of which
                                the Sisters of Charity lend their important and pious services.</p>
                    <p>The self-sacrificing conduct of the North American minister is a
                                demonstration of his sympathetic sentiments, and his opinion is a
                                most valuable assistance in the present situation.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0216" n="120" xml:id="pg_120"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure L.—Translation from the Ferro
                                    Carril.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-07-05">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">July</hi> 5,
                                        1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The Honorable Mr. Root, minister of the United States, is now sick
                                with the small-pox. Mr. Root has examined, visited, and Carefully
                                studied all the lazarettos of the capital with an indefatigable
                                constancy. The public health owes him a great debt of gratitude, and
                                the epidemic, of which to-day he is a victim, has found him among
                                its most vigorous adversaries.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Root possesses a grand spirit and a grand heart. The men of
                                science have been able to judge his works as above science. All
                                noble souls have been able to estimate the spontaneity of his
                                services. Representative of a friendly nation, he has contributed
                                with the sacrifice of his person to manifest the lofty sentiments of
                                that nation.</p>
                    <p>This time diplomacy has taught humanity, and humanity self-denial.
                                Mr. Root has been wounded on the field of battle. There is nothing
                                more honorable than the scars of war.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure M.—Translation from the Ferro
                                    Carril.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Words spoken by Don Domingo Arteagar, Alemparte,
                                    the editor, at a large banquet given to the medical students who
                                    had acted nobly during the epidemic.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-09-04">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">September</hi> 4,
                                        1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen</hi>: I arise to propose a toast in
                                honor of the Honorable Mr. Root, minister of the United States. The
                                Government of the United States sent him to Chili to cultivate with
                                our government the relations of good-fellowship and harmony, which
                                happily exist between the two countries.</p>
                    <p>In presence of the epidemic which afflicted us, Mr. Root contented
                                not himself alone with performing the duties of that noble mission.
                                Disregarding the advantages of his exalted position, the comforts
                                and securities of his home, he wished to cultivate also relations
                                with the suffering and the contagion of our city. He visited our
                                lazarettos, he attended and aided our sick—compromised his life by
                                saving our lives. He has been thus something more than the
                                diplomatic representative of the great republic. He has been a man
                                of charity.</p>
                    <p>Gentlemen: To the health of Mr. Root, envoy extraordinary and
                                minister plenipotentiary of the human brotherhood, near the
                                afflictions and sympathies of the Chilian people.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure N.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Important letter from the Hon. <persName type="from">J. P. Root</persName> to <gloss type="to">Santiago medical students</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-07-24">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 24,
                                        1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Saturday</hi>, <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 10, 1872.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Honorable Sir</hi>: Grateful for the zeal and
                                self-denial you have manifested, as well in the hospitals as in
                                private toward our unfortunate countrymen; and desirous likewise of
                                co-operating in the early extinction of the epidemic, we take the
                                liberty of requesting you to be so good as to put us in possession
                                of your professional observations with regard to the disease,
                                accompanied with the well-devised and successful method of treatment
                                which your knowledge has suggested to you.</p>
                    <p>We, mere beginners in the medical career, hope to second the efforts
                                you have made for the extirpation of the disease, availing ourselves
                                of the scientific information you may be so good as to provide us
                                with, on which account the victims of the epidemic, as well as your
                                attentive admirers and friends, will remain eternally obliged.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>JACINTO O DEL RIO.</item>
                                <item>ERNESTO TURENNE.</item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>The Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">J. P. Root</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Present.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure O]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-07-25">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 25,
                                        1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen</hi>: Your very complimentary letter
                                of yesterday, asking my views touching the treatment of small-pox, I
                                shall answer with much pleasure, and though unable in the short time
                                I can devote thereto to give you my ideas as fully as I should like,
                                I will endeavor to make what I do say so clear that my suggestions
                                may be easily <pb facs="0217" n="121" xml:id="pg_121"/>
                                comprehended; trusting also to your intelligence and kindness for
                                the more symmetrical arrangement of what I am obliged somewhat
                                hurriedly to throw together.</p>
                    <p>And permit me, in commencing, to state that it is no depreciation of
                                the efforts of the many noble, self-denying individuals, who have
                                given their personal and other services to the alleviation and care
                                of the unfortunate sick, in the terrible epidemic that now afflicts
                                this people, for me to say that your colleagues and co-workers, all
                                those young men preparing themselves for physicians, who have so
                                generously, and with so much self-sacrificing philanthropy, left
                                their homes, where they were surrounded with all that love, health,
                                wealth, and refinement could make attractive, to spend days and
                                nights in the very midst of pestilential and fetid odors, and in the
                                presence of the gravest contagion, disease and death, giving their
                                energies, mental and physical, to the curing of maladies of the
                                severest type, deserve a meed of praise and honorable remembrance
                                which cannot be overestimated. I have too often witnessed their
                                smile of satisfaction, as indications of returning health were
                                visible, and the look of sadness depicted in their countenances as
                                they beheld the unmistakable signs of approaching death in the
                                patients under their care, not to be thoroughly convinced that their
                                noble hearts, as well as intelligent heads, were devoted to their
                                arduous labors. Such scenes, however, are incident to the practice
                                of medicine, and must be prepared for by all who would be perfect in
                                their profession. And well may the city of Santiago congratulate
                                itself, while contemplating the fact that the health of its
                                fast-coming future, to a great extent, must be in the hands of these
                                young men now preparing themselves for the weighty responsibilities
                                of physicians and surgeons.</p>
                    <p>Allow me also to suggest that no one can be too well prepared for his
                                professional life, and also, no matter how much time has been spent
                                in the preparatory course, every day’s experience of the scientific
                                physician will demonstrate the fact that his education is still
                                incomplete, and there always ought and ever will be an earnest
                                longing for more knowledge.</p>
                    <p>I also regret to inform you that, as you advance in medical wisdom
                                and seek after truth, no matter from what source it may emanate, you
                                will continually find your way blocked up with the accumulated
                                rubbish of ages, and, unless you have more than ordinary courage,
                                you will give up, like thousands before you, and rest satisfied with
                                what is claimed upon a certain kind of authority to be truth, when
                                you have only obtained a feeble glimmering of the true light of
                                science. The great trouble in your most noble profession is that by
                                far too many men in it advance backward, with their faces ever
                                looking toward the dim and musty past, instead of fronting the
                                bright future with its brilliant omens of progress. While it is well
                                to consult all the learning and read as many books as possible of
                                ancient as well as modern times, it is of great importance to
                                recognize the fact that the great “book of nature” is the only
                                infallible work whose teachings never go astray, and the true
                                student thereof will never tire in his reading of its beautiful
                                pages, or fail to be captivated with the splendid results ever to be
                                expected from closely following its indications.</p>
                    <p>You will excuse me for these prefatory remarks, made in view of the
                                fact that yet you have not finished your course of medical studies,
                                when I tell you that it has taken me many long years of patient
                                research and practical experience to demonstrate satisfactorily to
                                myself the worse than utter folly of many things I was obliged to
                                learn through the means of standard books, colleges, and the wisest
                                preceptors and professors of my country, before receiving my degree
                                as physician and surgeon. Study for yourselves the cause and reason
                                for everything taught you, improving every opportunity for this
                                purpose; and just now a great lesson may be learned from watching
                                the progress of the epidemic raging in this vicinity, whose fearful
                                consequences have been rapidly decimating the inhabitants of this
                                city; and in accordance with your wishes I will allude to the same,
                                hoping my thoughts and experience may not be without some
                                benefit.</p>
                    <p>From time to time I have surveyed the whole field here; closely
                                examined every portion of the city, and especially those places
                                devoted to the care of the sick; and, thanks to those who have
                                kindly given me aid and information, I am in possession of the
                                condition of hospitals and patients, and have a very correct
                                knowledge of all the measures, medical and hygienic, adapted for the
                                care and cure of the small-pox patients. Upon examination I found
                                the sanitary condition of most of the hospitals so deplorable that
                                my first effort was to suggest changes in that direction, and I am
                                happy to know that, with one or two exceptions, a great improvement
                                has been made. One prominent hospital, however, has, up to the
                                present time, made no alteration whatever; as, on my first visit
                                about six weeks since, the only room ventilated is the “dead-house,”
                                through which, night and day, fresh air is allowed to circulate
                                freely. Unfortunately, however, for its occupants, the lungs which
                                might have been benefited a few hours earlier thereby have ceased to
                                act.</p>
                    <p>After doing what seemed within my power for the improvement of the
                                condition of the hospital buildings, I made public my views upon the
                                “treatment of small-pox patients,” which, though you have already
                                perused, I would recommend you again to read, for in It may be found
                                my unchanged ideas upon this important subject—ideas which are <pb facs="0218" n="122" xml:id="pg_122"/> the result of many years’
                                thought and experience in civil and military life, and which, if
                                thoroughly followed, will, I am satisfied, wonderful as it may seem,
                                save ninety-nine one-hundredths of all persons attacked with
                                small-pox. What little one of you has personally seen of my
                                treatment of this disease must tend to confirm this view. But that I
                                may better be understood, I will give you again some of my
                                suggestions.</p>
                    <p>The exact chemical poison of small-pox is yet a matter of
                                speculation; but of its potency and powder to multiply itself with
                                the most wonderful rapidity and malignancy we have abundant proof
                                from the fact that the most minute portion being taken into the
                                system has the faculty of so increasing itself that, after the lapse
                                of about eight days more or less, the whole system is so impregnated
                                that certain symptoms, usually easily recognized, are the result.
                                After yet a few more days, during which the poison has been unable
                                to find its way from the body, or rather the vital forces have been
                                unable to expel the virulent enemy, certain other symptoms occur.
                                During the first stage there has been more or less fever, and the
                                epidermis or cuticle has become thereby hardened, or rendered
                                slightly impervious to matters passing through the dermis, or skin
                                proper, so that often, when the poison of the disease at this stage
                                is driven to the surface, it finds a barrier sufficient to prevent
                                its entire escape, and soon, from its vicious character, a
                                constantly increasing depot of purulent matter is congregated,
                                affecting, to a greater or less extent, all the tissues in its
                                neighborhood, often leaving, after the recovery of the patient, deep
                                pits to henceforth mark its wrathful demonstrations. Not only is the
                                effect of these aggregations of poisonous pus visible upon the
                                surface of the body, but when from lack of proper and frequent
                                cleansing of the skin these poisonous substances are absorbed, other
                                parts of the system are affected, which, added to the already
                                enfeebled condition of the same by the presence of uneliminated
                                virus, with its consequent effects, tends to threaten the whole
                                economy with rapid destruction, as not only the tegumentary but the
                                osseous, nervous, muscular, vascular, and other systems are
                                sufferers. I have not time, however, to enlarge in this direction.
                                Further along I shall indicate a treatment preventing to a great
                                extent the above condition of the skin.</p>
                    <p>As it is now a pretty well understood fact that the poison of
                                contagious and infectious diseases may be rendered inert or harmless
                                when they can be reached by certain agents called disinfectants; as,
                                for instance, a room, or the clothing even, filled with the
                                contagion of small-pox, by the proper application of disinfecting
                                agents may be made perfectly sweet and wholesome. Mainly upon this
                                fact rests the theory for my peculiar treatment of small-pox and
                                kindred diseases, which somewhat of an extended practice has
                                demonstrated to be of perfect practicability.</p>
                    <p>Without the poison of the disease the patient would be well;
                                therefore, all that is needed is to destroy the poison without
                                destroying the patient, as is too often the case. And all the
                                remedies given with the idea of combating simply an inflammation or
                                fever are worse than useless. There are only two methods of
                                treatment which can by any possibility do the patient good. One is
                                to support the strength of the patient while nature fights its
                                venomous enemy, hoping that, eventually, the poisonous intruder may
                                be overcome and expelled, and then allow the enfeebled though
                                victorious vital energies of the poor sufferer to slowly renew their
                                wonted life. The other method, and the one I adopt, is, while doing
                                all in my power to sustain the severely taxed energies of the
                                patient in their great fight with their, malignant foe, at the same
                                time to at once close the contest by instantly, if possible,
                                rendering his poison harmless for evil. And when this is done early,
                                the few repairs needed are too insignificant to cause any trouble
                                whatever. All other theories and practices save these two should be
                                driven from the profession as unworthy the attention of scientific
                                minds. The vast army of antiphlogistic remedies often marshaled
                                against this disease are only too apt to become swift and powerful
                                allies of the same. Of course the golden moments in the treatment of
                                small-pox are the first hours or days of the disease, and he who
                                waits for the disease to fully develop itself before commencing
                                offensive operations against it ought to expect the same fate as the
                                captain who, in war, should wait for his citadel, with its guns and
                                magazines, to be in the hands of the enemy before making any hostile
                                demonstrations against him. Not a moment is to be lost; an expectant
                                treatment will not answer; go at once to work in every judicious
                                way, both outside and inside the body, and in no disease will you
                                find so sure a reward for the labor performed.</p>
                    <p>But you ask for more details. First, then, omit to give any
                                debilitating medicines, This is very easy, and can be performed by
                                any one.</p>
                    <p>There are so many remedial agents which may be used that different
                                physicians may be excused for not adopting the same articles, even
                                though desiring the same results.</p>
                    <p>My general sanatory ideas, relating to heat, ventilation, &amp;c, as
                                well as many of my medical ones, as said before, may be found in my
                                communication on the “treatment of small-pox;” therefore I will omit
                                many things found therein, and give some of my most common
                                practices.</p>
                    <p>For years I have been in the habit of giving the muriated tincture of
                                iron for erysipelas with decided success, and it occurred to me
                                that, as in small-pox, the inflammation has more or less of an
                                erysipelatous character, this remedy would be of service, <pb facs="0219" n="123" xml:id="pg_123"/> and, upon trial, I was
                                charmed with its beneficial results. In the very first stage of this
                                disease I am in the habit of giving it to adults in doses of from
                                five to forty drops, or even in larger quantities, every four, six,
                                eight, or ten hours, as the case may be, and to children in
                                proportionate doses. This medicine acts in many ways; it is highly
                                supporting to the system, aside from having powerful disinfecting
                                properties, and, in connection with other medicines and appliances,
                                reduces often in a marked manner the rapidity of the pulse and other
                                conditions of the patient, and anticipates and prevents one of the
                                most frightful phenomena of the disease, to wit, hemorrhage. I also
                                am in the habit of giving, midway between the doses of this
                                preparation of iron, some alkali; and I have often found the
                                carbonate of lime (prepared chalk) in larger or smaller quantities,
                                according to the age and condition of the patient, a very valuable
                                remedy; the doses being from a few grains to two teaspoonfuls. This
                                remedy acts as an antiseptic, and sometimes, combining with the
                                chlorine, from the hydrochloric acid of the muriated tincture of
                                iron, forms, within the body, the chloride of lime, a powerful
                                disinfectant. Chlorate of potash is also a favorite remedy with me,
                                and sometimes lime-water and charcoal have been used with good
                                effects, and other similar medicines, giving quinine in doses
                                proportioned to the age and condition of patient and stage of the
                                disease.</p>
                    <p>I generally prefer an enema rather than a purge, when either seems
                                indicated, and a favorite one for an adult is composed of three
                                teaspoonfuls of oil of turpentine, three tablesspoonfuls of
                                castor-oil, from one to two teaspoonful of common salt, (chloride of
                                sodium,) and often an addition of more or less carbonate of lime,
                                with about a pint of tepid water. These quantities can be varied to
                                suit the age and condition of the patient. While giving the chalk
                                and iron it will be found that often a laxative or opposite effect
                                may be produced by lessening the quantity of either the one or the
                                other as may be desired, the acid of the iron preparation, by
                                neutralizing the alkali of the other, often proving a pleasant
                                laxative; or, in case there has been too much chalk given, and a
                                constipated condition of the bowels is the result, lemonade or other
                                acidulated drinks will answer the purpose of a mild aperient. I have
                                frequently administered internally carbolic acid with good
                                results.</p>
                    <p>Touching nourishment, &amp;c, I shall not speak, as in another place
                                I have referred you for much omitted here.</p>
                    <p>For the soreness of the throat, which is often very severe, a
                                favorite remedy with me is the tincture of iodine, painted
                                externally over the diseased locality; also a gargle of chlorate of
                                potash. The external treatment, though emphatically spoken of in
                                another place, I cannot refrain from alluding to here, as upon it
                                depends so much to be expected in the curing of small-pox, and
                                without which it is the utmost waste of hope to expect to save a
                                goodly proportion of patients gravely sick.</p>
                    <p>The skin is one of the greatest emunctories, to which is brought, and
                                on which is deposited, a vast amount of filthy, effete, and diseased
                                emanations and excretions of the body, and there would be just as
                                much sense in confining the body of the patient in an accumulation
                                of all the other excretions of the body as in those of the skin; the
                                effect would be the same, only differing in degree. Therefore, from
                                the first to the last, every portion of the body must be washed from
                                one to many times each twenty-four hours, depending upon the stage
                                of the disease and condition of the patient. I am in the habit of
                                alternating an acid with an alkali; and I like a solution of
                                carbolic acid and water, alternating with a chalk mixture, using
                                each quite warm; and frequently I have found a combination of both
                                very beneficial. Sometimes, in case of extreme heat of the head,
                                thin cloths wet in cold water are of service, always keeping the
                                feet warm; but the habit of suddenly applying cold water, and then
                                allowing the consequent re-action to quickly follow, only adds to
                                heated condition of the part, a fact which may be made of great
                                service in many cases of disease’; but I prefer in this disease
                                tepid or even hot bathings, very frequently as hot as possible to
                                bear, all of which may be, for convenience’ sake, performed by
                                sponge bathings, and great care should always be observed that no
                                chilly sensations are allowed. Either the room should be made quite
                                warm for the purpose, and then only a portion of the body exposed at
                                one time, or, what is better, in a hospital or room with many
                                patients, is a sort of tent made of a light frame covered with thin,
                                white cloth, to be placed over the bed while the bathing is being
                                performed. In this way exposure and currents of air are prevented.
                                An alcohol-lamp, or some other appliance, can be placed under the
                                bed, and the air made quite warm in a few moments, in which case the
                                body may be more readily bathed, shirts and sheets changed, &amp;c;
                                but the general principle must be observed no matter how the bathing
                                is performed. In the early stages of the disease the entire surface
                                of the body should be cleansed in this way at least four times each
                                day, and, in case of great febrile excitement and much delirium,
                                even much oftener, such bathing being always grateful to the
                                patient. One of you may remember the little boy, a patient of mine,
                                whose treatment was witnessed, whose pulse from being one hundred
                                and sixty-eight in the evening, with a grave kind of delirium and a
                                fever coresponding thereto, as he came to his senses at 2 a.m.,
                                asking to be bathed again, having a semi-consciousness of what had
                                done him good, having been treated as indicated <pb facs="0220" n="124" xml:id="pg_124"/> above, and, in the morning feeling
                                free from pain, even sitting up in bed smilingly, with a pulse
                                sixty-six beats less than a few hours before, looking at an
                                illustrated paper, and past all danger. The poison of the disease
                                having been completely annihilated by the internal and external
                                remedies before the strength of the patient had been reduced, or any
                                serious inroads made on the system, there was no good reason why he
                                should not feel well, and, with only a little care resume his wonted
                                plays. The poison of the disease having been destroyed just at the
                                period when it should have developed itself upon the surface of the
                                body in the shape of pustular eruptions, as a matter of course these
                                latter demonstrations made almost an entire failure to “put in an
                                appearance;” a few faint efforts in this direction were only seen;
                                but, in my opinion, had this child been allowed to remain with all
                                the poisonous fetid emanations of his disease closely around him,
                                and been dosed with all sorts of debilitating sudorifics,
                                purgatives, emetics, &amp;c, given for exactly what purpose no one
                                can tell, except in a blind compliance with the time-honored
                                practice of many very excellent men and even intelligent physicians,
                                or because “the books say so,” said little rosy-cheeked child would
                                in all human probability have joined the army of little children
                                that have gone to the spirit-land from this vicinity during this
                                terrible epidemic.</p>
                    <p>In this connection I cannot help remembering a statement published
                                only a few days ago, that in one week fourteen children were sent to
                                a hospital in this city, and fourteen of them died; that another
                                week forty children were admitted, and thirty-eight died. Just
                                think, only two out of fifty-four children could be saved. It would
                                seem that such and similar records ought to suggest a change of
                                treatment. Up to this hour not a patient in any of the hospitals of
                                Santiago has been bathed, even, as I have indicated, notwithstanding
                                what has been said and written on the subject, and still more than
                                half who enter these institutions pass from thence to the “Panteon.”
                                I speak not thus desiring any credit for ideas I may entertain
                                differing from other men, or for what I may have done in the case of
                                the child cited above, or others of a similar nature. I am not
                                entirely responsible for my past experience, and wish no praise for
                                the peculiar beliefs I hold, even though proved to be valuable. They
                                are the result of circumstances which I did not create, and if there
                                is anything good in them I trust you may benefit thereby; but permit
                                me to caution you not to adopt anything I may suggest unless it is
                                commended to your intelligence and educated judgment. Never take the
                                    <hi rend="italic">dictum</hi> of any man or any authority
                                because of its personal claims, and never discard with the cry of<hi rend="italic">humbug</hi> any idea because of its humble, origin
                                or apparent inconsistency with the prescribed rules of the past.
                                “Prove all things, hold fast that which is good,” is sound
                                teaching.</p>
                    <p>It is very rarely necessary in this disease to use alcoholic
                                stimulation. This remark may surprise you, as you have witnessed a
                                widely different practice. The patient seldom dies from debility, as
                                that term is commonly used, but from the poison of the disease, and
                                the almost universal use of wines cannot but do harm. When an
                                alcoholic stimulant is indicated it should be one with as little
                                acid as possible; but, with the treatment I have suggested, not one
                                case in a hundred will need any such stimulation. Too much care in
                                this direction cannot be used. Tonics are more indicated than
                                stimulants, and alkalies much more than acids. In proof of the
                                latter it will be found almost universally that all the excretions
                                and secretions of the small-pox patient are of an acid character.
                                This is also not only true of the tears, saliva, perspiration,
                                urine, &amp;c, but of the poisonous purulent accumulations in the
                                pustular eruptions. I have known alkalies administered medicinally,
                                with very unsatisfactory results to the physician, as well as the
                                patient, from the fact that their good tendencies were more than
                                counterbalanced by the acid wines given ostensibly to support the
                                patient, whose real effect, however, was to support the disease.
                                These remarks hold true in most of the exanthematous diseases, and a
                                treatment similar to what I have given for this disease I have used
                                with perfect success in the gravest cases of scarlatina.</p>
                    <p>The great secret is to exterminate the poison of the disease wherever
                                found, and for this purpose all the needed appliances of science and
                                art, together with every health-giving element of nature, should be
                                brought into service and made to perform its part; and the
                                persistent effort to save the life of the patient should not be
                                given up until every chance for life is absolutely lost. It is not
                                enough that the breathing grows difficult, the circulation of the
                                blood apparently ceasing, together with many other signs of
                                approaching dissolution. Multitudes have been saved in this, as in
                                other diseases, long after the pulse has ceased to give indications
                                of vital power. Never yield the fight with the enemy until the last
                                ray of hope is gone.</p>
                    <p>In closing, excuse me for remarking that the idea that a person
                                laboring under the distressing influence of small-pox should be
                                still further prostrated with debilitating medicines, condemned to
                                suffer in a dark close room filled with a pestilential atmosphere,
                                without ventilation, without change of clothing, without ever
                                cleaning the vile, fetid infections from the body, &amp;c, &amp;c,
                                is perfectly incomprehensible, and totally at variance with the
                                teachings of nature, science, and reason; and I am sure that when
                                the great benefits to be derived from an opposite treatment are
                                understood, no sane man will be found encouraging or tolerating such
                                unfortunate practice.</p>
                    <pb facs="0221" n="125" xml:id="pg_125"/>
                    <p>Hoping these thoughts, hastily penned, may excite in your minds,
                                already full laudable ambition, yet increased desires for useful and
                                practical knowledge, so soon to be made serviceable to your
                                fellow-men, I remain, gentlemen, your sincere friend.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>J. P. ROOT.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Messrs. <hi rend="smallcaps">Jacinto O. del Rio and Ernesto
                                        Turenne</hi>,</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
