<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1871-12-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1871-12-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="75" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d75">
                        <head>No. 75<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Low</persName>
                                to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                        the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-12-26"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 26,
                                    1871</date>. (Received February 27.)</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 116.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Several weeks since Mr. C. D. Williams, an
                            American merchant, visited Peking for the purpose of ascertaining if the
                            port of Kiungchow, on the island of Hainan, could be availed of as a
                            place for permanent residence and trade; if so, he proposed to establish
                            a business there without delay. He further informed me that arrangements
                            were about completed for placing a line of American steamers on the
                            route between Canton, Hong-Kong, and Kiungchow, in case the latter port
                            be opened. Mr. Williams brought with him letters from some of the
                            largest American houses in Shanghai and Hong-Kong, expressing a strong
                            desire that steps be taken immediately for the opening of that port
                            officially, also a dispatch from the consul-general warmly indorsing the
                            movement.</p>
                        <p>In the British and French treaties of 1858, and also that of Germany,
                            Kiungchow is among the ports named for foreign residence and trade.
                            Neither in the American nor Russian treaties is that port mentioned,
                            although legally the right inures to us as fully through the “favored
                            nation clause” as if the place was specially mentioned. I may add that
                            neither power had availed itself of the treaty-right referred to up to
                            1869, when the British minister agreed in the convention concluded
                            between himself and Prince Kung, to exchange Kiungchow for Wenchow, a
                            port on the coast between Ningpo and Foochow. That convention, as you
                            are aware, failed to receive the sanction of Her Majesty’s government.
                            In view of the circumstances above mentioned, and the possible
                            misconception of the Chinese government of the real status as it now is,
                            it seemed the better policy to enlist the other treaty powers in the
                            movement.</p>
                        <p>It seemed to me desirable that a declaration of all the governments
                            represented here, of their intention to avail themselves of this
                            treaty-right, be made simultaneously if possible. Such a combined
                            movement would be likely to prevent further correspondence or
                            discussion, and lead the government to make provision for the
                            accommodation of trade and the safety of those who go there to reside,
                            more speedily and effectively than if the demand were made by me alone.
                            Upon consulting my colleagues, I found them all willing to join in
                            making the declaration I desired.</p>
                        <p>On the 29th ultimo I sent an unofficial note to the foreign office,
                            informing the ministers that American merchants were desirous of opening
                            trade at Kiungchow, and saying that I should address myself to Prince
                            Kung, officially, upon the same subject soon. On the 23d instant I sent
                            a note to the prince, copy of which I have the honor to inclose. On the
                                <pb facs="0222" n="126" xml:id="pg_126"/> same day the
                            representatives of England, France, Germany, and Russia sent notes of
                            the same purport as mine.</p>
                        <p>No objection can legally or properly be made to our demand, and I
                            apprehend there will be no delay in the formal opening of the port. It
                            is of course impossible to say now how important the trade may become,
                            but until its value is demonstrated by experience, it would not, in my
                            opinion, be advisable to incur much expense in the way of a consular
                            establishment.</p>
                        <p>I have, therefore, to recommend that Kiungchow be attached to the
                            consular district of Canton, with a resident consular agent, to be named
                            by the consul at Canton. I have already instructed Mr. Jewell to assume
                            consular jurisdiction over Kiungchow until the pleasure of the
                            Department is made known.</p>
                        <p>Trusting that my action as herein detailed may meet your sanction, I
                            have, &amp;c,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>FREDERICK F. LOW.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Low</persName> to Prince
                                        <persName type="to">Kung</persName>.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi><lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-12-23"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 23, 1871</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>In pursuance of the intimation contained in my unofficial note of the
                                29th ultimo, I have now the honor to inform your imperial highness
                                that the Government of the United States proposes to avail itself of
                                the provision contained in the several treaties by which the port of
                                Kiungchow, on the Island of Hainan, is declared open to foreign
                                residence and trade, and I have, most respectfully, to request that
                                you will, without delay, issue the necessary orders to the
                                provincial officers within whose jurisdiction the before-mentioned
                                port is, and also instruct the inspector-general of customs to make
                                the necessary arrangements to meet the requirements of trade.</p>
                            <p>With assurances of my high consideration, I have the honor to be,
                                &amp;c,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>FREDERICK F. LOW.</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>