<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-02-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="2" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d2">
                        <head>2. Memorandum From Secretary of the Treasury <persName corresp="#p_KDM1" type="from">Kennedy</persName> to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d2fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Agency Files, Box
                                289, Treasury Volume I. Confidential. Forwarded to the President
                                under cover of a February 20 memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> reminding the President
                                that Treasury Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KDM1">Kennedy</persName> had already raised this issue with him and
                                he had indicated his assent. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> noted that both bills moved in the
                                “desired direction of channeling our foreign aid through
                                multilateral agencies” and warranted the President’s approval,
                                although action on the <gloss target="#t_ADB1">ADB</gloss> Special
                                Fund could be delayed until after the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> review (see <ref target="#d1">Document 1</ref>).
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KDM1">Kennedy</persName>’s memorandum was
                                returned to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> under
                                cover of a March 3 memorandum from Kenneth Cole indicating the
                                President had approved the <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss>
                                proposal and was not opposed to the <gloss target="#t_ADB1">ADB</gloss> proposal but thought a firm commitment at that time
                                would be premature. (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials Project, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Agency Files, Box 289,
                                Treasury Volume I) <persName corresp="#p_BCF1">Bergsten</persName>
                                informed Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KDM1">Kennedy</persName>’s
                                office of the President’s decision on March 3. (Ibid.)</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1969-02-20">February 20, 1969</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The House Banking and Currency and the Senate Foreign Relations
                            Committees are asking my view on last year’s unfinished business of
                            authorizing U.S. participation in an internationally negotiated package
                            for the second replenishment of the International Development
                            Association. <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss> was established as a
                            World Bank affiliate for lending on concessionary repayment terms
                            following the initiative of then Secretary of the Treasury Robert
                            Anderson under President Eisenhower’s leadership. The pending
                            legislation author-izes our participation with a 40 percent share of the
                            total. We would provide $160 million in each of three years, starting in
                                <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1969. I believe it should have
                            this Administration’s strong and early support. The Secretary of State
                            concurs in this view.</p>
                        <p>It would be helpful if I could know of your support for this legislation
                            before your European trip<note n="2" xml:id="d2fn2">President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> traveled to Europe February
                                22-March 2.</note> so that I might be in a position to testify
                            positively should the House Banking and Currency Committee call a
                            hearing next week as they now seem to contemplate.<note n="3" xml:id="d2fn3">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KDM1">Kennedy</persName> testified before the House Committee on
                                Banking and Currency regarding <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss>
                                replenishment on March 4. His remarks are in <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the Secretary of the Treasury on the State of
                                    the Finances for the Fiscal Year Ended June 30, 1969</hi>
                                (Washington: Government Printing Office, 1969), pp. 315-317.</note>
                            I do not recommend any other specific action on this by you at this
                            time, but will inform you of any further actions that might be necessary
                            as legislative consideration progresses. I should add that all the
                            European countries you will be visiting approved the <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss> replenishment agreement last year, and
                            a number of them have made advance contributions to this replenishment
                            pending our action.</p>
                        <pb facs="0030" n="4" xml:id="pg_4"/>
                        <p>In addition to responding to a request for hearings, there are a number
                            of advantages to my taking early action to urge Congressional approval
                            of the <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss> replenishment. First, it will
                            demonstrate this Administration’s support for the multilateral approach.
                            It will concentrate this support on legislation that has a reasonable
                            chance of passage, where the previous Administration did not succeed in
                            securing approval. Second, it would help return bargaining power to the
                            U.S. vis-a-vis Europe for such multilateral endeavors, a position which
                            was eroded by last year’s failure to obtain U.S. ratification. Finally,
                            while it will not be easy, there is at least a fair chance to obtain
                            legislative action before foreign aid and other major issues divert
                            Congressional attention.</p>
                        <p>A sufficient number of other contributors to <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss> have completed their actions to make the international
                            agreement on the <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss> second
                            replenishment effective as of the date the United States acts. Unless we
                            do act the agreement cannot become effective. While the amount of each
                            country’s contribution is increased over the last replenishment, our
                            share of <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss> has been reduced from 43
                            percent when it was established to 40 percent in the current proposal.
                            This compares with about a 60 percent share of world-wide bilateral
                            assistance. The agreement provides for specific protection of the U.S.
                            balance of payments by providing for others to accelerate their actual
                            payments through <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1971 should the U.S.
                            balance of payments require it. While President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>’s budget makes provisions for
                            this contribution, the actual additional budgetary costs will be
                            substantially below the three annual contributions of $160 million each
                            we would make in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1969, 1970 and 1971.
                            We can be reasonably assured that <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss>
                            funds will be used effectively because <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss> is administered by the World Bank, and we know that the
                            funds are needed urgently because <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss>’s
                            existing resources are almost fully committed.</p>
                        <p>I would also hope to be in a position to indicate our support for a U.S.
                            contribution to the Asian Bank Special Funds. A U.S. contribution of
                            $200 million over a four-year period was recommended by the last
                            Administration, particularly on the advice of Eugene Black. While there
                            is not an internationally negotiated package, the legislative proposal
                            would limit our contribution to a minority share and to pay for U.S.
                            goods and services only. President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>’s budget provided for $25 million in each of the
                            first two years. Authorizing legislation did not get as far in the
                            Senate legislative process as the <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss>
                            proposal, but it is a worthwhile multilateral endeavor. Among other
                            donors, the Japanese and Canadians have shown a tangible interest by
                            unilaterally pledging contributions, but the major Europeans have been
                            slow in coming forward. I would prefer to deal only with <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss>
                            <pb facs="0031" n="5" xml:id="pg_5"/> legislatively at the outset, and
                            then deal with the Asian Bank specifically, as soon as <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss> is adequately on the legislative
                            track.</p>
                        <p>If you agree with the above, I will proceed accordingly.<note n="4" xml:id="d2fn4">President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> initialed his approval.</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_KDM1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">David M. Kennedy</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>