<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>352. Memorandum for the President’s File by the President’s Deputy Assistant
                    for National Security Affairs (Haig))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d352</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">352</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-12-07T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-12-07T16:15:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic affairs</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062603"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Housing</term>
                    <term ref="recXOpgZpMOhBqvrd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88006884"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Consumer goods</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85065851"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Industrial development</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="rec5leqjXNtlx0kjy" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="outer-space">Space cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="south-and-central-asia" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="south-and-central-asia">South Asia</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-12-07T16:15:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-12-07T15:00:00-05:00" n="352"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d352">
                <head>352. Memorandum for the President’s File by the President’s Deputy Assistant
                    for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1"
                        >Haig</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d352fn1">Source: National
                        Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                        Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Agency Files, Box 213,
                        Commerce, Volume II 1971. Confidential. The meeting lasted from 3:12 to 4:15
                        p.m. and included a brief press opportunity. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> and Ziegler were also present during the closing
                        minutes of the meeting. (Ibid., White House Central Files, President’s Daily
                        Diary) A December 6 memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_SHH1"
                            >Sonnenfeldt</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> transmitted a briefing paper and talking points
                        for the President’s use in his meeting with <persName corresp="#p_SMH3"
                            >Stans</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_SHH1">Sonnenfeldt</persName>
                        called <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s attention to the
                        section of the talking points urging the President to restrain <persName
                            corresp="#p_SMH3">Stans</persName>’ optimism. A stamp on <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s December 7 memorandum to the
                        President indicates the President saw it.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1971-12-07T15:00:00-05:00" to="1971-12-07T16:15:00-05:00"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date">undated</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Meeting with Secretary of Commerce Maurice H. Stans, on Tuesday, December
                        7, 1971, at 3:00 p.m., in the Oval Office</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The President</item>
                    <item>Maurice H. Stans, Secretary of Commerce</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_PPG1">Peter G. Peterson</persName>, Assistant to the
                        President for International Economic Affairs</item>
                    <item>B/Gen. <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Alexander M. Haig, Jr.</persName>,
                        Deputy Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0914" n="888" xml:id="pg_888"/>
                <p>The President met with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SMH3">Stans</persName> to
                    hear the Secretary’s report on his just-completed visit to the Soviet Union and
                    Poland.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SMH3">Stans</persName>, summarizing his written
                    report, told the President that he had gone to the Soviet Union with the
                    objective of establishing working groups to develop in more detail the means and
                    forms of cooperation with the USSR on trade. His complete report would be
                    forwarded to the President through Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PPG1"
                        >Peterson</persName>,<note n="2" xml:id="d352fn2">No written report on
                            <persName corresp="#p_SMH3">Stans</persName>’ visit to the Soviet Union
                        was found. On February 2, 1972, <persName corresp="#p_SMH3">Stans</persName>
                        sent <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> a copy of a report he
                        had submitted to the Secretary of State on his December 1-3, 1971, visit to
                        Poland. (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Agency Files, Box
                        214, Commerce, Volume III January-June, 1971)</note> but he wished to touch
                    upon the following highlights: <list>
                        <item>—The Soviets anticipate $2 billion of trade with the United States by
                            1975, and the Polish government anticipates $300 million in the same
                            timeframe.</item>
                        <item>—The Soviets hope to complete a five-year grain arrangement with the
                            United States.</item>
                        <item>—The Secretary highlighted the following impressions of the Soviet
                            economy: (1) a critical shortage of housing; (2) a few shortages of
                            consumer goods; (3) a general impression that the Soviets were a
                            generation behind the United States in industrial advances; (4) a
                            distinct inferiority complex among the Soviet leaders with respect to
                            their industrial development; (5) a Soviet compulsion to play the
                            big-company game in their future industrial development; (6) a distinct
                            “Avis” attitude in the Soviet demeanor.</item>
                        <item>—The Soviets are especially interested in achieving
                            Most-Favored-Nation status with the United States. They are also
                            interested in additional credits, relaxation of export controls,
                            completion of the trade agreement with the United States, and an
                            agreement for scientific and technological cooperation and space
                            cooperation.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary commented at some length on his discussions with Kosygin, whom he
                    described as an intelligent, cordial, and extremely capable bureaucrat. The
                    Secretary emphasized the importance of export-import credits for the Soviet
                    Union, as a means of greatly enhancing our ability to expand US-Soviet
                    trade.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> thanked Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_SMH3">Stans</persName> for his interesting report and
                    for undertaking his trade mission to the USSR. He pointed out to the Secretary
                    that it was essential that the U.S. attitude with respect to increasing trade
                    with the Soviet Union be governed completely by the state of our political
                    relations. The increasing tensions in South Asia would be an important factor in
                    this respect. He instructed Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SMH3"
                        >Stans</persName> to provide to General <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1"
                        >Haig</persName> a copy of the proposed talking points which the Secretary
                    would be using in a <pb facs="0915" n="889" xml:id="pg_889"/> press conference
                    in the near future covering his impressions of his trip.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d352fn3">On December 7 <persName corresp="#p_SMH3">Stans</persName>
                        sent <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> a memorandum to which he
                        attached the 37-page transcript of his December 6 U.S. News and World Report
                        interview, which he said was indicative of the approach he would take. He
                        would avoid any discussion of political relations, estimates of potential
                        dollar amounts of trade that might materialize, and compliments to the
                        Soviet Government other than for the hospitality accorded him and his party.
                            <persName corresp="#p_SMH3">Stans</persName> indicated he would feel
                        free to discuss specific interests of the two countries, including the
                        Soviet interest in MFN treatment and the relaxation of other American
                        discriminations. Among the points in <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1"
                            >Haig</persName>’s December 8 reply was an admonition against accepting
                        the Soviet “discrimination” term (see <ref target="#d349">Document
                        349</ref>). <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> noted that “what is
                        involved are measures undertaken in the political circumstances of the past
                        which can be revised as these circumstances change.” <persName
                            corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> continued: “in discussing MFN and
                        Government credit facilities, it should be made clear that these matters
                        must be considered by the President in light of a whole range of factors,
                        including political ones. You should not say anything that creates a
                        presumption of early Presidential decisions or initiatives in these
                        matters.” (National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Agency Files, Box 213, Commerce,
                        Volume II 1971)</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary noted that he had already given an interview to <hi rend="italic"
                        >U.S. News and World Report</hi>. The President instructed General <persName
                        corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> to get a copy of the transcript to insure
                    that it was consistent with the current state of political relations between the
                    two countries.<note n="4" xml:id="d352fn4">An undated note by John Scali on top
                        of his copy of the transcript of <persName corresp="#p_SMH3"
                            >Stans</persName>’ interview reads: “General <persName
                            corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName>: It seems to me that <persName
                            corresp="#p_SMH3">Stans</persName> discloses almost everything that the
                        Russians asked for and thus builds up public pressure for acceptance of
                        their positions. I seriously question whether he should in this interview be
                        permitted to spill all of this. I have outlined the sections that I have the
                        most serious questions about but undoubtedly Hal can find even more. I would
                        strongly recommend that we get him to knock out these areas and if U.S. News
                        and World Report objects, tell them to knock out the interview completely.”
                        (Ibid.) On December 8 <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> sent
                            <persName corresp="#p_SMH3">Stans</persName> a memorandum to which he
                        attached recommended modifications in the interview. (Ibid.) <persName
                            corresp="#p_SMH3">Stans</persName>’ interview is in the December 20,
                        1971, issue of U.S. News and World Report, pp. 56-63.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The President again thanked the Secretary for his interesting report, and the
                    meeting concluded.<note n="5" xml:id="d352fn5">Documentation on the discussions
                        leading up to, during, and after the U.S.-Soviet Summit held May 22-30,
                        1972, in Moscow, at which President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                            >Nixon</persName> and General Secretary Brezhnev considered a wide range
                        of economic issues, is scheduled for publication in Foreign Relations,
                        1969–1976, Moscow Summit, 1971-1972.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
