<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-08-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-08-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="362" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d362">
                        <head>362. Information Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_SHH1" type="from">Helmut Sonnenfeldt</persName> of the National Security
                            Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                                (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d362fn1">Source: National Archives,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                                Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Country
                                Files-Europe, Box 675, France, Volume III Jan 69-10/31/69. Secret;
                                Limdis.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1969-08-20">August 20, 1969</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Conversation with French Charge—Transistor Deal with Poland;
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SM2">Schumann</persName> visit; <persName corresp="#p_PG5">Pompidou</persName> visit</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Minister came in under instructions to follow up on Foreign Minister
                                <persName corresp="#p_SM2">Schumann</persName>’s conversation with
                            you in Paris on the proposed French transistor deal with Poland.<note n="2" xml:id="d362fn2">See <ref target="#d360">Document 360</ref>
                                and <ref target="#d360fn2">footnote 2</ref> thereto.</note> He said
                            the French had no intention to bypass <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss>. In their view the equipment was not so sophisticated
                            that the Soviets or East Europeans, not to mention some West Europeans,
                            could not furnish it to the Poles. Siemens, for example, was sending a
                            team to Poland in mid-September. (I interjected that the Germans were
                            also subject to <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> but Leprette
                            said they might be “more clever” in getting around it.) In the French
                            view, if the West loses the contract the Poles would be dependent on the
                            Soviets when it was in our interest to divert such Polish dependence.
                            (These are all old points.)</p>
                        <p>Leprette then read from his instructions to provide certain technical
                            data and to suggest that French technicians should come here to discuss
                            the matter with us. (Text attached.)<note n="3" xml:id="d362fn3">Not
                                printed. The one-page text, in French, indicated that Thomson-CSF
                                was prepared to send representatives to Washington.</note> He said
                            the matter was urgent because the French wanted to settle the matter
                            before the formal <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> meeting in
                            September.</p>
                        <p>I noted that as a result of your conversation with <persName corresp="#p_SM2">Schumann</persName>, Ambassador Shriver had been
                            instructed to suggest technical exchanges before the <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> meeting;<note n="4" xml:id="d362fn4">See <ref target="#d360fn5">footnote 5, Document
                                    360</ref>.</note> Leprette said he heard nothing of any such
                            demarche. (We have seen nothing either and <persName corresp="#p_BCF1">Fred Bergsten</persName> is checking.) Leprette asked what our
                            substantive position was and I said I did not have any information; our
                            first order of business had been to clear up the matter of getting the
                            technical information.</p>
                        <p>Leprette said <persName corresp="#p_SM2">Schumann</persName> planned to
                            be in Washington on September 25, following his <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> speech and he asked about the possibilities of an
                            appointment with the President. I said I would check and <pb facs="0938" n="912" xml:id="pg_912"/> recalled that you had also expressed an
                            interest in seeing the Foreign Minister.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Perhaps you would like to set up an
                            appointment on your calendar for September 25 and then take <persName corresp="#p_SM2">Schumann</persName> up the back steps to see the
                                President.<note n="5" xml:id="d362fn5">On August 27 <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> initialed his approval
                                for an appointment in the margin next to this sentence. There is no
                                indication in the Daily Diary that <persName corresp="#p_SM2">Schumann</persName> met with the President on September 25.
                                (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                                Presidential Materials, White House Central Files)</note> If we make
                            a public, formal appointment it will of course be much harder to turn
                            down requests from other Foreign Ministers. (We already have one from
                            the Belgian, and there is talk that Gromyko wants to come down. Manescu
                            also has expectations; and Stewart will be hard to ward off.)</p>
                        <p>On the <persName corresp="#p_PG5">Pompidou</persName> visit, I said we
                            still had no firm date but were working on it.<note n="6" xml:id="d362fn6">President <persName corresp="#p_PG5">Pompidou</persName> visited the United States in February
                                1970.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> We ought to get off the dime.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>