<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>425. Action Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Kissinger) to President ) to President Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d425</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">425</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-02-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-02-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="425"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d425">
                <head>425. Action Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>) to
                    President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d425fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Subject Files, Box 351, Meat Import
                        Policy. No classification marking.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-02-20">February 20, 1970</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Executive Order to Stop Indirect U.S. Imports of Meat from Australia, New
                        Zealand and Ireland</item>
                </list>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HCM1">Hardin</persName> at Tab B<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d425fn2">None of the tabs has been found.</note> has proposed an
                    Executive Order prohibiting U.S. imports of Irish, Australian and New Zealand
                    beef and mutton which have been shipped via third countries. Budget has approved
                    the Order and State, Treasury, Commerce, the Council of Economic Advisers, and
                    the Special Trade Representative concur (Tab C). The Department of Justice has
                    certified that the Order is correct as to form and legality (Tab D). <persName
                        corresp="#p_FPM1">Peter Flanigan</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_WJC1"
                        >John Whitaker</persName>, and Bill Timmons also concur.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Background</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The State Department, in cooperation with Agriculture, has nearly completed
                    negotiations with the principal exporting countries for a voluntary restraint
                    program on meat exports to the United States for 1970. Under most of these
                    agreements, the exporting country will restrain its total shipments of meat to
                    the United States whether they are sent directly or whether they are
                    transshipped through third countries.</p>
                <p>Three nations, however, (Australia, New Zealand and Ireland) informed us that
                    they would be able to control only the direct shipments to the United States.
                    They would not be able to control meat which they had originally sent to Canada
                    and which might then be transshipped to the United States. These Canadian
                    transshipments began to assume importance at the end of 1969 as the supplying
                    nations reached their voluntary restraint limits and private traders took
                    advantage of the Canadian loophole to get the highest possible (U.S.) prices for
                    their beef. (Canada does not participate in the restraint program.)</p>
                <p>For the 1970 program, the three countries have agreed to control by the United
                    States Government, since they cannot control the indirect shipments
                        themselves.<note n="3" xml:id="d425fn3">See also <ref target="#d423"
                            >Document 423</ref>.</note> This Order will accomplish such control.</p>
                <pb facs="1073" n="1047" xml:id="pg_1047"/>
                <p>Based on the voluntary restraint program, the Secretary of Agriculture has
                    estimated that 1970 meat imports will total 1,063 million pounds. Transshipments
                    would be additional, and there is less than a four percent margin for error
                    between the Secretary’s estimates and the point at which the Meat Import Act
                    would trigger import quotas. Continued transshipments could thus be sufficient
                    to trigger the quotas or, if their magnitude is revealed only by subsequent
                    figures, give the impression that the Secretary had knowingly made a false
                    estimate. The Agriculture Department estimates that 6 million pounds of
                    transshipped meat have already entered the United States this year.
                    Consequently, it is necessary to stop this traffic as soon as possible in order
                    to be sure that we can preserve the voluntary meat restraint program. The
                    Executive Order has been coordinated with Jim Keogh.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>That you sign the Executive Order at Tab A prohibiting indirect U.S. imports of
                    meat from Australia, New Zealand, and Ireland.<note n="4" xml:id="d425fn4">The
                        President did not initial either the Approve or Disapprove option but wrote
                        below: “no—Not until meat prices come down.”</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
