<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>44. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Kissinger) to President ) to President Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d44</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">44</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-12-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-12-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBS0IqgpfGXNR4a" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048310"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">International Financial Institutions</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-12-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-12-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="44"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d44">
                <head>44. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>) to President
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d44fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Agency Files, Box 289, Treasury,
                        Volume I. No classification marking. A stamped notation on the memorandum
                        reads, “The President has seen.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-12-15">December 15, 1970</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Need for Your Intervention on International Financial Institutions
                        Legislation</item>
                </list>
                <p>Our International Financial Institutions Bill (<gloss target="#t_IFI1"
                        >IFI</gloss>) is in deep trouble, and Treasury recommends (Tab B)<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d44fn2">
                        <ref target="#d43">Document 43</ref>.</note> that your personal intervention
                    is needed to make its passage possible during this session. Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> endorses <persName corresp="#p_WCE1"
                        >Walker</persName>’s recommendation (Tab C).<note n="3" xml:id="d44fn3">Not
                        printed; see <ref target="#d43fn1">footnote 1, Document 43</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_IFI1">IFI</gloss> bill includes authorizations for
                    continued US participation in the Inter-American Bank and the Asian Development
                    Bank. It also provides for our share in the expansion of the International
                    Monetary Fund and the World Bank.</p>
                <pb facs="0131" n="105" xml:id="pg_105"/>
                <p>Senator Gore is using this legislation as the vehicle for his swan song vendetta
                    against the Administration. The bill will pass easily if brought to a vote on
                    the Senate floor, but Gore has succeeded twice in talking it off the calendar.
                    It appears that only your strong personal intervention may be sufficient to
                    induce Senator Mansfield to shut off Gore, with long sessions, persuasion, and a
                    cloture vote if necessary.</p>
                <p>The bill is crucial to our foreign policy in several respects, and I therefore
                    urge you to intervene with Mansfield: <list>
                        <item>—The sharp increase in our Inter-American Development Bank
                            contribution is the most important concrete demonstration of our deep
                            interest in development in Latin America and is regarded by the Latins
                            as our major contribution to the new “mature partnership” with them. It
                            is particularly crucial now as we attempt to prevent Chile from
                            mobilizing hemispheric support against us.</item>
                        <item>—The Asian Development Bank is the only concrete evidence of our
                            interest in supporting Asian regionalism.</item>
                        <item>—The <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> quota increase must be passed
                            if we are to get our proportional share of the next allocation of
                            Special Drawing Rights. Failure of this legislation would cause us to
                            lose $130 million in essentially free international reserves.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The authorization bill has already passed the House. Senate author-ization is
                    needed now if the appropriations are to be available early next year, when they
                    are needed.</p>
                <p>More important, postponement into next year may delay the authorization
                    significantly because the committee may then wait to see your whole new aid
                    proposal before voting on it. In addition, early next year we must submit
                    legislation authorizing our share in the doubling of the resources of the
                    International Development Association, the soft-loan window of the World Bank,
                    which is the most important single component of our multilateral aid theme.
                    Linking that proposal with the other <gloss target="#t_IFI1">IFI</gloss>s would
                    present such a large sum of money that the Congress might balk. If we don’t get
                    this legislation now, it will thus probably be much harder to get the larger
                    package next session.</p>
                <p>It would be tragic to let a single lame duck Senator stop legislation which
                    constitutes a major element of your foreign policy. Senator Mansfield, however,
                    has so far been very reluctant to stand firm against Gore. It is not certain
                    that your intervention would succeed in getting him to do so, but it seems that
                    nothing else has a chance.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>That you call Senator Mansfield urgently to try to persuade him to bring the
                        <gloss target="#t_IFI1">IFI</gloss> bill to an early vote on the Senate
                    floor, using the talking points at Tab A. State and Treasury strongly support
                    your making such <pb facs="0132" n="106" xml:id="pg_106"/> a call. Bill Timmons
                    opposes, on the grounds that Ken BeLieu has already spoken to Mansfield about
                    the issue three times and that a further call is unlikely to change the
                    situation, in view of the availability to Gore of further delaying tactics.<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d44fn4">The President wrote “no” below the last paragraph. No
                        additional documentation on this legislation was found but a compromise
                        apparently was reached and the impasse broken. According to the President’s
                        signing statement on December 31, the soft loan funds for the Asian
                        Development Bank were dropped from the legislation and only a down-payment
                        was authorized for the Fund for Special Operations in the Inter-American
                        Development Bank. The President promised legislation to restore his requests
                        early in the new Congress. See <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the
                            Presidents of the United States: <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Richard
                                Nixon</persName>, 1970</hi>, pp. 1164-1165. That request was sent to
                        Congress on January 26, 1971; see ibid., 1971, p. 72.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
