<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-11-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="73" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d73">
                        <head>73. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RWP1" type="from">Rogers</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d73fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Subject Files, Box
                                323, Foreign Aid, Volume I 7/70-1971. Secret. A handwritten note by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> reads “HAK—our
                                friend explaineth all!” This Evening Report was included in the
                                President’s morning briefing material on November 4. (Ibid.,
                                President’s Daily Briefings, Boxes 1-61) During late 1971, in the
                                run-up to final Congressional action on the foreign assistance
                                authorizing legislation and a continuing resolution on December 17
                                (see <ref target="#d78">Document 78</ref>), the Evening Reports were
                                included more frequently in the morning briefing material because
                                they included reporting on legislative progress.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-11-03">November 3, 1971</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center">Evening Report</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is item 1 on the prospective visit of the First Lady to
                            Liberia for President Tolbert’s inauguration.]</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Senate Foreign Relations Committee—Foreign
                            Aid</hi>—Dr. <persName corresp="#p_HJA1">Hannah</persName> and I
                            appeared this morning for two hours before the full membership of the
                            Senate Foreign Relations Committee at their invitation to discuss the
                            future of foreign assistance. I think the discussion was useful.</p>
                        <p>We were able to avoid any discussions of a piecemeal program of foreign
                            assistance. In large part this was due to the Chairman’s and other
                            members’ efforts to focus attention on Southeast Asian policy.</p>
                        <p>In addition the discussion also gave me a chance to reassert the
                            Administration’s strong belief that a reduced program was not in the
                            national interest. A number of Senators, including <persName corresp="#p_CRN1">Cooper</persName>, Aiken, Spong and McGee, stated
                            their view that reductions in program levels below the 20% cut levied by
                            the Foreign Relations Committee on the last bill were possible ways of
                            achieving a compromise. I was able to make clear that the figure
                            reported out by the House ($3.2 billion) for the whole program was a
                            figure which the Administration felt it was necessary to have.</p>
                        <p>Similarly, on the question of restrictive amendments, through the
                            extensive discussions of Southeast Asia we made clear that amendments
                            which constricted or restrained Presidentially-proposed programs would
                            not be acceptable. Senator Symington in particular asked about his
                            compromise with Senator Stennis on providing a $341 million ceiling for
                            the Cambodian program, revised upward from the $250 million proposed by
                            the Committee. I indicated, following the Laos ceiling pattern in the
                            Defense Procurement Program, that a ceiling which provided for your full
                            program would be acceptable. As you know, Symington on the floor
                            re-endorsed on Thursday, October 28, your <pb facs="0199" n="173" xml:id="pg_173"/> receiving the full authorization and appropriation
                            for Cambodia. The essence of the compromise was that we are willing, in
                            return for getting the full money required, to accept the idea of later
                            going back to the Congress should additional funds be required. In any
                            event this is quite close to the situation as it existed in last year’s
                            Foreign Assistance Act where any additions to the Cambodia program would
                            be subject to 30 day Congressional notice. On the question of ceilings,
                            I took the opportunity to clear up for the Committee the mistaken
                            impression they had that the Administration would not respect a ceiling
                            and believed that Congress did not have the right to impose one. I
                            indicated that in our view ceilings were not advisable, but that
                            Congress had the right, should it wish to do so, to impose them.</p>
                        <p>Senator Case indicated strong concern over our involvement in Cambodia
                            and stated that in his view acceptance of the <persName corresp="#p_CRN1">Cooper</persName>-Church Amendment would be the
                            price for the passage of the bill. Senator <persName corresp="#p_CRN1">Cooper</persName> did not appear to endorse this view. Senator
                            Javits asked for a commitment that no U.S. ground or air forces would be
                            engaged for the next year in Cambodia or Laos and an “assurance” that we
                            would not be going down the same road as in Vietnam in those two
                            countries. I told Javits that we had already made clear that our ground
                            combat forces would not be involved in Cambodia or Laos, but that our
                            air power had an important interdiction role to play in both
                            countries.</p>
                        <p>I was asked about the Administration’s views on foreign aid reform. I
                            replied that after long study involving the <persName corresp="#p_PPG1">Peterson</persName> Task Force, the Administration had submitted
                            its own reform legislation.<note n="2" xml:id="d73fn2">The legislation
                                was submitted on April 21, 1971; see <ref target="#d60">Document
                                    60</ref>.</note> The Senate Foreign Relations Committee had held
                            no hearings on that legislation. I said that the Administration was
                            ready to cooperate in having hearings in order to have the President’s
                            new program receive full consideration in the Senate. We had in the
                            interim accepted the House judgment that a move to a new approach this
                            year would not be possible, and that is the reason why the
                            Administration, and we assume the Committee, had previously accepted the
                            House proposed bill.</p>
                        <p>Senator Symington during the course of discussion left the room and then
                            returned to say that the Conference on the Defense Procurement bill was
                            now agreed on money amounts. What remained to be settled was strong
                            House opposition to the Mansfield Amendment (on Indo-China). He asked if
                            the Administration was going to continue to oppose the Mansfield
                            Amendment and what would be the fate of an aid bill with the Mansfield
                            Amendment attached. I replied that we are strongly opposed to this
                            Amendment and had made that position clear to the Congress.</p>
                        <pb facs="0200" n="174" xml:id="pg_174"/>
                        <p>In sum, among the members of the Committee who spoke, Church and Spong
                            appeared to endorse the Fulbright-Mansfield-Symington strong opposition
                            to the present aid bill. Among the others who spoke there was support in
                            one degree or another for most of our development and humanitarian
                            programs and acceptance of the necessity for some security and military
                            programs. I believe this group may support a Continuing Resolution
                            Authority for foreign assistance to get us past the present November 15
                            deadline.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName>
                                    <hi rend="strong">David Passage</hi>
                                </persName><note n="3" xml:id="d73fn3">Passage signed for Secretary
                                        <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> above
                                        <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>’ typed
                                    signature.</note>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>