<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Briefing Book Paper</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945Malta</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d103</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">103</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-01-23T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-01-29T22:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="elections" subject="elections" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557" lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-01-29T22:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-01-23T23:00:00-05:00" n="103" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d103">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Executive Secretariat Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Briefing Book Paper</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1945-01-29T23:59:59-04:00" notBefore="1945-01-24T00:00:00-04:00">undated</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[<hi rend="smallcaps">Liberated Countries</hi>]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: The necessity of the three principal Allies arriving at
                    a common political program for liberated countries.</p>
                <p>Although the principal Allies have been able to work out a generally satisfactory
                    coordination of military strategy and operations in the prosecution of the war
                    against Germany, there has been no such coordination in regard to political
                    policies. Recent events in Europe have demonstrated the very real danger not
                    only to Allied unity during the war but to the hope of a stable peace, as a
                    result of the failure of the Allies to evolve an agreed and mutually acceptable
                    political program.</p>
                <p>Growing evidence of Anglo-Soviet rivalry on the continent of Europe and the
                    resulting power politics scramble for position is due less to the difficulties
                    over territorial questions than to the question of the political character of
                    the governments in various countries of Europe beyond the Soviet borders. On the
                    one hand, it is evident that the Soviet Government suspects that Great Britain
                    desires to see installed wherever possible right-wing governments which from the
                    Soviet point of view would be hostile to the Soviet Union. On the other hand,
                    the British view with apprehension the possibility that the Soviet Government
                    will endeavor in its turn to install and support left-wing totalitarian
                    governments as far west as possible in Europe.</p>
                <p>In actual fact these mutual suspicions appear to be unjustified in that it is not
                    a fixed and calculated British policy to support right-wing elements in Europe,
                    nor on the basis of existing evidence can it be said that the Soviet Government
                    is determined to install Communist regimes throughout Europe. However, these
                    interacting mutual suspicions tend to push British policy, in action, farther to
                    the right and Soviet policy farther to the left. Recent events in Greece will
                    undoubtedly be widely interpreted in Moscow as confirmation of their suspicions
                    of Great Britain’s intentions, and the recent events in Poland with the
                    formation of the Lublin Committee into a provisional government will likewise
                    confirm British fears in regard to Soviet policy.</p>
                <p>If the situation is to be saved it is essential for the three principal Allies to
                    examine carefully the present political forces at work in the <pb facs="0185" n="103" xml:id="pg_103"/> liberated countries in Europe in order to
                    ascertain if there are not political groups and parties which would be mutually
                    acceptable and to which all three countries could give whole-hearted support. It
                    would be necessary to start by excluding either a right-wing government in which
                    “reactionary” elements regarded by the Soviet Government as intrinsically
                    hostile would predominate, or a single party Communist totalitarian state.
                    Between these two extremes, however, lies the bulk of the political sentiment of
                    the peoples of Europe.</p>
                <p>Judging from present indications the general mood of the people of Europe is to
                    the left and strongly in favor of far-reaching economic and social reforms, but
                    not, however, in favor of a left-wing totalitarian regime to achieve these
                    reforms. Until such time as it is possible to hold genuine elections in the
                    liberated areas, in certain countries at least, such as Greece and Poland, it
                    will probably be necessary for the principal Allies, and for this purpose France
                    should be included in that category, to accept and support interim governments.
                    The character and composition of these governments is precisely the place where
                    the Allies must have an agreed political program. These governments must be
                    sufficiently to the left to satisfy the prevailing mood in Europe and to allay
                    Soviet suspicions. Conversely, they should be sufficiently representative of the
                    center and <hi rend="italic">petit bourgeois</hi> elements of the population so
                    that they would not be regarded as mere preludes to a Communist
                    dictatorship.</p>
                <p>In so far as the United States is concerned, the following two criteria could be
                    applied to any proposed interim government: (1) that it should be dedicated to
                    the preservation of civil liberties; (2) that it should favor social and
                    economic reforms.</p>
                <p>In order to work out with its Allies for the interim period an agreed, mutually
                    acceptable political basis for coordinated policies, the United States
                    Government should be prepared, when the internal condition of a liberated
                    country so demands, to participate in inter-Allied commissions to act as
                    observers and to insure that at the proper time the people of that country will
                    be given a genuine opportunity to elect their future government.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
