<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        British Ambassador (
                        Halifax
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945Malta</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d186</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">186</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1944-12-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-12-07T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec9429801e8b840d1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="lend-lease">Lend-Lease</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-12-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-12-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="186" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d186">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.0146/12–744</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        British Ambassador</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_H1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Halifax</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-12-07">December 7,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Lord <persName corresp="#p_H1">Halifax</persName>
                    </hi>: <persName corresp="#p_WM1">Michael Wright</persName> will tell you of our
                    talk yesterday. I am sure you know that it is a source of deep personal regret
                    to me that any differences between our two countries should have arisen during
                    my first few days in office. I am sending you a <pb facs="0358" n="272" xml:id="pg_272"/> copy of a personal private message which I sent Anthony
                    last night in reply to his message to me. It expresses my concern and I have
                    endeavored to stress therein the importance I attach to maintaining the closest
                    and most friendly personal relationship.</p>
                <p>I am sure you know how much I value your friendship; as long as we can talk
                    things out freely and frankly with each other at all times, there can be no
                    serious differences between us.</p>
                <p>With assurances of my respect and esteem,</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">E. R. <hi rend="smallcaps">Stettinius,
                            Jr</hi>.</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Attachment]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            British Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_EA1" type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Eden</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-12-06">December 6,
                                1944</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>“Your personal message was read to me this afternoon and I wish to let you
                        know without delay that it is a source of deep regret to me that so soon
                        after taking office a difference should have arisen between us. I have
                        always worked so closely with you and my British friends, both as Lend-Lease
                        Administrator before coming into the State Department and more particularly
                        since I have been here. We must keep up the close and intimate association
                        which has always been so helpful in getting over even points of difficult
                        discussion in dealing with our respective countries’ interests. I count
                        upon, as one of my greatest supports in the tasks ahead, your close
                        friendship. I know, and you must feel, that anything which we put up to each
                        other for cooperative working out can be solved to the entire satisfaction
                        of both our responsibilities. Let us resolve that we will see that
                        everything of any importance comes right up to the two of us for
                        approval.</p>
                    <p>If the reaffirmation of our policy with regard to Italy has caused you
                        embarrassment I am truly sorry. The feeling is such in this country,
                        however, and the inquiries from all quarters so pressing, following your
                        public statement in the House of Commons, that we had no other choice than
                        to make clear our position. I am sure that had there been prior consultation
                        we could have worked the matter out together as we have done in the past
                        and, I feel sure, we will be able to do in the future. <persName corresp="#p_WM1">Michael Wright</persName> has told me of the debate on
                        Greece which has been set for Friday and which you anticipate will cause the
                        Prime Minister and you some embarrassment. We are working up a friendly
                        statement to be given out tomorrow which I sincerely hope will be
                            helpful.”<note n="1" xml:id="d186fn1">This message was sent to the
                            Embassy in London in the Department’s telegram No. 10226, dated December
                            6, 1944, for delivery to <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>; and
                            a copy was sent to the President on December 10 (865.01/12–44). The text
                            of the “friendly statement” made by <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> at his press conference on December 7 is
                            printed <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_433">p.
                            433</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
