<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Prime Minister Churchill to President Roosevelt
                    
                    Sent by the United States Military Attaché, London,
                        via Army channels.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945Malta</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d195</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">195</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1944-11-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-11-16T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-11-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-11-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="195" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d195">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Roosevelt Papers: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CWS1" type="from">Churchill</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1" type="to">Roosevelt</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d195fn1">Sent by the United States Military Attaché, London,
                        via Army channels.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-11-16">16 November
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Prime Minister to President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName>.
                    Personal and Top Secret. Number 822.<note n="2" xml:id="d195fn2">Paragraph 2 of
                        this telegram is printed <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_15">p. 15</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">· · · · · · · · · · · · · ·</p>
                <p>3. Thank you for your kind wishes about the Paris-<persName corresp="#p_DG1">De
                        Gaulle</persName> trip.<note n="3" xml:id="d195fn3">The reference is to
                            <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName>’s No. 648, of November
                        14, 1944, <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_14">p.
                        14</ref>.</note> I certainly had a wonderful reception from about half a
                    million French in the Champs Élysées and also from the party opposition centre
                    at the Hôtel de Ville. I reestablished friendly private relations with <persName corresp="#p_DG1">De Gaulle</persName>, who is better since he has lost a
                    large part of his inferiority complex.</p>
                <p>4. I see statements being put out in the French press and other quarters that all
                    sorts of things were decided by us in Paris. You may be sure that our
                    discussions on important things took place solely on an <hi rend="italic">ad
                        referendum</hi> basis to the three great powers, and of course especially to
                    you who have by far the largest forces in France. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> and I had a two-hours talk with <persName corresp="#p_DG1">De Gaulle</persName> and two or three of his people after luncheon on the
                    11th. <persName corresp="#p_DG1">De Gaulle</persName> asked a number of
                    questions which made me feel how very little they were informed about anything
                    that had been decided or was taking place. He is of course anxious to obtain
                    full modern equipment for eight more divisions which can only be supplied by
                    you. <gloss target="#t_SHAEF1">SHAEF</gloss> reasonably contends that these will
                    not be ready for the defeat of Germany in the field and that shipping must be
                    devoted to the upkeep of the actual forces that will win the battles of the
                    winter and spring. I reinforced this argument.</p>
                <p>5. At the same time I sympathize with the French wish to take over more line, to
                    have the best share they can in the fighting or what is left of it, and there
                    may be plenty, and not to have to go into Germany as a so-called conqueror who
                    has not fought. I remarked that this was a sentimental point which ought never
                    the less to receive consideration. The important thing for France was to have an
                    army prepared for the task which it would actually have to discharge, <pb facs="0371" n="285" xml:id="pg_285"/> namely their obligation first to
                    maintain a peaceful and orderly France behind the front of our armies, and
                    secondly to assist in the holding down of parts of Germany later on.</p>
                <p>6. On this second point the French pressed very strongly to have a share in the
                    occupation of Germany not merely as subparticipation under British or American
                    command but as a French command. I expressed my sympathy with this, knowing well
                    that there will be a time not many years distant when the American armies will
                    go home and when the British will have great difficulty in maintaining large
                    forces overseas, so contrary to our mode of life and disproportionate to our
                    resources, and I urged them to study the type of army fitted for that purpose,
                    which is totally different in form from the organization by divisions required
                    to break the resistance of a modern war-hardened enemy army. They were impressed
                    by this argument but nevertheless pressed their view.</p>
                <p>7. I see a Reuter message, emanating no doubt unofficially from Paris, that it
                    was agreed France should be assigned certain areas, the Ruhr, the Rhineland,
                    etc., for their troops to garrison. There is no truth in this and it is obvious
                    that nothing of this kind can be settled on such a subject except in agreement
                    with you. All I said to <persName corresp="#p_DG1">De Gaulle</persName> on this
                    was that we had made a division of Germany into Russian, British and United
                    States spheres: roughly, the Russians had the east, the British the north and
                    the Americans the south. I further said that, speaking for His Majesty’s
                    Government, the less we had of it the better we should be pleased and that we
                    would certainly favour the French taking over as large a part as their capacity
                    allowed, but that all this must be settled at an inter-Allied table. I could of
                    course issue something which would be a disclaimer of any loose statements made
                    by Reuter, but you may not think this necessary in view of the obvious facts. I
                    am telegraphing to U. J. in the same sense. We did not attempt to settle
                    anything finally or make definite agreements.</p>
                <p>8. It is evident however that there are a number of questions which press for
                    decision at a level higher than that of the high commands, without which
                    decisions no clear guidance can be given to the high commands. Here is another
                    reason why we should have a triple meeting if U. J. will not come, or a
                    quadruple meeting if he will. In the latter case the French would be in on some
                    subjects and out on others. One must always realize that before five years are
                    out there must be made a French army to take on the main task of holding down
                    Germany. The main question of discussion between <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> was
                    Syria, which was troublesome, lengthy and inconclusive but primarily our
                    worry.</p>
                <p>9. I thought I would give you this account at once in case of further tendentious
                    statements being put out in the press.</p>
                <pb facs="0372" n="286" xml:id="pg_286"/>
                <p>10. I thought very well of <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName>. … He
                    made a very favourable impression on all of us and there is no doubt that he has
                    a strong share in the power. <persName corresp="#p_G1">Giraud</persName> was at
                    the banquet apparently quite content. What a change in fortunes since
                    Casablanca. Generally I felt in the presence of an organized government, broadly
                    based and of rapidly-growing strength, and I am certain that we should be most
                    unwise to do anything to weaken it in the eyes of France at this difficult,
                    critical time. I had a considerable feeling of stability in spite of communist
                    threats, and that we could safely take them more into our confidence. I hope you
                    will not consider that I am putting on French clothes when I say this. Let me
                    know your thoughts. I will cable you later about the meeting and the meat.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Prime</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
