<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-01-02T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-01-02T13:00:00-05:00" n="207" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d207">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 <gloss target="#t_EW1">EW</gloss>/l-245: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CJ1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-01-02T19:00:00+01:00">January 2, 1945—7 p. m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received January 3—4:31 a. m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>16. General <persName corresp="#p_DG1">De Gaulle</persName> asked me
                                this morning to send a letter (which I am transmitting by air) to
                                President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> and he
                                suggested that I telegraph the text therof.</p>
                            <p>The letter reads in translation as follows:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Mr. President, events have proved that we will not defeat
                                    Germany completely without throwing in new forces; now, France,
                                    in spite of the loss or absence of 3,000,000 men, is in a
                                    position to increase her military forces powerfully and rapidly.
                                    I might add that she ardently desires to do so.</p>
                                <p>We are trying to put our armament factories back into operation.
                                    But this takes a great deal of time because our machine tools
                                    have seriously suffered and above all we lack raw materials.</p>
                                <p>You have already furnished us in North Africa armament and
                                    equipment for eight divisions. It is an effort which I believe
                                    you know was not lost.</p>
                                <p>You have recently agreed to send United States armament and
                                    equipment for eight divisions. Thank you most sincerely, but I
                                    ask you, in our common interests, to hasten the shipment of this
                                    material, all of which the French Army is in a position to use
                                    on the battlefield within the next three months.</p>
                                <p>If I were sure that you would afterwards send us more armament
                                    and equipment material, and if I could know in advance, even
                                    approximately, the quantities, the nature and the rhythm of
                                    these shipments, <pb facs="0379" n="293" xml:id="pg_293"/> this
                                    information would be of great assistance to the French
                                    Government in preparing its plans for mobilization.</p>
                                <p>We could have before the end of this year about 50 good French
                                    divisions if we were able to arm and equip them. If you could
                                    give me a favorable reply in principle, all details could be
                                    settled with your technical services by General <persName corresp="#p_J2">Juin</persName>, Chief of the General Staff
                                    of National Defense, whom I would send at once to
                                    Washington.</p>
                                <p>With my deeply sincere wishes for this year 1945 which will be
                                    hard but glorious for our two countries, I beg of you to accept,
                                    Mr. President, the expression of my feelings of devoted
                                    friendship, <persName corresp="#p_DG1">De
                                    Gaulle</persName>.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>(I assume in paragraph four he is speaking of the conversations
                                mentioned in my 1146, December 30, 6 p. m.)<note n="1" xml:id="d207fn1">740.0011 <gloss target="#t_EW1">EW</gloss>/12–3044; not printed.</note>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>