<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-01-12T10:25:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-01-12T09:25:00-05:00" n="240" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d240">
                        <head>240. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d240fn1">Source: Ford Library, National Security Adviser,
                                Memoranda of Conversations, 1973–1977, Box 17. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. All brackets, except those
                                inserted by the editor to indicate omitted passages, are in the
                                original. The meeting was held in the Oval Office. The memorandum is
                                incorrectly dated January 8; the references in the text to the
                                Soviet note of January 9 and to the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> meeting of January 13 (“tomorrow”) indicate that
                                the meeting probably took place on January 12. According to the
                                President’s Daily Diary, <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> met with <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SB_1">Scowcroft</persName> on January 8 only once (with <persName corresp="#p_RD_2">Rumsfeld</persName>), at 9:23 a.m.; see <ref target="#d237">Document 237</ref>. The President did not meet
                                with the two men again until January 12, and then only once, from
                                9:25 to 10:25 a.m., the likely time of this meeting. (Ford Library,
                                White House Office Files)</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date ana="#date_imprecise-inferred-from-editorial-annotation" calendar="gregorian" from="1976-01-12T09:25:00-05:00" to="1976-01-12T10:25:00-05:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">January 12,
                                1976</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>President <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName></item>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>,
                                Secretary of State</item>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_SB_1">Brent Scowcroft</persName>, Assistant
                                to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                        </list>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We have had a message
                            from the Soviets which is mildly encouraging.<note n="2" xml:id="d240fn2"><ref target="#d239">Document 239</ref>.</note>
                            [Hands message to the President.]</p>
                        <p>The President: What does it really mean?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Our position is
                            basically hopeless in Angola. We have done miraculously at the <gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> at Addis Ababa, considering we have
                            nothing to offer compared to the Soviet Union.</p>
                        <p>The President: I would say we are doing pretty well.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: It is unbelievable
                            that Diggs<note n="3" xml:id="d240fn3">Congressman Charles C. Diggs, Jr.
                                (Democrat, Michigan).</note> would go there and attack us that
                            way—when his specific proposal is in fact ours.</p>
                        <p>The President: He is a lightweight and listens to the wrong people.</p>
                        <pb facs="0930" n="899" xml:id="pg_899"/>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: What could this mean .
                            . . We will ask them: Are we correct that if we remove the South
                            Africans, they will move with us to eliminate all foreign presence?</p>
                        <p>The President: How long would that take?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: It also raises the
                            question of my trip.</p>
                        <p>The President: You have negotiated under adverse criticism before. I
                            think you should go. If you don’t, <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II is probably down the drain and we may lose attempts
                            at solving Angola.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> may come after you. I am being
                            accused of being too tough on the Soviet Union and too soft at the same
                            time.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_MDP_1">Moynihan</persName> is a disaster. His
                            opening comments at the Security Council debate would have been
                            disastrous. [He described the comments.]</p>
                        <p>The President: The arguments against your going are political and those
                            for your going are substantive, and I think we should go with
                            substance.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I think you should
                            decide on <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> and make a decision at
                            the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> meeting tomorrow.<note n="4" xml:id="d240fn4">The record of the January 13 <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> meeting on <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> is scheduled for publication in
                                    <ref target="frus1969-76v33"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations,</hi> 1969–1976, volume XXXIII, <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II,
                            1972–1979</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>The President: I think Option III is what we should really work from. But
                            I want to get as much support from Defense as possible. I have been
                            thinking if you could get something between III and IV to give <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> . . . Obviously they won’t
                            buy it, but then you could go there and put Option III on the table.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: They will accept
                            everything except surface ships and counting Backfire. We have given
                            them some options on Backfire—like counting all the ones they build
                            after the date of a treaty—and they have rejected them.</p>
                        <p>The President: I would like to get Defense off our back.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We won’t get Option
                            III easily. I can’t go to Moscow without the full support of Defense.
                            They must be told that. [There is discussion of how to deal with
                            Backfire, etc.]</p>
                        <p>The President: How would you deal with it?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I could tell <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> this is as far as we can go
                            now, but I would have flexibility in Moscow. [There is more discussion
                            about counting surface ships, Backfire, etc.]</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SB_1">Scowcroft</persName>: If you start with
                            Option III, I am convinced you will have leaks that the <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss> was overruled.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: But if we go with
                            Option IV, I will be accused of not negotiating hard enough for Option
                            IV. But we can go with counting <pb facs="0931" n="900" xml:id="pg_900"/> Backfire after 1977, and count cruise missiles on surface ships as
                                <gloss target="#t_MIRV_1">MIRV</gloss>’s. If that fails, go to
                            Option III, with a separate protocol on Backfire and surface ships, with
                            a reduction to 2,300 for five years or an eight-year agreement with
                            higher numbers.</p>
                        <p>The President: This at least gives you the argument that we tried a
                            preferred position.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: It is a two-edged
                            sword—they could also claim we shouldn’t have fallen off.</p>
                        <p>The President: Let’s go that way. Give me a paper for the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> tomorrow.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is discussion of personnel matters, including <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s proposal to appoint
                                <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Joseph Sisco</persName> as Ambassador
                            to the Soviet Union.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>