<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-10-04T08:58:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-10-04T08:58:00-05:00" n="48" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d48">
                        <head>48. Transcript of Telephone Conversation Between Secretary of State
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> and the Soviet
                            Ambassador (<persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d48fn1">Source: Department of State,
                                Electronic Reading Room, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Transcripts of Telephone Conversations. No
                                classification marking. Brackets are in the original.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-10-04T09:58:00-04:00">October 4, 1974, 9:58 a.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>D: Hello!</p>
                        <p>K: Anatol.</p>
                        <p>D: Oh, good morning, Henry.</p>
                        <p>K: Anatol, it was good to see you yesterday.<note n="2" xml:id="d48fn2">No record of a meeting between <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> on October 3 has been found. According to
                                his Record of Schedule, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> returned to Washington from New York that
                                afternoon. (Library of Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box 439,
                                Miscellany, 1968–76)</note></p>
                        <p>D: It was really nice to see you, Henry, because you are spending so lot
                            of time. Is it true you met 75 minutes in Paris somewhere?</p>
                        <pb facs="0170" n="139" xml:id="pg_139"/>
                        <p>K: [Laughter] I don’t know whether it is true—it is such a ridiculous
                            statement.</p>
                        <p>D: Yeh, I know. It is like a notorious play in chess.</p>
                        <p>K: That’s right.</p>
                        <p>D: . . . sitting with a whole row of foreign ministers . . . and you just
                            going from one to another.</p>
                        <p>K: Well, on the Greek side you know I could do a little bit. We can’t do
                            serious work in New York.</p>
                        <p>D: I understand.</p>
                        <p>K: Anatol, we have some problem with grain purchases you are making.</p>
                        <p>D: What kind of purchases?</p>
                        <p>K: The problem we have is that it is probably our people’s fault in that
                            they have triggered you into doing something.</p>
                        <p>D: Yeh.</p>
                        <p>K: And what I wanted to point out is this: we are having a great
                            difficulty with corn and I understand that your people have placed an
                            order for a million tons.</p>
                        <p>D: For how many?</p>
                        <p>K: A million.</p>
                        <p>D: One million?</p>
                        <p>K: Yes.</p>
                        <p>D: Yes, but I also . . . one million.</p>
                        <p>K: Yes, but with frost and with the new difficulties. Our people think
                            that 500 thousand is really the maximum we can handle. And we
                            wondered—you see otherwise if you go through with it and if this gets
                            announced then we have to do something about restricting exports which
                            we don’t want to do.</p>
                        <p>D: I don’t know whether <persName corresp="#p_BEL_1">Butz</persName>
                            reported to you or whether he was doing everything on his own. I already
                            discussed with him<note n="3" xml:id="d48fn3">No records of the meetings
                                between <persName corresp="#p_BEL_1">Butz</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> have been found.</note>
                            and with Moscow authority and everything and it remained on a high
                            order.</p>
                        <p>K: I am absolutely positive, Anatol, that it is our fault. I am positive
                            that you responded to us.</p>
                        <p>D: Everything he asked me—so the last time he was with me—about five days
                            ago—if it is not more than one million, okay, but not more than one
                            million, so I said to Moscow all right. So now it’s changed in the past
                            three days. He came to the Embassy and said exactly not more than a
                            million.</p>
                        <pb facs="0171" n="140" xml:id="pg_140"/>
                        <p>K: I haven’t the foggiest idea since—it is the last time he will come to
                            your Embassy without permission—believe me.</p>
                        <p>D: Yes. I don’t complain he came to me.</p>
                        <p>K: I am telling you he is not coming to your Embassy again without
                            permission. Or we may have a new Secretary of Agriculture.</p>
                        <p>D: [laughter] Really he asked me several things and on all exchanges it
                            was a positive answer. So I reported everything this way. Now he is
                            telling me a different kind of thing.</p>
                        <p>K: Another thing he also placed for a million tons of wheat—was that also
                            arranged with <persName corresp="#p_BEL_1">Butz</persName>?</p>
                        <p>D: He said about one million—we didn’t discuss exactly with . . .</p>
                        <p>K: Well a million we can probably handle on wheat if you don’t go above a
                            million.</p>
                        <p>D: So what is your . . .</p>
                        <p>K: Oh, you have already ordered two?</p>
                        <p>D: I don’t know. I don’t know.</p>
                        <p>K: Well on wheat we can handle a million altogether. On corn we can
                            handle 500 thousand.</p>
                        <p>D: You mean by the end of this year or before the elections?</p>
                        <p>K: Before the election there shouldn’t really be anything.</p>
                        <p>D: They didn’t discuss it really—it was a question where it was
                            announced.</p>
                        <p>K: Well, it is going to be announced very soon and if this isn’t—if we
                            can’t get some understanding on it. Well let me get back to you within
                            an hour. Let me check with the Agriculture Department.</p>
                        <p>D: Please give me what is your explanation because I am a little bit
                            confused now.</p>
                        <p>K: Okay.</p>
                        <p>D: Okay, Henry.</p>
                        <p>K: Right.<note n="4" xml:id="d48fn4">As soon as he hung up with <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> called <persName corresp="#p_SH_3">Sonnenfeldt</persName> to discuss how to
                                proceed: “I’ve got guys running around like chickens without
                                heads—after all it is all in the same country—we are all speaking
                                English. Can somebody find out what the hell happened before we put
                                the lid on it. <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName>
                                says—and I didn’t volunteer it with <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName>—<persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> told me his assessment—that he doesn’t know
                                what it is all about. That <persName corresp="#p_BEL_1">Butz</persName> personally called on him without asking—without
                                being asked to come.” <persName corresp="#p_SH_3">Sonnenfeldt</persName> agreed to “try and find out” what
                                happened. (Department of State, Electronic Reading Room, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Transcripts of Telephone
                                Conversations) According to his Record of Schedule, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> called <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> twice that afternoon.
                                (Library of Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box 439,
                                Miscellany, 1968–76) No substantive record of either conversation
                                has been found.</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>