<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-05-17T06:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-05-17T06:30:00-05:00" n="123" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/5–1752: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in India (<persName corresp="#p_BCB1" type="from">Bowles</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                        Delhi</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-05-17T17:00:00+05:30">May 17, 1952—5
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>4282. In conversation with <persName corresp="#p_BSGS1">Bajpai</persName>
                            today he opened up question of Korea.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BSGS1">Bajpai</persName> stated great deal had been
                            going on last two or three days and he would like give me full
                            facts.…</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>On May 10 <persName corresp="#p_PSVLMP1">Madam Pandit</persName>
                                cabled <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> after talking to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou En-Lai</persName> she was
                                convinced Chinese Communists really wanted truce in Korea. She
                                admitted possibility trickery but stated he emphasized so hard
                                desire of Communist Government for some solution she personally
                                inclined believe him.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou En-lai</persName>, however,
                                stated his opinion Americans were anxious carry on war and if
                                possible to expand it in hopes that this might split Communist China
                                from Soviet Union.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_PSVLMP1">Madam Pandit</persName> expressed
                                strong opinion to <persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou En-lai</persName>
                                that Americans were fully anxious for peace, that they had no desire
                                to <pb facs="0241" n="207" xml:id="pg_207"/> attack anyone and that
                                if both sides generally wanted truce it should be easy to establish
                                it.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou En-lai</persName> stated his
                                government could not accept return of only 70,000 prisoners but
                                hinted compromise might be reached at 100,000.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_PSVLMP1">Madam Pandit</persName> urged her
                                government to do everything possible develop some compromise which
                                might be acceptable both sides.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>On Monday, May 12, after discussion with <persName>Bajpai
                                    Nehru</persName> sent cable to <persName corresp="#p_PSVLMP1">Madam Pandit</persName> stating in his opinion Chinese
                                Government position on promises was wholly unsound; that it was
                                wrong arbitrarily to condemn some prisoners to one side and others
                                to other; hence that it was not actual number of prisoners returned
                                that was important but the method by which the choices were made.
                                Cable emphasized that <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName>
                                is giving his views to her for background only and that <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> argument with <persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou En-lai</persName> might only harden
                                situation generally.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName>’s cable then
                                suggested that perhaps all prisoners could be placed under neutral
                                control, that Communists might be given opportunity to talk to them;
                                and every method developed to see that completely friendly decision
                                was made in each case. However, he urged <persName corresp="#p_PSVLMP1">Madam Pandit</persName> to propose this as
                                coming from her and not from him because it otherwise might be
                                assumed that he was simply forwarding suggestion from US Government.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> asked <persName corresp="#p_PSVLMP1">Madam Pandit</persName> to immediately
                                reopen subject on her own initiative again <persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou En-lai</persName>.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>On Wednesday, May 14, cable arrived from <persName corresp="#p_PKM1">Panikkar</persName> stating <persName corresp="#p_PSVLMP1">Madam Pandit</persName> was leaving Peking
                                and that she agreed with him it would be mistake to reopen subject
                                with <persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou En-lai</persName> following
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> speech in House of
                                Commons and President <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName>’s speech of May 7<note n="1" xml:id="d123fn1">For
                                    text of <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName>’s speech,
                                    see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the
                                        United States: <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Harry S.
                                            Truman</persName>, 1952–1953</hi>, pp. 321–322; for
                                        <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName>’s remarks of May
                                    7, 1952, see <hi rend="italic">Parliamentary Debates</hi>, House
                                    of Commons, 5th series, vol. 500, pp. 383–387.</note> which in
                                opinion of Chinese Government closed door to any agreement.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>On May 15 <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> cabled
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PKM1">Panikkar</persName> … that he had
                                received most reassuring message<note n="2" xml:id="d123fn2">Presumably <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> was
                                    referring to the letter from <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> described in footnote 2, <ref target="#pg_202">p. 202</ref>.</note> from <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> and that if <persName corresp="#p_PSVLMP1">Madam Pandit</persName> left Peking,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PKM1">Panikkar</persName> himself was
                                instructed carry on discussions in line with <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName>’s previous cable.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BSGS1">Bajpai</persName> asked for my comments. I
                            said I felt deeply appreciative of what <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> was trying to do and I thought their position was
                            proper and reasonable. I again went over all facts on prisoners of war
                            issue including missing 50,000 UN prisoners said to be captured by
                            Communists. I told him that under no circumstances would we depart from
                            moral position involving forced repatriation but it would be obvious to
                            anyone we were not anxious maintain and feed potential Communist
                            agitators in South Korean prison camps; that we had every reason to want
                            return of every Communist soldier who wanted to go back; but that I was
                            sure the method by which we might decide exactly who wanted to go back
                            and who did not was certainly open to full discussion and suggestions. I
                            happened to have President <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName>’s May 7 statement with me and went over it carefully
                            with <persName corresp="#p_BSGS1">Bajpai</persName> who agreed it <pb facs="0242" n="208" xml:id="pg_208"/> closed no doors and offered
                            absolutely no basis for Communist blowup.</p>
                        <p>I will discuss all this in detail again with Prime Minister Sunday
                            night.…</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_BCB1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Bowles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>