<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Commander in Chief, United Nations Command (Clark), to the Joint Chiefs
                    of Staff</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v15p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d170</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">170</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-06-05T03:44:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-06-05T03:44:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPjGjlVHIlHmzym" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112903"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Repatriation</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-06-05T03:44:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-06-05T03:44:00-05:00" n="170"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d170">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> files, lot 55 D 128, tab 34: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Commander in Chief, United Nations Command (<persName
                            corresp="#p_CGMW1" type="from">Clark</persName>), to the <gloss
                            type="to">Joint Chiefs of Staff</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>operational immediate</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-06-05T17:44:00+09:00"
                            >June 5, 1952—5:44 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>CX 69687. Re CX 64029.<note n="1" xml:id="d170fn1">Dated Feb. 21, <ref
                            target="#pg_57">p. 57</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Since <persName corresp="#p_RGMB1">General Ridgway</persName> notified you
                        in para 3 of referenced message of his decision to hold all civilian
                        internees until the plan for their release could be included in the overall
                        plan for the release of all internees, both military and civilian, there
                        have been several developments which indicate that those <gloss
                            target="#t_CIs1">CIs</gloss> who have been screened and have indicated
                        they do not wish to return to Communists control, should be released from
                            <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> custody as soon as appropriate
                        arrangements are made with <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>In arriving at the above decision, I have carefully examined all aspects
                        of this problem and have discussed it personally with <persName
                            corresp="#p_VFLGJA1">Van Fleet</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_HMGWKJ1">Harrison</persName>, both of whom recommend
                        release. The primary deterrent to releasing the <gloss target="#t_CIs1"
                            >CIs</gloss> to date has been the adverse effect upon the armistice
                        negotiations and a possible retaliation against UN <gloss target="#t_POWs1"
                            >POWs</gloss>. However, this deterrent is not considered valid at this
                        time. <persName corresp="#p_HMGWKJ1">Harrison</persName> submitted to me his
                        analysis of the question, pertinent parts of which are quoted below: <quote
                            rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“The civilian internees are not <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss>
                                in fact, having been reclassified as civilians and so reported to
                                the <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss>. They therefore are, or
                                should be, outside of the <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POW</gloss>
                                issue. In item 4 staff discussions the Communists tacitly accepted
                                this view when the [<hi rend="italic">they</hi>] proposed <gloss
                                    target="#t_POWs1">POW</gloss> exchange based on 18 December
                                lists. The release of the civilian internees I consider a matter of
                                justice consistent with our position on the entire <gloss
                                    target="#t_POWs1">POW</gloss> issue. If we do not release them
                                it can be inferred that our proclaimed final stand is not actually
                                final and that we are so afraid of not achieving an armistice that
                                we are prepared to sacrifice our widely publicized humanitarian
                                principles in the interests of expediency. Release of the civilian
                                internees would tend to prove that our stand is final and that we do
                                not fear the consequences of the act.</p>
                            <pb facs="0349" n="315" xml:id="pg_315"/>
                            <p>The objection has been advanced that their release may influence the
                                enemy to break off negotiations or to delay an armistice
                                indefinitely. I consider this risk negligible. Although current
                                enemy statements indicate that they include these persons among
                                those they want returned to them, their earlier statements in staff
                                discussions indicate their willingness to ignore them. I consider it
                                very unlikely that a major decision would be determined by an issue
                                that the enemy has already discounted.</p>
                            <p>I also consider it a negligible risk that release of civilian
                                internees might cause enemy to retaliate by holding UN <gloss
                                    target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss> now in their hands. The only way
                                we can expect the return of our men is through an armistice. If the
                                enemy wants an armistice sufficiently to agree to our package
                                proposal there will be no point in his not exchanging the 12,000 UN
                                prisoners for the 70,000 we hold, as specified in that proposal. We
                                can exercise some degree of control by regulating the rate of
                                exchange of the prisoners on a proportionate basis. For the enemy
                                not to return the UN prisoners, or to threaten not to return them in
                                order to influence negotiations would be a complete repudiation of
                                all that he has said in the conferences and to the world about
                                repatriation. In my opinion the probability of the return of our men
                                in enemy hands is approximately equal to the probability of
                                achieving an armistice.</p>
                            <p>While we cannot accurately foresee the consequences of releasing the
                                civilian internees, it would appear reasonably certain that the
                                enemy will use it as fuel for his propaganda and, if he desires, to
                                justify delay or prevention of an armistice. However, he already has
                                ample propaganda material and can manufacture more at will. Fear of
                                what the enemy might say should not, in my opinion, deter action
                                otherwise indicated. I believe that in case of doubt the bolder
                                course should be followed.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The question of the continued detention of the <gloss target="#t_CIs1"
                            >CIs</gloss> has been a constant source of irritation to the <gloss
                            target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> govt and the <gloss target="#t_ROK1"
                            >ROK</gloss> people. In this connection, Pres <persName corresp="#p_RS1"
                            >Rhee</persName> has repeatedly made strong representations to <gloss
                            target="#t_CGAE1">CGArEight</gloss> and AmEmbassy (<persName
                            corresp="#p_MJJ1">Muccio</persName>) for the release of <gloss
                            target="#t_CIs1">CIs</gloss>. Delay in their release will unquestionably
                        result in unrest and further incidents such as that which took place in
                        compound nbr 14 Yongchon, reported to you in para 3B, CX 69308 and para 3 CX
                            69622.<note n="2" xml:id="d170fn2">Neither of these telegrams, dated May
                            30 and June 4, is printed (<gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> files, lot
                            55 D 128, tabs 151 and 20, respectively).</note> We anticipate increased
                        activity by infiltrated Communist agents attempting to further this unrest.
                        It is also believed that the release of the <gloss target="#t_CIs1"
                            >CIs</gloss> can be accomplished without materially affecting the
                        present crisis within the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> govt.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>In addition to the advantages outlined above, the release of approximately
                        27,000 <gloss target="#t_CIs1">CIs</gloss> would materially reduce the
                        logistic burden of the military and free vitally needed overhead personnel
                        for other duties.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The timing and general plan for the release of the <gloss target="#t_CIs1"
                            >CIs</gloss> will be furnished you before actual release begins.</item>
                    <pb facs="0350" n="316" xml:id="pg_316"/>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Although I consider the decision to release <gloss target="#t_CIs1"
                            >CIs</gloss> within my province, in view of the effect such action might
                        have on the armistice negotiations, request your views soonest.<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d170fn3">The Joint Chiefs of Staff approved this proposal in
                            principle on June 10, 1952 in <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 910811
                            to <persName corresp="#p_CGMW1">Clark</persName> (<gloss target="#t_FE1"
                                >FE</gloss> files, lot 55 D 128, tab 82).</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
