<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-08-25T02:51:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-08-25T02:51:00-05:00" n="245" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d245">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/8—3052: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Commander in Chief, Far East (<persName corresp="#p_CGMW1" type="from">Clark</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Joint Chiefs of Staff</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d245fn1">The following names were handwritten on the source
                                text: <persName>Nagle</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MHF1">Matthews</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HJD1">Hickerson</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName>; presumably they received
                            copies.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret<lb/>operational
                                    immediate</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-08-25T16:51:00+09:00">August 25, 1952—4:51
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>CX 54177. 1. The <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> has in its custody
                            approximately 16,000 South Korean prisoners of war. Of this group
                            approximately 11,000 during screening, elected not to return to
                            Communist control. They were segregated and moved to Camp nbr 12, Masan,
                            on the Korean mainland. In my opinion the further retention of this
                            group of anti-Communists can no longer be justified. This conclusion is
                            based on the following considerations: <list>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>These are bona fide Nationals of the Republic of Korea who
                                    should be permitted to return to their home country.</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>All have elected not to return to Communist control.</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Insufficient information on the background of many of these
                                        <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss> did not permit their
                                    reclassification as civilian internees. However, there is strong
                                    reason to believe that in this group are ex-<gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> soldiers, civilians who had
                                    been impressed by the <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> Army,
                                    and others who had been swept up in the security dragnet when
                                    the <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> was threatened by large
                                    numbers of enemy infiltrators in civilian clothing. Insufficient
                                    evidence exists today to justify the continued detention of
                                    these individuals as bona fide prisoners of war.</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                <item>The <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Govt has already made
                                    strong appeals for the release of this group.</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                                <item>The Communist Armistice Delegation has in the past few months
                                    relaxed its demands for the return of <gloss target="#t_SK1">SK</gloss>s in our custody; however, this has been
                                    conditional on our agreement to repatriate all the <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>s and Chinese.</item>
                                <pb facs="0491" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Such release would materially decrease our requirements for
                                    administrative and logistical support of our <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POW</gloss>-CI population, and would
                                    release urgently needed security forces for other high priority
                                    missions.</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">g</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Of even greater importance than the above, the release of the
                                        <gloss target="#t_SK1">SK</gloss>
                                    <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss> at this time would impress
                                    upon the Communists the firmness of our stand at the conference
                                    table.</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">h</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Continued retention by the <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>
                                    of South Korean natls who have already renounced allegiance to
                                    the Communists regardless of the manner in which they were
                                    brought into our custody can only work to our disadvantage and
                                    may in fact, encourage them to lean toward Communism.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>2. It appears here that article 5 of the Geneva <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POW</gloss> Convention of 1949 affords a practicable legal basis
                            for releasing <gloss target="#t_SK1">SK</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss> at this time. Application of the
                            provisions of article 5 involves determination by a “competent tribunal”
                            that these persons have been held as “doubtful” <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss> and that screening conducted by the tribunal has
                            resolved the doubt against <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POW</gloss> status
                            under article 4. A “competent tribunal” as contemplated by this article
                            would, I believe, have to be organized and operated similar to a
                            screening board. Procedure along these lines differs from that by which
                                <gloss target="#t_SK1">SK</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss> were reclassified to “civilian
                            internees” and subsequently released, since under article 5 release from
                                <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POW</gloss> status is not contingent upon a
                            finding by the screening board that the individuals concerned are
                            properly “civilian internees.” The basic determination is simply that
                            investigation has disclosed that the individual is not in fact a <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POW</gloss>, and should not be detained further by
                            the <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>3. We consider that the tribunal should be composed of at least
                            representatives of the US and <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>. If
                            you consider it necessary we can attempt to secure additional
                            representation from other UN combatant forces in Korea. To avoid
                            excessive legal and administrative procedures, we believe that the
                            mission of the screening tribunal should be simple and should be limited
                            to determining the qualifications of each individual for release, using
                            the following criteria: <list>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>The <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POW</gloss> concerned is a South
                                    Korean.</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>As a result of previous screening he elected not to return to
                                    Communist control.</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                <item>He professes allegiance to the Sovereign State of the Republic
                                    of Korea.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>4. Actual release and resettlement within the Republic of Korea would be
                            acomplished in coordination with appropriate agencies of the <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                            following a procedure similar to that used in the disposition of
                            civilian internees released from our custody.</p>
                        <p>5. Total time to complete release after notification of approval,
                            estimated at 70 days. Screening of personnel, review of questionnaires
                            by tribunal, and a rostering by province of origin will take
                            approximately <pb facs="0492" n="458" xml:id="pg_458"/> 25 days. Actual
                            release can be completed in 45 days, based on <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> ability to receive released personnel.</p>
                        <p>6. We cannot estimate here what retaliatory measures, if any, might be
                            taken by the Communists against the <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>
                            prisoners they now hold. Anticipating the impact which this release
                            might have in the armistice negotiations I intend, and <persName corresp="#p_HMGWKJ1">Gen Harrison</persName> concurs, to adopt a
                            procedure similar to that used in the release of <gloss target="#t_CIs1">CIs</gloss>. Concurrent with actual release of the initial group, a
                            factual press release would be made. Should the Communists attempt to
                            propagandize on the release in armistice negotiations, as they probably
                            will, our delegation would dismiss their charges as being invalid since
                            the individuals concerned are loyal nationals of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and as such we recognize no Communist
                            claim on their disposition.</p>
                        <p>7. Appropriate notification would be made through normal channels to the
                                <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss> indicating that the <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> had released from its custody certain
                            persons erroneously retained as <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>8. Request your early consideration of course of action indicated
                            above.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>