<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Commander in Chief, United Nations Command (Clark) to the Joint Chiefs of
                    Staff</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v15p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d283</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">283</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-09-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-09-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPjGjlVHIlHmzym" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112903"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Repatriation</term>
                    <term ref="reckz6KR6qJLArS7N" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade">Naval blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recCxB7N65K8Uxxym" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ground forces</term>
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-09-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-09-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="283"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d283">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> Library, <persName
                        corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> papers, Material from the Department of
                    Defense Relating to the Korean War</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Commander in Chief, United Nations Command (<persName
                            corresp="#p_CGMW1" type="from">Clark</persName>) to the <gloss type="to"
                            >Joint Chiefs of Staff</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d283fn1">Repeated to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1"
                            >CINCPAC</gloss> for information.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-09-29">September 29,
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>CX 56022. Reur 919187.<note n="2" xml:id="d283fn2">Dated Sept. 23, <ref
                            target="#pg_527">p. 527</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>This is an interim reply which covers my curr planning on the
                        subject.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Since assumption of my present comd I have considered as one of my primary
                        missions the attainment of an honorable mil armistice in Korea. Constantly
                        cited as the reason for failure to achieve a mil armistice <pb facs="0583"
                            n="549" xml:id="pg_549"/> is the apparent impossibility of agreement on
                        repatriation of <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss>. On the surface that
                        does seem to be the final impediment to the realization of an armistice;
                        however, I am of the firm conviction that the basic, underlying reason for
                        failure thus far to achieve an armistice is that we have not exerted suf mil
                        pressure to impose the rqmt for an armistice on the enemy.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Our problem is, of course, difficult. We confront undemoralized enemy
                        forces, far superior in str, who occupy excellent, extremely well organized
                            <gloss target="#t_Def1">def</gloss> psns in depth and who cont to
                        provide themselves with suf log support. Under these conditions, it appears
                        evident that positive aggressive action, designed to obtain mil victory and
                        achieve an armistice on our terms, is not feasible by this comd with curr
                        forces operating under curr restrictions. Gains that might be achieved by
                        removal of restrictions cannot properly be exploited except by concurrent
                        ground action which is dependent upon augmentation of forces. On the other
                        hand, gains which might be achieved by intensified ground action with
                        augmented forces would be purchased at highly unpalatable pers cost, if not
                        accompanied by the advantages that would accrue from the removal of certain
                        restrictions.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>In consonance with my conviction that achievement of an armistice is
                        dependent upon a degree of mil victory, I have had this subject under active
                        study to determine the extent of aggressive action in Korea nec to establish
                        conditions whereby the enemy will be compelled to seek or accept an
                        armistice on our terms. This study develops the concept for a mil victory of
                        suf magnitude to establish these conditions.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In development of the concept of opns in this study, 3 assumptions were
                        made which have the force of my convictions. First, that the Communists will
                        not accept an armistice on present terms under the present mil sit. Second,
                        that the <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> will not recede from its stated
                        psn re forcible repatriation of <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss>. And
                        third, that the contemplated actions will not cause the USSR to enter the
                        hostilities, thereby possibly precipitating World War Three. The USSR has no
                        qualms about dishonoring pledges such as may be included in the Sino-Russian
                        mutual assistance pact. The USSR needs no excuses for her acts. In fact, the
                            <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> has already been accused of
                        countless alleged violations of the Manchurian border and atks on Chinese
                        territory. I believe that World War Three will not be brought about by
                        action on our part, that conflict will commence only when the USSR so
                        determines on her own appraisal, unaffected by US or <gloss target="#t_UNC1"
                            >UNC</gloss> actions, and that therefore any so called extension of the
                        Korean opns presents little risk insofar as precipitating World War Three is
                        concerned.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>In considering means that might be adopted to attain an armistice, a
                        distinction should be made between exertion of mil pressure on the one hand
                        and winning a mil victory on the other. It appears unwise to me to commit
                        the resources, both human and mat, and accept the losses <pb facs="0584"
                            n="550" xml:id="pg_550"/> inherent in offensive action or pressure that
                        does not contemplate the destruction of hostile forces. An advance to the
                        narrow waist of Korea (generally from Pyongyang to Wonsan) that failed to
                        encompass a concept aimed at major destruction of enemy mat and forces could
                        not be worth the cost and would be disadvantageous to the <gloss
                            target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> since a battle line there, though shorter,
                        would not be as strong for a considerable period of time as our main
                        defensive psn as presently organized. Therefore I feel that any contemplated
                        course of action must include provision for carrying the battle all the way
                        to the Yalu in the event that a mil victory cannot be achieved short of that
                        line.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>In connection with case one and case two of your para 3, my curr studies
                        have convinced me that no action in extension or intensification of Korean
                        hostilities under those conditions is feasible or recommendable except for
                        extension of the air war to suitable tgts beyond the Yalu including the
                        Antung <gloss target="#t_afld1">afld</gloss> complex. Altho this is a curr
                        capability of assigned forces and can be implemented upon order, I do not
                        feel that it will, by itself, achieve the desired mil objective. However, in
                        view of the fact that air atks against critical tgts in Manchuria and China
                        and an imposition of a naval blockade against China would to a degree
                        inflict damage, strain enemy resources, and decrease enemy capabilities, it
                        is possible that such actions would cause the Communists to accept an
                        armistice on curr terms. In any event, but subsequent to arrival in the
                        theater of force augmentations, I would wish to implement this extension of
                        the war before launching a maj ground offensive and committing maj elms to
                        an amph assault.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>With ref to case 3 of your para 3, preliminary <gloss target="#t_EST1"
                            >est</gloss> of force rqmts for our concept, which is also envisaged for
                        implementation in the spring of 1953, deviates from those cited. It calls
                        for additional ground forces, amph lift, and differently augmented air
                        forces.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>The study being developed here is now being elaborated into outline plan
                        form if suf detail to establish concept of opns, feasibility and force
                        rqmts. This project can be further developed and prepared for presentation
                        in Wash by a team of staff offs from this hq on or about 20 Oct. It is
                        visualized that enroute to Wash the team would acquaint <gloss
                            target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> with the details and coord approp
                        matters with him. I will discuss this with <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Adm
                            Radford</persName> during his contemplated visit to Tokyo on or about 6
                        Oct 52.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
