<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minutes of the Thirteenth Meeting of the United States Delegation at the
                    United Nations General Assembly</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v15p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d333</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">333</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-11-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="prisoners-of-war"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners of war</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recPjGjlVHIlHmzym" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112903"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Repatriation</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="rec8HXmBQjKyPk0EY" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062603"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Housing</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-11-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="333"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d333">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">IO files, lot 71 D 440</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Thirteenth Meeting of the United States
                        Delegation at the United Nations General Assembly</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d333fn1">These minutes were drafted by <persName>Charles D.
                            Cook</persName>, Adviser to the U.S. Permanent Mission at the United
                        Nations on Nov. 19. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ADG1"
                        >Acheson</persName>, <persName>Eleanor Roosevelt</persName>, Senator
                            <persName>Wiley</persName>, and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GEA1"
                            >Gross</persName> led the list of participants at this meeting which was
                        attended by 42 members of the U.S. Delegation and the Permanent
                        Staff.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/> US/A/M(Chr)/250</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-11-17">November 17,
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Secretary opened the meeting and referred to certain “corridor gossip”
                    regarding the election of a Secretary-General. He urged an attitude of reticence
                    upon the members of the Delegation. He said that it would be unwise to be drawn
                    into speculation regarding this or that individual. He himself had tried to give
                    the excuse as a means of buying more time for our preparations that perhaps Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_LTH1">Lie</persName> would not be adamant but rather
                    would be willing to finish his term. The Secretary suggested that the members of
                    the Delegation await the results of staff consideration of this matter before
                    becoming involved in conversations on it.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Korean Question</hi> (Document
                        SD/A/C.1/396/Rev.2);<note n="2" xml:id="d333fn2">For text of this position
                        paper, see <ref target="#pg_599">p. 599</ref>.</note> Draft Resolutions A/C.
                    1/725 (Twenty-one Power), A/C.1/730 (Mexican), A/C.1/732 (Peruvian),
                    A/C.1/729/Rev.2 (Soviet).</p>
                <p>The Secretary suggested that, since he and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GEA1"
                        >Gross</persName> had been doing most of the “infighting” of the last week,
                    he could give an adequate picture of the recent developments. He recalled that
                    during the week, prior to <persName corresp="#p_VAY1">Vishinsky</persName>’s
                        speech,<note n="3" xml:id="d333fn3">The speech of Nov. 10 before the First
                        Committee; see footnote 1 <ref target="#pg_598">p. 598</ref>.</note> the
                    Soviet Foreign Minister and Mr. <persName>Gromyko</persName> had been seeing the
                    “neutralists”, urging these delegations on with their various schemes for
                    solving the Korean question. After the Soviets had stimulated a good deal of
                    activity, <persName corresp="#p_VAY1">Vishinsky</persName> had spoken and said,
                    in effect, that he would not budge. This was a very familiar tactical move.
                    Having gotten these “neutralist” delegations aroused to the point where they
                    felt they must come forward with proposed solutions, the Soviets had then made
                    it quite clear that they would not move from their position. The momentum thus
                    created required an outlet which resulted in a search for some formula which
                    would be much closer to the wishes of the Soviets. It was no longer a question
                    of saving face for the Russians and satisfying our demands, but rather of giving
                    the Soviets the decision and trying to save our face.</p>
                <p>Everything had come to a head with the activities of <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1"
                        >Krishna Menon</persName> (India) who seemed to be a master of putting words
                    together so that they conveyed no idea at all. His scheme would be to turn the
                    prisoners of war over to some other “outfit” which would re-educate them. <pb
                        facs="0688" n="654" xml:id="pg_654"/> He had alleged that the number of
                    prisoners who were unwilling to be repatriated had been overestimated and that
                    in fact, very probably, as a result of the re-education, they would all want to
                    return.</p>
                <p>During many conversations with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName>,
                    the Secretary and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GEA1">Gross</persName> had
                    tried to make absolutely clear the firm proposals put forth by the Unified
                    Command at Panmunjom: (1) No force of any kind should be used on prisoners of
                    war; (2) Any group, whether a Commission or anything else, having the task of
                    applying the <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POW</gloss> provisions, must be clearly
                    organized and completely workable. If both sides have equal representation then
                    there must be an umpire. Otherwise a stalemate would exist. The problem of
                    solving the ultimate disposition of prisoners of war could not be worked out in
                    New York but only in Panmunjom by the men who knew all the related problems and
                    complicating factors; (3) Regardless of who would be in charge of determining
                    the wishes of the prisoners of war, there must be two exits: one for those who
                    wish to return and the other for those who refuse. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1"
                        >Menon</persName> had apparently been working on an idea which was
                    tantamount to having only one exit—that which led to repatriation. His idea
                    meant that the Unified Command would be required to use force, to turn them into
                    “a sausage machine” from which they could only emerge as “sausage”. This, of
                    course, was completely contrary to our position. Such was the “battle which had
                    raged” for the past few weeks.</p>
                <p>Every deviation from our principles pointed out in <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1"
                        >Menon</persName>’s draft was claimed by the Indian representative to be a
                    “typographical error”. The Secretary noted the text of the Indian resolution
                    which was before the Delegation, and which had not, up to that moment, been
                    tabled. In this text only the portion entitled “Proposals” was to be transmitted
                    to the Communists. He noted that whereas the idea that force was not to be used
                    was contained in the “inducing” paragraphs, it had been dropped out of the
                    proposals. There was a further confusion between paragraphs 8 and 9 which
                    literally meant that force was both in and out. This kind of operation was what
                    made one wonder whether <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> was trying
                    to achieve the same results as we were, said the Secretary. Furthermore,
                    paragraph 16 referred to the turning over of unrepatriated prisoners of war to
                    the post-armistice political conference. In simple terms this meant a
                    continuation of the deadlock. The Secretary had told <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> that there must be two exits, one for
                    those who wanted to go home, the other for those who would be released as free
                    men. The Secretary had suggested that there was really no problem in connection
                    with releasing North Koreans who did not want to go back to the Communist
                    regime. It was like people from Connecticut being released in New Jersey where
                    they speak the same language, have the same culture and simply live in another
                    part of the same country. As far as the Chinese Communists, who were unwilling
                    to return, were concerned, there were some 15,000 of them. When <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> had protested <pb facs="0689" n="655"
                        xml:id="pg_655"/> about the trouble necessitated by taking care of them, the
                    Secretary had replied that it was certainly no worse than the problems entailed
                    with the hundreds of thousands of Palestine refugees. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> had then expressed concern that
                        <persName corresp="#p_CKS1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName> might get these men.
                    The Secretary had pointed out that some 83,000 would be going back to the
                    Chinese Communists and that we could be expected to do much more to live up to
                    the armistice agreement which prohibited enlisting former prisoners of war on
                    our side than the Communists with regard to those going back to Communist
                    China.</p>
                <p>Finally, the Secretary said that <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName>
                    planned to table his resolution very soon, but whether it would be better or
                    worse than the draft we had seen was completely unknown. Mrs.
                        <persName>Roosevelt</persName> pointed out that the Indian draft resolution
                    made no provision for a Chairman for the Commission. The Secretary recalled that
                    paragraph 13 spoke in somewhat unclear terms of an umpire. This man would not be
                    a member of the Commission, but would apparently only walk into the Commission
                    Room when there was disagreement and magically solve all problems. What the
                    Indians, or at least <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName>, did not
                    understand was that the umpire would be the sole administrative officer. No
                    provision had been made for housing, feeding, clothing, or otherwise taking care
                    of the prisoners of war. The Secretary said that perhaps one <gloss
                        target="#t_POWs1">POW</gloss> camp at a time could be declared a
                    demilitarized zone where the Commission could take charge. He thought that
                    perhaps <persName corresp="#p_CGMW1">General Clark</persName> might be able to
                    work this out.</p>
                <p>The Secretary indicated that the Indian draft had gone to Washington where the
                    Joint Chiefs of Staff and State Department officers had worked on it Friday
                    night and all day Saturday.<note n="4" xml:id="d333fn4">For the formal
                        consultations between the Joint Chiefs and the Department of State, see the
                        memorandum of discussion, Nov. 15, <ref target="#pg_634">p.
                        634</ref>.</note> They had reworded it so as to be acceptable to the United
                    States. <persName corresp="#p_BGOTAON1">General Bradley</persName> and Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_LRA1">Lovett</persName> had come to New York on Sunday
                    and, after a meeting with the members of the Delegation, had spoken to some of
                    the representatives of the group of twenty-one powers who had become a little
                    weak on this matter.<note n="5" xml:id="d333fn5">For a report on the meeting
                        with the British and Canadians, see the draft memorandum of conversation,
                        Nov. 16, <ref target="#pg_637">p. 637</ref>.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGOTAON1">General Bradley</persName> had pointed out to
                    them that the Unified Command could not run the risk, if rioting should break
                    out among the prisoners of war, of not being able to handle matters
                    appropriately.</p>
                <p>The group of twenty-one was to meet that morning and consider the Indian draft
                    and our reactions to it. It might be possible to amend the twenty-one power
                    draft resolution with the acceptable parts of the Indian draft. On the other
                    hand, we could let <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> go ahead with
                    his draft and seek to amend it. There was one danger in following the latter
                    course. This was that each time a change was made we would <pb facs="0690"
                        n="656" xml:id="pg_656"/> have to be sure that all the twenty-one powers
                    knew where we stood with regard to it. Since inertia tended to operate against
                    rather than for amendments, it would be easier to follow the course of amending
                    our own resolution. However, it might be necessary to go along with <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> to the extent of trying to amend his
                    resolution. We might so amend his resolution that he would be unable to vote for
                    it. The Secretary asked Senator <persName>Wiley</persName> if he had any
                    comments.</p>
                <p>Senator <persName>Wiley</persName>
                    <note n="6" xml:id="d333fn6">Senator <persName>Alexander Wiley</persName>, U.S.
                        Representative at the Seventh UN General Assembly.</note> said “your wisdom
                    is so immense that I have nothing to say”. The Secretary answered that it was
                    not wisdom, but patience which was required in this situation. Admiral
                        <persName>Struble</persName>
                    <note n="7" xml:id="d333fn7">Vice Admiral <persName>Arthur D.
                        Struble</persName>, USN, Adviser to the U.S. Delegation at the Seventh UN
                        General Assembly.</note> had no comment to make. Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_GEA1">Gross</persName> noted that he had asked <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> whether the latter had given the
                    resolution with the “typographical error” in it to the Soviets. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> had dismissed this by saying that he
                    could always tell the Russians he might make changes in the text. Furthermore,
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> thought the attitude of the
                    Chinese Communists was much more important than that of the Russians. Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_GEA1">Gross</persName> said that he had raised this
                    simply to illustrate the “fuzziness” in the Indians’ thinking.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Charles Allen</persName>
                    <note n="8" xml:id="d333fn8">Director, Office of Public Affairs, U.S. Permanent
                        Mission at the United Nations.</note> referred to the press problems if
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> tabled his resolution and US
                    comment were sought. The Secretary agreed that this was an important aspect and
                    suggested emphasizing that he and others had pointed out our willingness to
                    accept constructive ideas not inconsistent with our principles. Then it could be
                    pointed out that there were certain disturbing elements in the Indian draft.
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GEA1">Gross</persName> felt that what was told
                    to the twenty other sponsors would doubtless become public. He thought we should
                    be frank both with them and with the public, which would amount to the same
                    thing.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Sprague</persName>
                    <note n="9" xml:id="d333fn9">
                        <persName>Charles A. Sprague</persName>, U.S. Alternate Representative at
                        the Seventh UN General Assembly.</note> cautioned against allowing our own
                    public opinion to become fuzzy. He felt that we should make clear what was
                    unacceptable without saying we were against the whole thing. Mr.
                        <persName>Allen</persName> agreed with this.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JPC1">Jessup</persName> suggested an
                    off-the-record or background press conference to accomplish the desired result.
                    Mr. <persName>Charles Allen</persName> noted that this idea had been discussed
                    and thought that the time might be at hand.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Sprague</persName> considered Korea to be the big question for the
                    American public, and suggested that we would have to “walk warily, but in a
                    straight line”.</p>
                <pb facs="0691" n="657" xml:id="pg_657"/>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GEA1">Gross</persName> thought that it would be
                    necessary for the Secretary to make another speech in the First Committee that
                    week. He warned that U.S. statements outside the Committee Room made our friends
                    think that we were taking the debate beyond the Assembly. He recalled an example
                    where after <persName>Zafrulla Khan</persName>’s<note n="10" xml:id="d333fn10">
                        <persName>Mohammad Zafrullah Khan</persName>, Pakistani Minister of Foreign
                        and Commonwealth Relations and Chairman of the Pakistani Delegation at the
                        Seventh UN General Assembly.</note> speech our opposition to his ideas had
                    been set forth in a background conference. This position had been picked up by
                    the paper as “a U.S. Delegate said…<note n="11" xml:id="d333fn11">Ellipsis in
                        the source text.</note> etc.”, and the Danish Delegation, for one, had told
                    us they felt this to be an unfortunate way of handling the matter.</p>
                <p>Mrs. <persName>Roosevelt</persName> said that it was important to point out the
                    things in a document which a newspaperman might not see. Stories were often
                    written based on a quick scanning of a document without a detailed knowledge
                    having been applied to it. Unless they were trained to look at the implications
                    behind the words, they might get the wrong idea entirely. Mr. <persName>Charles
                        Allen</persName> said that this could be and had been done. He suggested
                    that ten or twelve trusted American correspondents, who needed guidance very
                    badly, could be given this kind of information and thereby avoid unnecessary
                    commotion. The Secretary said that he would be glad to speak to the newsmen, but
                    had certain time limitations. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JPC1"
                        >Jessup</persName> suggested that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GEA1"
                        >Gross</persName> and Mr. <persName>Charles Allen</persName> handle this if
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> introduced his resolution.
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GEA1">Gross</persName> reported that <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> had told a United Kingdom representative
                    that he would table his resolution that morning. However, one never knew with
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> just what he was going to do.
                    Mr. <persName>Charles Allen</persName> suggested making quite sure with the
                    Indians when they would table their resolution and then quickly setting up a
                    background conference. After this was agreed to, the meeting was adjourned.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles D. Cook</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
