<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-04-15T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-04-15T07:00:00-05:00" n="460" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d460">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/4–1553: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Korea (<persName corresp="#p_BEO1" type="from">Briggs</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>priority</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Pusan</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-04-15T21:00:00+09:00">April 15, 1953—9
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1225. Rptd info <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss> eyes only
                                <persName corresp="#p_CGMW1">Clark</persName>
                            <gloss target="#t_DIP1">DIP</gloss> 464. Had lengthy conversation with
                            President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> yesterday with
                            reference to Korea’s attitude toward international developments
                            especially those brought up by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YCY1">Yang</persName> during conversation with Secretary on April 8,<note n="1" xml:id="d460fn1">For a report on this discussion, see the
                                memorandum of conversation, <ref target="#pg_897">p.
                                897</ref>.</note> including <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s five points and possibility of US–Korean security
                            pact.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item><p><persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> declared he does not
                                    want to rock boat and he deeply appreciates US aid without which
                                    his country would collapse but he wants peace with unification
                                    all Korea and he continues doubt whether such peace obtainable
                                    by program envisaged today by US and UN, namely (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) exchange sick and wounded <gloss target="#t_PW1">PW</gloss>’s (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                                    conclusion armistice along lines last autumn’s negotiations
                                    (Article 4 draft armistice agreement). President explained at
                                    length reasons for these beliefs which I gather are already
                                    largely known to Department. He was particularly emphatic
                                    regarding futility of political conference as vaguely defined in
                                    Article 4 which meeting he declares is perfect target for Commie
                                    tactics of indefinite delay while Commie efforts redoubled to
                                    subvert South Korea. <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>
                                    continues to urge “peace through victory” failing that, Commies
                                    should be told that as earnest of good faith Chinese forces in
                                    Korea should withdraw north of Yalu, after which peace
                                    conference could convene with some prospect of success.</p>
                                <p>Turning to immediate forthcoming problems of armistice
                                    negotiations, President said he greatly preoccupied lest talks
                                    merely duplicate period July 1951 to November 1952. He declared
                                    Korean people cannot endure another interminable fruitless
                                    session.</p>
                                <p>Would it not be possible President asked for US Government give
                                    assurance that if Commies do not within few days of resumption
                                    of armistice negotiations show unmistakable evidence of real
                                    desire for peace, negotiations will be terminated? President
                                    reiterated that moral Korean people cannot support further delay
                                    although at same time he insisted <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> army eager to get on with war, even alone if
                                    necessary. He also stated he lacks confidence in good faith
                                    Commie peace initiative to which I replied it was unnecessary
                                    believe in Commie good faith as prerequisite to testing whether
                                    peace move genuine in so far Korea concerned.</p></item>
                            <pb facs="0945" n="911" xml:id="pg_911"/>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item><p>Conversation on <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s
                                    side punctuated with repeated complaints over alleged cavalier
                                    treatment of Korean views or ignoring of Korean views and also
                                    with references to fourth of <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s five points: “Official representative of
                                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> shall participate fully
                                    in any international conference or meeting discussing or
                                    considering any phase of Korean problem.”</p>
                                <p>Without accepting foregoing at face value, Korean views
                                    nevertheless cannot altogether be dismissed. Some part of our
                                    present difficulty with <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> may result from belief on his part that
                                    having shouted unheeded in the wilderness, he is now obliged
                                    enter market place and speak his piece there, if not regardless
                                    of embarrassment that may cause us, at least in hopes that
                                    public declaration of his views may prove more effective
                                    propellant than further unpublicized discussions. This it seems
                                    to me is more likely explanation of <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s attitude (based on frustration) than
                                    desire on his part deliberately to cause trouble or to make US
                                    Government role more difficult.</p>
                                <p>When I asked what <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>
                                    would like to suggest as specific measure adopted to meet
                                    situation described President said “we don’t ask anything from
                                    America except not to be taken for granted;” when I pressed for
                                    less general answer he said that although Panmunjom talks have
                                    included Korean liaison officers, latter have really been merely
                                    subordinates of UN commander, rather than representatives of
                                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Government (or of
                                    President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>). What he
                                    would like therefore is “genuine Korean Government
                                    representative,” responsible to him as <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> President, attached to <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> negotiating group. <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> explained that by this he did not picture
                                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> representative at
                                    council table across from Commies arguing or disputing with
                                        <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> representative and thus
                                    disclosing division among allies, since before Commies we must
                                    always show solid front. What he has in mind <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> said is mechanism whereby
                                    Korean point of view may be made clear to <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> negotiators before those
                                    negotiators meet Commies (for example by having <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> representative present at
                                    Munsan headquarters) together with arrangement permitting <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> representative to attend
                                    Panmunjom sessions, even though he may take little or no part in
                                    discussion.</p></item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item><p>With reference to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YCY1">Yang</persName>’s talk with Secretary on April 8, President
                                    said thus far he has received only brief telegraphic summary
                                    (which I gather is less informative than Department’s telegram
                                    634 April 11).<note n="2" xml:id="d460fn2">Not printed.
                                        (795.00/4–1153)</note> I accordingly went over points set
                                    forth Department’s telegram 634 and suggested that as soon as
                                    awaited airmail summary from Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YCY1">Yang</persName> arrives, we have further
                                    meeting.</p>
                                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> then made
                                    following statement substance of which he requested I convey to
                                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> and
                                    through him to President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>:</p>
                                <pb facs="0946" n="912" xml:id="pg_912"/>
                                <p>Please say said President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> that our people are terribly tired. For
                                    you, with all respect, this has been a distant war, but for us
                                    all our country has been devastated and our capital city
                                    destroyed and our industries ruined. For three years we have
                                    existed on a hope. We have tried as hard as we can and you have
                                    given us wonderful support. I know you have to make very
                                    difficult world decisions; I know that to you Korea is only one
                                    of many places where Commie gangsters have to be faced. What
                                    little I have been able to do has been to hold my people
                                    together. I am old and tired, and my life—win or lose—is nearly
                                    over. My value to my people is the faith they have that all my
                                    life I have fought for Korean independence; my value to your
                                    government is that the Korean people trust me. If the American
                                    Government can give Korea security pact, that is what Korean
                                    people most need to help them continue fighting. But if American
                                    Government cannot give us security pact, then unilateral
                                    declaration would be next most helpful, even though Commies
                                    would probably try to exploit it as without any binding effect.
                                    So I say that if bilateral pact would make difficulties for us,
                                    then recognizing your problems within which Korea perhaps seems
                                    small to you, I hope at least your government can make statement
                                    saying that no matter what happens, American Government will not
                                    forget Korea. If President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> himself could make declaration on
                                    Korea’s behalf, President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> said that would be particularly effective
                                    insofar as Korean people concerned and be especially appreciated
                                    by him.</p></item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_BEO1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Briggs</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>