<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-05-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-05-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="507" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d507">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/5–853</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for
                                Far Eastern Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RWS1" type="from">Robertson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d507fn1">This memorandum
                                was drafted by <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName>. A
                                marginal note by <persName corresp="#p_OCRL1">O’Connor</persName> on
                                the source text indicated that the Secretary saw it on May
                            8.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-05-08">May 8, 1953</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Communist Proposal on <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POW</gloss>
                                Question</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Although we can probably somewhat mitigate the effects on India by
                            pointing out we are only adopting the formula embodied in the Indian
                            Resolution, a refusal by the U.S. to accept the Communist proposal for
                            India as the fifth member of the commission will undoubtedly offend
                            India and be exploited to the maximum by Communist and other unfriendly
                            propaganda within and without India. Agreeing to a formula which makes
                            the appointment of India virtually inevitable would not appear to do
                            much to mitigate the domestic aspects of the acceptance of India. Thus
                            we will end up with most of the international disadvantages of having
                            refused India as well as the domestic disadvantages of having accepted
                            India. India will enter on its duties on the commission more or less
                            offended by us and probably less subject to our influence than if we had
                            accepted India. Thus if we are willing to accept or acquiesce in India
                            being a member of the commission, <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> most
                            strongly recommends that we simply accept the Communist proposal in this
                            regard. In view of the previous consultations with Congressional leaders
                            we recommend that they be informed prior to such action becoming
                            public.</p>
                        <p>In so far as eventual disposition of prisoners are concerned there are
                            only three basic possibilities: (1) specifically provide in the
                            armistice agreement that prisoners are to be released by the commission
                            on the expiration of the period of custody or failure of political
                            conference to agree upon their disposition within a specified time
                            limit, to proceed to an available destination of their choice; (2) leave
                            the decision of the disposition of the remaining prisoners to the
                            commission; (3) provide for a UN decision for their disposition.</p>
                        <p>It will be extremely difficult to obtain agreement on the first formula.
                            Under the proposed Communist composition of the commission, the <pb facs="1029" n="995" xml:id="pg_995"/> second formula would present
                            serious dangers that at the least the prisoners would be indefinitely
                            held. The third formula was embodied in the Indian Resolution. While not
                            ideal, it may be the best obtainable.</p>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> seriously questions the workability of
                            a plan providing for custody of the prisoners being held by the combined
                            armed forces of five such dissimilar states as Poland, Czechoslovakia,
                            Sweden, Switzerland and India. The plan might be much more workable if
                            the required armed forces were furnished by India alone, acting under
                            the supervision of five members of the commission.</p>
                        <p>As <persName corresp="#p_CGMW1">General Clark</persName> states in his
                            message today (CX 62301)<note n="2" xml:id="d507fn2">Dated May 8, <ref target="#pg_987">p. 987</ref>.</note> “I believe we must realize
                            that we and the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s would be faced with
                            approximately 2500 carefully selected and thoroughly indoctrinated
                            Communist military thugs, not to mention such others as may be
                            introduced to ‘explain’ to the non-repatriates their rights, at mainland
                            or island installations, all free to engage in espionage and disorder”.
                            As <persName corresp="#p_CGMW1">Clark</persName> also points out the
                                <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> will violently oppose having
                            military forces of Communist satellite countries in Korea and probably
                            even on the offlying islands.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>