<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-05-22T18:58:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-05-22T18:58:00-05:00" n="544" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d544">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source"><persName corresp="#p_MHF1">Matthews</persName> files, lot 53 D 413: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Joint Chiefs of Staff</gloss>
                                to the Commander in Chief, Far East (<persName corresp="#p_CGMW1" type="to">Clark</persName>)</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret<lb/>operational
                                    immediate</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-05-22T19:58:00-04:00">May 22, 1953—7:58
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 939673. From <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss> reur CX
                                62456<note n="1" xml:id="d544fn1">Dated May 16, <ref target="#pg_1033">p. 1033</ref>.</note> and C 62419.<note n="2" xml:id="d544fn2">Dated May 14, <ref target="#pg_1022">p.
                                1022</ref>.</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <item><p><hi rend="italic">Part I</hi>.</p>
                                <p>1. Concur time has come take positive steps to bring negots to
                                    head and best method to attain this objective is to present our
                                    minimum posns on basic issues with air of finality.</p>
                                <p>2. As stated in para 3 <hi rend="italic">b</hi> of <gloss target="#t_DA1">DA</gloss> 938571,<note n="3" xml:id="d544fn3">Dated May 9, <ref target="#pg_997">p.
                                            997</ref>.</note> we did not consider ourselves bound by
                                    exact terms of <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> resolution
                                    of 3 Dec 52 (Indian resolution); moreover, we did not consider
                                    this resolution forestalled our attempting to obtain better
                                    terms. However, it must be recognized that our vote in the
                                        <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> in favor of this
                                    resolution leads Commies to conclusion that we are prepared
                                    accept principles of resolution and probably will not break on
                                    anything short of it. The tactics in the negots appear to bear
                                    this out. Moreover, we are under intensive pressure from our
                                    Allies to adhere closely to principles of the <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> resolution. Under
                                    circumstances, believe any further attempt obtain agreement on
                                    markedly more favorable terms not only futile but also
                                    undesirable. Therefore, we now consider that minimum posn which
                                    we next propose shld be in general consonance with <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> resolution. At same time
                                    under these conditions we consider it essential that terms of
                                    reference of custodial commission sustain the principle of no
                                    forced repatriation and insure that coercion and force not be
                                    used against non-repatriates. <pb facs="1117" n="1083" xml:id="pg_1083"/> If the Commies accept, we will have
                                    tolerable arrangement. On other hand, if they reject we will be
                                    in strongest possible posn to terminate negots.</p>
                                <p>3. Accordingly, PresUS has directed <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> set forth a final posn which incorporates folg
                                    essential elements: <list>
                                        <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>Maintenance of our present posn on accepting a
                                            five-nation custodial comsn, subj to condition that all
                                            armed forces and operating psnl be provided exclusively
                                            by India.</item>
                                        <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>Revise our present posn on immediate release Korean
                                            non-repatriates upon coming into effect of armistice so
                                            as to agree that Korean non-repatriates be turned over
                                            to comsn in same manner as Chinese.</item>
                                        <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>Revise our present posn that comsn will act on basis
                                            of unanimity on substantive matters, so as to agree that
                                            all decisions of comsn shall be by majority vote.</item>
                                        <label><hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>Maintenance of all elements of present posn re terms
                                            of reference for operation of custodial comsn, which are
                                            nec to assure that right of Chi Commies and North Korean
                                            access to <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss> is subj
                                            to conditions which will prevent use of coercion and
                                            force against non-repatriates. We consider folg elements
                                            essential: <list>
                                                <label>(1)</label>
                                                <item>That provision be made that no force or threat
                                                  of force shall be used against <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss> to prevent or
                                                  affect their repatriation.</item>
                                                <label>(2)</label>
                                                <item>That there be limitation on number of staff
                                                  assistants allowed to reptvs of 4 nations on comsn
                                                  other than India. Exact number left to ur
                                                  discretion.</item>
                                                <label>(3)</label>
                                                <item>That <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>
                                                  observers are present to observe operations of
                                                  custodial comsn and subordinate bodies to include
                                                  verifications and interviews as indicated in (5)
                                                  below.</item>
                                                <label>(4)</label>
                                                <item>That there be limitation on number of
                                                  verifying reptvs permitted access to <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss>. Exact number left
                                                  ur discretion.</item>
                                                <label>(5)</label>
                                                <item>That all verifications and interviews be
                                                  conducted in presence of reptvs of each member
                                                  nation of comsn.</item>
                                                <label>(6)</label>
                                                <item>That there be provision along lines indicated
                                                  in para 10 C 62385<note n="4" xml:id="d544fn4">Not
                                                  printed, but see the editorial note, <ref target="#pg_1020">p. 1020</ref>.</note> amended to
                                                  include provision that certificates submitted by
                                                  <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss> indicating
                                                  desire be repatriated must be validated by
                                                  majority vote of custodial comsn or subordinate
                                                  body.</item>
                                                <label>(7)</label>
                                                <item>That custodial comsn permit access of press to
                                                  entire opn. Not considered essential press
                                                  admitted to <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POW</gloss>
                                                  installations <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>
                                                  area be restricted to reptvs accredited <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>. Present proposal in
                                                  para 13 of C 62385 shld be amended
                                                  accordingly.</item>
                                                <label>(8)</label>
                                                <item>Para 14 of C 62385 providing for logistical
                                                  support of <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss>.</item>
                                                <label>(9)</label>
                                                <item>Para 15 of C 62385 providing for cost of
                                                  repatriating <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss>
                                                  be borne by detaining power in accordance with Art
                                                  118 of Geneva Conv.</item>
                                                <label>(10)</label>
                                                <item>Para 22 of C 62385 providing that terms of
                                                  agreement be made known to all non-repatriate
                                                  <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss>.</item>
                                            </list></item>
                                        <label><hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>Maintenance our previously planned final posn that
                                            period of access by each side to non-repatriates will be
                                            90 days.</item>
                                        <label><hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>To our previously planned final posn that we agree to
                                            submission to polit conf of question of disposition of
                                            remaining non-repatriates with <pb facs="1118" n="1084" xml:id="pg_1084"/> provision that failing
                                            determination their disposition within total of 120 days
                                            of their being handed over to custodial comsn they would
                                            be released (i.e. para 3 <hi rend="italic">d</hi> CX
                                            62456) add the alternative that question of disposition
                                            of remaining non-repatriates, after same 120 days, would
                                            be promptly referred to <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> with custodial comsn retaining custody
                                            of non-repatriates until decision reached by <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>. We would accept
                                            Communist choice of either alternative.</item>
                                    </list></p>
                                <p>4. If we are to maximize possibilities of Commie acceptance,
                                    manner of presentation and public info handling most important.
                                    While it must be made clear to Commies that these are, in fact,
                                    our final posns, <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> shld avoid
                                    insofar as possible, the aspects of an ultimatum which would
                                    render Commie acceptance more difficult. We believe that this
                                    can best be accomplished by presenting our proposals in exec
                                    session, whereby <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> would be
                                    better enabled make clear that <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> posn is final while avoiding adverse effects of
                                    public ultimatum which would be inherent in presentation of
                                    final posn in open session. We further believe <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> presentation shld be from
                                    standpoint of using proposal of 7 May as basis along lines of
                                        <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> 13 May presentation.
                                        <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> shld avoid connotation
                                    that <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> proposal is counter
                                    proposal and shld avoid use of specific terms such as “final”
                                    “take it or leave it”, etc. In proposing exec sessions the
                                        <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> shld make clear that
                                    purpose of such sessions is not to bargain as has sometimes in
                                    past been the case when one side has requested exec sessions,
                                    but rather to reinforce the solemn, non-propaganda character of
                                    the proceedings. If Commies reject exec sessions, <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> shld proceed with presentation
                                    final posn, but bearing in mind desirability of avoiding
                                    ultimatum aspects.</p>
                                <p>5. If on resumption negots folg one week recess (referred to in
                                    para 4 of CX 62456) Commies reject <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> proposals, make no proposal of their own
                                    incorporating basic principles of <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> proposals, or otherwise provide no basis for
                                    further useful negots, we consider that negots shld be
                                    terminated rather than recessed, and agreements affecting the
                                    Kaesong–Panmunjom–Munsan area shld be voided. While we might at
                                    some future time be prepared to renew negots on basis of current
                                    draft armistice agreement and currently outstanding <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> proposals re <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss>, we consider it undesirable
                                    for you to indicate that such might be the case. We do not wish
                                    place burden of decision to terminate either upon you or
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HMGWKJ1">Gen Harrison</persName>,
                                    feeling that such responsibility properly rests in Washington.
                                    It is to be expected that Commie reply will be neither a flat
                                    rejection nor acceptance of <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>
                                    proposals and will require careful assessment before decision to
                                    terminate actually can be made.</p></item>
                            <item><p><hi rend="italic">Part II</hi>.</p>
                                <p>6. In accordance with foregoing you are directed: <pb facs="1119" n="1085" xml:id="pg_1085"/>
                                    <list>
                                        <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>At mtg scheduled 25 May propose exec sessions and
                                            submit proposal incorporating final posns set forth in
                                            para 3 above. If Commies do not agree to exec session
                                            proceed to submit proposal in open session.</item>
                                        <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>Having submitted proposal, <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> will recess, unilaterally if nec, for
                                            one week to allow Commies time for consideration.</item>
                                        <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>During period of recess you will submit ltr<note n="5" xml:id="d544fn5">Not printed, but see footnote 6,
                                                  <ref target="#pg_1035">p. 1035</ref>.</note> to
                                            Commies as envisaged in para 5 of CX 62456, designed to
                                            reflect and reinforce approach indicated in para 4 this
                                            msg. Desire you submit text of ltr for approval prior to
                                            delivery.</item>
                                        <label><hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>If on resumption of negots folg one week recess
                                            Commies reject <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>
                                            proposals and make no proposal of their own
                                            incorporating basic principles <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> proposal, <persName corresp="#p_HMGWKJ1">Harrison</persName> shld merely
                                            note Commie action and indicate such action poses a most
                                            serious situation which he feels compelled report to
                                            higher auth, and propose recess of 72 hours. You shld
                                            then submit promptly ur assessment of Commie reply along
                                            with ur recommended action. We will be prepared to act
                                            expeditiously.</item>
                                        <label><hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>On other hand if on resumption of negots folg one week
                                            recess Commies accept principles of <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> proposal or give other
                                            evidence of willingness reach agreement on acceptable
                                            basis, you are authorized continue negots within
                                            framework of Part I this msg.</item>
                                    </list></p></item>
                            <item><p><hi rend="italic">Part III</hi>.</p>
                                <p>7. When and if decision is made to terminate negots you then
                                    authorized to: <list>
                                        <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>Inform Commies, by means of ur own choosing and at
                                            earliest possible time, that agreements affecting
                                            Munsan–Panmunjom–Kaesong area are voided.</item>
                                        <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>Undertake mil action indicated in Part 2 <hi rend="italic">a</hi> of C 62419.</item>
                                        <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>Effect prompt release of all non-repatriate <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss>. Instructions will
                                            subsequently be transmitted you re procedures for
                                            release and disposition of Chi non-repatriates.</item>
                                    </list></p></item>
                            <item><p><hi rend="italic">Part IV</hi>.</p>
                                <p>8. Re para 3 <hi rend="italic">b</hi> above. We fully appreciate
                                    sit <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> faces with <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> on issue release of Korean
                                    non-repatriates. However, immediate release of Korean
                                    non-repatriates upon coming into effect of an armistice, is not
                                    an essential element of our posn on no forced repatriation and
                                    has failed to comd any support outside Korea. It is not an issue
                                    on which we can permit negots to break down. By separate
                                        msg<note n="6" xml:id="d544fn6"><hi rend="italic"><ref target="#d545">Infra</ref></hi>.</note> through
                                    State channels you are being directed to undertake joint
                                    approach to <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> with
                                        <persName corresp="#p_BEO1">Briggs</persName>. Desire that
                                    on morning of 25 May prior to reconvening of negots you inform
                                        <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> of action <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> taking in negots and undertake
                                    with <persName corresp="#p_BEO1">Briggs</persName> approach
                                    outlined in State msg mentioned above. For security reasons we
                                    believe it undesirable inform <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> that we intend terminate negots if Commies
                                    reject <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> proposals, although
                                    you might indicate that Commie rejection would leave little
                                    grounds for further negots. However, this matter is left to ur
                                    discretion.</p>
                                <pb facs="1120" n="1086" xml:id="pg_1086"/>
                                <p>9. Ref para 3 <hi rend="italic">c</hi> above. You shld bear in
                                    mind that our willingness to agree to simple majority vote for
                                    all decisions by the cmsn is subj to Commie agreement on the
                                    essential elements in terms of reference for cmsn as set forth
                                    in para 3 <hi rend="italic">d</hi>. Method of handling this in
                                    negots left to ur discretion.</p>
                                <p>10. Re para 3 <hi rend="italic">f</hi>. above. Assurances being
                                    sought from other UN Govts having forces in Korea that they will
                                    support immediate consideration of a resolution in UN calling
                                    for prompt release of non-repatriates to proceed to any
                                    available destination of their choice.</p></item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>