<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Joint Chiefs of Staff to the Commander in Chief Far East
                    (Ridgway)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v15p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d59</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">59</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-03-15T19:44:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-03-15T19:44:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-03-15T19:44:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-03-15T19:44:00-05:00" n="59"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d59">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/3–2452: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Joint Chiefs of Staff</gloss> to the
                        Commander in Chief Far East (<persName corresp="#p_RGMB1" type="to"
                            >Ridgway</persName>)</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d59fn1">This telegram was the result of <persName
                            corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName>’s and Lt. Col <persName
                            corresp="#p_MHF1">Matthews</persName>’ combination of the drafts of the
                        Departments of State and Defense and the recommendations arising from the
                        discussion at the State-<gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> meeting of Mar.
                        12; see the memorandum of discussion, <ref target="#pg_82">p. 82</ref>. The
                        telegram was then discussed with President <persName corresp="#p_THS1"
                            >Truman</persName>, who approved it; see the memorandum, <hi
                            rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret<lb/>operational immediate</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-03-15T19:44:00-05:00"
                            >March 15, 1952—7:44 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 903687. From <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                        >JCS</gloss>.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>We have considered HNC 1033<note n="2" xml:id="d59fn2">Dated Mar. 11, <ref
                                target="#pg_80">p. 80</ref>.</note> and agree that time is near to
                        convince Communists of our determination to stand inflexibly on stated
                        minimum positions with respect to the three unresolved major issues and in
                        doing so to utilize fully the public backing of United States and Allied
                        Govts. We recognize that your recommended action represents one approach.
                        However, we feel that it may be more effective to present our minimum
                        positions on the three unresolved major issues in a single package rather
                        than on a piecemeal basis. Such an overall approach would possess certain
                        advantages in that it would have greater impact, it offers equal, if not
                        better, chances of acceptance by Communists, and, if rejected, would place
                        the <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> in a favorable position vis-à-vis
                        public opinion and international support should negotiations subsequently be
                        broken off by Communists.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Broad outline of this approach could be generally as follows: <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>Expedite resolution remaining minor issues at sub-del level. Those
                                not resolvable at sub-del level should be added to package indicated
                                in subpara D (1) below. (Your final and irrevocable positions on
                                such issues should be cleared with <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                                    >JCS</gloss> prior to presenting them as such to
                                Communists.)</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>As soon as minor issues are resolved or no further progress
                                thereon at sub-del level appears possible and you are prepared to
                                implement plans for reclassification and segregation <gloss
                                    target="#t_POWs1">POWs</gloss> as set forth in <gloss
                                    target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 902159,<note n="3" xml:id="d59fn3"
                                    >Dated Feb. 27, <ref target="#pg_70">p. 70</ref>.</note> negots
                                should be moved from sub-del level to plenary session.</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>At this plenary session review outstanding issues, seek to
                                determine whether Communists have any new suggestions for resolving
                                these issues, and assuming they do not, have <gloss target="#t_UNC1"
                                    >UNC</gloss> del propose on your behalf a mtg between yourself
                                and two opposing cdrs. This proposal should be substantiated by ltr
                                from you to two opposing cdrs to be delivered by <gloss
                                    target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> del. Your proposal for mtg should
                                be in such terms as would readily permit return of negotiations to
                                plenary session of dels if rejected. Date specified for such mtg to
                                be such as to allow prior implementation of plans for
                                reclassification and segregation <gloss target="#t_POWs1"
                                    >POWs</gloss> accordance <pb facs="0124" n="90" xml:id="pg_90"/>
                                subpara B above and announcement by you at such mtg along lines set
                                forth para 2, <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 902159.</item>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item>At mtg of senior cdrs: <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item>You would set forth final and irrevocable positions on
                                        major issues as follows and on such unresolved minor issues
                                        as have been approved previously by <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                                            >JCS</gloss>. <list>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>No restrictions in armistice agreement on
                                                reconstruction or rehabilitation of airfields. (In
                                                this connection if armistice is achieved, jt
                                                declaration will be issued in Washington as
                                                envisaged in <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                                                91600 and <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                                                  91602.)<note n="4" xml:id="d59fn4">Both dated Jan.
                                                  10, <ref target="#pg_13">pp. 13</ref> and <ref
                                                  target="#pg_14">14</ref>.</note>
                                            </item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Any one of folg alternatives, which we feel should
                                                be presented concurrently, concerning organization
                                                and composition of supervisory commission on which
                                                you can get agreement appears acceptable to US: <list>
                                                  <label>(<hi rend="italic">1</hi>)</label>
                                                  <item>As set forth in para 2 of <gloss
                                                  target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 902160,<note n="5"
                                                  xml:id="d59fn5">Dated Feb. 27, <ref
                                                  target="#pg_71">p. 71</ref>.</note> the “neutral”
                                                  designation of supervisory commission be entirely
                                                  eliminated and supervisory organization and
                                                  inspection teams be constituted to consist of
                                                  nations selected by each side regardless their
                                                  combatant status in Korean hostilities or
                                                  acceptability to other side. Under this proposal
                                                  <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> would be free
                                                  to select any countries whether or not
                                                  partcipating in hostilities and Commies would have
                                                  similar right to select any countries. In event
                                                  Commies select USSR (or Communist China) as mbr it
                                                  would then be mandatory that mbrs from our side
                                                  include United States. View here is that while
                                                  Soviet Union (or Communist China) entirely
                                                  unacceptable in position of “neutral” there is no
                                                  objection to Soviet Union as mbr of supervisory
                                                  commission that is not identified as “neutral”
                                                  provided United States is also mbr. Commission
                                                  would then be composed of United States along
                                                  with, for example, Sweden and Switzerland on our
                                                  side, while on Communist side Poland,
                                                  Czechoslovakia and USSR would be acceptable;
                                                  or</item>
                                                  <label>(<hi rend="italic">2</hi>)</label>
                                                  <item>Along lines already agreed in principle on
                                                  this issue, that is, composed of “neutral”
                                                  (noncombatant) countries acceptable to each side,
                                                  in which event <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>
                                                  refusal to accept Soviet Union as mbr of “neutral”
                                                  supervisory commission is absolutely firm as
                                                  stated in para 1, <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                                                  >JCS</gloss> 902160; and</item>
                                                  <label>(<hi rend="italic">3</hi>)</label>
                                                  <item>Inspection behind lines of each side to be
                                                  carried out by inspection teams composed equally
                                                  of reptvs of belligerents from opposing side
                                                  responsible to mil armistice commission as set
                                                  forth in original proposal this subj made by
                                                  <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>. (This
                                                  proposal would only involve composition and
                                                  organization of inspection teams and would not
                                                  imply any renunciation by <gloss target="#t_UNC1"
                                                  >UNC</gloss> of any such agreements as have thus
                                                  far been reached between two sides on places at
                                                  which teams will be stationed and duties and
                                                  rights of such teams.)</item>
                                                </list>
                                            </item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>All for all exchange of <gloss target="#t_POWs1"
                                                  >POWs</gloss> based on lists revised by having
                                                removed therefrom those <gloss target="#t_POWs1"
                                                  >POWs</gloss> reclassified and segregated <pb
                                                  facs="0125" n="91" xml:id="pg_91"/> accordance
                                                  <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 902159 and
                                                presentation thereof to be along lines set forth
                                                para 2 that msg.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item>In presenting foregoing final positions you should present
                                        all of them in such a manner that your position on each of
                                        these questions is inseparably related to your position on
                                        each of the other questions and Communists or public opinion
                                        will not be able to interpret action as willingness to
                                        concede on one question without Communist acceptance your
                                        position on others. Positions should also be presented so
                                        that it will be clear that they do in fact represent our
                                        final and irrevocable positions. However, in so doing you
                                        should also present these positions as fair and reasonable
                                        reconciliation of opposing points of view in interest of
                                        prompt attainment of armistice.</item>
                                    <label>(3)</label>
                                    <item>You would express willingness forthwith to sign armistice
                                        on foregoing basis, and expectation that two opposing cdrs
                                        as parties principal will be able and willing to do
                                        same.</item>
                                    <label>(4)</label>
                                    <item>If, as is likely, enemy cdrs demur and request time for
                                        consideration, your position would be that of complete
                                        willingness to meet with them at such time as they are
                                        prepared to reply to your proposals. In any such subsequent
                                        mtg between you and opposing cdrs or mtgs in plenary session
                                        of dels you would, as appropriate, reiterate positions set
                                        forth in first mtg. While responding to any reasonable
                                        requests for amplification or explanation, you would avoid
                                        being drawn into any extended debate.</item>
                                    <label>(5)</label>
                                    <item>If Communists then flatly reject your package proposal
                                        your position would continue to be that it remains your
                                        final and best offer and that while you or <gloss
                                            target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> del continue willing to
                                        meet whenever Communists desire, you would refuse to be
                                        drawn into debate on individual points. It is important that
                                        our proffered package not become a new point of departure
                                        for negots on individual issues.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>If Communists reject your proposal for mtg of opposing cdrs: <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>Actions indicated in para 2 D above could be carried out in
                                plenary session; or</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>Appropriate parts of para 2 D above could be transmitted in formal
                                msg from you to opposing cdrs.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>In undertaking actions outlined you would be accorded full polit and dipl
                        support of United States Govt. The details of this remain to be
                        developed.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Request your comments. Pending receipt thereof final action on HNC 1033 is
                        withheld.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
