<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Northeast Asian Affairs (Young)
                    to the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs (Allison)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v15p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d83</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">83</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-04-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recXe3hjASdIXoUSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066112"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Inflation</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec_world_war_ii" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="world-war-ii" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148273" lcsh-match="exact">World War II</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-04-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="83"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d83">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795B.5 <gloss target="#t_MSP1"
                    >MSP</gloss>/3–3152</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Northeast Asian
                        Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_YKT1" type="from">Young</persName>) to the
                        Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs (<persName
                            corresp="#p_AJM1" type="to">Allison</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-04-04">April 4,
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Background Memorandum on the Objectives of the Special Presidential
                        Mission to Korea, and Major Issues to be Negotiated.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0174" n="140" xml:id="pg_140"/>
                <p>This memorandum is for your use in meeting with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCE1"
                        >Meyer</persName> and any other members of his mission.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">I. <hi rend="italic">Objectives</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The basic objective of the mission is to negotiate an agreement with the Republic
                    of Korea which will provide for the establishment and operation of joint
                    machinery to stabilize the economy. This involves the effective utilization of
                    United States economic aid, the adoption of appropriate fiscal and monetary
                    trade measures to alleviate the inflation, and provisions for settlement by the
                    United States for some of the won drawings under the Financial Agreement of July
                    28, 1950.</p>
                <p>We intend to emphasize the importance of establishing the proper negotiating
                    atmosphere prior to the discussions. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCE1"
                        >Meyer</persName> will be briefed on the political situation in Korea and
                    the general feeling of frustration which the Government apparently now has with
                    respect to its efforts to stabilize the economy.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">II. <hi rend="italic">Economic and Financial Issues</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There are the following economic and financial issues to be resolved during the
                    course of the negotiations.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">The payment of the accumulated dollars in the Suspense
                            Account</hi>. The Suspense Account contains the dollar equivalent of the
                        won which has been advanced by Korea to the Unified Command. The Financial
                        Agreement of July 28, 1950 provides that a future settlement will be made of
                        these won drawings at a mutually agreed time. The Korean Government has
                        requested that full settlement be made immediately, so that private imports
                        can be increased to alleviate the inflation. It is the opinion of the
                        concerned agencies in Washington that it would be unwise to turn over to the
                        Korean Government the balance in the Suspense Account, which totals over $70
                        million. This is Korea’s main foreign exchange asset, and considering the
                        uncertainty of future United States budgetary appropriations for economic
                        aid to Korea, this money can probably be better utilized at some future date
                        for basic rehabilitation purposes. It is felt that if the United States
                        proceeds on a current settlement basis most of the inflationary pressure can
                        be removed. In addition, the question of claims and counterclaims
                        complicates a settlement, and in accordance with practice in other countries
                        during World War II a settlement is more practicable after the cessation of
                        hostilities.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Joint control of foreign exchange of the Republic of
                            Korea</hi>. This was the main point of contention in the negotiations
                        between <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss> and the Korean
                        Government. The Korean Government has stated in the strongest terms that
                        joint control of all foreign exchange is an unwarranted infringement of its
                        sovereignty. President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> has
                        indicated, however, that he would agree to joint control of foreign exchange
                        arising from United Nations operations. The Department of State opposes <pb
                            facs="0175" n="141" xml:id="pg_141"/> joint control of all foreign
                        exchange. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FWC1">Foster</persName> and the fiscal
                        people in the Department of Defense favor it.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">The conversion rate of won to dollars</hi>. The present
                        rate of 6,000 to 1 has been in effect for a year and is no longer realistic.
                        The present Korean price level would justify a rate of at least 10,000 to 1.
                        The Korean Government, however, desires to continue the 6,000 rate because
                        it feels that further depreciation would accelerate the inflation.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Financial Agreement of July 28, 1950</hi>. The Korean
                        Government wishes to supplant it with a new agreement providing for current
                        settlements. <persName corresp="#p_RGMB1">General Ridgway</persName>, on the
                        other hand, desires to continue the Financial Agreement, which provides for
                        the won drawing privilege, in the light of the highly uncertain military
                        situation in Korea.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Effective machinery for joint economic planning</hi>. This
                        should not be a serious problem, since both the Korean Government and <gloss
                            target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss> agree to the need for some formal
                        arrangements for a joint effort. The mission can direct its efforts toward
                        insuring that such a committee will actually be effective.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Adjustment of dollar payments to the Korean Government for
                            those expenditures made by the Unified Command which can be considered a
                            proper burden for the Korean budget</hi>. Examples of this type of
                        expenditure are the Unified Command’s support of the Korean Railway and of
                        certain public utilities. It will be difficult to obtain agreement of the
                        Korean Government both on the principle involved and the criteria which will
                        be applied in application of the principle.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">III. <hi rend="italic">Other Issues</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There is attached my memorandum of March 31, 1952<note n="1" xml:id="d83fn1">Not
                        printed; see footnote 5, <ref target="#pg_124">p. 124</ref>.</note>
                    outlining State’s opposition to a civil affairs agreement. This matter has been
                    deleted from our redraft of the terms of reference. Defense will probably fight
                        this.<note n="2" xml:id="d83fn2">As a result of staff level discussions
                        between the Departments of State and Defense, <persName corresp="#p_MCE1"
                            >Meyer</persName> was provided with only discretionary authority,
                        subject to further instructions from Washington, to initiate negotiations
                        with the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> for a Civil Affairs Agreement;
                        telegrams <gloss target="#t_Topad1">Topad</gloss> 2667 to Tokyo and 719 to
                        Pusan, Apr. 5 and telegram 726 to Pusan, Apr. 10 (795B.5 <gloss
                            target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/4–552 and 795B.5 <gloss target="#t_MSP1"
                            >MSP</gloss>/3–2952, respectively).</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
