<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Seward to to Mr. Adams</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d258</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">258</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-06-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-06-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="258"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d258">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Adams</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-06-07">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 7, 1865</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> It is proper that you should be informed that the
                    Secretary of the Navy has, by direction of the President, issued orders to
                    Rear-Admiral Goldsborough, who is about to start in the steamship Colorado, as
                    commander of the United States squadron in European waters, to the following
                    effect:</p>
                <p>The admiral is charged not to enter any port, unless absolutely necessary, where
                    belligerent privileges may be extended to the United States rebels, or where
                    naval honors are, by governmental authority, withheld from the flag of the
                    United States. If an emergency should compel him to enter such a port, he is to
                    refrain from all courtesies required by the navy regulations in friendly foreign
                    ports, unless to return salutes.</p>
                <p>The admiral is also forbidden to exchange any of the customary courtesies with
                    the officers of foreign governments whom he may meet, which governments extend
                    belligerent privileges to the insurgents in this country, or deny customary
                    naval courtesies to the United States.</p>
                <p>It is proper that, as occasion may require, you should make this subject known to
                    the proper persons in the country where you reside.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Francis Adams,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic"
                            >&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>[Same to our principal ministers in Europe.]</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
