<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-12-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-12-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="28" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 840.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">London,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-12-22"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 22, 1864</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> In connexion with your despatch, No. 1164,
                            of the 29th of November, I have the honor now to transmit copies of a
                            letter addressed by me to Earl Russell on the 12th, and of his
                            lordship’s reply of the 16th instant, relative to General Dix’s report
                            of the hostile movements in Canada.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, &amp;c., &amp;c.,
                                &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Earl Russell</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United
                                            States,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">London,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-12-12"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 12, 1864</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord:</hi> I have the honor to submit to your
                                consideration a copy of a letter addressed to the Secretary of War,
                                at Washington, by the officer holding the chief command in the
                                military department embracing the northern frontier of the United
                                States. I have already been called upon to enter so fully into the
                                argument connected with this subject, that I deem it superfluous on
                                the present occasion to do more than to furnish this paper as an
                                additional illustration.</p>
                            <p>I pray your lordship to accept the assurance of the highest
                                consideration with which I have the honor to be, my lord, your
                                lordship’s most obedient servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>The Right Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Earl Russell,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><persName type="from">Earl Russell</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Adams</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-12-16"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 16, 1864,</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                receipt of your letter of the 12th instant, enclosing a copy of a
                                letter addressed to the Secretary of War of the, United States, by
                                the officer holding the chief command in the military department
                                embracing the northern frontier of the United States, respecting the
                                organization of a party of persons in Canada, apparently with a view
                                of hostile operations against the territory of the United
                                States.</p>
                            <p>I have to state to you, in reply, that the attention of her Majesty’s
                                government is very seriously directed to the means of preventing
                                such inroads on the territory of the United States-as that which is
                                commonly known by the name of the St. Albans raid.</p>
                            <p>If it should appear that the persons concerned in such inroads are
                                for any reason not subject to extradition, they and others must in
                                some way be effectually prevented from committing similar offences
                                against a neighboring state.</p>
                            <p>But I need scarcely point out to you that any invasion of the Canada
                                territory from the United States would excite hostile feelings in
                                Canada against the people of the United States, and might prove
                                extremely injurious to the pacific relations between the two
                                countries.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to be, with the highest consideration, sir, your
                                most obedient, humble servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>RUSSELL.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Francis Adams,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>