<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Seward to  to Mr.
                                Adams</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d60</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">60</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-01-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-01-18T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-01-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-01-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="60" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d60">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Adams</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1241.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-01-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 18, 1865</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I transmit herewith, authenticated under
                            the seal of this department, a copy of a joint resolution of the
                            Congress of the United States approved on this date, in regard to the
                            termination of the treaty concluded between the United States and her
                            Britannic Majesty on the 5th of June, 1854, commonly known as the
                            reciprocity treaty. The President directs me, in compliance with the 5th
                            article of that instrument, and with the requirement of the aforenamed
                            resolution, to instruct you to communicate to her Majesty’s government a
                            certified copy of the enclosed papers, and formally to notify her
                            Majesty’s government, on the 17th of March next, or as soon thereafter
                            as possible, that as it is considered to be no longer for the interest
                            of the United States to continue the said treaty in force, it will
                            terminate and be of no further effect at the expiration of twelve months
                            from the date upon which the notice shall be given.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Francis Adams</hi>. Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                    <p rend="center">THIRTY-EIGHTH CONGRESS, SECOND SESSION.</p>
                    <p>JOINT RESOLUTION providing for the termination of the reciprocity
                                treaty of fifth of June, eighteen hundred and fifty-four, between
                                the United States and Great Britain.</p>
                    <p>Whereas it is provided in the reciprocity treaty concluded at
                                Washington, the fifth of June, eighteen hundred and fifty four,
                                between the United States of the one part, and the United Kingdom of
                                Great Britain and Ireland of the other part, that this treaty “shall
                                remain in force for ten years from the date at which it may come
                                into operation, and further, until the expiration of twelve months
                                after either of the high contracting parties shall give notice to
                                the other of its wish to terminate the same;” and whereas it
                                appears, by a proclamation of the President of the United States,
                                bearing date sixteenth of March, eighteen hundred and fifty-five,
                                that the treaty came into operation on that day; and whereas,
                                further, it is no longer for the interests of the United States to
                                continue the same in force: Therefore,</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolved by the Senate and House of Representatives
                                    of the United States of America in Congress assembled,</hi> That
                                notice be given of the termination of the reciprocity treaty,
                                according to the provision therein contained for the termination of
                                the same; and the President of the United States is hereby charged
                                with the communication of such notice to the government of the
                                United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Approved <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-01-18">January 18,
                                1865</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
