<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Seward to to Mr. Adams</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d63</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">63</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-01-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-01-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-01-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-01-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="63"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d63">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Adams</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1245.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                                >Washington,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-01-23">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 23, 1865</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: It was my belief, when the election closed, that
                    the national determination which it manifested would tend to demoralize the
                    insurgents, and if not to confound, at least to embarrass their abettors abroad.
                    I thought that the decisive tone of the President’s message would be effective
                    in the same way. I have been unable to believe that insurgent confidence, either
                    at home or abroad, could revive under the severe pressure of the national arms.
                    Nevertheless, we have ever since the election had occasional revelations here
                    and in Europe of insurgent expectations of recognition by Great Britain and
                    France, These revelations have sometimes come in the shape of warnings from
                    known and responsible insurgent agents, who professed to be desirous of saving
                    their own misguided people from the infamy of foreign protection.</p>
                <p>It has been heretofore impossible to find a clue to the premises upon which their
                    expectations were based. I think I have now found it in an article of the
                    Richmond Sentinel of the 18th of January, a copy of which I enclose. The idea of
                    the insurgents seems to be this: That insomuch as the rebels are prevented the
                    exercise of suffrage in the insurgent States in the late presidential election,
                    therefore this government in the next administration will not be <hi
                        rend="italic">de jure,</hi> a government over these States, which by the
                    treaty of peace of 1783 were acknowledged to be free, independent, sovereign
                    States. The conceit is a refinement of the secession principle, which the war
                    has already effectually exploded. Still I have thought it not inexpedient to
                    bring the subject to your notice. While I do not attribute any serious
                    importance to it, it may be worth your while to be watchful.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Francis Adams</hi>. Esq., <hi rend="italic"
                            >&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <postscript>
                    <p>(Same to Mr. Bigelow.)</p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#center">[Editorial from the
                                <placeName>Richmond</placeName> Sentinel, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1865-01-18">January 18</date>. ]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <head>Foreign relations of the Confederacy.</head>
                    <p>The nations of western Europe have just put themselves and us to many
                        disadvantages by their failure to recognize the confederate government, and
                        institute with us diplomatic relations. A state of war invests with a
                        peculiar delicacy the relations of a belligerent with a mutual power. It
                        requires much care and address to adjust satisfactorily the many questions
                        which arise between them; especially is this the case while there is. much
                        conflict of interests, such as an extensive intercourse necessarily
                        produces. To all these hazards and inconveniences to them and to us France
                        and England have submitted for four years without the ameliorations which a
                        diplomatic interchange would have afforded. They have denied themselves and
                        us the means of asking or giving explanation, and of making representation
                        closely affecting in many cases the interests of citizens entitled to
                        protection, or, in a more general sense, the rights and duties of the
                        respective governments.</p>
                    <p>The great convenience of the policy long recognized in America, of
                        acknowledging a <hi rend="italic">de</hi>
                        <pb facs="0137" n="97" xml:id="pg_97"/>
                        <hi rend="italic">facto</hi> government without delay, has been strikingly
                        illustrated by the effect of the different principles which France and
                        England have prescribed to themselves in their dealings with us. If American
                        policy had been applied to American affairs four years of embarrassment
                        would have been avoided. There is a prevalent presumption, however, that the
                        reserve which has produced so much inconvenience is about to be abandoned.
                        It is supposed by many who read the signs of the times, that France and
                        England will not much longer deny themselves the liberty of holding
                        interviews with a people with whom they have so much business to transact.
                        We say nothing of the comity or the duty which they owe to an organized
                        community so large and respectable as ours; viewing the subject simply in
                        the light of their own interest, and of their duty to their own citizens,
                        the shackles with which they have so long voluntarily restrained their
                        action are truly extraordinary.</p>
                    <p>If the two governments to whom we refer have come to the resolution of
                        terminating that deference, not to the principles but to the will of the
                        Washington government, which wears the appearance of vassalage, they would
                        have at any moment an abundance of solid and satisfactory measures to
                        sustain them in such a step. But the conjecture which is assigned as the
                        probable occasion on which the new attitude will be assumed, the next
                        inauguration of Mr. Lincoln, is singularly propitious to such a proceeding.
                        It will afford not merely a pretext for that action, but a new ground;
                        sufficient of itself to justify and to require it. We will explain this by
                        the narration of some, facts which we find collected in a very convenient
                        form in Mr. McHenry’s excellent book, “The Cotton Trade.”</p>
                    <p>France, on the 5th of February, 1778, acknowledged the independence of the
                        thirteen American colonies <hi rend="italic">as so many independent
                            States.</hi> Even the Articles of Confederation were not then adopted.
                        The United Netherlands followed this example October 8, 1782, and Sweden,
                        April 3, 1783. Great Britain, in the treaty of peace, concluded September 3,
                        1783, recognized the several States in like manner as so many independent
                        political communities. This recognition embraced Virginia, North Carolina,
                        South Carolina, and Georgia, by name, and it territorially included
                        Tennessee, Florida, and Mississippi. The remaining confederate States became
                        possessed by their organization and admission of equal rights with the
                        original States, and stand on the same footing. The independent nationality
                        of Texas was; recognized by France in 1839, and by Great Britain in 1840.
                        She did not enter the Union, until 1845.</p>
                    <p>In no other form has the nationality of the United States ever been
                        acknowledged by European courts. John Adams was, in 1777, sent to represent
                        the States in France, and was soon after succeeded by Dr. Franklin. They
                        both received their authority from, the Congress of Delegates of the several
                        States. The Articles of Confederation were not adopted till March, 1781. Mr.
                        Adams, under an appointment received in 1789, remained as minister, to
                        England till 1798.</p>
                    <p>The Union formed by the Articles of Confederation was dissolved March 3,
                        1789. The Union under the Constitution did not go into operation until April
                        30, 1789, and then only as between eleven States, Rhode Island and North
                        Carolina for a time remaining aloof.</p>
                    <p>In all these changes of the agency for conducting their foreign intercourse,,
                        the States deemed no notification necessary to other governments. No
                        recognition was asked for any such nation as the confederation of States,
                        for there was no such created, nor for any such nation as the United States,
                        for the same reasons. The governments established by the Articles, of
                        Confederation and by the Constitution were the mere foreign agencies of the
                        States, the true sovereigns, whose nationality was already acknowledged. The
                        European governments conceded to us the right to change the form of this
                        agency whenever we pleased. The recognition of the independence of the
                        States survived all these changes unharmed; the disbanding of the
                        confederation in 1783, the intervening of fifty-eight days that followed,
                        the separation of the State, which then continued for some time, Rhode
                        Island and North Carolina remaining distinct, and the accessions to the
                        number of States, which afterwards occurred from time to time. The ministers
                        sent by the federal agent were received on the original acknowledgment of
                        the nationality of the several States, and no other. No other was desired;
                        no other was proffered; no other was thought necessary or appropriate. Let
                        us notice some of the consequences which may be deduced from this view of
                        the case, looking at it from a foreign stand-point, and excluding all
                        reference to our own controversy as to the right of secession. France and
                        England might say that Mr. Lincoln was appointed in 1860 by an election in
                        which all the States participated.; that thus he was regularly constituted
                        the diplomatic representative of all the States for a specified term; that
                        as such Europe recognized him as appointed, according to our own forms.
                        After the fourth of March next he will sustain, however, a new character. He
                        will have entered upon a term of service to, which various of the States
                        acknowledged by Europe as independent had no part in electing;: him. He
                        cannot claim to have any commission from Virginia or North Carolina, or the
                        rest of the Confederate States. He can show no authority to represent them.
                        These latter States at once refrained, and were excluded from all share in
                        his appointment. Of this Europe is duly notified, and it would be both an
                        outrage and a perfidy to, acknowledge as the representative of States
                        recognized as independent an agent in whose appointment they had no share.
                        As well might the European Maximilian assume to represent the Confederate
                        States, as the man who rules at Washington. Virginia and the rest have
                        claimed to change their foreign agency frequently in the past, and it has
                        been accorded. How can the right be <pb facs="0138" n="98" xml:id="pg_98"/>
                        questioned now? Their responsibility for Lincoln’s appointment as the organ
                        for foreign intercourse has been discharged by the expiration of the term
                        for which he was elected: In the new appointment they had no part and were
                        allowed none, and hence it cannot be pretended that it represents them
                        either in substance or form. We say that such views as these may well be
                        adopted by France and England, without reference to the other merit of our
                        cause, and we do not see how they can be overlooked, or how they can be met;
                        and taking into consideration the duties which those governments owe to
                        their own people, to their own dignity, to sound international principles,
                        and to us—duties, however, which they have declined until the neglect has
                        become a severe reproach—we think it very reasonable and very probable, that
                        they will indeed profit by the opportunity to abandon their present
                        situation with good grace.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
