<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Political Adviser in Siam (
                        Yost
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d1001</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">1001</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-11-20T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-11-20T23:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-20T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-20T23:00:00-05:00" n="1001" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1001">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">741.92/11–2145: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Political Adviser in Siam</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Yost</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bangkok</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-21T11:00:00+07:00">November 21, 1945—11 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received November 22—8:58 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[14.] British <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> summarized in Dept’s No. 8,
                        undated,<note n="18" xml:id="d1001fn1">November 15, 1 p.m., not printed; it
                        summarized the British <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of November 12,
                            <ref target="#pg_1367">p. 1367</ref>.</note> demonstrates same
                    intransigent attitude reflected by Bird here. British, while granting it is not
                    in their interest to impose intolerable burden on Siamese economy, attach great
                    importance to acceptance by Siamese of heavy penalties as public admission of
                    guilt. British attitude is to some extent irrational but nonetheless obstinate
                    and would seem to demonstrate definite intention to proceed with unilateral
                    policy in Siam whenever they do not find us amenable.</p>
                <p>It seems to us that Dept would now be fully justified in presenting to British
                    strong note of protest at unilateral manner in which they are proposing to act.
                    US contribution to victory in Far East was certainly sufficiently great to
                    warrant our having a substantial voice in peace settlement in SEA (South East
                    Asia), particularly in case of only independent country in that area treatment
                    of which by any of the Allies is bound to affect overall relations of West with
                    East. British have no right to make fact they were at war with Siam and we were
                    not excuse for unilateral settlement since our policy was not expression of
                    disinterest in Siam but on contrary one of sympathy and support.</p>
                <p>If Dept does not wish to present to British note of protest along above lines,
                    following possible alternative is suggested. British claim they will be willing
                    to reduce penalties on Siam if it proves in fact after signature of agreement
                    that burden on Siamese economy is such <pb facs="1383" n="1371" xml:id="pg_1371"/> as to cause permanent dislocation. Siamese on other hand maintain that once
                    they have committed themselves they would have no assurance that burdens would
                    ever be lightened. Situation might be met without changing text of agreement by
                    British addressing to Siamese delegation at time of signature a letter stating
                    that should implementation of agreement place intolerably heavy strain on
                    economy of Siam His Majesty’s Govt would be glad to consult with Siamese Govt at
                    latter’s invitation with view to taking steps necessary in interest of Siamese
                    domestic economy, her international commercial relations and economic stability
                    of SEA. While such a step would be far less satisfactory than our proposal of an
                    Allied Claims Commission to assess all compensation and reparations, it would
                    nevertheless make clear to all parts so [<hi rend="italic">parties</hi>] that
                    modification of terms was envisaged if conditions warranted. We would then, even
                    though not a member of an Allied Commission, have a lever to exercise pressure
                    on British through diplomatic channels as soon as we felt situation so demanded.
                    Letter might moreover meet Regent’s need (ref my No. 2, November 13) for some
                    British concession, however slight, to demonstrate to Siamese that govt has had
                    some voice in negotiations.</p>
                <p>If British prove unwilling to reply favorably in case of either alternative
                    approaches above, we believe wisest course would be for us to resume diplomatic
                    relations with Siam without more ado. While this would be step to which British
                    could hardly take exception in view of long period we have already waited at
                    their request, we feel it would give them serious pause and might be more
                    effective than any other move on our part so causing them to reconsider their
                    policy.</p>
                <closer>[<signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Yost</hi>
                    </signed>]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
