<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="1034" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1034">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">892.014/12–2245</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Embassy</gloss> to
                                    the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>A member of the staff of the French Embassy in London called at the
                                Foreign Office on the 11th December to say that he had heard that
                                the Siamese Government would be willing to cede back to the French
                                the territories in dispute between Siam and France if told to do so
                                by the United Nations Organisation.</p>
                            <p>The French representative was informed that the view of the Siamese
                                Government, as expressed to Mr. Dening at Kandy, was that any
                                Siamese Government which agreed to restore those territories to the
                                French except at the instance of the United Nations Organisation
                                would lose support in Siam. The opinion of His Majesty’s Government
                                was that advice from His Majesty’s Government and from the United
                                States Government might move the Siamese from that attitude and that
                                the possibility of such advice being given by His Majesty’s
                                Government should not be ruled out.</p>
                            <p>On the 19th December the French Embassy in London was informed that
                                it was hoped to conclude the exchange of letters with the Siamese by
                                December 25th. The French Embassy was not given the impression that
                                the documents attached to the letters or the formal agreement to <pb facs="1421" n="1409" xml:id="pg_1409"/> follow the exchange of
                                letters would contain any reference to the disputed territories. The
                                French representative requested, however, that His Majesty’s
                                Government should record in a written communication to the Siamese,
                                their non-recognition of the Siamese acquisition of those
                                territories in 1941.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Dening has accordingly been instructed to exchange letters on the
                                subject with the Siamese representative at the same time as he
                                exchanges letters covering the terms of the agreements which are to
                                terminate the state of war. Mr. Dening will state that His Majesty’s
                                Government in the United Kingdom do not recognise the acquisition by
                                Siam of the French territories, and the Siamese representative will
                                reply taking note, on behalf of his Government, of the view of His
                                Majesty’s Government.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-22">December 22, 1945</date>.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>