<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="117" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d117">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.4127/11–2245</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The British Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Halifax</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>His Majesty’s Ambassador presents his compliments to the Secretary of
                                State and has the honour to refer to the Memorandum of November 19th
                                from the Department of State regarding the proposals for an interim
                                agreement on trans-Atlantic Commercial Air Services put forward by
                                the Embassy on November 13th 1945.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>His Majesty’s Ambassador is instructed to express the regret
                                    of His Majesty’s Government that the United States Government is
                                    not prepared to entertain these proposals and that the
                                    Department of State does not believe an interim agreement is
                                    essential at this stage in view of the proposed negotiations for
                                    a bilateral agreement between the two Governments covering all
                                    phases of the air transport problem.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>His Majesty’s Government wish to place on record their view
                                    that the failure to find a basis for a working agreement
                                    covering the Third and Fourth Freedoms<note n="23" xml:id="d117fn1">These two freedoms covered respectively the
                                        right to carry passengers, cargo, and mail from the country
                                        whose nationality the plane possessed to another country,
                                        and the right to carry such traffic from another country to
                                        the country whose nationality the plane possessed. For
                                        texts, see <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                                            International Civil Aviation Conference</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 179.</note> on the North
                                    Atlantic routes seriously impairs the prospects of wider
                                    negotiations. They wish to recall that in his conversation on
                                    November 15th with the President and the Secretary of State<note n="24" xml:id="d117fn2">No record of this conversation has
                                        been found. Prime Minister Attlee’s discussions with various
                                        officials on the occasion of his visit to the United States
                                        dealt principally with atomic energy matters.</note> the
                                    Prime Minister expressed his desire to discuss with the United
                                    States Government in conference points of difference in regard
                                    to a long term bilateral agreement in the expectation that the
                                    two Governments were already on the point of agreement on an
                                    actual working arrangement for an interim period on the North
                                    Atlantic routes.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>His Majesty’s Government is reluctant to believe that the
                                    Memorandum under reference from the Department of State
                                    represents the final position of the United States Government in
                                    this matter, more especially as it in no respect enters into the
                                    merits of the proposals which His Majesty’s Government in the
                                    United Kingdom put forward. His Majesty’s Ambassador is,
                                    therefore, instructed to inquire whether the State Department
                                    are prepared now to state the proposals which in their view
                                    should form the basis of negotiations on all phases of the air
                                    transport problem together with any suggestions they may have to
                                    offer for the transatlantic operations of the commercial air
                                    lines while the negotiations are in progress.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>In view of the desire of His Majesty’s Government to settle
                                    the arrangements for the United Kingdom representation in the
                                    prospective <pb facs="0244" n="232" xml:id="pg_232"/>
                                    negotiations, His Majesty’s Government would be glad to receive
                                    the observations of the Department of State as a matter of
                                    urgency.</item>
                            </list>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-22">November 22, 1945</date>.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>