<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Minister in Switzerland (
                    (Harrison))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d217</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">217</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-05-22T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-05-22T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="prisoners-of-war"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners of war</term>
                    <term ref="recRAvRT7ZvyjvRU2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-22T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-22T18:00:00-05:00" n="217"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d217">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.93114A/5–2245: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Minister in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harrison</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-22T19:00:00-04:00"
                            >[May 22, 1945]—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1871. Request Swiss Government to transmit textually to Japanese Government on
                    urgent basis the following:</p>
                <p>The United States Government has been informed<note n="45" xml:id="d217fn1"
                        >Airgrams A–690, May 7, and A–697, May 9, from Bern; neither printed.</note>
                    that the Japanese Government is removing the prisoners of war from the Kiangwan
                    camp in Shanghai and that they were due to depart on May 7 for Fengtai situated
                    on the Shanghai–Peking Railroad about 15 kilometers south of Peking.</p>
                <p>The United States Government demands assurance from the Japanese Government
                    without delay that it is not planning to quarter these prisoners of war in the
                    vicinity of the railroad junction and military installations at Fengtai in
                    violation of the humane provisions of Article 9 of the Geneva Convention which
                    states “No prisoner may, at any time, be sent into a region where he might be
                    exposed to the fire of the combat zone nor used to give protection from
                    bombardment to certain points or certain regions by his presence.” The United
                    States Government expects to receive the Japanese Government’s solemn assurance
                    that the camp to which the prisoners of war are being removed is situated
                    outside the zone of danger. In observance of its commitments the Japanese
                    Government is further obligated to guarantee that the camp is provided with
                    suitable barracks and an adequate hospital and is not deficient in the necessary
                    sanitary facilities and camp equipment.</p>
                <p>The United States Government also demands that the Japanese Government report to
                    this Government at once the names of the prisoners of war who are transferred
                    and inform this Government of the exact location of the place of their
                    transfer.</p>
                <p>The United States Government furthermore demands that the Japanese Government
                    issue authorization to the representatives of the protecting Power and the
                    International Red Cross Committee to visit the camp where the prisoners of war
                    are detained and to report to this Government without delay the conditions under
                    which they are held.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0351" n="339" xml:id="pg_339"/>
                <postscript>
                    <p>[In telegram 1884, May 24, to Bern, the Department requested that the Swiss
                        Government convey the demand of the United States Government that the
                        Japanese Government punish those responsible for the mistreatment of
                        American prisoners of war at Puerto Princesa, the Philippines; for text, see
                        Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, September 9, 1945, page
                        356.]</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
