<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Minister in Switzerland (
                        Harrison
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d232</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">232</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-06-28T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-06-28T10:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-06-28T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-06-28T10:00:00-05:00" n="232" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d232">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.94114A/6–2845: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harrison</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bern</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-06-28T16:00:00+01:00">June 28, 1945—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received June 29—12:15 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3349. Am[erican] Interests—Jap. Legtel 3129, June 11.<note n="69" xml:id="d232fn1">Not printed; it stated that according to Foreign Office
                        note of June 8, “Swiss Minister Tokyo again contacted Minister Togo May 30
                        in endeavor obtain authorization visit POW camp”. (711.94114A/6–1145)</note>
                    Notice June 20 from FonOff states Gorgé instructed Apr 1 [on] request British
                    Leg Bern intervene Jap authorities following matters: 1, right visit camps all
                    areas protecting Power and Intercross; 2, prompt notifications; 3, removal camps
                    from industrial areas and neighborhood military objectives.</p>
                <p>In recent telegram Gorgé replied no response Jap FonOff his numerous
                    interventions. Notwithstanding absence results, Gorgé will continue insist and
                    hopes obtain better result in examining these problems directly with Suzuki to
                    whom he has written personal letter. However, Gorgé of opinion Jap authorities
                    will maintain their negative attitude until torpedoing of <hi rend="italic">Awa
                        Maru</hi>
                    <note n="70" xml:id="d232fn2">For documentation on this subject, see telegram
                        1396, April 10, to Bern, <ref target="#pg_462">p. 462</ref>, and succeeding
                        messages.</note> settled by American Govt to satisfaction Jap Govt.<note n="71" xml:id="d232fn3">On August 24, the Delegation to the United States of
                        the International Committee of the Red Cross quoted, for the information of
                        the Department, from a letter of July 16 from Geneva headquarters, as
                        follows: “The Japanese authorities have repeatedly informed us that owing to
                        the torpedoing of the <hi rend="italic">Awa Maru</hi>, prisoner of war camp
                        visits by Delegates of the International Committee of the Red Cross were to
                        be held in abeyance. We were unable to convince the Japanese Authorities of
                        our opinion that POW camp visits by the International Committee bore no
                        relationship to the sinking of a vessel transporting relief.” The letter
                        also cited a Japanese spokesman as stating “he regretted the impasse reached
                        in relief activities due to the <hi rend="italic">Awa Maru</hi> case, as the
                        USA government’s reply was considered unsatisfactory and not conducive to an
                        early mutually acceptable settlement”. (711.94114 Supplies/8–2445)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Notice June 26 gives following summary Gorgé’s interview June 16 Suzuki: Suzuki
                    recently discussed with Jap Minister War<note n="72" xml:id="d232fn4">Gen.
                        Korechika Anami.</note> and convinced FonOff doing all possible aid Gorgé
                    but negotiations between FonOff and military authorities subject difficulties.
                    Interview concerned principally following which Gorgé discussed at length: 1,
                    visit POW camps; 2, location POW camps near military objectives.</p>
                <p>Regarding 1, Suzuki seemed anxious satisfy recent personal interventions Gorgé
                    and assured latter camp visits could doubtless be resumed near future. Suzuki
                    stated suspension visits result reorganization camps now under way. Numerous
                    transfers have occurred, but Suzuki apparently possessed no details their
                    regard.</p>
                <p>Under these circumstances Gorgé not aware whether certain camps closed and others
                    established but he hopes soon receive information <pb facs="0363" n="351" xml:id="pg_351"/> this regard. Personally he believes other reasons explain
                    present discontinuance visits, particularly fact military authorities do not
                    desire Swiss delegates visit camps near zones object of bombing.</p>
                <p>Regarding 2, states Gorgé would soon receive Jap reply to representations behalf
                    US, Great Britain which Swiss Legation will telegraph when received.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Harrison</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
