<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-09-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-09-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="270" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d270">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.94114A/9–1145: Airgram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Harrison</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bern</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-09-11">September 11,
                                        1945</date>.<lb/>[Received September 19—6 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>A–1064. American Interests—Far East. Department’s 1111, March 17,
                                Legation’s 3347<note n="46" xml:id="d270fn1">Telegram 3347 not
                                    printed; but for summary, see footnote 77, <ref target="#pg_352">p. 352</ref>.</note> and 3348, June 28, and 3541, July
                                12.</p>
                            <p>Foreign Office note, September 8, gives substance communication from
                                Minister Togo<note n="47" xml:id="d270fn2">Shigenori Togo resigned
                                    as Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs on August 15.</note>
                                telegraphed September 4 by Swiss Minister Tokyo. Following
                                translation: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>—Bodies of POWs deceased while in captivity will
                                        henceforth be buried except under certain special
                                        circumstances. This particularly in camps at Tokyo and Osaka
                                        where Japanese regulations forbid burials in vicinity of
                                        these camps. In Borneo cremation was ordered to prevent
                                        danger of epidemics.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>—Delays in notification POW names not intentional on part
                                        of Japanese authorities but principally due to circumstances
                                        surrounding <pb facs="0416" n="404" xml:id="pg_404"/>
                                        handling of matters. As soon as lists prepared, competent
                                        Japanese authorities will communicate them to Swiss
                                        Legation.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>—Japanese authorities will only deliver copies of death
                                        certificates on special request from interested Governments
                                        as it is unable send copies of all documents. All death
                                        certificates have been kept and will be submitted to
                                        American and British Governments after the war.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Although these statements superseded by recent events, Swiss Foreign
                                Office nevertheless communicates them for Legation’s
                                information.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Harrison</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>