<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Department of State to the
                            State-War-Navy Coordinating Committee</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d400</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">400</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-09-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-09-18T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-09-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-09-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="400" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d400">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 PW/9–1845</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">State-War-Navy Coordinating Committee</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-09-18">September 18,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Disposition of Equipment Surrendered to Allied Forces</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">I. <hi rend="italic">The Problem</hi>
                </p>
                <p>What disposition should be made of surrendered military equipment with respect to
                    the claims on that equipment of the territorial sovereign.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">II. <hi rend="italic">Facts Bearing on the Problem</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>A.</label>
                    <item>On September 8 the Supreme Allied Commander of the Southeast Asia Command
                        stated that he would temporarily allocate surrendered equipment for use by
                        occupying forces or for use where movement from one area to another was
                        involved and requested further guidance from the British Chiefs of Staff on
                        the question of the use of surrendered equipment, inquiring if it might be
                        used for the equipping of any Allied forces placed under his command for
                        reoccupation duties, or for the rehabilitation of Allied countries; and in
                        final disposition whether such equipment handed over in the territory of an
                        Ally is to be regarded as the property of the Government of that Ally. A
                        copy of the request was transmitted to the United States Joint Chiefs of
                        Staff for possible comment.</item>
                    <label>B.</label>
                    <item>Current practice in Europe and United States policy in the Far East as
                        indicated in SWNCC 58/5,<note n="30" xml:id="d400fn1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_539">p. 539</ref>.</note>
                        which was revised to become 58/9,<note n="31" xml:id="d400fn2">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_614">p. 614</ref>.</note>
                        is to destroy surrendered equipment. It is understood, however, that the
                        theatre commander is empowered to make surrendered material available to any
                        local police force which he desires to use to maintain order. In no
                        instance, however, may such equipment be used to equip and arm forces which
                        might become a postwar army in any area nor is such equipment handed over in
                        the territory of an Ally regarded as the property of the Government of that
                        Ally.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">III. <hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Equipment surrendered in Europe has in general been destroyed and it is United
                    States policy in the Far East likewise to destroy surrendered equipment. There
                    would be no objection, however, to the theatre commander using surrendered
                    material in equipping a police force to maintain order, but accepted practice
                    would permit objection to be raised to the arming of forces which might become a
                    postwar army in any given area or to the handing over of such equipment taken
                        <pb facs="0633" n="621" xml:id="pg_621"/> in the territory of an Ally to
                    become the property of that Ally. In view of the fact that the United States
                    does not oppose the reestablishment of French, British or Dutch control over
                    their former colonies but does not propose to be an active agent in supporting
                    the reestablishment of their control by force, it seems desirable to extend the
                    current policy to the Southeast Asia Command.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">IV. <hi rend="italic">Conclusions</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is concluded that equipment surrendered in the Southeast Asia Command should
                    in general be destroyed or, in a limited degree, at the discretion of the
                    theatre commander, be used to equip a police force to maintain local order. It
                    would be undesirable to establish a precedent that an Ally should turn over to
                    any territorial sovereign equipment seized in the territory of that
                    sovereign.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">V. <hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is recommended that the Joint Chiefs of Staff inform the Combined Chiefs of
                    Staff of the above conclusion with the suggestion that a directive be issued to
                    the Supreme Allied Commander of the Southeast Asia Command to that effect.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
