<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                        Winant
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d548</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">548</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-10-19T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-19T17:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                    <term ref="recd38b75873bd4a33" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="far-eastern-commission" subject="far-eastern-commission">Far Eastern Commission</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-19T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-19T17:00:00-05:00" n="548" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d548">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 F.E.A.C./10–1845: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-19T17:00:00-05:00">October 19, 1945—5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>9260. For Dunn. Sir George Sansom of British Embassy has communicated informally
                    to Vincent the substance of a telegram which British Embassy here received from
                    London several weeks ago, which reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“During the discussion in London as to the Far Eastern Commission, a
                            draft of amended terms of reference was worked out in agreement with Mr.
                            Dunn, as something which would be put forward by the United Kingdom
                            representative as soon as the Commission met in Washington, and which
                            the United States Government would then support.</p>
                        <p>It was agreed that the draft of the amended terms of reference and the
                            fact that the United States Government was prepared to support them were
                            to be regarded as strictly secret at present.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Bevin asked Mr. Byrnes privately to ensure that the position would
                            not be prejudiced by the publication of terms of reference originally
                            proposed by the United States Government. He suggested to Mr. Byrnes
                            that it was unnecessary to publish more than the fact that a Commission
                            of Representatives of certain powers was to be set up and would shortly
                            hold its first meeting in Washington.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>With reference to the third paragraph above Sir George commented on the fact that
                    an official press release of Oct 10 by the Department of State<note n="59" xml:id="d548fn1">Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                        October 14, 1945, pp. 561, 580.</note> gives the full text of the original
                    Terms of Reference proposed by the U.S. Government on August 21, but explained
                    that he was not making an official complaint or even an unofficial one. He was
                    told it is our understanding that the undertaking regarding publicity applied to
                    the revised Terms of Reference proposed by the British and regret was expressed
                    that a misunderstanding had arisen.</p>
                <pb facs="0774" n="762" xml:id="pg_762"/>
                <p>With regard to paragraphs 1 and 2 of Sir George’s communication it is my
                    understanding that no commitment whatsoever was made with regard to support of
                    the proposed revision of the Terms of Reference. I informed Bevin that we would
                    support a proposal to hold meetings of the Commission in Tokyo and that we would
                    request the Soviet Union and China to agree to inclusion of India among
                    countries represented on the Commission and would advise those governments we
                    agreed as to India, but I agreed only that the revision of Terms of Reference
                    might be considered at an early meeting of the Commission.</p>
                <p>I should appreciate receiving your interpretation and comment on this matter.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
