<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the Soviet Union (
                    (Harriman))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d551</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">551</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-10-20T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-20T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-20T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-20T20:00:00-05:00" n="551"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d551">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 F.E.A.C./10–2045: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-20T20:00:00-05:00"
                            >October 20, 1945—8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2198. Referring urtel regarding interview with Stalin.<note n="64"
                        xml:id="d551fn1">Telegram 3595, October 19, 10 a.m., to Moscow, <ref
                            target="#pg_758">p. 758</ref>.</note> On August 21 we sent a proposal to
                    the governments of USSR, United Kingdom, and China, proposing the establishment
                    of the Far Eastern Advisory Commission. Under the terms of reference the
                    Commission will make recommendations to the respective governments as to
                    occupation policies.</p>
                <p>On August 31 China accepted and on September 7, the Soviet Union accepted. We
                    received no response from the British government until September 28 when the
                    British accepted. In a separate communication <pb facs="0778" n="766"
                        xml:id="pg_766"/> the British made two requests: (1) that India be invited
                    to join the participating governments; and (2) that the Commission be authorized
                    to meet in Tokyo if it so desired. These were merely requests and not conditions
                    of acceptance.</p>
                <p>We advised the Foreign Ministers of USSR and China of the acceptance by the
                    United Kingdom and transmitted the two requests. We asked that representatives
                    be appointed at an early date for the organization meeting.</p>
                <p>On October 2 Molotov advised me that he thought the functioning of the Advisory
                    Commission should be preceded by the establishment of a Control Council.</p>
                <p>While in London, Mr. Molotov had proposed adding to the agenda of the Foreign
                    Ministers the question of establishing a Control Council. I took the position
                    that the subject was not on the agenda submitted to the Council by the Berlin
                        protocol<note n="65" xml:id="d551fn2">August 1, 1945, <ref
                            target="frus1945Berlinv02#pg_1478">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Conference of Berlin (The
                            Potsdam Conference), 1945, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p.
                            1478</ref>.</note> or by agreement of the governments concerned. I
                    stated that, consequently, I was not prepared to discuss the matter, did not
                    know the views of the President nor the views of the Supreme Commander, but
                    would, upon my return to Washington, present the matter to the President. On
                    several occasions I urged that the orderly procedure would be for the Advisory
                    Committee under its terms of reference to consider whether or not there should
                    be a Control Council and, if so, what form that Control Council should take. On
                    October 6 we telegraphed invitations to all governments mentioned in the
                    original proposal, asking them to meet October 23. The Soviet Government
                    responded that it was still of the opinion expressed October 2 that the Advisory
                    Commission which it had previously agreed to should not begin to function until
                    there was established a control council as now proposed by them. All the other
                    governments announced their intention to have representatives at the meeting.
                    Later at the request of two or three representatives, the meeting was postponed
                    until October 30.</p>
                <p>I advised Mr. Molotov that I would present his views to the President. I have
                    done so. The President, however, agreed with me that the representatives of the
                    Advisory Commission should be permitted, in accordance with their terms of
                    reference, to make recommendations to their governments as to policies to be
                    followed during the period of occupation. If proposals are made to revise the
                    original terms of reference and to broaden the authority of the commission, such
                    proposals would of course be considered with open-mindedness on their
                    merits.</p>
                <p>The Supreme Commander has not made any definite decision as to occupation forces.
                    The thought is that the USSR, United Kingdom <pb facs="0779" n="767"
                        xml:id="pg_767"/> and China should furnish 30,000 each. It is thought that
                    the Soviet Government contribution might be one reinforced infantry division.
                    The forces provided would be integrated operationally with the United States
                    forces under General MacArthur. It should be emphasized this plan is only under
                    study. When the details are worked out the proposal will be submitted to the
                    several governments for negotiation.</p>
                <p>Under the terms of surrender agreed upon by our governments and communicated to
                    the Japanese Government prior to surrender, the Emperor and the Japanese
                    government are to carry out the orders of the Supreme Commander of the Allied
                    Powers. Since no mention was made in the surrender terms of a Control Council,
                    we could not approve a proposal to substitute a Control Council for the Supreme
                    Allied Commander.</p>
                <p>It is my thought, however, that there should be established, under the Supreme
                    Allied Commander, an Allied Military Council composed of representatives of each
                    of the major governments having military forces in the Army of Occupation. This
                    Allied Military Council would thus be, in effect, an executive council of the
                    ranking allied commanders through whose military forces the allied decisions
                    must in the last analysis be carried out. The Supreme Commander would be its
                    chairman, and in cases of divergences of views his direction would resolve the
                    matter. General directives and important policy guidance forwarded to the
                    Supreme Commander through the regular channels of the United States Military
                    Command would be submitted to the Council for the consideration of appropriate
                    procedures for their execution.</p>
                <p>The above is simply for your own information and guidance. While it should enable
                    you to indicate to Stalin our approach to the problem, it is not intended for
                    direct communication to him. I hope to cable you further regarding the Military
                    Council as I have not yet cleared the proposal with our military.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
