<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                        Winant
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d699</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">699</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-11-06T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-11-06T18:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-06T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-06T18:00:00-05:00" n="699" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d699">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00116 PW/11–545: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-06T18:00:00-05:00">November 6, 1945—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>9753. For Hodgson. Urtel 11594, November 5. Depts instruction 19, October 23<note n="64" xml:id="d699fn1">Not printed.</note> contained copy of memorandum of
                    United States policy and copy of the identic note of October 18, communicating
                    memorandum to signatories of Japanese surrender document.</p>
                <p>Dept considers proposals of C–145 (1) very close to United States policy as
                    formulated by SWNCC, but does not believe it would be appropriate to request
                    FonOff to take action in accordance with Article 8 of that document. British
                    Embassy has informed Dept that FonOff has expressed hope that United States Govt
                    will not commit itself in any public declaration to recommending repetition of
                    European procedure in the case of major Far Eastern war criminals and that
                    British Govt is considering a means of securing a simpler procedure for dealing
                    with Far Eastern war criminals problem. In <pb facs="0964" n="952" xml:id="pg_952"/> view of this FonOff attitude, and appearance of subject of
                    apprehension and punishment of war criminals as item 9 on tentative agenda now
                    before Far Eastern Advisory Commission for its consideration, Dept suggests you
                    associate yourself with position Craigie proposes to take and that action on
                    C–145(1) should be deferred pending consideration of subject through diplomatic
                    channels.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
