<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Political Adviser in Japan (
                        Atcheson
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d709</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">709</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-11-17T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="709" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d709">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00116 PW/11–1745</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Political Adviser in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Atcheson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 58</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-17">November 17,
                            1945</date>.<lb/>[Received November 27.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my telegram 136,
                    November 15,<note n="3" xml:id="d709fn1">Not printed.</note> and despatch No.
                    57, November 16, 1945, in regard to major Japanese war criminal suspects whom we
                    have recommended be arrested at this time for trial, and especially to the case
                    of Prince Fuimimaro Konoye.</p>
                <p>There is enclosed a memorandum<note n="4" xml:id="d709fn2">Dated November 5, not
                        printed.</note> on the subject of Konoye’s war guilt prepared by Mr. E. H.
                    Norman, a Canadian national, author of <hi rend="italic">Japan’s Emergence as a
                        Modern State</hi> who is in Tokyo as representative of the Canadian
                    Department of External Affairs and who is temporarily acting as chief of the
                    Research and Analysis Section of the Office of the Chief Counter Intelligence
                    Officer of General Headquarters. This memorandum comprises, in our opinion, a
                    very able presentation of the political case against Konoye and is of special
                    interest at this time because, we understand, there is considerable reluctance
                    in some quarters to arrest Konoye along with the other (major suspects still at
                    large. The memorandum was originally written by Mr. Norman for Allied General
                    Headquarters.</p>
                <p>In his “Conclusion” Mr. Norman states in part: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The most valuable service which Konoye performed on behalf of Japanese
                            aggression was one which he alone could have accomplished—namely the
                            fusing of all the dominant sections of the ruling oligarchy, the Court,
                            Army, Zaibatsu and bureaucracy. His prestige with the Army and his
                            unassailable position at Court uniquely equipped him to reconcile
                            personal differences among the various leaders, to remove the frictions
                            between the Army cliques, to quiet the fears of the more timorous
                            business leaders, to show the Army intransigeants the need for appeasing
                            the Zaibatsu, to choose from the higher bureacracy those men most
                            suitable to administer the war program.</p>
                        <p>In only the final event does Konoye escape full responsibility, namely,
                            for the launching of the attack on Pearl Harbor. This is a very
                            considerable exception and one of which the Prince with his able coterie
                            of henchmen including journalists, courtiers, and young brain trusters
                            is making the most by direct and indirect propaganda. Yet he was the
                            Prime Minister and continued to be Prime Minister through July 1941
                            until mid-October during which months the question of a war with the
                            United States was fully canvassed and fairly faced both in the Cabinet
                            and at least in the Imperial conference.</p>
                        <p>In other words, Konoye set in motion those policies and alliances which
                            could only lead to a collision with the Western powers. Even though he
                            stepped aside in favor of Tojo in October 1941, he still bears <pb facs="0984" n="972" xml:id="pg_972"/> a heavy responsibility both
                            moral and legal (if he had a serious change of heart in October 1941),
                            since he made no move such as summoning an Imperial conference while
                            still Premier to prevent the coming Japanese attack upon the United
                            States and Britain”.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>As is well known, Konoye was Prime Minister when Japan attacked China, entered
                    the Tri-Partite Alliance with Germany and Italy, invaded French Indochina,
                    adopted the National Mobilization Law<note n="5" xml:id="d709fn3">It was
                        promulgated on April 1, 1938.</note> which laid the foundation for the
                    command economy for total war, and abolished the old political parties. He
                    created the Imperial Rule Assistance Association and was its first president.
                    While there is some question as to what effect his arrest might have upon the
                    present Government, the widepread criticism of him and his past policies in the
                    press suggest that the effect would not be adverse. The question of his
                    nobility, i. e. his closeness to the Throne and whether his arrest would raise
                    the question of the war guilt of the Emperor, is one for which there is even a
                    Japanese solution in the thesis, which is being publicized in the Japanese press
                    these days, that political responsibility rests in the Emperor’s advisers but
                    never in the Emperor because the Emperor acts only in accordance with the
                    recommendations of his advisers. It seems entirely inappropriate that a man with
                    Konoye’s political history should escape formal investigation as a war criminal
                    suspect and that he should continue to participate in important governmental
                    activities.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">George Atcheson, Jr.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
