<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Edwin W. Pauley, Personal Representative of the President on Reparations,
                    to President Truman and the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d747</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">747</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-12-08T06:51:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-12-08T06:51:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recSj13D27GJZ1DiT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Allocations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-08T06:51:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-08T06:51:00-05:00" n="747"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d747">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 P.W./12–845: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Edwin W. Pauley</persName>, Personal
                        Representative of the President on Reparations, to President <persName
                            type="to">Truman</persName> and the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-08T20:51:00+09:00">8
                            December, 1945—8:51 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>CA 55748. The following letter was delivered today to General MacArthur: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="flushleft">“General of the Army Douglas MacArthur,</p>
                        <p>“Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers,</p>
                        <p>“Tokyo, Japan.</p>
                        <p>“Dear General MacArthur:</p>
                        <p>“It has been reported to me through your headquarters that there is some
                            uneasiness in Korea as to the possibility that sizable quantities of
                            plant and equipment may be removed from that country as Japanese
                            reparations.</p>
                        <p>“In order that reparations policy with respect to Korea may be clear, I
                            am today issuing a statement pointing out that the interest of the
                            Reparations Mission is not to take things from Korea. On the contrary, I
                            intend to recommend to the President that we should try to determine
                            what Japanese plants and equipment, formerly used to exploit Korea,
                            could usefully be transferred from Japan to Korea. A copy of my
                            statement is enclosed.</p>
                        <p>“Sincerely Yours,</p>
                        <p rend="right">Edwin W. Pauley”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The following press release was delivered today to official press representatives
                    for immediate release: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Statement by Ambassador Edwin W. Pauley, Personal Representative of the
                            President of the United States and head of the United States Reparations
                            Mission to Japan.</p>
                        <p rend="right">“8 December 1945.</p>
                        <p>“Since issuing my statement of 7 December on Japanese reparations,<note
                                n="66" xml:id="d747fn1">See telegram of December 6, <ref
                                    target="#pg_1004">p. 1004</ref>.</note> I have been asked how
                            our reparations policy will affect Korea. The interest of the
                            Reparations Mission is, of course, not to take things from that
                            liberated country. On the contrary, I intend to recommend to President
                            Truman that the policy should be to determine what Japanese plants and
                            the Korean people, [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] could usefully be <pb
                                facs="1023" n="1011" xml:id="pg_1011"/> transferred from Japan
                            proper to help round out an independent Korean economy.</p>
                        <p>“Both the American occupation of South Korea and the Russian occupation
                            of North Korea are temporary. Under United Nations policy all Korea will
                            eventually be treated as a unit. I believe therefore that it may prove
                            preferable to postpone allocations and shipments on account of
                            reparations to Korea until the needs of the whole country—and by that I
                            mean the whole people, not the interests of any privileged group—can be
                            considered as a unit.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>[<signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Pauley</hi>
                    </signed>]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
