<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in China (
                        Hurley
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d775</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">775</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-08-31T01:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-08-31T01:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-08-31T01:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-08-31T01:00:00-05:00" n="775" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d775">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">895.01/8–3145: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hurley</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-08-31T13:00:00+07:00">August 31, 1945—1 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 2:59 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1485. Representative of “Korean Provisional Government” called at Embassy
                    yesterday (Embassy’s 1356, August 14) and left memorandum, substance of which he
                    requested be communicated to Department.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Begin summary of memorandum</hi>) 1. Having failed to
                    overthrow Korean Provisional Government, Korean Communists and their allies in
                    Chungking withdrew from Government to demonstrate their party loyalty and to
                    coordinate actions inside and outside Korea.</p>
                <p>2. Koreans from Russia and Korean Communists from Yenan are entering Korea in
                    large numbers. Before leaving Yenan for Manchuria on way to Korea, Kom Bakyun,
                    President of Korean College in Yenan, broadcast that they aimed to set up
                    government in Korea according to Communist ideals.</p>
                <p>3. In view of foregoing, Korean Democrats, who believe in Anglo-American
                    constitutionalism and who have been fighting for Korean freedom for past 40
                    years, are losing hope and their chances in Korea are decreasing.</p>
                <p>4. Korean revolutionary leaders hope to assist and cooperate with American
                    occupation forces in Korea and wish to mobilize public opinion in favor of
                    Americans in order to keep law and order. These men are more respected by and
                    better known to Koreans than Communist leaders. They hope United States will
                    permit leading members of Korean Provisional Government to enter Korea as
                    assistants to or interpreters for occupation forces or in any other manner
                    suitable to United States. They believe that question of whether Korea develops
                    into a democratic or communistic state depends on what United States does now.
                    Failure to make decision will work in favor of Communists.</p>
                <p>5. Korean leaders hope United States will send American missionaries at once to
                    northern Korea which is center of American missionary work and also is area
                    where such activity is in danger of being eliminated. Many Provisional
                    Government members are Christians.</p>
                <p>6. If United States could assist Korean leaders and send them to Korea, they
                    would do nothing contrary to wishes of United States occupation forces or State
                    Department.</p>
                <p>7. Korean Provisional Government is well aware of State Department’s policy of
                    treating all Korean groups alike, but invites attention to what Korean
                    Communists are now doing with outside assistance. (<hi rend="italic">Summary
                        ends here</hi>.)</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hurley</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
