<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                        Winant
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d862</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">862</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-12-01T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-12-01T07:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-01T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-01T07:00:00-05:00" n="862" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d862">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">856.E.00/12–2445</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-01T12:00:00+00:00">December 1, 1945—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received December 1—10:59
                        a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>12557. ReDept’s 10147, November 20 and Embassy’s 12323, November 24. FonOff has
                    now replied officially to our inquiry re proposed approach by American
                    Ambassador at Hague on Java situation. Reply is in form of “oral communication”
                    and expresses appreciation of the helpful intention of proposed US approach to
                    the Dutch. However, FonOff states situation has now changed considerably since
                    Lord Halifax<note n="28" xml:id="d862fn1">British Ambassador in the United
                        States.</note> spoke to Mr. Byrnes on November 9 and since Sterndale Bennett
                    had talked with Allison<note n="29" xml:id="d862fn2">John M. Allison, First
                        Secretary of Embassy in the United Kingdom.</note> re situation. According
                    to communication, there is no present difficulty from Dutch side as regards
                    meetings with Indonesian leaders. A joint meeting took place on November 17 when
                    it was hoped Van Mook’s statement of policy issued on November 6 would form
                    basis of further meetings. Present difficulties are said to be unwillingness of
                    Indonesian leaders to attend further meetings with Dutch and their inability to
                    control the extremists which has resulted in serious deterioration of situation
                    throughout Java. In these changed circumstances FonOff believes proposed US
                    approach at Hague would no longer be appropriate.</p>
                <p>FonOff asks however whether State Department would be ready to make some public
                    statement, not addressed specifically either to Dutch or to Indonesians, but
                    expressing concern at the cessation of conversations which seemed to have made a
                    promising start? The statement might perhaps suggest generally that no dispute
                    of this kind is likely to be settled satisfactorily by standing aloof instead of
                    getting round a table and that a broadminded and cooperative approach to the
                    question is likely to be in the best interests of the welfare and progress of
                    the NEI.</p>
                <p>FonOff states it would be helpful if any such statement could include an
                    acknowledgment of fact that British troops had gone to Java to carry out an
                    Allied task and if it could emphasize the importance of completing the Japanese
                    surrender and especially of insuring the safety of the many thousands of
                    internees whose fate is a source of serious anxiety under present
                    conditions.</p>
                <p>FonOff communication concludes by saying that if State Dept felt it possible to
                    give some such public indication of US views it would be of very great
                    assistance.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
