<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>25. Memorandum From the Director of the United States Information Agency
                    (Rowan) to United States Information Agency Heads of Elements and Country Public
                    Affairs Officers) to United States Information Agency Heads of Elements and
                    Country Public Affairs Officers</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1917-72PubDipv07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-07-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-07-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008008484"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Public affairs</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="recMrVNgNJpQ8DjcR" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037301"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deterrence</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-07-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-07-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="25"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d25">
                <head>25. Memorandum From the Director of the United States Information Agency
                        (<persName corresp="#p_RCT_1">Rowan</persName>) to United States Information
                    Agency Heads of Elements and Country Public Affairs Officers<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d25fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 306, Director’s Files: 1962–1965, Entry UD
                        WW 191, Director’s Office 1964. Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-07-17">July 17, 1964</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Assignment of Priority Project: Viet-Nam</item>
                </list>
                <p>The President has placed the highest priority on programs supporting U.S.
                    determination “to use its strength to help those who are defending themselves
                    against terror and aggression”<note n="2" xml:id="d25fn2">The quotation is from
                        a statement that <persName corresp="#p_JLB_1">Johnson</persName> read at his
                        June 23 news conference. For text, see Department of State <hi rend="italic"
                            >Bulletin</hi>, July 6, 1964, pp. 46–47.</note> instigated and supported
                    by Hanoi and Peking in Viet-Nam and other nations of Southeast Asia. I have
                    accordingly assured the President that <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>
                    will spare no resource or effort in support of that objective.</p>
                <p>We have almost doubled the size of our program in Viet-Nam and we have developed
                    a coordinated, mission-wide psychological effort in support of the <gloss
                        target="#t_GVN_1">GVN</gloss>.</p>
                <p>In Washington, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRJ_1">Robert Manning</persName>,
                    Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs, has been charged with creating
                    more positive public support in the United States for our policy.</p>
                <p>A third and vital area of concern is the necessity to impress upon other nations
                    that communist aggression and subversion in Southeast Asia is indeed a menace to
                    Free World security and that deterrence of that aggression is a responsibility
                    which all nations should share. To meet this need, the Agency must make a
                    maximum effort through all media and in all possible countries to achieve the
                    following objectives:</p>
                <p>(1) to explain the nature and significance of the struggle,</p>
                <p>(2) to expose the evil of communist aims and actions,</p>
                <p>(3) to stress the collective responsibility which other nations must share to
                    stop them,</p>
                <p>(4) to publicize third nation participation and support, and</p>
                <p>(5) to keep before world opinion U.S. determination to persist in its support of
                    those Southeast Asian nations which have requested our assistance until the
                    communist aggression is checked.</p>
                <pb facs="0109" n="68" xml:id="pg_68"/>
                <p>We should all keep in mind that the communists view their aggression in Southeast
                    Asia as a test case for “wars of national liberation” and that a communist
                    victory there would sharply increase the likelihood of future such adventures
                    elsewhere. We should strive to create in the minds of our audience a sense of
                    individual identification with the struggle against communism in Southeast
                    Asia.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">AGENCY REQUIREMENTS:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">MEDIA:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>(1) Under the direction of the Assistant Deputy Director for Media Content, the
                    media will launch an expanded and sustained flow of products in support of this
                    priority project. A listing of these products will be forthcoming from <gloss
                        target="#t_IOP_1">IOP</gloss> along with guidance and Talking Papers as
                    appropriate.</p>
                <p>(2) In the meantime, the media should give priority treatment to Viet-Nam, and
                    the objectives outlined, in their output. They should insure that all units of
                    their operation are made aware of the priority I place on this project.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">POSTS:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>(1) Should first assess their capabilities and potential to forward the aims
                    described above;</p>
                <p>(2) Work with or through whatever local <gloss target="#t_GVN_1">GVN</gloss>
                    representation may be present and with other friendly missions;</p>
                <p>(3) Cross report editorial comment supporting our objectives; and</p>
                <p>(4) Forward promptly any ideas on ways in which this project could be bettered,
                    suggestions for media output, etc.</p>
                <p>It will be the duty of Area Assistant Directors to insure that posts fulfill
                    these responsibilities.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_RCT_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_RCT_1">Carl T. Rowan</persName>
                        <note n="3" xml:id="d25fn3">
                            <persName corresp="#p_RCT_1">Rowan</persName> signed “<persName
                                corresp="#p_RCT_1">Carl T. Rowan</persName>” above this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
