<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>45. Memorandum From the Deputy Director of the United States Information
                    Agency (Wilson) to the President’s Special Assistant () to the President’s
                    Special Assistant (Moyers))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1917-72PubDipv07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d45</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">45</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-05-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-05-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="reclX4mzFRYzavuL4" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections">Free elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-05-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-05-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="45"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d45">
                <head>45. Memorandum From the Deputy Director of the United States Information
                    Agency (<persName corresp="#p_WDM_1">Wilson</persName>) to the President’s
                    Special Assistant (<persName corresp="#p_MBD_1">Moyers</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d45fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 306, Director’s Files: 1962–1965, Entry UD
                        WW 191, Box 12, <gloss target="#t_IAE_1">IAE</gloss> Director’s Office,
                        1965. No classification marking. Drafted in <gloss target="#t_IRS_1"
                            >IRS</gloss>; edited by <persName corresp="#p_WDM_1">Wilson</persName>.
                        Copies were sent to <persName corresp="#p_BM_1">Bundy</persName> and
                            <persName corresp="#p_KD_1">Klein</persName>. All brackets are in the
                        original.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-05-10">May 10, 1965</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Reaction to the President’s European Address</item>
                </list>
                <p>Editorial reaction to the President’s European address<note n="2" xml:id="d45fn2"
                        >On May 7, the President delivered remarks from the White House Theater on
                        the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Anniversary of V-E Day. For text, see
                            <hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_JLB_1"
                                >Johnson</persName>, 1965</hi>, Book I, pp. 506–509.</note> is
                    generally favorable in West Germany, Italy, and Great Britain and mixed in
                    France. British reaction is most often concerned with the President’s warning on
                    “narrow nationalism” which the press interprets as directed against <persName
                        corresp="#p_DGC_1">De Gaulle</persName>.</p>
                <p>Some editors focus positively on the President’s call for Atlantic unity but with
                    emphasis on national angles. German papers underscore <pb facs="0172" n="131"
                        xml:id="pg_131"/> passages referring to the German problem. In France the
                        Gaullist<note n="3" xml:id="d45fn3">Reference is to a supporter of France’s
                        President <persName corresp="#p_DGC_1">de Gaulle</persName>.</note> papers
                    are naturally most critical, although even such an elite paper as <hi
                        rend="italic">Le Monde</hi>, generally not uncritical of <persName
                        corresp="#p_DGC_1">De Gaulle</persName>, is as censorious of the U.S. as of
                    the French government. <hi rend="italic">Le Monde</hi> declares that the address
                    may “foreshadow a relaunching of the United States’ European policy.” The paper
                    also says that the address was a document “reflecting very faithfully the ways
                    and thinking of American leaders, the style of their reasoning and the logic of
                    their convictions.” An editorial in the same paper is more outspoken in its
                    criticism of the U.S. when it charged that “the stubbornness of the U.S. in
                    wishing to obtain support it demands is as ridiculous as that of French
                    stubbornness which refuses it.”</p>
                <p>Two of the leading pro-American French papers took a far more positive attitude
                    in their coverage of the address. Both moderate-conservative <hi rend="italic"
                        >Le Figaro</hi> and rightist <hi rend="italic">L’Aurore</hi> stress that the
                    President had spoken out against “narrow nationalism.” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Figaro</hi> coverage is factual although its Washington correspondent found
                    much of the speech “inspired” by the declarations of <persName
                        corresp="#p_DGC_1">De Gaulle</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">L’Aurore</hi>, on the other hand, urges Atlantic cooperation
                    and U.S. friendship when it writes: “Under the protection of this [U.S.] power,
                    we were able to live and to recover. . . . Many Frenchmen are stupified to see
                    French-American friendship threatened. Many Frenchmen remember, and read with
                    joy the words of President <persName corresp="#p_JLB_1">Johnson</persName> on
                    narrow nationalism which threatens to demolish the Atlantic Alliance and to turn
                    us back to the anguish of twenty years ago.”</p>
                <p>Mass-circulation <hi rend="italic">France-Soir</hi>, largest of the French
                    dailies and moderately Gaullist, remarks that “for the moment President
                        <persName corresp="#p_JLB_1">Johnson</persName> is not attacking <persName
                        corresp="#p_DGC_1">De Gaulle</persName> directly, but in his present state
                    of mind he will certainly do so if criticism continues from Paris with the same
                    virulence.”</p>
                <p>West German comments are overwhelmingly favorable and centered on the President’s
                    remarks on German affairs. Among the leading papers center-left <hi
                        rend="italic">Suddeutsche Zeitung</hi> states that the “address assumes an
                    importance of its own among the appeals and speeches devoted to the 8th of May.
                    . . . <persName corresp="#p_JLB_1">Johnson</persName> draws lessons from the
                    follies of the past and the most fundamental of these is a strict rebuff to the
                    idea of isolationism. Instead, stress is laid on partnership, primarily
                    partnership with Europe . . . <persName corresp="#p_JLB_1">Johnson</persName>
                    coined a new term in speaking about “Atlantic Civilization.’” The
                    moderate-conservative <hi rend="italic">Frankfurter Allgeimeine Zeitung</hi>
                    headlines: “<persName corresp="#p_JLB_1">Johnson</persName>—Reunification as a
                    Pressing Problem.” Independent <hi rend="italic">Stuttgart Zeitung</hi>
                    emphasizes: “<persName corresp="#p_JLB_1">Johnson</persName> Endorses <pb
                        facs="0173" n="132" xml:id="pg_132"/> Reunification” and the center-oriented
                        <hi rend="italic">General Anzeiger,</hi> Bonn, headlines: “<persName
                        corresp="#p_JLB_1">Johnson</persName>—Free Elections For All Germans.” The
                    opposition <hi rend="italic">Frankfurter Rundschau</hi>, similar to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Suddeutsche Zeitung</hi> quoted above, notices above all in
                    the President’s address a “rebuff to European nationalism.”</p>
                <p>West Berlin papers focus on the remark that “the shame of the East Zone must
                    end.” The independent <hi rend="italic">Spandauer Volksblatt</hi>, in addition,
                    notes the President’s call for improved relations and trade with Eastern
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>In Italy, the appeal for Atlantic unity is particularly stressed. Typical of
                    comment in the editorial in liberal <hi rend="italic">La Stampa</hi> (one of
                    Italy’s leading papers) which says: “In substance, <persName corresp="#p_JLB_1"
                        >Johnson</persName> has reverted to the essential outlines of the grand
                    design of President <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1">Kennedy</persName>, to wit an
                    Atlantic community linked by a common history and civilization, with even closer
                    relations. . .” Calling the speech of fundamental importance, the paper
                    continues: “The U.S. does not believe in nationalism but works toward closer and
                    deeper interdependence in the Atlantic Community.”</p>
                <p>Moderate-right <hi rend="italic">Il Tempo</hi>’s editorial is equally laudatory
                    when it praises the President for employing language “of truth, with the lofty
                    force of a leader who sees in the world responsibilities entrusted to him, the
                    stimulus to work not for peace at all costs, but for peace with freedom. The aim
                    of the speech so full of wise and realistic warnings is the relaunching of the
                    Atlantic Alliance; many people in Europe hope that his appeal will be listened
                    to, especially in Paris.”</p>
                <p>British comments most often single out, as the salient point of the speech, the
                    implied admonition of Gaullist nationalism. The liberal <hi rend="italic"
                        >Guardian</hi> headlines: “<gloss target="#t_LBJ_1">LBJ</gloss> Condemns
                    Gaullist Doctrine” and the conservative <hi rend="italic">Daily Telegraph</hi>
                    carries a headline: “<persName corresp="#p_JLB_1">Johnson</persName> Asks Europe
                    to Ignore <persName corresp="#p_DGC_1">De Gaulle</persName>.” The conservative
                        <hi rend="italic">Daily Mail</hi> declares this was the first major speech
                    on European affairs by the President since his inauguration. The paper adds that
                    “never before has he spoken with such force to condemn France’s policies.” The
                    independent <hi rend="italic">Scotsman</hi> remarks that while the President
                    “did not say anything new . . . what he had to say was both timely and
                    reassuring.” The paper says that evidently “Europe was not forgotten” in spite
                    of U.S. preoccupation with Vietnam and the Caribbean.”</p>
                <p>Sharp criticism of the publicity angle of the address was contained in the highly
                    respected <hi rend="italic">Daily Telegraph</hi> which carried a column from its
                    Washington correspondent titled “Misgivings Over Early Bird Speech”: “President
                        <persName corresp="#p_JLB_1">Johnson</persName> has set a cat among the
                    diplomatic pigeons by this Early Bird televised speech. . . . No European
                    government was notified in advance. Technicians were only given a few hours’
                    notice. Before Early Bird . . . an American President could speak ‘live’ on a
                    European <pb facs="0174" n="133" xml:id="pg_133"/> network only by being in that
                    continent. Protocol would demand that he give his host government reasonable
                    notice and let it see the text of the speech in advance. . .”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_WDM_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_WDM_1">Donald M. Wilson</persName>
                        <note n="4" xml:id="d45fn4">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
