<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Embassy in Bolivia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d140</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">140</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-09-08T18:28:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-09-08T18:28:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQFlapfZuYOQASo" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042795"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nationalization</term>
                    <term ref="recmcLXlokIhw3k5j" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-09-08T18:28:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-09-08T18:28:00-05:00" n="140"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d140">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">824.2544/9–852:Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in Bolivia</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d140fn1">Drafted by Assistant Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_MEG1">Miller</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-09-08T19:28:00-04:00"
                            >September 8, 1952—7:28 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>70. Amb<note n="2" xml:id="d140fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEJ1">Edward J. Sparks</persName> was appointed
                        Ambassador to Bolivia on Jan. 18, 1952; he arrived in La Paz on June 3 and
                        presented his credentials on June 13, 1952.</note> from <persName
                        corresp="#p_MEG1">Miller</persName>. Re urlet <persName corresp="#p_MTC1"
                        >Mann</persName> Aug 18<note n="3" xml:id="d140fn3">Not found in Department
                        of State files.</note> we have been reviewing in Dept position we have been
                    maintaining that <gloss target="#t_RFC1">RFC</gloss> shd sign no long term tin
                    contract so long as uncertainty exists re nationalization of mines. Depts
                    position has been based on fear that signing long term contract cld be
                    considered by Bol Govt as green light to confiscatory nationalization and that
                    this wld have bad effect in other countries where US property rights are at
                    stake. Statements from Chile since recent election re possible nationalization
                    copper mines give us new cause for concern this score.</p>
                <p>On other hand representatives of Mercantile Metal and Ore argued last week that
                    signing of long term contract with them wld help <persName corresp="#p_PEV1"
                        >Paz</persName> pursue more moderate course in dealing with tin mines and
                    that our continued refusal to sign contract wld play into hands of
                        <persName>Lechín</persName>. This argument does not appear convincing since
                    there is no reason why <persName>Lechín</persName> cld not take credit for
                    contract. Furthermore since Mercantile discussions with <persName
                        corresp="#p_PEV1">Paz</persName> latter has issued another public
                    affirmation of intention to take over mines immed. Also we are hesitant about
                    beginning discussions of contract while producing cos are still negotiating with
                    Govt.</p>
                <p>We wld appreciate ur comments on foregoing particularly on question whether immed
                    sig long term contract with escape clause wld tend be moderating influence in re
                    to Bol Govts tin policy or whether on other hand continued refusal to sign
                    contract wld play into hands of <persName>Lechín</persName>. Pls bear in mind
                    that in view of doubts as to Bol ability to pay prompt, adequate and effective
                    compensation upon nationalization, contract wld probably have to contain broad
                    escape clause giving <gloss target="#t_RFC1">RFC</gloss> right to terminate
                    contract or stop purchases upon nationalization. In this connection we have in
                    mind possibility of extensive litigation which wld arise as to title to
                    ores.</p>
                <p>We realize it is difficult for you to express view on foregoing questions except
                    in context of package deal involving econ assistance, but situation seems so
                    confused in Bol both with regard to nationalization and otherwise that we
                    hesitate to use even implied promise of such assistance as bargaining point at
                    this stage. However, we wld appreciate receiving your opinion as to whether you
                    cld effectively approach <persName corresp="#p_PEV1">Paz</persName> at this
                    stage to explain fully our point of view re tin. In such a conversation you
                    might stress our willingness continue buy tin on day-to-day basis pending
                    clarification of situation. You cld also say that once ultimate disposition of
                    tin mines has been made either <pb facs="0541" n="503" xml:id="pg_503"/> through
                    agreement with owners or through payment of adequate and effective compensation
                    we wld be willing work out with them a broader program of econ coop.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d140fn4">In telegram 80, from La Paz, dated Sept. 9, 1952, addressed
                        to Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MEG1">Miller</persName>,
                        Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SEJ1">Sparks</persName> stated that both
                        the Bolivian Government and the tin producing companies were convinced that
                        nationalization was an imperative political necessity. He stated further
                        that the signing of a long-term tin contract, coupled with an offer of a
                        broad program of economic cooperation, would be a moderating influence, but
                        that he was uncertain whether he could effectively approach President
                            <persName corresp="#p_PEV1">Paz Estenssoro</persName> at the present
                        time. (824.2544/9–952)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_ADG1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
