<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-06-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-06-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="268" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d268">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">821.413/6–1952</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by <persName corresp="#p_BMM1">Maurice M. Bernbaum</persName> of the Office
                                of South American Affairs</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1952-06-19">June 19,
                                    1952</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Protestant Difficulties in Colombia</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <item>Participants: Sr. <persName corresp="#p_RJC1">don Cipriano
                                    Restrepo-Jaramillo</persName>, Colombian Ambassador</item>
                            <item>Sr. <persName corresp="#p_BJM1">don José María Bernal</persName>,
                                Colombian Minister of War</item>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_UNA1">UNA</gloss>—Mr. <persName>John
                                    Hickerson</persName>, Assistant Secretary</item>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MEG1">Edward G. Miller, Jr.</persName>, Assistant Secretary</item>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_OSA1">OSA</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BWT1">W. Tapley Bennett</persName>, Deputy Director</item>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_OSA1">OSA</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMM1">Maurice M. Bernbaum</persName>, Officer in Charge, NWC</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The difficulties being experienced by Protestant Missionaries in Colombia
                            were discussed at a luncheon held today at the Colombian Embassy.</p>
                        <p>The subject was raised by Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BJM1">Bernal</persName> in connection with his description of current
                            guerrilla activities (see memorandum of conversation of same date<note n="1" xml:id="d268fn1">
                                <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note>). He stated that the
                            difficulties now being experienced by the Protestants were to a very
                            considerable extent related to civil unrest. As in the case of the
                            guerrillas who were being incited by the Communists for the purpose of
                            fomenting disorder, the Communists were taking advantage of antagonism
                            between the Catholics and Protestants for the same purpose. Dr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BJM1">Bernal</persName> went so far as to
                            state that most of the atrocities being committed against the
                            Protestants were Communist-inspired. He immediately back tracked,
                            however, when queried as to whether the Priests who had reportedly led
                            the mob action against the Baptist Church in Bogota of last December
                            were Communists. He admitted that these as well as many other Priests in
                            Colombia were fanatically opposed to the Protestants and often went out
                            of their way to oppose them. He emphasized, however, that such
                            activities were in no way a reflection of either church or government
                            policy. When asked regarding the prospects of a solution to the
                            Protestant problem, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BJM1">Bernal</persName>
                            responded that the prospects were indeed good. He felt, however, that
                            since the difficulties being experienced by them were so closely related
                            to civil strife the solution to their difficulties would be dependent
                            upon the ability of the Government to suppress guerrilla activities.
                            When this objective was achieved, he stated that the Protestants would
                            have nothing to fear.</p>
                        <p>The foregoing was to a large extent contradicted, however, by the
                            Ambassador, who entered the conversation with the statement that the <pb facs="0815" n="777" xml:id="pg_777"/> Protestant Missionaries could
                            not legitimately expect to operate unmolested in a predominately
                            Catholic country. He stated that regardless of the attitude of the
                            Government, it would be impossible for anybody to insure immunity for
                            Protestant Missionary activities in out-of-the-way parts of the country.
                            He then drew a parallel with the southern part of the United States,
                            particularly the bombings of Catholic Churches which had taken place
                            during the last year in the state of Florida. He then inquired regarding
                            the treatment to be expected by Catholic Missionaries in small,
                            predominately Protestant communities.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MEG1">Miller</persName> remarked at this point
                            that the treatment accorded Catholic Missionaries in the U.S. could
                            hardly be compared with that being experienced by Protestant
                            Missionaries in Colombia. He remarked that of all Churches, the Catholic
                            was one which had the greatest stake in the concept of the freedom of
                            religion in view of its extensive missionary interests all over the
                            world. He pointed out that Catholic Missionary activities were most
                            intensive in the Far East and Near East amongst the predominately Moslem
                            and Hindu populations. He then went on to say that the Department held
                            no brief for any particular missionary activity and had, as a matter of
                            fact, been instrumental in securing the admission into Guatemala of a
                            representative of the Catholic <persName>Maryknoll</persName> Order.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MEG1">Miller</persName> went on to say that the
                            Protestant Missionary problem in Colombia was a matter of increasing
                            concern to the Department, which had been experiencing considerable
                            pressure from Members of Congress as well as private individuals from
                            all parts of the country. While realizing the problems being faced by
                            the Colombian Government, he expressed the hope that something could be
                            done to eliminate this most unfortunate irritant in the relations
                            between the two countries.</p>
                        <p>Obviously uncomfortable, the Colombian Ambassador reaffirmed the
                            impracticability of expecting the Protestants to be immune from
                            opposition, particularly in a Catholic country undergoing civil strife.
                            He added, in response to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MEG1">Miller</persName>’s statement regarding Catholic Missionary
                            activities, that he did not believe there were any Colombian Catholic
                            Missionaries in the United States requiring protection. He then
                            laughingly remarked that he was probably in receipt of as many letters
                            of complaint as was the Department. He attributed this to the recent
                            propaganda campaign of the <hi rend="italic">Presbyterian Life</hi>
                            which was making a special point of stimulating protests.</p>
                        <p>Although the conversation terminated amicably, it had been made clear to
                            the Colombian Ambassador and to the Minister of War that the Protestant
                            Missionary problem was a most important factor in Departmental thinking
                            regarding US relations with Colombia.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>