<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Robert M. Sayre of the Office of Regional American Affairs to
                    John W. Fisher of the Office of Middle American Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d398</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">398</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-10-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recibBhfq1Nhuo5rk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-10-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="398"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d398">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">716.56/10–153</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by <persName type="from">Robert M. Sayre</persName>
                        of the Office of Regional American Affairs to <persName type="to">John W.
                            Fisher</persName> of the Office of Middle American Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-10-01">October 1,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Salvador Arms Request.</item>
                </list>
                <p>You will recall that a special delegation<note n="1" xml:id="d398fn1">The
                        delegation consisted of Minister of Labor <persName corresp="#p_SGC1"
                            >Salazar</persName>, Minister of Economy <persName>Jorge Arturo Sol
                            Castellanos</persName>, and Chief of Staff <persName>Marco Antonio
                            Molina</persName>.</note> from El Salvador came to the United States to
                    discuss with the Departments of State and Defense the procurement of arms. The
                    first discussion was held on February 24, at which time the Salvadorans were
                    informed that arms could be obtained in the United States (1) from commercial
                    sources, (2) from the Department of Defense or (3) under the terms of a military
                    assistance agreement with the United States. As to (3), it was made very clear
                    that we could make no commitment on a military assistance agreement under which
                    Salvador could obtain arms on a grant basis. The Salvadoran delegation promised
                    to supply us immediately with a list of the arms desired.</p>
                <pb facs="1048" n="1010" xml:id="pg_1010"/>
                <p>We received such a list on February 25 and transmitted it the same day to the
                    Department of Defense. The Department of Defense provided us with estimated
                    prices on February 27, but on such short notice was unable to provide us with
                    any availability data. on March 10 the Department of Defense furnished us with a
                    “refined” price list after they had had an opportunity to study the request
                    further, and this list was furnished the Salvadorans on March 11. They were
                    advised that we could take no further action until we received a firm request
                    from them for arms.</p>
                <p>The Army Attaché<note n="2" xml:id="d398fn2">Lt. Col. <persName>Henry J. Muller,
                            Jr.</persName>
                    </note> to El Salvador reported on March 2 that the Minister of Defense had
                    requested his assistance in obtaining arms for approximately 10,000 men without
                    going through the Department of State. On March 11, the Army Attaché reported
                    that a delegation was being sent from El Salvador to attempt to obtain arms in
                    the commercial market in addition to those which the United States was being
                    requested to supply.</p>
                <p>When on March 26, the Department had received no information from El Salvador as
                    to the action Salvador planned to take on the list of equipment furnished by the
                    Department of the Army on March 11, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJM1"
                        >Cabot</persName>, in a discussion<note n="3" xml:id="d398fn3">A memorandum
                        of the referenced conversation, dated Mar. 26, 1953, is in file
                        716.5614/3–2653.</note> with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_CHD1"
                        >Castro</persName> on Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName>’s
                    forthcoming trip to El Salvador, took the occasion to remind Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_CHD1">Castro</persName> that we had received no reply
                    on the military equipment list we had furnished and although we did not want to
                    press the matter, we did want to make it clear that we were prepared to help in
                    every way possible.</p>
                <p>When Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> was in El Salvador,
                    President <persName corresp="#p_OO1">Osorio</persName> gave Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> the list of equipment desired and it was
                    transmitted on the same day by Embassy D–679 of April 24, 1953.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d398fn4">Not printed (716.56/4–2453).</note> After clarification of
                    some problems which the list presented, the request was approved and transmitted
                    to the Department of Defense on May 12. The request stated that Salvador desired
                    to buy the equipment over a period of four years, but gave no indication as to
                    what part of the equipment was desired each year. When it appeared that the
                    Salvadoran Embassy would be unable to furnish us, in any reasonable time, with
                    information on the equipment from the list that was desired immediately, we
                    advised the Department of Defense in a memorandum of May 25<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d398fn5">Not printed (716.5 MSP/5–2653).</note> to make a pricing
                    and availability study and an offer on the entire list and <pb facs="1049"
                        n="1011" xml:id="pg_1011"/> leave it to the Salvadorans to select those
                    items which they desired immediately. Any other items they desired would then
                    have to be the basis of a further request because prices and availability would
                    change.</p>
                <p>The Department of the Army submitted on June 24 to the Salvadoran Ambassador a
                    firm offer to sell the equipment desired at a cost of about $2.3 million.<note
                        n="6" xml:id="d398fn6">The equipment requested by the Salvadoran Government
                        included rockets and rocket launchers, small arms and ammunition, signal
                        equipment, and quartermaster items.</note> At the same time the Department
                    sent a copy of this offer to Embassy San Salvador so that it could be brought to
                    the attention of the Salvadoran Government if the Embassy considered this
                    appropriate. The Army’s offer had a thirty day limit on it, but it was
                    understood that this was a flexible limit and acceptance of the offer within a
                    reasonable time would be satisfactory. Although both the Department and the
                    Embassy have urged the Salvadorans to take action on this arms request, no
                    acceptance of this offer has ever been made.</p>
                <p>The Department of the Air Force made an offer on that part of Salvador’s request
                    involving Air Force equipment on July 31, but to date has not received any
                    information from the Salvadoran Embassy regarding acceptance of the offer. We
                    have received information, however, that the Salvadorans are not very happy
                    about the Air Force offer both with respect to the non-availability of F–51’s
                    and the price of T–34’s.</p>
                <p>By a note of July 8,<note n="7" xml:id="d398fn7">Reference is to Salvadoran note
                        no. DE–109–A–820, dated July 8, 1953, not printed (716.5 MSP/7–853).</note>
                    the Salvador Embassy submitted an entirely separate request<note n="8"
                        xml:id="d398fn8">Referred to as El Salvador Case No. 7.</note> for a small
                    quantity of machine guns and rockets which would cost approximately $50,000.
                    This request was approved and transmitted to the Department of Defense by a
                    memorandum of July 14.<note n="9" xml:id="d398fn9">Not printed (716.5
                        MSP/7–853).</note> This request was modified by a note of July 24<note
                        n="10" xml:id="d398fn10">Reference is to Salvadoran note no. DE–118–A–820,
                        dated July 24, 1953, not printed (716.5 MSP/7–2453).</note> to drop the
                    machine guns from the list and add steel helmets. This modification was sent to
                    the Department of Defense by memorandum of July 27.<note n="11"
                        xml:id="d398fn11">Not printed (716.5 MSP/7–1453).</note> The Department
                    informally advised Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_CHD1">Castro</persName> on
                    August 24 of the total cost of the equipment covered by this request and the
                    Army presented its formal offer to him on August 24.</p>
                <p>I am informed by the Army that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_CHD1"
                        >Castro</persName> sent the money to cover the cost of this equipment on
                    September 1. Before the Army could proceed with shipping instructions to the
                    depots, etc., it required <pb facs="1050" n="1012" xml:id="pg_1012"/>
                    instructions for marking the matériel for shipment. This information was
                    received from the Salvadoran Embassy on September 21. The Army has now prepared
                    instructions to its supply people and it is expected that all of the matériel
                    can be shipped from its present location within 60 days upon the basis of
                    shipping instructions furnished by the Salvadoran Embassy.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
