<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Director of the Office of Regional
                    American Affairs ( (Cale))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d426</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">426</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-11-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-11-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040838"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recGiqhGF0E6qdj5q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2019102796"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Boycott</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-11-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-11-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="426"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d426">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">814.2333/11–2553</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Director of the Office of
                        Regional American Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CEG1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cale</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1953-11-25">November 25,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Guatemalan Coffee</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>Participants: Mr. <persName>Jim O’Connor</persName>, President, National
                        Coffee Association</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>R. A. Medina</persName>, R. A. Medina Co.</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Phil Nelson</persName>, <persName>Ruffner</persName>,
                        McDonnell &amp; Burch, Inc.</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Harry H. Allen</persName>, Vice President, Otis McAllister
                        Coffee Corp.</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>John F. McKiernan</persName>, Executive Vice President,
                        National Coffee Association</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName>, <gloss target="#t_ARA1"
                            >ARA</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CEG1">Cale</persName>, <gloss target="#t_AR1"
                            >AR</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> pointed out that the Department
                    is faced with a very difficult problem as a result of communist influence within
                    Guatemala. He said that in considering possible courses of action to meet the
                    situation the question of economic sanctions has to be considered. In this
                    connection, coffee, which supplies some 80 per cent of the Guatemalan foreign
                    exchange, is obviously the most important single individual commodity on which
                    action might be taken.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> stated that he wished members of
                    the group to understand that they had been invited to Washington not because any
                    immediate action involving coffee is now contemplated but because he wishes to
                    have the benefit of the advice of the representatives of the coffee trade in
                    connection with our consideration of possible action.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d426fn1">A previous conversation relating to possible action against
                        Guatemala involving coffee took place at the Department of State on Feb. 27,
                        1952, between Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName>, Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_CEG1">Cale</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SEV1"
                            >Siracusa</persName>, and a representative of the National Coffee
                        Association; a memorandum of that conversation, by Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_SEV1">Siracusa</persName>, dated Feb. 27, 1952, not printed,
                        is in file 814.2333/2–2752.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ORL1">O’Connor</persName> pointed out that the
                    companies of Messrs. <persName>Medina</persName>, <persName>Nelson</persName>
                    and <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen</persName> do the major part of the import
                    business in Guatemalan coffee and that they are accordingly in an excellent
                    position to advise the Department on the matter.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> stated that the Department would
                    like to have the group’s views as to the feasibility and mechanics of a
                    Government embargo against or an industry boycott of Guatemalan coffee.</p>
                <p>At Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ORL1">O’Connor</persName>’s suggestion, Mr.
                        <persName>Medina</persName> spoke first for the coffee representatives. He
                    said that the group had had an opportunity to discuss the question in a
                    preliminary fashion but that they had not considered the possibility of an
                    industry boycott in the absence of action by the Government. Mr.
                        <persName>Medina</persName> then called attention to the following
                    considerations: <pb facs="1127" n="1089" xml:id="pg_1089"/>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>That it is often impossible to distinguish between Guatemalan coffee
                            and coffee grown in nearby countries such as Mexico and El Salvador.
                            Under these conditions, even if the United States Government should
                            embargo Guatemalan coffee, it would be likely to find its way into this
                            country through Mexico, El Salvador and other Latin American
                            countries.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>That American coffee importers, at any time, have large investments in
                            coffee in Guatemala. Accordingly, an embargo on Guatemalan coffee would
                            subject such importers to considerable financial loss.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>To Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CEG1">Cale</persName>’s inquiry whether it would be
                    possible for the importers to avoid this loss, if they were informed several
                    months in advance of the contemplated action, Mr. <persName>Medina</persName>
                    stated that prior notice would be helpful. He pointed out, however, that the
                    helpfulness of the notice would depend not only on the period of the notice but
                    on the time of the embargo. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen</persName>
                    called attention to the fact that his company and certain other coffee importers
                    advance rather large sums of money early during a crop year to finance the
                    production and harvesting of the crop. The crop year in Guatemala, he said,
                    begins around October 1st. If the Government were contemplating action, he said
                    that June 1, with several months of advance notice, would probably be as good
                    from the point of view of timing as any other date.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ORL1">O’Connor</persName> pointed out, however, that,
                    in view of the present tight market situation, such a date would be about as
                    unfavorable as any that could be chosen from the viewpoint of its effect on
                    price, since there is very little coffee available for sale and shipment during
                    this period. It was Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ORL1">O’Connor</persName>’s
                    estimate that excluding the 800,000 bags of Guatemalan coffee which we normally
                    import, if such exclusion were possible, would probably raise the price of all
                    coffee to the United States consumer by as much as 10 cents per pound.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen</persName> called attention to another
                    adverse effect of embargoing Guatemalan coffee, namely, the fact that it would
                    force the Guatemalan Government to become much more involved in the coffee trade
                    than it is at present. This, he said, he regarded as contrary to the long-run
                    interests of the United States coffee industry.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CEG1">Cale</persName> then inquired whether it would be
                    possible for this Government to take action only against coffee now grown on the
                    Government’s lands, which amounts to some 15 per cent of the total Guatemalan
                    production. The group was of the opinion that even if United States importers
                    did not buy coffee produced on these lands at the auctions at which it is now
                    sold, such coffee would nevertheless find its way into the United States. They
                    pointed out that this coffee is sold before it is fully processed and that there
                    is no way of maintaining its identity.</p>
                <pb facs="1128" n="1090" xml:id="pg_1090"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Nelson</persName> referred to the fact that Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> had spoken of a possible boycott on the
                    part of the coffee trade. He expressed the view that this would simply not work,
                    since the coffee business is highly competitive and since, in the unlikely event
                    that all the present members of the coffee trade would cooperate, fly-by-night
                    operators would appear to handle this part of the business. Mr.
                        <persName>Nelson</persName> also called attention to the fact that even if
                    Guatemalan coffee were excluded from this market, it would very probably be sold
                    in Europe. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ORL1">O’Connor</persName> added that in
                    this event it might very well end up in the United States. He pointed out in
                    this connection that a considerable volume of Brazilian coffee is now being
                    imported into the United States via Europe.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Nelson</persName> also expressed the belief that embargoing
                    Guatemalan coffee would have a very adverse effect on our relations with the
                    Latin American countries generally, since they are very sensitive to economic
                    pressure of any kind by the United States.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen</persName> supported Mr.
                        <persName>Nelson</persName>’s views in this regard, pointing out that there
                    are very close family relationships throughout the Cental American area and that
                    these would tend to heighten the reaction against the United States.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> inquired as to the feasibility
                    of levying an import tax on Guatemalan coffee. Representatives of the group said
                    that this would be very dangerous since it might set a precedent for an import
                    tax on coffee from other countries as well. They pointed out that there have
                    been numerous proposals in the past for taxing the importation of coffee, all of
                    which have so far been successfully resisted. They indicated, however, that the
                    coffee trade, to a man, was fearful that an import tax on coffee might some day
                    become a reality. They stated that this would, of course, be harmful to the
                    coffee importers and roasters in this country as well as to the coffee producers
                    in Latin America.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CEG1">Cale</persName> inquired what the group’s views
                    would be as to the feasibility of requiring that the consumer be informed
                    whenever he buys Guatemalan coffee. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ORL1"
                        >O’Connor</persName> said that coffee purchased by the consumer is generally
                    a mixture of several types and that all coffee would have to be labelled in
                    order to show the consumer the proportion of Guatemalan coffee. He stated that
                    this would greatly hamper the operations of the coffee roasters who change their
                    blends often in accordance with availabilities of various types of coffee.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>McKiernan</persName> pointed out, in addition, that the net effect
                    of such a requirement might be to reduce coffee consumption generally. He
                    feared, he said, that any action to get the American public to consume less
                    Guatemalan coffee would result in a decline of consumption of all coffee.</p>
                <pb facs="1129" n="1091" xml:id="pg_1091"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> thanked the representatives of
                    the coffee industry for giving the Department the benefit of their views. They
                    expressed their pleasure in being able to do so and stated that they regretted
                    that they were not able to make any suggestion which they considered feasible
                    whereby coffee might be used as a means of improving the situation in Guatemala,
                    which they recognize as very serious.<note n="2" xml:id="d426fn2">On Feb. 8,
                        1954, Senator <persName>Margaret Chase Smith</persName> (<gloss
                            target="#t_R1">R</gloss>.–Maine) introduced Senate Resolution 211,
                        calling upon the President, <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>, to take the
                        necessary steps to institute an embargo against the importation of
                        Guatemalan coffee into the United States; for text, see <hi rend="italic"
                            >Congressional Record</hi>, 83d Cong., 2d sess., vol. 100 (pt. 2), p.
                        1475. Department of State files indicate that representatives of the
                        Department advised Congress against taking such action.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
