<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Statement of Policy by the National Security Council</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d455</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">455</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-05-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-05-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="receIYhB3LZw2jzyV" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general">Public
                        disclosure</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-05-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-05-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="455"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d455">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> files,
                    lot 62 D 1, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5419/1 Series</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Statement of Policy by the National Security Council</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d455fn1">
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Executive Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_LJS1">Lay</persName>, under a covering note dated May 28,
                        1954, not printed, transmitted the recommendations of <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5419 (paragraphs 5 to 9), adopted by the
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> subject to the changes set forth in
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 1135–<hi rend="italic"
                            >b</hi>, to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> as <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5419/1. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJS1"
                            >Lay</persName> informed the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> of the
                        President’s authorization to the Navy to halt Guatemalan coastal vessels,
                        including foreign-flag vessels suspected of carrying munitions of war, for
                        cargo inspection, and also the President’s reference to <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 144/1, paragraph 18–<hi rend="italic"
                            >b</hi> (see <ref target="#pg_10">p. 10</ref>) regarding U.S. policy on
                        training the military establishments of Latin American nations. President
                            <persName>Eisenhower</persName> approved the recommendations in <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5419/1 on May 28, 1954, directed their
                        implementation by all appropriate executive departments and agencies, and
                        designated the <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> as the coordinating
                        agency.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5419/1</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-05-28">May 28,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">U.S. Policy in the Event of Guatemalan Aggression in Latin
                        America</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">recommendations</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>If the government of any member of the Organization of American States
                        should, under Article 3, paragraph 2 of the Rio Treaty, request the
                        assistance of the United States to meet an armed attack by Guatemala, and if
                        the President should be satisfied that such an attack has occurred, it is
                        recommended that the President: <pb facs="1174" n="1136" xml:id="pg_1136"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Determine that such Guatemalan armed attack is considered by the
                                United States as an armed attack against all American states under
                                Article 3, paragraph 1 of the Rio Treaty,<note n="*"
                                    xml:id="d455fn2">For text of pertinent articles of the Rio
                                    Treaty, see Appendix. [Footnote in the source text; appendix not
                                    printed.]</note> and constitutes an imminent threat to the
                                security of the United States.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Direct that under Article 3, paragraph 2 of the Rio Treaty and to
                                protect the security of the United States, the armed forces of the
                                United States, in collaboration with the armed forces of other
                                members of the Organization of American States to the extent
                                feasible, and unilaterally only as a last resort, take military
                                action to the extent necessary to counter-act the attack and
                                eliminate the danger to the state attacked.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The United States should encourage any member of the Organization of
                        American States which requests the United States to come to its assistance,
                        also to request such action by other members of the Organization of American
                        States pending a decision by the Organ of Consultation.<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d455fn3">On Sept. 3, 1954, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            Acting Executive Secretary <persName corresp="#p_GSE1"
                                >Gleason</persName>, in a memorandum to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                >NSC</gloss>, not printed, stated that the Council at its 212th
                            meeting on Sept. 2, 1954, in connection with action on <gloss
                                target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5432, agreed that the statement of
                            policy in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5419/1 “should be
                            terminated as no longer applicable.” (<gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                >NSC</gloss> Action No. 1209) President
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName> approved the action of the Council
                            on Sept. 3, thereby terminating <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            5419/1. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GSE1">Gleason</persName> informed the
                            Council that “policy relating to action against anti-U.S. subversion or
                            intervention in Latin America and to the application of sanctions,
                            including military action, in the event of threatened or actual
                            domination of a Latin American state by Communism” was contained in
                            paragraph 6 of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5432/1 (see <ref
                                target="#pg_83">p. 83</ref>).</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The United States should take all practicable political steps to ensure
                        that the other members of Organization of American States are prepared for
                        collective action under the Rio Treaty to assist any member of Organization
                        of American States threatened by aggression or internal subversion inspired
                        by Guatemala.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Appropriate congressional leaders should be immediately informed of the
                        above policy.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The timing of public disclosure of the above policy should be determined
                        by the Secretary of State.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
