<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-24T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-24T17:00:00-05:00" n="484" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d484">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">714.00/6–2454:Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative at the United
                                Nations</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_LHC1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Lodge</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-24T18:00:00-04:00">June 24,
                                    1954—6 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>876. For the Secretary. Re Guatemala. I told <persName>Dixon</persName>
                            and <persName>Hoppenot</persName> this morning that we had worked hard
                            all yesterday to get <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> to take some
                            action in line their position<note n="1" xml:id="d484fn1">In telegram
                                867, from New York, dated June 23, 1954, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> stated in part the following:
                                    “<persName>Hoppenot</persName> and <persName>Dixon</persName>
                                called on me in private and told me that if the Soviet Union moved
                                to send a peace observation commission to the region of Guatemala
                                they would have to vote in favor of it unless the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> had taken action to send
                                observation of its own.” (714.00/6–2354)</note> yesterday. <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> did take action last night<note n="2" xml:id="d484fn2">On June 23, 1954, the Inter-American Peace
                                Committee decided to authorize the formation of a subcommittee of
                                information, composed of members of the <gloss target="#t_IAPC1">IAPC</gloss>, which might visit Guatemala, Nicaragua, and
                                Honduras, and with consent of those governments, conduct an
                                investigation of the complaints they had laid before the
                                committee.</note> which met their position.
                                <persName>Dixon</persName> had informed me this morning his
                            government’s policy had changed and they now insisted on <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> observation. I had immediately
                                reported<note n="3" xml:id="d484fn3">Reference is to telegram 870,
                                from New York, dated June 24, 1954, not printed
                                (714.00/6–2454).</note> this to Washington. I now had an important
                            statement to make to them and I had asked them to come to my office so
                            that I could do so in person. I said that this statement was not in any
                            sense of the word a threat because of course they represented strong
                            independent governments that would do whatever they wanted but that I
                            was instructed by the President to say to them that if Great Britain and
                            France felt that they must take an independent line backing the present
                            government of Guatemala, we would feel free to take an equally
                            independent line concerning such matters as Egypt and North Africa in
                            which we had hitherto tried to exercise the greatest forbearance so as
                            not to embarrass Great Britain and France.</p>
                        <p>My announcement was received with great solemnity.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lodge</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>