<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Director for Northern Division Latin America, Foreign
                    Operations Administration ( (Clay) ) to the Acting Regional Director of the
                    Office of Latin American Operations, Foreign Operations Administration (
                    (Hardesty))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d543</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">543</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-12-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-12-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recP2zv9bjAjSyYPT" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="recDNr3fFoY74D9ro" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recXe3hjASdIXoUSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066112"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Inflation</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recez5uVgqvmr6Nwm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006268"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Irrigation</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="foreign-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-12-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-12-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="543"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d543">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_MID1">MID</gloss> files, lot 57 D 148, “Point
                    IV–Miscellaneous”</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director for Northern Division Latin
                        America, Foreign Operations Administration</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Clay</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Acting Regional Director of the Office of
                        Latin American Operations, Foreign Operations Administration</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_HMN1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hardesty</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-12-27">December 27,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Emergency Economic Assistance to Haiti</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="1326" n="1288" xml:id="pg_1288"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary and Recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The $2,000,000 worth of surplus agricultural commodities plus funds for
                    transportation and the $350,000 worth of seeds and light agricultural tools
                    which have already been made available have provided the means for the
                    Government to maintain reasonably tranquil conditions in this immediate period
                    following the hurricane disaster. On the basis of initial reports, however, it
                    was anticipated that additional emergency assistance would be required to enable
                    Haiti to recover from this disaster. The <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>–1956
                    Program proposed by <gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss>, therefore, included
                    $3,000,000 in addition to the normal technical cooperation program for emergency
                    assistance. This proposed $3,000,000 was eliminated by State.</p>
                <p>Since that time, the President of Haiti has orally requested our Ambassador, at a
                        meeting<note n="1" xml:id="d543fn1">No record of this meeting was found in
                        Department of State files.</note> attended by the Director of <gloss
                        target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d543fn2">
                        <persName>Raymond C. Smith</persName>.</note> and myself, for emergency
                    assistance. The Ambassador informed the President that he did not know whether
                    such assistance could be made available, but that in any case, an official
                    written request would be required. Following the oral request, the Director of
                        <gloss target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss> and I met with a committee appointed
                    by the President and on each occasion it was carefully explained— <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>that no funds were contained in the <gloss target="#t_FY1"
                            >FY</gloss>–1955 or proposed <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>–1956
                            budget for such assistance;</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>that there was absolutely no assurance that funds could be obtained
                            and it would at best be extremely difficult;</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>that any request would have to be directly related to the disaster and
                            not for normal economic development, and</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>that before any request could even be considered, it would have to be
                            established that the emergency could not be met through maximum feasible
                            effective utilization of the country’s own resources and borrowing
                            capacities.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>It was added, however, that it was believed that the same type of analysis and
                    program would be required as the basis of any loans.</p>
                <p>The President again requested the Chargé and the Director of <gloss
                        target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss> for emergency assistance on December 22 and a
                    formal written request will probably be submitted to the Embassy within the next
                    two weeks. In the interim, however, both the Embassy and the <gloss
                        target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss> have reported on the basis of the information
                    available to them that emergency assistance will be required. I fully concur in
                    their conclusion on the basis of my own evaluation after a ten day visit to
                    Haiti and believe that the situation requires an immediate policy decision on
                    emergency assistance on the basis of the cables from <gloss target="#t_USOM1"
                        >USOM</gloss> and the Embassy even prior to receipt of the official written
                    request. It is understood, however, that the Department of State still believes
                    that such <pb facs="1327" n="1289" xml:id="pg_1289"/> emergency assistance is
                    not justified. I, therefore, strongly urge that someone at a high level in this
                    Agency request State to reconsider this decision.</p>
                <p>On the basis of preliminary estimates, it is believed that the minimum additional
                    emergency assistance required is approximately as follows: <table cols="2"
                        rows="3">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>–1955</cell>
                            <cell role="num">$500,000 to $750,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>–1956</cell>
                            <cell role="num">$250,000 to $3,000,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>–1957</cell>
                            <cell role="num">$1,000,000</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <p>It is recommended that the Mission should be immediately authorized to talk with
                    the Haitian Government in terms of figures as possible maximums in order to
                    induce the Government to get down to reality and to get a concrete program under
                    way while the emergency assistance already provided permits the situation to be
                    kept under control and before really serious trouble arises.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Background</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1953–54 revenues of Haiti were
                    approximately the equivalent of $35,000,000 of which approximately $10,000,000
                    was utilized for economic services and development including $3,000,000 for the
                    Artibonite Valley development for which the Export-Import Bank is also providing
                    a total of $14,000,000 in loans over a period of years. It is anticipated that
                    as a result of disaster damage to coffee and other crops, revenues will fall to
                    approximately $24,000,000 in the first year following the disaster and that
                    three years will be required before they can be restored to a normal level, even
                    if additional emergency assistance is made available. The Government of Haiti
                    estimates that exports will be down by as much as 50% and although this estimate
                    may be excessive, it is anticipated that they will be at least ⅓ below
                    normal.</p>
                <p>The regular normal expenditures of the Government can of course be cut and some
                    planned development projects postponed. The budget, however, cannot be cut to
                    the level of earlier years without bringing practically to a halt the meagre
                    economic development program which the Government has painfully gotten under way
                    in recent years and this, it is believed, would be disastrous. The Government,
                    moreover, is faced with the necessity for heavy additional expenditures for
                    reconstruction and rehabilitation essential to permit a large percentage of the
                    population to again earn a livelihood. There will, therefore, inevitably be an
                    extremely serious gap between revenues and essential expenditures. This gap can
                    not all be met by internal loans or by loans from Export-Import Bank and
                    International Bank for Reconstruction and Development. The only internal source
                    from which the Government can borrow funds is the Central Bank which can make
                    such funds available only by an expansion of the note circulation. The <pb
                        facs="1328" n="1290" xml:id="pg_1290"/> Bank believes that any further
                    drawings by the Government would result in disastrous inflation and while I do
                    not have the information to attempt to make a precise analysis, the extent to
                    which the note circulation could be further expanded is at best extremely
                    limited. The Government moreover, does not have the borrowing capacity to obtain
                    funds from the Export-Import Bank or the <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss>
                    to meet this emergency even if repayments were long deferred. The Export-Import
                    Bank has tentatively indicated its willingness to consider increasing the loan
                    for the Artibonite Valley because of increased costs since the time of the
                    original estimates, but this would not take care of internal costs which are
                    normally met from budgetary revenues. It is believed that the maximum additional
                    borrowing capacity above the possible increased loan for the Artibonite is
                    required for the Port-au-Prince–Aux Cayes road and the Artibonite hydro-electric
                    projects which are essential for the economic future of Haiti. These projects
                    are now being discussed with the <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss> and they
                    most emphatically should not be delayed until any loans for the present
                    emergency could be repaid.</p>
                <p>Emergency economic grant assistance is required primarily in <gloss
                        target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>–1956 and on a reduced scale in <gloss
                        target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>–1957. I believe, however, that it is essential
                    that some funds be made available in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>–1955
                    under Section 401 for rehabilitation and reconstruction. Work on restoration of
                    irrigation works and rehabilitation of the coffee industry should start
                    immediately, but the Government does not have funds to do so. There is also the
                    problem of the very existence of many of the people in the immediate disaster
                    areas. The emergency food supplies that have been provided should last to
                    approximately February 1. By that time there should be adequate internal food
                    supplies in the country as a whole. A large number of the population in the
                    immediate disaster areas, however, will have meagre crops of their own. Many of
                    them will not have the funds with which to purchase food from other areas in
                    Haiti and the Government will not have the funds to purchase the food for them.
                    Under these circumstances additional surplus agricultural commodities would
                    seriously disrupt the economy of the country and the only logical answer is
                    immediate initiation of the rehabilitation and reconstruction program which
                    would provide employment for at least some of these people.</p>
                <p>Any grant emergency assistance provided to Haiti must be strictly conditioned on
                    effective utilization of the Country’s own resources and anticipated borrowing
                    capacity. The need is so urgent, however, that the provision of emergency
                    economic assistance should not be delayed until the final decision is made on
                    loans. Instead, such assistance should be made available immediately on the
                    basis of written undertakings by the Government and funds then progressively
                    made available as the Government performs pursuant to its undertakings. <pb
                        facs="1329" n="1291" xml:id="pg_1291"/> The administration of a program of
                    this kind would be most difficult under conditions existing in Haiti, but the
                    fact that the Acting Mission Director, <persName>Stanly Baranson</persName>, was
                    able by standing firm to get the Government to distribute the emergency food
                    supplies honestly and effectively is at least some evidence that it could
                    succeed.</p>
                <p>[Here follows reference to attachments which were not found with the source
                    text.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
