<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs ( (Holland) ) to
                    the Ambassador in Honduras ( (Willauer))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d557</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">557</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-07-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-07-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recHROZWmaF1AEYg7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military Assistance Program</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recSkg5rdjWW1fsS7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Spare parts</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="557"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d557">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_HHF1">Holland</persName> files, lot 57 D 295,
                    “Honduras”</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HHF1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Holland</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Ambassador in Honduras</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_WW1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Willauer</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d557fn1">Drafted by Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_SGO1">Spencer</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">official–informal</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-07-16">July 16,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear <persName>Whitey</persName>
                    </hi>: I am devoting this letter wholly to the subject of additional military
                    equipment which you desire be added to the grant military assistance program we
                    are conducting for Honduras. I have requested that answers be obtained to the
                    other questions raised in your letter of June 7, 1954<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d557fn2">Not found in Department of State files.</note> and will
                    send them to you as soon as they become available.</p>
                <pb facs="1347" n="1309" xml:id="pg_1309"/>
                <p>We are awaiting a formal response from the Pentagon to your despatches Nos.
                        515<note n="3" xml:id="d557fn3">The referenced despatch, dated June 8, 1954,
                        is not printed (715.5 MSP/6–854).</note> and 517<note n="4" xml:id="d557fn4"
                        >The referenced despatch, dated June 11, 1954, is not printed (715.5
                        MSP/6–1154).</note> which recommended: (a) that the Honduran Army unit being
                    provided with grant assistance be activated by early September; (b) that in
                    order to accomplish activation by that date, Honduras be provided additional
                    equipment, such as tentage, building hardware, transportation equipment, etc.,
                    which was not originally planned for the Honduran program; and (c) that four
                    C–47 aircraft be included in the program and delivered at an early date. A copy
                    of your despatch No. 551,<note n="5" xml:id="d557fn5">Despatch 551, dated June
                        28, 1954, is not printed (715.5 MSP/6–2854).</note> reiterating your earlier
                    recommendation that Honduras be supplied with four C–47 aircraft and requesting
                    that Honduras be provided 28 additional planes, has also been forwarded to the
                    Pentagon. Yesterday we were told that we could expect to receive a Pentagon
                    reply within the next few days. However, from the information provided us
                    orally, I am sure that the Pentagon response will be negative. Some of the
                    problems which make a favorable response to your recommendations difficult are
                    enumerated below.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>First, most of the items requested in your despatch No. 515, such as
                        tentage, building hardware, etc., fall in the category of material defined
                        as “defense support”. The criteria used by the Joint Chiefs of Staff for
                        determining types of military assistance which should be provided to foreign
                        governments does not permit the provision of “defense support” items except
                        in very exceptional circumstances. The theory is that such items, although
                        they have a military application, are procurable from commerical sources.
                        There are cases, such as Indo-China, Formosa, Greece and Turkey where we are
                        providing defense support, but in each case separate funds for assistance
                        must be obtained each year from the Congress.</item>
                    <item>Secondly, we have been advised informally by the Pentagon that the U.S.
                        Air Force has no available C–47 or B–25 aircraft and that the only F4U–4’s
                        in the possession of the Department of the Navy are those which are now
                        being used by naval reserve units.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Even if all of the aircraft recommended in your despatch No. 551 could be made
                    available—and our understanding is that they cannot—the total estimated cost of
                    providing them to Honduras, according to the Pentagon, would be at the very
                    minimum about $1½ million. Funds appropriated for the Latin American program to
                    date are insufficient to absorb an increase of that amount. The grant assistance
                    program for Latin America has been justified to the Congress as a program which
                    can be carried out in its entirety with approximately $100 million, and slightly
                    more than that amount already has been appropriated to date. We are using this
                    relatively small amount of money to <pb facs="1348" n="1310" xml:id="pg_1310"/>
                    provide assistance to ten Latin American countries, with some expectation that
                    programs for El Salvador and Haiti may be commenced this year. The Congress is
                    being requested to appropriate $13 million for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                    1955, but virtually all of these funds have been earmarked by the Pentagon for
                    spare parts and training.</p>
                <p>In addition to the practical difficulties enumerated above, there are important
                    considerations of a policy nature which would make it difficult to comply with
                    the Honduran request. All of the programs we are conducting in Latin America are
                    based on the principle that mutual defense assistance funds shall be devoted
                    exclusively to assisting the other governments to activate units which they have
                    agreed to prepare for hemisphere defense missions specified in secret bilateral
                    military plans with the U.S. The Joint Chiefs of Staff in each case determined
                    the type of foreign military units which would be useful to U.S. military forces
                    engaged in the defense of the Caribbean area in time of war and defined the
                    hemisphere defense mission which each unit should perform. For example, the
                    secret military plan concluded with Honduras specifies that the Honduran
                    infantry battalion will be activated for the purpose of assisting the U.S. to
                    “protect the Panama Canal and the sea and air communications in the Caribbean
                    Sea excluding the territorial rights of other countries”. I realize that it is
                    somewhat theoretical to expect a country such as Honduras, which has military
                    forces barely sufficient to maintain internal order during an emergency, to
                    provide material assistance to U.S. military forces engaged in defense of the
                    hemisphere during an emergency. In fact, the Pentagon for a number of months
                    strongly resisted our efforts to induce it to develop a hemisphere defense
                    mission for Honduras, largely on the ground that Honduras, with limited U.S.
                    assistance, would not be able to perform a hemisphere defense role. However, the
                    Pentagon, after much urging on our part that a program would be desirable for
                    political and psychological reasons, taking into account our objectives in
                    Guatemala, finally did develop a hemisphere defense mission for Honduras and
                    thus make that country eligible for grant assistance. To alter the basic concept
                    underlying the Honduran program would require a decision at the very highest
                    level of the government through some instrumentality such as the National
                    Security Council. Moreover, it would be difficult to justify a change in the
                    concept underlying the Honduran program without at the same time justifying a
                    change in the concept underlying other Latin American programs, particularly in
                    those cases where the armed forces of the other country are not as well oriented
                    or equipped as they might be to meet the threat of subversion from within.</p>
                <p>I believe it is clear from the foregoing that in order to comply with the
                    Honduran request it would be necessary to urge the Pentagon to accord Honduras
                    extremely exceptional treatment all along the line, <pb facs="1349" n="1311"
                        xml:id="pg_1311"/> treatment which would require justification in the
                    strongest terms to the Department of Defense, the <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> and the Congress. I am inclined to believe that such an effort,
                    even if it had a chance of success, would not be warranted, particularly in view
                    of the fact that the threat of aggression against Honduras has been very
                    substantially reduced by the coming into power of an anti-communist regime in
                    Guatemala.</p>
                <p>I can appreciate what I take to be your basic position, namely, that by devoting
                    additional funds to the Honduran program, compared with the vast amounts we are
                    spending on military assistance world-wide, we might come very close to assuring
                    ourselves that subversion, wherever it might appear, in Honduras, would be
                    repressed effectively with armed force. However, our widely spread security
                    commitments throughout the world have necessarily limited the nature and size of
                    the Latin American program. In this connection, for example, the 32 aircraft
                    requested for Honduras would represent almost one quarter of the total number of
                    aircraft being provided to Latin American countries in the entire regional
                    program. Moreover, we are providing no country in the program with as many as 34
                    aircraft. Brazil, for example, is receiving only 30.</p>
                <p>Perhaps we can discuss this and other problems of mutual concern more fully
                    during your visit here later this month.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HHF1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry F. Holland</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
