<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="58" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d58">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">
                            <gloss target="#t_U1">U</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss>
                            files, lot 56 D 551, “Latin America”</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Secretary
                                of State for Inter-American Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HHF1"><hi rend="italic">Holland</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1954-07-20">July 20,
                                    1954</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Work of <gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss> and the Department of
                                Commerce on Investment Opportunities in Latin America</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <item>Participants: Governor <persName corresp="#p_SHE1">Harold E.
                                    Stassen</persName>, Director of Foreign Operations
                                Administration</item>
                            <item>Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HHF1">Henry F.
                                    Holland</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I suggested that the Governor let me summarize my views on his proposal
                            of an extensive program to achieve two ends in Latin America.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Discovery of investment opportunities and securing U.S. investors
                                for them.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Analysis of obstacles to an increased influx of U.S. capital into
                                Latin America.</item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="0265" n="227" xml:id="pg_227"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">The objections I stated were:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>His efforts would be cumulative of programs conducted by the
                                Department of Commerce and the Department of State. <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Commerce has published an excellent work on obstacles to
                                        private investment in Latin America. They should be better
                                        prepared than any other agency to keep that study up to
                                        date.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Commerce has long offered a service of bringing investment
                                        opportunities in Latin America to the attention of the U.S.
                                        public.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The program in many capitals of Latin America would duplicate
                                services available on investment opportunities through well prepared
                                private sources such as investment houses, banks, chambers of
                                commerce, and similar organizations.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The program would be affirmatively prejudicial to our foreign
                                policy in Latin America at this time because: <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Private capital is not entering Latin America today
                                        extensively because prospective investors are not accorded
                                        the protection of contract and property rights, assurances
                                        of sound monetary policies and of opportunities to earn a
                                        reasonable return on their investments which are conditions
                                        precedent to the entry of a reasonable prudent investor. If,
                                        while these conditions prevail, we persuade a large number
                                        of small U.S. investors to go into Latin America we will
                                        create problems that will severely strain our relations.
                                        Latin America today is a place where a well informed
                                        investor who can give adequate attention personally or by a
                                        trusted proxy to his business can make a good profit. On the
                                        other hand, there are a number of areas where the small
                                        investor who relies on absentee management will almost
                                        surely find himself in substantial difficulty.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item> We are trying hard to persuade Latin American Governments
                                        to institute those policies and local conditions that will
                                        cause private capital, particularly their own, to invest
                                        itself in projects that will strengthen their economies.
                                        Generally, in each of the countries there is enough domestic
                                        private capital to meet the development needs of the
                                        countries. Because of lack of the basic assurances required
                                        by private investors, this domestic capital is either sent
                                        out of the country or invested in real estate. If we now
                                        start a program to encourage small U.S. investors to enter
                                        Latin America in large numbers our efforts to solve the
                                        basic problem mentioned above will be largely
                                        nullified.</item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item>In other words, Latin Americans are reluctant to invest
                                        their capital in productive enterprises in their own
                                        countries. They are reluctant to do so because they know
                                        that local conditions are such that their investment might
                                        be lost. Often they are entirely right. We are trying to get
                                        the local governments to see that until they improve local
                                        conditions they cannot expect private investors to risk
                                        their capital. We cannot very well at the same time be
                                        conducting a campaign to persuade numerous small U.S.
                                        investors to enter the same investment markets. </item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>The accusation is made against us in Latin America that
                                        the United States must find homes abroad for large amounts
                                        of capital which cannot be invested here. It is said that
                                        our interest in creating conditions in Latin America
                                        favorable to the investment <pb facs="0266" n="228" xml:id="pg_228"/> of private capital are motivated by
                                        this selfish purpose, and not by any desire to strengthen
                                        their economies. The proposed <gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss> program would lend credibility to this
                                        argument.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>When I concluded the statement outlined above, Governor <persName corresp="#p_SHE1">Stassen</persName> asked me whether I thought the
                            tendency in Latin America was toward or away from private enterprise, I
                            replied that the trend was toward private enterprise. I pointed out the
                            situation in Peru, the growing belief in Brazil that its oil industry
                            will never prosper until private enterprise is admitted; the spectacular
                            results of private enterprise in Venezuela, and the new trend in
                            Mexico.</p>
                        <p>He asked me if I was satisfied with the labor situation in Latin America.
                            I replied that I was not; that I felt that we needed more labor
                            reporting officers in the embassies, men who had the language ability
                            and other capacities necessary for them to exert influence on the local
                            leaders.</p>
                        <p>Governor <persName corresp="#p_SHE1">Stassen</persName> then said that he
                            felt our conference had pointed out fundamental differences of opinion
                            on basic policy concepts which made it easy to understand how we could
                            disagree on the wisdom of a particular program. He went forward to
                            enumerate four basic differences of opinion which he felt existed
                            between us:</p>
                        <p>1. He felt that I was well satisfied with wages and living conditions
                            generally in Latin America whereas he felt that they should be
                            considerably improved.</p>
                        <p>I stated that he must have misunderstood me—that I shared his view that
                            both wages generally and living conditions should be improved throughout
                            Latin America.</p>
                        <p>2. He felt that, contrary to my belief, this was the time to encourage a
                            large number of small investors to go to Latin America. He recognized
                            that a good many of them might “lose their shirts,” but felt that the
                            net result of their entry would be beneficial.</p>
                        <p>I stated that on this point we did disagree.</p>
                        <p>3. He felt that I opposed the establishment of organized labor unions in
                            Latin America, whereas he felt that it would be a good thing.</p>
                        <p>I stated that he must have misunderstood; that it was my personal belief
                            and the policy of the Department that extension of the organized labor
                            movement to Latin America would be beneficial to this country as well as
                            to the Latin American countries.</p>
                        <p>4. He felt that I opposed treatment of economic problems in the
                            hemisphere on a multilateral basis. He said that the policy of the
                            Department of State and of the Treasury was to insist on a modern day
                            colonial approach, under which we insisted that the various Latin
                            American countries deal bilaterally with the United States but without
                            any extensive trade or economic relations among themselves. He drew
                            parallels from English and Spanish history regarding such a policy.</p>
                        <p>I stated that I felt he misunderstood the Department’s policy; that we
                            favored such multilateral relations between the Latin American
                            countries.</p>
                        <pb facs="0267" n="229" xml:id="pg_229"/>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SHE1">Stassen</persName> gave me the impression
                            when I left that he still felt there were basic and fundamental
                            differences of opinion between us. Despite this, the meeting was cordial
                            and I was happy to have the chance to explain our views.<note n="1" xml:id="d58fn1">Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HHF1">Holland</persName> forwarded a copy of this memorandum of
                                conversation to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> under cover of a memorandum dated July 23,
                                1954. In the July 23 memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_HHF1">Holland</persName> requested the Secretary to sign an attached
                                draft letter to Governor <persName corresp="#p_SHE1">Stassen</persName> asking that he continue to hold up the
                                proposed <gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss> program to stimulate
                                U.S. investments in Latin America. (811.05120/7–2354) The Secretary
                                signed the letter on July 28, and it went out on that date.
                                (811.05120/7–2854)</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>