<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Ambassador in Panama ( (Wiley), ), Temporarily in
                    Washington, to the Under Secretary of State ( (Smith))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d619</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">619</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-02-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-02-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recykDuvfC6iFH3Xe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85139643"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Unemployment</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recez5uVgqvmr6Nwm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006268"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Irrigation</term>
                    <term ref="recsTmAcLGbo1pCoe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic stability</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-02-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-02-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="619"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d619">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.19/2–1353</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Ambassador in Panama</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_WJC1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wiley</hi>
                    </persName>), <hi rend="italic">Temporarily in Washington, to the Under
                        Secretary of State</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SWB1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d619fn1">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WJC1"
                            >Wiley</persName> was in the United States from late January until the
                        end of February and returned to Panama on Mar. 4, 1953.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-02-13">February 13,
                            1953</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Panama</hi>
                </p>
                <p>For the United States the importance of the Republic of Panama derives from its
                    unique geographical situation and our special treaty rights having to do with
                    the Panama Canal Zone, which strategically, politically and economically is the
                    most important installation possessed by the United States anywhere. The Canal
                    Zone, a foreign corridor bisecting Panama, a sovereign nation, presents a
                    continuing problem of great delicacy to the United States. The security of the
                    Canal is linked with the stability of the Republic. The daily functioning of the
                    Canal depends to an important extent on friendly collaboration with the
                    Panamanian authorities. It is in the interest of this Government to ensure,
                    insofar as possible, that the Government of Panama at all times be well disposed
                    toward the United States.</p>
                <p>It is most desirable that American policy towards Panama be reviewed from time to
                    time with a view to meeting the exigencies of the moment and the developments of
                    the future. The nature of the relationship between the United States and Panama
                    is such that periodic readjustment will always be necessary by force of
                    circumstance. In recent years such readjustments took place in 1936 and again in
                    1942. Extensive and perhaps excessively generous concessions were made at that
                    time by the United States to Panama. Now a moment of readjustment seems again at
                    hand. The advent of a new administration in Panama has given impetus to a
                    growing and insistent clamor for new concessions, including <hi rend="italic"
                        >inter alia</hi> a higher annuity payment on the part of the United States.
                    President <persName corresp="#p_RCJA1">Remón</persName> and his government,
                    responsive to local pressures, seem to be embarked on an undisguised policy of
                    extracting as much as possible from the United States. Their attitude seems to
                    be that only in a forthright way will anything substantial be obtained from the
                    American Government and that they are in a position to exact demands without
                    concern or <pb facs="1441" n="1403" xml:id="pg_1403"/> preoccupation since
                    Panama, which in international affairs is friendly to the United States, is too
                    valuable to the United States for relations between the two countries to be
                    disturbed by their exigencies.</p>
                <p>The question of yielding periodically to Panamanian demands involves great danger
                    of encroachment upon the treaty rights enjoyed by the United States in the Canal
                    Zone since concessions could, in the course of years, have dangerous cumulative
                    effects. It would seem desirable, in view of the very extensive concessions made
                    to Panama in the past, that the United States avoid at this time a repetition of
                    the procedures followed in 1936 and 1942. If there are any inequities in the
                    Canal Zone to be remedied, measures for their correction should be limited to
                    unilateral administrative action. No “commercial treaty” or other formal
                    engagement should be entered into with the Government of Panama at this time
                    whereby action by the United States would take the form of a binding
                    international engagement.</p>
                <p>But an alternative course must be found, since our relationship with Panama
                    should not be based on a negative attitude alone. It might, therefore, be
                    opportune for the American Government to consider collaboration with the
                    Government of Panama in the economic field. Such a procedure at this time would
                    seem particularly desirable since the economy of Panama has been based almost
                    entirely on the Canal, a static installation which no longer suffices to support
                    the expanding population of the Republic. Economic conditions are illustrated by
                    the fact that there are at present 24 thousand Panamanians unemployed in the
                    terminal cities of Panama and Colón. This unemployment of a quarter of the
                    working population of the two cities is not due to economic depression—it is due
                    quite simply to the fact that the necessary jobs do not exist in the present
                    stage of economic development of the Republic. So neglected and undeveloped are
                    Panama’s own resources that Panama today imports over 60% of its foodstuffs at a
                    cost of about $11,000,000 annually, as compared to a total annual government
                    budget of about $40,000,000. This economic underdevelopment in turn begets and
                    aggravates political instability, which has resulted in Panama’s having had six
                    presidents since 1948. It bears heavily upon the masses in Panama and is
                    dangerously exploitable by leftists, communists and demagogues who find it
                    expedient to ascribe Panama’s many ills to the Canal Zone and United States
                    policies therein. It is, therefore, desirable and timely to do everything
                    possible to establish the economy of the Republic on a viable basis, in order to
                    take the Panamanian mind off the Canal Zone and to contribute constructively to
                    political and social evolution and progress. The logical point of departure for
                    this step lies in the field of agriculture.</p>
                <p>The annual income of the nation could be very substantially increased through an
                    intelligent and serious approach to the reorganization <pb facs="1442" n="1404"
                        xml:id="pg_1404"/> and development of agriculture. The fact that Panama is a
                    dollar country within the American economic orbit would save such an
                    appropriation from being a mere grant. Indeed, it would have in this respect
                    more the character of a domestic operation, since the benefits to the American
                    economy would be immediate and real. Another most important advantage of such a
                    program would be the development for the first time in the history of Panama of
                    a substantial hard core of trained Panamanians which would in time permit a
                    wholesome and much needed reorganization of the public services of the
                    country.</p>
                <p>It is suggested that the Department consider the possibility of seeking
                    appropriations from Congress whereby $5,000,000 a year could be expended in
                    Panama for, say, a period of ten years. The purpose of this grant should be
                    specifically to develop, in the interests of agriculture, access roads,
                    warehousing and market facilities for agricultural produce, agricultural
                    equipment pools, land settlement, irrigation and small industry related to the
                    processing of foodstuffs, as well as intensified technical collaboration.
                    Whatever financial aid may be decided upon should be expended in the Republic
                    for specific purposes under the sole and continuing control of the United
                    States, and such funds as might not be disbursed would revert to the Treasury of
                    the United States. The program should be entirely unilateral and without
                    negotiated commitment on the part of the United States.</p>
                <p>In furtherance of this program, an expression of the strategic interest of this
                    nation in the development of political and economic stability in Panama might be
                    sought from the Joint Chiefs of Staff. The development of agriculture in Panama
                    would provide a local source of food supply for the garrisons and population of
                    the Canal Zone, thus eliminating the present necessity in time of emergency of
                    diverting sufficient foodstuffs from the United States to feed the populations
                    of both Panama and the Canal Zone as well as to supply the necessary shipping
                    for the purpose. Recognition of this Government’s special interest in Panama
                    would provide ample justification for special programs in Panama without
                    creating a basis for claims by other Latin American Governments for similar
                    treatment.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
