<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-11-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="659" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d659">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.19/11–1754</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Ambassador in Panama</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CS1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Chapin</hi></persName>), <hi rend="italic">Temporarily in
                                Washington, to the Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American
                                Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HHF1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Holland</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-11-17">November 17, 1954</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>In the event of a breakdown in the treaty talks with Panama, should
                                <persName corresp="#p_RCJA1">Remon</persName> decline to accept our
                            global offer, it is possible that Panama may attempt some maneuver to
                            galvanize Latin American opinion against the U.S. This might take the
                            form of some appeal to the Organization of American States, to the
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, or World Court or a press
                            campaign with or without organized mass demonstrations.</p>
                        <p>It is my understanding that we would counter any such propaganda attack
                            with one of our own setting forth clearly and in detail the generous and
                            understanding nature of our offers to Panama. I believe that even the
                            most biased Latin American critic could find little fault with most of
                            our concessions, but am somewhat concerned as to how much headway the
                            Panamanians might make over old Article XII<note n="1" xml:id="d659fn1">Article XIII in the revised draft concerned the reopening of
                                treaties, etc.</note> or the revised alternates thereto given to Dr.
                                <persName>Arias</persName>. I do not suggest that we should in fact
                            depart from our position which is well grounded. Rather do I feel that
                            irrespective of the rights and wrongs of this position, we should
                            explore what effect a strong Panamanian protest, which might enlist
                            Latin American public opinion and which would undoubtedly be exploited
                            by Communist and other unfriendly elements, might have on our general
                            Latin American relations. Undoubtedly the effort would be made to have
                            us appear as the brutal domineering colossus attempting to cower a
                            small, peace-loving and deserving nation with all the lies and
                            exaggerations of which such a campaign is capable and with which
                            unfortunately we have been so familiar in the past.</p>
                        <p>Undoubtedly you have taken into consideration the above possibility which
                            could result in a setback to our whole Latin American policy. However,
                            it occurs to me that should <persName corresp="#p_RCJA1">Remon</persName> refuse the treaty on the grounds of Article XII or
                            its alternatives, we might, rather than risk the showdown, proceed with
                            the other alternative—namely that of striking such language and that
                            providing for an increase in the annuity and of offering direct economic
                            aid. In your conversation with <persName>Arias</persName> no mention was
                            made of the amount of such aid and the only figure, so far as I know,
                            given to the Panamanians was ten million over ten years. If, as I
                            understand from another Departmental memo, we are in fact prepared to
                            raise this to twenty million over ten years, it might be useful if I
                            were authorized to come forth with such a figure should the necessity
                            arise. I should be grateful for your views.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>