<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs ( (Miller) ) to
                    the Ambassador in Peru ( (Tittmann))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d674</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">674</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-03-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-03-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="collective-security" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="collective-security" subject="collective-security" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119471" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Collective defense</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-assistance-and-sales" lcsh-match="no_match">Mutual Defense Assistance Act of</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-03-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-03-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="674"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d674">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_MEG1">Miller</persName> files, lot 53 D 26, “Peru”</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MEG1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Miller</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Ambassador in Peru</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_THH2" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Tittmann</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d674fn1">Drafted by <persName>Duncan A. D.
                            Mackay</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_JEA1">Edward A.
                            Jamison</persName> of the Office of Regional American Affairs.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">official–informal</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-03-05">March 5,
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear <persName corresp="#p_THH2">Harold</persName>
                    </hi>: Thank you for your detailed letter of February 25<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d674fn2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> reporting on and analysing the attitude
                    of Peruvian officials, and especially President <persName>Odria</persName>,
                    toward the military grant-aid program and the other assistance Peru has received
                    or would like to receive from the United States in the military field. Before
                    discussing the points raised, however, I should like to express the appreciation
                    of those of us here particularly concerned with the grant-aid negotiations for
                    the excellent and effective manner in which you and others similarly involved in
                    Lima carried the negotiations with Peru to an expeditious and successful
                    conclusion. It was a job very well done.</p>
                <p>With reference to your impression that Peru is not enthusiastic about the
                    grant-aid program because of its preoccupation with internal security, it is
                    perhaps understandable that the transition from concepts of nationalistic
                    self-interest to genuine adherence to the practice as well as the principle of
                    collective defense will call for difficult adjustments both practical and
                    psychological, and, in some cases, such as Mexico and Argentina, will not happen
                    quickly. We can only hope to make some headway with the encouragement provided
                    in the present program, and Peru’s participation is all to the good.</p>
                <p>Insofar as Peruvian concern is related to the size of the program for that
                    country, while I do not know all of the factors and considerations which led the
                    Department of Defense to take up with Peru the particular tasks and units
                    specified in the Military Plan, it seems to me that, as one of a relatively
                    small number of countries approached with an offer of assistance to all three
                    armed services, Peru has come out rather well. After all, the total program is
                    not very large. Furthermore, there seems to be a slight inconsistency between
                    preoccupation with internal defense and concern at not being cut in for more in
                    the grant-aid program, which is so clearly directed at external military
                    effort.</p>
                <p>It is reassuring, however, that the President does not seem to consider that
                    Peru’s needs for her immediate security should be on a grant basis. One of the
                    most frequent adverse criticisms of our program has been the charge that,
                    however closely its purposes and objectives may be tied to strengthening the
                    hemisphere against the threat of Soviet imperialism, the assistance will
                    actually be used for other purposes.</p>
                <pb facs="1534" n="1496" xml:id="pg_1496"/>
                <p>With regard to President <persName>Odria</persName>’s concern lest the grant-aid
                    program will prejudice acquisition of military assistance on a reimbursable
                    basis, there are several points to be considered. In the first place, it is
                    entirely correct that participation in the grant-aid program will not prejudice
                    acquisition on a reimbursable basis of equipment, etc., which is available and
                    which is clearly needed by Peru to maintain her own defense. This does not mean,
                    of course, that we can escape the fact that the capacity of this country to meet
                    military requirements throughout the world limits availability, nor does it mean
                    that we shall approve without question any request that Peru may wish to make.
                    There are necessary limitations which must continue to be imposed.</p>
                <p>One of the basic assumptions of the Peruvian position as reported in your letter
                    appears to be that they have not been receiving fair or equitable treatment in
                    the acquisition of military assistance on a reimbursable basis. When one
                    compares what Peru has actually received with what Latin American countries of
                    Peru’s size, or even larger, have received under the Mutual Defense Assistance
                    Act of 1949, one is struck with the fact that Peru has not fared badly. In this
                    connection, I have enclosed for the Embassy’s own information the latest
                    cumulative figures of the transactions which have taken place under the <gloss
                        target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> with this area since October 1949, as of
                    January 31, 1952.<note n="3" xml:id="d674fn3">The enclosure attached to the
                        source text shows that Peru received reimbursable military assistance valued
                        at $1,343,236, an amount more than that received by any other Latin American
                        country, except Argentina, Brazil, and Chile. A footnote to the figure for
                        Peru, however, reads as follows: “This figure does not include the three
                        D–E’s which have now been delivered to Peru. Their cost plus rehabilitation
                        amounted to $4,425,000. With their delivery, Peru now probably leads all
                        countries in value of items actually received.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>With respect to the pending request for a cruiser for Peru, this question is, I
                    understand, far from being decided in Defense. No reply has as yet been received
                    to the Department’s letter to Defense of January 5, 1952,<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d674fn4">Not printed (723.5 MSP/1–552). The Department of Defense
                        reply is printed on <ref target="#pg_1499">p. 1499</ref>.</note> requesting
                    to be advised as to the military requirement of Peru for a heavy cruiser in
                    relation to any mission she would be likely to perform in hemisphere defense. I
                    believe a copy of this letter was sent to Lima informally. I shall see that you
                    are kept currently advised on developments in regard to this request and
                    appreciate receiving your views on it.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MEG1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward G. Miller, Jr.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
