<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-10-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="692" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d692">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">823.2542/10–2554</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for
                                Inter-American Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HHF1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Holland</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">and the Assistant Secretary of State for Economic Affairs</hi>
                                (<persName corresp="#p_WSC1"><hi rend="italic">Waugh</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Under Secretary of
                                State</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HH1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Hoover</hi></persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d692fn1">Drafted by
                                Director of the Office of Financial and Development Policy <persName corresp="#p_CJC1">Corbett</persName>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-10-25">October 25, 1954</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Toquepala Project.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Problem:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Views to be expressed by the Department in the discussion of the
                            Toquepala copper project in the <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>
                            meeting of October 26.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Department has continued to press for a favorable decision on the
                            financing of the Toquepala project in Peru. It has stated that it would
                            be very salutary if a large private investment offering substantial
                            benefits to Peru could be begun. Peru, at a time when nationalistic
                            feeling is rising in Latin America, has been outstanding in its
                            treatment of foreign private investment and, in particular, has adopted
                            a mining code unusually favorable to investments of that nature (Tab
                                A<note n="2" xml:id="d692fn2">Tabs A–F attached to the source text
                                are not printed.</note>). It is <pb facs="1569" n="1531" xml:id="pg_1531"/> believed that the institution of such a
                            development as Toquepala would create a favorable impression at the Rio
                            Economic Conference.</p>
                        <p>At the time this project was considered by the Defense Mobilization
                            Board, experts in that Agency reached a conclusion that the long-run
                            benefits of a new source of supply of copper in this hemisphere would be
                            of importance to the U.S. It would further diversify our sources of
                            supply in this hemisphere and it would improve our bargaining position
                            vis-à-vis Chile (Tab B).</p>
                        <p>The only real “limitation” upon the authority of the Bank to finance this
                            project is that of avoiding competition with private capital. A
                            corollary of this “limitation” is that the Bank should in its loans
                            supplement and encourage private capital (Tab C). The present proposal
                            of <gloss target="#t_ASR1">A.S.&amp;R.</gloss> contemplates the
                            participation by other partners of $46 million, slightly less than the
                            $50 million of equity capital being supplied by <gloss target="#t_ASR1">A.S.&amp;R.</gloss> (Tab D) An increase in the amount of equity
                            capital to be supplied by other partners would place <gloss target="#t_ASR1">A.S.&amp;R.</gloss> in a minority position, which
                            it wishes to avoid. The inclusion of Kennecott and Anaconda raises two
                            additional problems for <gloss target="#t_ASR1">A.S.&amp;R.</gloss>: (1)
                            both have interests in Chile which might make their participation
                            unacceptable to the Peruvian Government and (2) a combination of such
                            companies in this project may have anti-trust implications.</p>
                        <p>The Export-Import Bank is prepared to recommend a $90 million loan at 6%
                            for this project. <gloss target="#t_ASR1">A.S.&amp;R.</gloss> has stated
                            to both the Bank and Treasury that it would not wish to proceed with
                            this project with less than $90 million of financial assistance from the
                            Government. There are attached the most recent formal credit
                            applications to the Bank by <gloss target="#t_ASR1">A.S.&amp;R.</gloss>
                            and the minutes of the last <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> meeting
                            on Toquepala attended by yourself, General <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName> and others (Tabs E and F).</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Recommendation:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>That the Department support for reasons of foreign policy and long-run
                            need for copper the proposed extension of $90 million of credit
                            assistance to the Toquepala project by the Export-Import Bank.<note n="3" xml:id="d692fn3">This memorandum was initialed by Under
                                Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HH1">Hoover</persName>.</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>