<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Uruguay ( (Roddan) ) to the Assistant Secretary of State
                    for Inter-American Affairs ( (Cabot))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d706</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">706</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-05-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-05-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-05-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-05-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="706"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d706">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> files, lot 56 D 13,
                    “Uruguay”</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Uruguay</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_REL1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Roddan</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Inter-American Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CJM1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cabot</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">[Extract]</note>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Montevideo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-05-13">May 13,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName>
                    </hi>: This is a belated note of greeting and good wishes. Now that <persName
                        corresp="#p_MTC1">Tom Mann</persName> is leaving for the field, and in view
                    of the approaching visit of Dr. <persName>Eisenhower</persName>,<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d706fn1">Reference is to the factfinding mission to the countries of
                        South America undertaken by Dr. <persName>Milton Eisenhower</persName>
                        between June 23 and July 29, 1953, at the request of President
                            <persName>Eisenhower</persName>. Regarding Dr.
                            <persName>Eisenhower</persName>’s trip, see the editorial note, <ref
                            target="#pg_196">p. 196</ref>.</note> I believe this may be an opportune
                    time to give you a brief résumé of the Uruguayan situation.</p>
                <pb facs="1601" n="1563" xml:id="pg_1563"/>
                <p>The wool tops controversy is still smouldering although with diminishing heat.
                    The <persName>Batlle-Berres</persName> faction is really bitter because it has
                    long had political, and perhaps economic, ties to the tops industry. The
                    Herreristas keep up the clamor for reasons of political expediency. Their
                    interests are allied with the greasy wool producers and they never did like the
                    tops industry. There is a measure of public resentment, without a real
                    understanding of the issue, because many people believe the United States took
                    an unfriendly action towards Uruguay. However, underneath there is a realization
                    by moderates that the United States had justification for its action and hence
                    the resentment will probably die away. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MJA1"
                        >Mora</persName> now plans to leave for Washington this week-end and he
                    should be able to give you a worthwhile view of the situation. He was very
                    helpful here because of his restraining influence.</p>
                <p>There is one adverse consequence of the wool tops ban which will linger on—that
                    is, a worsening of the Uruguayan dollar position which is already bad. Exports
                    to the United States constitute the principal source of dollars, amounting last
                    year to $50,000,000 including $15,000,000 from tops, but this sum was more than
                    offset by the dollar value of imports from there. In addition, Uruguay carries
                    on trade in dollars with other countries at a net loss. Provisional estimates of
                    trade with the United States for the first quarter of 1953 show an improvement
                    of the Uruguayan position but at the expense of diminished imports from the
                    United States. While the subject is too involved for treatment in a letter, it
                    is certain that the loss of tops dollars will be fairly serious.</p>
                <p>Overshadowing the economic factors, there is always the sensitive question of
                    Uruguayan relations with Argentina. The Department was undoubtedly right in
                    failing to mention Argentina in connection with tops in view of the explosive
                    situation across the river, but this failure caused uneasiness here. The
                    Peronista pressure against Uruguay continues, and it will probably continue even
                    if the gentleman carries out his agreement to send an Ambassador here. Our
                    Embassy is convinced that <persName corresp="#p_PJD1">Perón</persName> did what
                    he could to undermine this government during the general strike last September
                    and the Uruguayan government is always apprehensive that he may try it
                    again.</p>
                <p>The Uruguayans, as we advised the Department, dislike the idea of Dr.
                        <persName>Eisenhower</persName> coming here on a week-end and they will
                    probably grumble again when they learn that he is visiting Argentina first. I
                    think we can work out an acceptable schedule of dates without complicating the
                    schedule too much and the business of visiting Argentina first should not be too
                    important.</p>
                <p>It is highly probable that on his visit here, the Uruguayans will seek some
                    assurances from Dr. <persName>Eisenhower</persName> vis-à-vis Argentina and it
                    may be well to begin thinking about it now. I appreciate that on a good will <pb
                        facs="1602" n="1564" xml:id="pg_1564"/> visit to eleven Latin American
                    countries, Dr. <persName>Eisenhower</persName> can hardly single out Uruguay for
                    preferential treatment. Yet, Uruguay has been constant in its friendship to the
                    United States and steadfast in its devotion to democratic principles and I think
                    it deserves a degree of consideration a little above the ordinary. (Perhaps each
                    Ambassador thinks the same about his post.) Quite frankly, just what we can do
                    to reassure Uruguay or possibly to help overcome its economic difficulties, I
                    haven’t been able to figure out.</p>
                <p>The press has reported that you may come along with Dr.
                        <persName>Eisenhower</persName> and if so we shall be happy to do what we
                    can to make your visit pleasant and profitable.</p>
                <p>With best wishes.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_REL1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward L. Roddan</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
