<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Anderson to Mr.
                                Blaine.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1889</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d115</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">115</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1889-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1889-07-01T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1889-07-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1889-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="115" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d115">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Anderson</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Copenhagen</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1889-07-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 1, 1889</date>.
                            (Received July 13.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 311.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to your dispatches Nos. 130 and 131,
                        dated June 6 and 7, I have the honor to report as follows:</p>
                <p>Both the above dispatches were received on June 26, and the same day I had an
                        interview with the director-general of the Royal Danish ministry for foreign
                        affairs. I suggested to him that my Government <pb facs="0273" n="155" xml:id="pg_155"/> preferred that I should sign a joint note. In reply
                        the director-general urged that it was a delicate point in diplomacy as to
                        who should sign first, and to avoid the raising of this and possibly other
                        questions his Government preferred that we should send separate identical
                        notes simultaneously, the Danish note to be written in the French language.
                        In accordance with your instructions I agreed to his proposition, and on the
                        next day (June 27) I sent a note to the Royal Danish minister for foreign
                        affairs, inclosing copies of the two drafts of a note suggested by you, but
                        still urging, as you will see by the copy thereof inclosed, the adoption of
                        the joint note in preference to separate identical notes. On the 29th I
                        received a reply from the Royal Danish minister for foreign affairs, in
                        which he repeats the preference of his Government for two identical notes,
                        and incloses a copy of the one in French, which he proposes to send to Sir
                        Edmund Monson to-day. I have carefully compared it with the separate note
                        transmitted by you to me, and find the two identical in all important
                        respects. I have this day mailed a note to Sir Edmund Monson in behalf of
                        the Government of the United States, inviting him to accept the task of
                        arbitrator in accordance with the treaty of December 6, 1888. I have made
                        such alterations in the draft you sent me as the case required, but none of
                        the changes are essential. I inclose herewith copies of my note to the Royal
                        Danish minister for foreign affairs, dated June 27, of my note to Sir Edmund
                        Monson, and, finally, of a note sent by me this day to the Royal Danish
                        minister for foreign affairs.</p>
                <p>I shall look for an answer from Sir Edmund Monson in about two weeks.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">R. B. Anderson.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 311.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Anderson</persName> to
                                    <persName type="to">Baron O. D.
                            Rosenörn-Lehn</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Copenhagen</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1889-06-27">
                                <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 27,
                                1889</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: The honorable the Secretary of
                            State at Washington informs me in a dispatch dated June 6 that the
                            ratifications of the treaty for the settlement of the claim of Carlos
                            Butterfield were exchanged at Washington on the 23d ultimo; and that it
                            was duly proclaimed by the President of the United States on the
                            following day.</p>
                    <p>The next step to be taken is the extension to Sir Edmund Monson, the
                            arbitrator named in the treaty, of a formal invitation to accept the
                            power therein conferred upon him.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to inclose herewith two drafts, one of a joint and the
                            other of an identic note to be written to Sir Edmund Monson, and also a
                            printed copy of the treaty in question.</p>
                    <p>The joint note secures absolute uniformity of language in the invitation,
                            and avoids the raising of any question at to the effect or intention of
                            variant phraseologies; but in a conversation which I had with the
                            director-general of the Royal Danish ministry of foreign affairs
                            yesterday I was led to believe that your excellency prefers that we
                            should send identic notes separately, and I am authorized by my
                            Government to sign either a joint or an identic note.</p>
                    <p>Hoping the inclosed documents may be found satisfactory, and adding that
                            I am ready to sign and transmit either one of the notes mentioned at any
                            time that may suit your excellency’s convenience, I seize, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">R. B. Anderson.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0274" n="156" xml:id="pg_156"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 311.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Anderson</persName> to Sir
                                    <persName type="to">Edmund Monson</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Copenhagen, Denmark</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1889-07-01">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 1, 1889</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: The Government of the United States
                            of America and the Government of His Majesty the King of Denmark have,
                            by a treaty concluded on the 6th day of December, 1888, of which the
                            ratifications have been duly exchanged, agreed to submit to the decision
                            of an arbitrator the claim of Carlos Butterfield and Company of which
                            Carlos Butterfield, now deceased, was the surviving partner, presented
                            by the Government of the United States against the Government of Denmark
                            for an indemnity for the seizure and detention of the two vessels, the
                            steamer <hi rend="italic">Ben Franklin</hi> and the bark <hi rend="italic">Catherine Augusta</hi>, by the authorities of the
                            Island of St. Thomas, of the Danish West India Islands, in the years
                            1854 and 1855, for the refusal of the ordinary right to land cargo for
                            the purpose of making repairs; for the injuries resulting from a shot
                            fired into one of the vessels, and for other wrongs. A copy of the
                            treaty is hereto annexed.</p>
                    <p>Both Governments having, as stated in the treaty, entire confidence in
                            the learning, ability, and impartiality of your excellency, I have been
                            instructed by the honorable the Secretary of State to express the great
                            satisfaction of my Government in agreeing upon you as the proper person
                            to whom to submit for decision the questions involved in the claim
                            referred to.</p>
                    <p>In performing the grateful duty of inviting your excellency in behalf of
                            my Government to accept the power conferred upon you by the treaty, I
                            have the honor to express the hope that I may have the pleasure, as soon
                            as it may suit your convenience to communicate your wishes to me, of
                            sending a notice to my Government that you have accepted the task now
                            tendered by me in its behalf.</p>
                    <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">R. B. Anderson.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 311.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Anderson</persName> to
                                    <persName type="to">Baron O. D.
                            Rosenörn-Lehn</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Copenhagen</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1889-07-01">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 1,
                                1889</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your esteemed note of June 29, informing me that you propose
                            to send the note of which you had the goodness to inclose a copy to Sir
                            Edmund Monson to-day. This note being identical with the one proposed by
                            my Government, I have the honor to inform your excellency that I have
                            this day mailed to Sir Edmund Monson at Athens, in behalf of my
                            Government, a note, of which I transmit inclosed a copy,</p>
                    <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">R. B. Anderson.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
