<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Lincoln to Mr.
                                Blaine.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1889</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d161</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">161</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1889-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1889-07-31T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650" lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1889-07-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1889-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="161" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d161">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Lincoln</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1889-07-31">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 31, 1889</date>.
                            (Received August 10.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 51.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit to you a copy of
                        a note from Sir James Fergusson (on behalf of Lord Salisbury) and of an
                        accompanying memorandum of the Government of Canada, which I have received
                        in reply to Mr. White’s note of February 20, 1889, in reference to the
                        American ship <hi rend="italic">Bridgewater</hi>, a copy of which was sent
                        to the Department of State by Mr. White in his No. 928 of the 23d of
                        February last. It will be observed that the statement of the claimant, Mr.
                        Allen, that he, on May 26, 1888, abandoned the suit begun by him in the
                        supreme court of Nova Scotia against the officer who seized and detained the
                            <hi rend="italic">Bridgewater</hi> is expressly contradicted by the
                        Canadian Government; it being stated that the action is still pending,
                        although subject to be dismissed for want of prosecution and for failure to
                        give the security for costs required of non-residents, but that the agent of
                        the Department of Justice in Nova Scotia has been instructed not to ask for
                        such dismissal until a reasonable time has elapsed after the transmission of
                        the memorandum of the Canadian Government for security to be given and for
                        the case to be proceeded with.</p>
                <p>It will also be observed that the Canadian Government asserts that
                        immediately upon the issuance of the adverse opinion of the minister of
                        justice Mr. Allen was informed that the opinion was withdrawn as having been
                        based solely on an erroneous statement of the date of beginning his suit and
                        not upon the merits of the case.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert T. Lincoln.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0576" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 51.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Sir. <persName type="from">James
                                    Fergusson</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Lincoln</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign
                                        Office</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1889-07-26">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 26,
                                1889</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my note to Mr. White of
                            the 27th of February last I have now the honor to transmit a memorandum
                            giving the reply of the Government of Canada to his note of the 20th of
                            that month respecting the case of the United States vessel <hi rend="italic">Bridgewater.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>I have the honor to request that you will communicate this memorandum to
                            the United States Government and point out to them that, as it is still
                            open to Mr. Allen to take his legal remedy by proceeding in the suit
                            already commenced and not discontinued in the supreme court of Nova
                            Scotia, the case is not one for diplomatic treatment.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>(For the Marquis of Salisbury),<lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">James Fergusson.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 51.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The Government of the Dominion have had under consideration the note
                            received through the foreign office from the United States chargé
                            d’affaires stating that the law courts of the Dominion of Canada could
                            afford no redress to the owner of the United States ship <hi rend="italic">Bridgewater</hi>, and inclosing papers laid before the
                            United States Congress relating to the case of this vessel.</p>
                    <p>The facts upon which the claim in relation to the ship <hi rend="italic">Bridgewater</hi> is based appear to be as follows:</p>
                    <p>The ship put into Shelburne, Nova Scotia, in a damaged condition about
                            the 5th April, 1887. An examination was made of the injuries which she
                            had sustained with the result that the captain was advised to discharge
                            his cargo and transfer it to another ship. The cargo was accordingly
                            unloaded and transferred to another vessel, and went to its destination.
                            The managing owner, John H. Aller, who has been active in promoting the
                            present claim against the Dominion Government, arrived at Shelburne soon
                            after the vessel put in there, and the decision seems to have been
                            formed about that time to treat the vessel as a constructive total loss
                            in consequence of the probable expense of repairing her, and to sell her
                            as a wreck not worth repairing in order to bind the underwriters to pay
                            for a total loss. In pursuance of this purpose the vessel was offered
                            for sale, and was bought in by Mr. Allen on the 8th June, 1887. This
                            attempted sale was abandoned at about the same time when the collector
                            of customs made it a reason for exacting customs duty, and Mr. Allen
                            proceeded to make the repairs which were required to put the ship in a
                            seaworthy condition.</p>
                    <p>The collector of customs at Shelburne, assuming that the sale had been a
                                <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> one, claimed that a duty of 25 per
                            cent, should be paid on the proceeds of the sale in pursuance of the act
                            relating to duties of customs.</p>
                    <p>The collector does not seem to have relinquished, entirely, his control
                            of the vessel until the 14th October, 1887. The owner claims damages
                            from the Canadian Government and its officers by reason of his ship
                            being delayed. The delay is claimed to have been from the date of the
                            seizure, about July 27, until the date of the ship’s release, and is
                            based on the vessel’s demurrage and loss of possible profits, together
                            with delays and difficulties in making her voyages after the release.
                            There is also a claim for injury and deterioration.</p>
                    <p>The Government of Canada do not deem it necessary at present to discuss
                            the merits, or want of merits, of the various portions of this claim,
                            but they desire to say generally with regard to it that the delay of the
                            vessel was not caused by the seizure.</p>
                    <p>The repairs had been begun before the seizure took place. What the
                            collector did was simply to place a watchman over the vessel to see that
                            she was not removed without his knowledge. This watchman had distinct
                            orders not to interfere in the slightest degree with the workmen who
                            were carrying on the repairs. So that there might be no misunderstanding
                            on that point, the collector informed the foreman of the workmen that
                            there would not be the slightest interference with his work or that of
                            his subordinates, and Mr. Allen, the managing owner, was also informed
                            of the same fact by the collector.</p>
                    <p>Notwithstanding this Mr. Allen availed himself of the watchman’s having
                            been employed by the collector to withdraw his workmen, cease all
                            repairs, and commence the present claim for damages. Notwithstanding
                            that the intimations that there would <pb facs="0577" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/> be no interference with the work of repairing the
                            vessel were repeated to him, Mr. Allen, and the United States consular
                            agent at Shelburne, both verbally and in writing, declared that the
                            owner would not go on with the repairs and Mr. Allen used the expression
                            that he would “throw her upon the customs.” His refusal continued until
                            the final relinquishment of all control by the collector. After that the
                            repairs had to be done at a most unfavorable season for them and for
                            continuing the navigation of the ship.</p>
                    <p>Some injury is alleged to have been done to the outfit or apparel of the
                            vessel, but as to this it seems at present that the customs officer is
                            able to show that no injury whatever was done to the property belonging
                            to the vessel or the vessel itself while she was under the care of the
                            watchman. These matters, however, are rather for the authority or
                            tribunal which may have to decide on the amount of compensation to be
                            awarded if the principle be established that the owner of the vessel is
                            entitled to compensation.</p>
                    <p>It is a preliminary point of some importance that neither Mr. Allen nor
                            any other person connected with the vessel has made any application by
                            petition of right to the Dominion Government, notwithstanding his
                            assertions and those of the honorable Mr. Bayard to the contrary. If
                            such a petition were presented it is not probable that a fiat would be
                            refused. At the same time it must be stated that the Canadian law upon
                            this subject is the same as that of England, and that it is not probable
                            that a petition of right would be an available remedy for a tort such as
                            the owner of the <hi rend="italic">Bridgewater</hi> claims was committed
                            with regard to that vessel. It by no means follows, however, from that
                            circumstance that the owner is without redress in the courts of Canada.
                            On the contrary, while the Crown (in right of Canada) is not liable for
                            a wrong any more than the Crown is liable in the courts of Great
                            Britain, any officer who commits a wrong against one of his fellow
                            subjects, or against a foreigner, is liable to answer for that wrong in
                            the courts of justice in the ordinary way.</p>
                    <p>If the <hi rend="italic">Bridgewater</hi> was properly liable to customs
                            duty and properly seized, there can be no claim against the Dominion
                            Government or against its officers. If she was improperly seized or
                            improperly detained, the officer who seized and detained her is liable
                            to compensate those whom he has injured by such illegal proceeding. On
                            these points Mr. Allen has no doubt been well advised.</p>
                    <p>The United States consular agent at Shelburne, who is likewise understood
                            to be his solicitor, is a member of the bar, thoroughly practiced in the
                            law, and of the highest character and attainments. It appears from the
                            documents which have been before the government that Mr. Allen was early
                            advised that a petition of right would not be an available remedy and he
                            therefore commenced an action for damages in the supreme court of Nova
                            Scotia, against the collector of customs, for all the injuries caused by
                            and resulting from the seizure.</p>
                    <p>The late Secretary of State of the United States has been incorrectly
                            informed as to what has taken place with regard to this suit for
                            damages. Being, of course, familiar with the rule, which has been
                            invariably followed in his own Department, as appears by the diplomatic
                            intercourse of that Department with other countries, that a claim can
                            not be entertained as a matter of diplomatic negotiation if it may be
                            the subject of redress in the courts of justice, he intimates “no
                            recovery can be had in any court against any officer of the Crown,” and
                            that “it was finally ascertained that redress through the Canadian law
                            courts or from the Canadian Government was not to be had.”</p>
                    <p>He professes to base these statements on the official opinion of the
                            minister of justice of Canada, conveyed, it is said, by the minister of
                            customs, on the 24th of May, 1888.</p>
                    <p>There can be doubt that the honorable Mr. Bayard was informed by Mr. J.
                            H. Allen to that effect. It appears by Mr. Allen’s letter to Mr. Bayard,
                            dated 19th January, 1889, that Mr. Allen made the statement that when
                            the owner was in Ottawa he “made an application to the minister of
                            customs for his permission to take the necessary steps (without which,
                            so he was advised, no progress could be made), to the end that the cause
                            could be tried in the Exchequer court, in which event the Government
                            itself would be the actual defendant; but the application met with
                            prompt and unequivocal refusal.”</p>
                    <p>The minister of customs has nothing to do with any such proceeding, and
                            in this case his permission was not asked, nor was any refusal given by
                            any person. Mr. Allen further states in that letter to Mr. Bayard that
                            an action was commenced in Nova Scotia against the seizing officer, but
                            that it was abandoned, as the Canadian authorities are well aware, on
                            May 26, 1888, on receipt of the official letter of that date, stating
                            that the claimant could not recover, etc.</p>
                    <p>The value of these statements will be presently seen, but it can not be
                            regarded as otherwise than remarkable that Mr. Allen, regardless of the
                            advice of his own counsel, should have abandoned his suit against the
                            seizing officer on the mere opinion alleged to have been given by the
                            minister of justice that he could not succeed.</p>
                    <p>Such a proceeding would have been remarkable if it had occurred, but the
                            statement <pb facs="0578" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/> that it did occur
                            and that the Canadian authorities are aware of it, is untrue. The
                            minister of customs on the 24th of May, 1888, wrote a letter to Mr.
                            Allen stating that he was in receipt, that day, of the opinion of the
                            minister of justice as to the claim for damages, and that the minister
                            of justice was of opinion that the claimant could not “recover against
                            any officer of the Crown for damages sustained in consequence of the
                            seizure.” The opinion of the minister of justice, referred to in this
                            connection, was conveyed in a letter, dated 22d May, 1888, from the
                            deputy minister of justice, in which, irrespective altogether of the
                            merits of the seizure, it was stated, according to the information then
                            in the possession of the Department of Justice, that the action against
                            the seizing officer had not been brought within three months of the time
                            when the action had accrued, as required by section 47 of the customs
                            act, and in which was stated the opinion that the claimant could not
                            recover; that opinion being based solely on the information then in the
                            possession of the Department. It was also stated in the letter of the
                            deputy minister of justice that the propriety of insisting on this
                            limitation was a question of policy to be decided by the minister of
                            customs.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Allen being then in Ottawa, was informed by the deputy minister of
                            justice of the reason on which the opinion was based, and he in reply
                            informed the deputy of the minister of justice that the action against
                            Collector Attwood had been commenced within the time limited by law, and
                            on the 25th of May, 1888, the deputy minister of justice informed the
                            minister of customs by letter that Mr. Allen had corrected the statement
                            on which the opinion of the 23d May had been formed. Mr. Allen had then
                            received and had shown to the deputy minister of justice a telegram from
                            his own solicitor stating that the date on which the action had been
                            brought was within the requirements of the law, and assuring him that
                            the case could be tried in September, 1888. This was at the time when
                            Mr. Allen asserts that the suit was discontinued and that the Canadian
                            Government well knew of its discontinuance.</p>
                    <p>So far from it being true, therefore, that Mr. Allen was in any way
                            induced by the answer of the minister of customs to discontinue his
                            suit, be understood before leaving Ottawa that the opinion communicated
                            to him had been formulated on an erroneous statement of dates and had
                            therefore been withdrawn, and he had been advised by his own solicitor
                            that the action was entered in due time and that it could be tried if he
                            pleased in September of that year.</p>
                    <p>It is untrue that he discontinued the suit against the collector or that
                            any intimation that he had done so or intended to do so was made to the
                            Canadian Government.</p>
                    <p>It is also a misrepresentation, to state that he finally ascertained that
                            redress through the Canadian law courts was not to be had. The suit has
                            never been discontinued. It is still pending in the supreme court of
                            Nova Scotia, and can be tried whenever the plaintiff cares to carry it
                            on to trial.</p>
                    <p>At present the proceedings have been stayed until security for costs
                            shall be given according to the law of the province in regard to suits
                            by persons living out of the jurisdiction.</p>
                    <p>The Canadian Government therefore are of opinion that the owner of the
                                <hi rend="italic">Bridgewater</hi> is not now in a position to
                            assert any claim against the Government of Canada, but must proceed with
                            the suit for redress which has been begun against the seizing officer
                            and which is still pending, notwithstanding the statements to the
                            contrary contained in the letter of Mr. Allen to Mr. Bayard, and in the
                            letter of Mr. Bayard to Mr. Phelps, which have been previously referred
                            to. It has been already stated that in such an action the legality of
                            the seizure could be tested and damages awarded in full compensation for
                            any illegal act which the officer may have committed. For reasons which
                            it is not now necessary to enter upon, any judgment which would be
                            finally recovered against the seizing officer would be sure of being
                            responded to, and it is by no means certain, even if the statutory
                            limitation were to apply as to the date when the action was brought, or
                            if it should stand as a bar to the recovery by the plaintiff on the
                            merits of the case, that such an objection would be insisted on. It
                            probably would not be insisted on, although there is probably no
                            sufficient reason why such a statute should not be made available, and
                            the rule has always prevailed in the United States, even in cases in
                            which the Government of that country was immediately concerned, to
                            insist on a statutory limitation even against foreign claimants as a
                            complete bar to redress.</p>
                    <p>It will be time enough, however, to consider the question as to
                            insistence on the limitation when it appears that that limitation is a
                            bar to the decision of the claim of the owner of the <hi rend="italic">Bridgewater</hi> on its merits. At the present moment that does not
                            appear to be the case, and the documents made public show that Mr. Allen
                            was not so advised. The suit pending in the supreme court of Nova Scotia
                            having been some time ago stayed until security for costs should be
                            given, according to the practice of the court, it is now in a position
                            to be dismissed for want of prosecution, but the agent of the department
                            of justice in Nova Scotia has been instructed not to ask for such
                            dismissal until a reasonable time has elapsed after the transmission of
                            this report for security to be given and for the case to be proceeded
                            with.</p>
                    <pb facs="0579" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/>
                    <p>The Government of Canada are further of opinion that if Mr. Allen does
                            not, after the United States authorities have been informed of their
                            opinion and of the position of the suit at law, proceed with his action,
                            application should be made to dismiss the suit, and no further
                            application to the Government should be entertained; for the
                            relinquishment of the suit, under all the circumstances, could only be
                            regarded as a deliberate abandonment of the proper and legitimate mode
                            of redress.</p>
                    <p>The delay which has occurred in bringing the suit to trial in face of the
                            advice of Mr. Allen’s own counsel that it might have been tried in
                            September, 1888, is incapable of explanation on any other ground than
                            that Mr. Allen was aware that he had incurred the expense and the loss
                            consequent on the ship’s delay by his own act only, and was unwilling to
                            have the facts investigated, but preferred to make his claim the subject
                            of diplomatic correspondence, in the hopes that he might thereby avoid
                            an investigation of the facts on which his claim ought to depend.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
