<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1889-06-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1889-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="248" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d248">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Ryan</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1889-06-10"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 10, 1889</date>.
                            (Received June 18.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 17.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Nothing further having reached this legation
                        concerning the case of Leon McLeod Baldwin, cruelly murdered in Durango in
                        August, 1887, since Mr. Whitehouse, acting under instructions of the
                        Department, <pb facs="0685" n="563" xml:id="pg_563"/> on December 17 last,
                        again called Mr. Mariscal’s attention to the matter, I have deemed it my
                        duty to renew the solicitations for a humane and equitable adjustment of the
                        case.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Whitehouse in his dispatch, No. 218, of December 17, 1888, stated that
                        Mr. Mariscal asserted that he was not yet in possession of sufficient
                        evidence to form a definite opinion.</p>
                    <p>It would certainly appear that since that time, nearly six months ago, Mr.
                        Mariscal had had ample time and opportunities to convince himself in the
                        matter.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas Ryan</hi>.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 17.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Ryan</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Mariscal</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1889-06-10"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 10,
                                1889</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Several months have expired since Mr.
                            Whitehouse, acting under instructions from the Department of State, drew
                            your excellency’s attention (December 17, 1888) anew to the case of Leon
                            McLeod Baldwin, who was murdered in Durango in 1887.</p>
                        <p>The details of this sad affair are so well known to your excellency that
                            it would be superfluous to enter into them again, but this legation
                            having up to the present received no communication concerning the matter
                            since your excellency’s note of June 4, 1888, I deem it my duty again to
                            draw your excellency’s attention to this most important case, and
                            respectfully to suggest the desirability for an early adjustment.</p>
                        <p>It will be looked upon as a singularly graceful and friendly act by my
                            Government should a decision in accordance with the principles of
                            humanity and equity be arrived at by your excellency’s Government.</p>
                        <p>I am confident that when your excellency has carefully considered the
                            exceptional and distressing conditions of the case you will be inclined
                            to agree with the views presented by my Government.</p>
                        <p>I take, etc.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas Ryan.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>