<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Winchester to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1889</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d311</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">311</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1888-12-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1888-12-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recT4bjXsa6CHJpTr" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000961"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">RAPP</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1888-12-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1888-12-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="311"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d311">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Winchester</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berne</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-12-22">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 22, 1888</date>. (Received January 7,
                        1889.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 242.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Soon after my assumption of the duties of this
                    post I submitted to the Department the pressing needs for urging upon the Swiss
                    Government the negotiation of a naturalization treaty, and in doing so it was
                    stated that, among other evils resulting from the absence of such a treaty, and
                    the Swiss contention as to Swiss citizenship in spite of the fact of a Swiss
                    being invested under our naturalization laws with all the rights and privileges
                    of an American citizen, one of the most serious and common was the detention of
                    property claimed by Switzers naturalized and residing in the United States—this
                    detention and refusal to surrender property to the legal and equitable owner
                    being done under the cover of most flimsy and frivolous pretexts by the local
                    authorities and tribunals.</p>
                <p>Through the intelligent and energetic efforts of our consul at Zurich (Mr.
                    Catlin) a case involving considerable property was appealed from the cantonal to
                    the federal tribunal, the Swiss supreme court, and an opinion obtained which
                    probably is the most decisive judicial pronouncement on one very characteristic
                    feature of such cases, and gives some assurance that the local contentions
                    heretofore held and expressed, if properly submitted to this tribunal, must be
                    reversed as this has been. A copy of the opinion is inclosed.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Boyd Winchester.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0811" n="689" xml:id="pg_689"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 242.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Judgment of the Swiss Federal Court</hi>.</head>
                    <p>In the matter of Carl Heinrich Weber, of Zurich, in Philadelphia, State of
                        Pennsylvania, North America, appellant, represented by Lawyer
                            Haggenmacher,<note n="*" xml:id="d311fn1">For George L. Catlin, U. S.
                            consul at Zurich, attorney for appellant.</note> of Zurich, concerning
                        waiver of Swiss citizenship, the following facts appear from the documents
                        presented, viz:</p>
                    <p>A.—Carl Heinrich Weber, of Zurich, born in 1845, emigrated in 1873 to the
                        United States of America; he was, at the time of emigrating, and has been
                        ever since, under guardianship in Zurich. In 1879, Weber, having acquired
                        United States citizenship, applied for release from his rights as a Swiss
                        citizen. His sister Maria, and his guardian, as well as the orphans’ court
                        of Zurich, then instituted proceedings against his release on the ground
                        that the identity of the applicant with the Zurich citizen C. H. Weber was
                        not proven, and because the said C. H. Weber was under guardianship, and
                        therefore, as not being competent to transact business on his own account,
                        could not waive his Swiss citizenship.</p>
                    <p>The federal court by a decision dated September 27, 1879, rejected the latter
                        objection as unfounded, but, on the other hand, deferred any judgment, in so
                        far as the question of the identity of Carl H. Weber with the applicant was
                        concerned, until sufficient further evidence could be produced. Therefore,
                        the judge of instruction of the federal court repeatedly accorded the
                        applicant a period of time for filing new means of proving his identity with
                        C. H. Weber. Inasmuch as during these periods the applicant appealed merely
                        to a comparison of handwritings which, however, the federal court held to be
                        insufficient, the court decreed on the 10th of July, 1880, that the
                        appellant’s application be rejected.</p>
                    <p>B.—In an application dated March 27, 1888, Lawyer Haggenmacher<note n="†"
                            xml:id="d311fn2">Representing Mr. Catlin, U. S. consul at Zurich,
                            attorney for Carl H. Weber.</note> of Zurich renewed in the name of Carl
                        Heinrich Weber a demand on the government council of the canton of Zurich
                        for said Weber’s release from Swiss citizenship, furnishing proof of the
                        fact that C. H. Weber had been an actual resident of the State of
                        Pennsylvania since 1873; that, under the laws there in force he is competent
                        to transact business, and that he had acquired the rights of citizenship of
                        the United States of America. On the 29th of March, 1888, the government
                        council of the canton of Zurich referred this application to the district
                        council of Zurich for its own information, and for transmission to the city
                        council of Zurich, and to all persons otherwise concerned, for action under
                        article 7, abst. I, of the federal law of 1876. The district council in
                        turn, March 31, 1888, referred the application, in a similar sense to the
                        city council of Zurich, which after calling upon the guardian of C. H. Weber
                        for a written opinion upon the subject, raised objection in a document dated
                        May 5, 1888, to the sought-for release from citizenship, advancing the
                        following reasons, viz, that Weber had never received his guardian’s
                        permission to emigrate; consequently, he could not have lawfully removed his
                        domicil from Zurich, and is therefore, according to article 6, litt. <hi
                            rend="italic">a</hi>. of the federal law of June 3, 1876, not entitled
                        to the right of waiver of his Swiss citizenship. The government council of
                        the canton of Zurich, by decree of June 2, 1888, referred this objection,
                        together with the papers in the case, to the federal court for its
                        decision.</p>
                    <p>C.—On the 31st of July, 1888, the attorney for C. H. Weber filed with the
                        federal court an application, demanding that the objection raised against
                        the waiver of citizenship by Carl Heinrich Weber, resident in Philadelphia,
                        be dismissed, and that instructions be given to the proper cantonal
                        authorities to pronounce C. H. Weber’s release from his Zurich state
                        (cantonal,) and town citizenship. He (the attorney), goes on to state that
                        neither Weber’s near relations in Zurich, nor his guardian there, but simply
                        and alone the city council of Zurich, have raised objection. But the said
                        city council’s objection was offered too late, inasmuch as it was not
                        offered within the four-weeks limit provided by art. 7, abst. I, of the
                        federal law of June 3, 1876, and is therefore not entitled to any further
                        consideration. There is, moreover, no reason presented for not granting the
                        release applied for; the appellant satisfies every requirement of the
                        federal law of June 3, 1876; he has no longer any domicil in Switzerland,
                        has acquired citizenship in the United States, and is also competent to
                        transact business under the laws of the State in which he resides. It is not
                        correct that the appellant did not receive-his guardian’s consent to
                        emigrate.</p>
                    <p>He gave his then guardian, from his then place of residence, Munich, notice
                        of his intention to emigrate, and the latter offered no opposition, but, on
                        the contrary sent him, shortly before his departure, 400 francs, to enable
                        him to provide himself with new clothing. Shortly after his arrival at
                        Philadelphia, the appellant informed his guardian of his address, but
                        received no answer thereto; he also, though at intervals, <pb facs="0812"
                            n="690" xml:id="pg_690"/> corresponded with his relatives at
                            Hirslanden.<note n="*" xml:id="d311fn3">A suburb of Zurich.</note> At no
                        time during the entire period of his stay in Philadelphia was he summoned by
                        his guardian, by the orphan’s court or by any other authority whatsoever, to
                        remove his domicile to his home township (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Heimath-Gemeinde</hi>) or to any other place whatsoever. This certainly
                        implies the guardian’s consent to his being where he at that time was. In
                        the former proceedings relative to the appellant’s release from Swiss
                        citizenship, ground was never taken that he had emigrated without his
                        guardian’s consent, and his present guardian sent him, by consent of the
                        orphans’ court, a sum of money he had asked for, for the purpose of making a
                        transient visit to his former home.</p>
                    <p>D.—The government council of the canton of Zurich transmitted the view taken
                        by the city council of Zurich of this complaint. The city council states as
                        follows: The appellant’s guardian, in his report to the city council,
                        advised the dismissal of the proceedings for release; the views of Weber’s
                        relatives had not been consulted. But the guardianship authorities and the
                        guardian are entitled to raise objections, even without assistance from the
                        relatives. Article 7 of the federal law of June 3, 1876, couples no menace
                        with the fixing of a period of four weeks for the filing of objections. It
                        would therefore be inadmissible to declare inoperative an objection filed
                        after the expiration of such period, and all the more so, as the right to
                        file objections serves simply for the protection of the public
                        interests.</p>
                    <p>The fixing of a limit of time is therefore simply a rule of order. The
                        consent of not only the guardian, but also of the guardianship authorities
                        (the orphans’ court), if not, indeed, that of the district council, was
                        requisite to a lawful change of domicile by the ward. What communications
                        the appellant made to his former guardian can not now be ascertained, as
                        said former guardian is deceased. It is certain, however, that the orphans’
                        court has at no time been approached for a consent to a change of domicile.
                        If said orphans’ court never summoned the appellant to return to Zurich,
                        such fact is entirely unimportant, for the reason that the said court could
                        not have compelled such return; moreover, indeed, Weber himself states that
                        the orphans’ court allowed the money necessary for his return journey to be
                        sent to him.</p>
                    <p>The federal court takes into consideration the following: <list>
                            <label>I.</label>
                            <item>The city council of Zurich is undoubtedly entitled to present
                                objections to the release of C. H. Weber, a citizen of the town of
                                Zurich, from his citizenship. Its objections, moreover, can not be
                                ruled out on account of delay in filing them. It is true that such
                                objections did not ensue within a period of four weeks, reckoned
                                from the time when the application for release was communicated to
                                the city council. But the limit provided in article 7 of the federal
                                law of June 3, 1876, is not one (according to the beginning,
                                duration and end of a limit exactly prescribed by law) to the
                                neglect of which the law would attach preclusive consequences. The
                                law rather leaves the fixing of the limit of time for filing
                                objections in individual cases to the cantonal governments inasmuch
                                as it simply decrees that the limit to be fixed shall not exceed
                                four weeks; it does not further prescribe that the neglect to
                                observe such fixed limit shall result in rendering the right of
                                objection inoperative. In this position of the case the limit is
                                simply to be regarded as a limit of order, and this all the more
                                since the question whether the legal conditions incident to a waiver
                                of Swiss citizenship exist, must in any event be examined into
                                officially by the authorities.</item>
                            <label>II.</label>
                            <item>It is established that the appellant has, in point of fact,
                                resided in Philadelphia since 1873; that under the laws there in
                                force he is competent to transact business, and that he has acquired
                                United States citizenship. The city council of Zurich contests his
                                competence to waive his Swiss citizenship, simply because he, as a
                                ward, without consent from the guardianship authorities, could not
                                legally change his domicile. Now, as a question of principle, it is
                                correct that a ward can not lawfully change his domicile without his
                                guardian’s consent. On the other hand, it is not requisite that such
                                a consent be expressly outspoken; it can rather occur tacitly, and
                                thus be concluded by actual circumstances. If, especially, both the
                                guardian and the guardianship authorities simply allow a change of
                                the ward’s residence, they being cognizant of it, to take place
                                without their protesting against it, and calling upon the ward to
                                return, it is at all events, as a rule, to be presumed that they
                                have consented to said ward’s removal to his new place of residence.
                                So far as the guardianship authorities consider the change of
                                residence as prejudicial to the ward’s interests, it is certainly
                                their duty, where possible to prevent it or thwart it. If,
                                therefore, they remain silent in regard to a change in his place of
                                residence by the ward, they being cognizant of the same, it is
                                certainly to be regularly presumed that such change takes place
                                because they have no opposition to offer against it. The
                                circumstances that in a case of emigration to a foreign country,
                                especially to those beyond the sea, the guardianship authorities are
                                not in position directly to compel the ward to return does not
                                affect the question at all. Even though the said authorities may
                                lack any power of coercion over the person of the ward, they can yet
                                ultimately bring an influence to bear upon his course, as for
                                instance by <pb facs="0813" n="691" xml:id="pg_691"/> granting him
                                the enjoyment of his fortune only in so far as he complies with his
                                guardian’s instructions in regard to his choice of his place of
                                residence. Now, in the present case, it may safely he presumed that
                                the guardianship authorities consented to the appellants emigrating;
                                at no time did either guardian or guardianship authorities,
                                notwithstanding that the ward’s place of sojourn was known to them,
                                express, in any way whatever, their disapproval of his emigrating:
                                in particular, during the former proceedings for the appellants
                                release from citizenship it was not even alluded, to from any
                                quarter, that said appellant had emigrated in an unlawful way,
                                without his guardian’s consent; the appellant’s right of waiver of
                                his Swiss citizenship was at that time contested on entirely
                                different grounds.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The federal court has accordingly recognized as follows: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>The objections of the city council of Zurich against the release
                                of Carl Heinrich Weber of Zurich, born 1845, from his right of
                                citizenship, are dismissed, and the government council of the canton
                                of Zurich is requested to confer upon the appellant a release from
                                his Swiss cantonal and town citizenship.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>The fees, amounting toll francs for drawing up this decision, and
                                the charges for postage, are to be charged to the objector.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>This decision is to be communicated in writing to the appellant,
                                as well as to the government council of the canton of Zurich for its
                                own information and for transmission to the city council of
                                Zurich.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Lausanne, October 19, 1888.</p>
                    <p>In the name of the Swiss federal court,</p>
                    <closer>[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>] <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Rapp</hi>, <hi rend="italic">President.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Roth</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Court Clerk.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>A true translation and copy.</p>
                        <closer>[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>] <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">George L. Catlin</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">United States Consul.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
