<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Denby to Mr. Blaine.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1889</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d76</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">76</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1889-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1889-06-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="european-economic-community" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="european-economic-community">European Community</term>
                    <term ref="recORcNZq5ClDOVNg" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046356"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exhibit</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1889-06-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1889-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="76"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d76">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Denby</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1889-06-10">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 10, 1889</date>. (Received July
                        22.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 908.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The spread of the Chinese race into the
                    dependencies of European powers in the east is interesting as illustrating its
                    vitality, perseverance, and colonizing qualities.</p>
                <p>From late sources I have prepared the following statement of the Chinese
                    population in the more important eastern localities.</p>
                <p>The population of Hong-Kong, by the census of 1881, was 160,402. Of this number
                    the foreign population was 8,000. These figures (8,000) include the entire
                    transient population, of which only 3,000 were permanent residents. It is
                    estimated that the total population is now 200,000, of which probably 190,000
                    are Chinese.</p>
                <p>According to the returns made in 1879, the population of Macao was, Chinese
                    63,532, Portuguese 4,476, other nationalities 78, or a total of 68,086. It is
                    thought that there has been no increase since 1879, but rather a decline.</p>
                <p>The population of Nagasaki, Japan, was, in 1887, 38,229. The number of foreigners
                    was 1,031, of whom 741 were Chinese. The population of Kobe in 1887 was 101,231,
                    of whom 1,139 were foreigners, the Chinese numbering 724. The population of
                    Osaka in 1887 was 361,694. Of foreign residents there were 284, of whom 185 were
                    Chinese. The population of Tokio in 1885 was 1,207,847. There were 300 foreign
                    residents, but I am unable to state the number of Chinese. The native population
                    of Yokohama is 89,545. The number of foreign residents in 1887 was 3,821, of
                    whom 2,359 were Chinese. According to the census of 1883 there were residing in
                    Manila of European origin 4, 189 European Spaniards, 15, 157 Chinese, 46,066
                    Chinese Mestizos (half-breeds), 3,849 Spanish half-breeds, and 160,896 pure
                    natives. The population of Saigon, the capitol of Cochin China, was, December
                    31, 1886, 18,009, of whom 8,986 were Annamites and 6,649 Chinese. The French
                    population numbers 1,257, and other Europeans 97. In Haiphong, the shipping port
                    of Hanoi, in Tonquin, the Chinese population is about 4,700 and the Annamite
                    3,800, the foreign population being <pb facs="0229" n="111" xml:id="pg_111"/>
                    323. In Borneo the Chinese conduct all the trading operations. In British North
                    Borneo there are many Chinese, but I am unable to state their number. In Labuan,
                    the smallest British colony in Asia, with a population of 6,000, 1,000 are
                    Chinese. The Chinese are the chief traders and most of the industries of the
                    island are in their hands. The number of Chinese in Siam is estimated at
                    1,300,000. The population of Singapore Island, according to the census of 1881,
                    was 139,208, of whom 86,768 were Chinese and 22,114 Malays. The European
                    community consists in the main of English and Germans, and numbers, with 783
                    military, a total of 2,769. In Malacca, with a population of 93,579, there are
                    19,741 Chinese. In Sungie Ujong the Chinese form a large proportion of the
                    population of 30,000. In Selangor, with a population of 97,106, 78,155 are
                    Chinese. The Chinese are a large part of the population of Perak, being
                    estimated at 47,000, while the Malays are about 53,000. In Penang, out of a
                    total population of 244,000, the Chinese number 67,502.</p>
                <p>It will be seen from this cursory exhibit that the Chinese are overrunning
                    contiguous commercial points in the East. They are gradually absorbing business
                    and ousting other native and foreign traders. In China proper, even at the open
                    ports, they are dangerous rivals to foreign merchants. They make no display, do
                    not leave their business to compradors; rely on quick returns, and, owing to a
                    wide-spread system of mutual responsibility, they are generally honest, and meet
                    all their obligations.</p>
                <p>It is easy to be seen that the time will come in the “far East” when the same
                    objections to their presence which have been heard in the United States and
                    Australia will be loudly uttered. They seem to possess the faculty of absorbing
                    even their conquerors. Thus the Chinese have absorbed the Mongolians and the
                    Manchus, and with their religion, their arts, and their government they dominate
                    these races. Wherever they go in the East they become the masters of trade. The
                    mutterings against them are loud in every locality where they are settled. But
                    their compact conservatism, their industry and their economical habits enable
                    them to win their way over all opposition short of absolute exclusion.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Denby.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
