<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1889-11-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1889-11-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="78" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d78">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Denby</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1889-11-10"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 10, 1889</date>.
                            (Received December 23.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 999.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In view of the practice of cremation, which is
                        sometimes resorted to in the United States and is there attracting some
                        attention, I have the honor to submit a few observations on this practice in
                        China:</p>
                    <p>Following their favorite idea of classification by numerical categories, the
                        Chinese distinguish five forms of burial; these follow the five elements or
                        primordial essences upon which the whole scheme of Chinese philosophy is
                        based, viz, water, wood, metal, earth, and fire.</p>
                    <p>Burial by water is practiced somewhat in South China by dwellers by rivers or
                        the sea, and consists, as the name indicates, simply in intrusting the body
                        to the water. Burial by wood is the usual interment in a wooden coffin, the
                        universal custom of the Chinese. Metal burial is said of the interment of an
                        Emperor, though, as a matter of fact, Emperors also are buried in wooden
                        coffins. Earth burial is the burial practiced by the Mohammedans. Followers
                        of this sect carry the dead to the grave in a coffin, but the body is
                        committed to the earth uninclosed. The last form, burial by fire, as the
                        Chinese call it, or cremation, is, in view of all circumstances, the most
                        remarkable of all.</p>
                    <p>It would seem somewhat inconsistent in a people whose deepest religious
                        instinct is reverence for ancestors to practice cremation. The teachings of
                        Confucius on the observance of funeral ceremonies and the performance of
                        certain rites at ancestral tombs would apparently be quite opposed to such a
                        custom. In spite of his teachings, however, this form of burial is practiced
                        somewhat to-day in China, and was much more so in the middle ages.</p>
                    <p>The foreign books on China usually consulted refer to it as practiced only by
                        Buddhist priests and lamas and as required in the case of <pb facs="0232" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/> lepers. Well-informed Chinese in North China
                        themselves will deny that the custom has ever existed outside of the
                        religious orders. It seems, however, that while perhaps never universal,
                        cremation was formerly practiced in many localities. A Chinese historical
                        work states that <hi rend="italic">huo tsang</hi> (burial by fire) was
                        introduced from <hi rend="italic">Tien Chu Kuo</hi>, now called <hi rend="italic">Yin Tu Kuo</hi> (India), during the Han dynasty (about the
                        beginning of the Christian era). It came as a feature of Buddhism and was
                        probably confined at first to priests.</p>
                    <p>It is well known that cremation in Japan was introduced with Buddhism and had
                        never been known there before. The cremation of a bonze in 700 A. D. is said
                        by Griffis (Mikado’s Empire, p. 175, note) to have been the first instance.
                        It is now regularly practiced there by certain Buddhist sects.</p>
                    <p>In a book called the <hi rend="italic">Kao Seng Chuan</hi>, it is stated that
                        the Chinese Emperor Han Wu Ti (92 B. C), in digging a lake, found some bone
                        ashes and asked his celebrated minister, Tung Fang So, what they were. The
                        reply was that they were the ashes of a Buddhist priest from <hi rend="italic">Hsi Yii</hi>, perhaps Thibet, and it was explained that
                        when a priest dies he is buried by fire, a custom which is therefore called
                            <hi rend="italic">chieh hui</hi>, “to reduce to ashes.” The minister
                        further stated that the people of <hi rend="italic">Ti Chiang</hi> have this
                        mode of burial. Williams states in his dictionary that <hi rend="italic">Ti
                            Chiang</hi> was “a tribe in the Shang dynasty, which occupied a region
                        on the upper waters of the river Wei, in Kansuh.” Whether or not this is the
                        place referred to it would be difficult to say, but the statement seems to
                        indicate the practice of cremation in that locality even anterior to
                        Buddhism.</p>
                    <p>Another Chinese work, the <hi rend="italic">Jih Chih Lu</hi>, refers to
                        “burial by fire” during the Sung dynasty (twelfth to fourteenth centuries).
                        It is stated that in the reign of the Emperor Shao Hsing (1131) the custom
                        of cremation prevailed in Kiang-nau, (Kiangsi, Kiangsu, and Anhui). It is
                        further stated that Han Chi (1008–1075), one of the most celebrated of the
                        statesmen of that dynasty and a man who was renowned,” says Mayers, “by
                        solicitude for the well-being of the people,” bought lands for free burial
                        grounds for the poor and thus abolished the custom. Marco Polo’s mention of
                        it, however, shows that it continued to be commonly practiced during the
                        thirteenth century. This great traveler seems to have been chiefly struck
                        during his journeys in China by the idolatry, the use of paper money, and
                        the practice of cremation. At that time there must, however, have already
                        been great feeling on the part of the officials and the educated classes
                        against the custom.</p>
                    <p>In the vicinity of Su Chow, in the year 1262, a cremation furnace was
                        destroyed by lightning. Upon the petition of the priests to whose temple it
                        was attached and who had derived a profit therefrom, requesting permission
                        to rebuild, a local official memorialized his superiors urging that this be
                        withheld, and wrote at length against the custom in general. He recommended,
                        in order to abolish the practice, that a free cemetery be furnished by the
                        Government for each five families. Such incidents, which were not uncommon,
                        show the prevalence of the practice of cremation at the time.</p>
                    <p>Were it not so opposed to the ideas of the Chinese on the disposition of the
                        dead, cremation might furnish a solution of several difficulties. It would
                        immensely reduce the area of ground required for graves, which continually
                        encroaches on the arable soil. The economy of the practice also is a great
                        recommendation. Funerals, as at present conducted, are ruinous to the poorer
                        classes. The amount devoted to this purpose requires, in my cases, years for
                        its collection, and frequently <pb facs="0233" n="115" xml:id="pg_115"/>
                        would suffice for the support of the family for several years. Cases are not
                        unheard of where sons sell themselves into slavery that their parents’
                        funeral may be conducted according to their ideas of propriety. It
                        frequently happens, also, that when there are not sufficient funds for the
                        purpose at the time of death, the body is kept in the house, incased in a
                        thick wooden coffin for three, four, and more years, awaiting the raising of
                        money.</p>
                    <p>Cremation is, however, forbidden by the statutes of the present dynasty, and
                        is rarely resorted to except to burn occasionally the bodies of Buddhist
                        priests or poor persons.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Denby.</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>