<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 10.Earl Granville to Mr. West.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1873p2v3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d37</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">37</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1871-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1871-03-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1871-03-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1871-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="37"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d37">
                <head>No. 10.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Earl <persName type="from">Granville</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">West</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-03-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 1, 1871</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have consulted the law-officers of the Grown
                    upon the point submitted to me in your dispatch of the 24th February, as to the
                    claims of British subjects to be indemnified for the loss of property during the
                    war; and I have now to acquaint you that I am advised by them that Her Majesty’s
                    subjects resident in France, whose property has been destroyed during the war,
                    cannot expect to be compensated, on the ground of their being British subjects,
                    for losses which the necessities of war have brought upon them in common with
                    French subjects.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GRANVILLE.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-03-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 28, 1871</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I am directed by Earl Granville to
                        acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 22d instant, containing a
                        statement of certain property possessed by you in Paris and the
                        neighborhood, and referring to the losses which you state you have sustained
                        in consequence of the occupation of such property by French and German
                        troops, and requesting that your interests may be placed under the
                        protection of Lord Lyons, with the object of your claim being ultimately
                        urged upon the French government on account of such losses and
                        dilapidations.</p>
                    <p>I am now to inform you that Lord Granville has taken the opinion of the
                        law-officers of the Crown as to the liability of the French government to
                        compensate British subjects resident in France for loss and damage to their
                        property during the Me war, and that his lordship has been advised by them
                        that the British subjects resident in France would have, in their opinion,
                        no just ground of complaint against the French authorities in the event of
                        their property having been destroyed by the invading armies; their losses
                        under such circumstances would be among the inevitable consequences of war
                        raging in a state within <pb facs="0427" n="369" xml:id="pg_369"/> which
                        they have chosen, as foreigners, to take up their residence; and with regard
                        to such losses British subjects would not be entitled to claim any
                        compensation from the French authorities.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>E. HAMMOND.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
