<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador to Greece (
                        MacVeagh
                    ) to the Greek Prime Minister (
                        Maximos
                    )Transmitted to Athens in telegram 449
                        with the instruction: “Please convey following personal message to Mr.
                        Maximos from MacVeagh.” The Ambassador was in the United States for
                        consultation.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d107</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">107</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-04-11T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-04-11T19:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-04-11T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-04-11T19:00:00-05:00" n="107" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d107">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">868.00/4–1147: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador to Greece</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacVeagh</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Greek Prime Minister</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Maximos</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d107fn1">Transmitted to Athens in telegram 449
                        with the instruction: “Please convey following personal message to Mr.
                        Maximos from MacVeagh.” The Ambassador was in the United States for
                        consultation.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-04-11T19:00:00-05:00">April 11, 1947—7 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>While every effort is being made here to secure implementation of the President’s
                    program for aid to Greece, public opinion is being constantly disturbed by
                    reports of official toleration of rightist excesses and the application of
                    security measures to non-subversive political opponents of the govt. The
                    impression created by these reports is that the President’s program aims to
                    assist a reactionary regime with all the earmarks of a police state, which is an
                    idea unacceptable to the American people.</p>
                <p>Officials of the Dept of State and many others in authority realize fully that
                    Greece is in danger from the communist menace both within and without the
                    country, and that drastic measures are necessary in such a situation. They also
                    understand the difficulty of administering even-handed justice at all times and
                    in all places under such circumstances. Nevertheless, they are being
                    embarrassed, and the success of the President’s proposals is being imperilled,
                    by the reports above mentioned.</p>
                <p>You will remember my concern over this matter expressed to you on numerous
                    occasions. You will also remember your assurance to me that in my absence your
                    policy would be in accord with the President’s message. I would now respectfully
                    emphasize again, but with a new urgency born of a critical moment, the
                    advisability (1) of your Govt’s giving some clear factual evidence of its
                    political tolerance and broad national character by proceeding with equal
                    vigilance and severity <pb facs="0157" n="143" xml:id="pg_143"/> against all
                    lawlessness whether of the right or left, and (2) of its giving its actions in
                    this respect the fullest and most persistent publicity. That the Government of
                    Greece is “fascist” in mind and action is the argument which is telling more
                    potently than any other against the President’s program and it can be
                    effectively answered only by the observed conduct of that Govt itself.<note n="2" xml:id="d107fn2">In telegram 522, April 14, 5 p. m., from Athens,
                        Chargé Keeley reported that Ambassador MacVeagh’s message was received at
                        Athens on April 13 “and communicated Prime Minister same evening. He said he
                        would shortly furnish for reassurance of the Ambassador copies of orders
                        already issued by his direction to all security agencies to proceed with
                        equal vigilance and severity against all lawlessness whether of the right or
                        left. I reiterated previous comment … that equally important to issuance
                        such orders is to see that they are obeyed and that more important than
                        reassurance to Ambassador was to see that conduct of security agencies is so
                        unmistakably impartial that observers, particularly foreign news
                        correspondents, would so report instead of contrary. He said he fully agreed
                        but that hatred engendered by left excesses is so great it is difficult to
                        control rightist retaliation. However, I might assure Ambassador that he
                        would continue to do his utmost to keep govt’s actions in accord with his
                        policy which would continue to be in harmony with President’s message.”
                        (868.00/4–1447). Prime Minister Maximos’ formal reply to Ambassador MacVeagh
                        was conveyed by the Embassy in Athens in telegram 539, April 17, midnight
                        (868.00/4–1747).</note>
                </p>
                <closer>[<signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">MacVeagh</hi>
                    </signed>]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
