<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-05-07T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-05-07T18:00:00-05:00" n="127" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d127">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">868.20/4–2647: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Greece</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-05-07T19:00:00-04:00">May 7,
                                    1947—7 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>603. <gloss target="#t_urtel1">Urtels</gloss> 570 Apr 24<note n="1" xml:id="d127fn1">Not printed; but see footnote 1, <ref target="#pg_152">p. 152</ref>.</note> and 590 Apr 26. Please
                            advise appropriate Greek officials Depts opinion neither Army nor <hi rend="italic">Gendarmerie</hi> should be increased in size pending
                            further study of both military and economic implications. In discussing
                            issue you should emphasize following: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Present aid program does not provide for financing costs of
                                    increased forces.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>US Govt is not prepared to approve diversion directly or
                                    indirectly to the military of aid planned for stabilizing
                                    civilian economy and reconstruction without its concurrence.
                                    This would include diversion of any category of goods, whether
                                    imported or domestically produced, the supply of which is to be
                                    augmented from abroad under the aid program.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>On basis of Greek estimates revenues and expenditures 1947–48,
                                    internal financing increased forces will result in serious
                                    inflationary pressure aggravating problems of maintaining price
                                    stability, of combating hoarding, of facilitating exports, and
                                    of effecting reconstruction.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item> Dept particularly concerned over proposed permanent increase
                                    in <hi rend="italic">Gendarmerie</hi> and strongly believes no
                                    action should be taken at present to implement this decision.
                                    According to available information, increase is not required for
                                    anti-bandit operations and gives force to fears that <hi rend="italic">Gendarmerie</hi> may be used for unacceptable
                                    political purposes.</item>
                                <label/>
                                <item>For your info at time when aid bill is under debate, to
                                    augment forces under Zervas command strengthens accusations that
                                    reactionary elements Greek Govt are entrenching themselves with
                                    US approval and financial support.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>If recruiting for relief older age groups is urgently
                                    necessary from military viewpoint (Para 1 <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 620 May 13 [<hi rend="italic">3</hi>]) such changeover should be
                                    accomplished without enlargement present strength and/or
                                    financial burden.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Without passing judgment at present on short run needs of
                                    military establishment, Dept has strong convictions re military
                                    expenditures after immediate crisis has passed: <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Current military burden would be far beyond capacity
                                            of Greek economy to bear even after substantial degree
                                            of recovery.</item>
                                        <pb facs="0177" n="163" xml:id="pg_163"/>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Plans must be made now to reduce military expenditures
                                            drastically if Greece is to avoid financial collapse
                                            after present aid is terminated.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Please report Greek reaction to above.</p>
                        <p>Appreciate any further expression British views on subject.<note n="2" xml:id="d127fn2">This telegram was repeated to London as No.
                                1999.</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>