<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Greece ( (MacVeagh) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-05-10T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-05-10T04:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckOJp7RF2apAIO3" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85004558"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Amnesty</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-05-10T04:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-05-10T04:00:00-05:00" n="132"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d132">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">868.00/5–1047: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Greece</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacVeagh</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-05-10T11:00:00+02:00"
                            >May 10, 1947—11 a. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>672. Mytel 654, May 7. Following is Greek Govt’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >aide-mémoire</hi> dated May 10 in reply to mine of May 7: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Political Council is studying with due attention the contents of the
                            United States Ambassador’s communication referring to the amnesty. The
                            granting of amnesty to the surrendering rebels has been the policy
                            pursued three last months by the present and previous governments, and
                            has already had as a result the surrender of hundreds of rebels to the
                            authorities, which put them under their full protection.</p>
                        <p>“It is natural, that in view of the granting of a more liberal amnesty,
                            which presents many internal and external aspects, this subject be
                            studied from all sides and with the utmost attention.</p>
                        <p>“Before reaching a decision on this matter, the Hellenic Government
                            requests certain clarifications on concrete points of the American
                            suggestion, which have a decisive bearing on the various aspects of the
                            subject.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>“(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) According to the American
                                communication, the unilateral declaration of the Greek Govt
                                regarding amnesty is supposed to remove the eventuality of a
                                recommendation to this effect in the final report of the
                                Investigation Committee to the Security Council. However, since such
                                a declaration on the part of the Greek Govt would be noted in the
                                report of the Committee, there is no doubt that the Security Council
                                would give it equal consideration with all the other recommendations
                                and therefore nothing would be gained.</item>
                            <item> “(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) The Greek Govt-does not clearly
                                discern in the American communication whether a declaration of
                                intention regarding the granting of a more liberal amnesty is
                                understood to mean an amnesty having as a prerequisite a general
                                laying down of arms on the part of the rebels, or whether it means
                                more liberal application of amnesty which has already twice been
                                granted to all but civil criminals willing to lay down their
                                arms.</item>
                            <pb facs="0182" n="168" xml:id="pg_168"/>
                            <item>“The Royal Govt wishes to have it made clear whether, regarding
                                the application of the amnesty, it is suggested that foreign
                                observers be invited to be present in Greece during the continuation
                                of the bandit movement or only after its termination. It is obvious
                                that the psychological repercussion of their presence would be quite
                                different in each case, and that in the former the ability of the
                                Greek state to bring the revolt to an end would be greatly
                                enfeebled.</item>
                            <item>“The Greek Govt wonders whether, in the spirit of the American <hi
                                    rend="italic">démarche</hi>, the announcement of intention to
                                grant a more liberal amnesty, would if not followed by a general
                                deposition of weapons on the part of the rebels mean the granting of
                                all aid for the immediate dynamic suppression of the guerrilla
                                movement.</item>
                            <item>“(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) The Greek Govt sees, neither in the
                                    <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi> of Mr. MacVeagh, nor in the
                                Ethridge plan, submitted to the Investigation Committee, those
                                concrete assurances, to which Greece feels she is entitled, against
                                the continuation of the fostering of the guerrilla movement from
                                abroad.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>“It wonders, how it would be possible to proceed to the announcement of
                            an act so important in political consequences, without having beforehand
                            the certainty that concrete and substantial measures are envisaged in
                            the Investigation Committee’s report for the termination of alien
                            aid.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Sent Dept as No. 672, repeated Geneva for Ethridge.</p>
                <p>For comment see my next following telegram.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">MacVeagh</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
