<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-06-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-06-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="159" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d159">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">867.00/6–1347: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Charge in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Kohler</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-06-13">June 13,
                                1947</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>2133. <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> June 12 “on American plans for
                            ‘moderization’ of Turkey” by G. Vershinin stresses military provisions
                            in aid to Turkey.</p>
                        <pb facs="0213" n="199" xml:id="pg_199"/>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">Summary follows</hi>.</p>
                            <p>Objections Turk public opinion don’t in least trouble new “trustees”
                                Turkey. They behave in this country as though they owned it and they
                                plan establish control American advisers over spending credits by
                                Turkey on “moderniz[ation]” of army. Having proffered their “aid”
                                Americans at same time showed complete disregard for Turk
                                sovereignty, entrusting to special military representatives not only
                                determination of program of works to be carried out on Turk
                                territory but also direction of their carrying out political tasks
                                which are at basis of “Truman Doctrine” correspond admirably to
                                interests American industrialists. Not only is surplus war material
                                and some part products American war industry being sold off to
                                Turkey but in addition all this being done under full American
                                control.</p>
                            <p>Unending stream highly placed Americans coming to Turkey. Other such
                                American military missions are expected. Members are discussing with
                                Turk staff “requirements” of country for armaments. Conversations
                                are concerned with motorization Turk infantry, supplies arms of high
                                fire power and contemp[orary?] antiaircraft guns, reorganization old
                                and construction new aerodromes, modernization and extension war
                                factories, reconstruction harbors, etc. Even new uniform for various
                                types Turk troops being discussed. American missions also visit all
                                important strategic areas Turkey.</p>
                            <p>Very program of work US military missions in Turkey and list
                                questions which are to be “study” American specialists bear witness
                                to fact that from military viewpoint Turkey has ceased be
                                independent country.</p>
                            <p>American capital penetrating deeply into economy country. Already
                                branches American banks have been opened in Istanbul and Izmir, and
                                branch American firm, American Middle East Co., which unites more
                                than sixty American industrialists, has been established. American
                                trusts are allowed to prospect widely for oil.</p>
                            <p>Under American pressure all restrictions for foreign capital have
                                been abolished thus extraordinarily favorable conditions have been
                                created for influx American capital. In fact USA has gained in
                                Turkey fulfillment its beloved principle “open door and equal
                                opportunity”.</p>
                            <p>In sphere economics Turkey also losing independence. British are
                                having yield place to stronger and wealthier rival. Prospect being
                                colony USA is deeply alarming democratic circles in Turkey. One can
                                understand alarm of simple people in Turkey. They are disturbed by
                                fact Turkey has become one of objects for application of alien
                                “doctrine” which threatens Turk sovereignty.</p>
                        </quote>
                        <p>Department please repeat Ankara 26.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Kohler</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>