<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Director of the Office of Near Eastern and
                    African Affairs ( (Henderson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-02-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-02-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="30"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d30">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">868.00/2–2447</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Director of the Office of
                        Near Eastern and African Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Henderson</hi>)<note n="1" xml:id="d30fn1">Initialed by the Secretary of
                        State.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-02-24">February 24,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>The Secretary.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Loy Henderson, Director, <gloss target="#t_NEA1"
                            >NEA</gloss>.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Lord Inverchapel, British Ambassador.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Herbert M. Sichel, First Secretary, British Embassy.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The British Ambassador, accompanied by Mr. Sichel, First Secretary of the British
                    Embassy, was received at their request by the Secretary this morning at 9
                    o’clock. The Ambassador informed the Secretary that, upon instructions from his
                    Government, he had come to hand him the two <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoires</hi>
                    attached hereto,<note n="2" xml:id="d30fn2">The <hi rend="italic"
                            >aide-mémoire</hi> of February 21, <ref target="#pg_32">pp. 32</ref> and
                            <ref target="#pg_35">35</ref>.</note> one relating to Greece and the
                    other to Turkey.</p>
                <p>After reading the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> relating to Greece, the
                    Secretary stated that he realized that the matter treated in it was of the
                    utmost urgency and importance, that it would be discussed at once with the
                    President and the Chiefs of Staffs, and that he hoped that a reply could be made
                    in the near future.</p>
                <p>After examining the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> relating to Turkey, the
                    Secretray stated that what he had said with regard to the first note also
                    applied to the second; that the question of Turkey would also be given the
                    urgent attention of the United States Government. He added that the problem with
                    regard to Turkey seemed to be somewhat different, however, from the Greek
                    problem. The Ambassador agreed, adding that the Greek problem was undoubtedly
                    the more urgent of the two; nevertheless, it seemed wise to the British
                    Government that the problem of Turkey should not be neglected.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that it was his understanding that the Russians had made no
                    move with regard to Turkey for some time and asked if the Ambassador had any
                    ideas regarding the reasons for the Russian <pb facs="0058" n="44"
                        xml:id="pg_44"/> silence. The Ambassador said that in his opinion no
                    foreigner knows why Russia takes or fails to take certain actions. Therefore, as
                    an honest man, he must admit that he is not in a position to explain what is
                    responsible for the present Soviet attitude towards Turkey. He could make
                    guesses, but his guesses would be of no more value than those of any other
                    person.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador emphasized the fact that neither the Greek nor the Turkish
                    Government had as yet been informed of the decision of Great Britain that it
                    could no longer extend financial assistance to Greece and Turkey. He added that
                    it probably would be disastrous: to give such information to the Greeks or the
                    Turks unless they could be informed at the same time that the United States
                    Government had definite plans to aid them.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>L[<hi rend="smallcaps">oy</hi>] W. H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >enderson</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
