<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Secretary of State to
                        the Embassy in Turkey</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d301</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">301</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-10-10T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-10-10T17:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="sovereignty" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696" lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-10-10T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-10-10T17:00:00-05:00" n="301" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d301">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">867.20/10–447: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Turkey</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-10-10T17:00:00-05:00">October 10, 1947—5 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>582. From a review of Embtel 751, Sept 29, Wilson’s Oct 2 from Bern and <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 769, Oct 4,<note n="1" xml:id="d301fn1">Not
                        printed.</note> Turk Govt’s plans for demobilization still appear somewhat
                    confused. It might assist them in reaching definite decision if you were to
                    convey following message which has been cleared with appropriate officials Dept
                    of Army. Communication should be personal and oral to either Sadak or Saka<note n="2" xml:id="d301fn2">Hasan Saka bad become Turkish Prime Minister the
                        previous month, with Necmettin Sadak as Foreign Minister.</note> (re
                    latter’s approach to Wilson Aug 16, Embtel 655).</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Our estimate of international situation is that while it is obviously bad,
                        there is no immediate danger of war. We do not believe USSR wants war.
                        Soviet policy appears to be directed toward achievement of its aims through
                        subversive activities of communist parties in various foreign countries and
                        such other political, economic and psychological weapons as it finds
                        available. First objective is obviously creation in strategic areas of state
                        of chaos which Russians and their satellites can utilize to establish
                        regimes subservient to them. So long as they find this policy promises
                        results, and at least until they have made greater progress in their
                        internal rehabilitation, we believe Russians will avoid armed clash.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>We do not believe that partial demobilization of sort Turks are
                        considering would have any material effect on Russian attitude or course of
                        action in area. However, if Turks should decide to carry out demobilization
                        plans, it would seem to us highly desirable that they be presented in such
                        way as to make move appear part of reorganization of army having as one of
                        its effects and advantages reduction in number of men under arms. It might
                        be given out that because of receipt of new American equipment effective
                        strength of army would actually be increased despite smaller size. It could
                        be emphasized in addition that release of manpower for productive work and
                        reduction of military expenses would build up economic strength of country,
                        thus defeating hope of those who would like to see Turkey weakened <pb facs="0379" n="365" xml:id="pg_365"/> internally. Turks should of course
                        be careful to prevent any impression that demobilization implied change in
                        foreign policy or lessening of determination to maintain their sovereignty,
                        independence and integrity.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Explain that foregoing is not intended as advice, since we consider Turks must
                    make own decision, but is merely reflection our thinking which Turks may take
                    into consideration or not as they choose.</p>
                <p>For your background info Army considers that planned Turk reduction in force
                    prior to time aid program becomes effective would definitely weaken Turk
                    capacity to resist attack but concurs our feeling that attack unlikely and
                    acknowledges that advantages of reducing military burden may outweigh purely
                    military considerations.</p>
                <p>Question has been actively discussed with Brit Emb here. London will instruct
                        Kelly<note n="3" xml:id="d301fn3">Sir David V. Kelly, British Ambassador in
                        Turkey.</note> to make separate approach to Turks expressing forthright view
                    that balance of advantage on side of reduction. Not a joint Anglo-US
                    approach.</p>
                <p>Turk military situation has been reviewed by Gen Morgan of Brit Joint Staff
                    Mission and high US Army officers.<note n="4" xml:id="d301fn4">According to
                        telegram 795, October 14, from Ankara, Chargé Bursley had that morning given
                        the information contained in telegram 582 to the Turkish Foreign Minister.
                        The latter said that the thinking of the Turkish Government was very much
                        along the same lines (867.20/10–1447).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Sent Ankara 582; rptd Moscow as 1829, and London as 4379.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
