<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Draft Notes for Remarks by the United Kingdom at the Opening
                        of the United States–United Kingdom Talks on the Middle East</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d398</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">398</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-10-16T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="oil" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Oil</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-10-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="398" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d398">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> Files: Lot 55–D36</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Draft Notes for Remarks by the United Kingdom at the Opening
                        of the United States–United Kingdom Talks on the Middle East</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-10-16">October 16,
                            1947</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acting Secretary of State</hi>: We on our side are
                    equally happy to have this opportunity to talk over frankly and informally our
                    common problems relating to certain areas of the Mediterranean and the Middle
                    East. We are in full agreement on the scope and objectives of these talks as you
                    have stated them. We agree also on the procedure which you suggest. Our
                    representatives at the meetings with members of the Department of State will be
                    Sir John Balfour,<note n="1" xml:id="d398fn1">British Minister in the United
                        States.</note> Mr. <pb facs="0580" n="566" xml:id="pg_566"/> Wright, Mr.
                        Allen<note n="2" xml:id="d398fn2">William D. Allen, Counselor of the British
                        Embassy.</note> and Mr. Bromley,<note n="3" xml:id="d398fn3">Thomas E.
                        Bromley, First Secretary of the British Embassy.</note> with such assistants
                    as they may call upon from time to time. Military representation at these
                    meetings, and conversations between military representatives without the
                    attendance of the political representatives can be arranged as you suggest.</p>
                <p>And now I may perhaps say a few words to indicate the general lines on which our
                    minds are working.</p>
                <p>There lies between the western countries and the countries which are Communist or
                    Communist controlled, a [kind of]<note n="4" xml:id="d398fn4">The bracketed
                        portions in this paper seem to represent insertions or changes in the
                        original draft notes and were presumably included in Lord Inverchapel’s
                        actual remarks.</note> crescent of middle lands stretching from Scandinavia
                    through Europe, the Middle East and South East Asia to the Far East, whose
                    orientation will either be towards Western ideas or towards Communism. It is in
                    our view essential that the approach of our two countries towards these peoples,
                    on whom the preservation [issues] of peace so largely depends, should be
                    co-ordinated and that we should work together on a constructive basis in a
                    spirit of complete understanding and cooperation.</p>
                <p>In these [particular] talks we are concerned with one segment of this crescent,
                    namely the Eastern Mediterranean and the Middle East.</p>
                <p>In this segment we on our side are confronted with a number of problems which are
                    of vital importance to our future and to the future of peace. On one or two
                    occasions lately [in recent past] you have said to us reproachfully that we have
                    only informed you at the last moment of decisions we had taken on matters of
                    interest to us both. We want to be sure that in the area which we are now
                    discussing there should be no ground for such reproach between us. We should
                    like to have the fullest possible consultation and discussion with you before we
                    crystallise our own policy and take any final decisions.</p>
                <p>Our basic problem in the Middle East is as follows. Our Chiefs of Staff inform
                    our Government that in the event of any major power violating the Charter and
                    resorting to war, the Middle East will, as proved to be the case in both the
                    last wars, be a strategic theatre second only in importance, or perhaps equal in
                    importance, to the United Kingdom. The reasons which they adduce are not merely
                    that the Middle East is a vital theatre of communication for the Commonwealth,
                    or that it contains vital supplies of oil, although both these reasons are
                    valid. But they adduce the still more important argument that in meeting future
                    aggression conditions of modern warfare will not permit of merely passive or
                    even active defence, but require counter <pb facs="0581" n="567" xml:id="pg_567"/> offence. The Middle East is perhaps the one area from which offensive action
                    could be taken, both to relieve the pressure of attack on the United Kingdom and
                    from which to strike at the aggressor where he is vulnerable.</p>
                <p>The Chiefs of Staff go on to say that if the Middle East is to play this role in
                    action against a possible aggressor it is essential, as was again proved during
                    the last war, for us to maintain strategic facilities in the Middle East in
                    peace time. In other words, we must not only maintain bases in Africa, at Aden
                    and at other places within reach of the Middle East, but must have advanced
                    bases in peace time in the Middle East area itself.</p>
                <p>But if we are to possess the strategic facilities in the Middle East in peace
                    time, they must be located somewhere.</p>
                <p>We are therefore brought squarely up against a perfectly definite and concrete
                    issue. Either we must obtain or maintain the requisite strategic facilities [in
                    certain definite localities] in the Middle East in peace time or withdraw
                    strategically from the Middle East altogether.</p>
                <p>At this point strategy merges with politics. It does not appear probable that we
                    can maintain the strategic facilities we require either in Egypt or in
                    Palestine. We have two air bases in Iraq and hope to reach agreement with the
                    Government of Iraq for maintaining at least modified rights there. We also have
                    treaty rights in Transjordan and there are always possibilities of certain
                    rights in the Persian Gulf. We shall certainly wish to maintain rights in the
                    Sudan. But without Egypt or Palestine these are insufficient, [not enough,]
                    since they would leave us without the essential rights in the southeastern
                    corner of the Mediterranean. The whole question whether we can retain adequate
                    strategic facilities in the Middle East in peace time therefore turns upon
                    Cyrenaica.</p>
                <p>Cyrenaica is therefore the first question we want to talk over with you, since
                    upon it so many others depend. There are roughly speaking two means by which we
                    could obtain what we need. The first would be by a British trusteeship for
                    Cyrenaica [in Libya]. This, under the Italian peace treaty, would require either
                    the consent of the four powers within the year or, failing that, the consent of
                    the Assembly. Apart from possible objections on the part of some countries there
                    is the further complication that an ordinary trusteeship would not normally
                    provide for the full strategic facilities we should require, and that a
                    strategic trusteeship would need the approval of the Council. The second course
                    would be to work for the early independence of Cyrenaica, and then to conclude a
                    treaty with Emir giving us the facilities we require. There are of course
                    variants to these alternatives, such as a temporary trusteeship to be followed
                    by early independence <pb facs="0582" n="568" xml:id="pg_568"/> and a treaty.
                    And lastly there is the possibility that we might prevent any other solution
                    being adopted and simply retain the necessary strategic facilities by default
                    under Article 23 (ii) of the Italian peace treaty.</p>
                <p>I need hardly add that the question of Cyrenaica is intimately linked with
                    others. We have to consider the attitude of the Soviet Union, of France, and of
                    the Arab States; and we can hardly take a decision about Cyrenaica without also
                    clearing our minds on Tripolitania and on the future of the other former Italian
                    colonies.</p>
                <p>Here perhaps you will allow me to make a suggestion about possible procedure.
                    Since all the other problems in the Middle East are dependent upon this vital
                    strategic problem of bases, and in particular Cyrenaica, might it be wise to
                    have these studied first both from the strategical and the political angle? In
                    other words, the first points we should like to put to you are as follows. Do
                    you agree that it is of essential importance to us both that we [Britain] should
                    remain in the Middle East rather than withdraw? If we are to remain, do you
                    agree that it is essential that we should possess the necessary strategic
                    facilities in Cyrenaica in peace time, in addition to other facilities elsewhere
                    than in Egypt and Palestine? If so, can we work out a common approach to the
                    problem and agree to work together for whatever solution commends itself to us
                    after further study as being the most practicable? And finally, do you agree, in
                    studying the question of Cyrenaica, we should simultaneously study the questions
                    of other bases in the Middle East and of the Italian colonies other than
                    Cyrenaica, all of which more or less hang together? When we have examined these
                    problems, we could go on to examine other problems in the area.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
