<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-02-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-02-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="447" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d447">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">800.6363/2–2147</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Director of the Office of
                                International Trade Policy</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Nitze</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                Under Secretary of State for Economic Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Clayton</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-02-21">February 21, 1947</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Since announcement of the proposed two Middle East oil deals involving
                            Standard of New Jersey and Socony, serious thought has been given to
                            possible alternatives that, while not preventing the objectives of the
                            deals to be achieved, would be free of some of their immediate and
                            obvious, as well as possible long run, disadvantages. The most desirable
                            alternative would seem to be for Socony to purchase the 11.875 per cent
                            interest of Jersey in the Iraq Petroleum Company and for Socony to
                            withdraw from the Saudi Arabian deal, and possibly also from the
                            Jersey-Socony–Anglo-Iranian crude oil purchase agreement.</p>
                        <p>This realignment of interests would from a public policy standpoint have
                            the following advantages over the arrangements as presently proposed:
                            (1) It would afford a simple, clear-cut solution to the immediate
                            problem, in contrast to the complex negotiations that have been going on
                            between the parties in London for weeks seeking to accommodate the oil
                            requirements of the French within the framework of the deals as
                            presently proposed by the companies. At the same time it would
                            presumably be an acceptable solution to the French in that no question
                            of their rights under the Red Line Agreement would then be involved. (2)
                            It would also have certain indirect long run advantages: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) It would simplify and perhaps arrest the trend
                            toward multiplication of the interlocking arrangements between and among
                            the oil companies engaged in the international oil trade. Under the
                            proposed alternative Socony would become the sole American partner in
                                <gloss target="#t_IPC1">IPC</gloss>, and in the Saudi Arabian deal
                            there would be three companies instead of four. Moreover, if Socony also
                            withdrew from the Anglo-Iranian crude oil purchase agreement, there
                            would remain one less company involved in it. (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                            Belated to (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>), but more specific, it would
                            retard the growing consolidation outside the United States of the
                            interests of the two largest American oil companies, Jersey and Socony.
                            These companies gradually have become, and would continue under their
                            presently proposed arrangements to be, partners in all their ventures in
                            the Eastern Hemisphere except in their refining and marketing operations
                            in Europe, and in their marketing in Africa. (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)
                            Also related to the foregoing points is the fact that it would serve, in
                            part, to meet criticism of the deals, such as directed against them by
                            Senator O’Mahoney. (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) Finally, would perhaps go
                            some way <pb facs="0661" n="647" xml:id="pg_647"/> toward meeting the
                            criticism of the deals by outside American companies who feel that the
                            petroleum resources of the Middle East are being preempted by various
                            combinations of a very small group of large American and British
                            companies.</p>
                        <p>It has been reported to the Department that the proposed alternative
                            arrangement was being, or had been, considered by Jersey and Socony at
                            the time the enemy status of France under British legislation on
                            commerce with an enemy gave them a legal basis to go ahead with the
                            deals as proposed by them. Therefore, it is not an entirely new
                            arrangement devised within the Department. I believe the alternative
                            arrangement proposed possesses sufficient merits for you to give serious
                            consideration to inviting Mr. Harden of Jersey, and Mr. Sheets of Socony
                            to Washington to discuss it with the Department as soon as a meeting can
                            be arranged. This should be done promptly since negotiations have been,
                            and still are, going on with the French in London, and the adoption by
                            Jersey and Socony of the alternative above proposed presumably would
                            require a substantial readjustment of their position.</p>
                        <p>Another alternative which might also be considered, and perhaps discussed
                            with Jersey and Socony, is one that would involve the offer by Jersey of
                            its interest in <gloss target="#t_IPC1">IPC</gloss> to a group composed
                            of all other American companies desiring to participate. This would
                            essentially restore ownership to an American group similar to that which
                            originally owned the present Jersey–Socony 23.75 per cent interest in
                                <gloss target="#t_IPC1">IPC</gloss>. As compared with the other
                            alternative, this possibility might be considerably less attractive to
                            Jersey and Socony, and would require more positive action on the part of
                            the Department. It would afford the same kind of immediate solution to
                            the present difficulties and possess certain of the long run advantages
                            of the first proposal.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>