<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Department of State to the
                            British Embassy</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d47</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">47</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-03-01T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-03-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="47" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d47">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">868.00/2–2447</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">British Embassy</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary of State refers to the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                    delivered today to the British Embassy expressing the decision by the Executive
                    Branch of the Government of the United States to extend aid to Greece and
                    Turkey.</p>
                <p>In this <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> it was pointed out that the
                    Government of the United States desires confirmation of its assumption that the
                    British Government will continue to the extent of its ability, fully to
                    cooperate in supporting the political independence and territorial integrity of
                    Greece and Turkey. It is the view of the Government of the United States that
                    the problem of the maintenance of Greek and Turkish independence and territorial
                    integrity is closely related to problems of common concern involving other
                    countries in Europe and Asia.</p>
                <p>It is suggested, therefore, that informal conversations be entered into at the
                    earliest possible moment between the two Governments with regard to these
                    problems. These conversations might begin initially in Washington and continue
                    in Washington and elsewhere as they develop. These discussions would undoubtedly
                    involve considerations of the respective intentions, capabilities and
                    responsibilities of the two Governments.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, [<date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-03-01">March 1,
                            1947</date>].</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
