<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-06-03T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-06-03T07:00:00-05:00" n="533" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d533">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">800.3383/6–347: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Egypt</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Patterson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-06-03T14:00:00+02:00">June 3,
                                    1947—2 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>652. Foreign Office advises by circular note<note n="1" xml:id="d533fn1">No. 30.8/5, dated May 28, 1947. A copy of the note was transmitted
                                to the Department in despatch 2584, June 5, from Cairo
                                (800.3383/6–547).</note> to diplomatic missions Cairo of decision
                            Egyptian Government not to permit war vessels to anchor in Egyptian
                            harbors except after special application to Foreign Office at least
                            three weeks prior to date of projected naval visit.</p>
                        <pb facs="0790" n="776" xml:id="pg_776"/>
                        <p>Same note states that in respect of transit of such vessels through
                            Egyptian territorial waters and, by this fact the transit of the Suez
                            Canal, notification should be given to Egyptian Foreign Office at least
                            ten days prior to arrival on such vessels.</p>
                        <p>Following consultation with Naval Attaché, I orally drew attention
                            yesterday of Undersecretary Foreign Office to possibility that reference
                            to Suez Canal might not be in conformity with international status that
                            waterway Kemal Bey has stated that he would investigate this point,
                            since Egypt is especially desirous of maintaining legal status of Suez
                                Canal.<note n="2" xml:id="d533fn2">Airgram 349, June 12, from Cairo
                                reported that Kemal Bey informed the Chargé on June 11 “that since
                                the Egyptian Government’s reference to the Suez Canal was not to be
                                considered mandatory, but merely an expression of desire on the part
                                of the Egyptian Government, he did not perceive that any infraction
                                of the Suez Canal Convention was intended.” (800.3383/6–1247)</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Patterson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>