<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Acting United States Representative at the
                    United Nations ( (Johnson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d546</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">546</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-08-08T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-08-08T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-08-08T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-08-08T13:00:00-05:00" n="546"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d546">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BC/8–847: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Acting United States Representative at the United Nations</hi> (<persName
                        type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-08-08T14:00:00-04:00"
                            >August 8, 1947—2 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>341. Following is US position on Anglo-Egyptian case for your guidance.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">I. <hi rend="italic">Background:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On August 5, 1947 <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> heard statements of Egyptian
                    PriMin and representative of UK on Anglo-Egyptian controversy.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d546fn1">For the statements by Prime Minister Nokrashy and British
                        Representative Sir Alexander Cadogan, see <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>,
                            <hi rend="italic">2nd yr., No. 70</hi>, pp. 1745, 1767.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0802" n="788" xml:id="pg_788"/>
                <p>Egyptian PriMin stated to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> that dispute which
                    has arisen with UK over presence Brit troops in Egyptian territory and
                    administration and future status Anglo-Egyptian Sudan is endangering
                    international peace and security. He claimed that presence foreign troops in
                    Egyptian territory is infringement of Egyptian sovereignty, is contrary to
                    wishes of Egyptian people, and is without legal sanction. Latter position is
                    based on argument that Anglo-Egyptian Treaty of 1936 which provides for
                    stationing of Brit troops in Egypt is no longer valid because it was signed
                    under duress, conditions have changed, and is contrary to UN Charter. Egyptian
                    PriMin also maintained that question of administration and future status of
                    Sudan was matter for “people of Nile Valley” to decide. He asked <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> to direct immediate evacuation of all Brit forces
                    from Egypt and the Sudan and to direct termination of administrative regime in
                    the Sudan.</p>
                <p>Reply of UK representative was devoted largely to a refutation of the claims of
                    Egypt, i.e., UK representative asserted that Egyptian Govt had shown no grounds
                    for <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> action, since presence of Brit troops in
                    Egypt and arrangements for Govt of the Sudan are based on valid treaties, freely
                    negotiated and publicly acknowledged, which are continuing in force. He
                    emphasized that Brit policy with respect to the future right of the Sudanese to
                    choose their status would not be abandoned.</p>
                <p>Hence, statements of both Egyptian PriMin and UK representative were, in fact,
                    based principally on the question of the validity of the Treaty of 1936 as the
                    legal sanction for presence of Brit troops in Egypt and for the present Govt of
                    the Sudan.</p>
                <p>Preliminary conversations between representatives of <gloss target="#t_USUN1"
                        >USUN</gloss> and the two disputants have indicated that neither side is
                    ready either to resume negotiations at this time or to accept a recommendation
                    by <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> that they do so. As to the possibility,
                    however, that negotiations may be resumed, see Baghdad’s #318 of August 2.<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d546fn2">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">II. <hi rend="italic">The Problem:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The withdrawal of the UK from Egypt sooner than the UK has already agreed upon
                    raises serious questions involving the security of that area, questions which
                    are of great interest to all Members of the UN. At the same time, in view of
                    intensely nationalistic feeling in Egypt, this Govt has not wished to take
                    position which would further complicate our relations with the peoples of the
                    Near East. Moreover, should question arise as to whether Anglo-Egyptian question
                    is dispute continuance of which is likely to endanger international peace and
                    security, we could not, on merits of question at the present time, <pb
                        facs="0803" n="789" xml:id="pg_789"/> support Egyptian position. Dept also
                    wishes to minimize opportunity this case provides USSR to propagandize and
                    perhaps propose solutions not in interests of this Govt or UN. Finally,
                    prolonged argument of case in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> might have some
                    adverse affects on American opinion.</p>
                <p>For these reasons, US Govt is particularly interested in early settlement of
                    controversy.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">III. <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It would be most desirable if UK and Egypt could agree to accept <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> resolution recommending that parties continue
                    negotiations or settle their dispute by peaceful means of their own choice.
                        <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> should immediately explore this
                    possibility with UK and Egyptian delegations. If, as seems likely, two parties
                    cannot agree to a solution of this nature, <gloss target="#t_USUN1"
                    >USUN</gloss>” should proceed along following lines: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item> US should immediately explore with UK and Egyptian representatives
                            possibility of introduction of resolution at next meeting of <gloss
                                target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> by which <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                                >SC</gloss> would suggest to parties that case be referred to <gloss
                                target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss> under terms of reference to be agreed
                            upon by two parties. (Reference to <gloss target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss>
                            could be made on legal issues and/or <hi rend="italic">ex aequo et
                                bono</hi> depending on which course most acceptable to two
                            parties.)</item>
                        <label/>
                        <item>It would be desirable if parties could agree in advance to such
                            resolution and every effort by <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>
                            should promptly be made to seek such agreement. In view of statements by
                            member of UK Delegation, it is believed that UK would not oppose
                            adoption of such a resolution. It is recognized, of course, that
                            reference to <gloss target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss> of legal issues alone
                            would most likely result in decision for UK, and that a court decision
                            might not provide solution of some of the substantive issues which have
                            been in dispute during negotiations between UK and Egypt. (Dept office
                            of legal advisor has expressed opinion that 1936 Treaty is valid,
                            continues in force, and is consistent with UN Charter. Dept regards
                            these legal questions as justiciable by <gloss target="#t_ICJ1"
                                >ICJ</gloss>.) Egyptian delegate might prefer reference <hi
                                rend="italic">ex aequo et bono</hi> since equities in case could
                            thereby be determined.</item>
                        <label/>
                        <item>If it is thought that the two Governments would not oppose a
                            resolution along above lines, US should make every effort to obtain
                            agreement of another member of Council to introduce such a resolution at
                            earliest opportunity. By an early action of this kind, possibility of
                            protracted argument by other members of <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                                >SC</gloss> on case might be diminished. <gloss target="#t_USUN1"
                                >USUN</gloss> has been advised that both Belgian and French
                            representatives are thinking of a settlement of this nature.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>If one or both parties will not accept reference to Court as proposed
                            in above, <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> should explore
                            acceptability of resolution suggesting that parties would settle dispute
                            by submitting it to an arbitration tribunal of their own choice. In
                            meantime matter could remain on list of those matters of which <gloss
                                target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> is seized and parties should report to
                                <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> results obtained.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>In event that agreement of parties cannot be obtained in advance to
                            one of aforesaid recommendations and parties are not themselves able to
                            propose suitable alternative acceptable to US, <gloss target="#t_USUN1"
                                >USUN</gloss> should <pb facs="0804" n="790" xml:id="pg_790"/> seek
                            agreement of Belgian or some other representative to introduce
                            resolution recommended in paragraph “<hi rend="italic">a</hi>”. If it is
                            impossible to obtain consent of Belgian or some other representative on
                            Council to introduce such a resolution, US should itself make such a
                            proposal in next meeting of <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> or as soon
                            thereafter as practicable.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                        <item>To avoid possible restrictions on future <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                                >SC</gloss> jurisdiction and politically undesirable reactions in
                            Near East, Dept believes that it is important that <gloss
                                target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> avoid a decision as to whether this
                            dispute is likely to endanger the maintenance of international peace and
                            security. In discussing with Egyptians proposal to refer case to Court,
                            you may wish if other arguments prove unavailing, to point out to them
                            as last resort that if <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> must make
                            determination US cannot agree that their complaint as it now stands
                            establishes a dispute the continuance of which is likely to endanger the
                            maintenance of international peace and security.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                        <item>For your information Dept would not agree to act as mediator in this
                            dispute.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Sent to New York, repeated to London [as 3402] and Cairo [as 1161].</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
